<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0126EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a BC-Panama-ProducerHeld     12-21 0323</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Panama-Producer Held,0330</SECOND>
<HEAD>ABC News Producer Tells of Abduction</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: No PMs separate planned</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An ABC News producer taken hostage in Panama
said he was held in a Panamanian army intelligence headquarters,
where he was ``threatened constantly'' but released.
   The producer, Robert Campos, said Wednesday night he was
abducted at the Panama City Marriott Hotel with four other
Americans, and that to his knowledge none of the others had been
released. CBS producer Jon Meyersohn and an American businessman
staying at the Marriott were separated from Campos and a Colombian
national after their abduction, Campos said by telephone on
ABC-TV'S ``Nightline.''
   CBS said it had received no word of Meyersohn's whereabouts.
   ``A group of us were on the mezzanine level of the hotel when we
saw the `dignity battalion' soldiers entering the hotel from the
lower level,'' he said, referring to Gen. Manuel Noriega's
staunchly loyal paramilitary force.
   ``We tried to run away by taking an elevator up to a higher
floor and when the elevator doors opened, two soldiers leveled
their AK-47s at us. We again tried to run but they said that they
would kill us if we did. They laid us on the floor and took us off
in a pickup truck.''
   Campos said they were taken to an army intelligence headquarters
near downtown Panama City, about a mile from the military
headquarters. About 75 people were at the building, all armed,
mostly with AK-47s, he said.
   ``We were threatened constantly,'' Campos said. ``We were told
that many Panamanians were dying because of this invasion and that
we would pay. This Colombian gentleman spoke up and said he had a
wife and a daughter to worry about and one of the soldiers told
him, `If I feel like it, I'll make sure you never see them for
Christmas.'''
   Campos was held nearly six hours before being released, said
Laura Wessner, a spokeswoman for ABC News.
</TEXT>

</DOC>