<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0136 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 2021EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama 1stLd-Writethru a0612 12-28 1144</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0612,1178</SECOND>
<HEAD>Top Noriega Aides Arrested as Strongman Remains Closeted</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS throughout to UPDATE with arrests of top aides, quote
from priest, details. Minor editing to trim. No pickup</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PAN7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. forces arrested an Israeli
security adviser and three other top aides of Manuel Antonio
Noriega on Thursday, including two associates who abandoned the
Vatican embassy where the ousted general has taken refuge.
   Banks meanwhile opened for the first time since the Dec. 20 U.S.
invasion and thousands of public workers were paid as millions of
dollars confiscated by U.S. troops were returned to Panama's new
government.
   Noriega, the nation's fallen strongman, remained in the Vatican
embassy with 17 other people, including at least two senior aides,
according to the Rev. Javier Villanueva.
   ``Noriega has spoken very little and does not go out on the
patio. Generally he stays in his room,'' said Villanueva in a
telephone interview with The Associated Press.
   But two of the general's top aides, Lt. Col. Carlos Velardes and
Lt. Col. Arnulfo Castrejon, left the shelter of the embassy and
were taken into custody by U.S. troops that surround the area,
according to U.S. Army Lt. Col. Jerry Murguia.
   Murguia also said Lt. Col. Roberto Cedeno was arrested in the
last 24 hours, and a senior U.S. Embassy official said Michel
Harari, a former Israeli intelligence agent and top security
adviser to Noriega, had also been detained.
   The senior official said the United States would like to pull
out by February the 14,000 troops it sent in for the attack, but
said the soldiers will probably stay longer because Panama needs
time to recreate a security force.
   Traffic jams resumed in the capital of 1 million, and the Panama
Canal returned to 24-hour operation for the first time since the
invasion.
   People raced to withdraw money from banks. With Noriega
seemingly out of the picture, many Panamanians said they felt a
sense of security returning.
   ``I'm here because I need some cash. I don't want to withdraw
all my money,'' said a man who identified himself only as Carlos.
``It is safer here now than ever before.''
   A Panamanian official said President Guillermo Endara's
government sent a letter to the Vatican asking that Noriega be
turned over.
   The official, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said the
letter was sent by the Foreign Ministry, but he did not know
whether the government asked that Noriega be turned over to U.S.
authorities or to Panama.
   U.S. armored cars were on the streets, and occasional patrols
roamed residential neighborhoods to search cars for Noriega
loyalists.
   The U.S. Embassy official, speaking on condition of anonymity,
said the United States estimated the Panamanian Defense Forces had
been 16,000 strong, and that most of the 3,300 ``shooters'' capable
of resistance were accounted for.
   He said the security forces are being reconstituted, but there
is some concern about holdovers from the Noriega days.
   ``It is no secret that the new government does not have a lot of
confidence in some of these people,'' said the official.
   Troops surrounding the Vatican embassy seemed prepared to stay
awhile as negotiations lingered. In Rome, spokesman Joaquin Navarro
said the Vatican still hoped to resolve the crisis within days but
he gave no details.
   Villanueva came out of the embassy at one point Thursday and
appeared to argue with U.S. soldiers, pointing to his ears and then
to small but powerful olive-green loudspeakers blasting rock music.
   The troops set up the outdoor stereo system Wednesday, but it
was unclear whether it was to relieve their own boredom or serenade
Noriega with such tunes as ``Somebody's Watching You'' and ``You're
No Good.''
   In Texas, where President Bush is hunting, White House spokesman
Marlin Fitzwater said Noriega's fate is now ``in the hands of the
Vatican.'' He said U.S. troops were ready to move in if hostages
were taken but that there was no indication this could happen.
   The Los Angeles Times reported that Monsignor Sebastian Laboa,
the papal nuncio, had given U.S. forces a letter authorizing them
to enter the embassy if Noriega took hostages, but the existence of
a letter could not be confirmed.
   Villanueva, a parish priest helping the papal nuncio, said
Noriega largely keeps to his room, speaks with few people and does
not go out in the yard.
   ``Remember, he is not the owner of this house,'' said
Villanueva. ``He does not move around.''
   Velardes, who left the embassy, was chaplain of the Panamanian
Defense Forces, and Castrejon had been the officer on duty at
Noriega's military headquarters on Dec. 16, the day an unarmed U.S.
Marine officer was killed nearby.
   Harari had served as one of Noriega's top security advisers and
an instructor for the Defense Forces, while Cedeno had been chief
of Noriega's state security intelligence.
   Villanueva said Col. Nivaldo Madrinan, chief of Noriega's
investigations department, and Capt. Eliezer Gaytan, chief of
security, were among those inside the nunciature.
   He said four members of the Basque separatist group ETA, along
with one of their wives, also had taken shelter as a precaution.
They were in exile in Panama as part of an agreement with the
Spanish government, Villanueva said.
   He refused to identify 10 other people staying at the embassy.
   The embassy official said Noriega's wife, Felicidad, was inside
the Cuban Embassy residence. That embassy is also surrounded by
U.S. troops because it was thought Noriega henchmen would flee
there.
   Fitzwater reiterated the U.S. stance that Noriega should be
handed over to the United States, where he is wanted on drug
trafficking charges.
   A U.S. military spokesman said Thursday that $5.8 million had
been confiscated from Noriega's men and turned over to the
Panamanian government.
   As Panama's 110 banks reopened and the cash began to flow into
the economy, the country's 150,000 public employees began receiving
their paychecks. Customers lined up early.
   Comptroller Ruben Dario Carles said Japanese ships will keep
flying the Panamanian flag. More than 12,000 Japanese ships fly
Panama's flag, representing nearly $50 million in annual income
through fees and services.
   In its efforts to oust Noriega, the Bush administration had
ordered U.S. ports closed to Panamanian-flag ships and imposed
economic sanctions that froze $400 million in government assets and
revenues.
   U.S. officials also told the government the United States will
consider some form of assistance to compensate for the $1 billion
lost when looters sacked hundreds of stores after the U.S. invasion.
   The U.S. Embassy official said about 300 Panamanian civilians
died in the fighting. He said reports of large numbers of civilian
bodies being found were unfounded.
   The Southern Command said Wednesday that 23 American servicemen
and two dependents have been killed and 322 Americans wounded since
the United States invaded. It said 297 Panamanians troops were
killed and 123 wounded.
</TEXT>

</DOC>