<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 2141EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-NewYear     12-31 0325</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-New Year,0333</SECOND>
<HEAD>114 Injured In Trafalgar Square</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 70,000 revelers welcomed the new year in
Trafalgar Square with dancing, singing, drinking and frolicking
that left at least 114 people injured, police said.
   Two people were rushed to the hospital from the central London
square, one with a suspected fractured skull and another with a
heart attack, police said.
   Police arrested 36 people for public order offenses, mainly
drunken and disorderly behavior, a spokeswoman said on condition of
anonymity.
   The turnout was one of the largest since violent New Year's
revels in 1983, attended by more than 100,000 people, police said.
Two women were trampled to death that year in a surging crowd in
the square.
   The midnight signal from the Big Ben clocktower overlooking the
Houses of Parliament by the River Thames was barely audible half a
mile away in noisy Trafalgar Square, the traditional focal point of
celebrations in the British capital.
   Many revelers only realized the 1990s had arrived when a huge
electronic sign suspended from Nelson's Column flashed the message
``A Happy New Year.''
   Crowd-control barriers were erected around the column, a
145-foot monument to the British naval hero Horatio Nelson which
dominates the square.
   Several hundred policemen were deployed in and around the
square. Its two fountains were switched off and boarded up, nearby
roads were closed to traffic and police confiscated bottles and
cans of liquor at entrance points to the square.
   Scotland Yard police headquarters said security had been the
same as in previous years. The aim was to allow people to have ``a
happy but law-abiding time,'' a spokesman said.
   Rock fans in Eastern Europe were scheduled to hear Ireland's top
international rock band U2 in a live broadcast from Dublin.
   The U2 New Year's Eve show had been scheduled for European
Community-wide radio coverage, but arrangements were made to air
the show in the Soviet Union, East Germany, Hungary, Yugoslavia and
Czechoslovakia.
</TEXT>

</DOC>