<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1154EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-DrugWar-Individuals 2Takes   12-25 0725</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Drug War-Individuals, 2 Takes,720-1,350</SECOND>
<HEAD>Twenty Cited For Work In Fight Against Drugs</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Embargoed for Tuesday AM papers; Not to be broadcast before
12:01 a.m. Tuesday; Time set by source</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAROLYN SKORNECK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   National drug control policy director William
J. Bennett cited 20 people ``on the true front lines'' of the war
on drugs for their grass roots efforts, proving that ``It is
possible to fight back _ even to win.''
   ``These people are not angels,'' Bennett said in a statement
released Monday. ``They are not saints. They are men and women who
have seen their communities ravaged by drugs and they have decided
to act.
   ``These Americans have figured out what armchair critics have
not. It is possible to fight back _ even to win.''
   Bennett said he met those cited during his travels to some three
dozen cities throughout the country since the drug control strategy
he developed was presented to the nation by President Bush on Sept.
5.
   The 20, with background from the Office of National Drug Control
Policy, are:
   _Robert Armstrong, director of the Omaha Housing Authority, who
``implemented non-nosense eviction policies and went after known
pushers'' whom, he said, ``nobody else wanted to touch. Once we got
'em out, the other residents knew we were serious, and they
appreciated it.''
   _Alvin Brooks, founder of the Ad Hoc Group Against Crime in
Kansas City, Mo., also helped start Black Men Together, which is
intended to offer role models for young blacks. Members of Black
Men Together walk some drug-infested streets, toting bull horns and
warning drug dealers to get off the street.
   _Jack Candelaria, president of the South San Jose Neighborhood
Association in Albuquerque, N.M., who brought members of his group
together with police to win establishment of a police sub-station
in the neighborhood. Today, police and residents work closely
together, and Police Chief Sam Baca said, ``months will go by when
the police don't receive calls about drug pushing in the
neighborhood'' which was once overrun by dealers.
   _The Rev. George Clements, pastor of Holy Angels Church and
School in Chicago, who led a boycott of stores in Chicago's South
Side selling drug paraphernalia after he found that all of his
parishioners had relatives who were either hooked on drugs or had
died because of them. Despite death threats, Clements said, ``We,
the citizens, have to get out there and let people know that we
really mean business. ... There are more of us than there are of
them. Their only weapon is fear. They've conned us into thinking
they're invincible. They're not. They're cowards, and once the
community stands up against them, they tuck their tails between
their legs and run.''
   _Dorothy Davis, organizer of STOP Crime Watch in Dallas, and
Assistant Chief of Police Sam Gonzales. Davis started STOP Crime
Watch after a 12-year-old girl was killed by drug violence in 1988.
The grass roots anti-crime and anti-drug organization has helped
city police and other city agencies in Operation CLEAN, Community
and Law Enforcement Against Narcotics, an effort to root out drug
offenders from targeted residential neighborhoods.
   _Edward Johnson, organizer of the Fairlawn Coalition in
Washington, D.C., which patrols the streets of the tough Anacostia
section. Members wear bright orange baseball caps, carry radios,
video cameras and binoculars and confront drug dealers and users
with stares instead of verbal or physical confrontation. They have
driven the drug buyers out, according to coalition founder James
Foreman. ``This is one program where police and citizens working
together bring people closer to law enforcement and let people see
that police are human,'' Johnson said. ``The police know that the
people here will give them water or coffee and help them to do
their job better.''
   _Ray Leary and Tony Hopson, directors of Self Enhancement, Inc.,
in Portland, Ore., a program designed to provide young people with
alternatives to gang and drug involvement. ``We want to show
children that there is a sense of value to their lives,'' Leary
said.
   _The Rev. Michael Lewis of Faith House, Inc., in Tampa, Fla.,
one of the first black child placement agencies in that state to
deal exclusively with cocaine and AIDS babies. ``We took a crack
house and turned it into a faith house,'' said Lewis, where foster
parents are recruited and trained.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>