<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2350EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DayCareAbuse     12-18 0770</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Day Care Abuse,0792</SECOND>
<HEAD>Small Town Rocked by Allegations of Abuse at Day-Care Center</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Note contents of 2nd graf; also in Tuesday AMs report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By F. ALAN BOYCE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EDENTON, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When five people were indicted on charges
of sexually abusing children at a day-care center, the news
reverberated through this town of 5,800, seemingly touching
everyone.
   In the months since the first allegations were made against
Little Rascals' Day Care Center last January, wave after wave of
indictments have been handed up. Court documents listing 202
charges say day-care workers had intercourse in front of children
and performed oral and anal sex with them from September 1988 to
January 1989.
   The initial reports were based on evidence from 21 children who
were allegedly molested, but prosecutors say all of the
approximately 70 children who attended the center are potential
witnesses. The center lost its license in June and was closed.
   Nearly everyone here knows someone who has been indicted or the
family of a child involved in the case.
   ``I've watched some of the parents of victims grow up,'' said
Alton Elmore, owner of Edenton Furniture and a Chowan County
commissioner. ``And I've watched some of them who've been charged
grow up.''
   That sense of community makes it doubly difficult for residents
to deal with the sudden onslaught of news media and curiosity
seekers.
   A clerk at a children's clothing store shied away from
discussing the case with a stranger. ``The manager of the store's
little girl is involved in it, so I don't think I should say
anything,'' she said.
   Other people offered similar responses.
   ``It's just a bad situation. Some are very upset,'' said John
Smith, owner of Edenton Floral Co., a block away from the choppy
waters of the Albemarle Sound.
   But while people are reluctant to talk about the case to
outsiders, they are freer among themselves. Rumors grew so abundant
at one point that District Attorney H.P. Williams issued a
statement warning residents that they could jeopardize the state's
case.
   Townspeople are beginning to tire of the lengthy pre-trial
hearings, sometimes grumbling that Williams has been dragging his
feet since the first hearing April 14, when the first arrest
occurred.
   Williams, up for re-election next November, has sometimes found
himself in an unkind public spotlight and appeared reluctant to
discuss even tangential issues.
   Public outrage and a concern for the children may have prompted
bonds ranging from $375,000 to $1.5 million _ so high that only one
defendant has been released.
   All but one of the defendants is charged with the same four
crimes: engaging in sex with a child under 13, taking indecent
liberties with a minor, crimes against nature, and conspiracy to
commit indecent liberties with a child.
   The fifth, former Little Rascals' employee Shelley Stone, is
charged with all but crimes against nature.
   All five defendants have pleaded innocent.
   Robert Kelly Jr., 41, who operated Little Rascals with his wife,
Elizabeth Kelly, 34, is in jail on $1.5 million bond. He is charged
with 152 counts involving at least 21 boys and girls under age 13.
   Mrs. Kelly is charged with 19 counts involving eight children
and faces a $1 million bond. A friend of the Kellys', Willard Scott
Privott, 40, has been charged with 13 counts involving six
children, plus kidnapping and terrorizing one girl. He is being
held on $1 million bond.
   Kathryn Dawn Wilson, 23, another employee, is charged with 19
counts involving eight children.
   Ms. Stone, who is accused of nine counts, is the only one of the
five to post bond _ $375,000 in her case. However her lawyer said
he was worried that she might be named in new indictments and
arrested without warning.
   Joe Cheshire, the Raleigh attorney representing Kelly, called it
``an incredible case.'' He contended that much of the children's
testimony would show that nothing wrong had taken place, and would
exonerate his client.
   ``It's very strange to me,'' Cheshire said. ``You have a couple
of kids make some statements and months later you have some more
and now we hear there are some more. I'd just like to find out how
that process happened.''
   But Assistant Attorney General Bill Hart said there is no
mystery about the process.
   ``We have had continuing disclosure just like the defense has
been getting,'' he said. ``Children don't just come running out of
their houses screaming, `I've been molested.'''
   Elmore said each new revelation rocks the community in a way
he's never experienced. ``A lot of good people and the families of
good people have gotten hurt,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>