<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0142 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 2155EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d e BC-Theater     12-28 0458</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Theater,0480</SECOND>
<HEAD>Whimsical Depression Musical Opens Off-Broadway</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: No PMs Planned.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY CAMPBELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ``Romance in Hard Times,'' a new musical set in
the Depression, attempts to be whimsical but follows too many
tangents and rattles around rather messily.
   At least it has some goofily charming moments. The show was
written and composed by William Finn, who has been acclaimed here
for ``March of the Falsettos.'' It opened Thursday night at the
off-Broadway Newman Theater at the Public Theater complex.
   Lillias White is a plus. She has a striking voice, which she
wisely doesn't push to its limits, and a stage presence which adds
up to adorable. She played Effie the second time ``Dreamgirls'' was
on Broadway.
   Finn's abilities to write good songs, at least for part of his
extensive score, and to float more than one song at the same time
are pluses. So are some of the other performers, particularly a
five-person singing-dancing chorus of unemployed. But the plot,
which doesn't really arise from the Depression, is a mess.
   ``Romance in Hard Times'' is set in a Manhattan soup kitchen.
The unemployed are ``Standing in Line'' for soup.
   Hennie, played by Miss White, tells her always silent husband
Harvey (Lawrence Clayton) that she's pregnant and hopes that he
will now speak. Everybody sings ``Harvey Promised To Change the
World,'' explaining that when he didn't, he quit talking. However,
Clayton displays a fine voice in songs which convey his thoughts.
   Boris, played by Cleavant Derricks, proclaims his love for
Hennie, though she is married.
   Now, events, fantasy and the muddle speed up. Eleanor Roosevelt
enters, made up like Pat Nixon, in Nancy Reagan's red and Barbara
Bush's pearls, with a shallow optimism like nobody's. She stays.
Babe Ruth, Shirley Temple and Bojangles have walk-ons.
   Hennie saves the Supreme Court from a fire, is promised a
reward, doesn't get it. Boris robs a bank. Harvey gets shot. Hennie
decides not to have her baby in that kind of world and gets
continually larger for some two years.
   The soup kitchen becomes prosperous selling Hennie's Soup. But
Boris, who robbed to give money to Hennie, has become a national
hero. Buyers boycot the soup when Boris is imprisoned after
proclaiming his love to the now-widowed but still-pregnant Hennie.
She called the police.
   In a final plea for romance, no matter what, Victor Trent Cook
steps out of the chorus and unleashes his rock-oriented high tenor
on ``You Can't Let Romance Die.'' That is, presumably, the message.
   David Warren directed, keeping movement flowing briskly over a
stage design by James Youmans in which ``outdoors'' is a ramp above
the soup kitchen. Marcia Milgrom Dodge choreographed. Bruce
Coughlin's orchestrations didn't enhance the songs.
</TEXT>

</DOC>