<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0135EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-US-China Bjt   12-20 0826</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-China, Bjt,830</SECOND>
<HEAD>Baker `Regrets' Misleading Statement</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BARRY SCHWEID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Diplomatic Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III says he
regrets possibly misleading the American public about a secret trip
to China taken by two high-level Bush administration officials.
   Baker said through a spokeswoman Tuesday night ``he felt
obligated to protect the secrecy of a mission the president wished
to have classified.''
   Speaking for Baker, spokeswoman Margaret D. Tutwiler added: ``He
regrets that he may have misled some...''
   It was the first acknowledgement of error since the White House
announced on Dec. 9 that national security adviser Brent Scowcroft
and Deputy Secretary of State Lawrence Eagleburger were visiting
Beijing.
   Their trip was roundly condemned in Congress as a friendly
gesture to China and a cancellation of the ban President Bush
imposed on high-level exchanges after pro-democracy students were
massacred in early June in Tiananmen Square.
   Another sanction crumbled Tuesday night when Bush moved to end a
ban that prevented the U.S. Export-Import bank from providing
financial aid to companies doing business in China.
   Also, the White House announced that Bush had approved the
export of three communications satellites expected to be launched
by China, saying the deal was in the ``national interest.''
   Sen. Albert Gore, D-Tenn., called Bush's approval of the
satellite export licenses ``a true outrage'' and ``another effort
to curry favor with the hardliners in Beijing and an insult to the
memory of those who died for democracy in Tiananmen Square.''
   Criticism also mounted on Capitol Hill against this month's
visit by Scowcroft and Eagleburger to Beijing, as well as an
earlier one in July.
   ``To have sent two of our highest level officials to Beijing
only weeks after announcing a ban on such exchanges makes the
president look like a wimp in Beijing and a hypocrite in
Washington,'' said Rep. Stephen Solarz, D-N.Y., a leading
congressional spokesman on Asia issues.
   In defense of Bush's actions, White House spokesman Marlin
Fitzwater said: ``It is not misleading to not tell you about
everything he's doing. The president's up there in the Oval Office
doing things all day long that you don't know and won't know about
and that's not misleading.''
   Baker, appearing on ABC-TV on Dec. 10, called the trip taken in
early December to Beijing by Scowcroft and Eagleburger ``the first
time we've had high-level U.S. officials go to the People's
Republic of China.''
   On Monday, however, the White House disclosed Scowcroft and
Eagleburger also had made a secret trip to China in July.
   Asked about the apparent discrepancy, State Department
spokeswoman Tutwiler said Baker had explicitly acknowledged the
December trip by Scowcroft and Eagleburger ``was not the first time
we had high-level contacts'' with China since the crackdown.
   She noted that Baker mentioned on ABC his own meeting in August
with Chinese Foreign Minister Qian Qichen at a conference on
Cambodia in Paris.
   ``He specifically referred to his own contacts,'' Ms. Tutwiler
said. ``But he felt obligated to protect the secrecy of a mission
that the president wished to have classified.
   ``He regrets that he may have misled some, but he felt that by
acknowledging his own direct involvement it was sufficient to make
the point that this was not the first case of high-level contact.''
   Gore sponsored the legislation that forbids the launch of
U.S.-manufacturered satellites on Chinese rockets unless the
president declares it to be in the U.S. national interest, as Bush
has done.
   The Hughes Aircraft Co. is selling the satellites to firms in
Australia and Hong Kong for launching on a Chinese rocket.
   ``Approval of these licences is in keeping with the president's
policy not to disrupt normal commercial relations with China,'' a
White House statement added.
   ``These satellites are intended for civil use and represent
significant investments for the firms, based in Australia and Hong
Kong,'' the statement said. ``It is in the national interest of the
United States to approve export licenses for the three satellites
currently being prepared for launch in China.''
   The White House also cited ``national interest'' in waiving
restrictions on the Export-Import bank's financing of U.S. business
activities within China.
   The White House said the waiver ``preserves a level playing
field for U.S. business. Additional business activity with China
will be considered on a case-by-case basis as part of a continuing
review process.''
   One of the few on Capitol Hill who has supported Bush's
overtures, Rep. Jim Leach, R-Iowa, said sending Scowcroft and
Eagleburger to underscore human rights concerns ``was exactly in
conformity with the congressional position, which reflected the
views of the American people.''
   But Rep. Lee Hamilton, D-Ind., a senior member of the House
Foreign Affairs Committee, said ``the administration did what it
told us they were not doing.''
   ``Surely the Chinese would see it that way. If we send the
national security adviser to the president, there is no sanction
from the standpoint of China. I don't buy that distinction at
all,'' Hamilton said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>