<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0164 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 2028EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WKD--FilmReview Adv00   12-26 0544</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--Film Review, Adv 00,0554</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv 00</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Anytime</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WEEKEND ENTERTAINMENT AND ARTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>At the Movies: `Always'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BOB THOMAS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   It's a curious irony that the leading commercial filmmaker of
the cynical 1980s is a devout romantic.
   Throughout his career, Steven Spielberg has taken a sunshiny
view of the human situation. His heroes, notably Indiana Jones,
always triumph over insuperable odds. Life may hold its miseries,
as in ``The Color Purple,'' but the struggle is always worth it in
the long run. Even Spielberg's space visitors (``Close Encounters
of the Third Kind,'' ``E.T. The Extra-Terrestrial'') prove benign.
   ``Always'' is Spielberg's most romantic film yet. The new movie
stems from his fondness for the happy-ending films of the 1940s,
especially ``A Guy Named Joe.'' That film provides the basis for
``Always,'' which is not likely to win the hearts of hardbitten
critics but should appeal to the millions who embraced ``Field of
Dreams'' early in 1989.
   In the new version, the air war of World War II has been
supplanted by the battle against devastating forest fires. The
sense of jeopardy is not the same, hence the dramatic tension is
diminished.
   Richard Dreyfuss is the hotshot pilot of the tanker bomber base,
taking risks that alarm his sweetheart, Holly Hunter, an air
controller. He believes he is invincible, but during a daring
rescue of his buddy, played by John Goodman, his plane explodes.
Dreyfuss finds himself on a grassy oasis amid a burned-out forest,
getting instructions from an angel _ Audrey Hepburn in a white
designer pantsuit.
   The guardian angel tells Dreyfuss his mission: to return to
Earth unseen and help Hunter overcome her grief and pass on his
flying prowess to another pilot. Enter Brad Johnson, a klutzy flier
who needs Dreyfuss' help but is handsome enough to sway Hunter's
heart.
   Spielberg lavishes all his craft on ``Always,'' and no director
makes better use of the camera. The fire scenes have a frightening
immediacy, and the flying is among the best in recent times.
   The fault lies in the script, credited to Jerry Belson and the
late Diane Thomas but seemingly the work of many hands. Consistency
of tone is lacking, and the plot has certain confusions, as though
important scenes had been cut.
   The cast performs admirably. Dreyfuss displays the solidity of
Spencer Tracy, who originated the role. Hunter is highly effective,
especially after she drops her down-home cuteness. Goodman neatly
fits his large frame into the Ward Bond-Alan Hale kinds of roles.
Johnson has the looks of a '40s screen idol and is likely to become
a star of the '90s.
   ``Always'' is a Universal-United Artists picture produced by
Spielberg, Frank Marshall and Kathleen Kennedy. The rating is PG,
probably for mild swearing and excitement. Running time: 121
minutes.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Motion Picture Association of America rating definitions:
   G _ General audiences. All ages admitted.
   PG _ Parental guidance suggested. Some material may not be
suitable for children.
   PG-13 _ Special parental guidance strongly suggested for
children under 13. Some material may be inappropriate for young
children.
   R _ Restricted. Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult
guardian.
   X _ No one under 17 admitted. Some states may have higher age
restrictions.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Release Anytime</NOTE>

</DOC>