<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0124 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1526EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-VictimJailed     12-29 0440</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Victim Jailed,0453</SECOND>
<HEAD>Victim of Alleged Rape, Kidnapping Jailed after Failing to Appear
to Testify</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Stantley is cq in 6th graf</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TUCSON, Ariz. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An alleged rape and kidnap victim was
jailed at the request of a prosecutor after she failed to appear to
testify during the scheduled trial of an ex-convict charged in her
attack.
   The 24-year-old woman was ordered jailed Thursday as a material
witness. The woman's lawyer said she remained in custody Friday.
   Prosecutor Eric A. Larsen, a deputy Pima County attorney, said
Thursday he regretted having the woman jailed but feared she would
leave the state and not be available to testify against the
defendant.
   Larsen said the woman missed the first scheduled rape trial and
also missed her arraignment on an unrelated drug charge.
   Superior Court Judge Pro Tem Howard Hantman ordered the woman
held as a material witness and set a $5,000 bond for her. He
scheduled a hearing Tuesday before Superior Court Judge Nanette
Warner.
   The woman is the key witness in the case against Stantley Welch,
28, of Tucson, who was charged with burglary, kidnapping, attempted
sexual assault, sexual assault and aggravated assault.
   Welch is accused of assaulting the woman at her rented home at
about midnight on June 11 after visiting earlier in the day to
inquire about the sale of the house, according to court records.
   When the woman did not appear in court Dec. 12 to testify in
Welch's trial, scheduled to start that day, Ms. Warner dismissed
the charges against Welch without prejudice, meaning they could be
refiled.
   ``On the date of the trial, she failed to appear after assuring
the state that she would,'' Larsen wrote in a motion to hold the
woman as a material witness.
   Larsen's motion also said the woman threatened on Dec. 21 to
leave the state if she were released. That was the date she was
arrested on an unrelated drug charge.
   Ms. Warner had given prosecutors 60 days to locate the woman and
refile charges before the charges would be dismissed with
prejudice, meaning they could not be refiled.
   Larsen said Friday his office was preparing to refile the
charges against Welch but had not yet done so.
   In the drug case, the woman was indicted in November by a county
grand jury on a charge of unlawfully possessing a dangerous drug _
methamphetamines, according to court records.
   She was released from jail after being arrested Dec. 21 on a
warrant stemming from her failure to appear in the drug case, but
she was taken into custody again Thursday when she appeared before
Hantman in the rape case.
</TEXT>

</DOC>