<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0204 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 2131EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Judge-Explosion 1stLd-Writethru a0815 12-22 1017</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Judge-Explosion, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0815,1046</SECOND>
<HEAD>Latest Bombing Attack Injures Judge in Apartment</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 13 grafs to UPDATE with bomb identified as pipe bomb,
authorities saying appears to be unrelated to other bombings, details of
injuries, quotes. Picks up 9th graf, `Parcel bombs...; INSERTS 3 grafs
after 2nd, `Hagerstown attorney..., to give further details of injuries.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Mail Bombs</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto HAG1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEB RIECHMANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HAGERSTOWN, Md. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A pipe bomb delivered to a county judge's
apartment exploded and injured him Friday, but appeared to be
unrelated to four other bomb attacks in four states since Saturday,
authorities said.
   Washington County Circuit Judge John Corderman, 47, was in
stable condition after undergoing surgery to remove shrapnel in his
abdomen and right hand, said Washington County Hospital spokeswoman
Diana Donegan.
   Corderman also lost the tip of his right middle finger and
suffered severe damage to both eardrums, but he never lost
consciousness and his life was in no immediate danger, hospital
officials said.
   A neighbor said the bomb exploded in Corderman's third-floor
downtown apartment about 10 minutes after a delivery man left a
package in the building. The judge apparently was alone at the
time, police said.
   ``Apparently, the device was situated outside when he arrived
home. He retrieved it, entered the apartment and a short time later
it exploded. We don't know whether it was opened or not,'' said
Chuck Jackson, Maryland State Police spokesman.
   Corderman made his way outside his apartment, used a fire alarm
to call for help and went back inside, where he collapsed, Jackson
said.
   ``This was a life-threatening bomb. It was not of small
proportion. The injuries however did not threaten him,'' said Dr.
Charles Chaney, a surgeon at Washington County Hospital. Based on
the injuries, Chaney said he believed Corderman was holding the
parcel in his lap when it exploded.
   A second, unexploded pipe bomb was found in the same package as
the device that exploded, and was designed to detonate when the
first one did, said Deputy Fire Marshal Faron Taylor. The second
device was disarmed by two bomb specialists, he said. The building
was evacuated.
   George Hopgood, an assistant special agent in charge for the
federal Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms, said the explosion
appeared to be unrelated to four package bombs in the past week
that exploded or were defused.
   ``It is not similar to the ones that have been found in the
southeast. At this time there doesn't appear to be any
connection,'' Hopgood said.
   Hagerstown Police Chief Paul Wood said investigators had not yet
identified a motive.
   Earlier, police Lt. Robert Frick said the blast had some
similarities to the bombs that killed a federal judge in Alabama on
Dec. 16 and, two days later, a city councilman who was also an
NAACP attorney in Savannah, Ga.
   However, ``we've got a lot of leads to follow up,'' he said.
   Parcel bombs were also found this week at the Jacksonville,
Fla., chapter of the NAACP and the 11th Circuit courthouse in
Atlanta. Both were defused without incident.
   Colleagues of the U.S. appellate judge who was killed, Robert S.
Vance, have since received threatening letters, sources told The
Associated Press on Friday.
   In Washington, Justice Department spokesman David Runkel said he
was unaware that letters had been delivered to judges on the 11th
Circuit.
   But Runkel said four threatening letters delivered this week
bore physical evidence linking them to the bombs that killed Vance
and the attorney, Robert E. Robinson. He would not say to whom they
were delivered.
   Following the Hagerstown explosion, agents of the Bureau of
Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms arrived from the Baltimore office,
about 65 miles southeast of here. FBI agents were also on the scene.
   A neighbor of Corderman, Steven Keyes, 30, said he saw a
delivery man bring a package to the building about 20 minutes
before the 2:30 p.m. explosion.
   ``It looked like a normal person to me, a normal delivery,''
Keyes said. The delivery man stayed inside five to 10 minutes, and
the explosion occurred about 10 minutes after he left, Keyes said.
   ``I thought maybe it was a neighbor who had dropped something on
the floor. It sounded like a muffled-type bomb. My brother-in-law
thought the truck had backfired,'' Keyes said.
   Corderman, known as one of the toughest judges in the county,
was not at work Friday because the courthouse was closed for the
Christmas holiday.
   ``He's a judge. He's put a lot of people away,'' Frick said.
   Corderman obtained a gun permit several years ago because of
death threats.
   According to Baltimore attorney Chris Brown, ``He's the kind of
gentleman who you like him or don't like him. He has rubbed people
the wrong way.''
   Brown said the judge ``takes unusual stances and gives lawyers a
hard time. He's a very colorful outspoken, controversial judge.''
   Hagerstown attorney Edward Button called Corderman a legal
scholar and ``an extremely competent judge. He knows the law very,
very well.''
   The explosion blew holes in both Corderman's eardrums, and he
lost 75 percent hearing in his right ear and 50 percent in the
left, Chaney said. Reconstructive surgery could restore some of
Corderman's hearing, he said.
   He said the judge was under guard and would probably stay in the
hospital for three days.
   ``His only concern was that the other judges be made aware of
the incident and take precautions,'' Chaney said.
   An FBI-led investigation has been concentrating on possible
racial motivations for the killings in Georgia and Alabama.
   Brown said Corderman is unlikely to have handled racially
sensitive cases because few of them arise in Washington County,
which has a relatively small black population. However, inmates at
two state prisons in Washington County often go before circuit
judges in Hagerstown.
   A Democrat, Corderman gave up his state senate seat in 1977 at
age 35 to fill a vacancy on the bench and was elected to a 15-year
term as judge the next year. He was elected in 1983 as president of
the Maryland State Bar Association, the first judge in decades to
hold the post.
</TEXT>

</DOC>