<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0036EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BridgeAccident     12-23 0593</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bridge Accident,0615</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bridge Drawspan Activates Accidentally, Killing One</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATIA BLACKBURN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A drawspan on the world's longest floating bridge
was raised accidentally during a test Friday, sending rush-hour
traffic into a rising wall of steel that killed one woman and
injured at least five other people.
   State officials were at a loss to explain what went wrong in the
test, which has been conducted every Friday morning for 18 years
without incident, said Leslie Salisbury, a Department of
Transportation spokeswoman.
   She said operator error had virtually been ruled out in the 8:50
a.m. accident, which blocked traffic in both directions on the
Evergreen Point Bridge. The span reopened at 2:45 p.m.
   The 25-year-old bridge, a series of concrete pontoons across
Lake Washington, opens by raising two, 100-foot-long steel grids
about 7 feet and moving an adjacent pontoon beneath them.
   The weekly test checks drawbridge circuitry and does not involve
actually moving the span.
   Salisbury said the bridge-opening sequence requires 18 distinct
steps. ``When the operator got to the 10th step, for some reason
one part of the drawspan opened up,'' she said.
   Transportation Department crews ran through the procedure three
times Friday afternoon, ``and every time we got to that step the
drawspan opened,'' Salisbury said.
   The step should not have involved the drawspan mechanism at all,
she said. Ron Anderson, department district administrator,
``likened it to turning on your windshield wipers and having the
radio come on instead,'' Salisbury said.
   The bridge drawspan lifted about 4{ feet, creating a wall that
three vehicles drove into head-on. Several cars were left perched
on the elevated section of the bridge, some with blown tires and
mangled metal from hitting the rising span. No cars went into the
water.
   Mark Bauty, a motorist, told radio station KIRO that his car
bounced over the lip of the drawspan just as it started to open and
he could hear tires screeching and metal crunching behind him.
   ``The bridge was probably 6 inches high I guess when I hit it
and the car made it over the front end, kept right on going and
flew off the back end when the bridge was probably about a
foot-and-a-half to two feet high,'' he said.
   ``When I realized what happened and I looked in the rear view
mirror I could see some cars who had headed into what appeared to
be solid steel.''
   There was no warning the bridge was opening, said DOT
spokeswoman Heidi Keller. Normally, gates are lowered and lights
flash to stop traffic.
   The identity of the 44-year-old Seattle woman killed in the
accident was not released. John Lombardini, county Medical Examiner
investigator, said an autopsy would be conducted to determine the
cause of death.
   Three people were hospitalized in serious but stable condition
with multiple injuries, and two other people were treated and
discharged.
   Salisbury said the motors for the bridge span were disengaged
and the control panel locked.
   State inspectors will check the bridge further on Tuesday for
possible damage and expect to close the bridge briefly in January
for a more detailed look.
   She said the department also has recommended an independent
consultant do an investigation.
   Opening the drawspan, which provides a 200-foot opening, is
necessary only 30 to 40 times a year because most vessels can pass
under elevated portions of the bridge at each end, officials said.
   Evergreen Point Bridge, formally known as the Albert D.
Rosellini Bridge, is more than two miles long, and more than 7,000
feet of it is on pontoons.
</TEXT>

</DOC>