<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0151EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Romania-Dissidents     12-22 0724</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Dissidents,0746</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dissent Is Rare Under Ceausescu, But Few Brave Ones Speak Out</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TEDDIE WEYR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dissent has been rare in Romanian
President Nicolae Ceausescu's realm, where a vast secret police
force and a wide network of informants have traditionally stifled
public criticism of the Bucharest regime.
   Many of those who have protested Ceausescu's policies are
unknown to Westerners, largely because of the regime's swift
repression. Critics have landed in jail or been committed to mental
hospitals for speaking to the Western media or standing up for
human rights.
   Leaders of a worker protest by some 10,000 people in Brasov in
November 1987 disappeared without trace.
   Here is a list of some of the most prominent people known to
have criticized Ceausescu's policies:
   _ Doina Cornea, 60, a French teacher who lives in the western
city of Cluj, is the most prominent dissident. She has been
persecuted repeatedly, put under surveillance and house arrest and
beaten by police for her outspoken support for human and religious
rights.
   Cornea has been especially vocal in criticizing a national
resettlement plan that Western human rights activists say could
destroy village culture and tradition.
   _ Laszlo Toekes, a Protestant minister who has championed
religious rights as well as those of the ethnic Hungarian minority
in Transylvania. An attempt to arrest him one week ago sparked the
anti-government protests in Timisoara that have now spread around
Romania.
   _ Silviu Brucan, 73, a former ambassador to the United States,
who early this yeasr joined five other prominent former Communists
in signing a letter to Ceausescu criticizing the president's
policies and disrespect for the law.
   Brucan also issued a statement to Western media after the 1987
worker protest in Brasov, supporting the worker's demands. For that
he was placed under house arrest for several months.
   The other signatories of the letter to Ceausescu were Gheorge
Apostel, a former Politburo member and first deputy premier;
Alexandru Birladenanu, a former Politburo member and former
minister of foreign trade and chief of state planning; Corneliu
Manescu, a former foreign minister and ambassador to France.
   Constantin Pirvulescu, one of the founding fathers of the
Romanian Communist Party who accused Ceausescu in 1979 of putting
personal interests above the interests of the party, also signed
the letter, as did Grigore Raceanu. Raceanu held various positions
in the Central Committee, was purged in 1958 and later
rehabilitated.
   His son, Mircea Raceanu, a diplomat in the United States in the
1970s, was arrested in January and charged with espionage. His
arrest was linked in the official media with the letter of the six
party veterans.
   Among others harassed for critical stands is poet Dan Desliu,
who in April sent a letter to Ceausescu deploring the lack of human
rights in his country. He was reported on hunger strike in March
and was later placed in a mental hospital.
   Writer Dan Petrescu, a resident of the northern university town
of Iasi, was arrested for a month before November's party congress
in Romania after he gave an outspoken interview to Radio Free
Europe. He is now reported again under house arrest in Iasi.
   Mircea Dinescu, also a poet, was fired from his job with the
literary weekly Romania Literara for an interview published in the
French daily Liberation in March in which he criticized official
policies on writers.
   Four people were reportedly arrested in January for other
criticism of Ceausescu's policies. They were Petre Mihai Bacanu and
Anton Uncu, from the government newspaper Romania Libera; theater
critic Mihai Creanga of the magazine Romania Pitoreasca; and
Alexandru Ghiroiu, who worked as a linotypist at Romania's largest
state publishing house of Casa Scinteii.
   Others imprisoned for their dissenting views include:
   _ Ion Puiu, veteran politican of the National Peasant Party who
gathered mostly young supporters of the outlawed party.
   _ Florian Russu, leader of two independent youth groups.
   _ Nicolae Stancescu, who was arrested after giving interviews to
Western news media.
   _ Mihai Pavelescu, who was detained after describing the
repressive policies in an interview with a French news agency.
   _ Nestor Popescu, a film editor and Baptist activist who was
placed in a psychiatric hospital.
   _ Dumitru Mazilu, a U.N. human rights investigator who has been
prevented from leaving the country to file his report on youth and
human rights.
</TEXT>

</DOC>