<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0094 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1530EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CreativeToys     12-19 0555</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Creative Toys,0568</SECOND>
<HEAD>Toys To Stimulate The Imagination</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto CD1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DWIGHT WOODWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In an age of Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles and
Nintendo, two women who started a toy company in their basement
have created a growing business that relies on an endless source of
entertainment _ a child's imagination.
   Phyllis Brody and Evelyn Greenwald, owners of Creative Art
Activities Inc., banked on children's curiosity and ingenuity when
they founded Creativity for Kids in 1979.
   ``So many of the other toys are entertaining you ... With our
toys, rather than a child being passive, they participate,'' said
Mrs. Brody, 53, a former social worker. ``People go into one of the
toy supermarkets and buy what the kids says they want from
television ads rather than buying something that is more in line
with the kids' interests.''
   The idea has paid off. The business has moved into a Cleveland
warehouse as sales have increased 30 to 40 percent each of the last
five years. The two Cleveland Heights owners say it is accurate to
estimate that sales exceeded $2 million in 1989, though they
decline to give specific sales figures.
   The company's 40 kits contain materials to transform old boxes
into cars or dollhouses, safety pins and sequins into bracelets and
cardboard tubes and clothespins into dolls, puppets and monsters.
   Harry Guckert, publisher of Playthings, the New York-based trade
magazine founded in 1903 for the toy industry, said Creativity for
Kids has carved out a special niche in the toy market.
   ``Creativity for Kids is excellent,'' Guckert said. ``We call
them specialty retailers. The two gals have researched the market
and their company is strong. There are a lot of companies in this
differentiated market that are not.''
   The company's products have won seven Parents' Choice awards, a
toy industry award for excellence.
   Many of the kits are just a collection of household items, the
kind of stuff parents used to assemble for play on a rainy day _
feathers, glue, colored paper, corks, paint, fabric, wood and yarn,
said Ms. Greenwald, 49, a lawyer. She said the kits satisfy the
needs of working parents who don't have the time to round up craft
items but still want to offer children creative opportunities.
   Ten employees work at company headquarters, mailing orders to
about 1,000 small toy shops nationwide that feature educational and
specialty products.
   The employees order hundreds of pounds of feathers, millions of
wiggly eyes, pine cones and an array of other items. The suppliers
ship the items to a sheltered workshop program where handicapped
workers assemble the toy kits.
   Aimed at children 4 and older, the kits range in price from $3
for a party favors kit to $25 for a pre-cut doll bed. The product
line is inexpensive in an industry with annual sales of $12 billion.
   ``The kits are a combination of facts, playing and learning.
They make up their own rules _ no one tells them how to do it,''
Ms. Brody said.
   For $7.95, the Let's Pretend Travel Kit includes maps,
passports, postcards and tickets. The Let's Pretend Restaurant
offers dinnerware, menus, placemats, order pads and other items
needed for a restaurant.
   Other kits include the ingredients to make a personalized
T-shirt, hat or masks or items to operate a hotel or supermarket.
</TEXT>

</DOC>