<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0613EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-SchoolPaper-Condom     12-23 0519</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-School Paper-Condom,0537</SECOND>
<HEAD>School Officials Censor Student Paper for Explicit Articles</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Note language in 8th graf</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HOLMDEL TOWNSHIP, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   School officials censored a
student-run newspaper that ran several stories on sex education
which were deemed inappropriate, including one that explained how
to use a condom.
   Principal Richard White at Holmdel High School said he met with
the eight-student editorial board of The Sting on Friday and agreed
to allow the paper to publish without the three stories in question
on Jan. 2, when classes resume.
   Craig LaCava, the newspaper's 18-year-old editor, said the
articles were prompted by the 800-student school's inadequate sex
education program.
   ``We get a week of it freshman year, then a good course that
lasts several weeks during senior year,'' LaCava said. ``By then
it's much, much too late.''
   ``We decided to do this because we think parents should know how
uniformed their kids are about these things,'' he said. ``We were
very concerned about the pregnancy and abortion rate in our
school.''
   ``I had agreed the students had a valid issue,'' said White.
``But one article in particular, on skills and techniques of using
a condom, was just inappropriate for a school newspaper.''
   The articles, one each dealing with sexually transmitted
diseases, sex education curriculum and condoms, were described by
LaCava as ``explicit but accurate.''
   ``It was our feeling that it had to be explicit,'' said LaCava.
``There's no other word for penis.''
   The newspaper staff had showed the articles to White the
previous week, LaCava said, adding he left the meeting feeling that
White was shocked but would still allow them to be published.
   But on Tuesday, ``just before we were going to go to the
printer, Dr. White came in and said we wouldn't be allowed to do
it,'' LaCava said.
   LaCava and his co-editor, 17-year-old M. Liwanag Querijero,
decided to take the proofs to the printer despite White's
objections.
   ``We felt strongly enough to defy him,'' LaCava said.
   Bill Sachs, owner of Fast Copy Printing Center in Keyport, where
the paper is normally printed, said a school official came to the
shop Wednesday and asked him to hand over the proofs. He refused.
   About an hour later, he said, he received a call from the school
board warning that he could lose his contract if he did not turn
over the proofs.
   ``They made it clear I had to turn them over,'' he said.
   White said no disciplinary action is contemplated against LaCava
or Miss Querijero.
   ``I wanted them to proceed at a slower pace and do a series of
articles rather than to broadside the thing and alienate allies
they might have needed later on to make real changes,'' he said.
   The limitations of the sex education courses result from ``a
sort of combination of political and educational decision-making,''
he said. ``Parents think teaching kids about sex will promote
promiscuity. That's a constant theme we battle.''
   But the issue of reforming the curriculum is now solidly on the
front burner, he said. ``I think they've made their point that what
we have is too little, too late.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>