<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0228 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1428EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r e BC-WKD--FilmReviews Adv00   12-18 1167</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--Film Reviews, Adv 00,1206</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv00</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Anytime</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WEEKEND ENTERTAINMENT AND ARTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>At the Movies: `Valmont,' `Enemies, a Love Story'</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: ``Valmont'' opened in New York, Chicago, Los Angeles and Toronto
Nov. 17 and is being released elsewhere through January. ``Enemies'' opened
in New York on Nov. 13 and will be released elsewhere in coming months.
   </HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DOLORES BARCLAY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Arts Editor</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   ``Valmont''
   
   Filmmakers seem to have a love affair with Choderlos de Laclos'
1782 epistolary novel, ``Les Liaisons Dangereuses.'' And with his
story of seduction, hedonism and revenge in 18th century France,
it's no surprise.
   The work was first interpreted on film by Roger Vadim in 1959.
It starred Gerard Phillipe and Jeanne Moreau as Vicomte de Valmont
and his wife, Juliette, two icy, modern-day opportunists with an
``open marriage.'' It had a jazzy score by Thelonius Monk and Jack
Murray.
   The second movie version was last year's ``Dangerous Liaisons,''
an Americanized, fast-paced drama directed by Stephen Frears and
starring Glenn Close as the scheming Marquise de Merteuil and John
Malkovich as the notorious rake Valmont.
   Now comes Milos Forman with ``Valmont,'' and it is as different
from the other efforts as the many interpretations of William
Shakespeare's ``Hamlet.'' It is a lush and elegant movie, graced by
the seductive camera work of Miroslav Ondricek.
   With a keen eye for detail _ cheese wrapped in leaves in the
market, a bathtub with a little bench on which to sit, Forman eases
into de Laclos' story against the blind morals of prerevolutionary
France. His vision is sweeping _ there's no rush but still much
activity. Forman loves the bustle and business of earlier times _
jugglers, merchants, servants always underfoot.
   As Madame de Merteuil, Annette Bening brings a sugary
bitchiness. She is less brittle than the Glenn Close interpretation
and also less focused. But her intent is clear: She loves playing
games, wicked, vicious games that ultimately destroy people and
bring ruin to a way of life.
   Colin Firth's Valmont is far more attractive than Malkovich's.
Indeed, one wondered why women would ever be drawn to the Malkovich
character, with his pasty visage and deep-set eyes, and Bronx
sounding voice.
   Firth is almost too cute, almost too soft. He's sexy, sensual,
flirty. But the steely maliciousness is missing.
   Meg Tilly, who is about to emerge as a leading actress with her
role in ``Valmont'' and her upcoming part as Harvey Keitel's
unfaithful wife in ``The Two Jakes,'' is convincing as the
vulnerable and pious young wife Madame de Tourvel. She is the woman
Valmont worships and for whom he lusts.
   Fairuza Balk, who starred in the horrendous ``Return to Oz,''
portrays Cecile, the target of Valmont's seduction and the innocent
victim of Merteuil's revenge. Her mother has arranged for the
convent school girl to marry Gercourt, an older man who will take
only a virgin as his wife. He's also Merteuil's ex-lover.
   Forman dances his characters about in a game of musical beds, a
game that's a no-win for just about all.
   Jean-Claude Carriere's screenplay makes good use of de Laclos'
focus on letter writing. Letters show up just about everywhere and
even Valmont gets into the spirit by dictating erotic passages to
an unsuspecting Cecile to send to the young music teacher (Henry
Thomas) who loves her.
   Forman's denouement is almost anti-climatic. The duel and
Valmont's death is almost a mirthful moment. But ``Valmont'' is
worth watching.
   The Orion Pictures release has a running time of 134 minutes and
is rated R.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   
   ``Enemies, a Love Story''
   
   Herman Broder, who's never really been a faithful husband, leads
what he thinks is a fairly uncomplicated and acceptable life: He
has a wife in Brooklyn and a mistress in the Bronx.
   But when his first wife, whom he had thought was dead, suddenly
shows up, his ``uncomplicated'' life becomes a shambles.
   Paul Mazursky has adapted a novel by Isaac Bashevis Singer and
crafted it into a richly told human drama, ``Enemies, a Love
Story.'' It's a tale filled with irony, humor, joy, tragedy set in
the world of Holocaust survivors in New York, 1949.
   Herman (Ron Silver) survived the war by hiding in a hayloft. His
family's former servant, Yadwiga (Margaret Sophie Stein), cared for
him. What's a lad to do after the war? He marries her and brings
her to America _ Coney Island, U.S.A.
   Yadwiga exists to be the perfect wife (slave). She polishes his
bedroom slippers, practices Judaism so she can convert, never
questions his many trips out of town to sell encyclopedias.
   The trips are to the Bronx home of his hot lover, Masha (Lena
Olin). Theirs is a passionate and totally physical arrangement,
despite the presence of Masha's mother.
   Herman can't live without Masha so he marries her. He feels
obligated to Yadwiga and remains married to her as well.
   But Tamara (Anjelica Huston) is another story.
   Crippled by the Nazi bullets she took in her hip at a death
camp, Tamara is the woman who bore his children, the woman who is
all-woman and who knows him best. Her independence and humor about
his current situation drive him up a wall. Still, he does not want
to lose her.
   Mazursky's touch is masterful. He pulls just the right
performances from his ensemble with little effort, and retains the
integrity of each character. His camera is not judgmental. If
anything, it acts as an understanding lover.
   Huston is marvelous: She's strong, witty, vulnerable but
independent, sexy, knowing, charming and bitchy. Her accent is a
little irritating at times, but soon is obscured by an excellent
piece of acting.
   Olin, who so impressed with her role as one of the passionate
lovers in ``The Unbearable Lightness of Being,'' gives a stunning
and moving performance as the troubled Masha.
   Stein is a Polish stage and screen actress who makes her
American movie debut with ``Enemies.'' She lends a tender grace to
the simple adoring peasant woman, and emerges a strong film
presence.
   Silver does most of his acting with expressions and moves.
Herman is a man who harbors many ghosts and who, like many who
survived the Nazis, is deeply scarred by history. It's what he
doesn't say, what he doesn't do that tells us who he is.
   ``Enemies, a Love Story,'' is a deeply felt testament to any
survivor at any time, and its universality is in its ability to
caress the humanity and joy of everyday life.
   The Morgan Creek production for 20th Century Fox is rated R.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Motion Picture Association of America rating definitions:
   G _ General audiences. All ages admitted.
   PG _ Parental guidance suggested. Some material may not be
suitable for children.
   PG-13 _ Special parental guidance strongly suggested for
children under 13. Some material may be inappropriate for young
children.
   R _ Restricted. Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult
guardian.
   X _ No one under 17 admitted. Some states may have higher age
restrictions.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Release Anytime</NOTE>

</DOC>