<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0192 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2252EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Buchwald-Paramount 2ndLd-Writethru a0653 12-18 0751</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Buchwald-Paramount, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0653,0778</SECOND>
<HEAD>Arsenio Hall Opens Testimony In Art Buchwald Suit</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: UPDATES throughout with testimony by Buchwald, Mancuso, quotes
from Buchwald; no pickup.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LINDA DEUTSCH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Entertainer Arsenio Hall testified Monday
that he and Eddie Murphy conceived the idea for the movie ``Coming
to America,'' but columnist Art Buchwald said he wrote a similar
story five years earlier.
   Buchwald, testifying in his $5 million lawsuit against Paramount
Pictures, said he later heard his story had been optioned to Murphy.
   The Pulitzer Prize-winning columnist and author claims he wrote
the original idea and had a contract with Paramount to develop it
into a script.
   Hall, testifying for Paramount, said he never saw Buchwald's
screenplay idea, ``King For A Day,'' before he and Murphy began
work.
   Both stories involve a member of African royalty who comes to
the United States, falls in love and takes home a bride. Paramount
says Buchwald's script idea and ``Coming to America'' were not
similar.
   Outside court, Hall, who co-starred in the 1988 hit film and is
host of a late-night talk show, told reporters he considered
accusations of plagiarism insulting and absurd. He insisted: ``It's
obviously our script.''
   ``... I'm offended (by the accusations) because Eddie is a very
bright man. I'm a bright guy. Why do we have to seek a stolen
concept? It's insulting,'' he said.
   Buchwald told reporters he was sorry Hall felt insulted.
   ``I like Arsenio. He's a nice fellow,'' he said. ``This is
between Paramount and me.''
   In court, Buchwald told Superior Court Judge Harvey Schneider
that his script idea, ``It's a Crude, Crude World,'' was based on a
``data bank'' of experiences he keeps in his head.
   Buchwald said the king he wrote about may have been based on a
Watusi king he interviewed in Africa in the 1950s. ``He was a real
king and he drove a Studebaker,'' he recalled.
   He also said he also used an incident in which he saw a protest
against the shah of Iran and wondered what the shah would do if he
couldn't go home.
   Soon after he wrote the script idea, Buchwald said, producer
Alain Bernheim sold the option to Paramount. The writer said he
received $17,500, ``less 10 per cent to my agent.''
   He said negotiations began for Louis Malle to direct and then he
heard that Eddie Murphy would star. ``I was delighted,'' Buchwald
said.
   The writer was to take the stand again Tuesday to explain how
plans for the movie were abandoned and the option was dropped.
   Earlier, Hall testified that he and Murphy had been intent on
improving the image of black people as well as Murphy's own screen
image.
   ``There had never been a black fairy tale,'' Hall said. ``We
wanted to create like a fairy tale _ beautiful _ like the prince
got the girl. We wanted a fairy tale everyone could relate to.''
   Hall said he and Murphy wanted to shape the screenplay
themselves because ``otherwise, it would just be another black
story written by white people.''
   As far as Murphy's image, he said: ``We did a facelift on his
character. He was not the wisecracking Axel Foley character from
`Beverly Hills Cop.' This showed him soft, sensitive,
non-materialistic. He was a gentleman. In this movie, he was the
perfect man. Any woman would love him.''
   At one point, Hall said he and Murphy are as close as brothers,
but under questioning said he would not lie for Murphy.
   Hall noted that two other writers got the screen credit for
``Coming to America'' and said that if Murphy knew Buchwald was the
writer, he would have had no problem giving him credit.
   Hall was followed to the witness stand by Paramount Chairman
Frank Mancuso who described Murphy's rich contract with the studio,
which gives him $8 million a picture plus 15 per cent of gross
profits.
   He indicated Murphy wants more.
   ``Like a good baseball player, we're always negotiating with
him,'' Mancuso said. ``He's a very important star.''
   Courtroom spectators included famed screenwriter and director
Billy Wilder, who said he came to give moral support to Buchwald
and Bernheim, who is also a plaintiff.
   Hall's appearance in the downtown courthouse set off a buzz of
excitement. Several deputies and bailiffs rushed to the court to
get his autograph and one brought a camera to get his picture taken
with Hall.
   Buchwald, observing the commotion, shook his head and said,
``All this over a breach-of-contract suit?''
</TEXT>

</DOC>