<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 2036EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d e BC-Theater     12-17 0391</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Theater,0398</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Sunshine,' A Play by William Mastrosimone, Opens Off-Broadway</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: No PMs planned.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL KUCHWARA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Drama Critic</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It's not exactly boy-meets-girl, but
``Sunshine'' by William Mastrosimone deals unconvincingly with the
relationship between two unhappy strangers looking for love.
   The play, the second offering of the season by off-Broadway's
Circle Repertory Company, opened Sunday night.
   The title character (Jennifer Jason Leigh) is a small-time porno
queen who works in a place called Club Paradise where the women sit
in isolated Plexiglas booths and talk dirty to the customers. She's
the star of the place, has a large following of regular customers
and even gets her name up in lights.
   Two such raunchy scenes frame the heart of the one-act play, an
unlikely and lengthy encounter between Sunshine and her White
Knight, a disillusioned paramedic named Nelson. Their meeting
occurs bizarrely. Sunshine bursts into Nelson's shabby studio
apartment one night after jumping out of a van driven by her
husband.
   It doesn't take long before they are serving as each other's
analyst and patient, offering advice and telling their individual
tales of woe. The anguish level is pretty high. He's trying to
reconcile with his wife who left him some seven years ago. She's
trying to break from a dominating husband and a degrading job.
   John Dossett is fine as Nelson, considering he is forced to
recite _ with a straight face _ such lines as ``My soul hurts.''
Leigh is even better. She brings a conviction to what could be _
and often is _ the stock role of the bad girl with a good heart.
Her tough-as-nails exterior gradually softens, revealing a
vulnerability that rings true no matter what Mastrosimone has her
say. And Jordan Mott delivers a memorable vignette as a college
student, one of Sunshine's more pathetic customers.
   The playwright is best known for ``Extremities,'' a revenge
fantasy play that later became a film. It dealt with one woman's
attempt to punish a would-be rapist. ``Sunshine'' takes a less
savage look at the same subject _ how men and women regard each
other and what sex, whether violent or not, can do to a
relationship.
   Marshall W. Mason directs ``Sunshine'' with his customary
energy, and the production rarely falters, even if you don't
believe the dialogue or plot Mastrosimone has concocted.
</TEXT>

</DOC>