<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0183 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2242EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-BusCrashTrial 5thLd-Writethru a0829 12-21 0959</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bus Crash Trial, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0829,0983</SECOND>
<HEAD>Manslaughter Convictions in Nation's Worst Alcohol-Related Accident</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: RETRANSMITTING to CORRECT writethru sequence; leads with 11
grafs to UPDATE with Mahoney quotes, sentencing hearing, jury adjourned
for the night.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos XCRL2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHARLES WOLFE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CARROLLTON, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Larry Mahoney was convicted Thursday of
27 counts of second-degree manslaughter in the nation's deadliest
alcohol-related traffic crash, which claimed the lives of 27 people
riding home from a church outing.
   The jury also convicted Mahoney on 12 counts of first-degree
assault and all but one of the 42 wanton endangerment counts he was
charged with in the fiery crash on May 14, 1988.
   ``I accept your verdict,'' Mahoney later told jurors, and
collapsed in tears.
   Mahoney, a 36-year-old chemical plant worker, escaped a possible
life sentence when the jury opted for the less serious charge of
manslaughter, which carries a maximum prison sentence of five to 10
years. He had been charged with 27 murder counts, but the jurors
had the option of two lesser charges.
   The only acquittal was on a charge of wanton endangerment of
Clint Bradley, a motorist whose car nearly was struck by Mahoney's
pickup, which was traveling the wrong way down an interstate
highway.
   Defense attorneys had acknowledged that Mahoney was drinking on
the day of the accident; however, they argued that a defective bus
design was the primary cause of the deaths, and that he had been
tricked into drunkenness.
   The jury deliberated about 11 hours and returning shortly before
4 p.m., when the lengthy verdict was read in Carroll County Circuit
Court. Jurors decided to begin immediately the penalty phase of the
trial, in which they would make a sentencing recommendation to
Circuit Judge Charles Satterwhite.
   Mahoney took the witness stand during the sentencing hearing and
told the jurors that he intended, after prison, to warn
schoolchildren of the dangers of drinking and driving.
   ``I know God kept me alive for a reason,'' Mahoney said. ``I
accept your verdict. ... I want you to know I don't feel bad toward
you in any way.''
   If at least one school child heeds his warning, Mahoney said,
``at least that will be one life saved.''
   After the one-hour hearing, the jury decided to quit for the
night and resume its work Friday in recommending the sentence to
Satterwhite. Two jurors were sick, said William Summers, a defense
attorney.
   Besides the manslaughter penalty, Mahoney could be punished more
severely for first-degree assault, which carries a possible
sentence of 10 to 20 years in prison. First-degree wanton
endangerment is punishable by one to five years in prison.
   The judge decides whether the prison sentences are served at the
same time or consecutively.
   Mahoney bowed his head slightly, his eyes fixed on the tabletop
before him as the judge slowly read the verdict on each of the 82
counts. Mahoney remained composed throughout, but members of his
family broke down in tears.
   Mahoney's sister, Judy O'Donovan, patted him and whispered to
him before he was led from the courtroom. Mrs. Donovan later said
she told him ``that everything's going to be all right and that I
love him.''
   On the other side of the courtroom, crash survivors and victims'
families also reacted emotionally, some covering their mouths or
touching and holding one another for support.
   Before he read the verdicts, Satterwhite warned spectators that
``there should be no outbursts.''
   He advised all those in the courtroom to envision the worst
verdict from each person's standpoint, prepare themselves ``and if
you don't think you can handle it, leave the courtroom now.'' No
one left.
   Under Kentucky law, the jury had immediately recommended a
penalty for drunken driving and it set Mahoney's punishment at 30
days in jail with a $500 fine.
   Mahoney was driving his pickup in the wrong direction on
Interstate 71 near Carrollton when it rammed head-on into a bus,
killing 24 children and three adults who belonged to the Radcliff
First Assembly of God church.
   Mahoney's lawyers said he admitted being drunk and driving north
in the southbound lanes of the divided highway, striking the
church-owned former school bus as it returned a youth group from a
Cincinnati amusement park. But the defense said faulty design of
the bus gas tank, not the collision, caused the explosion and fire
that killed the victims.
   The former school bus' fuel tank ruptured and the bus burst into
flames, killing 24 children and three adults. Forty people escaped,
but 12 were severely burned.
   Autopsies showed the fire, not the crash, killed the victims.
   The jury began deliberating Wednesday afternoon.
   ``It's in my mind that I might go to jail, but another part of
my mind says everything will come out all right,'' Mahoney said in
an interview published in Thursday's editions of The
Courier-Journal of Louisville.
   Relatives of many of the victims watched Wednesday as Mahoney's
lawyers and special prosecutor Paul Richwalsky gave closing
arguments in the trial that began with jury selection Nov. 8.
   Lead defense attorney William Summers said Mahoney had been
beaten by public opinion like a ``cur dog'' since the crash.
   ``This tragedy needs to be put behind people,'' Summers said.
``Everyone needs to begin rebuilding their lives. The world has to
start anew.''
   Richwalsky, an assistant attorney general, said it was difficult
to reconcile the spirit of the season with the task before the
jury. But he told jurors they should not be ``more charitable''
toward Mahoney and his family because Christmas was near.
   Summers and co-counsel Jack Hildebrand stressed the twin themes
of Mahoney's defense _ that his intoxication was unintentional and
that the bus was unsafe because of a vulnerable fuel tank and seats
that spewed toxic fumes as they burned.
</TEXT>

</DOC>