<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0108 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1612EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     12-27 0379</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0394</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN JOSE, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   On the 100th anniversary of the Eiffel
Tower, mock charges calculated to wound French pride claim the
Parisian landmark was copied from an ordinary light tower in San
Jose.
   The claim, a just-for-fun charge filed with San Jose's mock
Court of Historical Inquiry, was brought against the estate of
Alexandre Gustave Eiffel and demanded all profits the French have
received since the 984-foot iron framework structure opened to
sightseers at the Paris Exposition of 1889.
   The ``trial'' was set for Jan. 25.
   The complaint says Eiffel got his idea for the tower after being
stricken dumb with admiration upon gazing at a now-defunct,
208-foot light tower at a San Jose intersection in 1881. The claim
does not say what business Eiffel, an engineer, had in the orchard
capital of Northern California.
   The claim will be prosecuted by Santa Clara County Deputy
District Attorney Paul R. Bernal, who admitted his case was built
on hearsay and not a hint of direct evidence.
   ``It was rumored at the time the light tower was built that
Gustave Eiffel came to see it. ... We are going to substantiate
that rumor,'' Bernal heatedly told reporters.
   Lawyer Jacques Dulin pledged to defend the French origin of the
tower, describing the San Jose version as puny.
   ``We,'' he fumed, ``gave (the Americans) the Statue of Liberty.
We did not give them the liberty to steal any of the other
monuments of France.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WALLED LAKE, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mohair and cashmere are nice, but a
weaver has another idea for your next sweater _ fido's fur.
   ``It's becoming very chic to have a scarf or sweater made from
your own dog's hair,'' Kim Mikel, 28, said recently.
   Two years ago, Mikel turned her hobby of spinning yarn into a
venture called Traditional Homespuns. She makes and sells such
items as clothing and throw rugs.
   Mikel uses yarn made from the more than 30 Angora rabbits she
and her husband, Jim, raise in their barn for scarves, sweaters and
mittens.
   She also experiments with various combinations using Angora,
sheep's wool, mohair, cotton yarns, and soon, dog hair.
   For her first experiment with dog hair, Mikel said, she will use
fur from her pet Afghan, Oliver.
</TEXT>

</DOC>