<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0203EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-FarmScene     12-22 0850</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Farm Scene,800</SECOND>
<HEAD>Yeutter Wants Private Sector Pressure on Trade Talks</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Agriculture Secretary Clayton Yeutter says the
private sector should get behind the U.S. negotiating effort to
gain more freedom in international trade for farm commodities.
   Negotiations under the Uruguay Round of the General Agreement on
Tariffs and Trade are aimed at revamping global trading rules. The
talks in Geneva, Switzerland are scheduled to end a year from now.
   At a news conference on Thursday, Yeutter said American farmers
are closing out one of their best years financially and that
decisions in Congress and Geneva will bear heavily on their
fortunes in the 1990s.
   Yeutter said it will require ``an immense amount of effort and a
strong political commitment'' on the part of the United States, the
European Economic Community, Japan, the developing countries and
others to bring the GATT talks to a close a year from now.
   The private sector, including farm groups, also will be
important in reaching U.S. objectives during the negotiations, he
said.
   ``They can disagree about tactics if they wish, or they can
disagree about particular nuances of the program,'' Yeutter said.
``But it's important that we have broad support for our fundamental
objectives.''
   Yeutter said he believes there is broad support for the Bush
administration's GATT proposals but that it is not unanimous.
   ``We have seen some evidence of some undercutting here and there
by particular groups, but we'll have to try to minimize that, of
course, because that simply reduces and weakens our negotiating
leverage in Geneva,'' he said. ``And we're going to need all the
negotiating leverage that we can possibly muster if we're going to
make the progress that we believe is important.''
   Meanwhile, Yeutter said, farm income reached near-record levels
in 1989, agricultural exports have improved and that the farm
credit situation has eased for both lenders and borrowers.
   This will help provide building blocks for new farm legislation
due next year as well as the GATT talks, he said. The 1985 farm law
will expire next year, and Congress is writing a new bill to
succeed it.
   Yeutter was asked if he thought there would be a freer
international market by 1999, one of the goals sought by U.S.
negotiators, particularly for agricultural products.
   ``My personal assessment is that we have the best chance for
significant trade liberalization in agriculture that we've
experienced since the GATT began'' 40 years ago, he replied.
   ``I do believe it'll be a freer market 10 years from now than it
is today, and I also believe firmly that that will work to the
advantage of the American farmer.''
   The United States at the GATT talks has sought a gradual
reduction and eventual elimination of all trade-distorting
subsidies and policies. But administration officials have adamantly
insisted that no U.S. programs would be scrapped unless other
countries did likewise.
   ``Though we may want to make some changes in all of these
programs in the 1990 farm bill because those may be desirable in
their own right ... we're not going to unilaterally disarm
internationally in that legislation,'' Yeutter said.
   ``So, whether we're talking about sugar, the wheat program or
any other program, I determined that we not forgo any of our
negotiating leverage in that 1990 legislative debate,'' he added.
``But at the same time, I am not prepared to accept the arguments
of any individual industry to the effect that says all changes in
the program are off-limits.''
   Yeutter, who joined President Bush's Cabinet last January, was
U.S. trade representative in the Reagan administration and has been
in the thick of Uruguay Round negotiations since those began Sept.
20, 1986, in Punta del Esta, Uruguay.
   While many farm organizations have endorsed all or parts of the
U.S. plan to overhaul global trade, some have reservations about
``free trade'' and how that might affect specific commodities.
   Mike Dunn, legislative director for the National Farmers Union,
said in an interview that GATT operates in many legitimate areas
but that ``free trade'' raises serious questions.
   The Bush administration, he said, has a ``rather myopic view''
that free trade is a total solution to agricultural woes.
   ``But if free trade ends up hurting (U.S.) producers, then we
ought not to be pursuing that,'' he said. ``I think we ought to be
pursuing fair trade.''
   One of the fears expressed by Dunn is that under a global system
of free trade, a country that produces a commodity at the lowest
cost would have an automatic competitive advantage.
   ``I have serious reservations about the wholesale shipping of
commodities to other nations simply because they can do it
cheaper,'' he said.
   Assurances by Yeutter that no U.S. farm program or price support
structure would be abandoned by GATT negotiators unless all other
countries did likewise are not good enough, Dunn said.
   ``When he can come up with positive proof that what they're
trying to do would increase the net farm income of individual
operators _ family farmers _ I think we would support it,'' he
said. ``But that's not the case.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>