<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0215EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-AFL-CIO-Soviets     12-20 0400</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AFL-CIO-Soviets,400</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Miners to Visit; Solidarity-like Support Promised</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN KING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Labor Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The AFL-CIO says it will host a nearly
month-long visit to the United States by 10 Soviet miners seeking
to form independent unions and promises to support the miners even
if it has to defy the Soviet government.
   Lane Kirkland, president of the 14.1 million-member labor
federation, announced Tuesday that the delegation would arrive in
the United States on Dec. 29 for a nearly month-long stay.
   The visit will begin in New York and bring the miners to
Washington on Jan. 3. A more detailed itinerary was not available,
but the delegation plans to visit some U.S. mines to study mining
and safety practices, Kirkland said.
   The miners will be the guests of the AFL-CIO but their trip is
being paid for by through a U.S. Information Agency exchange
program.
   The AFL-CIO has repeatedly refused torecognize visits by members
of government-sanctioned Soviet unions, arguing those are little
more than puppet organizations.
   The miners requested the AFL-CIO's support last month and
Kirkland, likening their struggle to that of Solidarity organizers
in Poland in the early 1980s, promised American unions would
deliver.
   ``If necessary,'' was Kirkland's response when asked if the
AFL-CIO would take the same steps it took to support Solidarity,
which included the smuggling of printing and other communications
equipment into Poland during the period in which Solidarity was
outlawed. In all, the federation gave about $5 million worth of
equipment and other assistance to Solidarity.
   Although it refused to allow the federation delegation into the
Soviet Union, Kirkland noted that the Soviet government had allowed
two trade union activists to attend the AFL-CIO's recent convention
and had granted exit visas to the miners, all members of strike
committees which have been at loggerheads with the Kremlin.
   Because of those steps, Kirkland said it was clear ``there is a
measure of glasnost'' in Kremlin policy toward independent union
activity and said that made it unclear whether the Soviet
government would move to block AFL-CIO support of the miners.
   ``I'm interested in testing its limits,'' Kirkland said of the
Soviet government.
   The Soviet miners scheduled to visit were among the leaders of
strikes by thousands of Soviet miners beginning last summer. Soviet
leader Mikhail S. Gorbachev was critical of the strikers, accusing
them of undermining his efforts to revive the Soviet economy.
</TEXT>

</DOC>