<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0177 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2158EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p AM-VaGovernorRecount 1stLd-Writethru a0683 12-21 0452</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Va Governor Recount, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0683,0458</SECOND>
<HEAD>Governor's Race Recount Certifies Wilder Victory</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: UPDATES throughout to show Wilder victory certified; quotes
from Coleman and Wilder; no pickup.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JEAN McNAIR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A three-judge panel on Thursday certified
the election to governor of Democrat L. Douglas Wilder in a recount
that gave him a 6,741-vote margin over Republican J. Marshall
Coleman.
   The recount confirmed Wilder as the first black elected governor
in history, with 896,936 votes to 890,195 for Coleman, who picked
up 113 votes in the recount.
   The first count of the Nov. 7 election gave Wilder victory by
6,854 votes, or four-tenths of 1 percent of the 1.78 million votes
cast. Under state law, that margin was close enough for Coleman to
get a recount at state expense.
   The first statewide recount in Virginia was conducted Wednesday
in the state's 136 localities. The results were driven to the State
Board of Elections.
   William H. Hurd, Coleman's attorney, said the Republican would
not challenge the judges' decision in the General Assembly.
   ``The outcome of this hard-fought contest is no longer in
doubt,'' Coleman said in a prepared statement handed to reporters.
   ``As an individual and as the nominee of my party, I cannot deny
that it hurts to come so close and yet fall short,'' Coleman said.
``But the system has worked, the people have spoken, and Doug
Wilder deserves and will have my full support as our new governor.''
   Wilder also issued a statement declaring that he ``never had any
doubt about the outcome.''
   Board of Elections employees tabulated the results from each
voting machine to get totals for each of the state's 1,967
precincts and then added those figures to get a total for each
locality. The numbers were checked by independent auditors before
being passed for inspection to the lawyers for Wilder and Coleman.
   ``The results are an outstanding tribute to the accuracy and
integrity of the electoral process,'' said Lawrence Framme,
chairman of the state Democratic Party. He said it was ``truly
amazing'' that only 113 errors were made of almost 1.8 million
votes cast, only 113 errors were made.
   The Republicans, however, said the process needs to be changed
to prevent felons from registering to vote. Hurd said the Coleman
camp found 3,000 to 4,000 felons on the voter rolls, and he
estimated that 2,000 to 3,000 voted.
   Earlier, Hurd had called the recount a ``very worthwhile
proceeding as I think the results will bear out.''
   Circuit Judges Melvin R. Hughes Jr. of Richmond, Robert W.
Stewart of Norfolk and Herbert A. Pickford III of Charlottesville
were present to settle any disputes and to certify the results.
</TEXT>

</DOC>