<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1328EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-HumanHelicopter Bjt   12-24 0678</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Human Helicopter, Bjt,0698</SECOND>
<HEAD>Making Leonardo Proud: Students Fly World's First Human-Power Helicopter</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto SLO1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL FLEEMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN LUIS OBISPO, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Leonardo da Vinci long ago drew a
flying machine powered by a man cranking levers that could take off
vertically and hover above the Earth.
   Five centuries and thousands of inventors later, da Vinci's
dream of a human-powered helicopter was realized this month by
students at California Polytechnic State University, San Luis
Obispo.
   The Dec. 10 flight of the Da Vinci III, powered by an Olympic
bicyclist, lasted just a few seconds and got the craft only a few
inches off the ground.
   Even so, it was the first ever flight by a human-powered
helicopter and was hailed as a historic aviation achievement.
   As a result, the Cal Poly students are spending Christmas break
raising money and designing the Da Vinci IV.
   ``Until this point, nobody had ever broken the pull of the
Earth. This is a great leap forward,'' said Mark Paris, spokesman
for the American Helicopter Society in Alexandria, Va., an
organization of engineers.
   The 97-pound Da Vinci III, completely designed and built by
undergraduate engineering students, officially flew for 6.8
seconds, rising eight inches off a gym floor on this campus halfway
between Los Angeles and San Francisco.
   The Dec. 10 flight, made before an official from the National
Aeronautic Association and a cheering crowd, and two November
practice flights left the inventors feeling like Orville and Wilbur
Wright must have felt at Kitty Hawk.
   ``I was very surprised,'' said Neal Saiki, a 23-year-old senior
and the guiding force of the project since 1987. ``The time it
first took off, I wasn't really expecting it, to tell you the
truth. Then it was just all kinds of emotions going through me.''
   The project has been in the works off and on since 1980, with
much of the work done in a cluttered workshop. The whole project
has cost about $100,000, money donated from aerospace companies and
private contributors.
   It has taken several versions of the helicopter, hundreds of
hours behind a computer, scores of crashes and other mishaps, and
lots of old-fashioned head scratching before the students came up
with a workable design.
   In the end, they found they didn't so much have to refine
helicopter technology as virtually reinvent the machine. What they
have created is a craft that looks more like a spinning wing than a
helicopter.
   The Da Vinci III has a 100-foot rotor made of carbon graphite
fiber (the stuff in expensive golf clubs), heavy-duty foam and a
covering similar to the plastic that dry cleaners put around
clothes.
   The pilot sits in a contraption made of lightweight metal and
balsa wood that hangs from the rotor on a swivel. Bicycle pedals,
rather than the levers in da Vinci's design, operate the Cal Poly
helicopter.
   Even at top speed, the rotor moves slowly, taking about six
seconds for one rotation.
   One key change from earlier helicopters was having the rotor
support a dangling driver, instead of the driver's compartment
propping up the rotor. The change shaved 35 pounds off previous
designs.
   ``Even though this seems like an obvious solution, it took years
to come up with it,'' said Saiki.
   The students hope to save more weight in the next design. Saiki
said, ``We'd like to have someone other that Greg McNeil be able to
drive this thing.''
   McNeil is a Cal Poly student and member of the U.S. Olympic
cycling team who had to pedal as if it were the final lap for the
gold medal before the helicopter got off the ground.
   Even a new and improved human helicopter, the students and their
faculty adviser concede, will have few if any practical
applications. But that doesn't seem to bother them as they go back
to the drawing board.
   ``Saying this isn't practical is like telling the Wright
Brothers, `Sure, you flew, but you didn't make it to Europe,'''
said the adviser, engineering professor Bill Patterson. ``Just
proving the skeptics wrong was enough.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>