<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0226 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1949EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Campbell-Executive     12-29 0315</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Campbell-Executive,0328</SECOND>
<HEAD>Campbell Soup Board Completes Search for New Executive</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAMDEN, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Campbell Soup Co. said Friday it has
completed its search for a new chief executive officer but will not
disclose its choice until next week.
   Campbell Chairman Robert J. Vlasic said the board of directors'
first choice has accepted an offer to succeed R. Gordon McGovern,
who retired in November as president and chief executive officer of
the food-products company.
   The announcement comes amid growing dissent among members of
Campbell's founding family, who control about 59 percent of the
company's 129.6 million outstanding common shares. Three family
members announced Thursday they would sell their 17 percent stake
and urge a sale of the entire company.
   The board is to hold final deliberations on the selection next
week, but company officials said the talks are a formality.
   ``We have interviewed many candidates and are confident that we
have the best qualified person for the job,'' Vlasic said in a
statement.
   Campbell spokesman James H. Moran said he did not know if the
announcement was prompted by a growing rift in the Dorrance family
and increased speculation the company would be put up for sale.
   At the company's annual shareholders meeting in November, Vlasic
said a successor to McGovern would be named early next year.
   Moran said he did not know whom the board picked and could
provide no information about the search.
   The board of directors formed a management succession committee
about a year ago in anticipation of McGovern's retirement.
McGovern, 63, became president and CEO in 1980.
   Executive vice-presidents Herbert M. Baum and Edwin L. Harper
were named to oversee the company's day-to-day operations on an
interim basis. Both were considered candidates to succeed McGovern.
   Campbell sells about 5 billion cans of soup a year. It also owns
Pepperidge Farm, Vlasic Foods, Mrs. Paul's Kitchens, Godiva
Chocolatier and Casera Foods.
</TEXT>

</DOC>