<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0140 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0746EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv02   12-26 0424</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv02,0445</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv02</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Tuesday, Jan. 2</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is Tuesday, Jan. 2 the second day of 1990. There are 363
days left in the year.
   Today's highlight in history:
   On Jan. 2, 1900, Secretary of State John Hay announced the
``Open Door Policy'' to facilitate trade with China.
   On this date:
   In 1788, Georgia became the fourth state to ratify the U.S.
Constitution.
   In 1921, religious services were broadcast for the first time as
KDKA in Pittsburgh aired the regular Sunday service of the city's
Calvary Episcopal Church.
   In 1929, the United States and Canada reached an agreement on
joint action to preserve Niagara Falls.
   In 1935, Bruno Hauptmann went on trial in Flemington, N.J., on
charges of kidnapping and murdering the infant son of aviator
Charles A. Lindbergh. (Hauptmann was found guilty, and executed.)
   In 1939, Time magazine named German chancellor Adolf Hitler its
``Man of the Year.''
   In 1942, the Philippine capital of Manila was captured by the
Japanese in the early days of the Pacific war.
   In 1960, Sen. John F. Kennedy of Massachusetts announced his
candidacy for the Democratic presidential nomination.
   In 1965, the New York Jets signed University of Alabama
quarterback Joe Namath for a reported $400,000.
   In 1974, President Nixon signed legislation requiring states to
limit highway speeds to 55 mph.
   In 1983, the Broadway musical ``Annie'' closed after 2,377
performances.
   In 1984, W. Wilson Goode, the son of a sharecropper, was sworn
in as Philadelphia's first black mayor.
   In 1988, President Reagan and Canadian Prime Minister Brian
Mulroney signed an agreement to lift trade restrictions between
their countries.
   Ten years ago: In response to the Soviet intervention in
Afghanistan, President Jimmy Carter held a day-long series of
meetings and recalled the U.S. ambassador to Moscow for
consultations.
   Five years ago: Japanese Prime Minister Yasuhiro Nakasone
visited President Reagan in Los Angeles, where they discussed ways
of opening up Japanese markets to United States goods.
   One year ago: PTL founders Jim and Tammy Faye Bakker returned to
the television pulpit for the first time in two years, broadcasting
from a borrowed house in Pineville, North Carolina.
   Today's birthdays: Author Isaac Asimov is 70. Singer Julius
LaRosa is 60. Singer Roger Miller is 54. Former television
evangelist Jim Bakker is 51.
   Thought for today: ``It is good to have an end to journey
towards; but it is the journey that matters, in the end.'' _ Ursula
K. Le Guin, American author (1929- ).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Tues Jan 2</NOTE>

</DOC>