<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0149 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1444EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--SalvationArmy Adv07   12-26 0880</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Salvation Army, Adv 07,0907</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv07</HEAD>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Jan. 7</HEAD>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<HEAD>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 3 b&amp;w photos.
ColorFoto subscribers get 1 35mm slide.)</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   They get most of their training in the slums and
ghettos of the inner cities, but officers of the Salvation Army
also must go to a special school for two years. It's a tough school
to enter and a tough school to stay in.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By JOSEPH B. FRAZIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than a century ago, Salvation Army founder
William Booth bade his charges, ``Go for souls and go for the
worst.'' From a brick campus on the edge of Atlanta, officer
candidates spend two years in classes and working in ghettos
preparing to carry out that order.
   The public image of the Salvation Army is that of a brass band,
the rattle of a tambourine and a blue-hooded woman on the corner
with a bell and an iron kettle.
   Less visible are the officer cadets, men and women in their blue
uniforms and sensible shoes, who some day will run one of America's
most least-understood churches. Yes, it is a church, a worldwide
one with more than 260,000 members in the United States alone.
   It costs the Salvation Army about $40,000 to put a cadet through
the training program, described by Maj. Phillip Needham, principal
of the Atlanta officer school, as a ``total immersion,'' heavy in
hands-on fieldwork, usually in Atlanta's inner city.
   The school, one of four in the country, has about 90 students.
The others are located in Chicago, a suburb of New York City and in
Ranch Palo Verdes in the Los Angeles area.
   Typically, Needham says, about half of the students who are
commissioned will stick with the work until mandatory retirement at
age 65. Most will start helping run smaller Salvation Army missions
or other programs and advance from there, probably in the South and
probably not in their home areas.
   Work will include organizing shelters for the homeless,
Christmas dinners and summer camps for poor kids, helping poor
families with rent and food money and, of course, spreading the
Word.
   Classes run the range from Bible study to social work to
computer programming. It's a tough school to enter, a tough one to
stay in. Many who make it are dropped, usually within five years of
graduation.
   ``Some can't set limits for themselves,'' Needham says.
``Care-givers want to help. They are oriented that way and some
people overextend themselves. They don't realize that they cannot
be all things to all people.''
   About two-thirds of the cadets are married, and both husband and
wife must be in the program.
   The average cadet here is 27, probably finished high school and
comes from a Salvation Army church in the 15 Southern states and
the District of Columbia that the Atlanta training school serves.
   Cadets live on campus and are not allowed to work during the two
years. They get a bare-bones budget for basic needs and can look
ahead to more of the same.
   An officer couple with more than 20 years in the program and two
teen-age children receive living quarters, a car and about $250 a
week. That may increase slightly with years of service, but not
with rank.
   ``There is no financial incentive,`` Needham says. ``We're
comfortable, but we don't have any money.''
   Needham and his wife, Keitha, both are fifth-generation
Salvation Army officers, and one of their children is interested in
signing on. Needham holds graduate degrees from Princeton and Emory
University's Candler School of Theology, but that much education is
rare.
   ``This is not primarily an educational institution,'' Needham
says. ``Educational institutions tend to create reactive modes,
with students regurgitating what the teacher tells them.
   ``We prefer to nurture pro-active leaders who find their own
talents and their own leadership abilities. Formal education is low
on our list. We seek out people with basic competencies.''
   The school insists on a 12th-grade reading capability, and
candidates undergo rigorous psychological testing and interviews
before being accepted.
   Minorities are encouraged, Needham says, and Hispanics,
especially, are heeding the call. Black enrollment has begun to
increase.
   Aside from Salvation Army officers, there are ``soldiers'' and
``adherents.'' Adherents, Needham says, consider the Salvation Army
to be their church but do not submit to the discipline.
   Soldiers and officers, for example, cannot use tobacco or
alcohol. Adherents can.
   Most of the training is done in slums and ghettos of inner
cities, much like the East London slums where the Salvation Army
was founded in 1865.
   Booth, Needham says, broke off from the Methodist Church to
create an evangelistic ministry that would inspire the working
class poor and get them into established churches.
   ``But the local churches didn't want them,'' he says. ``They
were smelly. They dressed shabbily. They couldn't afford pew
rental. So they went back and the Salvation Army became their
church. It adopted, and retains, a working-class culture.
   ``In Britain a brass band is a working man's orchestra; it's
tremendously popular.''
   The iron collection kettle originated in San Francisco about 100
years ago when the Salvation Army was collecting relief funds for
families of victims of a shipwreck.
   It worked.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>

</DOC>