<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0248 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2211EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s e BC-APArts:Martin Adv24   12-20 1080</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-AP Arts: Martin, Adv 24,1125</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv24</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 22, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Mary Martin: Youth, Joy, Freedom</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY CAMPBELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Others have dared, but there's really only one
Peter Pan, and her name is Mary Martin.
   Along with her role as nurse Nellie Forbush in ``South
Pacific,'' Peter Pan is the 76-year-old entertainer's favorite
part. It's in his self-description that she'd like to be
remembered: ``I'm youth. I'm joy. I'm freedom.''
   Right now, though, she's happy to be recognized by the Kennedy
Center for the Performing Arts in its annual ``The Kennedy Center
Honors.'' A taped show of the early December festivities in
Washington will be broadcast by CBS on Dec. 29. Other honorees are
actress Claudette Colbert, entertainer Harry Belafonte, composer
William Schuman and ballerina Alexandra Danilova.
   Miss Martin found out she was to be honored from her old friend,
Miss Colbert. ``I was on Martha's Vineyard last summer and she
called from Barbados and said, `Did you hear we're going to be
together?'''
   Although Miss Martin counts her three years of making movies as
the low part of her life, she did make some close friends in the
business, including Miss Colbert.
   ``She came to stay with me in England when I was doing `South
Pacific' over there. She had just lost her husband,'' Miss Martin
recalled in an interview in the New York apartment of her son,
actor Larry Hagman.
   ``In the Paramount (studio) days, they made me up to look like
her. In those days whoever was very famous, they made you look like
her. One night we were at a party at Jack and Mary Benny's house. I
was sitting with Claudette's husband, a very famous doctor. We were
talking at great length. He said he must go see a man. He came back
and said, `I think we have to go home now.'
   ``I said: `I'd like to go home with you, but you can't go home
with me. I'm not Claudette.'
   ``They made me look so much like her, he thought it was. I have
pictures. You can't tell us apart.''
   Miss Martin went to Paramount Pictures after her star-making
debut on Broadway in 1938, singing ``My Heart Belongs to Daddy'' in
``Leave It to Me.''
   ``I didn't like making movies at all,'' she said. She and the
president of Paramount ``out-Southerned each other,'' talking tough
in honeyed accents over her declared intention of leaving _ she
saying she'd go back to Weatherford, Texas, and reopen her dance
studio, he saying she couldn't break her contract.
   The compromise was a leave of absence to star on Broadway in
``One Touch of Venus'' in 1943. She went on to portray Maria in
``The Sound of Music'' and to star in ``Peter Pan'' and ``South
Pacific.''
   Her last show, ``Legends!,'' in which she toured with Carol
Channing in 1986, didn't make it to Broadway.
   ``It's one show I didn't like,'' she said. ``I did the show
because Larry said to me, `Mother, you've been off long enough.'
Now I think my children are going to decide to let me do what I
want to. I think it's very sweet of them. I have many ideas. I
might do something after New Year's. I'm superstitious; I won't say
what.''
   Miss Martin last flew in Peter Pan's aerial rig when she was 70,
at a benefit in San Francisco. ``I could do it this minute,'' she
said.
   Learning to fly came naturally _ and very young.
   ``I put my arms up and took off from our garage. I heard mother
screaming from the kitchen, `What have you done now?' She saw me
take off. I knew I could fly. There was a little problem there. I
hit the ground first. Peter Pan hadn't come along. I broke my
collarbone.''
   Miss Martin was 13 years younger than her sister. Her mother had
wanted a boy but got a tomboy who broke many bones. And young Mary
married at 16 to get away from school, had a son at 17 and went
into show business, her mother was more than happy to raise her
grandson.
   ``She worshiped him; I couldn't take him away from her,'' Miss
Martin said. Hagman, 13-year star of ``Dallas,'' grew up saying he
wanted nothing to do with sow business, because it took his mother
away from him. ``He felt neglected,'' she admits. But he overcame
negative feelings about both show business and his mother.
   Miss Martin was divorced from Ben Hageman, a Weatherford lawyer,
shortly after their son was born (Larry later dropped the `e' in
his last name). In 1940, she married agent Richard Halliday. They
had a daughter, Heller.
   ``Richard was fabulous. We had a wonderful marriage.'' He died
in 1973, a few years after they retired to a ranch in Brazil.
Heller was getting married, so Miss Martin spent a year in London,
then sold the ranch and bought homes on Martha's Vineyard and in
the California desert. She has six grandchildren and one
great-grandchild. All attended the Kennedy Center ceremony.
   Miss Martin has had two abdominal operations for cancer and says
she's now all right. ``Let's hope it stays like that.
   ``In my life I don't dwell on anything. If it's going to happen
it'll happen. I believe a great deal in a higher being. Every time
I can't figure anything out, I think about it and ask, `What else
can I do?' It is always turning out.
   ``I've had an absolutely wonderful life, with my family and my
children and my friends and the theater, which I love more than
anything,'' she said.
   ``I have no fear of leaving the world. I think you have a
happier life if you can feel that way. You go on to the next step.
When it's time to go, you go.
   ``I said to the man who owns Madison Square Garden, who lives in
the same place I do, Rancho Mirage, Calif., `Do you have a window
in the back of Madison Square Garden?' He asked why. `I'd like to
use it sometime.' He asked for what. `I'm going to fly out the
window and not come back.' Every time he sees me he asks, `When do
we start on that window?' I say, `I'll let you know.'
   ``I'm not kidding much. What a way to go, if you could.''
   Just like Peter Pan.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, Dec. 24</NOTE>

</DOC>