<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1048EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Panama 3rdLd-Writethru a0513 12-29 0958</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0513,0985</SECOND>
<HEAD>Top Aides to Noriega Arrested; Vatican Urges Noriega To Leave</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 30 grafs to UPDATE with two more Noriega aides detained,
music continues outside Vatican embassy; picks up 28th, `Endara, whose...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PAN22</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. troops arrested an Israeli
intelligence expert and five other close aides to Manuel Antonio
Noriega, U.S. sources said. The Vatican today said it was urging
Noriega to leave its embassy.
   The deposed military leader was holed up in the embassy with 17
others.
   For the first time since the U.S. invasion Dec. 20, U.S. sources
said there was no shooting overnight.
   Newspapers in Panama City today ran advertisements asking people
to bring back looted merchandise, offering rewards with no
questions asked. In other ads, companies such as Kodak said
warranties would not apply to looted items.
   Army Lt. Col. Jerry Murguia, a U.S. military spokesman, said
Noriega's chief economic adviser and his personal physician were
detained within the past 24 hours.
   Angel Mina, Noriega's economic chief, was detained trying to
leave the country, Murguia said today. Murguia also said that Dr.
Sosa, whose first name was not available, was caught while trying
to enter the Cuban Embassy.
   U.S. troops arrested Michel Harari, a former Israeli
intelligence agent and top security adviser to Noriega who was an
instructor for Noriega's Panamanian Defense Forces, a U.S. Embassy
officical said Thursday on condition of anonymity.
   Lt. Col. Roberto Cedeno, chief of Noriega's state security
intelligence, also was detained.
   Harari and Cedeno were not previously in the Vatican embassy but
it was not known where they were arrested.
   Two more top aides, Lt. Col. Carlos Velardes and Lt. Col.
Arnulfo Castrejon, left the embassy and were taken into custody by
U.S. troops, said U.S. Army Lt. Col. Jerry Murguia.
   Velardes was chaplain of the Defense Forces, and Castrejon was
the officer on duty at Noriega's military headquarters on Dec. 16,
the day an unarmed U.S. Marine officer was killed nearby.
   They are among more than 4,000 people being held without
charges, U.S. sources have said.
   The Vatican for the first time today said publicly it was trying
to persuade Noriega to leave.
   ``The nuncio is doing his best to convince Gen. Noriega to
abandon the nunciature on his own, by himself,'' spokesman Joaquin
Navarro said in Rome. ``At the same time he cannot force Noriega to
leave nor can he consign him to U.S forces.''
   Navarro said the possibility had been discussed with Noriega
since he took refuge at the mission on Sunday.
   A Panamanian official said Endara's government sent a letter to
the Vatican asking that Noriega be expelled from the embassy, where
he sought refuge on Sunday.
   The official, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said he did
not know whether the government asked that Noriega be turned over
to U.S. authorities or to Panama.
   Navarro today said the Vatican has received no formal request.
He also said ``steps'' would be taken if the United States kept up
harassment of itw embassy in Panama.
   U.S. troops ringing the embassy with tanks and armored vehicles
continued to blast heavy metal and rock music all night and today.
White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater suggested it was designed to
foil eavesdropping on any negotiations at the palm-studded
diplomatic compound.
   But the music also seemed intended to grate on Noriega's nerves.
The playlist included ``You're No Good,'' ``Nowhere to Run, Nowhere
to Hide,'' and ``Voodoo Child.''
   ``They should keep it up. To see if Noriega gets fed up and
leaves,'' said one neighborhood resident, Guadalupe Warner.
   Many residents have had their pictures taken with soldiers and
some make several trips a day to feed the Americans.
   The Rev. Javier Villanueva, a parish priest helping the papal
nuncio, said among the 17 people staying in the embassy with
Noriega were Col. Nivaldo Madrinan, chief of Noriega's
investigations department, and Capt. Eliezer Gaytan, chief of
security.
   He said four members of the Basque separatist group ETA, along
with one of their wives, also had taken shelter there as a
precaution. They were in exile in Panama as part of an agreement
with the Spanish government, Villanueva said.
   He refused to identify the 10 others staying at the embassy.
   On Thursday, U.S. troops stopped a car carrying Cuban Ambassador
Lazaro Mora and a companion for inspection and briefly prevented
the companion from entering the ambassador's residence because he
wasn't carrying the proper identification, a U.S. Embassy spokesman
said. The companion got the identification and was later admitted,
said the spokesman, William Barr.
   Also Thursday, the U.S. diplomat said that the 14,000 U.S.
troops sent in the invasion would remain at least through February
while local security forces are reconstituted. He also acknowledged
there was concern about holdovers from the Noriega regime.
   About 12,000 U.S. troops are permanently stationed in Panama.
   In Texas, where President Bush was hunting, Fitzwater reiterated
the U.S. stance that Noriega should be handed over to the United
States to stand trial on drug trafficking charges.
   Endara, whose government appeared to falter at first, received
another boost Thursday when the pro-Noriega Labor Party recognized
his government.
   Party leader Ramon Sieiro, a brother-in-law of Noriega's, read a
statement acknowledging Endara's victory in the May 7 balloting
that Noriega annulled. Sieiro was a vice presidential candidate on
the pro-Noriega coalition ticket in the election.
   Twenty-three American servicemen and two dependents were killed
and 322 Americans were wounded during the invasion, according to
the Southern Command. It said 297 Panamanians troops were killed
and 123 wounded.
   The U.S. Embassy official said about 300 Panamanian civilians
died in the fighting. He said reports of large numbers of uncounted
civilian casualties were unfounded.
</TEXT>

</DOC>