<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0113 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1330EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Glasnost-Books     12-22 0619</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Glasnost-Books,630</SECOND>
<HEAD>At Russian Bookstore, Monopoly Games Amid the Samovars</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT M. ANDREWS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ROCKVILLE, Md. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Panicked over finding a Christmas gift for
somebody who's got everything? Why not pick up a Russian-language
version of Monopoly, where glasnost-happy capitalists can build
hotels on Gorky Street and pay 200 rubles to get sprung from jail.
   The trendy tribute to Gorbachev-style openness is available for
$29.50 at the suburban Rockville, Md., headquarters of Victor
Kamkin Inc., the largest Russian bookstore in the Western world.
   The Monopoly game follows the format of the long-popular U.S.
version and both are published by Parker Brothers Inc., but the
board names are Russian and the play money is rubles.
   The most expensive property is not Boardwalk but the Arbat, a
fashionable historic district of Moscow, which sells for 400 rubles
(about $75).
   ``The game is bought mostly by our American customers who speak
Russian, and is very popular among students,'' said Anatoly
Zabavsky, the bookstore's vice president and general manager.
``Russian emigrees are not familiar with Monopoly. They consider it
more a purely capitalist invention.''
   Nestled among the samovars, lacquered wooden dolls and
balalaikas at the Kamkin gift counter, the Monopoly game is a
symbolic reminder of the way that Soviet leader Mikhail S.
Gorbachev has turned East-West relations upside down.
   Not to mention the glasnost's impact on the Kamkin bookstore,
where business is booming.
   The store was founded by Russian emigre Victor Kamkin and his
wife, Elena, in 1953. Zabavsky, who was born in Poland of Russian
parents, moved to the United States from Germany in 1951 and, after
becoming an electrical engineer, joined Kamkin nearly 20 years
later.
   Since Kamkin died in 1974, Zabavsky has shared day-to-day
supervision of the business with Elena Kamkin.
   The bookstore boasts about 2.5 million volumes and an estimated
250,000 separate titles, as well as numerous Russian magazines and
newspapers. It had $2.5 million in sales last year. Its biggest
customers are U.S. government agencies, the academic community,
corporations and Soviet emigrees.
   ``I see grandmothers _ babushkas _ coming in here and spending
their pension money on Russian children's books, to make sure their
grandchildren will learn their mother tongue,'' he said.
   By all accounts, those figures make Kamkin the biggest Russian
bookstore outside the Soviet Union. In Moscow, the four-story Dom
Knigi (``House of Books'') a mile from the Kremlin stocks more
volumes _ many of them obscure, unread political documents _ but
students of Soviet affairs say Kamkin offers a much wider selection
of titles.
   Glasnost has meant the end of Kamkin's role as a clandestine
rendezvous point for Cold War adversaries, Zabavsky said in an
interview.
   Nowadays, he said, U.S. intelligence agents and KGB officers
from the Soviet Embassy no longer appear regularly to roam Kamkin's
aisles, spying on each other in the hope of learning what the other
side is reading.
   Moreover, Zabavsky says he's astounded by the abundance of
Russian books flooding the export market, many of them once
suppressed or banned by Soviet authorities.
   ``We publish a weekly catalog of books for our 18,000 mail-order
subscribers, and we offer about 1,000 new titles every month,''
Zabavsky said. ``In the past, a half-dozen of those titles might be
bestsellers. Now we have a problem deciding because everything is a
bestseller, many of them never been published before.''
   He shakes his head as he mentions Soviet exports of works by
once-disgraced authors Alexander Solzhenitsyn, Vasily Aksenov, Roy
Medvedev, Vasily Grossman and Vladimir Voinovich. Even Vladimir
Nabokov's erotic ``Lolita'' is now published by the Soviets, he
says.
   ``Never in my wildest dreams did I think I would ever see them
in print,'' he said. ``This glasnost, it's really overwhelming.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>