<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0095 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1547EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WaterWoes     12-19 0644</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Water Woes,0665</SECOND>
<HEAD>Early Rising Necessary to Cope With South Florida Water Limits</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRIAN MURPHY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FORT LAUDERDALE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   David Register rose with the sun
Tuesday and by 7 a.m. his pickup was gleaming under a cloudless
sky. Neighbor Allan Edwards was already spraying fertilizer and
water on new sod patches and palm trees.
   ``Man, I'd usually be sleeping now,'' Register, 19, said as he
hosed suds from the truck's hood.
   By the dawn's early light, residents of southern Florida
sprinkled their lawns and scrubbed their cars under mandatory
water-use restrictions that limit such activities to early-morning
hours on certain days.
   ``It's a little inconvenience, sure,'' said Edwards. ``But the
alternative _ no water _ is a lot worse.''
   The restrictions, drafted in response to the region's worst
drought in 27 years, took effect Monday and limit home car washing
and lawn watering to 4 a.m. to 8 a.m. for the more than 4 million
people from Jupiter to Key West.
   Residents of even-numbered addresses were allowed the water-use
privilege Tuesday. Odd-numbered homes can open the tap early
Wednesday.
   Police and water management officials say no $25 violation fines
were issued Monday, but no records were kept for first-time
warnings.
   ``People have generally responded very quickly, and I'm
impressed with that,'' said Bruce Adams, water shortage coordinator
for the South Florida Water Management District.
   In Miami, Metro-Dade police Detective Donald Blocker said
officers will not actively seek out violators but will investigate
complaints.
   ``We don't have a special task force or anything,'' he said.
``We'll be looking into reports on a low-priority basis.''
   Water managers are seeking a 15 percent reduction in the nearly
745 million gallons of water used each day in Palm Beach, Broward,
Dade and Monroe counties. Later this week, officials will determine
if the cutbacks are successful.
   For the time being, water officials are busy answering
questions. Nearly 900 calls an hour were registered Monday at the
water management district's West Palm Beach office.
   As of Tuesday, the National Weather Service in Miami reported
42.31 inches of rain this year, more than 14.4 inches below normal.
That compared to 42.23 inches in 1962 and 41.78 inches in 1961,
according to weather service records.
   Some sections of Florida's southeast coast are 33 inches below
normal rainfall amounts, and most are off by at least 15 inches.
   In addition, much of the region has had record high temperatures
in the mid- to upper 80s since Monday.
   Mandatory water restrictions have been in effect since February
in the 16-county Southwest Florida Water Management District, which
includes the Tampa Bay area. The Palatka-based St. Johns River
district in northern Florida adopted restrictions in August.
   The restrictions in South Florida are the most extensive since
1981, the area's last major drought.
   Pressure on the region's water system is exacerbated by seasonal
tourists, who swell beachside populations.
   ``If Florida's in trouble, we have to do our part,'' said Sal
Crocco, 70, of Albany, N.Y., who washed his car about 6:30 a.m.
near Fort Lauderdale Beach. ``Visitors use water, too.''
   But Alex Green, a New York City resident who has been coming to
Miami Beach since the 1970s, said he does not believe the large
tourist hotels will turn off sprinklers and decorative fountains.
   ``You think they want dead trees and brown grass?'' he said.
``They'd rather pay a fine than lose customers.''
   At Deluxe Wash &amp; Wax Inc. in Oakland Park, only a few additional
cars arrived Monday, said manager Phil Rinland. Car washes that
recycle water are not affected by the restrictions.
   ``Nobody's going to listen to a $25 fine,'' he said. ``You got
to hit them with $100, then $500, if you really want people to pay
attention to this. As long as water is coming out of the tap,
people are not going to take this seriously.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>