<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0160 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2235EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-StelloNomination 1stLd-Writethru   12-19 0716</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stello Nomination, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0738,690</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Nominee For Weapons Post Draws Mixed Reviews</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS penultimate graf to CORRECT Greenspun's first name to Julian
sted Julius</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush's nominee to head nuclear
weapons production said Tuesday that delays in a Senate
confirmation vote are undermining national security by prolonging a
leadership vacuum in the arms program.
   ``It is our country that is suffering'' as a result of Senate
inaction, Victor Stello Jr., told the Armed Services Committee at
the close of a five-hour hearing. It was the second time in five
weeks that Stello had testified to the panel.
   ``The defense nuclear facilities are in a state of disarray,''
Stello said, alluding to a series of safety and management crises
at the weapons production plants that have forced many of the key
facilities to close in recent years.
   Bush submitted Stello's nomination to the Senate on July 24 but
the first confirmation hearing was not held mid-November, when
Energy Secretary James D. Watkins personally pleaded with the
committee to approve the nomination quickly. Watkins said he needed
Stello to improve safety conditions at the arms plants.
   The department has been without a confirmed head of weapons
production for more than a year.
   The committee Tuesday heard sharply conflicting testimony about
Stello's qualifications for the job and about controversial actions
he took during his more than two decades as a staff official of the
Nuclear Regulatory Commission, which establishes and enforces rules
on the commercial use of nuclear power.
   Sen. James Exon, D-Neb., acting chairman of the committee, said
the panel probably would meet in closed session shortly after
Congress reconvenes in January to decide when to vote on
recommending either confirmation or rejection of the nominee.
   Fewer than half of the 20-member committee attended Tuesday's
hearing. Most panel members have not said publicly whether they
will vote for Stello, although at least three Democratic members _
Timothy Wirth of Colorado, John Glenn of Ohio and Edward Kennedy of
Massachusetts _ are strongly opposed, and all nine Republican
members are expected to support the nomination.
   Of the five former members of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission
who testified, three strongly endorsed Stello's nomination and two
raised serious doubts about his suitability.
   John Ahearne, who was a commission member from 1978-83, said the
Energy Department ``needs somebody who is tough'' enough to force a
turnaround in the management of the nuclear weapons facilities, and
that Stello would fit the bill.
   ``Vic Stello is the first name that would come to my mind'' as a
good candidate for the job of assistant energy secretary for
defense programs, Ahearne said.
   Peter Bradford, a commission member from 1977-82, said he was
troubled by several allegations that have been made against Stello
since the time Bradford left the agency, including a charge that
Stello authorized an unusual cash payment to an informant in order
to pursue a personal vendetta within the commission.
   Bradford said this and other allegations must be ``credibly
disposed of'' by the Senate before any confirmation vote is taken.
   Sen. Albert Gore Jr., D-Tenn., questioned a panel of former NRC
investigators about Stello's role in the investigations of the 1979
Three Mile Island nuclear power plant accident in Pennsylvania, the
worst nuclear accident in U.S. history.
   John Sinclair, a former NRC investigator and now a member of the
Commerce Department inspector general's office, said under
questioning from Gore that Stello had misled Justice Department
investigators about the existence of cooling pipe test records held
by the utility that operated the Three Mile Island reactors.
   ``That makes me think Mr. Stello was more interested in making
sure the company wasn't subject to any punishment ... than in
protecting the public safety,'' Gore said. ``I'm deeply troubled by
this testimony.''
   Sinclair and two other former NRC investigators, Jim McCarten
and David Gamble, plus Julian Greenspun, a former Justice
Department investigator, said in response to a question from Exon
that they would not recommend Stello's confirmation.
   In seeking to defend his actions following the Three Mile Island
accident, Stello tried to read from an FBI report, but Exon stopped
him, saying the report's contents could not be made public until
the FBI agreed. Exon said the panel would seek to get that approval.
</TEXT>

</DOC>