<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0182 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2013EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Pacific-Bases     12-20 0292</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pacific-Bases,280</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pentagon Says No Major Withdrawal from Pacific Bases Planned</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pentagon officials said Wednesday they were
not actively considering a major military withdrawal from East
Asia, although planners recently drafted a memorandum outlining
such a possibility.
   The Asahi Shimbun and Washington Post reported this week that
Pentagon officials were considering closing U.S. bases in the
Philippines and withdrawing forces from South Korea and Japan.
   That policy was outlined in a paper discussed at a meeting
Monday involving Defense Secretary Dick Cheney and Gen. Colin
Powell, chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, but many other
options also were discussed, said two Pentagon officials.
   ``There is no decision and no deadline for a decision,'' said
one of the sources. Both officials spoke on the condition he not be
further identified.
   Another source said that no such withdrawal was being considered
for the next two or three years.
   ``Our security in the Pacific is based on a robust presence,
based on agreements with as many nations as possible,'' and
therefore the United States is unlikely to close any East Asian
bases in the near future, said another official.
   The meeting among the top Pentagon brass concerned ``the future
of U.S. security interests in the Pacific. We are looking at a
number of long-term possibilities,'' said one source.
   Consideration of reducing the U.S. military presence in the
Pacific was prompted by changes in Eastern Europe and budgetary
restraints.
   ``There has been a change'' in the Soviet Bloc. ``The threat is
reduced,'' said the source.
   U.S. Pacific forces include 222,238 personnel _ 50,000 in Japan,
45,000 in Hawaii, 32,000 in South Korea, and 34,000 at sea,
according to Pentagon statistics. Additionally, the United States
operates two important bases in the Philippines.
</TEXT>

</DOC>