<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0092 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1505EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Economy Bjt   12-19 0820</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Economy, Bjt,780</SECOND>
<HEAD>Inflation Up 0.4 Percent, Led by Food and Heating Fuel</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVE SKIDMORE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Stubborn price increases for services kept
consumer inflation at 0.4 percent last month despite a drop in
gasoline costs, the government said Tuesday in a report economists
said could discourage the Federal Reserve Board from cutting
interest rates.
   The gain in the Labor Department's Consumer Price Index,
bolstered by a 0.6 percent advance in the service sector, showed
that inflation is persisting despite sluggishness in housing and
manufacturing, analysts said.
   November's seasonally adjusted increase, which translated into
an annual inflation rate of 4.9 percent, followed a brisk 0.5
percent rise in October and relatively modest hikes from June
through September.
   Through the first 11 months of this year, consumer prices have
risen at an annual rate of 4.6 percent, up only slightly from the
4.4 percent price gains in both 1988 and 1987.
   ``There's no evidence that inflation is accelerating, but
there's a lot of evidence that says inflation is pretty stubborn at
current levels,'' said economist Robert Brusca of Nikko
International Securities Co. Inc.
   Last month's price spurt, slightly higher than many analysts had
been expecting, contributed to more skittishness on Wall Street,
where the Dow Jones industrial stock average fell in early trading
before recovering later in the day.
   Before Tuesday's report, many traders had been hoping that
Federal Reserve policymakers, finishing a two-day, closed-door
meeting Tuesday, would push interest rates down another notch
before Christmas. The Fed had brought rates down 0.25 percentage
point in early November.
   That hope had been strengthened Friday, when the Labor
Department said wholesale prices fell 0.1 percent in November, the
third decline in five months. But the prospects of further Fed
action were dampened by the consumer price report.
   ``The Fed could still move,'' Brusca said. ``However ... I think
they're going to sit on the sidelines a while longer.''
   He and other analysts noted that the wholesale price index does
not measure the cost of services, which are being pushed up by wage
increases resulting from a tight labor market. Services make up
about 55 percent of the consumer index.
   ``We've scarcely made any inroads on services inflation,'' said
economist Robert G. Dederick of Northern Trust Co. in Chicago.
``The Fed has a classic problem. It's really hard to break
inflation down in the absence of a full-fledged recession.''
   The Labor Department's calculation of overall service costs rose
4.8 percent in the six months ended in November, only marginally
better than the 5.1 percent gain posted in the preceding six months.
   The department said in a separate report that Americans' average
weekly earnings, after adjusting for inflation, fell 0.7 percent
last month following a 0.6 percent rise in October. The department
attributed the decline to drops in average earnings per hour and
average hours worked per week, in addition to consumer price hikes.
   In another report showing sluggishness, the Commerce Department
said housing starts fell 4.7 percent in November following a 13
percent jump a month earlier.
   Leading the November advance in consumer costs was a 0.6 percent
boost in food prices, the steepest since May. Dairy products jumped
1.7 percent, their third consecutive sharp increase. The price of
fruits and vegetables soared 1.8 percent, the second big gain in a
row.
   Economist Donald Ratajczak of Georgia State University said the
rise in fruit and vegetable prices was probably temporary but
cautioned that the dairy increase, accounting for about a fourth of
the overall food increase, could persist into next year.
   ``We slaughtered a lot of cows (during the drought) last year
and ... it takes a while to get new cows,'' he said.
   Gasoline prices fell 2.1 percent in November following a 0.9
percent rise in October. However, other forms of energy were more
expensive. The index for natural gas and electricity rose 1.5
percent, while fuel oil edged up 0.2 percent following a big 2.5
percent gain a month earlier. Overall, energy prices fell 0.1
percent last month.
   If colder-than-average winter weather continues, energy prices
could rise over the coming months, Ratajczak warned. The price of
crude oil this week topped $22 a barrel for the first time since
April.
   In other details:
   _The cost of medical care, which has been increasing at an 8.5
percent rate over the last year, was up 0.8 percent in November, in
line with previous increases.
   _Clothing costs edged up 0.1 percent in November, following two
months of steep increases that coincided with the introduction of
fall lines.
   _New-car prices rose 0.8 percent; tobacco was down 0.1 percent,
and entertainment costs climbed 0.2 percent.
   Before taking into account normal seasonal changes, the Consumer
Price Index stood at 125.9 in November. That meant that a
hypothetical selection of goods and services costing $100 in the
1982-84 base period would have cost $125.90 last month, up from
$120.30 a year ago.
</TEXT>

</DOC>