<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 0633EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Israel     12-31 0350</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Israel,0362</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shamir To Fire Minister for PLO Contacts; Police Accused Of Overreacting</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir on Sunday said he
will fire Science Minister Ezer Weizman of the left-leaning Labor
Party for alleged contacts with the PLO.
   The surprise move by Shamir, who heads the right-wing Likud
bloc, was certain to trigger a crisis in the shaky governing
coalition formed after inconclusive elections in November 1988.
   According to the coalition agreement, the premier cannot remove
a Labor minister without the consent of Vice Premier Shimon Peres,
the Labor leader.
   Transport Minister Moshe Katsav of Shamir's Likud Bloc said on
Israel radio that Shamir made the announcement during the weekly
Cabinet session.
   ``The prime minister announced his intention to fire Minister
Weizman, because Weizman conducted direct and indirect meetings
with the PLO, which is against the laws of the state of Israel,''
said Katzav.
   Also Sunday, peace activists accused police of brutality and
overreaction in breaking up a demonstration by 15,000 Palestinians,
Israelis and Europeans.
   Police said they were provoked by stones, bottles and outlawed
PLO flags. Police spokesman Uzi Sandori said that in Saturday's
rally 45 arrests were made and 25 people were injured by rubber
bullets and tear gas, including an Italian woman who lost her eye
after a water canon was used. Organizers estimated 50 people were
injured.
   Israeli, Palestinian and European demonstrators joined hands to
form a human chain around the Old Walled City of Jerusalem under
the theme, ``1990- Time for Peace.''
   Sandori said several police were hit by the stones and bottles.
   Four Associated Press reporters stationed along the old city
walls said they heard pro-Palestinian slogans shouted but did not
see any stones thrown or PLO flags waved. The independent Israeli
daily Yediot Ahronot said stones were thrown but only after police
opened up with a water canon.
   Peace Now leaders demanded an official inquiry into the
shootings, claiming police had overreacted and used excessive
force, instigating much of the Palestinian violence in the largely
peaceful three-hour rally.
   The Cabinet and Parliament's Internal Affairs Committee debated
the issue Sunday.
</TEXT>

</DOC>