<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0187 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2217EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama 2ndLd-Writethru a0707 12-18 0954</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0707,0992</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Lieutenant Shoots Panama Corporal in Second Incident</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS throughout to UPDATE with Panamanian denial, further details,
quotes, minor editing. No pickup</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A U.S. lieutenant shot and wounded a
Panamanian corporal near an American installation Monday, U.S.
officials reported. It was the second shooting incident in three
days between U.S. and Panamanian forces.
   On Saturday, Panamanian soldiers shot and killed an American
officer near Panamanian military headquarters. President Bush on
Monday called that shooting ``an enormous outrage'' and said he
would not rule out military action.
   A U.S. Southern Command statement said that on Monday an
American was leaving a U.S. Army laundry in the Curundu area of
western Panama City when a uniformed Panamanian signaled him to
stop and approached him.
   The area is near Southern Command headquarters and less than a
mile from Panamanian Defense Forces headquarters.
   The statement said the U.S. officer fired when the Panamanian
appeared to reach for a weapon.
   ``The American responded defensively by pulling a weapon and
fired two shots,'' it said. ``The Panamanian went down, then got up
and left the scene. The extent of his injuries is unknown at this
time.''
   U.S. officials said the officer was being ``debriefed.''
   A Panamanian Defense Forces communique later called it
``reckless aggression'' by the U.S. Army.
   It said the American ``fired two shots from a firearm, one of
them hitting the left forearm'' of policeman Cesar Tejada. It said
the American was traveling in a vehicle that ``never stopped and on
the contrary, accelerated.''
   The communique said Tejada was hospitalized, but did not give
his condition.
   Capt. Moises Cortizo, Panama's chief of police, said police were
investigating.
   According to a Command official, the civilian laundry has a
contract to clean uniforms for U.S. forces.
   In Washington, a Defense Department official, speaking on
condition of anonymity, gave this account:
   A Panamanian traffic officer signaled the American to stop and
approached his car. The Panamanian pulled his weapon ``and the
lieutenant did the same.''
   The American fired two shots and it was believed the Panamanian
was wounded in a leg and an arm.
   Tensions still were high at the time because of Saturday's
death. Panamanian officials said the U.S. Army commander in Panama
threatened an invasion.
   ``This is the most serious incident we have had,'' a Command
spokesman said. ``This involved a loss of life. No course of action
is being ruled out as a response.''
   ``We are trying to be rational in our response. We are going to
take a calculated plan of action. The U.S. government does not
respond without thinking results through.''
   He spoke on the condition of anonymity.
   Photographs of the 1981 Chevrolet with Michigan plates in which
the Americans were riding showed bullet holes, including two on the
driver's side and one through the trunk.
   U.S. officers said the shots came from Soviet-made AK rifles.
   The United States has taken no visible action since Saturday
other than to put its forces on maximum alert and display them
visibly in its military installations.
   The Pentagon said the officer was fatally shot and a Navy
officer and his wife were arrested and beaten Saturday night not
far from the military headquarters of Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega,
the Panamanian leader.
   Panamanian Lt. Col. Arnulfo Castrejon Garcia on Monday called
``completely false'' allegations that the couple were mistreated,
though he confirmed they were arrested.
   U.S. troops in battle gear patrolled perimeter fences at their
bases Monday and Panamanian troops blocked the street in front of
the military headquarters, but life was normal in the rest of the
city.
   U.S. and Panamanian forces were holding a ``dialogue'' by
messenger, Castrejon told reporters. He said the U.S. Army South
commander, Gen. Marc Cisneros, had threatened an invasion.
   Asked why the United States had not already invaded, Castrejon
said, ``It could be they realize they went through the checkpoint.''
   A spokesman for the U.S. Southern Command, which controls all
U.S. forces in Panama, including U.S. Army South, said he could not
comment on Castrejon's statements.
   The Associated Press learned Panama's Defense Forces sent a
letter to U.S. military officials apparently trying to gain time
following the U.S. demand for an explanation.
   The Panamanian military said the letter ``demanded that U.S.
forces exercise maximum prudence to avoid unfortunate incidents.''
   It said U.S. forces ``disregarded our observations resulting in
unfortunate incidents as the one which occurred on the evening of
Dec. 16.''
   A U.S. military source said there had been no ``negotiations''
with the Panamanians concerning the incident.
   The United States said Panamanian troops were solely responsible
for the violence Saturday, that the U.S. officer and three
companions took a wrong turn and were lost.
   The Defense Forces accused U.S. officers of provocation and said
they ran through a Defense Forces checkpoint.
   In Washington, the White House said the violence was a
``consequence'' of Panama's being run by Noriega.
   Since February 1988, when Noriega was indicted in Florida on
narcotics charges, the United States has tried to drive him from
power with economic, diplomatic and political pressure.
   Noriega denies the charges. He claims Washington wants to renege
on treaties under which the United States is to transfer control of
the canal to Panama at the end of the century and close U.S.
military installations.
   Thousands of U.S. soldiers lived in Panama City until earlier
this year, when they and their dependents were ordered to move onto
the bases. Many dependents returned to the United States.
   The Command confirmed that the transfer of civilian dependents
from military posts ``was being stepped up.''
   The number of families still on post is 500, down from 3,200
last May.
</TEXT>

</DOC>