<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1306EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Czechoslovakia 2ndLd-Writethru a0516 12-28 0653</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Czechoslovakia, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0516,0672</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dubcek, Disgraced After 1968 Soviet-Led Invasion, Returns To Power</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 5 grafs to UPDATE with former Prague Communist chief
in custody; picks up 4th pvs, `This is...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ONDREJ HEJMA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Alexander Dubcek, the former
Communist Party chief ousted two decades ago for leading the
``Prague Spring'' reforms, returned triumphantly to power today as
speaker of Czechoslovakia's parliament.
   In a political renaissance unimaginable only two months ago,
Dubcek was elected unanimously by 269 deputies present out of the
350-member, Communist-dominated Federal Assembly.
   The newspaper Vecerni Praha today reported that the former
Prague Communist Party boss has been in custody since Dec. 23 under
indictment on charges of abuse of power.
   Miroslav Stepan oversaw police attacks on demonstrators in
Prague in November that sparked Czechoslovakia's peaceful
revolution against its hard-line Communist leadership.
   In the parliament, Dubcek shook hands quietly with a few
colleagues and shuffled papers nervously during the vote.
   ``This is a moral satisfaction to the hundreds of thousands of
people who have upheld the ideals of the `Prague Spring,''' Dubcek
said in an address carried live on state TV.
   In 1968, Soviet-led tanks and troops crushed Dubcek's reform
movement and oversaw the installation of a hard-line Communist
leadership that ruled until the peaceful uprising began Nov. 17.
   Dubcek praised the revolution and said it was inspired by ideas
that began in 1968.
   Earlier, Dubcek sat unsmiling before the parliament as deputy
Josef Simuth praised Dubcek as a man who ``showed courage and
resolve in making a personal sacrifice for truth.''
   Simuth, who represents the Slovak district of Uhrovce where
Dubcek was born 68 years ago, said the current democraic revolution
is an outgrowth of the liberal reforms championed by Dubcek.
   Dubcek was among 23 new deputies elected by parliament today to
replace hard-liners and serve until free elections next year.
   Among the new deputies were at least five former dissidents who
signed the human rights manifesto Charter 77.
   The 35O-member Federal Assembly has been dominated for more than
four decades by the Communist Party, and the ``restructuring'' to
take place today is the latest victory by the opposition that has
overturned party control in the past two months.
   Communists will continue to hold a majority in the bicameral
parliament, although without many of the most rigid members.
   Of the 23 new deputies, only one was a member of the Communist
Party. The rest were members of other, smaller parties or were
unaffiliated members of the opposition.
   Those named to fill the seats were agreed to during negotiations
last week between the opposition, the Communist Party and several
other smaller political forces.
   Dubcek was ousted from power one year after the Soviet-led
invasion in 1968 that crushed his ``Prague Spring'' reform movement.
   The current speaker, Stanislav Kukral, resigned today.
   The election will be a vindication of the humanistic reforms
that Dubcek tried to introduce as Communist Party secretary general
in 1968. His hopes for liberalization and his political career were
crushed under the invasion that ushered in 21 years of hard-line
Communist rule.
   Dubcek was expelled from the party and sent to work as a
forestry manager in Bratislava.
   On Nov. 24, he made a triumphant comeback, speaking to 250,000
admirers gathered on Prague's Wenceslas Square for a pro-democracy
demonstration.
   Next to Vaclav Havel, the opposition leader and sole
presidential candidate, Dubcek is the second most potent symbol of
reform in Czechoslovakia and is the favorite son in his native
Slovakia.
   Havel said a condition of his accepting the presidency was that
Dubcek be ``somewhere close by my side.''
   On Friday, deputies will reconvene in special televised session
at Prague's Hradcany Castle to vote for president. Havel will be
sworn in immediately afterward.
   Deputies began the session today by amending the presidential
oath that Havel will take, eliminating a pledge of allegiance to
Socialism.
</TEXT>

</DOC>