<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0215 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1433EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a AM-Flight103-Hudsons Adv20   12-18 0867</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Flight 103-Hudsons, Adv 20,0893</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv20</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Wednesday AMs, Dec. 20</HEAD>
<HEAD>Victim's Family Fights for Air Safety Changes</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL HILL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Months after their daughter Melina was
killed on Pan Am Flight 103, a notebook she carried was returned to
Paul and Eleanor Hudson. A quote written in the back by the
teen-ager read: ``No one dies unless they're forgotten.''
   The Hudsons have spent much of the past year making sure that
Melina and the 269 other people killed when the jumbo jet was blown
up over Lockerbie, Scotland, last Dec. 21 are not forgotten.
   The organization they started, Families of Pan Am 103-Lockerbie,
takes up a whole room at Hudson's law offices. The room is filled
with evidence of the couple's life this past year: letters to
politicians, transcripts of congressional hearings, news clippings,
lists of victims' families, newsletters, a sketch of Melina.
   Melina's mother says she spends countless hours at the office.
``I'm a teacher by profession, but this is my job. There's a duty
here,'' she said.
   That duty _ to reveal the full story of the Flight 103 bombing _
has taken Hudson, a soft-spoken, well-to-do lawyer, to the halls of
Congress, to Europe and to a private session with President Bush.
   He still has questions.
   Why wasn't the bombing of Flight 103 prevented? Why was his
daughter, coming home for Christmas after a semester abroad in
London, allowed to take a plane with a bomb on it?
   ``We thought, `What do we do now that she died? Do we pretend
that she just died in a drowning?''' Eleanor Hudson said. ``She was
sixteen. She was coming home from Christmas ... What kind of joke
is this?''
   She shows a picture of Melina on the front steps of their Albany
townhouse: she is thin, her blonde hair is swept back and she is
smiling coyly. ``She was beautiful. How could we not do this?''
   Days after the crash, Hudson took Melina's dental records to
Lockerbie for her identification. The Hudsons' dentist told Eleanor
Hudson, who remained in Albany, that another area family who lost a
daughter in the crash, the Hartunians, was unable to get
information from Scotland.
   She spoke to them on Christmas Eve and realized her husband
could help.
   ``They just wanted to know whether their daughter was in a body
bag or in a morgue,'' she said. ``I said, `My husband is there, he
can find out.'''
   The Hudsons met more families at nine funerals and at a memorial
service for the 36 Syracuse University students killed on the
flight. They, too, were frustrated by the State Department's
silence after the crash, Hudson said.
   ``To see nothing but a cloak of silence _ it gave us not only an
angry feeling, but frankly it was very ominous,'' he said.
   ``It was clear to me by the end of January that unless there was
some public outcry, and unless people formally organized, that the
government was going to do nothing,'' he said.
   On Feb. 19, the Families of Pan Am Flight 103-Lockerbie held its
first meeting, in Hasbrouk Heights, N.J.
   The organization is partially a support group. But Hudson, as
chairman, has spearheaded government lobbying asking for an
investigation of the bombing.
   The group is pressing the government to tighten security for
international flights. Hudson contends that if Pan Am had competent
security, the bombing could have been avoided.
   ``We've known (Pan Am's) security was a sham for many months,
and it still is,'' he said. ``It's geared to public relations, not
to effectively stopping bombings.''
   He wants a ban on electronic devices used to hide bombs like the
one in a radio-cassette player that blew up Flight 103. He says
luggage should be searched by hand and all luggage be matched with
passengers.
   He also wants the government to make public all credible threats
made by terrorists concerning international flights.
   Private investigations found the State Department received as
many as four warnings of possible terrorist actions directed at
U.S. air carriers last December, one of them apparently directed at
Flight 103, Hudson said.
   ``They had a lot of intelligence in the case of 103, it's just a
matter of what they did with it,'' he said.
   After extended pressure from families and congressmen, President
Bush appointed a seven-member committee in August to investigate
the crash and draft a report.
   Hudson said that could be the definitive document explaining the
disaster. It is tentatively due on May 1.
   Meanwhile, the Hudsons have gone to Scotland to mark the crime
that has brought them together with dozens of other families. On
Thursday evening in Lockerbie, luminares _ candles stuck in bags of
sand _ are to be lit for each of the 270 victims of Pan Am Flight
103.
   The quiet lawyer and his wife say they refuse to let anyone
forget.
   ``I felt, and I feel, that unless something is done about these
things, we will see hundreds, perhaps thousands of more Americans
coming back in body bags,'' he said.
   ``I have three other children. I don't want to see this happen
again.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Wednesday AMs, Dec. 20</NOTE>

</DOC>