<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0257 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0800EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-CommonMarket     12-20 0601</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Common Market,0623</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mexican-U.S. Business Groups Proposing Common Market for North America</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By F.N. D'ALESSIO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Creation of a North American common market,
consisting of the United States, Canada and Mexico, is an idea
which appeals to a large majority of U.S. residents, according to a
new poll.
   The poll, released this week, was taken for a group of leading
Mexican business executives and an affiliated group in this country.
   The groups, the Mexican Council of Businessmen and the U.S.
Mexican Development Corporation, say such a common market is needed
to compete successfully with Japan and the European Economic
Community.
   ``Of the 1,200 individuals polled throughout the U.S., 85
percent favored a North American common market to offset
anticipated heavy competition when the EEC countries drop their
trade frontiers in 1992,'' said Jeffrey Peters, president of the
U.S. Mexican Development Corporation (USDC).
   Francisco del Cueto, a spokesman for the Mexican Council of
Businessmen (MCB), also said 1992 would be a critical year for
international trade.
   His organization, which includes owners, chairmen and executive
officers of Mexico's top 36 industrial groups, has long stressed
U.S.-Mexican cooperation.
   Nino Noriega, a USDC spokesman, said no formal proposals for the
creation of such a common market had been submitted to government
officials in the three nations involved.
   Noriega, however, said there had been some preliminary talks
with several U.S. congressmen.
   ``It's an evolutionary thing that appears to be inevitable,''
Noriega said of the elimination of North American trade barriers.
``It's a matter of common sense.
   ``You have: Mexico, with vast natural resources and a large pool
of less expensive labor; the U.S., with technological expertise and
a highly developed economy; and Canada, with a small population,
but a strong currency and credit power.''
   ``Trade barriers have essentially been erased between the U.S.
and Canada,'' Noriega said.
   ``And we have proof that the same thing would work between the
U.S. and Mexico through the `Maquiladora' program, whereby U.S.
manufacturers have goods finished in communities across the Mexican
border and reimported into this country.''
   Noriega said some people worry about cheap Mexican labor taking
jobs away from U.S. workers, but that that wouldn't be the case if
cooperation created jobs in Mexico.
   ``Consider,'' he said, ``the resources in Mexico and the
potential Mexican market for luxury goods the U.S. market is
already saturated with.
   ``People think of the Rio Grande as being like the Berlin Wall.
Most don't realize that if that wall came down, the heavy traffic _
businesswise _ would be southbound.''
   The telephone poll taken during November for the MCB and USDC
employed a sample similar to the U.S. national averages by gender,
age, ethnic background, educationl level and political philosophy,
Noriega said.
   Not surprisingly, the poll found that people of Hispanic
background, whether it be Mexican, Puerto Rican, Cuban or from
another Spanish-speaking region, took a greater interest in Mexican
affairs than the general U.S. population.
   While only one third of the total respondents considered Mexico
a good place for American investment, more than 55 percent of the
Hispanic respondents considered it so.
   At the same time, though, 90 percent of the total respondents
said it was important for the U.S. to help Mexico to move ahead
economically.
   The poll, however, also revealed that many non-Hispanic
Americans have little knowledge of Mexico's political institutions
and recent history.
   ``Only about a third correctly identified Mexico as a democratic
country,'' said del Cueto. ``A greater number _ almost 40 percent,
in fact _ believe it to be socialistic, while more than 7 percent
even termed it a communist nation.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>