<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0418EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Koch     12-27 0390</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Koch,0403</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mayor Regrets That Blacks Did Not See Him as a Friend</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN SHANAHAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mayor Edward I. Koch says his biggest regret as
he leaves office is that blacks ``do not perceive that I was their
friend.''
   ``I believe this administration has been more helpful to the
black minority than all administrations before us,'' he said
Tuesday. ``I don't think we got credit for it.''
   Koch, who lost his re-election bid to black Democrat David
Dinkins, spoke at his annual year-end meeting with reporters, the
last scheduled news conference of his 12 years in City Hall.
   He appointed the city's first black police commissioner and the
first black deputy mayor for economic development, and under his
administration, the percentage of civil service jobs held by
members of minority groups grew from 31 percent to 62 percent.
   Yet, he noted, ``Many people in the black community do not
perceive that I was their friend.''
   He also discussed his statement during the 1988 presidential
campaign that ``Jews and other supporters of Israel would be
crazy'' to vote for Jesse Jackson. The remark caused a black
backlash that carried into the 1989 Democratic mayoral primary,
when Dinkins took 97 percent of the black vote.
   Koch said the second half of his remark about Jackson went
unheeded. It was, ``... in the same way that blacks and supporters
of black causes would be crazy to vote for George Bush.''
   Koch said he would try to refrain from criticizing Dinkins for
the first six months after he takes office.
   But the mayor did not refrain from criticizing South African
Archbishop Desmond M. Tutu, who will speak at Dinkins' swearing-in.
   Koch said Tutu, who recently criticized Israel for its handling
of the Palestinian uprising and called for a Palestinian state, was
wrong for ``singling out Israel when it's under attack.''
   After 25 years in city and federal government, Koch, 65, a
former congressman and city councilman, said he won't consider
re-entering politics.
   Instead, he'll juggle a half-dozen new jobs _ including
commercial endorsements, a newspaper column, radio and TV
commentaries and teaching.
   Koch said the city is better off than when he took office in
1978 during a fiscal crisis that nearly bankrupted the city.
   ``I took the city and saved it from bankruptcy,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>