<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0155 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1656EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Flight103-Suspect     12-20 0442</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Flight 103-Suspect,0454</SECOND>
<HEAD>Court Hears Evidence in Lockerbie Case</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Flight 103</HEAD>
<DATELINE>STOCKHOLM, Sweden (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An appeals court Wednesday reviewed
evidence against a Palestinian suspect in the Pan Am Flight 103
bombing amid heightened security for the first anniversary of the
disaster.
   Another court in Uppsala will announce its verdict Thursday
against the Palestinian, Mohammed Abu Talb, on separate charges of
murder and attempted murder for bombs directed against U.S. and
Jewish targets in northern Europe in 1985 and 1986.
   Abu Talb faces a maximum life sentence, which in Sweden means 20
years or less. If convicted, he still could be extradited to stand
trial in a foreign country on charges related to the Dec. 21, 1988,
explosion over Lockerbie, Scotland, legal experts said.
   Scottish detectives questioned Abu Talb in the Flight 103 case
Tuesday, but the Swedish news agency TT reported that he refused to
cooperate.
   Abu Talb was charged on one count of murder in the death of a
passerby from a bomb outside the Northwest Orient airline office in
Copenhagen in 1985. He was accused in other bombings in Amsterdam
and Stockholm.
   The 35-year-old former Egyptian army soldier and member of the
Palestine Popular Struggle Front has lived in Sweden for six years.
   As friends and relatives of the 270 people killed on Flight 103
gathered in Lockerbie for the anniversary of the bombing,
anti-terrorism experts in Sweden warned of possible attacks
Thursday to mark the occasion.
   They said a guilty verdict by the Uppsala court could increase
the risk of a vengeance attack. Tougher security checks were being
imposed in airports around Sweden, TT said.
   Foreign Minister Sten Andersson, who has been active in Middle
East diplomacy for the last two years, took a charter plane for his
travels in Europe and was assigned extra bodyguards, the
Aftonbladet newspaper reported.
   Suspicion of a link to the Flight 103 case arose when it was
established that Abu Talb visited Malta before the bombing. He is
believed to possess clothing from the same store to which
detectives traced clothes from the bomb-rigged suitcase.
   According to one theory, the bomb was brought from Malta to
Frankfurt, where it was loaded onto Flight 103.
   The Stockholm appeals court was reviewing the legality of the
seizure of clothing Nov. 27 from Abu Talb's home in Uppsala, a
university town north of Stockholm.
   An Uppsala court had approved the removal of 15 bags of clothing
and authorized the Scottish police to take the evidence to Britain
for analysis. Abu Talb's lawyer appealed the decision.
   TT said the court was weighing whether the suspicions against
Abu Talb justified upholding the lower court's ruling.
</TEXT>

</DOC>