<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0041EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Names     12-26 0979</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Names,1019</SECOND>
<HEAD>Names in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY14</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ELDERSBURG, Md. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former burlesque queen Blaze Starr is
still seeing stars after a whirlwind trip to New York for the
premiere of ``Blaze,'' a film based on her love affair with former
Louisiana Gov. Earl K. Long.
   ``I felt like Cinderella after the ball when I got out of the
limousine and boarded the plane home,'' Starr said. ``Unlike
Cinderella, though, I am very glad to be here.''
   Starr is back selling her homemade jewelry in a Maryland mall,
but she said she loved her five-day stay last week in New York.
   ``Every time we stepped out of the hotel, we stepped into a
stretch,'' she said. ``Nobody calls them limos.''
   Starr did all she could in New York to promote the movie, from
which she will earn 4 percent of the profits. She participated in
14 straight hours of interviews along with actors Paul Newman and
Lolita Davidovitch and director Ron Shelton.
   Many critics have praised the movie, but decried its historic
inaccuracies. For one, the movie has Long dying on Starr's lap,
when he actually suffered a fatal heart attack nowhere near his
sweetheart.
   Starr said she flew to Baton Rouge where his body lay in state.
   ``I walked into the Capitol with a single red rose in my
breasts. I didn't look right or left as I walked to the casket,''
she said. ``Then, I pulled out the rose and said `This is for you,
Earl.' I knew that's what he would like.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Eds: Single name Costa-Gavras cq.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actress Jessica Lange has become accustomed to
working in movies that are not commercial films.
   ``So if one of them does become that, it would be a real
surprise to me,'' she said.
   ``It's just because I'm attracted to things that are somewhat
out of the mainstream,'' she said in an interview in the January
issue of Premiere magazine.
   The 40-year-old Lange's latest roles are in Costa-Gavras'
``Music Box,'' in which she plays a Chicago lawyer contesting
charges that her father is a Nazi war criminal. She's also in Paul
Brickman's ``Men Don't Leave,'' in which she plays a newly widowed
mother.
   ``The roles and the stories that make it interesting for me to
spend six months or three months of my life involved in the playing
of are maybe not what's going to appeal to the majority, which is
fine,'' she said.
   Langes lives with actor-playwright Sam Shepard and they have two
children. She has a third child by dancer Mikhail Baryshnikov.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Leonard Bernstein conducted an orchestra of
international musicians to celebrate the struggle for freedom
throughout Eastern Europe, and then appealed for brotherhood in
East and West Germany.
   ``I am experiencing a historical moment _ incomparable with
others in my long, long life,'' the American conductor said during
the performance, which was broadcast live in more than 20 countries.
   The Christmas performance of Beethoven's ``Ninth Symphony''
capped three days of concerts. The symphony was inspired by 18th
century German writer Friedrich Schiller's poem ``Ode to Joy.''
   In the concert, Bernstein substituted the word ``freedom'' for
``joy'' in the chorus to reflect his personal message.
   The 71-year-old musician conducted the same symphony in West
Berlin in a performance timed to end at midnight Saturday, when
West Germans were allowed to travel without visas into East Germany
for the first time.
   The musicians were from East and West Germany as well as the
United States, Britain, France and the Soviet Union _ the four
victorious World War II allies still technically responsible for
governing Berlin.
   The East German government presented Bernstein the ``Star of
People's Friendship.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Alyssa Smith, the 22-month-old girl who underwent
the nation's first liver transplant from a living donor, played
with Christmas gifts sent by well-wishers from strangers including
Frank Sinatra.
   ``She's received a lot of cards and gifts from everywhere,'' her
father John Smith said Monday. ``People from all walks of life have
given things like dolls and stuff.
   ``Frank Sinatra sent her a doll,'' added the father. ``I thought
that was real neat. People sent cards and money. That made us feel
very loved.''
   Alyssa and 16-month-old Sarina Jones, who received the nation's
second living-donor liver transplant, were recovering remarkably
well at the University of Chicago Medical Center, though both girls
remained in critical but stable condition, spokeswoman Susan
Phillips said.
   The girls suffered from biliary atresia, a usually fatal
congenital defect.
   Alyssa received her transplant from her 29-year-old mother,
Teresa, an elementary school teacher who was released from the
hospital two weeks ago.
   Since her Nov. 27 transplant, Alyssa has undergone three
operations to stop bleeding on the liver's surface, but doctors say
she still is expected to be able to leave the hospital sometime
after Jan. 1.
   Said the girl's father, ``If the surgery had not been good, we'd
not be having the Christmas we're having.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Eds: Version moved on sports wires.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>FORT WAYNE, Ind. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Indianapolis Colts rookie wide receiver
Andre Rison was in too much of a hurry to get home for Christmas.
   Rison was charged with reckless driving early Monday after
police clocked him at driving his 1989 Mercedes at 128 mph on
Interstate 69 near Fort Wayne, authorities said. The speed limit is
55 mph.
   He was taken to the Allen County Lockup where he posted $500
bond and was released.
   ``He told the officer he thought he was driving between 95 and
100 miles per hour because he said that's what it feels like when
you're driving 55 miles per hour in a regular car,'' said Sgt.
Dallard Tackett of the State Police post at Fort Wayne.
   Rison, the Colts' top draft pick out of Michigan State, was
headed to Flint, Mich., for Christmas. The Colts' season ended
Sunday.
</TEXT>

</DOC>