<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0600EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Deaths 1stLd-Writethru a0518 12-22 0478</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Deaths, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0518,0495</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eds: DELETES item on Lee Van Cleef, which was in an earlier PM-Deaths
column; No separates moved for PMs</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Soedjatmoko</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JAKARTA, Indonesia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soedjatmoko, the former rector of the
United Nations University, died Thursday after suffering a stroke
in Jogjakarta, Central Java. He was 77.
   Before heading the university, Soedjatmoko was Indonesian
ambassador to the United States.
   The U.N. University, based in Tokyo, is a loose association of
scholars who research peace issues and development worldwide.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Dwane Wallace</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WICHITA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dwane Wallace, who guided Cessna Aircraft
Co. to dominance in the light plane industry, died Thursday of a
stroke at age 78.
   Wallace worked briefly as an engineer for Walter Beech, founder
of Beech Aircraft Corp., in 1933. He assumed control at Cessna
after his uncle, company founder Clyde Cessna, was forced to close
by the Depression.
   Wallace and his attorney brother, Dwight, reopened the company
in 1934 in Wichita. Clyde Cessna, who had started it in 1927, was
installed as president. Dwane Wallace was general manager.
   The first Dwane Wallace design Cessna manufactured, the C-34,
was a classic monoplane that became world reknowned as the Cessna
Airmaster.
   Wallace relinquished his board chairmanship at Cessna in 1975,
staying on as a $75,000-a-year consultant and a board member.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>William Ray</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RENO, Nev. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   William W. Ray, the executive director of the
William F. Harrah Foundation National Automobile Museum, died
Wednesday of cancer at age 42.
   Ray had served as executive director of the Reno automobile
museum since last year. During his 20-year career in the business
he also directed operations at the Kentucky Derby Museum in
Louisville, the Museum of Science and Industry in Tampa, Fla., the
California State Railroad Museum in Sacramento and the Petroleum
Museum in Midland, Texas.
   At one time, the Harrah's collection had more than 1,400
vehicles before it was sold to the Holiday Corp. The company
auctioned off many of the vehicles and donated the remainder to the
foundation, which now has about 225 vehicles in the downtown Reno
collection.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Roger Hallowell</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PEABODY, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Roger H. Hallowell, former president and
chairman of Reed &amp; Barton silver company and a decorated Navy
commander, died Wednesday of a stroke at age 79.
   Hallowell joined Reed &amp; Barton in 1938 as personnel director and
became president in 1953. He retired in 1971, but served as
chairman of the Taunton company until 1986.
   As the commander of a Navy PT boat squadron in the South Pacific
during World War II, Hallowell was decorated with a Silver Star for
directing the sinking or destruction of six enemy barges off the
coasts of New Guinea in 1943.
   Since the early 1970s, he operated the Cruising Information
Center in Salem, which advised on sailing trips anywhere in the
world.
</TEXT>

</DOC>