<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0166 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1912EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-HongKong     12-20 0735</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Hong Kong,0757</SECOND>
<HEAD>Britain Will Give Passports to Estimated 225,000 in Hong Kong</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EDITH M. LEDERER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Britain said Wednesday it will give special
residence rights to an estimated 225,000 Hong Kong Chinese to
prevent a crippling brain drain in the colony before it reverts to
China in 1997.
   Right-wing legislators in the governing Conservative Party
threatened a parliamentary rebellion against what one called an
appalling wave of immigration. The opposition Labor Party condemned
the plan.
   Foreign Secretary Douglas Hurd told the House of Commons that a
maximum of 50,000 key people in Hong Kong's public and private
sector would be given full British citizenship, along with their
families. He estimated the total at 225,000 people.
   Giving key people in government, business and the professions
the right to live in Britain was essential to persuade them to
remain in Hong Kong and ensure that it passes ``successfully
through the final eight years of British rule,'' he said.
   The confidence of Hong Kong's 6 million residents was ``at a low
ebb'' and the ``hemorrhage of talent'' was increasing, putting the
competitiveness of its economy at risk, Hurd said. This year,
42,000 people left and 55,000 are expected to leave next year.
   ``Many of those who are leaving would not do so if they could
obtain the assurance of right of abode in the United Kingdom,'' he
said.
   Britain therefore decided to offer full British citizenship to a
maximum 50,000 key people from many walks of life who will be
selected on a ``points system,'' Hurd said. An estimated 1,500
families of Indian descent will be included.
   ``The decisive criteria will be the value of the individual's
service to Hong Kong and the extent to which people in their
category of employment are emigrating,'' Hurd said.
   He said long service with British institutions and knowledge of
English would be taken into account.
   About 3.25 million Hong Kong Chinese have British passports, but
no residence rights.
   Hurd said giving all of them the right to live in Britain would
create ``unacceptable strains here'' while giving residency to just
a few wouldn't solve Hong Kong's problem and might make it worse.
   In Hong Kong, the government welcomed the package though
Governor Sir David Wilson. Several legislators said they would have
preferred full passports for all British nationals. Wilson said the
package was not ``solely for the elite'' and would help create the
stability the colony needed.
   But former Conservative Party chairman Norman Tebbit, the
ringleader of an estimated 50 Tory rebels, icily told the foreign
secretary he disagreed ``with almost everything you said.''
   He demanded: ``Does the pledge that we have given for the last
four general elections that there would be no further large scale
immigration still stand or not?''
   Hurd retorted the aim was to persuade key people to stay in Hong
Kong but even if many of them did emigrate, Britain would gain
professional talent and expertise from one of the world's most
successful societies.
   ``This is the last main chapter in the story of this country's
empire. I am rather keen, and I'm sure you are rather keen, that
the last chapter should not end in a shabby way,'' he said.
   Conservative lawmaker Terry Dicks called the decision
``appalling'' and a guaranteed vote-loser in the next election,
which must be held by June 1992.
   Fellow Conservative Tony Marlow said many people would never
forgive the government for opening the door to further immigration
in overcrowded Britain.
   ``They feel a deep resentment after a generation that imposed
immigration into this country. I believe you will not be
forgiven,'' he said.
   Labor lawmaker Diane Abbott, the first black woman elected to
Parliament, accused Marlow of holding views similar to former
Conservative legislator Enoch Powell who opposed black immigration.
   ``Speaking in Mr Marlow's words as an `imposed immigrant' and an
MP,'' she noted that ``people outside the House have listened with
mounting incredulity while elements in the Tory backbenches have
out-bid each other with sub-Powellite rhetoric on this subject.''
   She said Britain must withdraw from Hong Kong ``with honor, and
not in the shabby and shameful way some members are trying to
create an issue of an imminent yellow peril.''
   Labor's foreign affairs spokesman Gerald Kaufman called the plan
``unreasonable, unworkable, invidious and divisive.''
   Laborite Keith Vaz said the plan represented ``one law for the
rich and another for the poor.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>