<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0274 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1655EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Dollar-Gold     12-18 0420</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dollar-Gold,0439</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar Mixed, Gold Down</HEAD>
<HEAD>Precede LONDON BC</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dollar ended mixed Monday against key
foreign currencies in quiet, directionless trading.
   Gold prices declined.
   On the Commodity Exchange in New York, gold bullion for current
delivery settled at $411.80 a troy ounce, down $2.10 from Friday.
Republic National Bank in New York quoted a late bid for gold at
$412.75 an ounce, off $1.75.
   Currency dealers said market activity was light since many
traders already have started to close out their books for the
calendar year.
   But Earl I. Johnson, a trader with Harris Trust &amp; Co. in
Chicago, said, ``The dollar is vulnerable on the downside,'' as
evidence of a weaker economy continues to surface.
   Some traders have turned their attention toward the Federal
Reserve's policy-making Federal Open Market Committee, which began
meeting Monday for a two-day gathering.
   Economists maintain the Fed is likely to decide to push interest
rates lower because of softening economic growth, thereby lowering
the value of the dollar.
   ``(U.S.) interest rates should head down, while West German
rates are firm,'' Johnson said. ``That's a prescription for a
weaker dollar.''
   In Tokyo, where trading ends before Europe's business day
begins, the dollar closed at 144.22 Japanese yen, down from 144.30
yen Friday. It traded at 144.10 yen in London, and at 143.725 yen
in New York, down from 144.15 yen Friday.
   The dollar was mixed against the British pound. Sterling fetched
$1.6020 in London, down from $1.6055 late Friday, and $1.60685 in
New York, up from $1.6030.
   Other late dollar rates in New York, compared with late Friday,
included: 1.7210 West German marks, up from 1.7190; 1.5410 Swiss
francs, down from 1.5480; 5.8800 French francs, up from 5.8785;
1,285.00 Italian lire, up from 1,283.50; and 1.16075 Canadian
dollars, unchanged.
   Late dollar rates in Europe compared with Friday: 1.7245 West
German marks, up from 1.7225; 1.5480 Swiss francs, down from
1.5485; 5.8890 French francs, up from 5.8885; 1.9455 Dutch
guilders, down from 1.9480; 1,289.25 Italian lire, up from
1,286.50; and 1.1610 Canadian dollars, up from 1.1606.
   Gold declined in London to a late bid price of $409.25 an ounce
from $412.25 Friday. In Zurich, gold closed at $408.50 an ounce,
off from $412.50 Friday.
   Earlier, in Hong Kong, gold slipped $2.10 to close at $410.97 an
ounce.
   Silver prices also declined. On New York's Comex, silver bullion
for current delivery closed at $5.565 a troy ounce, down from
$5.607 Friday. Silver fell in London to $5.55 an ounce from $5.62.
</TEXT>

</DOC>