<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0155 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1636EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Soviet     12-22 0649</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Soviet,0669</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gorbachev Supports Romanian Uprising</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANN IMSE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Mikhail S. Gorbachev and Soviet
lawmakers on Friday threw their support to the Romanian people who
overthrew the 24-year regime of Nicolae Ceausescu.
   Members of the parliament broke into applause when Gorbachev
announced that Romanian radio had reported Ceausescu's arrest.
Then, on Gorbachev's suggestion, they adopted a resolution offering
``decisive support for the just cause of the people of Romania.''
   The evening news show ``Vremya'' showed stunning footage of
hundreds of thousands of Romanians packed into vast squares in
downtown Bucharest, demonstrating to topple Ceausescu's regime.
   Jubilant Romanians dumped books from the balcony of the
Communist Party building, rode armored personnel carriers through
the streets and waved tri-color national flags with gaping holes
where the emblem of socialist Romania had been cut out.
   ``At this very moment, the capital of Romania is swept away with
happiness,'' reported Sergei Zheleznyak from Bucharest.
   However, later reports from East bloc media said that
pro-Ceausescu forces attacked the city, and that fierce battles
raged between army units sympathetic to the protesters and security
forces loyal to their fallen leader.
   The official news agency Tass, formerly a mouthpiece of
Communist orthodoxy, graphically chronicled Ceausescu's ouster.
   ``Hundreds of people have climbed up on tanks and APCs (armored
personnel carriers) and unfurled slogans, such as `We are for
freedom!' `We want democracy!' and `Away with the dictatorship!' ''
it said.
   At the parliament, the Congress of People's Deputies, about 200
deputies crowded around a Tass news monitor in the lobby when it
flashed the first report of Ceausescu's flight.
   ``It's a holiday!'' said deputy Roald Z. Sagdeyev.
   Another deputy was heard to comment, ``We are the only two
dictatorships left _ Albania and the Soviet Union.'' A more
conservative colleague muttered, ``They are surrounding us from all
sides.''
   Soviet officials refrained from condemning the violent
confrontations between the government and demonstrators this past
week, until it was reported that Ceausescu was trying to flee.
   On Thursday, government spokesman Vadim Perfiliev would say only
that ``We will be very sorry for them'' if reports of casualties
were correct. Even Friday morning, Gorbachev supported a mild
resolution that merely called for a peaceful solution.
   At midday, Gorbachev announced the latest news to a hushed
session: 500,000 people were marching in the streets, the army had
gone over to the people, the defense minister had committed suicide
and helicopters were hovering over Ceausescu's home.
   Left hanging with that tantalizing report, the deputies broke
for lunch.
   At the close of the session Friday night, Gorbachev announced
that Romanian radio was reporting that Ceausescu had been arrested,
and the majority of the Congress broke into applause. Gorbachev
then proposed the resolution, and it passed on a show of hands.
   ``Vremya'' said thousands of people responding to an overnight
call for a strike moved to the center of Bucharest on Friday, and
soldiers fraternized instead of shooting as they had on Thursday.
   When students captured the Romanian government TV station,
``Vremya'' said, it broadcast speeches by ``the best people of the
country: writers, actors, poets'' who declared the end of the
tyranny and called for army transport to bring representatives from
around the country to form a democratic government.
   ``Vremya'' also kept up with electrifying new developments,
interrupting the news moments after its first report to announce
unconfirmed reports that Ceausescu had been arrested.
   In Soviet Moldavia, which was once part of Romania, about 8,000
people demonstrated in downtown Kishinev on Friday evening,
sporting signs that congratulated their Romanian brothers and
calling Ceausescu a ``fascist,'' according to Moldavian People's
Front activist Serjiu Burke.
   Other slogans called for the border fence to be ripped down,
portending possible further ethnic trouble for the Soviet Union.
Some Moldavian activists have said they would like to reunite with
Romania if it were not ruled by Ceausescu.
</TEXT>

</DOC>