<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0139 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0741EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv01   12-26 0469</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv01,0493</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv01</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Monday, Jan. 1</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is Monday, Jan. 1, the first day of 1990. There are 364
days left in the year.
   Today's highlight in history:
   On Jan. 1, 1863, President Abraham Lincoln signed the
Emancipation Proclamation, declaring that slaves in rebel states
were free.
   On this date:
   In 1735, Paul Revere was born in Boston.
   In 1752, flagmaker Betsy Ross was born in Philadelphia.
   In 1785, the ``Daily Universal Register'' _ which later became
the ``Times of London'' _ published its first issue.
   In 1892, the Ellis Island Immigrant Station formally opened in
New York.
   In 1901, the Commonwealth of Australia was proclaimed.
   In 1902, the University of Michigan defeated Stanford 49-0 in
the first Rose Bowl game.
   In 1913, the United States Parcel Post system went into
operation.
   In 1935, The Associated Press inaugurated Wirephoto, the first
successful service for transmitting photographs by wire to member
newspapers.
   In 1945, France was admitted to the United Nations.
   In 1959, Fidel Castro led Cuban revolutionaries to victory over
Fulgencio Batista.
   In 1975, former Nixon administration officials H.R. Haldeman,
John D. Ehrlichman, John N. Mitchell and Robert C. Mardian were
convicted in the Watergate cover-up trial.
   In 1977, Jacqueline Means, a licensed practical nurse, became
the first woman to be formally ordained a priest in the Episcopal
Church. She was ordained during a ceremony in Indianapolis.
   In 1978, an Air India jumbo jet flying to the Middle East
exploded and crashed into the Arabian Sea, killing all 213 aboard.
   In 1979, the United States and communist China held celebrations
in Beijing and Washington to mark the establishment of diplomatic
relations between the two countries.
   In 1984, the breakup of AT&amp;T took place as the
telecommunications giant was divested of its 22 Bell System
companies under terms of an antitrust agreement.
   Ten years ago: United Nations Secretary-General Kurt Waldheim
arrived in Tehran on a three-day mission aimed at paving the way
toward a resolution of the Iranian hostage crisis.
   Five years ago: Secretary of the Interior William P. Clark
announced plans to resign his post.
   One year ago: British Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher distanced
herself from U.S. vows to punish whoever bombed Pam Am Flight 103,
saying in a television interview that revenge ``can affect innocent
people.''
   Today's birthdays: Bandleader Xavier Cugat is 90. Former Senator
Barry Goldwater, R-Ariz., is 81. Actor Dana Andrews is 81.
Financial writer Eliot Janeway is 77. Author J.D. Salinger is 71.
Senator Ernest Hollings, D-S.C., is 68. Actor Frank Langella is 50.
Writer-comedian Don Novello is 47.
   Thought for today: ``No one ever regarded the first of January
with indifference. It is the nativity of our common Adam.'' _
Charles Lamb, English essayist and author (1775-1834).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Mon Jan 1</NOTE>

</DOC>