<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0306EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-WashingtonInBrief     12-28 0415</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Washington In Brief,420</SECOND>
<HEAD>Organized Crime Strike Forces Will Be Disbanded on Jan. 1</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Attorney General Dick Thornburgh says a
restructuring of the Justice Department's organized crime strike
forces will enhance efforts against both traditional organized
crime families and new organized crime elements.
   Starting Jan. 1, the Justice Department's 14 strike forces will
be folded into 23 U.S. attorneys offices across the country,
Thornburgh said Wednesday in announcing plans to proceed with the
reorganization, despite some congressional claims the move is
unwarranted.
   He defended the reorganization, which had been revealed
previously, on the grounds that traditional organized crime run by
Mafia families has changed, with the mob often working in tandem
with Colombian drug cartels and others.
   Moreover, organized crime is also operated by elements in the
Asian community and gangs ``such as the Crips and Bloods and the
Jamaican posses,'' he said.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Army Flooded With Panama Volunteer Offers</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Army has set up a 24-hour operation to
screen the flood of offers it's had from volunteers who want to go
to Panama and help restore battered public services.
   So many have volunteered, spokesman Maj. Henry Fitts said
Wednesday, that he's been unable to get a count.
   The Pentagon already has dispatched 25 reserve civil affairs
specialists along with 107 active duty experts to Panama.
   Civil affairs specialists act as liaison officers between the
military and the civilian government to help re-establish public
services disrupted by fighting, such as utilities and
transportation.
   Virtually all the Army's civil affairs specialists are in
reserve units, and the Pentagon paged those units for volunteers,
said Fitts, a spokesman at the U.S. Army Reserve Special Operations
Command at Fort Bragg, N.C.
   The Army particularly sought specialists, such as engineers or
people familiar with transit systems or sanitation programs.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Mexico Denies Cuba Using Its Territory for Arms Shipments</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mexican officials are denying U.S. allegations
that its territory has been used by Cuba to transport weapons to
leftist rebels in El Salvador.
   An official Mexican source on Wednesday rejected the allegation
``categorically'' because Mexico has built up a ``surveillance
infrastructure'' to avoid use of its territory for such purchases.
   U.S. officials have said that there are strong indications that
Cuban-supplied weaponry is being sent to the Salvadoran rebels via
a remote route that begins in the Yucatan Peninsula.
   The Mexican source, asking not to be identified, called the
statements by the U.S. officials ``irresponsible, lacking in
substance and false.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>