<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1939EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Afghanistan     12-17 0397</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Afghanistan,0410</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rocket Attacks Kill 10 in Kabul</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRYAN WILDER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ISLAMABAD, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S.-backed insurgents rocketed
Afghanistan's capital Sunday, killing 10 people and wounding 27,
official Afghan radio said.
   Radio Kabul, monitored in Islamabad, said the rebels fired three
U.S.-made rockets from the Paghman heights about 15 miles west of
Kabul. It did not say what kind of rockets were used.
   The guerrillas claimed earlier in the day they had killed 50
troops of the Communist government who tried to dislodge them from
the strategic heights in fighting Dec. 11-13.
   MIDIA, a rebel news agency, also reported heavy losses on both
sides in northern clashes near the Soviet border.
   Radio Kabul blamed Sunday's rocketing of Kabul on the
fundamentalist Ittehad-i-Islami rebel party of Abdul Rasul Sayyaf.
It said children were among the casualties.
   Afghanistan's Soviet-backed government has reported hundreds of
civilians killed in guerrilla rocket attacks on the capital since
June.
   In its telex dispatch, the MIDIA agency said rebels killed 20
government officers and 30 soldiers when troops attacked guerrilla
positions in Paghman. It also said the guerrillas destroyed three
tanks and five other military vehicles while repelling the attack.
   It said two rebels and two civilians were also killed in the
fighting.
   Official Afghan media have not reported any such offensive, but
Radio Kabul claimed on Dec. 15 that government forces found and
destroyed 50 rebel rockets in the Paghman area.
   MIDIA also said Sunday that clashes occurred Dec. 6 and Dec. 8
in Daulatabad in northern Balkh province, about 27 miles south of
the Soviet border.
   It claimed that 22 government troops and militiamen were killed,
and 20 deserted to the rebel side.
   The agency said the government responded with heavy bombing and
shelling that killed 20 rebels and civilians, including two
guerrilla commanders it identified as Chari and Mohammad Nabi. It
said 40 other people were wounded.
   ``Fighting is still going on in full swing,'' MIDIA said.
   The ruling People's Democratic Party of Afghanistan seized power
in a 1978 military coup that set off the insurgency. Soviet forces
ended nine years of military intervention on Feb. 15, but Moscow
continues to back the ruling Marxists.
   Despite predictions of their early defeat after the Soviet
pullout, government forces continue to hold Afghanistan's major
cities. The guerrillas, who are based in Pakistan, reportedly
control most of the rugged countryside.
</TEXT>

</DOC>