<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0038EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-MaineCutbacks     12-25 0684</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Maine Cutbacks,0702</SECOND>
<HEAD>Economic Tailspin Forces Budget Cuts in Maine</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER JACKSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AUGUSTA, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Barely a year ago state taxpayers were
cashing pre-holiday rebate checks worth nearly $42 million. But
with the Northeast's economy in a tailspin, Maine officials face
spending cuts of half again that much.
   While the officials say they hope to avoid any serious
disruption in existing services or layoffs of state workers, they
acknowledge it otherwise may be impossible to achieve a $67 million
reduction through mid-1991.
   The targeted amount represents 2 percent of the state's
two-year, $3.2 billion budget, which by law must be balanced.
   ``To assume that we can cut this level of dollars without some
impact on services, I think, is unrealistic,'' state Finance
Commissioner H. Sawin Millett said last week. ``Sooner or later,
you get into programs.''
   Heads of state departments and agencies have until Tuesday to
propose the initial round of cuts for the rest of the fiscal year
that started July 1.
   Gov. John R. McKernan, who also has expanded a partial hiring
freeze and called for cutbacks in state employees' travel as part
of the new austerity policy, is expected to make the final
decisions by mid-January and present a budget-reduction bill to the
Legislature by the end of the month.
   McKernan has ruled out any increase in the state income or sales
taxes.
   State executives said it's too early to specify what cuts would
be proposed.
   ``We're all scrambling,'' said Robert L. Woodbury, chancellor of
the seven-campus University of Maine system.
   ``At this point, nothing is sacred,'' said Human Services
Commissioner H. Rollin Ives, whose department administers most
social-service programs. ``The last thing I want to do is cut
essential, existing services.''
   The pending cuts come in response to a sharp downturn in the
economy that has caused budget problems of varying degrees for
other states throughout the Northeast, following several years of
robust growth in the mid-1980s. That growth generated such a
windfall in Maine's income-tax revenue that lawmakers voted last
fall to return nearly $42 million in an election-year rebate.
   Among the states worst off now is Massachusetts, which faces a
fiscal year 1990 budget deficit that the administration of Gov.
Michael S. Dukakis estimates at more than $800 million. Dukakis has
urged a tax increase by the end of the year, but that prospect
appears unlikely as lawmakers approach the end of this year's
session, and the budget debate is expected to spill over into next
year's Legislature.
   In New Hampshire, Gov. Judd Gregg is forecasting a shortfall of
$30 million to $50 million. Gregg imposed a hiring freeze in
October and is working with lawmakers to pare state spending by
about $18 million for the biennium.
   McKernan's call for spending cuts in Maine resulted from the
second reduction this year in his administration's projections of
sales-tax revenues, following a review of state finances by an
outside accounting firm.
   The consultant concluded that the money generated by the 5
percent state sales tax, which is second only to the individual
income tax in the amount of revenue generated, should continue to
grow in the months ahead but that the increases would be much
smaller than anticipated. Sluggish sales of motor vehicles and
building supplies have been cited as the chief reasons.
   The governor ordered department heads to recommend spending cuts
equal to 5 percent of their discretionary income for the six months
left in this fiscal year and to revise their fiscal 1991 budgets to
eliminate any growth.
   Those proposals are expected to yield about $94 million in
potential cuts, administration officials have said.
   Some agencies are expected to be affected more than others,
because McKernan has pledged to preserve critical services,
particularly those provided through the departments of Mental
Health, Corrections and Human Services, as much as possible.
   The administration's consultant, Washington-based Peat Marwick
Main &amp; Co., has been contracted to help state officials devise a
more reliable economic model to use in forecasting revenues.
   ``Clearly, we'll be in better shape when we build the next
budget,'' said Finance Commissioner Millett.
</TEXT>

</DOC>