<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0146 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 2231EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SriLanka     12-28 0304</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sri Lanka,0313</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gunfight Kills Last Senior Leader of Sri Lankan Extremist Group</HEAD>
<DATELINE>COLOMBO, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Officials said Thursday that the last
senior leader of the militant, ultranationalist Sinhalese People's
Liberation Front was killed in a gun battle after being taken into
custody.
   They also said the Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam, the
dominant Tamil guerrilla group, killed 28 members of a rival Tamil
organization in an ambush late Wednesday, but three Tigers also
died.
   Foreign Minister Ranjan Wijeratne said Sinhalese extremist Saman
Piyasiri Fernando was seized Tuesday in a Colombo suburb but died
``when a police team escorting him was fired at from inside a
house.''
   He said six more men were killed inside the house by police
gunfire, including another Sinhalese extremist leader known as
Ragama Soma.
   Three other leaders died earlier in similar circumstances,
including the Sinhalese front's supreme leader, Rohana Wijeweera,
after he was captured in November.
   According to accounts by government officials and witnesses, as
of Thursday at least 67 people died over a three-day span in the
ethnic wars.
   The Sinhalese People's Liberation Front began a terrorist
offensive against the Sinhalese-dominated government in 1987,
saying it compromised the interests of the Sinhalese majority
through its peace efforts with the Tamil minority.
   Initial fighting tended to pit Sinhalese against Tamils, but
massacres and jungle wars led to killings within each ethnic
community.
   Sri Lankan military officials said the Tigers ambushed two
trucks carrying 35 members of the Eelam People's Revolutionary
Liberation Front near Nelukulam, about 130 miles northeast of
Colombo.
   Residents of the area gave the casualty figures of 31 dead.
   Sri Lanka's violence grew out of friction between the Sinhalese
and the Tamils, who make up 18 percent of the country's 16 million
people and claim they are discriminated against in jobs, education
and language.
</TEXT>

</DOC>