<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0545EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     12-22 0578</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cold Snap Reaches New Depths</HEAD>
<HEAD>By The Associated Press</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Plenty of evidence of winter was available today on the first
full day of the season, with wind chill readings down to 80 degrees
below zero and up to 1{ feet of snow in the nation's Northern
regions.
   Meanwhile, Miami reported a record high of 81 degrees Thursday,
tying a 1948 record for the date.
   Brutally cold, windy conditions were reported across much of the
Central and Northeastern United States. On Thursday, strong
northerly winds kept temperatures dropping right through the
morning and afternoon hours.
   Temperatures remained below freezing all day from the Texas
plains to the northern half of the Atlantic Coast.
   Temperatures remained below zero all day across the upper half
of the Mississippi Valley, the northern Plains and much of the
central Plains. In north-central Montana, the mercury hovered close
to 40 degrees below zero all day at Havre.
   A total of 40 cities reported new record lows Thursday,
including 13 cities in Iowa.
   The cold created shortages of heating oil in some Northeastern
depots, and led the Tennessee Valley Authority to ask its customers
to reduce their morning electrical use. Schools were closed in many
Central and Northern states.
   More records were expected to be broken today and Saturday.
   Wind chill readings of 70 to 80 degrees below zero were forecast
for early today in the north-central states and down to 50 degrees
below in the Northeast. Squalls were producing heavy snow over
parts of the Great Lakes, with up to 16 inches in northern Indiana,
and smaller amounts in Ohio and Pennsylvania.
   A mixture of snow, sleet and freezing rain was forecast for
southern Texas, with a snow advisory in effect for the panhandle
and Texas plains.
   A gale warning was posted along the western Gulf late Thursday.
   Temperatures were above 50 degrees Thursday in extreme southern
Texas, Florida and parts of Georgia and South Carolina.
   The high for the nation Thursday was 82 degrees at Key West, Fla.
   Sunny skies and mild temperatures prevailed west of the Rockies,
with highs mostly in the 40s and 50s, and in the 60s and 70s in
Southern California and southern Arizona.
   Other reports at 3 a.m. EST:
   _East: Atlanta 17 fair; Boston 9 fair; Charleston, S.C. 34 fair;
Chattanooga 9 fair; Cincinnati 17 fair; Cleveland 10 fair; Detroit
6 fair; Hatteras 29 windy; Jacksonville 36 fair; Key West 69 partly
cloudy; Knoxville 7 fair; Macon 25 fair; Miami 64 rain; New York 12
windy; Philadelphia 8 fair; Pittsburgh 9 fair; Portland, Maine 0
fair; Richmond 12 fair.
   _Central: Bismarck 26 fair; Chicago 11 fair; Denver 11 fair; Des
Moines 17 fair; Indianapolis 20 fair; Kansas City 19 fair; Little
Rock 4 fair; Louisville 12 partly cloudy; Memphis 2 windy;
Nashville 6 windy; New Orleans 30 cloudy; North Platte 28 fair;
Oklahoma City 0 snow; Omaha 21 fair; Rapid City 25 fair; St. Louis
13 fair; Minneapolis-St. Paul 17 fair; Sault Ste. Marie 6 cloudy;
San Antonio 22 cloudy.
   _West: Anchorage 25 snow; Boise 24 fair; Casper 27 fair;
Fairbanks 0 cloudy; Great Falls 21 fair; Honolulu 69 fair; Las
Vegas 40 fair; Los Angeles 54 foggy; Medford 26 snow; Pendleton 25
foggy; Phoenix 48 fair; Portland, Ore. 34 fair; Reno 24 fair; Salt
Lake City 25 fair; San Diego 52 foggy; San Francisco 47 foggy;
Seattle 44 partly cloudy; Spokane 27 cloudy.
   _International: Montreal 10 fair; Ottawa 14 fair; Toronto 7 fair.
</TEXT>

</DOC>