<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1433EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-SECEnforcementChief     12-26 0308</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-SEC Enforcement Chief,300</SECOND>
<HEAD>McLucas Named To Head SEC Enforcement</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN CRUTSINGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Economics Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   William C. McLucas, a senior lawyer at the
Securities and Exchange Commission, was named today as the new head
of enforcement of the SEC.
   SEC Chairman Richard Breeden, in his first major decision since
taking over as head of the SEC in October, made the announcement of
McLucas' appointment at a news conference.
   The nomination of an enforcement director does not require
Senate confirmation, but it is considered the second-most powerful
position at the agency because it is the enforcement division which
has the job of policing the multibillion-dollar securities industry.
   McLucas, a senior SEC enforcement lawyer, had been considered a
top contender to get the nod to succeed Gary Lynch, who announced
he was stepping down last May after serving for four years as the
head of enforcement.
   Lynch received widespread praise for the job he did in breaking
open a series of big insider trading cases, beginning with the
exposure of stockbroker Dennis Levine, continuing through a $100
million settlement with speculator Ivan Boesky and culminating with
the settlement of a massive civil fraud case with junk bond-giant
Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc.
   Lynch took over the enforcement division at a time of turmoil
for the SEC after his predecessor, John Fedders, stepped down amid
allegations that he beat his wife.
   Lynch was credited with restoring morale at the agency and
spearheading a series of major investigations.
   In May 1986, the SEC filed charges against Levine, whose
cooperation led to Boesky, who in turn implicated Drexel Burnham in
the largest securities fraud case ever brought by the government.
   The scandals in recent years have forced Wall Street's big
brokerage houses to re-evaluate their compliance and ethics codes
and led Congress to increase the penalties for insider trading.
</TEXT>

</DOC>