<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0235 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1754EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-CommodityRdp     12-19 0729</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Commodity Rdp,0752</SECOND>
<HEAD>Freeze Fears Power Limit Gains In Orange Juice Market</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID DISHNEAU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Forecasts for a frosty weekend in Florida's citrus belt drove
orange juice futures prices up sharply Tuesday while harsh winter
weather in the North spurred the heating-oil market to greater
gains.
   On other commodity markets Tuesday, grains and soybeans,
livestock and meat, and precious-metals futures were mixed.
   Frozen concentrated orange juice futures settled 5 cents to 5.4
cents higher on the New York Cotton Exchange with the contract for
delivery in January at $1.3245 a pound. Orange juice futures
normally are limited to daily moves of 5 cents but the limit on the
January contract has been lifted pending the contract's upcoming
expiration.
   The runup reflected predictions for freezing temperatures
Saturday and Sunday night in the Florida citrus region, the result
of an intensifying cold air mass that shattered records in the
Northern Plains on Tuesday and was working its way east and south.
   The severity and timing of the cold wave are reminiscent of a
deep freeze that badly damaged the Flordia orange crop six years
ago, said Celeste Georkakis, an analyst in New York with Cargill
Investor Services Inc.
   Nevertheless, she said, ``being that weather forecasters have
been predicting freezes all along, the growers will be better
prepared than in 1983, when the freeze came on Christmas Eve.''
   A hard freeze forecast for the citrus country last week failed
to materialize. Freezing temperatures touched only the northernmost
edge of the citrus groves.
   Heating-oil for near-term delivery rose on the New York
Mercantile Exchange for the third straight day and the 14th time in
the last 15 sessions, still supported by strong, weather-driven
demand for increasingly tight supplies.
   Crude-oil futures finished mixed after a day of erratic price
swings linked to the expiration of the January contract, which went
off the board 11 cents higher at $22.33 a barrel. Gasoline and
deferred deliveries of heating oil finished lower.
   An American Petroleum Institute report released after the close
showed a 1.7-million-barrel reduction in U.S. stocks of petroleum
distillates last week while inventories of crude oil rose 4.1
million barrels and gasoline stocks rose by 3.6 million barrels.
   West Texas Intermediate crude oil futures settled 15 cents lower
to 11 cents higher with February at $21.28 a barrel; heating oil
was .94 cent lower to .35 cent higher with January at 75.01 cents a
gallon; unleaded gasoline was .58 cent to 1.2 cents lower with
January at 53.93 cents a gallon.
   Wheat futures prices rose modestly Tuesday on the Chicago Board
of Trade on indications that China had bid for 410,000 metric tons
of U.S. wheat at subsidized prices. Corn closed mixed and soybean
futures finished lower.
   After the close, the Agriculture Department announced it had
targeted the Soviet Union for sales of 2 million metric tons of
wheat at subsidized prices, which could prompt further buying of
wheat futures Wednesday.
   All grain contracts for December deliveries expired at noon
Central time. December wheat went off the board 4 cents lower at
$4.11 a bushel, December corn was 1 cent lower at $2.33{ a bushel
and December oats were 2 cents lower at $1.40 a bushel. There was
no December soybean contract.
   Wheat futures settled } cent to 2\ cents higher with March at
$4.14\ a bushel; corn was 1 cent lower to 1\ cents higher with
March at $2.38} a bushel; oats were \ cent to } cent higher with
March at $1.52{ a bushel; soybeans were unchanged to 2{ cents lower
with January at $5.78{ a bushel.
   Livestock and meat futures finished mixed on the Chicago
Mercantile Exchange with cattle mostly higher, boosted by strong
cash fundamentals.
   Live cattle futures settled .07 cent lower to .78 cent higher
with December at 78.92 cents a pound; feeder cattle were .15 cent
lower to .43 cent higher with January at 84.60 cents a pound; live
hogs were .12 cent lower to .27 cent higher with December at 53.45
cents a pound; frozen pork bellies were unchanged to .53 cent lower
with February at 51.60 cents a pound.
   Gold futures ended nearly unchanged on New York's Commodity
Exchange while silver futures slipped moderately.
   Gold settled unchanged to .10 cent higher with December at
$411.90 a troy ounce; silver was 3.8 cents to 5.5 cents lower with
December at $5.527 a troy ounce.
</TEXT>

</DOC>