<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0049EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-EnergyPolicy Bjt   12-18 0690</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Energy Policy, Bjt,680</SECOND>
<HEAD>Administration Planning Renewed Emphasis on Energy Conservation</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Six months into its review of federal energy
policy, the Bush administration has come to at least one clear
conclusion: the Reagan-era theme of ``just keep the oil flowing and
keep it cheap'' is too simplistic for the 1990s.
   Energy Secretary James D. Watkins says oil inevitably will be
the dominant fuel well into the 21st century. He has become
convinced, though, that the federal government must do more now to
begin curing the nation of its costly oil addiction.
   It's not yet clear how the new federal role will be written, but
almost certainly it will emphasize the virtues of conservation and
renewable energy resources.
   That alone would be a major change from the eight years of the
Reagan administration, which tried to abolish the Energy Department
and, failing that, consistently cut its budget for energy
conservation. The department's 1989 conservation budget was less
than one-third its 1980 level, adjusted for inflation.
   There are at least three main reasons for the turnabout under
Watkins: the Exxon Valdez oil spill, which turned much of public
opinion against the oil industry, longer-range concerns about
environmental damage from burning fossil fuels, and fear that the
United States is becoming overly reliant on Middle Eastern oil.
   The Reagan administration ``went too far ... in getting rid of
many good programs'' in energy conservation and renewable energy
research, Watkins told a hearing Wednesday in Washington on the
link between energy and national security.
   The hearing was one in a series that Watkins and his chief
deputies have held in cities across the nation this fall. Watkins
says he is looking for ideas on how to devise a ``national energy
strategy'' to last for the next four decades.
   Shortly after he took office last March, Watkins said he found
the department's bookshelves contained plenty of good descriptions
of the nation's energy goals but no policy document that spelled
out how it could reach those goals.
   Watkins also discovered that the department's credibility was
low and still slipping. So rather than piece together an energy
plan on his own, Watkins decided take his policy-writing show on
the road to solicit advice from the public.
   What he has heard so far, after public sessions in 11 cities
from coast to coast, is that conservation, with a bigger push from
the federal government, can help achieve many key energy goals:
holding down oil imports, keeping prices steady, limiting the need
for new power plants and curbing air pollution.
   At the Washington hearing Watkins made it clear he has gotten
the message.
   If the final energy plan that the administration submits to the
Congress a year from now does not put a major emphasis on
conservation and renewable energy resources such as solar power,
``then this thing is dead on arrival,'' he said.
   Even some supporters of Reagan's conservation-cutting moves are
now singing a different tune.
   ``I have been converted to a greater appreciation of
conservation and renewable energy,'' Henson Moore, the deputy
energy secretary, said recently. As a Louisiana congressman during
most of the Reagan administration, Moore voted for repeated cuts in
conservation funds and research on energy efficiency.
   ``I know more about it now,'' said Moore, who is fond of saying
his roots are in the oil patch.
   The big oil companies know a lot about conservation, and they
think it's overrated. The American Petroleum Institute, the main
oil trade association, recently published a leaflet that said a
greater federal role in promoting conservation would only give the
public ``false hopes'' and sharply higher energy prices.
   Public opinion polls, however, indicate that Americans want more
emphasis on conservation and development of renewable energy
sources, and less on oil production.
   A poll conducted in November for the Union of Concerned
Scientists asked people across the nation how best to meet future
energy needs and reduce air pollution. Eight out of 10 said use
more renewable sources and increase energy efficiency. About one in
10 said produce more oil, natural gas and coal. The rest didn't
answer.
</TEXT>

</DOC>