<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1726EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-White     12-17 0292</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-White,0300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pioneer in Diabetes Research Dies at 89</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ASHLAND, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dr. Priscilla White, whose research
sharply increased the survival rate of babies born to diabetic
women, died at age 89 after a long illness.
   White died Saturday at her home in this Boston suburb, according
to a statement from the Joslin Diabetes Center in Boston.
   Her studies identified ways to decrease the risk of maternal and
child death in pregnancies complicated by diabetes, the statement
said.
   White's research and the treatment process she developed
increased the fetal survival rate around the country from 54
percent in the 1920s to about 97 percent in the late 1970s and
1980s, it said.
   Born in Boston, White attended Radcliffe College and graduated
third in her class from Tufts University Medical School in 1923.
   She joined a diabetes practice headed by Elliott P. Joslin, and
in 1924 became the youngest member of the team that established the
clinic now known as the Joslin Diabetes Center.
   White taught at Harvard Medical School and was an assistant
professor of medicine at Tufts. She received numerous honors, and
was the first woman to receive the Banting Medal, the American
Diabetes Association's highest scientific award.
   In her research, White found that a fetus of a diabetic mother
often would be healthy a month before delivery but would die if
allowed to go full term. She concluded that babies of diabetic
women should be delivered by Caesarean section at eight months.
   She gradually discovered that babies could remain in the womb an
extra week to develop. She also learned that although infants of
diabetic mothers usually are normal or larger than normal in size
despite premature birth, they require the same special care needed
for premature infants.
</TEXT>

</DOC>