<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0141 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1521EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-OAS-Panama     12-22 0641</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-OAS-Panama,640</SECOND>
<HEAD>OAS Issues Mild Resolution Calling for Troops to Leave Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-US-Panama Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRYNA BRENNAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Organization of American States, in a rare
move, closed ranks formally against the United States on Friday for
invading Panama. A State Department spokesman said: ``We are
outraged.''
   A pre-dawn OAS vote followed a marathon emergency session that
began Wednesday hours after thousands of U.S. troops assaulted
Panama and attempted to capture dictator Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   OAS members cast aside Nicaraguan and Panamanian calls for
condemnation, approving instead a resolution ``to deeply regret the
military intervention in Panama'' and call for the withdrawal of
troops used in the U.S. action. It did not specify a timetable.
   The written resolution was considerably milder than the oral
debates in which even staunch U.S. allies spoke out against the
invasion. But it was the first time since the so-called tuna wars
along South America's Pacific coast in early 1970s that the OAS
issued such a strong document against an American action.
   The United States, however, said it opposed any type of rebuff.
   ``We are outraged,'' State Department spokesman Richard Boucher
said. ``It is unacceptable.''
   A prepared State Department statement said: ``We are
disappointed that the OAS missed an historic opportunity to get
beyond its traditional narrow concern over nonintervention. The
resolution is unbalanced. It does not cite the root problem _
Noriega. It also fails to recognize the threat to Americans in
Noriega's `state of war' declaration, our Panama Canal Treaty
rights and our sovereign right to self-defense.''
   The State Department statement noted that the language of the
resolution was to ``regret'' rather than condemn. The Spanish
version of the resolution, however, translates closer to ``deeply
deplore.''
   ``That's how they sold it to the Caribbean nations,'' said a
State Department official who asked not to be identified.
   Shastri Ali, the No. 2 at the Trinidad and Tobago Embassy, said
Friday: ``What we voted in favor of was to deeply regret. It seems
we agreed to different things.''
   John Maisto, the U.S. deputy permanent representative to the
OAS, earlier called the final resolution ``a mixed bag. ... We're a
little disappointed. It certainly wasn't an extreme resolution, but
it's a little detached from what is really happening in Panama.''
   The OAS approved the resolution on a 20-1 vote. Abstentions came
from El Salvador, Honduras, Venezuela, Antigua and Barbuda, Costa
Rica and Guatemala.
   The resolution noted ``the serious events (in Panama),
especially the armed clashes resulting from the military
intervention by the United States and the deplorable loss of lives
and property.''
   The State Department statement said ``part of the explanation''
for the resolution was ``that the rightful representative of the
new Panamanian government was not at the meeting.''
   The OAS members rebuffed a request by Panama's newly installed
President Guillermo Endara to seat his appointed representative.
Noriega loyalist, Jose Maria Cabrera, spoke out repeatedly against
the ``criminal abuse'' by the United States.
   U.S. Ambassador Luigi Einaudi cast the only negative vote on the
motion outlined by Peru, Brazil, Mexico, Colombia, Uruguay and
Argentina.
   He failed on an 11-4 vote with two abstentions to add to the
resolution a mention that the OAS charter itself allows each nation
the right of self-defense.
   Einaudi said that once Noriega declared a state of war against
the United States, U.S. officials ``clearly have the legitimate
right of self-defense.''
   The ambassador also said the United States has tried to work out
a peacefully solution of the Panamanian situation through the OAS
but ``it is impossible to reason with a dictator. At the end,
Noriega has got what he deserved.''
   A U.S. attempt to label the invasion a ``military action''
failed with only three votes among the 26 delegates who attended
the 17-hour debate and negotiation. Only Honduras and Costa Rica
supported the United States.
</TEXT>

</DOC>