<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0278 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1757EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-OilPrices     12-18 0387</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Oil Prices,0399</SECOND>
<HEAD>Energy Futures Climb</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The unabating pre-Christmas cold snap drove
heating oil futures prices to their highest closing levels in
nearly four years on Monday, and crude oil futures soared above $22
a barrel for the first time since April.
   On the New York Mercantile Exchange, the January contract for
No. 2 heating oil climbed 4.24 cents to 74.66 cents a gallon in
active trading. Domestic heating oil last closed higher on Jan. 7,
1986, when it hit 75.67 cents a gallon. The January contract had
risen 3.14 cents a gallon on Friday.
   The January contract for West Texas Intermediate, the leading
grade of U.S. crude, rocketed $1.12 to settle at $22.22 per
42-gallon barrel.
   It was the highest level since April 20, when the near-month
crude contract closed at $24.65 a barrel, according to a New York
Merc statistician, who asked not to be identified by name. The
January contract rose 45 cents a barrel on Friday.
   Wholesale unleaded gasoline for January ended the session at
54.51 cents a gallon, up 1.71 cents from Friday's settlement. The
unleaded gasoline contract rose 1.19 cents on Friday.
   ``We are seeing weather-driven markets right now, led by heating
oil,'' said Evan Baron of the energy group at Elders Futures Inc.
in New York.
   He said the cold weather that has swept across much of the
nation in the past week is usually not seen until January or
February.
   ``Heating oil distributors were simply not prepared for this
kind of extended cold weather this early in the season,'' Baron
said.
   William Byers, director of futures research at Bear Stearns &amp;
Co. Inc., said cold weather in Europe several weeks ago inhibited
shipments of oil products, adding to the problems when the weather
worsened in the United States.
   In addition, he said, inventories of home heating oil are
slightly below what they were a year ago.
   Byers said one reason for the jump in crude prices was that the
January contract expires at the end of trading on Tuesday. Other
contract months rose but finished below $22 a barrel.
   He said reports of continued turmoil in Panama failed to exert
as much influence on the market as on Friday, when the reports were
cited as a major factor in the rise in crude prices.
</TEXT>

</DOC>