<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1119EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-Judges-Security 2ndLd-Writethru a0534 12-19 0532</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Judges-Security, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0534,510</SECOND>
<HEAD>Marshals Screening Packages Mailed to Courthouses After Mail-Bombings</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 6th graf pvs, Employees were, with pen set found in suspicious
package</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES ROWLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Federal marshals examined packages delivered
to U.S. courthouses and officials briefly evacuated a Justice
Department corridor today in the wake of mail-bomb killings of an
appellate judge in Alabama and a lawyer in Savannah, Ga.
   The nation's federal judges were advised to let the U.S.
marshals inspect any package mailed to their chambers, even those
bearing a familiar return address.
   Judges were told ``to bring all packages to the attention of the
marshals so they can be screened and X-rayed before opening,'' said
William Dempsey, a spokesman for the Marshals Service in Washington.
   The advisory also applies to packages bearing familiar names
because ``return addresses can be forged or faked,'' Dempsey said.
   At the Justice Department, security officials briefly evacuated
offices along a section of a first-floor corridor when a suspicious
package addressed to Attorney General Dick Thornburgh turned up in
the basement mailroom, officials said.
   Employees were allowed to return to their offices 10 minutes
later after officials determined the parcel was not dangerous.
After X-raying the package, security officials determined it
contained a pen set for the attorney general, said Justice
Department spokesman David Runkel.
   ``We're being more vigilant,'' said Flavio Lorenzoni, Chief
Deputy U.S. Marshal for the Southern District of New York. ``All
packages are being checked carefully.''
   Lorenzoni, like colleagues elsewhere across the country,
declined to discuss specific security precautions taken since the
assassination of Circuit Judge Robert S. Vance, who was killed
Saturday by a package bomb sent to his home outside Birmingham, Ala.
   Authorities also were investigating a mailed bomb that killed
Savannah, Ga., attorney Robert Robinson, who was a city alderman
and black civil rights activist. Robinson died Monday night after
undergoing emergency surgery for injuries he received in the blast
in his office several hours earlier, officials said.
   Just as security was being redoubled Monday at many federal
courthouses across the country, another package bomb turned up at
the 11th Circuit Court of Appeals in Atlanta.
   The bomb was found in a package during a screening of mail sent
to the courthouse, which is the headquarters of the 11th Circuit,
on which Vance sat.
   In Miami, Chief Deputy U.S. Marshal James Tassone said packages
and mail entering the federal courthouses in that city as well as
in Fort Lauderdale and West Palm Beach were being X-rayed.
   Extra inspections of people entering the courthouses also were
being conducted by guards, he said. Some courthouse employees were
asked to empty their pockets as they passed through metal detectors.
   Officials in other courthouses reported that security was
already tight and didn't need to be upgraded.
   But Deputy Marshal Jeff Whitney in Evansville, Ind., said judges
were instructed not to open any uninspected packages.
   White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said President Bush
discussed the Vance assassination with Attorney General Dick
Thornburgh, who reported that investigators ``have not reached any
conclusions'' about the case.
   ``We just don't have any answers yet as to who might have done
it to him,'' Fitzwater said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>