<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0316EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-HuntingDeath Bjt   12-28 0724</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hunting Death, Bjt,0748</SECOND>
<HEAD>Debate Flares Over Shooting of Woman Mistaken for Deer</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BAN1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JERRY HARKAVY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hunting deaths in Maine aren't unusual _
two generations ago the state recorded 15-plus a year. But the lone
death last season has ignited a debate greater than all the rest
combined.
   The accidental shooting of Karen Wood in the trees behind her
home struck a raw nerve in a state where tens of thousands pour
into the woods when deer season opens each autumn.
   More than a year later, the death of the 37-year-old mother of
year-old twin daughters remains a focus of wrangling between
hunters and non-hunters.
   The case sparked arguments over the adequacy of the state's
hunting regulations and raised questions about the criminal justice
system after the grand jury that first heard the evidence declined
to hand up an indictment.
   A second grand jury this month returned a manslaughter
indictment against Donald Rogerson, the Bangor man who admitted
shooting Mrs. Wood when he mistook her for a deer while hunting in
woods in the Bangor suburb of Hermon.
   The 45-year-old Rogerson, a supermarket produce manager, has
pleaded innocent and remains free on his own recognizance while
awaiting trial. If convicted, he faces up to 20 years in prison.
   The case prompted some people to call for tighter restrictions
on hunting near homes. The current law forbids shooting within 300
feet of an occupied residence.
   But others suggested Mrs. Wood should have worn bright clothing,
like the fluorescent orange garb required of hunters, before
venturing into the woods during deer season. Some faulted her for
wearing white mittens that could have been mistaken for the
underside of a deer's tail.
   The head of the state Inland Fisheries and Wildlife Department
notes the uproar comes at a time when state safety programs have
reduced hunting deaths to their lowest level in history, even
though more hunters are in the woods than ever.
   ``The public has been somewhat tolerant over the years of
hunters shooting other hunters,'' said Commissioner William J.
Vail, noting that hunters assume some risk whenever they go into
the field. ``This particular case involved a non-participant,
someone who was not hunting, and I think that was at the root of
the outrage.''
   Mrs. Wood, who had just moved to the area from Iowa that summer,
was shot in the chest the afternoon of Nov. 15, 1988, while she
stood amid some hardwoods behind her home in a new residential
subdivision.
   Rogerson was arrested that evening and charged with
manslaughter. But the charge was dropped the following month after
the grand jury concluded that his actions were neither criminally
negligent nor criminally reckless.
   Vail bristles at the suggestion Mrs. Wood may unknowingly have
contributed to her death.
   ``That sort of criticism is outrageous,'' he said. ``Hunters are
required to wear fluorescent orange. Non-hunters are not, and there
are literally thousands of people who live and work in the Maine
woods in November who do not wear it.''
   While anyone in Maine during that time of year should be aware
that deer season is on, Vail said, ``the responsibility is clearly
with the hunter to make sure of his target before firing.''
   Stephen Duren, executive director of the Sportsman's Alliance of
Maine, said he believes Rogerson bore some blame for the killing.
   ``There must have been some violation of the hunter safety code
that you be certain of your target,'' Duren said. ``The hunter
knows very plainly what Don Rogerson should have done and failed to
do.''
   A year after Mrs. Wood was shot, the Legislature rejected an
attempt to increase the 300-foot restriction on firearms
discharges. Fish and game officials opposed the change, saying the
current law was adequate.
   A wrongful death lawsuit by Mrs. Wood's husband against Rogerson
was settled for $122,000, most of it covered by Rogerson's
homeowners' insurance. Rogerson also agreed he wouldn't seek a new
hunting license, according to his lawyer, Lewis Vafiades, who said
his client doesn't want to resume the sport.
   Rogerson has declined to talk to reporters.
   Mrs. Wood's husband, Kevin, a pediatric psychologist who has
since moved back to Iowa with his daughters, said he was encouraged
by the indictment and believes that the grand jury had reached
``the only decision logic and reason would allow.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>