<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0168 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0220EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-BusinessHighlights     12-28 0821</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Business Highlights,0862</SECOND>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sales of existing homes advanced 3.2 percent
in November, with a big jump in activity in the South spurring the
fastest growth rate in 11 months, a real estate trade group
reported.
   The National Association of Realtors said Wednesday that sales
of existing single-family homes rose to a seasonally adjusted
annual rate of 3.59 million units last month, the best performance
since sales reached a rate of 3.92 million units in December 1988.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Heating oil prices surged higher again _ with
consumers paying more than $1 a gallon in many parts of the country
_ as cold weather continued depleting stocks of the fuel.
   Oil customers weren't the only ones being pinched. Prices rose
Wednesday for other fuels, such as propane, and some utilities
asked natural gas customers to limit consumption.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Produce prices have shot higher at the wholesale
level and soon should climb in supermarkets as the economic impact
of devastating freezes hits pocketbooks, experts said.
   ``The pipeline stays filled for three to seven days in advance
of any major prices change in the marketplace,'' said Reggie Brown,
spokesman for the Florida Fruit and Vegetable Association in
Orlando. ``You'll start seeing it showing up probably within a
week.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CINCINNATI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Manufacturers who supply merchandise to
Campeau Corp.'s department stores continued to watch for clues
whether the retail operations would file for bankruptcy protection.
   In the meantime, many of the clothing makers and other companies
that do business with the stores have stopped shipments or
postponed decisions about future shipments amid worries about
Campeau's solvency.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A strikebound coal company sued the
United Mine Workers for $60 million, accusing the union and its
members of attempted murder, arson and extortion as part of a
nationwide racketeering scheme.
   The lawsuit was filed Wednesday in federal court in Beckley by
the New Beckley Mining Corp., which also announced it will close
its nearby Glen Daniel mine because of what it called union
violence stemming from the UMW's selective strikes.
   The UMW has been on strike against New Beckley since January,
idling 130 miners. The union also is engaged in a bitter strike
against the Pittston Coal Group Inc. in West Virginia, Virginia and
Kentucky.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Negotiators for striking coal miners and the
Pittston Co. resumed talks and were expected to bargain around the
clock to settle the 9-month-long walkout by New Year's Day.
   The two sides returned Wednesday after a Christmas break from
negotiations that officials said came close to agreement last week.
   ``A great deal of progress was made,'' said Herb Fishgold,
spokesman for mediator W.J. Usery.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two major television networks, CBS and ABC, have
decided not to run commercials featuring President Bush and Soviet
leader Mikhail S. Gorbachev unless they get permission from the two
heads of state.
   Schering-Plough Corp. is using pictures of Bush and Gorbachev to
help promote its own weapon against the cold war, Drixoral cold
medicine. The company is using footage of the two leaders from
their recent summit talks in Malta in a television and newspaper
advertising campaign for Drixoral starting today.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   For many people, trips to crowded shopping malls, airports or
restaurants this holiday season weren't complete without a stop at
an automated teller machine.
   One of the world's largest ATM networks, Plus System Inc. of
Denver, predicts that between Dec. 1 and New Year's Day consumers
will have used the high-tech bank machines twice as much as last
year, largely for withdrawals.
   That's good news for many financial institutions who charge
anywhere from 10 cents to $3 per transaction for such ATM services
as cash withdrawals, deposits, transfers or balance inquiries.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Energy Department soon will end its
decades-old practice of paying all bills, including environmental
fines and other penalties, incurred by the companies that run
nuclear weapons plants, officials said.
   The government will continue paying normal operating expenses,
but for the first time since nuclear arms production began in the
1940s, costs resulting from negligence by the plant operators will
be borne by the companies instead of taxpayers, Energy Department
General Counsel Stephen A. Wakefield said.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The stock market gained ground in a quiet session Wednesday,
bidding again to mount a yearend rally. The Dow Jones average of 30
industrials, down 2.13 on Tuesday, climbed 15.14 to 2,724.40.
   Bond prices were mixed in thin trading.
   The dollar drifted mostly lower in very light trading. Gold
prices declined sharply in the United States and overseas.
   Heating oil futures rose dramatically again as speculation
continued that supplies would be tight amid continued cold weather.
On other commodity markets, gold and silver prices plummeted;
orange juice futures were widely mixed; livestock and meat were
mixed; and grains and soybeans were mostly lower.
</TEXT>

</DOC>