<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0164 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1500EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-Preview1990s Adv31   12-27 1253</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Preview 1990s, Adv 31,1308</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 31, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Human Endeavor, Human Concerns in Coming Decade</HEAD>
<BYLINE>Eds: This is a condensation, for year-end use, of the multipart
AP series `The '90s,' which moved in October and November. It is accompanied
by a new sidebar, BC-Forecasters 1990s, in which prominent personalities
look ahead to the decade's promise and challenges.    ___</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Advances in science and technology promise to make the 10 years
that begin Jan. 1 a decade of unparalleled accomplishment. But
damage to the atmosphere, accumulation of solid wastes, the spread
of AIDS and other threats also make the 1990s a decade of potential
peril.
   ``Human beings now have the power to control their own fate to a
degree that they've never had before,'' said Edward Cornish,
president of the World Future Society.
   Topping the World Future Society's list of challenges for the
1990s: environmental damage to the Earth's climate, land, water and
atmosphere.
   Here, in capsules drawn from the reporting of Associated Press
specialists, is a look at some major areas of human endeavor and
concern for the coming decade:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>THE AIR ABOVE</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The intertwined issues of air pollution, the ozone layer and the
greenhouse effect will all be high on the environmental agenda in
the 1990s.
   In smog-bound Los Angeles, authorities will try to change a way
of life by starting to wean commuters off gasoline-powered
automobiles. Other cities are likely to follow suit.
   Scientists, meanwhile, will train their instruments on the
thinning ozone in the stratosphere, a layer that shields the Earth
from ultraviolet rays, which can cause skin cancer. A human
pollutant _ chlorofluorocarbons, or CFCs _ is destroying the ozone.
Governments are trying to reduce CFC releases, but the question for
the 1990s is whether it is too little too late.
   Scientists almost universally agree that carbon dioxide and
other gases released into the atmosphere will produce the
greenhouse effect _ letting sunlight in, but not letting Earth's
heat out. But specialists disagree on when the warming will occur
and how bad it will be. Pessimists predict the 1990s will be even
warmer than the 1980s, one of the warmest recent decades.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>SOLID WASTE</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Specialists see an upcoming crunch on the garbage front: Half
the nation's 6,000 dumps will be filled and closed in the '90s.
   Said Bruce Weddle, director of the Environmental Protection
Agency's municipal solid waste program: ``By the end of the decade,
I think recycling is going to be part of the cultural fabric of
society. People will be separating out all bottles, cans,
newspapers, plastics, leaves and grass clippings instead of
throwing them in one can.''
   Americans now bury about 80 percent of their waste in dumps,
burn 10 percent and recycle the remainder. The EPA predicts
recycling will jump to 25 percent by 1992.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>THE AIDS EPIDEMIC</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The World Health Organization estimates that nine times more
people around the world will get AIDS in the 1990s than did in the
1980s. By the year 2000, there could be 6 million AIDS cases, and
18 million people could be infected.
   An estimated 1 million to 1.5 million Americans are now infected
with the deadly disease. Most, perhaps all, will eventually become
ill.
   Researchers cannot confidently predict a vaccine or cure in the
coming decade, but they believe AIDS could be subdued to the point
of becoming a chronic disease, one for which those infected must
take long-term medication.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>HEART DISEASE-CANCER</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   If current death rates continue, 13 million American lives will
be claimed in the 1990s by two big killers _ heart disease and
cancer.
   Medical researchers do not expect cures in the next decade.
Instead, they look for new insights to help them attack the
diseases from many directions.
   Better understanding of cancer-causing genes and how to block
them, for example, and of cancer-suppressing genes and how to
harness them, would give medical scientists crucial new weapons to
wield against cancer.
   New discoveries about the relationship of diet to heart disease
might lead to innovative treatments for the nation's leading killer.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>GENETICS</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Biologists who have uncovered the genetic causes of such
ailments as cystic fibrosis will turn their attention to the
genetics of human behavior in the 1990s.
   In human genes, scientists may find the roots of such complex
disorders as manic-depressive illness and schizophrenia.
Specialists believe understanding of some behavioral disorders
should come by the year 2000.
   ``I think this will be a tremendously exciting field in the next
10 years,'' says David Baltimore, a Nobel laureate at the
Massachusetts Institute of Technology.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>SPACE</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   After years of tight budgets, American scientists hope the 1990s
will introduce a new ``golden age'' of space exploration.
   President Bush has proposed a major commitment to completing the
manned space station Freedom in the 1990s and to a permanent base
on the moon and a manned mission to Mars early in the next century.
   The U.S. probe Magellan, launched from a space shuttle last May,
is to orbit Venus next August. The probe Galileo, launched from a
shuttle in October, is to orbit Jupiter in 1995. En route, Galileo
will also study Venus and take the first closeup look at an
asteroid. In 1992, the Mars Observer will be launched, to orbit the
red planet for a multi-year examination.
   The Soviets, meanwhile, will continue development of a space
shuttle and exploit their own space station Mir, as they pursue
their stated goal of dispatching cosmonauts to Mars early in the
21st century.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MASS TRANSPORT</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Specialists foresee more automobiles on the road in the 1990s,
on a U.S. highway system that will never keep pace.
   Experts say air pollution and possible oil shortages in the '90s
will spur production of cleaner, higher-mileage cars; increased use
of vehicles that run on methanol, natural gas, electricity or solar
power; construction of more trolleys and other ``light rail''
systems, and more vacation travel done by trains, planes and cruise
ships.
   Traffic management will include synchronized traffic lights,
metered on-ramps, car-pool and bus lanes, reversible traffic lanes,
staggered work hours, and limits on times trucks can move goods.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>COMPUTERS</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The high technologists look ahead to a personal computer in the
1990s that will be a blend of 3-D television and quadraphonic
stereo with the hand controls of a video game machine and more
speed than car-sized mainframes of the 1980s.
   ``Multimedia'' computers will rival television for attention,
able to surround the user with, for example, the sights and sounds
of an early morning in Paris or an erupting Hawaiian volcano.
Experts say they will help educate the next generation of
video-hungry schoolchildren.
   Other advances expected in the '90s: Machine translation of
language, and telerobots with human guidance that will clean up
crippled nuclear reactors and scour sclerotic arteries.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>U.S. SOCIETY</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Demographics will change the face of the U.S. factory and office
_ and of American society _ in the coming decade.
   The private Population Reference Bureau reports that in the
1970s, 24.1 million young people entered the workforce, in the
1980s only 18.0 million did so, and in the 1990s the number is
expected to decline to 15.6 million.
   Much of the dropoff is among non-Hispanic white males. Women and
minority-group members will account for more than 80 percent of all
new entrants in the labor force in the '90s, the bureau says.
   Some businesses, such as fast-food outlets, are already feeling
the shortage of new labor-market entrants and have begun seeking
out retired people to fill jobs.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, Dec. 31</NOTE>

</DOC>