<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0037EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-Military     12-27 0914</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Military,0940</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S., Panamanian Officials Argue About Military Strength</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Wednesday AMs report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega is gone,
but the question of fashioning a security force to replace his
bully boys is causing friction between the U.S. military and the
new Panamanian civilian government.
   Sources on both sides agree there's a problem.
   The civilians want a weakened army that would be little more
than a police force and would not represent a threat to the
government. The United States is pressing for a professional army
to provide security for the Panama Canal.
   Panamanian civilians have been intimidated by the military for
more than 20 years, suffering exile, torture, imprisonment and
death. The Panamanian military has not had much respect for
politicians, whom they considered weak and beholden to the United
States.
   ``The truth is that both, the civilian and the military must be
re-educated,'' a U.S. military source told The Associated Press.
   ``We are telling the Panamanian military that they must
understand their role in society under civilian power. And we are
telling the civilians that a strong military organization is needed
too,'' the source said, on condition of anonymity.
   The Panama Canal is due to be turned over to Panama on Dec. 31,
1999, and U.S. bases are to be closed unless a further agreement is
reached with the Panamanian government. Since the treaties give the
two countries joint responsibiilty for canal security even after
2000, U.S. sources say at least two bases probably will be
maintained, rather than the 10 major installations that now support
12,000 troops.
   Ironically, the Panamanian army under Omar Torrijos was the core
of the long drive to eliminate the sovereign U.S. enclave in the
Canal Zone and negotiate the 1977 treaties. U.S. officials insist
the United States will honor the treaties.
   The dispute over how to reconstitute the Panamanian forces is
taking place even as U.S. officers work with Panamanian officers to
do exactly that, despite civilian unease.
   ``It is a matter of concern that the members of the Defense
Forces are being reintegrated, and not by the Panamanian
government, but by the American Army,'' said Juan Materno Vasquez,
a lawyer who helped negotiate the 1977 canal treaties but left the
government in a dispute with Noriega.
   Vice president and minister of government Ricardo Arias Calderon
has spoken of a Public Security Force, avoiding all reference to
the old name of Defense Forces or previous names, such as National
Guard.
   ``You can call it what you will,'' a U.S. source said. ``It has
to be a professional force, army, national guard or whatever.''
   U.S. military leaders here, who worked with the Panamanians for
years and know them well, feel some _ especially those jailed by
Noriega following coup attempts _ can be trusted enough to form the
core of an army.
   Before the U.S. attack that toppled Noriega Dec. 20, U.S.
military sources told the AP that U.S. forces could ``work with
some of the Panamanian top officers, even if they are not shining
examples of democracy.''
   According to a Panamanian military source, U.S. officers were
rather blunt when they told President Guillermo Endara what they
want in a Panamanian army. Endara was elected president May 7, but
Noriega nullified the vote and Endara was not installed until after
the U.S. assault.
   ``The politicians did not shed any blood,'' another source said.
``The blood was shed by the Americans and the few Defense Forces
units that fought.''
   Both the U.S. and Panamanian military, even those opposed to
Noriega, feel the opposition was unwilling to take risks to try to
topple Noriega. Comparisons with uprisings in South Korea, China
and, lately, Eastern Europe were raised frequently.
   ``They want us to do the job for them,'' a top-ranking U.S.
officer told the AP before U.S. forces did exactly that.
   Some of the new leaders of the future Panamanian military are
the majors and captains who were arrested March 16, 1988, after
their failed coup against Noriega.
   They include men like Maj. Santiago Fundora and Maj. Aristides
Valdonedo, who have been named directors of logistics and public
security respectively, and Maj. August Villalaz, who will be in
charge of the Air Force.
   They have been working closely with the commander of U.S. Army
South, Maj. Gen. Marc Cisneros, and other Army officers at Fort
Clayton, near Panama City.
   ``The person who is really governing in Panama now is Marc
Cisneros,'' Vasquez said.
   Vasquez said he saw a former lieutenant colonel surrender with
other officers and return home with a ``passport from Cisneros, not
even from Panamanian authorities.''
   ``We're concerned about too many of those guys coming back in,''
said a Christian Democratic politician involved in forming the new
government. The Endara government would like to set up ``something
like what Costa Rica has.''
   Costa Rica, just north of Panama, has been spared coups and
military rule in large measure because the armed forces were
dissolved more than 40 years ago. Costa Rica has only a civilian
police force and relies on the Organization of American States
charter, which calls for collective defense in case of attack.
   In essence that means relying on the United States, but U.S.
officials are not sympathetic to the civilian government's desires.
   ``Endara may feel that he was elected in May,'' one source said
``but his majority meant nothing and he is where he is because of
the American guns.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>