<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0139EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-FurProtests Bjt   12-22 0701</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Fur Protests, Bjt,0720</SECOND>
<HEAD>Animal-Rights Movement Growing But Impact Debated</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL GEITNER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Women with furs are facing a new threat on the
streets _ not muggers, but animal-rights activists who have adopted
confrontational tactics in their fight to mothball the fur industry.
   Women strolling down the street in fur coats report they've been
jeered at, sprayed with ketchup or red paint, even had their coats
slashed.
   ``We're encouraging people to go up to fur wearers and to say
something to them,'' said Dana Stuchell, national director of
Trans-Species Unlimited, one of the country's leading animal-rights
groups.
   ``Some people are extremely mild, some people are more abrasive,
but the point is to let them know how you feel about their fur coat
and to explain that animals had to suffer and die for it.''
   Trans-Species Unlimited says it doesn't condone violence _
``that's what animal rights are all about _ non-violence,''
Stuchell said.
   But the attacks on fur-wearers and vandalism at some fur stores
by extremists has begun to raise the hackles of furriers.
   ``There was a feeling a couple of years ago that the thing would
go away, that if we responded to it it would just lend credit to
the movement,'' said Jack Neal, a spokesman for the Fur Information
Council of America. ``But it's gotten to the point where furriers
were under such attack that we couldn't ignore it.''
   The animal-rights movement has been growing in recent years.
   People for the Ethical Treatment of Animals was started in
Washington by two friends in 1980. It now has 250,000 members, a
staff of 70 and a $7 million budget, said spokeswoman Carol L.
Burnett.
   Trans-Species Unlimited, based in Williamsport, Pa., led the
first national anti-fur protest in 1985. Since then, it has
organized ever larger annual marches the day after Thanksgiving _
kickoff day of the holiday shopping season.
   This year, protests were held in 94 cities, including a march
with more than 3,000 people on New York's Fifth Avenue, led by game
show host Bob Barker. One fur store in Miami's posh Coconut Grove
allegedly was vandalized by activists.
   On another front, Aspen, Colo., voters are being asked whether
their tony ski resort should become the world's first fur-free zone.
   The Aspen City Council voted last month to hold a special
election in February on banning fur sales within city limits. They
have already banned the use of steel-jawed leg-hold traps and the
sale of all furs caught in such traps.
   ``Instead of Aspen's being known as a glitzy, egocentric kind of
place, I think it can be known as a town that's sensitive to the
environment and sensitive to the delicate balance between humans
and wildlife,'' Mayor Bill Stirling said.
   The measure could put the city's four furriers out of business
and drastically change the stock in another 25 to 30 ski accessory
shops.
   The fur industry denies the animal-rights movement has had any
economic impact.
   Sales of fur items have quintupled since 1972, and retailers say
they are selling more coats each year. But overproduction and
price-cutting have kept the total sales figure at a flat $1.8
billion since 1986.
   Mink, the most popular fur, has dropped in price from a recent
high of $43 a pelt in 1987 to about $26 this year, according to
David Bavins, marketing director at the Seattle Fur Exchange, which
handles most of the U.S. crop.
   New York-based Fur Vault Inc. announced last month that it is up
for sale after losing $7.2 million in the past two fiscal years.
   Animal-rights groups _ which generally oppose use of animals for
research, food and clothing _ like to take some credit.
   ``People are starting to change their attitudes about fur,''
Stuchell said. ``They're no longer a symbol of status.''
   Although this year's fur season is still young, early reports
are that furriers are doing better than last year, thanks in part
to the frigid temperatures in much of the country.
   Chuck Kehoe, president of Revillon Furs, which are sold at Saks
Fifth Avenue and other stores nationwide, said business in the
first three weeks of December was up 12 percent over last year.
</TEXT>

</DOC>