<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0104 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1149EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-Panama-Suspects 1stLd-Writethru a0645 12-20 0418</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Suspects, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0645,410</SECOND>
<HEAD>FBI, DEA Agents Dispatched to Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-US-Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Inserts grafs 8-9, Under an, on legal opinion.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES ROWLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A team of FBI and Drug Enforcement
Administration agents was dispatched to Panama today to help
American forces round up fugitives wanted on U.S. criminal charges,
the Justice Department said.
   In addition to Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega, there are a number
of other fugitives from U.S. law, said Justice Department spokesman
David Runkel.
   ``We will round up as many people as we can who are wanted in
this country on charges, many of them drug-related,'' Runkel told
reporters.
   A team of more than 10 FBI and DEA agents was being sent to
Panama to help U.S. military authorities make the arrests, Runkel
said.
   Noriega and 16 associates were named in two 1988 federal
drug-trafficking indictments returned by grand juries in Miami and
Tampa, Fla.
   Runkel said Noreiga is accused of making $10 million by shipping
cocaine and marijuana from Colombia through Panama to the United
States.
   If Noriega is captured, Runkel said, the Justice Department
would try him first on the Miami charges. The Miami indictment,
returned Feb. 4, 1988, accuses Noriega of receiving more than $4.6
million to protect cocaine shipments from Medellin, Colombia, that
were shipped to this country through Panama.
   Under an opinion issued last month by the Justice Department's
Office of Legal Counsel, U.S. military forces overseas have the
power to arrest and detain criminal suspects.
   The opinion, which Runkel said was not issued in response to
preparations for a Panama invasion, will empower U.S. forces to
help round up criminal suspects such as Noriega.
   Runkel, meanwhile, offered a legal justification for the U.S.
invasion in Panama, saying Attorney General Dick Thornburgh
``believes there is a legal basis for this action being taken under
U.S. law.''
   The attorney general met with President Bush on Tuesday to
discuss the operation and give his legal advice, Runkel said.
   Runkel cited the ``inherent right of self-defense'' in Article
51 of the United Nations Charter and the right of the U.S.
government to protect its citizens, military installations and
institutions under Article 21 of the Organization of American
States treaty.
   The Panama Canal Treaty also empowers the United States ``to
protect and defend the canal and its availability to all nations,''
Runkel said.
   The spokesman said that ``the democratically elected government
of Panama was consulted prior to and welcomed the action taken by
the United States.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>