<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1248EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Korea-Communism     12-27 0331</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Korea-Communism,0339</SECOND>
<HEAD>North Korea Warns of Efforts by `Imperialists' to Wreck Socialism</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   North Korea urged fellow Communist countries
Wednesday to heighten vigilance and unite against ``imperialist''
efforts to undermine socialism.
   A commentary in the official Communist Party newspaper Rodong
Shinmun did not directly mention the fall of the hard-line
dictatorship of Nicolae Ceausescu in Romania or other changes in
Eastern Europe, although it blamed ``imperialists'' for what it
called a ``scheme to make the most of changes in political and
economic life in some socialist countries.''
   China and Cuba were the only countries identified in the report.
   North Korea is ruled by a hard-line Communist leadership headed
by Kim Il Sung, who, like Ceausescu, built a strong personality
cult.
   The commentary, broadcast in part by Pyongyang's official Korean
Central News Agency, said the U.S. ``imperialists'' were trying
military threats, blackmail, political and diplomatic pressure and
an economic blockade against Cuba.
   ``They are also continuing a vicious and shameless interference
in the internal affairs of China, displeased at the fact that the
Chinese people keep to the road of socialism ... after quelling the
counterrevolutionary riot'' _ a reference to China's June 3-4
military crackdown of a student-led pro-democracy movement.
   Rodong Shinmun said ``imperialists'' claim that ``some socialist
countries should be given `assistance' needed for leading some of
their policies to the capitalist market economy. They scheme to win
over and bring under their control socialist countries, declaring
that they would render economic `aid' to somer country and treat
some other country as `most favored nation.'''
   They slander socialism in the media, seek to ``infiltrate the
corrupt bourgeois ideology, culture and way of life into socialist
countries,'' and send in spies and saboteurs, the paper said.
   ``The situation makes it incumbent upon all socialist countries
and the anti-imperialist independent forces to heighten vigilance
over the vicious and crafty anti-socialist moves and reactionary
offensive of the imperialists and pool their strength to repulse
them,'' it added.
</TEXT>

</DOC>