<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0160 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2100EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Yugoslavia     12-21 0422</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Yugoslavia,0433</SECOND>
<HEAD>Western Creditors May Advance Yugoslavia Up to $4 Billion</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DUSAN STOJANOVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BELGRADE, Yugoslavia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Western creditors may lend
Yugoslavia up to $4 billion in the next two years if it adopts
Premier Ante Markovic's new market-oriented economic program,
sources and press reports said Thursday.
   Yugoslav banking sources told The Associated Press the
International Monetary Fund agreed to grant Yugoslavia an 18-month
stand-by credit worth $600 million. The loan, once fully approved
by IMF authorities, will be available from Jan. 1, 1990.
   Yugoslavia hopes the IMF will increase that to $900 million for
a two-year period, said sources close to the negotiations, which
ended in Belgrade this week.
   The newspaper Vecernje Novosti said Yugoslavia now has a shot at
obtaining additional Western credits, because commercial banks and
governments usually follow the IMF lead in gauging whether to keep
supporting a debtor country.
   It quoted National Bank Vice Gov. Zarko Trbojevic as saying the
World Bank, the European Community, the IMF and the European Free
Trade Association have already agreed to grant Yugoslavia a total
of $3 billion in new credits.
   Italy, Japan and Canada have also ``given guarantees'' to supply
Yugoslavia with additional loans worth about $1 billion in the next
two years if Markovic's reform package is put into effect, Vecernje
Novosti said.
   The money would be used mainly for importing new Western
technology and restructuring Yugoslavia's economy and its banking
system, which is being reformed in accordance with Western
standards, the sources said, speaking on condition of anonymity.
   They said money was needed to prop up banks that have been
backing money-losing ventures that would lose government subsidies
under market-oriented reforms.
   Markovic has apparently won a battle in Parliament against
conservatives who oppose his efforts to introduce market mechanisms
into the economy _ now burdened by a 2,000 percent inflation rate,
a $17 billion foreign debt and a 17 percent unemployment rate.
   His reform package calls for compulsory shutdown of all
money-losing firms, wide introduction of private and foreign
investments, wage freezes and tight monetary and budgetary controls.
   Yugoslavia on Wednesday became the first communist country to
introduce convertible currency when part of Markovic's program was
adopted in parliament.
   Communist leaders in Serbia, Yugoslavia's largest republic,
oppose Markovic's efforts to restructure the state-run economy and
promote greater political pluralism, but his measures are likely to
be adopted despite the opposition.
   About 650,000 workers held a half-hour warning strike in
Belgrade, the capital, on Wednesday to protest planned austerity
measures, Tanjug news agency reported.
</TEXT>

</DOC>