<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0120 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 2200EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Cavallon     12-23 0320</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Cavallon,0332</SECOND>
<HEAD>Giorgio Cavallon, Pioneer in Abstract Expressionism, Dead at 85</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Artist Giorgio Cavallon, considered a pioneer of
abstract expressionism, has died at age 85.
   Cavallon, who died Friday night at New York Hospital, had a
following among poets and painters even though his work was not
widely known.
   ``I had conditioned myself to think of him as a lesser artist.
But he kept showing us to be wrong in that,'' said William Agee, a
historian of American art.
   Abstract expressionism is characterized by an emphasis on the
artist's spontaneous and self-expressive application of paint in
creating a non-representational composition. Cavallon's paintings
often featured color rectangles with soft, irregular edges.
   The artist was born in the village of Sorio in Italy in 1904.
During World War I, he lived on an uncle's farm, where he drew in
the earth or scratched drawings on bombshells.
   In 1920, he came to the United States, settling with his family
in Springfield, Mass. Six years later, he moved to New York.
   He began as a figurative painter at the National Academy of
Design. He began exploring abstract expressionism in the 1930s but
like other abstract expressionists did not take the full plunge
until the late 1940s.
   In 1936, he was a founding member of the American Abstract
Artists, a contentious and polemical group that championed the
cause of abstract art.
   Cavallon preferred to do everything by hand, including building
his own freezer, stove and sofa. He even made his own paints.
   His work was exhibited in several New York galleries and last
year was shown at the Peggy Guggenheim Foundation in Venice, Italy.
His work is in several major museums' collections, including New
York's Metropolitan Museum of Art and Museum of Modern Art.
   Cavallon's first marriage to singer Fabiola Caron ended in
divorce. He later married painter Linda Lindeberg. She died in 1973.
   He is survived by two sisters.
</TEXT>

</DOC>