<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1918EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DrugDecriminalization     12-17 0307</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Drug Decriminalization,0317</SECOND>
<HEAD>Michigan's Crockett First Congressman on Record for Decriminalization</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Bennett-Drugs</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rep. George Crockett has called for the
decriminalization of drugs, becoming the first member of Congress
to do so publicly and drawing sharp criticism from drug czar
William Bennett.
   ``Decriminalization is the only solution,'' Crockett, D-Mich.,
said in an interview in Washington published Sunday in The Detroit
News.
   ``Our courts are burdened down with these drug cases and there
is nothing they can do about it,'' he said. ``And here we are
talking about spending additional billions to build jails and
prisons to send people to.''
   Money now spent on drug enforcement should be shifted to job
training for the urban poor, education, health care and day care,
said Crockett, whose district includes Detroit's economically
depressed east side.
   Crockett said he had no immediate plans to introduce legislation
decriminalizing drugs because it could not win congressional
approval.
   Told of Crockett's position, Bennett cursed, and said, ``Here we
go. We were wondering who was going to be the first,'' the News
said.
   Bennett, director of the Office of National Drug Control Policy,
said he feared others in Congress could join Crockett and subvert
the administration's anti-drug efforts.
   Last week, U.S. District Judge Robert Sweet became the first
federal judge to publicly support decriminalization. Also favoring
decriminalization are Baltimore Mayor Kurt L. Schmoke and economist
Milton Friedman.
   Bennett said that giving drugs the same legal status as alcohol
could cause even greater social and economic problems.
   ``Alcohol has done quite enough damage, thank you,'' he told the
News. ``And if you want to see people using crack go from 1
(million) or 2 million to 10 million, make it as available as
alcohol.''
   Bennett also spoke against legalizing drugs Sunday in an
appearance on the ABC-TV program ``This Week With David Brinkley.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>