<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0826EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-EastGermany 1stLd-Writethru a0492 12-23 0710</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-East Germany, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0492,0727</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands Pour Through Newly Opened Brandenburg Gate</HEAD>
<HEAD>RETRANSMITTING to indicate 1st Ld-Writethru</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 6 grafs to UPDATE thousands pouring into West Berlin
for last-minute Christmas shopping. Pickup 7th, `West German Chancellor...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH G. SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of East Berliners poured through
new Berlin Wall border crossings at the Brandenburg Gate today for
a final, frantic day of Christmas shopping in the well-stocked
stores of the West.
   Other Berliners headed for home after singing and dancing late
into the night at the newly opened gate, which has been transformed
from a symbol of Germany's divisions into one of East-West
rapprochement.
   Although visa-free travel for West Germans to East Germany
technically does not take effect until Sunday, there were few
formalities at the Brandenburg Gate, opened only Friday, for those
who headed East today.
   Throughout the night Friday, a steady clink of metal against
stone accompanied the merrymakers as hundreds of souvenir seekers
chipped away at the Berlin Wall near the gate in the 28-year-old
Berlin Wall.
   At other crossing points, East German shoppers laden with
purchases from West Berlin carried Christmas presents, cases of
beer and bags of oranges.
   West German television periodically carried live coverage of the
festivities Friday night, showing the crowd dancing on top of the
wall, popping champagne corks and waving sparklers.
   West German Chancellor Helmut Kohl and East German Premier Hans
Modrow met Friday for the second time in a week at a ceremony
formally opening two border crossings in the wall just north and
south of the towering gate.
   Security collapsed as soon as the two crossings were opened.
Thousands of people pushed down metal barriers erected to control
the crowd and swept through the vast Paris square, snaking through
the gate and climbing the wall.
   West Berlin police estimated that more than 30,000 people had
gathered on the Western side for the ceremony. The crowd on the
Eastern side appeared to be much larger, but there were no official
estimates.
   Although more than 20 border crossings have been cut through the
Berlin Wall since East Germany opened its borders to the West on
Nov. 9, the opening of the Brandenburg Gate was the emotional
climax of the rapid merger of the people divided since the end of
World War II.
   The openings resulted from a popular uprising in East Germany
that drove out its hard-line Communist leaders.
   When the Berlin Wall was built in 1961, the Brandenburg Gate,
Berlin's most famous landmark that straddled a main prewar
thoroughfare, remained in the East. It was also inaccessible to
East Berliners until Friday because it was part of the off-limit
East German border zone.
   The crowd carried Berlin, West German and East German flags. One
large sign saying in English ``Come Together'' was held aloft by
several people who climbed atop the wall.
   The thick section of the wall directly in front of the gate
remains, but hundreds climbed on top to dance and hug in joyful
scenes reminiscent of the time when the borders were first opened
in November.
   Kohl said the opening of the gate was a ``fantastic thing.''
   He and Modrow met Friday afternoon on the border line, shook
hands and then walked together to a platform to address the crowd.
   The two leaders were nearly mobbed by the exultant crowd as
security officials tried in vain to establish some control.
   The ceremony was broadcast live on both countries' national
television.
   ``This is where the heart of Berlin pounds,'' said a commentator
for West Germany's ZDF network.
   Modrow reminded the crowd of the role the gate has played in
German history, then said its new function should be ``to serve the
peace.''
   Kohl said, ``This is the happiest day in my life, because I feel
that here in Berlin I am standing in the middle of Germany.''
   ``We need the sympathy, the support and the approval of our
neighbors'' as the two Germanys move closer together, he said. ``We
want peace and freedom.''
   The speeches were drowned out by the noisy crowd. Many people
had tears in their eyes as they mingled together.
   ``Berlin, have fun now,'' West Berlin mayor Walter Momper told
the crowd.
</TEXT>

</DOC>