<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0144 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1746EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-OrleansMurders     12-18 0483</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Orleans Murders,0498</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Orleans Breaks Its 1979 Murder Record</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHEVEL JOHNSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Killings in the French Quarter got widespread
publicity but drug-related shootings in low-income areas made 1989
New Orleans' most murderous year on record, the head of the police
force said Monday.
   Two unrelated weekend killings brought the city's murder total
so far this year to 242, two above the 1979 record of 240, Police
Superintendent Warren Woodfork said.
   Almost 60 percent of the slayings were drug-related and about 40
percent took place in public housing projects, Woodfork said.
   In spite of city budget problems, Mayor Sidney Barthelemy has
promised more overtime money for the city's 1,300-member police
force in 1991, saying expected federal grants will help.
   Woodfork said too many people are apathetic about the drug
problem and complained that the media paint the wrong picture in
covering New Orleans murders.
   ``Look at the story you all tend to put out on the front page of
the paper or the first story on television when a tourist is killed
in the French Quarter, et cetera.'' Woodfork said. ``But that's not
the bulk of your homicides.''
   He referred to two widely publicized killings of French Quarter
visitors this year. One man was shot to death by a robber and
another was killed when he tried to intervene in a purse snatching.
   ``Those kind of homicides incidental to robberies, if you look
at the scheme of things, that's small compared to the day-to-day
homicides in housing developments and other areas of the city. I'm
saying something needs to be done about those,'' Woodfork said.
   In August, federal Uniform Crime Reports showed New Orleans had
the fourth-highest murder rate in the nation in 1988 with 228
people killed.
   According to the statistics released by Woodfork, the motive
listed for 59.5 percent of the murders was narcotics; arguments
were the motive in 15.7 percent; domestic disputes, 9.5 percent;
robbery, 7.85 percent.
   Motives in the remainder were listed as burglary, child abuse or
unknown.
   Woodfork said the public must fight drug abuse.
   ``If it's not your problem today, I can guarantee you, it will
be yours tomorrow,'' he said.
   Woodfork said other major cities also have seen their 1989
murder rates increase, including Atlanta with 242 murders
year-to-date compared to 219 for 1988; and Washington, D.C., with
414 so far this year compared to 369 in 1988.
   The two killings that pushed the city over its previous record
occurred Sunday.
   In one, two men were shot when they interrupted some horseplay
among several other men outside a pool hall, police said. One died.
   In the second killing, a man was shot in the Fischer housing
project. The victim and two other men had left an apartment and
gotten into an argument. The victim was shot three times. Police
said they didn't know what the argument was about.
</TEXT>

</DOC>