<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0203 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 2058EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Scene     12-22 0519</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Scene,0541</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Shooting Continues in Bucharest Early Saturday</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The AP's Mort Rosenblum was among the first
Western journalists to reach the Romanian capital Friday night. The
veteran AP special correspondent, who has reported from Africa,
Eastern Europe, Latin America, and the Far East, filed this
dispatch from inside the Romanian TV building Saturday morning just
as it came under attack.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By MORT ROSENBLUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fighting continued in the streets of
Bucharest early Saturday, with automatic weapons fire erupting
around the TV and radio studios that had been captured by opponents
of President Nicolae Ceausescu.
   For all the joyous celebrations in the center of Bucharest on
Friday at the ouster of Ceausescu, the mood on the capital's
streets after nightfall was tense.
   All over town, there were makeshift roadblocks of buses,
bulldozers, even bakery trolleys, testifying to the impromptu
nature of the uprising.
   Army units supporting the popular revolt that forced Ceausescu
from power battled on after midnight against pro-Ceausescu security
forces.
   Just after 2:30 a.m. (7:30 p.m. EST Friday), heavy gunfire broke
out around the television station, where occupants ducked below
windows as shots rained toward the building. Lights went out as the
gunfire pounded in.
   Minutes before the shooting began, crowds still were outside the
TV building, chanting slogans in support of the popular revolt
against Ceausescu.
   Gunfire also was heard echoing through the streets around the
radio station about two miles away from the TV building.
   On arrival at the airport Friday night, a guard smiled at this
correspondent and said: ``Welcome to Romania.''
   When asked how things were, he replied, ``Now, it's OK.''
   A woman customs inspector also seemed relaxed, waving visitors
through with a big smile.
   Travelers from the airport to the Park Hotel in the north of
Bucharest had to pass through seven roadblocks.
   At one, soldiers and police flashed ``V'' for victory signs and
held up their fists in gestures of triumph. At another, soldiers
sat with sullen faces in the scoop of a bulldozer.
   Bucharest residents appeared happy that Ceausescu had fled the
capital, but were anxious as the fighting continued.
   The president's exact whereabouts were still unknown early
Saturday. On Friday, he left his presidential palace by helicopter
with his wife, Elena, but there conflicting reports in the hours
afterward on his detention.
   ``Ceausescu is finished,'' hospital worker Alec Florescu
declared with certainty.
   ``The people that are fighting now know that if they give up,
they're in big trouble,'' said Florescu, whop supports the
uprising. ``So they're fighting to the end.''
   He branded the shooting of unarmed civilians in Timisoara last
weekend and in Bucharest on Thursday as ``absolutely inhuman.''
   An unidentified man said troops had shot his girlfriend in the
arm Friday, but they were pinned down by gunfire as they tried to
reach a hospital. ``They were just shooting directly at people,''
he said.
   A man who gave a Western reporter a ride through the darkened
city, when asked what he thought of the situation, was more laconic.
   ``A small revolution in a small country,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>