<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1426EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Bush 3rdLd-Writethru a0531 12-30 1000</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bush, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0531,990</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Calls US Military Search in Panama a ``Screw-Up''</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDs: Leads with eight grafs to UPDATE with Bush comments on search
of Nicaraguan ambassador's residence and situation with Vatican over Noriega.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM RAUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush today said today the U.S. military
search of the Nicaraguan ambassador's residence in Panama City
``was a screw-up,'' but added that the heavy arsenal found in the
home ``makes you wonder exactly what our young men are up against
down there.''
   The president, speaking to reporters after an 18-hole game of
golf at the Houston Country Club, said that apologies were being
made to the Nicaraguan government for the episode. But, Bush said,
``life goes on.''
   ``When you find those kind of weapons caches, even though I
think in retrospect that we shouldn't have gone in there, it makes
you wonder exactly what our young men are up against down there,''
Bush said. ``I don't know what they need rocket launchers for in a
man's house.''
   ``It's a screw-up and they (U.S. military officials in Panama)
have expressed their regrets that it happened,'' Bush said. He
added that ``it shouldn't have happened and that's been explained
to the Nicaraguans.''
   Bush also said that he was not seeking a fight with the Vatican
and that he hoped that rhetoric could cool down on both sides of
the stalemate over the fate of deposed Panamanian dictator Manuel
Antonio Noriega, who has sought refuge in the Vatican's embassy in
Panama.
   ``If need be, I'll get on the phone with the holy father,'' Bush
said, adding, ``I don't think it will come to that ... we have good
relations with the Vatican.''
   However, Bush added, ``they have a history of giving asylum to
people who are fleeing _ even thugs like Noriega.''
   The president said he was ending the year satisfied that
conditions are stabilizing in Panama, despite the standoff on
Noriega's future. ``The man at least is off the streets,'' Bush
said.
   Earlier today, White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater, asked if
the United States would retaliate for the expulsion of its
diplomats from Nicaragua, said, ``No course of action's been set.''
   Defending the U.S. military search of the residence where the
Nicaraguan ambassador was staying, Fitzwater said, ``We didn't know
it was an ambassador's residence.''
   ``They got a tip. They were looking for arms and they found
arms,'' Fitzwater told reporters in Houston. ``We were looking for
arms caches. We're finding them all over Panama City. Arms caches
are turning up everywhere.''
   ``It's part of the standard mopping-up operation. Discovering
and confiscating these weapons is important to maintaining the
peace and in line with all the reasons we went into Panama in the
first place,'' Fitzwater said.
   He said the people in the home did not identify themselves when
U.S. troops arrived to conduct the search.
   On Friday's 75-20 vote by the United Nations General Assembly
condemning the U.S. invasion of Panama, Fitzwater said, ``We felt
we did the right thing for the right reasons.'
   The administration disputed Friday a Vatican claim that the
United States is ``an occupying power'' in Panama. But it also
sought to sooth building tensions with the Roman Catholic Church.
   ``The Vatican's doing a fine job,'' Fitzwater said. ``We
appreciate their efforts. We continue to work with them in a very
positive way. We think that they've taken a very serious and
constructive role in this episode.''
   The Vatican has refused to turn over Noriega _ holed up in the
Vatican Embassy in Panama City since Christmas Eve _ to the United
States, despite insistent U.S. demands that he be brought to
Florida to face drug-trafficking charges.
   On his flight to Houston aboard Air Force One on Friday, the
president waved and grinned at reporters traveling with him but had
nothing to say.
   And Fitzwater made it clear the White House preferred to have as
little as possible to say about the tense standoff or about
negotiations on Noriega's future.
   ``There's just not much that we have to say or want to say while
this is going on,'' he told reporters.
   After arriving here, Bush had dinner with Secretary of State
James A. Baker III and Scowcroft at a private Houston club.
   On Sunday, Bush was to travel to San Antonio to visit two
military hospitals, Wilford Hall Air Force Medical Center and
Brooke Army Medical Center, where many of the more than 300 troops
wounded in Panama are being treated.
   The president was to return to Washington late New Year's Day
after a half-day fishing excursion in Alabama.
   Bush and hunting companions Baker and Houston oilman William
Farish bagged 20 quail during their hunting excursions on Farish's
10,000-acre ranch near the South Texas town of Beeville, Fitzwater
said.
   Baker also caught a 19-pound turkey, which was cleaned and
dressed and brought to Houston by the president. ``We eat our
game,'' Fitzwater said.
   Animal rights demonstrators had staged a protest outside the
ranch, claiming Bush's hunting did not square with his ``kinder but
gentler'' rhetoric.
   Although Fitzwater said the administration wanted to avoid
further confrontation with the Vatican, State Department spokesman
Richard Boucher in Washington took issue with the Vatican's
description of the United States as an occupation force in Panama.
   ``We are down there with the consent of the government of
Panama, the legitimately elected leaders of Panama,'' Boucher said.
``That means we're not an occupying power.''
   Fitzwater had said talks with Roman Catholic Church officials
were proceeding in ``a positive vein'' and refused to be drawn into
an argument with the Vatican.
   On how long it might take to end the stalemate, Fitzwater said:
``We can't predict how long it will take. We'll just go calmly
along....''
   Meanwhile, Bush on Friday sent ``warm'' congratulations to
Vaclav Havel on his election as president of Czechoslovakia.
   The White House said the election of the once dissident
playwright ``marks a fitting end to a year of astonishing change in
Eastern Europe.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>