<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0209 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1011EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a PM-Flight103-Syracuse Adv20   12-18 0948</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Flight 103-Syracuse, Adv 20,0972</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv20</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Wednesday PMs, Dec. 20</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pall From Flight 103 Bombing Lingers at University</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM KATES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SYRACUSE, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Darkness comes early on Dec. 21, the
winter solstice.
   But the darkness that fell over Syracuse University last Dec. 21
when students learned 35 homeward-bound classmates had been killed
by a terrorist bomb aboard Pan Am Flight 103 never completely
lifted.
   ``It's getting harder to think about it without it becoming
overwhelming,'' said Ann Lareau, a senior who studied in London
with several of the victims, including her best friend, 20-year-old
Theo Cohen.
   ``This was the time of year we were together there. When we were
starting to talk about the things we were going to do when we got
back,'' said Lareau, who added in a hushed voice: ``I miss them.''
   Donine Carrington, a junior, said not a day goes by that she
doesn't think of her friend, Frederick ``Sandy'' Phillips.
   ``You just don't expect people to die at that age. At that age
you're looking forward to the future,'' she said. ``I guess in time
the pain will diminish, but in my heart it won't start until those
who are responsible are brought to justice. They're not buried with
peace. Their story is not whole.''
   Phillips, Cohen and 33 other students who spent the semester
studying overseas under Syracuse's Division of International
Studies Abroad program were returning home when their Pan Am jumbo
jetliner exploded in the sky over Lockerbie, Scotland.
   The bombing killed all 259 people aboard the jet and 11
residents of Lockerbie, who died when debris from the plane crashed
into the town.
   The bombing cast a pall over the Syracuse campus.
   ``It was oppressive here last spring but those feelings started
to wane over the summer and earlier this semester,'' said Nan
Jensen, the university's religious counseling coordinator. ``But
it's never been forgotten and many students still are having
trouble letting go.''
   For some students, it was days before they could leave their
rooms to go to class, she said. Others immersed themselves in
campaigns for tighter airport security and for travellers' right to
know about terroristic threats as a way to cope with the murders.
   Jensen said attendance at her weekly grief support sessions
picked up as the anniversary drew nearer.
   Kathleen Deters, who coordinates counseling services in the
university's dormitories, said residence hall counselors had not
seen the same increase, but that it was more likely students simply
did not need to see the therapists that work with her office.
   ``I've talked to students and I know they're still dealing with
feelings of loss, but I don't think it's so deep-seeded they need
the kind of counseling we offer,'' she said.
   ``The bombing hasn't been forgotten and I doubt that it ever
will be. Every time this part of the season rolls around it will
come to mind,'' Deters said. ``I think that the students organized
a vigil tells us they still needed an outlet to express themselves
and reflect on it.''
   An interfaith vigil was held Dec. 13 in Hendricks Chapel, where
hundreds of students converged a year ago after the news of the
bombing. A procession of 35 students carrying candles in memory of
the victims and a song composed especially for the victims by
senior Marshall Whinney highlighted the service, which was the day
before final exams started.
   The university is building a memorial wall and has established
scholarships in tribute to the slain students. Syracuse's football
coach, Dick MacPherson, made a goodwill trip to Lockerbie over the
summer and the university's two-time defending national champion
lacrosse team is making a trip in January.
   Twenty-five of the student victims attended Syracuse, while the
remaining 10 were from other schools who traveled abroad as part of
the university's foreign studies program.
   ``They've never been very far from our minds, from my mind,''
said Geri Clark, a drama professor who had taught seven of the
victims. ``I still get a number of students in my office every week
who just want to talk about the bombing or the friends they've
lost. There's a real sense that our numbers have been diminished in
a profound way.''
   Many of her students have taken it upon themselves to contact
the families of the victims they knew, Clark said.
   ``I guess they just don't want them to feel lonely at this time
of year,'' she said.
   While grieving continues to be the most visible legacy,
Hendricks Chapel Dean Richard L. Phillips has witnessed another
effect from the bombing.
   ``There is always some good to be found in the worst of
tragedies,'' he said. ``As a university as a whole, we have become
a more sensitive people because of this tragedy. There is more
reverence for the sanctity of life. People are more caring in their
interpersonal relationships.''
   Phillips said he speaks often to students about the bombing, but
he always tries to focus on the need to reflect on the beauty of
the lives lost.
   ``They were among the best and brightest and we must never
forget that,'' he said, echoing the words delivered by Chancellor
Melvin Eggers during a memorial service last January that drew
15,000 people.
   Lareau, the senior who lost her best friend, said a recent visit
to London, while difficult, helped revive good memories that had
been blocked out the past year. But the effects of the bombing are
mostly negative.
   ``It's a big battle to make friends for me now,'' she said.
``I'm afraid to get close to people. I let them in and it seems
they die.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Wednesday PMs, Dec. 20</NOTE>

</DOC>