<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 0447EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama 4thLd-Writethru a0680 12-17 0696</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0680,0711</SECOND>
<HEAD>American Soldier Shot to Death Near Defense Forces Headquarters</HEAD>
<BYLINE>Eds: LEADS with 10 grafs to UPDATE with Panama calling incident
a provocation, says three Panamanians wounded; picks up 9th pvs, `The television...'
^By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A U.S. soldier was fatally shot
Saturday night as he and three other American servicemen tried to
flee a crowd of Panamanian troopers and civilians, a U.S. Southern
Command spokesman reported.
   The Panamanian Defense Forces said Sunday that the U.S.
servicemen had fired several shots at the military headquarters of
Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega, wounding three Panamanians, including
a soldier and a 1-year-old girl. U.S. officials said the Americans
were unarmed.
   U.S. and Panamanian troops went on alert after the incident, the
most serious in a series of confrontations between the two forces.
American troops in battle gear could be seen around Fort Clayton,
and tanks were heading toward the base. Several unidentified
helicopters flew over the city shortly after midnight.
   A U.S. spokesman, Col. Ronald Sconyers, said four off-duty
American soldiers in civilian clothes were stopped by about 40
civilians and five Defense Forces troopers as they were driving by
military headquarters.
   The spokesman said the crowd tried to pull the Americans out of
the car, and as the U.S. soldiers drove off shots were fired at the
car, wounding one of the Americans. He said the other U.S.
servicemen were not injured.
   The wounded American was taken to the U.S. military's Gorgas
Hospital where he died, Sconyers said. He did not identify the
victim pending notification of his relatives.
   The Defense Forces made no mention of the American casualty in a
statement issued at 4 a.m. Sunday.
   It said a car with U.S. license plates broke through
checkpoints, drove past the Defense Headquarters and fired several
shots at it, wounding three Panamanians. The 1-year-old, Elin
Bethancourt, was wounded in the left arm, the Defense Forces said.
   Lt. Col. Arnulfo Castrejon, the duty officer at the time, called
the incident ``a provocation against the life and property of our
people.''
   Civilians said Panamanian troopers condoned off the area
surrounding the Defense Forces headquarters.
   The television channel of the U.S. Southern Command announced
that a ``Delta'' alert was in effect, restricting U.S. military
personnel to their bases. That alert was ordered during the October
revolt by a small group of Defense Forces personnel.
   Since May, there have been several confrontations between
Panamanian and U.S. forces in Panama that included shouting
matches, but no shooting.
   A Noriega-organized paramilitary force, the Dignity Battalions,
have demonstrated and tried to block recent U.S. maneuvers. In a
recent letter, the U.S. high command told the Panamanian military
that any action against U.S. personnel would be considered an
action by the Defense Forces.
   A government official, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said
Noriega, who was declared Panama's chief of government Friday, was
in the western province of Chiriqui late Saturday.
   In appointing Noriega chief executive, the rubber-stamp
legislature said the action was necessary because Panama was in a
``state of war'' with the United States. It based the state-of-war
declaration on severe ecnomic sanctions imposed on Panama in an
effort to force Noriega to step down.
   Noriega had been Panama's de facto ruler as Defense Forces chief.
   The general, who is under indictment on drug-trafficking charges
in the United States, thwarted an Oct. 3 coup attempt when loyal
troops came to his support after he was trapped and held hostage by
the rebels for several hours.
   At least 10 of the rebellious officers and soldiers who launched
the October coup were killed, either in fighting or after they
surrendered.
   Noriega has denied the U.S. drug charges and says Washington's
efforts to oust him are an attempt to avoid complying with the 1977
Panama Canal Treaties. The accords turn the waterway over to Panama
at the end of the century.
   After the October coup he claimed the United States was behind
the revolt, but Washington denied that. Some of the 12,000 American
troops stationed in Panama had blocked streets near Defense Forces
headquarters but they did not become engaged in the conflict.
</TEXT>

</DOC>