<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0922EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-GreenpeaceAcquittal     12-29 0323</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Greenpeace Acquittal,0331</SECOND>
<HEAD>Canadian Judge Acquits Greenpeace Protesters, Calls Countrymen `Too
Passive'</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Dollar figures in last graf are Canadian.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VANCOUVER, British Columbia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Five Greenpeace members were
acquitted of mischief by a judge who ruled that the anchoring of a
nuclear-capable U.S. Navy vessel off Vancouver was an invitation to
protest.
   Calling the defendants' fears ``the concerns of all right-minded
people'' about the dangers of nuclear weapons, provincial court
Judge Wallace Craig said Thursday that they were right to protest
and that Canadians had been too passive in the past.
   ``I think it's remarkable that the (Canadian) government has
seen fit to invite a vessel of this type,'' Craig said.
   The five were charged after they spray-painted peace symbols and
the international radiation warning symbol on the aircraft carrier
USS Independence as it attempted to anchor in English Bay on Aug.
9. A sixth protester charged with mischief, Rolph Reynolds, was
given a conditional discharge.
   The court was told Reynolds climbed the carrier's anchor chain
waving a flag.
   Craig said he accepted that the defendants believed there were
nuclear weapons aboard the ship. The U.S. Navy routinely refuses to
confirm or deny whether nuclear weapons are aboard a vessel.
   Carrier navigator Cmdr. Richard Ormsbee said Reynolds put the
vessel's captain in a perilous situation because the carrier was in
danger of running aground near Stanley Park.
   If Reynolds hadn't been dragged off the anchor chain, he said,
the captain would have been faced with dangerous choices.
   He would have been forced to either drop the port anchor,
endangering small boats near the ship's bow, drop the starboard
anchor with Reynolds on it, or throw the engines into full reverse,
swamping several small boats, Ormsbee said.
   Craig said Reynolds' actions could have caused the accident he
was trying to prevent, but refused to grant the Navy's request for
$1,950 for fuel the ship burned while the carrier was attempting to
anchor.
</TEXT>

</DOC>