<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0220 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1513EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-ToySafety Bjt   12-19 0666</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Toy Safety, Bjt,0692</SECOND>
<HEAD>Toy Manufacturer Looks to Increase Regulation</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOYA L. WESLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MILWAUKEE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   With just a few days left before Christmas, at
least one toy manufacturer's thoughts have turned from sales to
safety.
   Peter Reynolds, president of Milwaukee toymaker Brio USA, is
taking advantage of the season to amplify his call for stronger
regulation in the $12.5 billion-a-year toy industry.
   Reynolds, whose company is best known for its wooden train sets,
wants the Consumer Product Safety Commission to shift from
voluntary to mandatory safety standards.
   ``The toy industry as a whole has a pretty good record,''
Reynolds said in an interview. ``But, obviously, one death or one
injury is too many. To me, the big problem with safety is that the
law does not require any manufacturer to test any toy.''
   He said the commission's voluntary standards allow too many
hazards to slip through its safety net.
   But others in the industry, including several charged with the
duty of ensuring toy safety, say Reynolds' concerns are overblown.
   David Miller, president of Toy Manufacturers of America, said
the voluntary standards the industry uses are some of the ``most
comprehensive in the world.''
   ``We're usually complaining that we're over-regulated and that
they mettle too much in how we do our business,'' Miller said.
   In 1988, the commission logged 142,000 toy-related injuries for
children of all ages. Between January 1988 and September 1989 it
received reports of 34 toy-related deaths, spokeswoman Anne Pavlich
said.
   Most large manufacturers _ including Brio, whose parent company
is based in Sweden _ already test their toys for safety. The vast
majority of injuries and deaths are caused by the toys of smaller
companies and imports, Reynolds claimed.
   ``The major manufacturers would probably question my sanity in
doing this,'' he said. ``What I'm doing is I'm voicing an opinion
and hopefully someone will hear it.''
   Ms. Pavlich said the commission receives complaints both for too
much interference and not enough regulation.
   ``We're damned if we do, damned if we don't,'' she said. ``There
are people telling us that they want us to do more, and others
telling us that we're doing too much.''
   The commission's activities include monitoring injuries and
deaths through reports from hospital emergency rooms and other
sources; recalling hazardous toys through reports from its
investigators, consumers and the manufacturers themselves; and
working with the U.S. Customs Service to prevent imports of illegal
toys, she said.
   The commission and Miller's association work together with the
Philadelphia-based American Society for Testing and Materials to
develop the voluntary safety standards for toys.
   ASTM is a 90-year-old organization with 32,000 members who
represent manufacturers, consumers and other interests, said
Patricia Downey, public relations manager. The members make up 135
committees that develop standards, she said.
   ``The important thing about our standards is that they're not
mandatory,'' Ms. Downey said. ``The main premise is that there be a
balance between the producer and the user.''
   The commission is represented on the consumer products committee
to make sure the testing standards for toys ``meet the consumer's
needs,'' Ms. Pavlich said.
   If the commission were to decide that the requirements were
insufficient, it could establish mandatory requirements, she said.
   Miller said his association, which represents manufacturers
accounting for 90 percent of U.S. toy sales, works with the society
and regularly reviews testing requirements.
   Miller said those voluntary requirements and the commission's
other efforts are enough to keep the market safe.
   ``I find it amusing to be defending them, but the people who are
picking on them know very little about toy safety,'' Miller said.
   Toy experts also agree that much of toy safety depends on
parents, who must buy the right toys for their children and make
sure they're used properly.
   Reynolds said parents often ignore age labels, and by doing that
put their children in danger.
   ``If it says for 3 years old and up and you give it to a
10-month-old, it could be potentially dangerous,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>