<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0116 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2000EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-PeaceEconomy     12-19 0416</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Peace Economy,420</SECOND>
<HEAD>Economists Say Subsidies Not Answer to Defense-Linked Economy</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Bush-Budget, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DONNA CASSATA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Cuts in U.S. military spending in response to
a waning Soviet threat will create economic problems in
defense-oriented regions, but a group of economists said Tuesday
that federal subsidies aren't the answer.
   ``Major federal spending to support particular regions is
counterproductive to the economy,'' Donald H. Straszheim, chief
economist at Merrill Lynch Capital Markets, told Congress' Joint
Economic Committee.
   ``Regional interests overwhelming the national interest is part
of the problem, not part of the solution,'' he said.
   Defense Secretary Dick Cheney is considering cuts in the armed
forces and cancellation or lengthening weapons programs as part of
an effort to reduce the defense budget.
   Last month, Cheney directed the services to come up with between
$140 billion and $180 billion in cuts from the fiscal 1992 to 1994
military budgets.
   Straszheim and two other economists testifying before the
committee, which is examining the economic adjustment after the
Cold War, said cuts in military spending will affect defense
contractors nationwide. However, they said financial assistance
from Washington and a national job retraining program should not be
options.
   Pressed by Rep. James Scheuer, D-N.Y., Straszheim said that
although the approach was a ``cold, hard position of doing
nothing,'' he would not suggest a wide-ranging program to help
areas that might be financially strapped.
   ``A few years ago, Texas was devastated when oil prices went up
and then down. ... That's life,'' Straszheim said.
   Scheuer, whose district includes parts of New York City and Long
Island, wondered about Grumman Corp., the Long Island manufacturer
of the Navy's F-14D Tomcat jet fighter.
   Cheney, in the fiscal 1990 defense budget, proposed canceling
the program. Congress agreed to continue it for one more year but
forced Grumman to sign an agreement that included a termination
clause.
   ``Grumman sits over that Long Island economy like a 600-pound
canary,'' Scheuer said. ``What do we do about the 10,000 employees
at risk? What do we do about the Long Island economy? Do we have a
retraining program?''
   Other hard hit areas that rely heavily on defense business
include San Antonio, San Diego and the tidewater region of Virginia.
   Charles L. Schultze, director of the economic studies program at
the Brookings Institution, said the adjustment from cuts in defense
would be no different from changes that occur every year across the
nation in other businesses.
   ``This isn't a big deal,'' Schultze said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>