<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0104 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1537EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Yeutter-Farm     12-21 0570</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Yeutter-Farm,590</SECOND>
<HEAD>Yeutter Says Farmers Had Good Year</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Farmers are closing out ``one of the best
years ever'' but will be subject to pivotal decisions in 1990 by
Congress and international trade negotiators, Agriculture Secretary
Clayton Yeutter said Thursday.
   Yeutter said 1989 income reached near-record levels,
agricultural exports have improved and the farm-credit situation
has eased for both lenders and borrowers.
   ``Net farm income will be either at or near a record for 1989,''
he said. ``The numbers are not fully determined yet, but certainly
it's been a very good year for American agriculture, one of the
best ever.''
   Most questions at Yeutter's year-end news conference related to
the Uruguay Round trade negotations under the General Agreement on
Tariffs and Trade, or GATT. Those talks are scheduled to conclude a
year from now.
   Yeutter was asked if he thought there would be a freer
international market by 1999, one of the goals sought by U.S.
negotiators, particularly for agricultural products.
   ``My personal assessment is that we have the best chance for
significant trade liberalization in agriculture that we've
experienced since the GATT began'' 40 years ago, he replied.
   ``I do believe it'll be a freer market 10 years from now than it
is today, and I also believe firmly that that will work to the
advantage of the American farmer.''
   Other questions related to legislation being drafted by Congress
to succeed the 1985 farm law that expires next year. Yeutter said
teams of Agriculture Department experts are working on plans for
the 1990 farm bill but did not divulge details.
   The United States at the GATT talks has sought a gradual
reduction and eventual elimination of all trade-distorting
subsidies and policies. But administration officials have adamantly
insisted that no U.S. programs would be scrapped unless other
countries did likewise.
   ``Though we may want to make some changes in all of these
programs in the 1990 farm bill because those may be desirable in
their own right ... we're not going to unilaterally disarm
internationally in that legislation,'' Yeutter said.
   ``So, whether we're talking about sugar, the wheat program or
any other program, I determined that we not forgo any of our
negotiating leverage in that 1990 legislative debate,'' he said.
``But at the same time, I am not prepared to accept the arguments
of any individual industry to the effect that says all changes in
the program are off-limits.''
   Yeutter, who joined President Bush's cabinet in January, was
U.S. trade representative in the Reagan administration and has been
in the thick of Uruguay round negotiations since they began Sept.
20, 1986, in Punta del Esta, Uruguay.
   ``I'm always an optimist, as you know,'' he said about the final
push during talks in 1990. ``But, certainly, I do not underestimate
the negotiating challenge. It will be significant indeed.''
   Yeutter said it would require ``an immense amount of effort and
a strong political commitment'' on the part of the United States,
the European Economic Community, Japan, the developing countries
and others to bring the GATT talks to a close a year from now.
   The private sector, including farm groups, also will be
important in reaching U.S. objectives during the negotiations, he
said.
   ``They can disagree about tactics ... or they can disagree about
particular nuances of the program,'' Yeutter said. ``But it's
important that we have broad support for our fundamental
objectives.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>