<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0217 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1331EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--Millennium Adv31-1stAdd   12-18 1088</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Millennium, Adv 31-1st Add,1113</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv24</HEAD>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 24</HEAD>
<HEAD>UNDATED: there yet.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   This brings us to 1285 A.U.C., which the abbot of Rome,
Dionysius Exiguus, decided after much research was 532 A.D., that
many years since the birth of Christ. Everything else was B.C. even
though, for instance, it was year 146 of the Yuan Wei dynasty in
China. The century before, early Christians at the Council of
Nicaea (1206 A.U.C, 4214 A.M. or 453 A.D.) had pegged Easter to the
spring equinox, as well as Passover, out of respect for Christ's
Jewish origins. This tie-in became important in Christian dogma.
   Enter the Moslems. They began counting from Thursday, July 16,
622 A.D., when Allah directed Mohammed to flee from Mecca. His
successor, Omar, opted for a lunar calendar of 12 alternating
29-and 30-day months for a year of 354 days. Since intercalation
was forbidden, Islam has a lot of movable feasts and fasts. As the
lunar year gains a year on solar about every 32 years, you can
figure a Moslem is a year older if not wiser for every such period.
   In India, astronomers picked up on solar time, but there were a
lot of calendars that kings and rajahs dated for themselves. The
Sivajli Era began, for example, with year one as of June 6, 1674,
when King Maratha was crowned in western India.
   The Era of Parasurama began in 1176 B.C. around Madras but is so
complicated you don't even want to think about it. The Saka
calendar dates from March 3, A.D. 78 when the visible planets were
lined up.
   India had about 17 calendars when it went Gregorian in 1957 when
March 22 became 1 chatra 1879 Saka. There is also a time period of
4,320,000 years in the Hindu religion called the mahayuga, which is
one day in the life of Brahman, god of creation, which makes A.U.C.
look like a split second.
   As Julian time passed, Easter was increasingly out of synch with
equinox-Passover and well on its way to summer. In the 13th century
a worried Roger Bacon in England wrote Pope Clement IV about it.
Nothing happened. The Council of Trent, which began in 1545,
authorized reform.
   Pope Gregory XIII finally sat down with Italian astronomer
Aloisius Lilius and German math whiz Christopher Clavius and
devised a new calendar. Years ending in double zero were only leap
years if they could be divided by 400. That meant the calendar was
only off 26 seconds a year and only one day by the 1420th olympiad,
plus a year of A.D. 4905. Gregory forthwith decreed that Thursday,
Oct. 4, 1582, would be followed by Friday, Oct. 15.
   Catholic nations dutifully complied. Protestants, being
protesters, protested Gregory was trying to confuse Christ's second
coming and wasn't he afraid the world would end sooner? Suspicious,
Britain didn't go Gregorian until Sept. 2, 1752, a Wednesday to be
followed by Thursday the 14th, the Julian calendar then being 11
days out of whack.
   Laborers rioted over lost pay. Landlords screamed about lost
rent. Ben Franklin, cool as ever, counseled his fellow British
subjects to ``lie down in peace on the 2nd and not wake till the
morning of the 14th.'' Which they did. As usual, time healed all
wounds, including George Washington's, who, since Gregory moved New
Year's from March 25 to January 1, was now born in 1732 instead of
1731, thus becoming a year younger.
   The Russians stuck with Julius Caesar until after the Bolshevik
Revolution, hence the October parade in November. Alaska lost 12
days when it changed hands from the czar to the United States in
1867, but life went on.
   For some reason, revolutionaries seem to take it out on the
calendar. For a time American redhots dated from their rebellion
against England. The French Revolution all but guillotined the
calendar, abolishing Sunday with a 10-day week. The new calendar
had 12 30-day months poetically named, e.g. Floreal (``blossom
month'') and Vendemaire (``vintage month''). The last five days of
the year were named ``sans cullotides'' (without pantaloons) in
honor of the Paris freedom fighters of the barricades who couldn't
afford aristocratic knickers. Napoleon went Gregorian again in 1805.
   Not that Gregory's work is ideal. ``Untidy,'' says Doggett.
   Gregory's year can't be divided into handy halves and quarters,
upsetting finicky accountants. Dates keep falling on different
days. The Western Clock Co. of La Salle, Ill., decided in 1892 to
go its own bookkeeping way with a regular quarterly calendar. By
1950, 1,062 companies in the United States and Canada had followed
suit.
   One suggested reform is for 13 months of 28 days each. Each year
would begin Sunday and end Saturday, followed by a Year Day. People
born Jan. 29, for example, would blow out the candles Feb. 1. In
all, 94 days would have to be moved.
   In 1930, Elisabeth Achelis, an American, proposed a World
Calendar of even quarters moving only eight days and making the
same date recur on the same day every year, adding leap year at the
end of June and putting a year day at the end that would not be
Sunday or anything else. The United Nations has mulled it over, but
Seventh Day Adventists and Orthodox Jews object to the
disappearance of a sabbath.
   Then there's the Earth herself. In A.D. 1654, James Ussher,
archbishop of the Church of England, delved into assorted Old
Testaments and astronomical works and decided time began when
Creation did: 9 a.m. Oct. 4, 4004 B.C. By this reckoning 1-1-2000
or even 1-1-2001 aren't millennia at all. It's just 6004.
   But Earth, like a proper dowager, is coy about her age.
Scientists know sometimes she spins slower, sometimes faster. They
don't know why. Several hours have been lost in the past 3,000
years.
   What's official, however, is that in just 10 years your
insurance company's Gregorian calendar will end in 000. That means
Earth will have embarked on her 2,000th orbit around the sun since
Dionysius Exiguus's year zero. (A lot of people have claimed
Exiguus was four years off about A.D.-B.C., but they were too late,
so to speak).
   Whether purists deign to salute 2000 with a toot or two remains
to be seen. To many Mayans in the crowd, it will be a humdrum
5113th year for those crackerjack astronomers. The Japanese will
toast 2660. Indians will celebrate Saka 1922. Romulus may wish
Remus a prosperous 2573 A.U.C.
   To the rest of you, happy millennium.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>

</DOC>