<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0173 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0235EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Freeze-Prices Bjt   12-28 0532</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Freeze-Prices, Bjt,0549</SECOND>
<HEAD>Freeze Effects Will Appear in Supermarkets Within Days</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CATHERINE WILSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Wholesale vegetable prices have tripled in some
cases as Florida farmers scramble to harvest crops that survived a
deadly two-night freeze and plant replacement vegetables.
   ``A lot of people have a built-in resistance to paying over a
dollar a pound for tomatoes or over a dollar a head for lettuce,''
said Pete Packett, spokesman for the state Department of
Agriculture. ``Some people will obviously choose other foods until
the price comes back down.''
   Prices jumped Wednesday at the wholesale level as vegetables
harvested before the freeze Saturday and Sunday night are shipped
from cold storage to stores, primarily in the East and in Midwest.
   ``The pipeline stays filled for three to seven days in advance
of any major prices change in the marketplace,'' said Reggie Brown,
spokesman for the Florida Fruit and Vegetable Association in
Orlando. ``You'll start seeing it showing up probably within a
week.''
   Wholesalers are seeing the early effects of the freeze and
passing them along.
   ``Everything has just tripled in price. Green cabbage was doing
about $8.75 (a box) and they're asking over $20 for it now,'' said
Paul Graff, manager of the Len Strom brokerage in Miami. ``Zucchini
is way up in the $25 range, which was between $11 and $12 before,
and so it goes.''
   All of the state's major vegetables, including tomatoes, bell
peppers, sweet corn, lettuce, cucumbers and celery, have been hurt,
Brown said.
   Collier County agricultural agent Steve Dobbs estimated $150
million damage to vegetables in the Immokalee area alone, a prime
growing district southwest of Lake Okeechobee.
   ``In the near term, 40 to 60 days, we're going to see some very
strong prices come out of Florida,'' said Brown. ``Then about 60 to
90 days down the road we'll probably see a large return in the
marketplace of volume, and we'll see those prices fall.''
   But even with the bitter cold taken into consideration, the U.S.
Department of Agriculture is predicting a modest 3 percent to 5
percent rise in consumer food prices for 1990.
   Buyers for Lakeland-based Publix Super Markets Inc., the
nation's eight-largest chain with 370 stores in Florida, have been
told it will be another day or two before the full extent of crop
damage is determined.
   ``It's a devastating blow, but nobody is pressing any panic
buttons because of the alternative sources on standby,'' said
Publix Vice President Bill Schroter, referring to substitute
supplies from California, Mexico and Latin America.
   But the widespread arctic chill also hurt crops elsewhere,
further clouding the supply.
   ``Not only did we get it but Texas got it,'' Packett said.
``We're the kingpins in the market. Now you're going to be looking
all the way across the country to California and Mexico for
imported produce.''
   More than 80 percent of the state's 700,000-acre citrus crop was
still on the trees when the freeze hit, but a large juice reserve
in Florida, a boom year in Brazil and swift processing of iced
oranges were expected to stabilize juice prices.
   The fresh citrus growing region of Indian River County showed
limited damage, Packett said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>