<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0092 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1701EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Panama-delCid     12-26 0729</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-del Cid,0753</SECOND>
<HEAD>Top Noriega Aide Pleads Innocent to Drug Charges</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD COLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Panamanian officer considered one of Manuel
Noriega's ``right-hand men'' and accused of helping the deposed
dictator smuggle cocaine for the Medellin cartel pleaded innocent
before a federal judge Tuesday.
   ``I surrendered myself _ I wanted to be brought here,'' Lt. Col.
Luis del Cid told U.S. District Judge William Hoeveler.
   Del Cid, 46, faces racketeering, drug-smuggling and
money-laundering charges in the same February 1988 indictment that
accused Noriega and Medellin cartel figures of importing cocaine
into the United States.
   The commander of a Panama Defense Forces unit in the northern
Panama province of Chiriqui, del Cid surrendered to U.S. forces
Saturday after last week's invasion and was brought to Miami on
Monday. He is the first key Noriega aide named in the case to be
brought into court.
   Del Cid was ``a liason, courier and emissary for Manuel Noriega,
dealing with drug trafficking,'' U.S. Attorney Dexter Lehtinen
said. ``We allege he personally imported shipments of cocaine, and
he personally transmitted large amounts of cash.''
   Lehtinen called del Cid ``one of the right-hand men of Gen.
Noriega.''
   Wearing faded jeans and a blue polo shirt, del Cid strongly
denied the four counts in court and demanded a jury trial.
   Hoeveler appointed a public defender as del Cid's temporary
counsel after the Panamanian testified he carried only $7,000 in
cash with him and had no access to a frozen savings account in
Panama.
   The judge turned back efforts by the U.S. attorney's office to
ask detailed questions of del Cid in an effort to uncover any
additional assets, saying such testimony could affect the
racketeering counts against him.
   Outside the courtroom, Lehtinen said federal investigators are
convinced the conspirators are sitting on large amounts of cash.
   ``They were dealing with large amounts of drugs _ that makes a
potential for a lot of profit,'' Lehtinen said. ``We've always
believed they made a lot of money.''
   One of Noriega's criminal attorneys, Frank Rubino, appeared at
the hearing. He said he did not expect to represent del Cid but
wanted to monitor the case.
   Lehtinen asked the judge to bar any consultations between del
Cid and Noriega's attorney, saying the defendant might not
understand that Rubino might not have del Cid's best interests in
mind, but Hoeveler refused.
   Asked if his real concern was that Noriega might try to pressure
his former aide, Lehtinen said only, ``I'd rather go with my
explanation.''
   The U.S. attorney referred any questions about Noriega to
officials in Washington. Lehtinen refused to say what contacts his
office had made with del Cid, or if he had indicated a willingness
to testify against Noriega.
   Del Cid faces a maximum of 70 years in prison and fines of
$550,000. He was ordered held without bond at the Metropolitan
Correctional Center outside Miami until a full hearing Jan. 2.
   The Miami indictment accuses Noriega, del Cid, cartel leader
Pablo Escobar Gaviria and 12 others of running drugs and using
Panama as a safe haven. Noriega, using del Cid as an emissary,
allegedly allowed the cartel to process drugs, launder money and
ship cocaine through Panama, accepting a $4.6 million bribe from
the Colombians.
   Del Cid is accused of having a personal role in a 400-kilogram
cocaine shipment to Florida in December 1982.
   He also allegedly picked up $100,000 from Noriega's personal
pilot, Floyd Carlton Cacerez, in November 1982, and delivered
$200,000 to Carlton at the military headquarters in Panama City a
month later. Carlton is one of the principal witnesses in the case.
   Two minor defendants, Brian Alden Davidow and William
Saldarriaga, were to go on trial here Jan. 8, but Lehtinen
indicated Tuesday he expects to ask for a delay in that case.
   It will not take long to begin any prosecution of del Cid,
however, the U.S. attorney said.
   ``We are confident that we have the evidence to convict him,''
Lehtinen said. ``We're ready to try him.''
   A separate federal grand jury in Tampa indicted Noriega and
others on charges of taking a $5.4 million bribe from the Medellin
cartel. But the Justice Department has said if Noriega is brought
to the United States, he would be tried first in Miami because the
prosecution case there is stronger.
   Del Cid was not named in the Tampa indictment.
</TEXT>

</DOC>