<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0231 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1826EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Airlines-Fuel 2ndLd-Writethru f0287 12-29 0622</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Airlines-Fuel, 2nd Ld-Writethru, f0287,0640</SECOND>
<HEAD>Airlines Considering Fuel Surcharges on Tickets</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 10th graf pvs to CORRECT punctuation of `decision's'; PICKS
UP 11th graf pvs, `The airline...</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCY GORDON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   United Airlines, Trans World Airlines and
Eastern Airlines said Friday they were considering new surcharges
on tickets to help cover the skyrocketing cost of jet fuel.
   Other airlines also may be weighing the measure, which if
imposed would be the first special fuel surcharge by the airlines
since the 1970s oil crisis.
   ``It is a fare increase,'' said Louis Marckesano, an airline
analyst at the Philadelphia brokerage Janney Montgomery Scott Inc.
``It's going to raise the cost of the ticket.''
   A fuel surcharge likely would be figured into fares rather than
charged separately, analysts suggested. They speculated the
airlines might charge around $3 per ticket.
   Earlier this week, in an effort to lure passengers during the
slow winter months, the nation's big airlines cut fares as much as
30 percent in selected markets.
   Oil prices have been catapulted higher recently by the
record-setting cold snap and refinery problems in Texas and
Louisiana. Jet fuel, which represents around 35 percent of an
airline's operating budget, has jumped to 96 cents a gallon from 64
cents at the end of October.
   Every 1 cent rise in the price of jet fuel costs U.S. airlines a
total $150 million a year, according to the Air Transport
Association, an industry group in Washington, D.C.
   ``It has been a precipitous and unprecedented increase in fuel
prices ... considering there hasn't been a disruption in
supplies,'' said Robin Matell, a spokesman for Eastern at its
headquarters in Miami. ``We're reviewing the situation and suspect
other carriers are doing the same. In that sense, a surcharge
cannot be ruled out.''
   Don Morrison, a TWA spokesman in St. Louis, Mo., said, ``We're
in the process of looking at some fuel data. We are looking at some
possibilities.''
   United, the nation's second-largest airline, also is pondering a
charge, said Rob Doughty, a spokesman in Chicago. ``We're looking
at it; no decision's been made,'' he said.
   The airline spokesmen all declined to give further details.
   On Thursday, explaining a new hike in Northeast shuttle fares
from $99 one way to $119 on weekdays, Trump Shuttle cited increased
costs for fuel and other expenses. Trump Shuttle officials weren't
immediately available for comment Friday on whether they were
weighing a surcharge as well.
   Spokesmen for Delta Air Lines, USAir Group Inc. and Pan Am Corp.
said those airlines were not considering a fuel surcharge at the
present time.
   A special fuel surcharge would not require government approval
for domestic flights.
   Such a charge hasn't been imposed in the United States since
1973, when oil prices rose steeply and the federal government
allowed the airlines to raise fares a few dollars to help cover
costs. The U.S. airline industry was deregulated in October 1978.
   Since then, other types of surcharges have been instituted _ for
airport security and for the Airport and Airway Trust Fund. Some
U.S. carriers, such as Pan Am and TWA, add $5 to the cost of a
trans-Atlantic ticket to cover security screening for international
flights.
   The aviation trust fund is supplied by an 8 percent tax that is
included in fares. Because of pressure to reduce the federal budget
deficit, neither the White House nor Congress has been willing to
dip into the fund, which hit $6.9 billion in September.
   Under legislation before Congress, the money would be released
to pay for devices to detect plastic explosives in baggage.
   ``Fuel surcharges are a way of life in Europe,'' said Paul Turk,
an analyst with consulting firm Avmark Inc. in Arlington, Va.
</TEXT>

</DOC>