<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0182 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1933EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-PRI--Gardening Adv28   12-26 0744</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-PRI--Gardening, Adv 28,0763</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv28</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Thursday, Dec. 28, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Home Landscape Maintenance, KISS and KISS Again</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   James Walters worked for the AP as a reporter
and editor from 1947 until he retired in 1984.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By JAMES E. WALTERS</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   If maintaining a home landscape is more work than
pleasure, a few changes may help. Retirement offers a splendid
opportunity to take time for a detailed assessment, and it's worth
doing whether you're 20 or 70.
   Start by determining what you and the family like, dislike or
have no strong opinion about. Be realistic. Be pragmatic. Be
diplomatic. But above all, get an honest reading. Then, have a
little fun and adopt ``KISS'' as the game plan: Keep It Simple,
Stupid.
   For example, is it worth the effort to plant, water, weed,
fertilize and prune that bed of annual flowers or bulbs? Would
low-maintenance flowering shrubs be as pleasing? Don't apologize if
the choice is the bed of flowers; just be sure. And say KISS often
when looking at things that take time.
   Before I retired, my home had a gorgeous lawn. There was Bermuda
grass in summer and, in this subtropical climate, even greener
ryegrass all winter. At least once a week, I'd empty the mower's
grasscatcher seven or eight times. The family loved that lawn _
badminton, croquet, just sprawling on the grass.
   But children and grandchildren grow older. It was used less and
less. Water bills kept climbing. Decomposed granite and native
shrubs and trees became an increasingly attractive alternative.
Now, I fill only one grasscatcher each time I mow. The saving in
time alone is considerable.
   One person's solution, of course, can be another's horror story.
But the basics never change: simplify maintenance by eliminating
unnecessary things.
   Folks who move to a different climate also need to forget
nostalgia. Heroic urban horticulture may keep alive long-time
favorites from other states, but it's usually time-consuming,
expensive and generally self-defeating. Make sure, say, that a
lilac or ceanothus will grow in the new neighborhood. Can you even
tell the difference between the East's lilac and the West's
ceanothus?
   Take the time to understand your plants' needs. Can they be
replaced with something better or simpler? The Cooperative
Extension Service, listed under the U.S. Department of Agriculture
in most telephone books, is a good source.
   Hybrid tea roses are an example of something that can be changed
without much difficulty. Their floral display is seldom matched,
yet they need enormous care. One solution is to have a hybrid tea
or two for cut flowers and replace the others with less demanding
types such as floribunda or shrub roses.
   Systemic insecticides eliminate a lot of mixing of chemicals and
spraying. Just be sure to follow the label directions carefully.
Fertilizing often can be simplified with slow-release types, though
these tend to be expensive and can be deadly if timing of the
application induces plant growth when it should be slowing. But
they're a great convenience and unmatched in container growing.
   Avoid scattered plantings. If cutting the grass, can you keep
going for long periods without backing and turning? Does a certain
shrub have to be where it impedes the mower? Would a mowing strip
eliminate hand trimming?
   Perhaps stone or gravel would look better in areas under garden
benches or house overhangs. Is a raised bed called for? Does
traffic make grass a losing battle in a certain area, dictating
paving? Would ground cover hide litter from a tree? Do some plants
always seem to be nibbled by grasshoppers, attacked by aphids or
sunburned? Why not replace them? Consider the same approach for a
tree or shrub that requires frequent pruning or leaf raking.
   A pre-emergence herbicide will control many weeds before they
start. Vegetation-killing sprays formulated with glyphosate are one
of the most important gardening developments in recent years. Even
toughies like Bermuda are a soft touch, but don't get it close to
anything green you want to keep.
   Sometimes changing the land's contour just an inch or two is all
that's needed to improve drainage. Maybe a shade-loving plant is
getting too much sun, while moving it a few feet will make it
happy. A mulch can give a neat appearance, save moisture and
protect against climate extremes.
   The list of potential problem-solvers is just about endless.
   But no solution is possible until the problem is pinpointed.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Dec. 28</NOTE>

</DOC>