<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0202 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0819EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Inland-Nippon     12-19 0290</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Inland-Nippon,0302</SECOND>
<HEAD>Inland to Sell 13 Percent Stake to Nippon Steel</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Inland Steel Industries Inc. has announced plans
to sell a 13 percent stake to Nippon Steel Corp. of Japan for $185
million.
   The proposed transaction was announced after the close of
trading Monday on the New York Stock Exchange and involves the sale
of 185,000 shares of a newly issued preferred stock for $1,000 a
share.
   Chicago-based Inland will spend proceeds from the sale to buy
back its common stock on the open market within a year, said
company spokesman Sam Saran.
   Inland also agreed to place a mutually acceptable designee of
Nippon Steel on its board of directors. Nippon agreed it would not
acquire additional Inland shares for 10 years without Inland's
approval.
   Nippon paid $15 million for 1 percent of Inland's common stock
earlier this year, and the new transaction would raise Nippon's
stake to 14 percent.
   The transaction will ``strengthen the company's long-term
competitive position in the steel industry through an expanded
strategic partnership with Nippon Steel,'' Inland Chairman Frank
Luerssen said in a statement.
   In addition, it will provide significant benefits to
stockholders, he said.
   Saran called the development ``another strategic move involving
the close collaborative relationship between our two companies.''
He said the announcement was not an antitakeover defense.
   In a statement from Tokyo, Nippon Steel President Hiroshi Saito
said: ``With the growth of global manufacturing enterprises, strong
international relationships are increasingly important to assure
our steel customers' needs in North America.''
   In 1986, the two firms agreed to build a $400 million continuous
cold-rolling mill in New Carlisle, Ind. The mill, which uses
Nippon's technology for manufacturing sheet steel for the
automotive industry, is to begin operation next year.
</TEXT>

</DOC>