<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0128 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1701EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Panama-Smithsonian     12-21 0304</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Smithsonian,300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Smithsonian Group Freed In Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-US-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eleven people associated with the Smithsonian
Institution were reported free but awaiting pickup by U.S. troops a
day after Panamanian forces abducted them, President Bush and
Smithsonian officials said Thursday.
   ``They have been released by the Panamanian Defense Forces,''
said Madeleine Jacobs, a Smithsonian spokeswoman. ``But they are
not safe; they are not in U.S. hands; we are very concerned.''
   Bush, questioned at a news conference about Americans hostages
in Panama, said the Smithsonian people ``have now been released.''
He said he had no idea how many other people were being held in
Panama against their will.
   Smithsonian officials said the group who worked at the
Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute on the San Blas islands in
the Caribbean off the coast of Panama was in a remote location
between Cerro Carti and El Llano on the mainland.
   Members of the group had access to a radio that enabled them to
contact Smithsonian employees in Panama City, Jacobs said.
   At the time the group was kidnapped by members of the PDF, a
technician on the island called Panama City to say they were being
transferred to the mainland and taken by truck to an unknown
destination, Jacobs said.
   The group _ five Americans, five Panamanians and one Venezuelan
_ worked as scientists or technicians. They were performing marine
research on the coral reef.
   Jacobs refused to identify members of the group. But she said
only one American worked for the Smithsonian. The others were
affiliated with universities or research operations.
   Besides its station at Sanblas and the headquarters at Panama
City, the tropical institute has several other stations throughout
the isthmus. Most of the staff members, 120 of whom work full time,
are Americans and Panamanians.
</TEXT>

</DOC>