<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0848EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Iran-Romania     12-26 0462</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Iran-Romania,0476</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tehran Sacks Envoy In Bucharest After Ceausescu Visit</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ED BLANCHE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iran dismissed its ambassador to Romania
for having failed to report the revolt against President Nicolae
Ceausescu, who visited Tehran the same week he was ousted, the
Foreign Ministry announced today.
   Mohammad Jamshid Gowhari was sacked on orders of Foreign
Minister Ali Akbar Velayati, the official Islamic Republic News
Agency quoted the ministry's director-general for press affairs,
Mohammad Hassan Qadiri, as saying.
   IRNA, monitored in Nicosia, said the dismissal ``was due to
Gowhari's failure to furnish the Foreign Ministry with a
comprehensive report on the internal situation in Romania'' before
Ceausescu flew to Tehran for a three-day visit Dec. 18.
   Also today, the Foreign Ministry announced recognition of the
new Romanian government, reported Tehran Radio monitored in Cyprus.
Iran joins the United States, the Soviet Union and a host of other
Eastern and Western nations in recognizing the country's new
leadership.
   Gowhari's dismissal reflected what appears to be mounting
embarrassment in Tehran stemming from Ceausescu's visit at a time
when his countrymen were in open revolt against him. Two days after
Ceausescu's return to Bucharest, he was overthrown by the uprising
that began a week earlier.
   Bucharest Radio reported that Ceausescu and his wife, Elena,
were executed Monday after they were found guilty during a secret
military trial of genocide and ``grave crimes'' during his
tyrannical 24-year rule.
   Gowhari was dismissed only three months before he was due to
return to Tehran, IRNA reported.
   Ceausescu was given a red carpet welcome in Tehran. Romania was
Iran's second-biggest trading partner in Eastern Europe, and during
his visit Ceausescu signed an agreement to buy 1 million barrels of
oil a year.
   After Ceausescu left and reports from Romania underlined the
brutality of his regime as the mass graves of victims of his secret
police were uncovered, Iranian newspapers demanded an official
explanation why the Romanian leader had been allowed to visit
Tehran.
   Velayati responded Sunday by saying the visit had been arranged
after frequent requests from Bucharest. But he stressed that
Iranian leaders repeatedly advised Ceausescu to ``bow to his
people's demands'' while he was in Tehran.
   During Ceausescu's visit, however, IRNA praised Romania as ``the
sole east European country rigidly adhering to its past
government.''
   IRNA reported that legislator Hojatoleslamn Sadeq Khalkhali
``strongly objected to Ceausescu's visit.''
   Khalkhali was president of the revolutionary courts in the early
days of the 1979 Islamic revolution and was notorious for
sentencing thousands of ``counter-revolutionaries'' to death, often
on the flimsiest of pretexts.
   Iran has also hotly denied European reports that Iranians were
fighting alongside Ceausescu's security police against rebel forces
and that Ceausescu had stashed a fortune in gold in Tehran banks.
</TEXT>

</DOC>