<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1131EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Romania-Journalist     12-28 0283</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Journalist,0292</SECOND>
<HEAD>Burial For TV Journalist Killed in Romania</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 1,000 people packed into a small chapel to
honor a French television reporter crushed by a tank as he reported
on the revolution in Romania.
   A Romanian flag with its Communist symbols cut from the center
draped the coffin of Jean-Louis Calderon, 31, before his burial
Wednesday in the Parisian suburb of Poissy.
   A ceremony was held earlier in the afternoon at the Chapelle
Notre-Dame de Compassion in western Paris near the headquarters of
La Cinq, the station where Calderon worked.
   In attendance were Minister for Humanitarian Affairs Bernard
Kouchner and Robert Hersant, the French media magnate who serves as
president of the private network.
   Calderon arrived Friday in Bucharest to report on the ouster of
Nicolae Ceausescu and fighting between the army and security forces
loyal to the former dictator.
   About 30 army tanks entered the square before the Central
Committee headquarters about 2 a.m. Saturday, where Calderon and
cameraman Patrice Dutertre were photographing a crowd of
demonstrators.
   One of the tanks turned unexpectedly and ran over Calderon.
Dutertre narrowly avoided injury.
   Calderon had worked as a radio and television reporter since
1981 and reported from Lebanon, Chad, Chile, South Africa, Morocco,
Portugal and the United States. His survivors include a wife and
two daughters.
   A Belgian TV reporter, Danny Huwe, 42, died Sunday when snipers
ambushed a car bringing him and other journalists from Sofia,
Bulgaria to Bucharest. Turkish reporter Emre Aygen was wounded.
   At least four other journalists have been wounded, including
John Daniszewski of The Associated Press, John Tagliabue of The New
York Times, Italian photographer Pasquale Modica and a Yugoslavian
reporter.
</TEXT>

</DOC>