<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0090 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1535EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Nicaragua-StateDepartment 1stLd-Writethru a0544 12-30
0470</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nicaragua-State Department, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0544,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>US: Nicaragua's Expulsion of Diplomats `Irresponsible Overreaction'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS final graf with 2 grafs to UPDATE with Nicaragua releasing
names of expelled diplomats and that top U.S. diplomat not on list</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KAREN BALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nicaragua's expulsion of 20 American diplomats
from Managua after U.S. troops found an arms cache at a Nicaraguan
diplomat's residence in Panama City was an ``irresponsible
overreaction,'' the State Department said Saturday.
   The expulsion order from Nicaraguan President Daniel Ortega was
``clearly motivated by Nicaraguan desires to reduce the size of our
mission before Nicaraguan elections in February,'' the State
Department said in a statement.
   ``By reducing our mission drastically, the Nicaraguan government
hopes to curtail severely our ability to monitor the fairness and
openness of the elections,'' the statement said.
   The wide array of weapons discovered during Friday's search of
the residence were returned when U.S. troops determined they had
searched the residence of a Nicaraguan diplomat, the State
Department said.
   Shortly after the search, Ortega said 20 American diplomats were
being expelled from Managua in retaliation for the incident.
   Nicaragua's ambassador to Panama, Antenor Ferrey, said U.S.
troops surrounded his residence in Panama City, ordered all
personnel outside and searched the building for weapons.
   The State Department said U.S. troops were ``reacting to
reliable information regarding an arms cache'' when it searched the
residence. It was occupied by individuals who turned out to be
members of the Nicaraguan diplomatic mission, the department said.
   Ferrey had said five rifles were seized and later returned by
U.S. troops with apologies, but the State Department said Saturday
that U.S. troops located weapons ``in excess of normal requirements
for defending the residence.''
   The State Department said the cache included four Uzi machine
guns, six rocket-propelled grenade launchers, 12 AK-47s, three hand
grenades, 10 FEN rifles, 17 bayonets, one M-1 carbine, one shotgun,
four rocket-propelled grenade sights, one light anti-tank weapon,
27 rocket-propelled grenade rounds and approximately 1,300 rounds
of ammunition of various caliber.
   The residence was not damaged and there were no injuries to the
occupants, the department said, adding that the United States had
``expressed our regrets'' about the incident.
   The State Department declined to identify the expelled
diplomats, but Nicaragua's Foreign Ministry identified them as:
Louis Falino, John S. Boarman, J. Warren Navarre, Christopher
McMullen, Katherine M. Igmanson, Susan Kay Mutschler, Barbara M.
Hamm, Jacqueline N. Dontric, William J. Overton, Robert L. Delves,
John W. Fuhrer, Mary S. Gaber, Santiago Urieta, John Durham,
Michael J. Weidmann, Frank R. Newland, Deolinda S. Armijo, John T.
Torres, Pauline E. Davis and Valentino Martinez. Government
newspapers have accused Martinez of being an adviser to Nicaragua's
political opposition alliance.
   The top U.S. official in Managua, charge d'affaires John
Leonard, was not on the list.
</TEXT>

</DOC>