<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0137 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1802EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Romania     12-21 0525</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Romania,0543</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tass Gives Details on Romanian Protests, No Defense of Ceausescu</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The official Tass news agency dispatched dramatic
and detailed reports from Romania's capital early Friday, making
little attempt to hide the swelling public feelings against
President Nicolae Ceausescu.
   Absent from the Tass reports were any details of Ceausescu's
speech at an official rally in Bucharest, where he was shouted down.
   In years past, Tass would have emphasized Ceausescu's views.
Instead, it reported the growing protests against him and clashes
between demonstrators and police.
   The coverage highlighted the Kremlin's changing attitude toward
the conservative Communist stalwart, which has resulted in frosty
meetings between Ceausescu and reform-minded Soviet President
Mikhail S. Gorbachev.
   Gorbachev repeatedly has expressed support for the reformers who
have taken power this year in other Eastern European countries.
   The Soviet president withheld comment on the events in Romania,
where hundreds, perhaps thousands, have been reported killed in
recent days. He told the Soviet parliament that members from the
republic of Moldavia had called for adoption of a statement on the
turmoil in the country on their eastern border.
   But Gorbachev said the Soviet Union had not received enough
information about the events to warrant comment, even though the
Foreign Ministry summoned the Romanian ambassador in Moscow and
asked its envoy in Bucharest to supply details.
   ``The Romanian ambassador here does not provide an opportunity
to form a notion of what is taking place in that country,''
Gorbachev told the 2,250 deputies.
   Tass, meanwhile, spoke of swelling numbers of demonstrators
shouting anti-Ceausescu slogans. It said the government responded
with tanks patrolling the streets, and ``There is yet no official
response to the events in Bucharest.''
   Tass also reported that at least two people were killed after
they were run over by an armored personnel carrier and that
demonstrators were fired on.
   Soviet Foreign Ministry spokesman Vadim Perfiliev, at a Moscow
briefing, declined comment.
   ``If we do receive information on victims among people we of
course will be extremely sorry for them,'' he said.
   But he added: ``We should emphasize that we do have opinions on
what is happening but in my place as an official representative of
the Ministry of Foreign Affairs I cannot go into comments without
having all-inclusive information and orders in that regard.''
   The Kremlin's attitude toward the Romanian leader became
apparent Dec. 4 after Ceausescu met Gorbachev in Moscow.
   An official report said the two met in ``comradely fashion in
the spirit of an open exchange of opinions.'' In diplomatic jargon,
that means they disagreed sharply.
   In the Soviet republic of Moldavia, which borders Romania and
has a large populace that speak a Romanian dialect, activists said
they planned an outdoor religious service Friday for victims of the
bloodshed in Romania.
   Moldavians are ethnically very close to Romanians, but the
border between their republic and Romania has been tightly guarded
since Ceausescu refused in 1968 to take part in the Warsaw Pact
invasion of Czechoslovakia.
   Natalya Pascal, a spokeswoman for the Moldavian People's Front,
said ethnic Moldavians had not been able to gather any detailed
information on the events across the border.
</TEXT>

</DOC>