<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0629EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-China-Party     12-30 0365</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-China-Party,0380</SECOND>
<HEAD>Party Chief Jiang Calls For Corruption Fight To Restore Ties with
People</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHY WILHELM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The head of the Communist Party renewed his
attack on reform movements while officials took steps to halt
students' display of support for Romania's revolution.
   ``The Chinese Communist Party and China are at a critical moment
and we should continue to keep the domestic political situation
stable,'' party General Secretary Jiang Zemin said Friday.
   ``The fight against bourgeois-liberalism is a long-term and
strenuous task,'' he told a party forum in a speech described as
important by the official radio and television, which reported on
it at length. A summary was issued by the Xinhua News Agency.
   It was Jiang's first publicized speech since Romania's hard-line
Communist leadership was ousted last week by a popular uprising.
Chinese college students celebrated by putting up several protest
posters.
   Authorities since have increased surveillance and political
study.
   Jiang said the party showed its strength by crushing
pro-democracy protests in June and ``smashing the efforts by
hostile foreign forces to foist on China a so-called peaceful
evolution'' away from socialism.
   Bourgeois-liberalism is the catch-phrase for Western democratic
ideas. In private, Chinese party officials have denounced Eastern
Europe's turn from communist rule as bourgeois-liberal and
revisionist.
   In his publicized comments Jiang did not mention Romania or the
democratic changes that have swept the rest of Eastern Europe.
However, his remarks appeared to be directed at the challenge
presented by these changes.
   He also said the party needs to perfect its leadership and
strengthen ideological education and discipline.
   ``The rampant corruption which has come to public notice in
recent years has aroused the discontent of the masses,'' Jiang
said, ``and effective measures should be adopted to resume the
close ties the party once maintained with the masses of the
people.''
   Despite repeated campaigns in recent years, however, the party
has shown itself unable to wipe out corruption stemming from party
members' privileged position in society.
   Xinhua said Jiang stressed ``that the party should trust the
masses of the people and depend on them absolutely.'' However,
police have stepped up patrols on Beijing college campuses since
the Romanian uprising.
</TEXT>

</DOC>