<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0189 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0052EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-SEC-International Bjt   12-19 0581</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-SEC-International, Bjt,0601</SECOND>
<HEAD>Breeden Wants To Cut Out Squabbles Over New Products</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN M. DOYLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Securities and Exchange Commission Chairman
Richard C. Breeden says he'd like to see federal futures law
``repealed or modified'' to prevent interagency squabbles over new
financial products.
   Breeden used a news conference Monday on cooperation agreements
with French and Dutch securities regulators to repeat his complaint
about jurisdictional disputes with the rival Commodity Futures
Trading Commission.
   Such disputes were keeping new ``hybrid'' financial products
``in the courthouse instead of in the marketplace'' while foreign
exchanges were trading in similar products, said Breeden.
   He suggested repealing or amending the Commodity Exchange Act,
which governs the futures industry, ``to let the markets decide
where the products will be most actively traded.''
   Breeden also announced he is creating an Office of International
Affairs to coordinate enforcement cooperation with foreign stock
regulators.
   The new international affairs office will be headed by Michael
D. Mann, now an associate director for international affairs in the
SEC's Enforcement Division.
   Breeden said the new office, which will be responsible for
negotiating formal cooperation agreements, known as memoranda of
understanding, ``underlines the very high priority the commission
places on international cooperation.''
   While the SEC is ``concerned a great deal about maintaining
regulatory cooperation,'' said Breeden, ``we at the commission are
also very concerned about competitive issues.''
   Hybrid products are securities with elements of commodity
futures, or futures with elements of a security. Earlier this year,
a federal appeals court in Chicago ruled the SEC overstepped its
authority when it approved trading in a type of hybrid instrument
known as an index participation, or IP.
   IPs, which have been likened to baskets of stocks, may not be
traded in U.S. markets until the dispute, which is still in the
courts, is resolved.
   Breeden first spoke out against the jurisdictional disputes to
securities lawyers last month in Washington.
   Such litigation delays are ``a direct threat to American
competitiveness'' in the financial trading markets, Breeden said
Monday. ``Our foreign competitors have not imposed this type of
restriction on themselves.''
   He cited a recent story in the Financial Times of London that a
consortium of European business people planned to offer a stock
basket product, similar to the one blocked in the United States.
   Breeden said that ``early next year we hope to work together
with the CFTC and discuss with Congress ways of moving this
unneccessary barrier to our competitiveness.''
   David Gary, a CFTC spokesman, said Monday: ``We will be meeting
and have been meeting with fellow regulators, particularly the SEC.
We feel there are a number of questions that relate to the
financial services industry. We are more than willing to sit down
and discuss them, but we want to see them answered with the big
picture in mind. Futures are not isolated by themselves.''
   Last week, Breeden signed cooperation agreements with Dutch and
French securities regulators that will allow the exchange of
information to help stamp out insider trading and other market
abuses.
   Breeden said Monday he would travel to Japan in mid-January as
part of an ongoing series of visits both countries have exchanged
since signing a limited cooperation agreement in 1986.
   Breeden, who was sworn into office in October, said he expected
the talks would cover enforcement topics as well as capital rules,
disclosure and other matters.
   On another matter, Breeden declined to discuss when he would
name a director to head the SEC's Enforcement Division.
</TEXT>

</DOC>