<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0163 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1542EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Panama-Congress 1stLd-Writethru   12-20 0922</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Congress, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0703,780</SECOND>
<HEAD>Most Members of Congress Rally Behind Panama Invasion</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 2nd graf pvs `I support ...' to UPDATE
with criticism. INSERTS 2 grafs after 7th graf pvs `Lugar also ...' to
UPDATE with Hamilton comment. INSERTS 2 grafs after penultimate graf pvs
`Manuel Noreiga ...' to UPDATE with call for U.S. to try to freeze Noreiga
assets</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-US-Panama Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM DRINKARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Members of Congress in both parties rallied
behind the president's decision to invade Panama, with most saying
he had little choice, though there were scattered objections.
   ``I support the president's decision,'' said Senate Majority
Leader George Mitchell, D-Maine, who has been among Bush's harshest
critics on other foreign policy matters. ``It was made necessary by
the reckless actions of General (Manuel Antonio) Noriega.''
   There was a small core of harsh dissent, with one lawmaker
calling Bush's action ``a trigger-happy act of gunboat diplomacy''
and saying the move rested on shaky legal ground. But for the most
part, members of Congress welcomed the restoration of a democratic
government and said all other possibilities had been exhausted.
   ``It's an action the president determined, and I think under the
circumstances Congress will support his position,'' said House
Speaker Thomas S. Foley, D-Wash. ``American troops are in the field
and casualties are being taken. Under these circumstances, it's not
the proper time for a lot of complicated debate.''
   Foley said he expressed ``some concerns'' when Bush called about
10 p.m. Tuesday to inform him of the impending operation. But,
Foley added, the concerns ``don't qualify my support for the
president's action.''
   The White House informed the top four leaders of the House and
Senate of the planned assault just before it was launched late
Tuesday, and contacted other key members of Congress once the
operation was under way.
   Sen. Richard Lugar, R-Ind., a senior Foreign Relations Committee
member, called the action ``an overwhelming success because
democracy has now been inaugurated and installed in Panama.''
   Lugar also called the operation ``a very important moment in the
presidency of George Bush. It is a time when the president asserted
his own leadership and did so effectively.''
   Rep. Lee Hamilton, D-Ind., said the action was justified.
   ``We've had a long period of provocation by Noriega,'' Hamilton
said. ``You can only go so long with this provocation, this
pushing, this harassment. He crossed over the line. It backfired on
him. I think he's a cornered tiger.''
   A rare dissent came from the chairman of the Foreign Relations
Committee, Sen. Claiborne Pell, D-R.I., who said the threat to the
canal was less than clear and Bush did not adequately inform U.S.
allies in Central America.
   ``Personally, unless very clear evidence emerges of a direct
threat against the Panama Canal or against American people or
installations, I would not have engaged in such unilateral or such
go-it-alone action,'' Pell said.
   But, he said he would support the administration until the
operation was completed and hoped for ``as few deaths as possible''
among U.S. forces.
   Rep. Don Edwards, D-Calif., harshly criticized Bush's action,
calling it ``a trigger-happy act of gunboat diplomacy that
continues our mindless 100-year abuse of small Central American
nations.''
   Edwards, chairman of the House Judiciary subcommittee on the
Constitution, said Bush had violated the provision that requires
Congress' consent to go to war.
   ``There was no danger to our national security from this weak,
small country, nor was the Panama Canal in real peril,'' he said.
   However, the consensus on Capitol Hill was that Bush had
exhausted diplomatic efforts and economic pressure, and was left
with little alternative after Noriega's public declaration of war
against the United States last week.
   Sen. Christopher Dodd, D-Conn., chairman of the Foreign
Relations Western Hemisphere subcommittee, said the lack of
immediate criticism from Latin American governments was testimony
to Bush's earlier diplomatic efforts through the Organization of
American States and other groups.
   ``The reaction is one of silence, and that would have to be
interpreted as benign support at this point,'' Dodd said. ``If we
end up having to be the security blanket for the new government and
you have a divided Panamanian public, then I think that support
would turn into criticism.''
   Senate Republican Leader Bob Dole of Kansas said the Panama
operation erases criticism by Democrats that Bush has been ``overly
timid'' in dealing with Panama and other critical foreign policy
issues.
   ``I think what it says politically is that George Bush keeps his
own counsel and makes his own decisions,'' Dole told reporters.
   Sen. Carl Levin, D-Mich., a member of the Senate Armed Services
Committee, endorsed Bush's decision and praised the action as a
``blow against the international drug trade.''
   ``Manuel Noriega had explicitly declared war on us and on his
own people. He killed an unarmed U.S. citizen and had brutalized
others,'' Levin said. ``The president has protected American lives
in Panama and has struck a blow against the international drug
trade.''
   Some lawmakers expressed concern about whether the Panamanian
military could be purged of those who aided Noriega in drug
trafficking and won over to support the new government.
   Rep. David Obey, D-Wis., said the United States should try to
freeze the millions of dollars Noriega has reportedly accumulated
as a result of his drug involvement.
   ``Noriega was like a cancer,'' said Rep. Bill Richardson,
D-N.M., a member of the House Intelligence Committee. ``He was
making us a laughingstock, he was baiting us, he was threatening
American lives. We had no choice.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>