<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0194 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0727EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APonTV-KatieKelly Adv22   12-21 0719</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP on TV-Katie Kelly, Adv 22,0738</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv22</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Friday PMs, Dec. 22, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>TV Critic To Teach English To GI's Kids In Vietnam</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAY SHARBUTT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Television Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At this time last year, Katie Kelly, once an
``Entertainment Tonight'' movie critic, was in Ho Chi Minh City, on
vacation, of all things, spending Christmas in a peaceful Vietnam.
   Now she's spending Christmas preparing to return as an English
teacher for the kids the Vietnam War left in the city then called
Saigon _ the Amerasians, born to Vietnamese mothers and American
servicemen.
   ``The kids obviously have no father and in many cases no mother,
for a number of reasons,'' Kelly says. ``It's a heartbreaker when
you see a whole bunch of them sleeping on the streets of Saigon.
   ``You see these little freckled noses and these little green
eyes, and the curly hair ... my God.''
   Generally shunned by other Vietnamese, they are teen-agers or
young adults now. The youngest would be 14, the war having ended in
April 1975.
   Kelly, who on Dec. 29 will quit her present job as a television
critic here at NBC-owned WNBC-TV, met these children of war
because, as she jokes, ``I take weird vacations. I'm Irish. I don't
go to the beach.''
   She sees the world instead. This took her to Vietnam last year.
Most countries make her think, she says, ``this is nice, I'll visit
again some day. But Vietnam was different. It was, `My God, I've
got to get back here.'
   ``That attitude was prompted by running into these Amerasian
kids. You start finding them in Hue, Da Nang, but they're all over
the streets of Saigon, black and white. I spent a couple of weeks
there, just hanging out with them.
   ``And they are truly remarkable human beings. And they suffer.''
   She learned of an operation set up for the children in Ho Chi
Minh City by a group of Vietnam veterans in the United States.
Based in Wahiawia, Hawaii, and run by a retired Army master
sergeant, John Rogers, it's called Foundation for Amerasian
Children Emergency Support, she says.
   The group's aim is ``to get these kids off the street, get them
food, shelter, some medical treatment,'' she says.
   The Vietnamese government donated a house, she says, ``because
the Vietnamese government is interested in having the people learn
English. I'm a former schoolteacher. So I'll be tutoring these
children in English.''
   The aim is not to ready the young people for when and if they're
allowed to emigrate to this country, although her work would help
that.
   The main goal, she says, is to prepare the Amerasians for when
and if the United States and Vietnam ever resume normal relations.
If that happens, ``there will be Americans over there, and this
would provide future job opportunities for these children.''
   Kelly plans to leave in March. She doesn't know how long she'll
stay. It could be a year or the rest of her life.
   It's a far cry, she says, from growing up in tiny Albion, Neb.,
``out there in corn country,'' and even farther from being a TV or
movie critic at WNBC-TV, then WABC-TV here, then ``Entertainment
Tonight'' and then back at WNBC.
   But the way she sees things, it's payback time.
   ``I'm 53 years old,'' she explains. ``I consider myself the
luckiest human being on the face of the Earth. I've had the best
run of luck the last 10 years, working in television.
   ``I've made a good wage, saved a good deal of money. I'm very
restless, and it's just time to cash in on my restlessness and
maybe do some good. It's time to put a little of it back.''
   While not a victim of the bah-humbug disease that affects some
at yuletide, Kelly feels uncomfortable this Christmas in New York.
The reason: her previous Christmas in Vietnam.
   ``You're surrounded by Christmas here, and it's so commercial,''
she says. ``People are spending all this money, and I keep
thinking, `15 bucks would support one of these kids for a month.'
   ``A woman walked into the makeup room the other night with $100
for gag presents that will be thrown away. That would support a kid
for six months.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Friday PMs, Dec. 22</NOTE>

</DOC>