<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0135 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1509EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-SavannahRiver     12-22 0532</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Savannah River,530</SECOND>
<HEAD>Official Says Westinghouse May Appeal Bonus Payment</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Westinghouse Electric Corp. is considering
appealing for an increase in the $3.9 million bonus it won for
running the Savannah River nuclear weapons plant despite safety
lapses such as workers sleeping on the job, an Energy Department
official said Friday.
   Westinghouse officials at the South Carolina plant, however,
said there were no plans to appeal.
   Stephen A. Wakefield, the department's general counsel, said
Westinghouse President Paul E. Lego told Energy Secretary James D.
Watkins in a meeting earlier this week that the company was
considering contesting the amount of the award.
   ``I know they're considering it,'' Wakefield said in an
interview in his office, adding that Lego gave no indication that a
firm decision had been made.
   At the Savannah River plant, near Aiken, S.C., Westinghouse
spokesman Jack Herman said James Moore, president of the
Westinghouse subsidiary that operates the facility, told him
Friday, ``There's no intention to appeal.''
   ``We view this as a fait accompli,'' Herman said in reference to
the department's decision announced earlier this week to give the
company $3.9 million out of a maximum possible award fee of $7.5
million for its first six months as operator.
   Wakefield said Westinghouse was unhappy that it had been docked
so heavily for not meeting the Energy Department's expectations for
improving the plant's performance.
   Westinghouse, which runs all or parts of five other Energy
Department weapons plants, took over from E.I. du Pont de Nemours &amp;
Co. at Savannah River last April amid rising public criticism of
environmental, health and safety problems in the weapons complex.
   Savannah River's three nuclear reactors, which are the nation's
only source of tritium needed to make nuclear warheads, have been
closed down for more than a year for safety reasons. Westinghouse
has been conducting a massive overhaul of the plant in preparation
for restarting the reactors next year.
   In a letter Dec. 13, P.W. Kaspar, DOE's manager of the Savannah
River operations office, told Moore that although Westinghouse had
made some important improvements, its overall approach to
instilling more discipline in plant operations was too narrow and
not yet effective.
   Kaspar said the company had not adequately reacted to
``anomalies throughout the site.'' Among the anomalies cited were
employees found asleep when they were supposed to have been
monitoring the testing of cooling pipes at one of the reactors.
   Westinghouse said unspecified disciplinary action was taken
against the two workers found asleep. They were not fired.
   Another problem cited by Kaspar was that Westinghouse employees
had intentionally disabled alarms meant to detect excessive
radiation. The company said two employees recently were fired for
tampering with alarms, one in a reactor area.
   Wakefield said Westinghouse's displeasure with the amount of its
bonus payment did not indicate that the contract relationship was
deteriorating. He said Savannah River operations had improved
greatly since Westinghouse took over last April, and that no one
was aware then of how bad the problems there were.
   ``Westinghouse found a much more difficult situation there than
they expected or than we expected,'' said Wakefield. ``Du Pont had
really let the place run down.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>