<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0126 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1718EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Chess     12-18 0431</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chess,0444</SECOND>
<HEAD>Possible U.S. Sponsorship for World Championship Chess</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID GOODMAN</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PALMA DE MAJORCA, Spain (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An American group is trying to
bring the second part of the 1990 World Chess Championship final to
the United States, an official said Monday.
   ``We are very excited to be involved in the world of chess in
the present climate,'' said Robert L. Burkett, president of World
Professional Chess Promotion, Inc., and a senior vice-president for
corporate affairs at the Interscope Group, both owned by Ted Field,
whose family formerly owned the Chicago Sun-Times.
   ``If we are successful in obtaining the rights to conduct the
world championship in the United States, we plan to negotiate with
a number of cities in hopes of finding the ideal venue,'' Burkett
said.
   Earlier, at a general meeting of the Grandmasters Association,
chairman Bessel Kok suggested splitting the world championship
match between Lyon, France, and a U.S. city.
   The governing body of chess, known by its French acronym FIDE,
awarded the match to Lyon in August. But reigning world champion
Gary Kasparov of the Soviet Union and other grandmasters objected
that Lyon was awarded the match without their being consulted.
   Kok told grandmasters he would meet with FIDE officials Dec. 28
to try to work out a solution.
   At Monday's meeting, Kasparov successfully pushed through an
amendment to a peace agreement proposed Nov. 26 in Lucerne,
Switzerland between FIDE and the Grandmasters Association (GMA)
calling for the World Championship match to be organized under the
auspices of the association.
   ``We are looking seriously at the possibility of making a bid,''
Burkett said. ``We are extremely pleased the GMA by popular acclaim
endorsed the concept of splitting the venues and are particularly
looking forward to working with the city of Lyon.''
   Burkett did not discuss possible sites in the United States nor
did he comment on the size of the proposed prize fund.
   Lyon offerred a prize fund of $1.94 million.
   Joel Benjamin, a grandmaster from New York City, said he had
heard rumors New York was the best bet to stage the second half of
the contest.
   The 24-game championship will be spread over 10 weeks, and the
second half is likely to last for five weeks.
   In 1986, the third clash between Kasparov and Anatoly Karpov was
split between London and Leningrad.
   U.S. chess players long have hoped a major corporate sponsor
would get involved in chess and revitalize commercial support for
the game in the United States, which has remained virtually dormant
since Bobby Fischer refused to defend his championship crown in
1975.
</TEXT>

</DOC>