<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0097 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1107EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ShoeThief     12-20 0329</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Shoe Thief,0341</SECOND>
<HEAD>If the Shoe Fits, Thief Wears It</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MADISON, Wis. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A campus detective says he waited five
years for the other shoe to drop _ make that shoes, dozens of shoes.
   That's what happened Tuesday when Herb Hanson of the University
of Wisconsin police questioned a 33-year-old Iowa man who admitted
taking side trips to Wisconsin and Illinois for five years to steal
shoes from students at campus libraries.
   Most of the shoes taken were men's penny loafers and deck shoes
that students had kicked off while working.
   The man, identified as an assistant business professor at a
private college, said he took shoes from libraries at UW-Madison,
Illinois State University-Normal and the University of Illinois at
Champagne-Urbana, Hanson said.
   Hanson would not identify the man but said he had been convicted
of theft in a missing shoe case at Illinois-Normal in July and is
seeing a therapist.
   During six weeks in 1988, 12 pairs of shoes were stolen from the
two UW-Madison libraries. Typically, a student would get up to get
a drink of water and return to find his shoes gone. Police stepped
up patrols in the libraries with no success.
   The break in the case came after shoes was stolen from a student
Dec. 9, Hanson said.
   The victim and a friend saw a man hanging around at the library
with a pair of shoes sticking out of his backpack and questioned
him, Hanson said. The shoes were not the student's, but the man
identified himself with an Iowa driver's license.
   When two more thefts were reported the same day, Hanson tracked
down the man.
   Police found 80 pairs of shoes in his apartment.
   The man claimed he had purchased 60 of them. Hanson said the man
told him if the shoes he took fit, he kept them. Others he donated
to charities.
   No charges were immediately filed. At least 34 unsolved shoe
theft cases are pending in Madison, Hanson said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>