<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0103 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1409EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Drive-InAttack     12-18 0357</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Drive-In Attack,0366</SECOND>
<HEAD>Victim's Father Suffers Heart Attack After Learning of Slaying</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LA2</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CARSON, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Friends have mourned a young immigrant who
was abducted during a drive-in movie date and then raped and slain,
and donors are paying to return her body to her homeland.
   The Rev. Luis Valbuena addressed more than 1,000 parishioners
Sunday at Holy Family parish in Wilmington, where 20-year-old Irene
Franco often prayed.
   ``How can we have tragic incidents like the case of Irene in our
midst? It's not human,'' the Roman Catholic priest said. ``But even
animals kill only in self-defense or because they have to eat. They
don't kill like this.''
   There had been no arrests as of Monday in what authorities said
was an apparently random attack. There was no sign that drugs or
gangs were involved, said Los Angeles County sheriff's Detective
Joe Barnes.
   Valbuena said Ms. Franco's father, Roberto Franco, suffered a
mild heart attack after learning about her death. Franco had
planned to oversee the return of his daughter's body to
Guadalajara, Mexico, Valbuena said.
   The priest said anonymous donors contributed money to pay for
the return of Ms. Franco's body. A funeral home in Guadalajara
planned to pay the cost of burial, Valbuena said.
   Authorities said Ms. Franco, who had been living in nearby
Wilmington for about a year, was watching a drive-in movie with her
boyfriend, Jesus Martinez, when they were kidnapped at gunpoint
Friday.
   Martinez, 26, a Gardena construction worker, told authorities
that three men commandeered their car at gunpoint, tied them up and
drove them to an alley, where they took turns beating Martinez with
a board and beating and raping Ms. Franco.
   Martinez called authorities from a pay telephone after the men
drove off with Ms. Franco.
   Before leaving, they shouted something like, ``Don't worry about
your girlfriend. we'll drop her off in a few minutes,'' sheriff's
Deputy Dean Scoville said.
   A 13-year-old boy found Ms. Franco's body Saturday morning
several miles from the drive-in in Carson, 17 miles south of Los
Angeles. She had been shot in the head. The couple's car was found
burned near Watts.
</TEXT>

</DOC>