<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1234EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mandela     12-18 0297</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mandela,0304</SECOND>
<HEAD>Church Leader, Mandela Discuss Talks With Government</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nelson Mandela's talks with
government officials are not a bid by the jailed black leader to
open power-sharing negotiations singlehandedly, a church leader
said Monday after visiting Mandela.
   The Rev. Frank Chikane, general secretary of the South African
Council of Churches, said he conferred with Mandela for three hours
at the Victor Verster prison farm near Cape Town.
   One of the topics, Chikane said, were the meetings between
Mandela and government leaders, including last week's unprecedented
talks with President F.W. de Klerk.
   There has been press speculation, but no firm corroboration,
that some members and supporters of Mandela's African National
Congress guerrilla movement are worried the 71-year-old prisoner is
opening talks with the government before it meets the ANC's
preconditions. These preconditions include release of all political
prisoners, lifting of the state of emergency and removing a ban on
the ANC.
   Chikane said Mandela ``emphasized that he was not negotiating
with the government, but merely trying to act as a facilitator to
create conditions conducive for meaningful negotiations.''
   Chikane said Mandela ``looked very well. He was vibrant, alert
and applied his mind carefully on every matter we discussed.''
   Mandela, the most popular leader among South Africa's black
majority, has been jailed since 1962 and is serving a life sentence
for plotting an anti-government sabotage campaign. Virtually all
prominent black leaders have said they will not enter negotiations
until he is freed, and there is strong speculation he will be
released next month.
   De Klerk has offered to negotiate a new constitution in five
years that would extend political rights to blacks. He says he
won't accept a one-person, one-vote system and wants whites to
maintain a veto power over major policy decisions.
</TEXT>

</DOC>