<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0118 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1844EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-Peru 1stLd-Writethru a0608 12-27 0349</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Peru, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0608,330</SECOND>
<HEAD>Peru Resumes Joint Drug-Fighting Efforts With United States</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf to FIX name of agency to Drug Enforcement Administration</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Peru has decided to resume joint anti-drug
operations with the United States, a week after the Peruvian leader
halted the activity to protest the invasion of Panama, the Justice
Department said Wednesday.
   David Runkel, a department spokesman, said the ``reconstituted
joint efforts in Peru'' between Drug Enforcement Administration and
Peruvian officials began Tuesday.
   The Peruvian Embassy said joint operations resumed because ``the
fight against drugs is so important.'' '
   The anti-drug operations ceased after the U.S. invasion of
Panama on Dec. 20. Peruvian officials called the invasion an
``outrage against Latin America.''
   At the time, Peruvian President Alan Garcia said he would
boycott the Feb. 15 drug summit that is to be held in Colombia.
President Bush plans to attend.
   An embassy official, speaking on condition he remain anonymous,
said he didn't know whether Garcia had changed his mind and would
attend.
   Bush, talking to reporters as he began a vacation in Texas
Wednesday, said, ``I would hope that Garcia would change his
mind.'' He said that ``inasmuch as Peru is an Andean country and
this is an Andean summit with the United States participating,
trying to help them, I would think it would be lessened _ you know,
less inclusive, obviously _ but I'd think that there are ways to
continue to help Peru in this fight.''
   The Peruvian embassy official said Peruvian officials intend to
send representatives to a meeting in Bolivia on Jan. 10 at which
officials from Bogota, Quito and Lima will coordinate strategy for
the drug summit.
   The United States finances a number of joint operations aimed at
wiping out the drug trade from Peru. They include anti-drug patrols
in the Upper Huallaga Valley where most of the Peruvian coca leaf
is derived. Cocaine is derived from coca.
   DEA agents also work on joint paramilitary operations with the
Peruvians and help them with investigations, including locating
drug traffickers.
</TEXT>

</DOC>