<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1202EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Yugoslavia     12-24 0313</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Yugoslavia,0323</SECOND>
<HEAD>Communists in Slovenia Pledge Support For Democracy</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BELGRADE, Yugoslavia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Communist Party in Yugoslavia's
liberal state of Slovenia on Sunday pledged its full suppport for
the establishment of Western-style democracy in the country.
   ``We shall strive for the creation of a multiparty system,''
Ciril Ribicic, the party's newly elected leader, told delegates at
a regional party congress.
   Slovenia's Communists under Milan Kucan, the regional party's
outgoing leader, have moved quickly over the past three years to
create a pluralistic political system in the republic.
   This has put it at odds with Serbia, the largest of Yugoslavia's
six republics, where Communist leaders are opposed to any form of
pluralism.
   Numerous independent political movements and opposition parties,
including the Social Democratic and Christian Democratic parties,
have been established in Slovenia and are preparing to compete in
the region's first free legislative elections scheduled for March.
   ``The decision to implement ... radical reforms makes it
possible for Slovenes to be proud,'' Ribicic said.
   Croatia, Yugoslavia's second-largest republic, has also
announced that free elections will be held next spring.
   Only the leadership of Serbia has remained consistently opposed
to pluralism. Last month, Serbia's central republic broke off all
business and government ties with Slovenia over their political
differences.
   The Slovene party congress, which opened Friday and adopted as
its slogan ``Europe Now,'' voted to disband all party cells in
state enterprises and government institutions and decided that
Kucan should head its list of parliamentary candidates at the
upcoming elections.
   The policy-setting body also denounced repression in Romania and
said a similar problem exists in Serbia's province of Kosovo.
   Ethnic Albanians make up about 85 percent of the population in
the province, and tensions are high there because Serbian leaders
are trying to curb the province's autonomy.
   At least 28 people have died in ethnic violence in Kosovo this
year.
</TEXT>

</DOC>