<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0194 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2309EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-HaitianChildren 3rdLd-Writethru a0720 12-18 0748</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Haitian Children, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0720,0768</SECOND>
<HEAD>Indiana Couple Plans Adoption of 28 Haitian Children</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 4th graf, `The children ..., to restore dropped word `came;'
SUBS 7th graf, `Lay said ..., to restore 1st reference to the Rev. Bob
Lay.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BETH HARRIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>INDIANAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A missionary couple and 28 Haitian children
they intend to adopt and raise as one family were welcomed home
Monday by applauding friends and relatives.
   Dan and Kathy Blackburn, Christian Evangelical missionaries who
fled Haiti for the Dominican Republic with the children in 1987,
took the children to a church camp in Letts, Ind., where they will
live temporarily in a dormitory.
   ``We're coming home after fifteen years. We'll just take it day
by day,'' Blackburn, 45, said as the greeters gave candy to the
sweater-clad children at Indianapolis International Airport.
   The children, who speak English, range in age from 3 to 14 and
most have lived with the Blackburns since infancy. All but two came
to the couple as babies, including one who was just six hours old.
   ``The baby was found in a hut, and its mother was dead,'' said
Mrs. Blackburn, 42.
   Asked how she and her husband managed to keep track of 28
children, she said: ``Jesus Christ. There is no other secret. Jesus
has always taken care of us.''
   Her husband, asked how the couple planned to feed and cloth the
children, said, ``I think the Lord will provide.''
   The Rev. Bob Lay, pastor of Community Church near the
Blackburns' hometown of Elizabethtown, said the family eventually
will find another place or build a home large enough to accommodate
the whole group.
   ``The churches and organizations that have sponsored them for 14
years will continue,'' he said.
   The U.S. Immigration and Naturalization Service granted the
children special holiday parole status allowing them legal entry
with the couple.
   ``Cases like the Blackburns' show us that the law can be
administered with heart,'' INS commissioner Gene McNary said in
Miami earlier in the day. ``We would have made the same decision at
any time of year but getting the family home before Christmas made
it all the more satisfying.''
   The Blackburns and the children fled from Haiti to the Dominican
Republic in 1987 to escape political turmoil when the Hatian
government collapsed. The two countries split a Caribbean island.
   Mrs. Blackburn said they left Haiti because of threats from
villagers.
   ``We left in the middle of the night with the clothes on our
backs,'' she said. ``We ran for our lives. ... I was trying to save
their lives and ours too.''
   Asked if she had smuggled the children out of Haiti, she said:
``I guess so.... Yeah, I did.''
   INS spokesman Duke Austin said the conditions under which the
Blackburns and the children left Haiti was not an issue.
   Monday the group flew first to Miami International Airport,
where the children, some clutching stuffed animals, played and
watched planes take off while their new parents took care of
last-minute red tape.
   They then boarded a flight to Indianapolis.
   McNary granted the children humanitarian parole because they
were ineligible for entry under any other immigration category.
Under INS law, the commissioner may allow an otherwise inadmissable
alien to enter the country temporarily for humanitarian reasons, or
when such entry is in the national interest.
   The Blackburns, Christian Evangelical missionaries, went to
Haiti in 1976 with their two sons and started a ministry in a small
mountain village, the U.S. Justice Department said. After about 18
months, they began caring for sick or abandoned children taken to
their home.
   The Blackburns and the children were forced to flee into the
Dominican Republic in 1987 after rebels threatened to kill them
during the turmoil when the Duvalier government collapsed, the INS
said.
   In the Dominican Republic, they found a home with the help of
other missionaries while they worked to find a way to adopt the
children and return to Indiana.
   They were unable to complete the adoptions in Haiti or the
Dominican Republic because the children's natural parents are dead,
unknown or untraceable.
   With the help of various church groups, the Blackburns
petitioned the INS to permit the children to come to this country
so they could complete the adoptions in Indiana, said Austin.
   After their petition was approved by McNary in early December,
the INS worked with the State Department to speed up the paperwork
so the family could be home together by Christmas.
</TEXT>

</DOC>