<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0804EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Colombia     12-18 0546</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Colombia,0562</SECOND>
<HEAD>Family Reburies Body Of Medellin Cartel Leader</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STAN YARBRO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of villagers in the hometown
of drug lord Gonzalo Rodriguez Gacha turned out for his reburial,
after security forces killed him in a shootout and interred him in
an unmarked grave.
   Police units in the town of Pacho, 25 miles from Bogota,
remained on alert near the local cemetery during Sunday's funeral
and no incidents were reported.
   Authorities had stalked Rodriguez Gacha for months before
shooting and killing him, his 17-year-old son, Freddy, and five
bodyguards Friday in a gunfight near the Caribbean port of Covenas.
   Authorities used public funds to bury the seven late Saturday in
a common grave in Sincelejo, 320 miles north of Bogota.
   The bodies of father and son were claimed by family members
after being exhumed at their request. They were then flown to
Bogota in a private plane and driven to Pacho.
   They were placed in luxurious, wooden coffins reportedly paid
for by a brother of Rodriguez Gacha.
   Rodriguez Gacha, a 42-year-old billionaire, was the most
celebrated son of Pacho, hated or loved by most of its population
of 20,000. He lavishly provided residents with money, personal
favors and jobs, but demanded unquestioning cooperation in his drug
dealings.
   Sucre state Gov. Arturo Martinez said on Caracol radio network
that Freddy's mother claimed her son's body from the common grave.
He identified her as Luz Dari Celades, reportedly one of Rodriguez
Gacha's mistresses.
   Two of Rodriguez Gacha's brothers claimed the drug trafficker's
body, Martinez said. He did not give their names.
   The judge in charge of the burial, Bienvenido Zuniga, agreed to
open the common grave and give family members a chance to claim the
bodies. He told the El Espectador newspaper that the only request
for the bodies prior to the burial came from a funeral home in the
city of Medellin, the hub of the country's cocaine trade. He denied
that request, El Espectador said.
   Rodriguez Gacha, who had set up private armies to protect both
his cocaine business and his vast stretches of land in the country,
was initially buried in a wooden coffin at a cost of $700 in public
funds.
   With the killing, President Virgilio Barco's government appeared
strengthened in its anti-drug offensive. Critics had said Colombian
cocaine chiefs were impervious to attack.
   The government's success in tracking down Rodriguez Gacha drew
praise from Colombian newspapers, which a week ago suggested Barco
had all but lost his struggle against the traffickers.
   The administration has extradited 10 middle-level traffickers to
the United States as part of its crackdown, but had failed to track
down any of the 12 traffickers most wanted by U.S. authorities.
   Then came the raid on Rodriguez Gacha's hideout. Police said the
operation by more than 1,000 security force members, supported by
seven helicopters, was the result of weeks of intelligence work.
   Enrique Santos Calderon, a columnist for Bogota's leading daily,
El Tiempo, wrote that until Rodriguez Gacha's death ``the war
against the drug traffickers was viewed as going from bad to
worse.''
   ``All of this changed with the death of Rodriguez,'' Santos
wrote. ``The invulnerable image of the cartel chiefs has been
shattered, while that of the public's force has been strengthened.''

</TEXT>

</DOC>