<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1250EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-SovietBloc Bjt 2Takes 12-23 0999</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet Bloc, Bjt, 2 Takes,1024</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fortress Stalin Built Collapses From Its Failures, Mass Discontent</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The ouster of Romania's hard-line Communist
regime caps five months of political upheaval that rocked Eastern
Europe. The events demonstrated the Kremlin's new attitude toward
countries it once treated like virtual fiefdoms. Here is a report.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By JOHN-THOR DAHLBURG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It was the fortress Stalin built, from the Baltic
to the Adriatic. It held some 100 million human souls. Two days ago
its last bastion fell, stormed by hundreds of thousands of
Romanians enraged by Nicolae Ceausescu's tyranny.
   Though the brutal security forces that kept Ceausescu in power
for 24 years fought back across the country, killing hundreds, it
was clearly the culminating act of a revolution that may deprive
the term ``Soviet bloc'' of any meaning.
   A new order in Europe, in the making through 40 years of
repression and economic failure, suddenly is being born with the
blessing and connivance of President Mikhail S. Gorbachev.
   In the 19th century, another European who thought in
continent-wide terms, the French emperor Napoleon, dreamed of a
``continental system'' to integrate the territory he conquered from
Spain to Russia. The philosophical father of communism, Karl Marx,
predicted a proletarian revolution would sweep Europe.
   Now Gorbachev, one of Marx's ideological heirs, preaches the
creation of a ``common European home'' where after years of Kremlin
domination, the nations of Eastern Europe will be virtually free to
pursue policies they set themselves.
   The fundamental changes of 1989 mean that the five East bloc
countries must set up new governments, reorganize economies and
begin to work out what kinds of relations they will have with the
Soviet Union, what ties will be forged with Western countries. The
events in East Germany raise the special issue of a reunified
Germany in the heart of Europe.
   Gorbachev's vision supplants agreements by the World War II
Allies that led to the continent's division into East and West
after the defeat of Nazi Germany.
   For more than four decades, with the Red Army serving as its
gendarme, Soviet-style communism reigned in Eastern Europe from the
Bug River on the Soviet-Polish border to the German city of Weimar,
where Bach wrote his great fugues. Europe seemed immutably divided
into socialist and capitalist camps.
   The West set up a military alliance, NATO, to deal with any
military threat, and the members of the Communist bloc formed the
Warsaw Pact.
   The schism of Europe had its hated symbol, the Berlin Wall. It
made concrete Winston Churchill's alarmed rhetoric in 1946 when he
told students at a small college in Missouri that ``from Stettin in
the Baltic to Trieste in the Adriatic, an iron curtain has
descended across the continent.''
   True, there were rips in that curtain _ when Yugoslavia in the
late 1940s and later Albania successfully rebelled against Moscow's
domination. But the most stunning changes awaited the advent of
Gorbachev and the whirlwind year of 1989.
   Beginning in August, hard-line regimes were ousted in Poland,
Bulgaria, East Germany, Czechoslovakia and finally Romania. Roman
Catholic Tadeusz Mazowiecki became Poland's first non-Communist
premier since World War II.
   Czechoslovakia's new government is no longer
Communist-dominated, and Hungary's Parliament has approved
democratic, multiparty elections next year.
   In Berlin, millions of East Germans have poured through newly
cut breaches in the wall, personifying the growing symbiosis
between East and West. Berliners sang and danced with joy Friday
night when an opening was made in the 28-year-old wall near the
Brandenburg Gate, long a symbol of Germany's division.
   The five months that remade politics in Eastern Europe passed
with breathtaking speed. With Gorbachev in power, leaders like
Czechoslovakia's Milos Jakes and Bulgaria's Todor Zhivkov, who
bankrupted themselves by failing to meet human or economic needs,
could no longer count on Kremlin support.
   Without that backing, unpopular Communists had to compromise
with the people, or give up power.
   In 1942, Josef Stalin raged that the Nazis had ``turned Europe
into a prison of nations.'' But it was the Soviet dictator, his
army and his political disciples who would subjugate Central Europe
and its inhabitants after driving out the German invaders.
   In a sense, revolt began a month after Stalin's death. On an
April morning in 1953, East Berlin construction workers from the
Stalinallee site went on strike over pay cuts. Within 48 hours the
protests spread throughout the city, with demonstrators chanting
``We want to be free and not slaves!'' Mobs tried to take over
government headquarters.
   The Soviet army commandant in Berlin proclaimed a state of siege
and two motorized divisions occupied the city. Protesters who were
caught were executed. Order was restored by 9 p.m., and the Red
Army moved to crush worker revolts in Leipzig, Dresden and
elsewhere.
   The scenario was repeated in Hungary in 1956 and Czechoslovakia
in 1968, when Red Army soldiers were sent in to stop reform efforts.
   But this fall, when East German leader Erich Honecker's rule was
menaced by a popular uprising, Soviet troops remained in their
barracks, and Honecker was deposed Oct. 18.
   It was renewed proof of Gorbachev's professed unwillingness to
meddle in the internal affairs of his allies, as well as a way of
getting rid of an Old Guard Communist who rejected much of his
reform agenda.
   ``The truth, about which we spoke so often in the past few
years, has been reaffirmed once again _ where there is a delay in
dealing with overripe problems, excesses are inevitable,''
Gorbachev told Soviet Communists Dec. 9, warning them their East
European colleagues' fall from power means they must urgently solve
domestic problems.
   The Soviets stress the countries they once treated as virtual
provinces of their own nation must remain in the Warsaw Pact,
meaning Europe's ``Age of the Blocs'' is not yet over, at least
militarily.
   But with non-Communist leaders seeking a mix of capitalism and
socialism to better their citizens' lives, the East-West
ideological schism is dying.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>