<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0115 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2008EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AIDS-BoneMarrow     12-21 0633</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-AIDS-Bone Marrow,0645</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Study Shows Failure of Bone Marrow Transplants in AIDS</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RAEBURN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Editor</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At least 26 American AIDS patients have been
given bone marrow transplants as a possible cure, but at least 10
have died and the rest have shown only temporary improvement,
researchers say.
   Interest in these apparent failures was sparked by a report from
Johns Hopkins University that a bone marrow transplant combined
with the anti-AIDS drug AZT might have eliminated the AIDS virus
from one patient. The patient died before the researchers could be
certain the virus was gone.
   The Hopkins case was widely reported in June when it was
announced at an international AIDS meeting in Montreal. The case
received renewed attention this week when it was described in The
New York Times.
   On Wednesday, Dr. Clifford Lane of the National Institute of
Allergy and Infectious Diseases said his study of 16 patients
produced ``16 failures.'' He found ``only transient improvement in
immunity'' in patients getting AZT and bone marrow transplants.
   Lane's study used identical twins, so that a perfect bone marrow
match could be obtained for each patient from his twin. The Hopkins
study did not use twins, and so it was necessary to destroy, or
``ablate,'' the patient's immune system with chemotherapy and
radiation before the transplant.
   Lane said at least 10 other U.S. AIDS patients had received
transplants after their immune systems were ablated, with
exceedingly poor results.
   ``Every case I know of where the recipient was ablated, the
recipient died,'' Lane said. That includes the Hopkins patient.
   ``There are lots of us who haven't published our results because
they've been so dismal,'' said Dr. Ronald Mitsuyasu of the
University of California, Los Angeles, who has handled four such
cases. ``All we can say is that it's an interesting concept and
that additional patients will need to be studied.''
   Bone marrow transplantation, used most commonly to treat rare
genetic immune disorders and certain forms of cancer, is risky and
expensive. The cost averages about $125,000, and 35 percent to 40
percent of recipients over age 35 die from the procedure, said Dr.
Richard O'Reilly, chief of bone marrow transplantation at Memorial
Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center in New York. The mortality rate drops
below 15 percent in children, he said.
   It is unlikely, therefore, that the technique could be used on a
large scale to treat patients, some researchers said. ``You have to
be young, you have to be rich, and you have to be willing to risk a
one-in-four chance that the cure will kill you,'' said Dr. Mark
Jacobson, an AIDS specialist at the University of California, San
Francisco.
   In Lane's study, done in collaboration with Dr. Anthony Fauci,
director of the allergy institute, AZT did not prevent the virus
from infecting transplanted bone marrow, as the researchers had
hoped it might. Planned studies using different AIDS drugs might be
more successful, Lane said.
   The Hopkins team, led by Dr. Rein Saral, used drugs and
radiation to wipe out the immune system of a 41-year-old AIDS
patient with lymphoma, a form of cancer. They then gave him AZT and
a bone marrow transplant. Thirty-five days later, they used a
sensitive test called polymerase chain reaction, or PCR, to search
for the AIDS virus in his body. They found no evidence of it.
   The patient died of the lymphoma 47 days after the transplant.
Tests again failed to show the virus in his blood or in various
tissue samples, but researchers couldn't be sure the virus was
eliminated.
   ``The virus could be there but in such small numbers that we
couldn't detect it,'' said Dr. H. Kent Holland, a member of the
Hopkins team. ``It's possible there was no virus. ... That's all we
can say.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>