<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0700EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Romania-Americans     12-26 0607</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Americans,0626</SECOND>
<HEAD>No Sorrow for Ceausescu as Romanian Immigrants Pray</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Romanian-Americans prayed for the thousands killed in the
uprising in their homeland, but few had sympathy for executed
President Nicolae Ceausescu, blamed for ``the worst nightmares in
Europe since World War II.''
   ``I didn't want him to die ... it's too easy,'' said Lidia
Oprean of Concord, Calif. ``I wanted him to suffer for a lot of
years and understand the Romanian people suffered.''
   Ms. Oprean was one of about 200 who gathered on the steps of San
Francisco City Hall Monday to call for U.S. aid to Romania.
   That was one of many gatherings around the country in response
to the execution Monday of Ceausescu, 71, and his wife, Elena.
Their executions were ordered after a secret military trial found
them guilty of the deaths of more than 60,000 Romanians and the
theft of more than $1 billion from the country, the new provisional
government announced.
   The Warsaw Pact's last hard-line communist ruler was ousted by a
popular revolt Friday. The uprising was triggered by the massacre
of thousands of people protesting Ceausescu's harsh rule, and at
least several hundred more are believed to have died in fighting
since Friday.
   In a service at St. Thomas the Apostle Romanian Orthodox Church
in St. Louis Hills, Mo., the Rev. Dimitrie Vincent said his
country's glimpse of freedom was won at a high cost in bloodshed.
   ``This is agonizing. This is a terrible tragedy,'' Vincent said.
``In the last 40 years, there hasn't been a peaceful Christmas, a
Christmas where Christians in Romania were free to worship until
this year.''
   About 100 people attended a memorial service outside the United
Nations in New York for those killed in the uprising. Mark Sherman,
who left Romania five years ago to join his mother who defected
earlier, said Ceausescu ``got what he deserved.''
   ``He's one of the worst nightmares in Europe since World War
II,'' Sherman said.
   The group lit 48 candles at the bottom of a wooden cross on
which hung a lantern and a sign saying, ``In memory of the Romanian
heroes who have died for freedom of religion, liberty and justice.''
   Isai Hotaran, 25, who left Romania in 1987, joined about 20
other emigres in Lansing, Mich., to set up a fund-raising network
to channel aid back to their impoverished homeland.
   ``I am not pleased with the death,'' Hotaran said. ``Killing him
is not enough punishment. Letting him and his family live in prison
would have been more just. I don't think that Ceausescu had any
idea what he had done to Romania.''
   In Seattle, Dr. V. Alin Botoman, who fled Romania as a
teen-ager, described the despair he encountered on an August vist
to his hometown of Fagaras in southern Transylvania.
   ``I met childhood friends who looked 10 years older than I do,
just blank faces,'' Botoman said. ``People were desperate. They
were standing in lines for bones they wouldn't feed their dogs
here. They were only giving out meat on holidays.''
   Simona Simut, a Romanian-American activist in Chicago, said a
public trial for Ceausescu wouldn't have worked.
   ``The people of Romania hate him so much that they probably
would have just ran to the courtroom and killed him themselves
before he even got to a trial,'' she said.
   A group of Romanian immigrants in Denver held a tearful memorial
for victims of the revolt at the end of Sunday Mass at the
Transfiguration Orthodox Church. Dumitru Manea mourned the dead,
but celebrated the country's chances for change.
   ``Nothing can happen without sacrifice,'' Manea said. ``This is
the lesson of history.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>