<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 1137EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania-Intellectuals     12-31 0571</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Intellectuals,0589</SECOND>
<HEAD>Writer Recounts Horror of Ceausescu's Rule</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALISON SMALE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Seated among relics of old Romania in
his 19th century villa, writer Marin Sorescu recounted how Nicolae
Ceausescu and Communism ``strangled, almost literally'' the
nation's intellectuals and the traditions they preserved.
   ``We are an intelligentsia of survivors,'' Sorescu said softly.
In the first years of Communism, ``intellectuals were
systematically hunted. Tens of thousands were exterminated in
camps,'' he said.
   That horror of the Stalinist 1950s _ when teachers, priests,
anybody with a brain or mastery of a foreign language was a
suspected spy or enemy of the people _ gave way in 1965 to
President Ceausescu.
   At first, Ceausescu appeared to many Romanians to be a liberal
Communist leader. He permitted more nationalist culture, defied the
Kremlin and refused to take part in the invasion of Czechoslovakia
in 1968.
   ``1968 was a big trap,'' Sorescu recalled, sitting in the
favorite room of his Bucharest home, lined with books, paintings
and other examples of traditional Romanian culture. After that, he
said, ``evil became a way of life.''
   ``The terror was horrible, and sacrifice was continuous, every
year,'' said the slim, moustachioed writer. ``Imagine if the
Jacobin terror had lasted 40 years.''
   According to Sorescu, the terror peaked for intellectuals in the
early 1980s, when Ceausescu decided to impose his order on the
Writers' Union, one of the last bastions of potential resistance to
his increasingly paranoic rule.
   Sorescu was one leading intellectual who, while avoiding open
dissidence, refused to go along with the constant pressure to sign
his name to prepared poems eulogizing Ceausescu, to inform on his
friends, or to live and write as Ceausescu thought fit.
   As a result, he received death threats on the phone and in his
mail. Neighbors and other informants would keep careful watch on
his house.
   In 1982, he spent three months under house arrest after he was
linked to a ``conspiracy'' against Ceausescu for dedicating a book
to a member of a group of arrested transcendentalists.
   The constant surveillance and awareness that all conversations
in his house were bugged meant that Sorescu never uttered
Ceausescu's name and never discussed with friends where his
manuscripts were hidden.
   Despite the repression, he managed to publish some 30 volumes of
poetry, essays and plays in Romania. But, he said, all were missing
banned passages or verses that he could only publish abroad or keep
in his drawer.
   ``The leading couple couldn't bear any popularity beyond their
own,'' he said of Nicolae and Elena Ceausescu. ``They were jealous,
jealous of the living and of the dead.''
   For this reason, Sorescu said, Ceausescu forbade any celebration
this year of the centenary of the 19th century writer Mihai Manescu.
   Sorescu cautioned that the revolution that toppled Ceausescu
Dec. 22 is not over yet. ``The social mechanism of Communism has to
be destroyed,'' he stressed.
   ``When we see the underground tunnels, the double walls in every
building, the fact that people could simply disappear,'' he said,
``we will realize what torture our lives were until now and wonder
if we escaped psychologically sane.''
   For Sorescu, the network of terror inspired him to write and to
reject several offers to live abroad, knowing he should stay and
preserve the Romania he said Ceausescu was destroying.
   Repression ``created the contrary'' for Sorescu. ``It gave me
extraordinary energy to write,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>