<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0601EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Romania-Airwaves 1stLd-Writethru   12-23 0471</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Airwaves, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0448,0483</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fighting Around TV Station Underlines TV's Role In Uprising</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 6 grafs to UPDATE with bloody faces in TV studio,
grenades hitting TV building. Pickup 7th graf, `As today's...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>With PM-Romania, Bjt ^By MORT ROSENBLUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Romania's uprising turned into a
battle for the airwaves today, as members of ousted dictator
Nicolae Ceausescu's despised security forces tried to retake
national television and radio stations.
   National television showed the bloody faces of some people
crowding one of its studios after apparently fleeing the fighting
outside.
   The provisional government formed after army units joined the
masses in toppling Ceausescu on Friday, appealed for help.
   ``Army units and citizens we need you,'' a Bucharest radio
announcer implored. ``Block off the radio-television area.''
   Machine-gun fire and the sound of light tank shells filled the
air and tracers crossed the smoky skyline outside the government TV
building at dawn in a firefight between army units and Ceausescu
loyalists.
   The attackers appeared mostly to be in surrounding apartment
buildings. Bullets and rocket-propelled grenades hit the TV
building, and a TV announcer reported without elaborating that
injuries resulted.
   As today's firefight started, Marin Constantin, normally editor
of youth programs, took charge of herding staff and visitors into
hallways, away from windows.
   ``Safe here, halfway,'' he said, noting the eighth floor was a
safe compromise between first and 13th. He seized a wooden chair
and smashed a ceiling light to darken the corridor.
   Gratiela Ripeanu, who normally handles visitors and external
relations for the TV station, chuckled as the noise grew deafening.
   ``Are you a war correspondent?'' she chided a colleague far more
used to reporting on rallies and government communiques.
   A MiG fighter jet flew low overhead, and TV reporters said it
was in a dogfight with diehard units. But that could not be
independently confirmed.
   The new army-backed leadership on Friday used the newly captured
TV to broadcast demonstrations nationwide and propose new elections
next year. Ceausescu's son, Nicu, was shown with a bloody face
after he was arrested.
   About 2:30 a.m. today, Ceausescu loyalists in the security
forces tried to seize radio and TV headquarters _ about two miles
apart _ and were beaten back. Then they counterattacked.
   The TV station stayed on the air during the first attack, with
reporter Victor Ionesco exhorting residents of Bucharest to come to
scene of the shooting. ``Come help us,'' he implored. ``We're
helping you.''
   People who had been chanting outside the TV building only
minutes before the shooting scattered briefly during the attack,
but they came back and cheered when tanks on side of the uprising
took up new positions around the building.
   A crowd of about 3,000 people then took up a vigil through the
night outside the building, continuing their chants for liberty.
</TEXT>

</DOC>