<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0159 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1356EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a AM-ReligionToday Adv29   12-27 0697</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Religion Today, Adv 29,0716</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv29</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Friday AMs, Dec. 29, or Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Gorbachev Picked Top `Religion Newsmaker' Of 1989</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE W. CORNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Religion Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Although he ostensibly is not a religious man,
Soviet President Mikhail Gorbachev is the top ``religion
newsmaker'' of 1989, according to specialists in reporting that
field.
   A poll of members of the Religion Newswriters Association made
that choice, and also picked the extraordinary meeting of Gorbachev
and Pope John Paul II as the No. 1 religion news story of the year.
   It was the first meeting ever between a pope and leader of a
government that for decades has upheld atheism and spurned
religion, shackling it. But Gorbachev, baptized as an infant but a
committed Communist, broke the pattern.
   ``We need spiritual values,'' he told the pope.
   The meeting presaged diplomatic relations between the two, long
antagonistic leaderships, cleared the way for a possible papal
visit to the USSR and brought assurances from Gorbachev of
broadened religious freedoms.
   Those expanding religious freedoms already were proliferating in
the Soviet orbit _ in the swift shift toward democracy in East
Germany, Poland, Hungary and Czechoslovakia _ in what some hailed
as a triumph of faith over Marxism.
   That tide, and the fading of restrictions on religion in that
area, even ahead of revised statutes, was picked by religion news
specialists as 1989's third ranked religion story.
   ``A lot of that reform movement was fueled by the churches,''
said religion reporter Bill Thorkelson of Minneapolis who compiled
the survey results. ``By and large, that aspect hasn't been told.''
   The second-ranked religion story was the trial, conviction and
sentencing of television evangelist Jim Bakker to 45 years in
prison and $500,000 in fines for defrauding contributors. He had
quit his network in 1987 in a sex scandal.
   Other religion events ranked in this order:
   Fourth _ The murder of six Roman Catholic priests and jailing
and torture of other church workers in El Salvador, sparking new
demands by religious groups for an end to U.S. military aid to that
nation.
   Fifth _ Worldwide controvery over publication of Salman
Rushdie's ``The Satanic Verses,'' which Islamic zealots called
blasphemous and degrading to the prophet Mohammed. Iranian death
threats sent Rushdie into hiding.
   Sixth _ Election by the Massachusetts diocese of the Episcopal
Church of Barbara Clementine Harris, 55, as suffragan bishop, the
first woman to become a bishop in the worldwide Anglican communion.
   Seventh _ A warning by U.S. Catholic bishops to politicians
against taking pro-choice stands on abortion. Lucy Killea, running
for the California state Senate, did so and was barred from Holy
Communion by San Diego's Bishop Leo Maher. She won.
   Eighth _ The Rev. George Augustus Stallings Jr., a Washington
D.C., Catholic priest, was suspended after he formed his own
African-American congregation in Washington, D.C., calling
Catholicism racist.
   Ninth _ The Vatican backed relocation of a Carmelite convent
from the Auschwitz death camp after Polish Cardinal Jozef Glemp
outraged Jews and some Catholic prelates with his comments about
Jews in the controversy.
   Tenth _ Religious leaders condemned suppression of a student
democracy movement in China, and the Dalia Lama, exiled Tibetan
Buddhist leader, receives the Nobel Peace Prize in a move to point
up the brutal crackdown.
   Besides picking the top-rated religion stories, religion
reporters singled out incidents that tended to cover up religious
affairs and stifle the public's right to know.
   Cited for first place in this ``Into the Darkness Award'' was
the National Conference of Catholic Bishops, who went into closed
session for an entire afternoon at their Novermber meeting and
refused to disclose even their topic.
   Second place went to the Southern Baptist Convention at which
newly predominant fundamentalist trustees of denominational
agencies summoned executives behind closed doors to lay down
tightened rules.
   Other ``darkness'' citations went to Episcopal bishops, who
barred reporters from small-group discussions about women bishops,
and the United Church of Christ, which refused to divulge vote
totals in election of the denomination's new president in which a
white won over a black. Church officials said people simply should
take their word on the outcome.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Fri AMs, Dec. 29.</NOTE>

</DOC>