<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0288 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2341EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-BoeingUnion     12-18 0346</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Boeing Union,0360</SECOND>
<HEAD>Boeing Engineers Reject Contract, Technicians Approve Theirs</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TIM KLASS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Boeing Co. engineers and scientists rejected a
three-year contract with the world's largest commercial jet builder
but technicians and support workers ratified a separate pact, union
leaders said Monday night.
   Charles Bofferding, president of the Seattle Professional
Engineering Employees Association, said members of the professional
unit voted by 69 percent to reject their contract offer but also
voted 52 percent against authorizing negotiators to call a strike.
   It was the first time in the unaffiliated union's history that
engineers and scientists rejected a contract offer, he said. The
union consists of nearly 9,300 of 15,200 affected Boeing scientists
and engineers.
   About 8,300 of Boeing's nearly 12,800 technical and support
workers belong to the technical workers unit. Almost all of those
covered by both contracts are in the Puget Sound area.
   Leaders of the engineers union will contact Boeing officials
immediately about returning to the table, Bofferding said.
   ``We are critical parts of the Boeing team, and we affect them
in all areas,'' he said.
   Bofferding said the voting rate for both units exceeded 80
percent, a record. The unions vote by mail.
   The offers included general pay hikes totaling 3 percent for
engineers and 7 percent for the lower-paid technicians.
   Bofferding said he believed the main factor in the engineers'
rejection was the belief that the money package was too small
compared with that won by Boeing production workers in a 48-day
strike that ended last month.
   The Machinists' three-year pact includes pay increases of 4
percent the first year, 3 percent the next two years; productivity
bonuses of 10 percent, 5 percent and 4 percent of annual gross pay;
and a boost in the cost-of-living formula from 86 percent of
inflation to nearly 100 percent.
   The offer to engineers, who now make an average of nearly
$40,000 a year, called for a 3 percent wage increase and a
productivity bonus of 10 percent of gross pay in the first year and
no further general increases.
</TEXT>

</DOC>