<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0230EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Panama-Quotes     12-21 0305</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Quotes,290</SECOND>
<HEAD>With PM-US-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a roundup of quotes on the U.S.
invasion of Panama:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``Yesterday a dictator ruled Panama and today, constitutionally
elected leaders govern.'' _ President Bush.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``I'm not going to tell you that the crisis in Panama has been
totally resolved. ... But Manuel Noriega, who was yesterday's
`maximum leader,' is today's hunted fugitive.'' Secretary of State
James A. Baker III.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``We had him spotted several times during the day; we thought we
had a pretty good idea where he was at night; we went there and he
wasn't there.'' _ Lt. Gen. Tom Kelly, Army deputy chief of staff,
on efforts to apprehend Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``I think we can safely conclude that this ends his career as a
drug trafficker. He's not running drugs. He's not running Panama.
He's just running. And that's good.'' _ National drug control
director William. J. Bennett.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``As a practical matter, we have decapitated him from the
dictatorship of this country and he is now a fugitive and will be
treated as such. ... We will chase him and we will find him.'' _
Gen. Colin Powell, chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``It's an action the president determined, and I think under the
circumstances Congress will support his position. American troops
are in the field and casualties are being taken. Under these
circumstances, it's not the proper time for a lot of complicated
debate.'' _ House Speaker Thomas S. Foley, D-Wash.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Bush's action was ``a trigger-happy act of gunboat diplomacy
that continues our mindless 100-year abuse of small Central
American nations.'' _ Rep. Don Edwards, D-Calif., chairman of the
House Judiciary subcommittee on the Constitution, who said Bush
violated the provision that requires Congress' consent to go to war.
</TEXT>

</DOC>