<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0086 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1006EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Panama-WorldReax 1stLd-Writethru   12-20 0774</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-World Reax, 1st Ld - Writethru,a0558,0791</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Condemns U.S., Britain Hails U.S. `Courage'</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 10 grafs to UPDATE with Latin American nations to
meet, Canada reaction. Pickup 6th pvs, ``Foreign Minister Francisco...''</HEAD>
<BYLINE>With PM-Panama, Bjt ^By MAUREEN JOHNSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Soviet Union today swiftly condemned the U.S.
military assault to seize Panamanian leader Manuel Antonio Noriega,
while British Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher praised it as a
``courageous decision.''
   ``Someone has to uphold democracy,'' Mrs. Thatcher said.
   Reactions contrasted sharply as news flashed around the world
that President Bush had ordered troops to capture Gen. Noriega, who
was indicted on cocaine trafficking charges in the United States in
1988.
   Among other Western allies, Dutch Foreign Minister Han van den
Broek said in a radio interview that he sympathized partly because
U.S. troops had been endangered recently in the Panama Canal zone.
   Tensions had been rising in Panama between U.S. and Panamanian
forces after Panamanians killed a U.S. Marine lieutenant on
Saturday in what American officials called an unprovoked attack.
   Foreign ministers of Argentina, Brazil, Mexico, Uruguay, Peru,
Venezuela and Colombia conferred by telephone on the situation,
then agreed to meet in Bogota tonight to discuss the developments
in Panama and issue a declaration, the Colombian Foreign Ministry
announced.
   Panama was part of the so called Latin American Group of Eight
but was excluded after Noriega ousted Panamanian President Eric
Delvalle in 1988.
   The group has condemned Noriega's regime, but it has also
advanced a consistent rejection of any direct intervention of the
U.S. in Panama.
   Canada expressed regret today about the use of force by the
United States in Panama but was sympathetic to the American action
under the circumstances.
   A statement from External Affairs Minister Joe Clark also said
that ``intervention by force is a dangerous precedent,'' adding
that Canada notes that the United States relied on force as a last
resort after failing to resolve the situation in Panama peacefully.
   Foreign Minister Francisco Fernandez Ordonez of Spain said he
``deeply lamented'' the U.S. action. He said the Spanish
government, ``which always has been opposed to foreign military
intervention, expresses its hope that the Panamanian people can
decide their future in freedom.''
   Foreign Minister Taro Nakayama of Japan said he hoped the
confrontation would end soon.
   ``Japan has long been expressing its hope to see a democratic
government established in Panama that reflects the will of the
Panamanian people,'' the Kyodo news service quoted Nakayama as
telling Japanese reporters. ``We hope this takes place as soon as
possible.''
   In Moscow, Foreign Ministry spokesman Vadim P. Perfiliev said,
``These actions, a violation of the U.N. Charter and generally
recognized rules of state relations, should be condemned by the
international community. The United States must immediately stop
its armed intervention in Panama.''
   Perfiliev, quoted by the official Tass news agency, said the
U.S. action, ``whatever its motivation, has provoked a feeling of
serious concern in the Soviet Union.''
   State-run Radio Moscow accused the United States of invading
Panama in what in called ``an act of aggression.''
   Yugoslavia also said the U.S. action was unacceptable.
   ``Yugoslavia has always considered as unacceptable any foreign _
and especially a military _ intervention under any excuse, as it
represents a crude violation of sovereignty,'' a Yugoslav Foreign
Ministry statement said.
   Mrs. Thatcher spoke to reporters on the steps of her 10 Downing
Street office after Bush telephoned at 7 a.m. (2 a.m. EST) to tell
her the military assault was under way. They spoke for 10 minutes.
   ``I said we would fully support him in the action he was taking
to bring an end to this rule of terror,'' Mrs. Thatcher said. ``I
believe he was right to do so. I believe this is what friends are
for, to give support at this time. It was a courageous decision.''
   Mrs. Thatcher called on other world leaders to declare support
for Bush, saying, ``Every action has a risk and it is important
that it be successful.''
   ``Gen. Noriega is wanted on drugs allegations in the United
States. We are fighting terror and the battle against drugs as
well. The rule of democracy should be upheld,'' she added.
   Mrs. Thatcher's warm response contrasted with her sharp
criticism of the U.S.-led invasion of Grenada in 1983 to topple a
leftist administration in the Caribbean island. Grenada is a former
British colony that regards Britain's Queen Elizabeth II as its
titular head of state.
   Britain's opposition Labor Party criticized the U.S. action,
saying it had ``nothing to do with democracy in Panama and
everything to do with protecting the American interests in the
canal zone.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>