<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0112 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1600EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Panama-Soldiers'Families 4thLd-Writethruege</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Soldiers' Families, 4th Ld - Writethru, a0596,0868</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soldiers' Families Await Word on Loved Ones; Some Notified of Fatalities</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with six grafs to UPDATE with arrival of soldiers' remains
at Dover Air Force Base. Picks up 6th graf, `I would...'.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto JO1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DOUGLAS J. ROWE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Soldiers' families across the United States hoped for the best,
but some got the unwanted word: Their loved ones were among the
first fatalities from what the White House called Operation Just
Cause.
   The Pentagon today reported 19 U.S. servicemen killed, 117
wounded and one missing in the attack on Panama.
   In all, President Bush ordered 9,500 soldiers and Marines into
Panama to bolster the 13,000 normally based there.
   The remains of four soliders arrived this afternoon at Dover Air
Force Base, Del., from Kelly Air Force Base in San Antonio, where
the wounded from the invasion were taken en route to military
hospitals.
   The bodies in flag-draped caskets were taken off a C-141
Starlifter which landed shortly after 3 p.m. EST. The Delaware base
is the site of the Department of Defense's East Coast Port Mortuary.
   The body of Lt. j.g. John Patrick Connors, 25, of Arlington,
Mass., was among the four flown to Dover. Connors, a member of the
Navy's special operations unit known as the SEALS, was described as
``fearless,'' by his resident adviser at Worcester Polytechnic
Institute, where Connors received a bachelor's in chemical
engineering.
   ``I would come back in the middle of the night from studying and
he'd be hanging from the sprinkler pipes going hand over hand,''
said Walter Towner Jr.
   Also among those killed was 22-year-old Cpl. Ivan D. Perez, who
according to his sister, always wanted to be a soldier and passed
up a chance to get out of the service last year.
   ``He wanted to keep going,'' said his 24-year-old sister,
Andriana. ``We told him to get out. ... He just really enjoyed
being there. Ever since he was a little kid, he wanted to be a
soldier.''
   The Pawtucket, R.I., family sent him several Christmas cards,
including one the day before the invasion.
   Ten-year-old Miguel, who idolized his big brother, contributed
to the last card. ``He drew little soldiers and tanks on the
Christmas card,'' his sister said.
   A soldier from Cincinnati _ James Markwell, a 21-year-old medic
_ also was identified by his family as being among those killed.
   ``This was his first mission,'' said his stepfather, Bill Rouse.
``And I'll bet you he was patching somebody up when he got hit.''
   In Leesville, La., residents kept an eye on the television,
watching for word on their family members and friends from nearby
Fort Polk who were participating in the action against Panamanian
Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   Mary Oliver, the 14-year-old daughter of an Army sergeant in
Panama, spent the day relaying news reports to her mother at work.
   Mary, who tried to explain the situation to her 10-year-old
brother about their father, Sgt. Frank Oliver, said: ``My brother,
I don't think he understands. I just keep telling him it must be
good, because we haven't heard anything bad.''
   Teresa O'Dell, the instructor at a beauty school where several
Army wives are in training, said there were a lot of tears when two
of her students received calls Wednesday that their husbands were
being shipped out to Panama.
   ``Several of them left here to tell their husbands goodbye,''
O'Dell said.
   Such rushed, tearful departures also played out in the Spring
Lake, N.C., area, a cluster of strip shopping centers, fast-food
outlets and trailer parks adjacent to Fort Bragg, home of the
Army's 82nd Airborne Division.
   Sgt. Timothy W. Bolton rushed into his North Carolina home,
tossed a few things into a gripsack and turned to his wife, Treva.
   ``I've got to go,'' he told her. ``I love you. 'Bye.''
   A kiss, an embrace, then he was gone, headed back to Fort Bragg,
where he boarded a military plane headed to Panama.
   ``It was quick, but I was one of the lucky ones,'' said Mrs.
Bolton, 22. ``I was fortunate he didn't have his bags (on base). If
he'd had them with him, I wouldn't have gotten a chance to say
goodbye.''
   Since her husband's departure, anchormen have become her
companions.
   While she worked at a laundry in a shopping center, she
frequently turned to the television to see what new developments
were being reported.
   At Fort Polk, sentries stood guard outside the La Louisiane
Recreation Center, where family members received word of the
operation.
   Inside, Army spokesmen said, the mood calmed after the initial
announcement Wednesday morning of the move against Noriega.
   Several women left the center in the afternoon smiling, their
children in tow with coloring books in their hands. Army officials
didn't allow interviews on the base.
   ``It's just really high tension now, especially at Christmas
time,'' said the Rev. Dennis Hackler, pastor of Cooper Baptist
Church. ``They're worried; if things do escalate down there,
there'll probably be a lot of people shipped out. It's just kind of
a waiting game.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>