<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0160 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1407EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a AM-ReligionRoundup Adv29   12-27 0617</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Religion Roundup, Adv 29,0643</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv29</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Friday AMs, Dec. 29, or Thereafter</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GENEVA, Switzerland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The World Council of Churches has
made new grants totalling $635,000 to organizations fighting
racism, one of them a South Africa-banned group which dominated
recent elections in adjoining Namibia.
   The largest grant from the council's fund to combat racism,
$165,000, went to the South West African People's Organization,
SWAPO, which garnered 57 percent of votes to elect 41 of 72 members
of Namibia's assembly which is to produce a constitution for the
newly forming state.
   SWAPO's chairman, Sam Nujoma, who presided at the assembly,
``expressed gratitude for the role churches have played in the
struggle'' for Namibia's independence from South Africa, reports a
U.S. observer, Diane Porter, the Episcopal Church's deputy for
public policy.
   Three other groups fighting white-minority rule in South Africa
and previously in Namibia also received major grants, including the
African National Congress.
   The fund, supported by designated contributions, mainly from
European churches and governments, makes grants only for
humanitarian, non-military purposes. Since 1970, the fund has made
grants totalling $8,716,000.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BALTIMORE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Retired Roman Catholic Bishop William E.
McManus of South Bend, Ind., asked how he dared speak out on such a
taboo topic as women's ordination and optional celibacy for
priests, said:
   ``I'm a retired bishop. I have nowhere to go but heaven or
hell.''
   He had told last month's meeting of bishops here it was time
they quit avoiding women's ordination and optional celibacy as
``some kind of ecclesial obscenity.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A leader of the Synagogue Council of America
has urged its 4 million synagogue members to join with blacks,
Hispanics and others to eliminate racial and religious prejudice.
   ``Jews and blacks have a long history of working together,''
Rabbi Richard Yellin of Boston told a service on the steps of the
nation's capitol, launching a broad effort by churches and
synagogues for intergroup harmony.
   ``This partnership must be renewed and expanded to include
Hispanics, Asians and other minority groups,'' said Yellin,
chairman of the council's domestic affairs committee.
   The council embraces all three major branches of Judaism,
Reform, Orthodox and Conservative.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A survey to which 2,055 United Methodist leaders
responded shows they're deadlocked on whether the church's Board of
Global Ministries shoud stay in New York or move elsewhere. Each
option drew 40 percent support, with the other 20 percent undecided.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>ST. PAUL, Minn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A report of six years of dialogue between
Eastern Orthodox and Lutheran churches says several differences
remain but participants found themsleves ``drawn together in Christ
on the very topics on which we had anticipated greater
disagreement.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>DUNEDIN, New Zealand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Anglican Church in New Zealand
has elected the first woman diocesan bishop in the worldwide
Anglican communion. The Rev. Penelope Ann Bansall Jamieson is to
head the diocese of Dunedin.
   Her election came about a year after the election of the Rev.
Barbara C. Harris as suffragan, or assistant, to the Episcopal
bishop of Massachusetts. The Episcopal Church is among 28 national
provinces of world Anglicanism.
   In distinction from the American case, Bishop-Elect Jamieson,
47, will head a diocese with jurisdiction over its priests and
parishes. The New Zealand church has been ordaining women as
priests since 1977, and lists 94 women among its 800 clergy.
   Suffragan Bishop Harris, the first woman elevated to the U.S.
church's episcopacy, said of New Zealand's new bishop that ``being
a first is both a joy and a challenge. I wish for her the same joy,
support, and fulfillment that I have experienced here from the
people of Massachusetts.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Fri AMs, Dec. 29.</NOTE>

</DOC>