<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1512EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-UnfinishedMural     12-25 0691</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Unfinished Mural,0714</SECOND>
<HEAD>At 81, Artist Finally Gets Funds to Complete 1934 Mural</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto GS1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LISA PERLMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MUSKEGON, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In a musty basement storage room of the
Muskegon County Museum, surrounded by mannequin parts and antique
canoes in disrepair, Wilfrid Berg is picking up where he left off
55 years ago.
   The 81-year-old artist is finally getting the chance to paint
the second of two murals commissioned from him in 1934 by the Works
Progress Administration for the children's reading room at the city
library.
   ``I had the sketches done. I was all ready to do it back then,
and then the money ran out,'' said Berg, a slight man with white
hair and sparkling blue eyes.
   The WPA, a New Deal program of President Franklin D. Roosevelt
to help economic recovery from the Depression, notified the Lake
Michigan city it was eligible for mural funds. At the time, artists
were being put to work on murals in public buildings nationwide.
   Berg, then 26, was contacted, and ``the next morning I was
looking for a spot,'' he recalled.
   The children's reading room of the Hackley Public Library was
chosen.
   The WPA commissioned two murals for opposite walls of the room
above oak bookcases. Berg finished one, now mounted on the west
wall. Called ``The World at Your Door,'' it features people of
different nations in native dress.
   He recalls being paid either $100 or $200 for that project
before funds ran out. He worked five more weeks on his own time to
complete it.
   The second mural _ featuring characters from classic children's
literature _ was canceled.
   ``I put the sketches away and forgot about it. But really, it's
something I always wanted to do,'' Berg says as he glances at his
sketches of intermingling characters such as Pinocchio, Robinson
Crusoe, Peter Rabbit, Cinderella and Huck Finn.
   Library officials had been trying to find the sketches for the
29-foot mural for two or three years before they surfaced at the
adjacent Muskegon Museum of Art a couple of years ago, said Dale
Pretzer, the library's director.
   ``It was like looking for a lost manuscript that's a sequel to a
great book,'' Pretzer said.
   Once the sketches were found, there still was the challenge of
finding funds for Berg to take up his task again.
   Along came Muskegon residents Shirley and Daniel Rapoport,
long-time supporters of the library, which is celebrating its
centennial in 1990.
   ``My children loved that library so much as they were growing
up,'' said Mrs. Rapoport, a retired schoolteacher. ``When we found
out about the other mural and that the artist was still alive, I
thought it would be such a lovely gift for the centennial
celebration.''
   She won't say how much she is contributing for the work, calling
it a modest amount.
   Meanwhile, Berg, dressed in blue jeans and a denim shirt, is
working in his makeshift studio seven hours a day, and is expecting
to finish the project in about four months.
   ``I don't move quite as fast as I used to,'' he said with a
smile.
   He is keeping the mural's original design and theme, ``Idle
Hours with Good Books is Time Well Spent.'' The dedication of the
mural is scheduled for July.
   The project has not overwhelmed Berg; he's never retired. The
never-married Muskegon native (``I could never afford a wife,'' he
says) recently completed a mural for the county museum chronicling
the history of the city, and paints Lake Michigan landscapes.
   He recalls taking odd jobs _ truck driving, house painting,
framing _ to support his love of creating art. Although he's been
painting most of his life, recognition has come only in the last
few years.
   In 1988, the art museum featured his varied work _ including
watercolors, oils, lithographs _ even cartoons _ in a one-man show,
``Wilfrid Berg: A Muskegon Treasure.''
   ``Muskegon's not exactly a hotbed of art ... so we're very lucky
to have him,'' said volunteer curator Robert Youngman, who found
the sketches. ``I have a great respect for his talent and I'm
thrilled he's finally getting the recognition he deserves.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>