<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0342EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Romania-Chronology     12-26 0381</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Chronology,0401</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romania's 11-Day Revolution</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Key events in the Romania's popular
uprising:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Dec. 15 _ Demonstrators ring a chuch in Timisoara, in western
Romania, to prevent security forces from arresting a dissident
clergyman who was active in promoting the rights of ethnic
Hungarians.

</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Dec. 16-17 _ Security forces open fire on thousands of
demonstators in Timisoara, who have expanded their protest to
demand freedom and a better life. Hundreds are buried in mass
graves.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Dec. 18 _ The United States issues a formal protest over the use
of force in Timisoara.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Dec. 19 _ More shooting is reported in Timisoara. Britain,
Poland's parliament and Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard Shevardnadze
condemn the violence.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Wednesday _ President Nicolae Ceausescu, returning from a state
visit to Iran, declares a state of emergency in western Romania and
blames the unrest on ``facist, reactionary groups.'' Protests
spread to at least eight other cities and in Timisoara tens of
thousands of people take to the streets, chanting ``Give us our
dead!''
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Thursday _ The revolution spreads to the capital, and security
forces open fire on protesters. Ceausescu is shouted down while
addressing what he had planned as an orchestrated rally. State
television shows his shocked face.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Friday _ Army units join the rebellion, and a group known as the
National Salvation Committee announces it has overthown Ceausescu
and will form a provincial government. It says it will try leaders
of his 24-year-old regime and restore democracy. Ceausescu and his
wife, Elena, flee the presidential palace by helicopter. The United
States and European nations applaud his ouster.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Saturday _ The provisional government says the Ceausescus are
captured in a town north of Bucharest. Savage street fighting takes
place between the army, which backs to the new government, and
elements of the hated secret police, loyal to Ceausescu.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Sunday _ Fierce street fighting continues in the capital and
other cities.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Monday _ State radio announces the execution of Ceausescu and
his wife after a secret trial that found them guilty of genocide
and plundering more than $1 billion. The United States, the Soviet
Union and other major powers recognize the provisional government.
Romanians openly celebrate their first Christmas in four decades.
</TEXT>

</DOC>