<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1438EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-US-Panama 7thLd-Writethru 2Takes 12-26 0935</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-Panama, 7th Ld-Writethru, 2 Takes, a0576-579,900-1,400</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. to Seize Noriega Assets, Push Vatican To Turn Him Over</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Combines pvs; INSERTS 5 grafs after 13th graf, The spokesman,
to include Pentagon briefing, pick up pvs 14th graf, Earlier, an.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bush administration announced its
intention today to seize millions of dollars in assets that deposed
dictator Manuel Antonio Noriega allegedly shipped out of Panama,
while it continued diplomatic efforts to bring him to trial in the
United States on drug charges.
   Justice Department spokesman David Runkel said the assets are
all liquid and are primarily in bank accounts in half a dozen
countries, many of them in Europe. They amount to ``in excess of
$10 million,'' he said.
   He refused to name the countries where Noriega placed his money,
which the spokesman referred to as ``illegal drug money.''
   Noriega touched off a behind-the-scenes diplomatic struggle on
Sunday when he presented himself at the Vatican Embassy in Panama
City and asked for asylum. U.S. troops have surrounded the facility.
   President Bush remained at his Camp David retreat, while an aide
said he was monitoring the situation closely. Bush sent roughly
14,000 troops to Panama a week ago in an effort to restore
democracy there and apprehend Noriega.
   White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater told reporters today the
administration has told the Vatican ``very directly'' of its desire
to Noriega returned to the United States to stand trial.
   At the same time, Fitzwater declined to rule out the possibility
that some other option might be under consideration in the
international negotiations that began over the weekend when Noriega
turned up at the Vatican Embassy in Panana City requesting asylum.
Sources have said the discussions have included sending Noriega to
a third country.
   Runkel told reporters that Noriega has ``10 associate thugs'' in
the Papal Nunciature with him. Runkel said he did not know their
names.
   ``Our position is we mean to bring him back to the United
States,'' Fitzwater said.
   He said this was the primary goal, although he would not rule
out the possiblity that some other option might be under
consideration. The Vatican has ruled out simply turning Noriega
over to the United States, according to a spokesman who noted that
the Holy See does not have an extradition treaty with the United
States.
   Fitzwater said U.S.troops would continue to ring the Vatican
Embassy ``as long as he's there.''
   Although Bush has not directly communicated with Pope John Paul
II on the subject, or with other Vatican officials, ``we told them
very directly what our feelings were,'' Fitzwater said.
   The spokesman said that the United States had offered Noriega,
wanted in Florida on drug trafficking charges, a deal as recently
as October in exchange for his stepping down from power
voluntarily. But he did not accept it and now such deals are off,
Fitzwater said.
   Pentagon spokesman Pete Williams said today that when Noriega
turned himself in at the Vatican Embassy he was ``said to be so
exhausted from the chase that he could barely speak.'' He said
Noriega had been on the run since the U.S. operations began on
Tuesday and that he was never in command of the Panamanian Defense
Forces resisting U.S. soldiers.
   Williams also said the Panama Canal was now open 24 hours and
Panama City's two major airports, Torrijos and Tocumen, are open
during limited hours.
   ``It's much quieter in Panama City than it has been since the
operation began,'' Williams said.
   He said some U. S. troops remained in city streets and others
were moving west ``to check the countryside.'' He said they were
meeting very little resistance, with citizens turning in their
weapons to U.S. soldiers.
   The spokesman said about 33,000 weapons have been captured,
discovered or turned in, including 6,000 under a program which
offers rewards to former PDF members who give up their arms.
   Earlier, an administration source said that the United States
was talking in ``extraordinarily tough terms'' in its bid to
convince the Vatican to turn over Noriega.
   Defense Secretary Dick Cheney, just back from a Christmas Day
visit with the 26,000 troops in Panama, said today he hoped a
quieting situation will allow the United States to speed up the
withdrawal of some American forces. But in an interview with ABC
News he did not provide a timetable for troop movements.
   Papal representatives have contacted several Latin American and
European countries in hopes one will agree to accept Noriega, said
the U.S. official. He described the situation as ``a Mexican
standoff.''
   ``He has no place to go yet,'' the official said. ``Nobody wants
him.''
   The White House disputed an account in today's editions of the
Washington Post that Bush had talked by telephone Monday with the
papal nuncio in Panama, Monsignor Sebastian Laboa. Popadiuk said
Bush engaged in no such conversation.
   The Post also said Cuba indicated it would be willing to give
political asylum to Noriega.
   Spain, Cuba and the Dominican Republic were mentioned in the
past as possible exile sites when Noriega's representatives were
negotiating with the United States in 1988 and again this year
about the possibility of Noriega stepping down.
   But Spain might not be acceptable to Noriega because it has an
extradition treaty with the United States. And Cuba might not be
palatable to the United States because that country would reject
any U.S. request for Noriega to be turned over to U.S. custody.
   The State Department official said most of the discussions have
been carried out between the State Department and church officials
at the Vatican.
   MORE
</TEXT>

</DOC>