<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0257EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-People-Buchwald     12-21 0424</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-People-Buchwald,0436</SECOND>
<HEAD>Executive Says Murphy Unmoved by Buchwald Movie Script</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LINDA DEUTSCH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A former Paramount Pictures executive said
Eddie Murphy was told in 1983 about an Art Buchwald script idea for
Murphy to play an African king visiting America.
   ``We had just made a new deal with Eddie to make four or five
more movies,'' David Kirkpatrick recalled Wednesday at the trial of
Buchwald's $5 million lawsuit against Paramount. ``The purpose of
the meeting was to tell him what was ahead for him.''
   He said Murphy listened politely to several script ideas
including the one by Buchwald, then titled ``King for a Day.'' ``He
didn't react negatively to `King for a Day,' but he didn't jump up
and down about any of the projects,'' said Kirkpatrick.
   Later, he said, Murphy's manager, Bob Wachs, read five or 10
pages of a script written from Buchwald's treatment, and did not
like the script.
   Buchwald, the Pulitzer Prize-winning columnist, claims Paramount
stole his idea for Murphy's hit movie, ``Coming to America.''
   On cross-examination by Paramount lawyer Robert Draper,
Kirkpatrick sought to explain why he and other executives generated
a blizzard of memos in 1983 and 1984 about the anticipated
production of ``King for a Day.''
   He said a new studio chief, Ned Tanen, had arrived recently and
the memos were intended to show Tanen that projects were in the
works for Murphy.
   He said the proposals included plans for Murphy to play a
priest, a prisoner, a detective, a witch doctor and a schizophrenic
with 10 personalities.
   Kirkpatrick, chief of production at Walt Disney Studios,
identified dozens of memos written in 1983 and 1984 that included
the story idea entitled, ``King For A Day,'' among the top projects
in the works for Murphy and director John Landis.
   In one 1984 memo, Kirkpatrick said another executive had circled
the ``King for a Day'' entry and scribbled the word: ``Great.''
   But later that year, Paramount dropped the idea, which involved
an African prince coming to America in search of a bride. Three
years later, Paramount produced ``Coming to America'' starring
Murphy and directed by Landis. The story involved an African prince
who comes to America in search of a bride.
   The film, one of Murphy's biggest hits, grossed more than $300
million.
   Studio officials say there are no similarities between
Buchwald's script idea and ``Coming to America.'' They contend that
Murphy and his co-star, Arsenio Hall, conceived the idea and
created a series of humorous incidents never mentioned by Buchwald.
</TEXT>

</DOC>