<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0189 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1809EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Poland     12-20 0485</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland,0497</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Wins First Bill in Economic Package</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DANISZEWSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Parliament approved a farm bill with only
one dissenting vote Wednesday, indicating it will accept the entire
government plan to transform Poland's centralized economy into a
market-oriented system.
   The vote of 284-1 followed more than two days of sharp debate,
much of it critical of the government's agricultural policies, and
represented overall support for reform beyond party lines.
   Industry Minister Tadeusz Syryjczyk and the head of the Central
Planning Office, Jerzy Osiatynski, said they felt the entire
package would be approved. A finance official said a letter of
intent on an International Monetary Fund agreement would be signed
with the IMF soon.
   The Soviet bloc's first non-Communist government, led by
Solidarity, is pushing economic reform in an effort to conquer
annual inflation of 900 percent a burdensome $39 billion foreign
debt and qualify for desperately needed Western economic aid.
   Officials acknowledge the program, which takes controls off
prices, ends most subsidies and limits wage increases and will be
painful in the beginning. It is expected to cause a 20 percent drop
in real incomes and put 400,000 people out of work in a nation
unaccustomed to unemployment.
   Before Wednesday's vote, Bronislaw Geremek, the Solidarity
leader in Parliament, said in urging support for the farm
resolution: ``We are convinced that Polish farmers ... will be able
to understand the interests of the state.''
   Prime Minister Tadeusz Mazowiecki and the architect of economic
reform, Deputy Premier Leszek Balcerowicz, sat side by side in the
chamber as the vote was taken.
   By Wednesday, three days after Balcerowicz presented the
economic plan to Parliament, the government appeared increasingly
confident of passage.
   Osiatynski, head the planning office, said: ``I think it will be
voted in before the first of January. The difficulties will start
only once it is voted in and once we start carrying it out.''
   Janusz Sawicki, deputy finance minister, said Poland would sign
a letter of intent with the IMF ``within the upcoming few days.''
   After the letter is signed, Sawicki said, he expects the IMF to
announce preliminary acceptance of Poland's economic reform program.
   He said that would allow Poland to get a $215 million bridge
loan from the Bank of International Settlements in Switzerland and
release a $1 billion loan pledged by a group of Western countries,
led by the United States and West Germany, to support turning the
zloty into a convertible currency.
   The IMF is expected to ratify the agreement at the end of
January or early February, Sawicki said. In it, Poland agrees to
continue a strict regimen of reform in exchange for a $700 million
line of credit from the IMF.
   Certification by the IMF would open the way to money from other
Western lenders, including a World Bank loan of $300 million, and
rescheduling of Poland's $40 billion hard-currency debt.
</TEXT>

</DOC>