<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0106 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1612EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Bush 1stLd-Writethru   12-28 0836</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0580,820</SECOND>
<HEAD>White House Says Next Move Is Up To Vatican</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: CORRECTS ``results'' to ``routes'' in quote in 4th graf: ``On
another,''</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama Bjt, AM-US-Panama Aid Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER CONNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CORPUS CHRISTI, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The White House said Thursday that
Manuel Noriega's fate rests ``in the hands of the Vatican,'' and it
ruled out the possibility of a third-country refuge for the
ex-dictator of Panama.
   Press secretary Marlin Fitzwater said the United States has
agreed to come to the papal nuncio's rescue should Noriega and his
cronies take hostages inside Panama City embassy where Noriega has
been holed up since Christmas Eve.
   But Fitzwater, briefing reporters here while Bush was off
hunting quail at a remote ranch 60 miles away, said, ``We don't see
a hostage situation or any danger at the moment. But we're willing
to offer assistance should that be necessary.''
   On another issue, Fitzwater confirmed that Bush is readying
plans to use the U.S. military to disrupt drug supply routes in
South and Central America. Asked about a report that the Pentagon
was planning a virtual blockade of Colombia, Fitzwater said, ``We
have decided to take certain actions to help the countries of Latin
America interdict those supply routes.''
   Whatever is done will be in close concert with Colombian
authorities, he said.
   Papal officials reportedly sent U.S. authorities a letter
Tuesday authorizing a rescue effort should a hostage situation
develop. ``I assume that when you have people of the ilk of Mr.
Noriega and his cronies in the embassy, there certainly is reason
to be concerned,'' said Fitzwater.
   A Vatican spokesman said Wednesday in Italy that the papal
nuncio could not legally turn Noriega over to U.S. authorities, who
want to try him on drug trafficking charges. The papal embassy in
Panama City is empowered only to deal with the government of
Panama, and no other foreign governments, the spokesman said.
   ``Our position remains the same, that we want Noriega returned
to the United States for prosecution, but this matter is now in the
hands of the Vatican and we will work with them and with the Endara
government to calmly consider the issue,'' said Fitzwater.
   Asked why the United States opposes letting Noriega seek refuge
in a third country _ as both the Reagan and Bush administrations
had suggested over the past two years as part of deals to restore
democracy in Panama _ the presidential spokesman said those offers
were contingent on Noriega giving up power peacefully.
   ``We had to go in militarily. We have paid a price for this,''
said Fitzwater, referring to the 23 American servicemen killed and
322 wounded in the Dec. 20 invasion that toppled Noriega's regime.
   Fitzwater said U.S. authorities have detained and interviewed
some Noriega associates who have left the Vatican Embassy. ``Most
of his cronies ... are still in the embassy with him,'' said
Fitzwater, who would not disclose how many there were.
   U.S. authorities blared loud rock music _ including such tunes
as ``Nowhere to Run'' and ``I Fought the Law and the Law Won'' _
outside the Vatican Embassy Wednesday.
   Fitzwater said it was not a pressure tactic on the Vatican, but
simply ``fairly standard practice'' to disrupt any attempt to
eavesdrop on U.S. officials' conversations. The same thing was done
during the 1988 Moscow summit, he said.
   Of the choice of records, he added, ``I'm certainly glad to see
the American sense of whimsy comes forward in this situation.''
   Bush was off hunting quail with Secretary of State James A.
Baker III at their friend Will Farish's 10,000-acre Lazy F Ranch
outside Beeville, Texas, on a vacation that began Wednesday and
continues through New Year's Day.
   Fitzwater said he had no response to protests by animal rights
activists against the hunt, an annual Christmastime ritual for
Bush, an avid outdoorsman.
   The quail that Bush bags are ``always dressed for consumption,''
said Fitzwater, who added that in his own youth on a Kansas farm he
hunted and ate quail ``all the time. It's a great dish.'
   Bush departs the Lazy F Ranch late Friday afternoon to join his
wife Barbara for the weekend in Houston, still their legal
residence, although their ``home'' consists only of a hotel suite
they use when there.
   They will visit servicemen wounded in Panama at two military
hospitals on Sunday and Bush will stop in Montgomery, Ala., to go
bass fishing before returning to the White House Monday night.
   Bush was accompanied by an ever-present military aide and
personal assistant Tim McBride on the ranch, as well as Baker and a
Secret Service contingent. But neither national security adviser
Brent Scowcroft nor deputy Robert Gates accompanied him to Texas,
and Bush relied on written reports for his daily morning
intelligence briefing, Fitzwater said.
   Bush got up at 6 a.m., read the intelligence report and morning
newspapers, ate breakfast and was out hunting by 8:45 a.m.,
Fitzwater said. It was a foggy, chilly morning in much of south
Texas.
</TEXT>

</DOC>