<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0637EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather 1stLd-Writethru a0461 12-27 0637</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0461,0649</SECOND>
<HEAD>South Warms a Bit; Cold Front Moves East from Plains</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 7th graf pvs, `Fog was ... valleys' with 4 grafs to ADD
that fog delayed airline flights in Seattle, Salt Lake City. Pick up 8th
graf pvs, `Temperatures were...</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Warmer weather was making a welcome return to the South today,
and a cold front was moving east from the Plains, bringing more
cold, dry weather.
   Mild, dry weather was expected across the West, and a cold front
with a little rain or snow was forecast for the Pacific Northwest,
where snow fell in Pendleton, Ore., this morning.
   In much of the South, where a Christmas weekend freeze burst
water pipes in thousands of homes and businesses, overnight
temperatures were at or near freezing. Temperatures today were
forecast to rise to the 60s from Texas across Louisiana through
Florida, and the 40s and 50s in the rest of the South.
   Miami's highs could reach 80 by the weekend, according to the
National Weather Service.
   A cold high-pressure system moved east from Iowa today, followed
by slightly warmer air. The front was expected to scatter freezing
rain and light snow as it moved across the Ohio Valley and Great
Lakes into New England.
   The front was expected to bring dry, sunny and cold weather to
the Northeast today, with tempratures from near zero in far
northern New England, rising to the 20s in New York City, New
Jersey and Pennsylvania, and to the 30s in Maryland and Virginia.
   Fog returned this morning to Seattle and Salt Lake City, where
heavy fog disrupted airline travel Tuesday.
   At Seattle-Tacoma International Airport, flights were diverted
or delayed for nine hours Tuesday, causing a traffic snarl on
nearby roads because stranded passengers' cars jammed all the
garages.
   At Salt Lake City International Airport, some flights were
diverted and others delayed up to an hour Tuesday, despite efforts
at fog-dispersal _ a technique much like cloud-seeding that
involves sprinkling dry ice, or carbon dioxide, from planes.
   Fog also was expected this morning in parts of Montana, Idaho
and Utah, as well as in California's Sacramento and San Joaquin
valleys.
   Temperatures were expected to rise to the 70s along the southern
fringe of the desert Southwest, and the 50s in northern New Mexico,
Arizona and California.
   Other reports at 3 a.m. EDT:
   _East: Albany, N.Y. 02 fair; Atlanta 30 fair; Boston 11 windy;
Buffalo 02; Charleston, S.C. 30 fair; Chattanooga 24 partly cloudy;
Cincinnati 17 cloudy; Cleveland 11 partly cloudy; Detroit 09;
Jacksonville 35 foggy; Key West 51 fair; Knoxville 20 partly
cloudy; Macon 25 fair; Miami 44 fair; New York 12 windy;
Philadelphia 12 fair; Pittsburgh 04 snow; Portland, Maine, 08 fair;
Richmond 22 fair; Tampa 46 fair; Washington, D.C., 14 fair.
   _Central: Birmingham 28 fair; Bismarck 37; Denver 32 fair; Des
Moines 34 cloudy; Fort Worth 50; Indianapolis 16 cloudy; Kansas
City 31 fair; Little Rock 34 fair; Louisville 23 cloudy; Memphis 38
cloudy; Nashville 27 cloudy; New Orleans 41 fair; North Platte 35
fair; Oklahoma City 40 fair; Omaha 40 cloudy; Rapid City 36 fair;
St. Louis 25 snow; Minneapolis-St. Paul 14 cloudy; Sault Ste. Marie
-6 cloudy; San Antonio 50 partly cloudy.
   _West: Albuquerque 33 fair; Anchorage 18 snow; Boise 22 foggy;
Casper 34 fair; Fairbanks -13 fair; Great Falls 42 partly cloudy;
Honolulu 71 fair; Las Vegas 45 cloudy; Los Angeles 60 foggy;
Medford 25 foggy; Pendleton 27 snow; Phoenix 55 partly cloudy;
Portland, Ore., 35 fair; Reno 30 cloudy; Salt Lake City 22 foggy;
San Diego 61 cloudy; San Francisco 46 fair; Seattle 34 foggy;
Spokane 30 foggy.
   _International: Calgary 50 partly cloudy; Montreal -8 fair;
Ottawa -14 fair; Regina 32 fair; Toronto -1 partly cloudy; Winnipeg
16; Nassau 63 fair; San Juan 72.
</TEXT>

</DOC>