<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0039EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-RobinsonProfile     12-20 0558</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Robinson Profile,0576</SECOND>
<HEAD>Savannah Leaders Praise Slain Alderman</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Wednesday AMs report.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Mail Bombs</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURAN NEERGAARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAVANNAH, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Robert Robinson, the alderman and lawyer
assassinated by a mail bomb, is being remembered as an easygoing,
generous man whose community affairs work made people ``believe
they can make a difference.''
   Robinson, whom even new acquaintances called ``Robbie,'' died
Monday when a package containing an explosive and nails blew up at
his law office.
   Robinson and Mayor John Rousakis had planned to attend a meeting
that evening at the lawyer's church to discuss how blacks could
fight drugs in their neighborhoods. Robinson was black.
   The 42-year-old attorney was the second victim in a rash of mail
bombs in the South. A package bomb killed 11th U.S. Circuit Court
of Appeals Judge Robert S. Vance on Saturday. A mail bomb found at
the federal courthouse in Atlanta was disarmed Monday. A parcel
bomb mailed to the NAACP's Jacksonville, Fla., office was disarmed
Tuesday.
   On Tuesday, Savannah's legislative offices were closed in
mourning.
   Rousakis said Robinson ``was a warm, kind person, always with a
smile on his face and a hand out to help.''
   ``He meant the future to Savannah, he gave to the community in
such a selfless way that he made people just believe they can make
a difference,'' said Alderman Willie Brown.
   At a news conference, city leaders said they believed Robinson's
involvement with the National Association for the Advancement of
Colored People, which he represented in a school desegregation
case, was related to his death.
   Rousakis said Robinson was an active member of his church and
was worked to help the homeless.
   Friends said Robinson's political activity was not the kind that
would be expected to generate murderous enemies.
   ``I've known him a very long time, and he is not the kind of guy
I would think would be a target of such an action,'' said Superior
Court Judge Eugene Gadsden. ``He was easygoing and went about his
business.''
   Longtime friend Al Rivers said Robinson took part in civil
rights protests until he went off to college. ``Then he came back,
got into politics and his time began to get tight.''
   Rousakis said Robinson had been a city councilman for eight
years, but had served on other government and community boards his
entire adult life.
   As city transit authority chairman 10 years ago, Robinson led a
move to provide transportation for the poor and the elderly.
   Robinson, one of the first black students to attend Savannah
High School in the 1960s, represented the NAACP in the long-running
Savannah schools desegregation case.
   The 11th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals ruled in October that the
city's magnet-school plan was appropriate for desegregation.
   Neither city nor school officials knew whether the NAACP was
planning to appeal, and NACCP head Curtis Cooper could not be
reached for comment.
   Robinson is survived by his wife, Ann, and three daughters.
Alderman Floyd Adams Jr. said city officials would start a fund for
Robinson's family.
   Rousakis said a local business, All-American Builders, had
already donated a $1,000 reward for information in the case.
   ``We are sure the Savannah Police Department will not quit until
they come to some conclusion,'' Alderman Brown said. ``Meanwhile,
the fund gives people a way to prove their love for Robbie.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>