<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2357EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-MysteryWoman     12-18 0411</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mystery Woman,0426</SECOND>
<HEAD>Amnesia Victim Says She'll Stay in Nashville</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A woman who turned up here with amnesia
says she'll spend the holidays in Nashville because she ``felt like
a duck out of water'' during a recent trip to her Ohio hometown.
   Ruth Ellish will send presents to her family in Akron but stay
in Nashville, where she's spent the past year in the care of a
shelter for homeless women.
   ``I feel comfortable here,'' she said. ``I feel like this is
where I belong. It's my home now; it's the only place I really
know.''
   The 50-year-old woman prefers to be called Kitty Jordan, a name
she adopted during her mysterious memory loss. She said she's
grateful her perplexing past was cleared up after 10 months.
   ``A lot of my prayers have been answered,'' Jordan said.
   She woke up in a Nashville motel Dec. 10, 1988, bruised and
unable to remember her name or where she lived.
   After national publicity, she was reunited Oct. 4 with her
mother, Irene Christ, and sister, Elise White, both of Ohio.
   White said the family believes her sister fled under stress when
she was threatened by a boyfriend of her 18-year-old daughter.
   Since the reunion, Jordan has visited her former home, but said
she still doesn't remember her earlier life.
   ``It was strange,'' she said of a November trip to Akron. ``I
felt like a duck out of water. ...
   ``They know me, and the warmth they show me, well, I feel like
they are family. But I don't really know them,'' she said. ``The
best part about all of it was seeing the Nashville skyline when I
was flying back.''
   Jordan also has two sons, ages 20 and 29. Relatives said she was
a computer analyst at the Alltel-Western Reserve Telephone Co. in
Hudson, north of Akron.
   She works as a junior staff cook for room and board and $50 a
week at a shelter for homeless women and children operated by the
Nashville Union Rescue Mission.
   ``I am happy here,'' she said. ``I'm just hoping that in 1990 I
will be able to get a full-time job with the mission, because I
love my work here.
   ``Otherwise, if I have to, I'll try and get another job, perhaps
as an administrative assistant or an executive secretary. I need to
be making more money to start my own life.
   ``But I've got a lot to be thankful for.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>