<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0148 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0645EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DigestBriefs     12-28 0553</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Digest Briefs,0570</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government will stop reimbursing operators
of nuclear weapons plants for their own criminal fines,
environmental penalties, fraudulent losses and other questionable
costs, officials say.
   The decision, spurred by growing congressional criticism of the
weapons program, marks the most fundamental change in the Energy
Department's weapons contracting system since companies were
recruited to build the first atomic bombs in the 1940s.
   The companies traditionally have been allowed to recover
virtually all their costs, even those resulting from their own
negligence. The logic was that weapons production was so
specialized and vital to national security that the government
could not afford to risk losing a plant operator over money matters.
   The new thinking, under Energy Secretary James D. Watkins, is
that the weapons contractors will perform better if they are held
accountable for their mistakes.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Angry homeowners, besieged oil delivery
companies and governors across the Northeast are calling on federal
officials to find out why home heating oil prices skyrocketed this
month to their highest levels ever.
   The price jump from about 85 cents a gallon two weeks ago to as
high as $1.62 per gallon now has led officials from Gov. Mario
Cuomo of New York to Gov. Judd Gregg in New Hampshire to call for
federal investigations of possible gouging and price-fixing.
   Whether oil companies are in collusion or not, public officials
and industry experts agree that an unusual confluence of events has
led to the highest prices ever for home heating oil.
   Events ranging from low water levels on the Rhine River in
Germany to a refinery explosion in Louisiana have contributed to
the upsurge, officials say. Above all, though, is the record cold
spell that has gripped much of the nation this month. For the
Northeast, forecasters are calling for more chill temperatures this
weekend after a brief respite.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush is mulling a Pentagon plan to
draw a ``much, much tighter noose'' around Colombia with a virtual
air and sea blockade designed to halt illicit drug exports, a
senior administration official says.
   The plan is part of a comprehensive set of proposals from the
nation's regional and specialized military commanders that Defense
Secretary Dick Cheney directed to the White House, said the
Pentagon official, who spoke on condition of anonymity.
   Bush is slated to attend an anti-drug summit in Colombia in
February.
   Although the operation could be launched before the summit, the
official refused to offer a start-up date for the maneuver.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Murder rates soared to new highs in some of the nation's largest
cities in 1989, but at least eight cities saw a surprising drop in
homicides.
   Police were quick to blame crack for homicide records that were
set in at least seven cities, but they were less certain about why
there was less killing elsewhere.
   One official suggested that violence may have ebbed in cities
where drug dealers have already won their turf wars by killing off
rivals and dividing up territory.
   Final 1989 statistics in most cities won't be prepared for at
least several weeks, but a preliminary survey by The Associated
Press of police departments in more than 30 cities shows that the
number of homicides rose in most of them.
</TEXT>

</DOC>