<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0124 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1808EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania 2ndLd-Writethru a0592 12-19 1192</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0592,1226</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Violence Reported Continuing in Romania; Hundreds Feared Dead</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS 15 grafs with unconfirmed account from Tanjug of up to
2,000 dead, details. Picks up 12th, `Tass said ...''</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BEL3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALISON SMALE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Shooting and fires were reported Tuesday
in western Romania, where witnesses say security forces may have
killed hundreds of people who protested the harsh Communist regime
of President Nicolae Ceausescu.
   Greek students who crossed into Yugoslavia from the Romanian
city of Timisoara, site of the greatest unrest over the weekend,
said shots were fired indiscriminately, ``killing dozens.''
   They said many children were killed or wounded ``because people
used them as shields,'' assuming security forces would hold their
fire.
   A Romanian doctor who arrived in Austria spoke of protesters
stoning armored vehicles. He said one vehicle drove into the crowd,
crushing a woman, and rows of people were mowed down by gunfire.
   Ceausescu was on the second day of a three-day official visit to
Iran. He has run Romania for 24 years, and the tide of reform
sweeping out the old guard elsewhere has made him the
longest-serving Communist ruler.
   Late Tuesday, the Yugoslav state news agency Tanjug in what it
called an eyewitness account said there were unconfirmed reports of
up to 2,000 dead. Most previous accounts from a variety of sources
leaving Romania estimated 300 to 400 dead.
   ``Some travelers say that in Timisoara, police are brutally
fighting demonstrators, mostly young people. Unconfirmed reports
speak of large numbers of victims, as many as 2,000 people _ men,
women and children,'' Tanjug said without identifying its sources.
   It added, ``Witnesses claim that police are taking the arrested
demonstrators to the central Timisoara Square, where they beat them
and stab them with bayonets, before shoving them into lorries
(trucks) and driving them away no one knows where.''
   The news agency said the clashes in Timisoara, a Translyvanian
city, were continuing and that late Tuesday the government in
Belgrade called on Romania ``to immediately put an end to violence
and prevent further bloodshed.''
   The Roman Catholic news agency Kathpress in Vienna said a doctor
told them by telephone from Timisoara, 30 miles from the Yugoslav
and Hungarian borders, that hundreds were wounded and deaths could
surpass 400.
   None of the accounts could be confirmed because journalists and
nearly all other foreigners were barred in an effort to stop word
of the unrest from spreading. Repeated attempts to telephone
Bucharest from Vienna and Budapest on Tuesday were unsuccessful.
   Tanjug reported from Bucharest, capital of Romania, that
students there had declared solidarity with the protesters in
Timisoara and, in response, police guards were posted in
dormitories.
   The Soviet news agency Tass said ``an unusual tension is
noticeable'' in Bucharest. ``The guarding of government agencies,
plants and factories has been strengthened. ... On the streets,
soldiers armed with automatic weapons and members of the Patriotic
People's Front (militia) are patrolling. ... Buses are parked with
soliders and policemen.''
   In Washington, the Bush administration condemned the ``brutal
use of police force'' and said the United States was consulting
with allies about the possibility of sending independent observers
to Romania.
   Accounts trickling out suggested Ceausescu, the last Stalinist
ruler in the Soviet bloc, sanctioned unprecedented force to crush
the protest.
   Tass said Soviet authorities had been told no Soviet tourists
could be accepted ``due to adverse weather conditions, the absence
of snow needed for winter tourism and a great demand'' for hotel
space from students on holidays.
   Romanians have been comparatively quiet for years, largely out
of fear, but have been made restive by austerity policies that
subjected the nation of 23 million to widespread rationing and
other hardships.
   Timisoara, a city of 350,000 people, is a major point of contact
with other countries. Foreign traders travel there regularly to
sell goods that are scarce in Romania.
   Official Romanian media made no mention of disturbances, but the
Communist Party daily Scinteia said in a commentary the ``spirit as
well as the letter of the law must be applied in every field and
every circumstance.''
   A Western resident of Timisoara traveled to Yugoslavia on
Tuesday and said the violence was ``horrifying.''
   He reported seeing several corpses in the streets and said parts
of the downtown area, including local Communist Party headquarters,
were badly damaged.
   Hungarian radio quoted a Hungarian who said several of his
relatives were physicians working in Timisoara hospitals. He said
he estimated from their telephone reports that 300 to 400 people
were killed in the city, and 250 bodies were taken to one hospital
alone.
   About 20 percent of the dead and wounded were ethnic Hungarians,
he said.
   That would substantiate other accounts that the protest began
with a few hundred ethnic Hungarians defending a local pastor
Friday and grew into a demonstration against Ceausescu on Sunday.
It was the largest anti-government protest since a march by 10,000
workers in Brasov in November 1987.
   A Romanian doctor arrived at Graz from Timisoara on Monday
evening told the Austria Press Agency thousands of people chanting
``Down with Ceausescu!'' ``We are hungry!'' and ``We want
freedom!'' movedtoward the center of the city at about 2 p.m.
Sunday, stoning armored vehicles.
   He said one armored vehicle ``drove into the crowd like crazy. .
.. I saw a woman of about 40 driven over and crushed,'' but the
protesters did not disperse.
   Security forces opened fire without warning about 7 p.m., and
``the first three rows just collapsed, dead or wounded,'' he was
quoted as saying.
   ``There was panic, some people wanted to go back. The crowd was
pushing forward. People were stopping private cars and loading dead
or wounded into the trunks.''
   Magyar Hirlap, a Hungarian daily, said violence had spread to
Arad and Brasov, two other cities in Transylvania, but gave no
specifics.
   It quoted Col. Janos Pal of the Hungarian border police as
saying crowds in Curtici, between Arad and Timisoara, broke into
the local Communist Party headquarters Sunday and burned documents.
   Romania and Hungary have a long-standing dispute about alleged
harassment of the 1.7 million ethnic Hungarians in Romania, most of
whom live in Transylvania. That region, along with Moldavia in the
north, has been the center of what little protest has occurred.
   Frank Zemberi, a Yugoslav trucker bound from Cluj, Romania, to
London, said he passed through Timisoara early Tuesday and saw two
large fires raging in distant parts of town.
   ``Countless'' tanks were parked on the outskirts of Timisoara,
he said, but the city appeared calm. He reported seeing five
armored vehicles parked in the downtown area and police vans
cruising the streets.
   Hungarian radio said a caller from Timisoara reported gunfire in
the streets Tuesday, then the telephone went dead.
   Radio Kossuth, which said it got a call through briefly to
Timisoara on Tuesday morning, quoted a resident it did not name as
saying things were calm during the day, ``but at night it's like
during the war.''
   ``All main intersections have roadblocks. Everybody is ...
checked and people are not allowed to leave town except in extreme
cases,'' the radio quoted the resident as saying.
</TEXT>

</DOC>