<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0180 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1413EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-PRI--HarvestMagazine Adv28   12-26 0563</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-PRI--Harvest Magazine, Adv 28,0576</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv28</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Thursday, Dec. 28, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Magazine Focuses on People's Personal Experiences</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRAD CAIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SALEM, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When families lived together, older people
were a link between the past and future, reminiscing about the
history they'd lived. Today, families are far-flung and often out
of touch, but the need for a link remains.
   ``One of the important lessons of the book `Roots' is that
family and society are enormously interested in the past
experiences of individuals that they know,'' said Dr. Gene Cohen, a
psychiatrist and deputy director of the National Institute on
Aging. ``Look at how excited people are to look at old photo
albums. That's a form of reminiscing.''
   ``A lot of people have stories in them, but they haven't written
them down because there's just no place for their writing to
appear,'' said Jay Thomas Collins who, with partner William
Michaelian, offers just such a forum.
   The two in May 1988 launched Harvest, a literary magazine
featuring the reminiscences of people over 50. Michaelian, 33, and
Collins, 29, who both grew up in storytelling families, aren't
interested in family histories that merely list the comings and
goings of a particular family or group of people. Harvest is filled
mainly with the remembrances of everyday people whose good times
and bad times preceded shopping malls, freeways and fast-food
restaurants.
   The bimonthly magazine has grown in circulation to about 1,500
and gets about 40 or 50 submissions a week from around the country.
Harvest doesn't pay, but people whose articles are published get 10
free copies. Some stories are sent by professionals, but most
writers have never had anything published.
   ``We're looking for stories that really have something to say.
Whether it's polished or not is not our major concern. We just want
to present simple, honest stories,'' Michaelian said.
   ``We look for something that has lasting meaning to someone's
life,'' Collins said. ``There used to be a role for older people as
storytellers. They used to be valued for that. They've been through
good times and bad times. They have perspective, and some of their
reflections can teach you a great deal.''
   Consider ``Thanksgiving 1930,'' a story in the November-December
issue. Albert Bessler recalls waiting for several days during the
Depression to get a free food basket from the Salvation Army.
Bessler describes huddling with his brothers and sister in the
family's Model T to keep warm after their meal:
   ``When you're in a warm place and your belly is full and you
have someone to hold, what more could you want? I was thankful for
Thanksgiving Day. I was satisfied. I had a good deal.''
   Such reminiscences offer younger people new perspectives _
``they invariably derive new insights about themselves'' _ while
being a healthy experience for older people, Cohen said. ``For a
number of people, it can be a very helpful and therapeutic process
that brings them back to a broader perspective in terms of what
their life has been.
   ``The past has undoubtedly contained a number of situations
which at the time might have seemed insurmountable but yet we found
that we've gotten over them. Those reminders are very important to
help restore someone's perspective on the present.''
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Harvest's address: 2322 Latona Drive NE, Salem, OR 97303.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Dec. 28</NOTE>

</DOC>