<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0205 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1921EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-DogBurials     12-20 0544</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dog Burials,0559</SECOND>
<HEAD>Allegations That Dogs Were Buried Alive at Landfill</HEAD>
<HEAD>By SHERA GROSS</HEAD>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CARBONDALE, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A regional humane society is
investigating charges that a county dog pound has been burying
alive unwanted dogs and cats, officials said Wednesday.
   A number of people reported seeing animals squirming in the back
of a pickup that was taking animals to a landfill for burial.
However, Franklin County officials are denying that the animals,
which were supposed to have been killed by carbon monoxide
poisoning, were alive when buried.
   Debbie Allen, who works at the landfill office, said she was
working Tuesday when a truck filled with animals in plastic bags
from the Franklin County Dog Pound pulled up.
   ``I saw movement in the back of the truck,'' Ms. Allen said.
``At first I thought it was the wind, but then I noticed it made a
teepee effect, like a paw reaching up.''
   The driver, who was outside the truck to obtain papers from Ms.
Allen's office, ``swatted the bag with the back of his hand,'' Ms.
Allen said. ``Then he pulled up two other trash bags as if he was
trying to cover it up.''
   Franklin County Board member Cliff Cockrum said the animals were
checked before they left the pound in Benton. The board oversees
the pound.
   ``When we destroyed animals yesterday (Tuesday) morning we had a
veterinarian to check each and every animal and he assured us that
each one was dead before they left the pound,'' Cockrum said.
   Billy Hammond Sr. of Benton said he and his two sons examined
four dogs they found at the landfill.
   ``One of them my boy picked up and it gave out a pitiful whine
and then it went limp in his arms,'' he said Wednesday. The other
three animals were warm and limp and appeared to have been dead
only minutes, Hammond said.
   Cockrum called the reports by Ms. Allen and Hammond hearsay.
   About 45 animals are destroyed every two weeks at the pound.
They are put in steel boxes linked to the exhaust pipe of a vehicle
and are asphyxiated with carbon monoxide, Cockrum said.
   The carcasses are dumped at the landfill within two hours of
death, including the 45-minute ride from Benton to Carbondale.
Cockrum said 28 animals were killed Tuesday, including eight or
nine cats.
   Hammond said he found another dog barely alive in October and
asked the state Department of Agriculture to perform an autopsy on
the dog. Dr. D.K. Mann confirmed that he performed the procedure at
the department's Animal Disease Laboratory in Centralia.
   The autopsy found that the dog had been alive about three hours
after it was buried, Hammond said. It also found that the animal's
organs were severely burned from inhaling carbon monoxide, Hammond
said.
   Frantz Dantzler, regional director for the Humane Society of the
United States, said asphyxiation with carbon monoxide is an
``extremely painful'' method of euthanasia. The most humane and
least painful method is lethal injection of barbiturates, he said.
   Dantzler said his offers to the county for help in finding a
more humane euthansia system were ignored.
   The society plans to investigate the matter further, Dantzler
said in a telephone interview from his home in South Bend, Ind.
</TEXT>

</DOC>