<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1222EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Colombia-Jail     12-26 0334</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Colombia-Jail,0345</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Free Hostages Held By Prisoners, Kill Five Criminals</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STAN YARBRO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police stormed a cell block controlled
by drug traffickers holding 18 hostages, and six traffickers were
killed and five hostages wounded, authorities said today.
   Police late Monday gained the release of all of the hostages,
including two children, and the situation at the La Picota jail in
southern Bogota had returned to normal, a Justice Department
spokesman said.
   The spokesman asked not to be identified so he would not become
the target of revenge by any of the prisoners involved.
   The rescue came after two days of fruitless negotiations with
the prisoners, who had taken the hostages after a failed jailbreak
Sunday.
   The prisoners subdued guards during visiting hours at the jail
and were putting on their uniforms in an attempt to escape,
Bogota's El Tiempo newspaper reported today.
   The paper, quoting prison sources, said authorities discovered
the plan and sealed off the cell block before the prisoners, all
held on drug trafficking charges, could flee.
   The trapped criminals then took hostages, including some
civilians who had been visiting their jailed family members, and
made a series of protests and demands, El Tiempo reported.
   The paper said the prisoners began by protesting the death of
Gonzalo Rodriguez Gacha, the trafficker of the Medellin cartel who
was killed Dec. 15 in a gunfight with police on Colombia's northern
coast.
   The prisoners said they would release the hostages only if the
administration of President Virgilio Barco agreed to end its
extradition of drug traffickers to the United States, El Tiempo
said.
   The administration has extradited 11 drug suspects since August
when it decreed the policy.
   The prisoners also demanded a meeting with the Colombian Justice
Minister, Roberto Salazar and other officials. They said that they
wanted to be transferred to another, less crowded jail, El Tiempo
reported.
   The Justice Ministry official reached by telephone said he could
not confirm the details of the takeover.
</TEXT>

</DOC>