<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0132 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1855EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-Insurance     12-27 0397</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Insurance,0413</SECOND>
<HEAD>Store Owners Told Looting Not Covered by Insurance</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dozens of store owners whose shops
were sacked by frenzied looting after the U.S. invasion were told
Wednesday that ``acts of war'' were not covered by their insurance
policies.
   ``We regret to inform you that the claim you have submitted ...
must be rejected because the insurance policy excludes losses
suffered as a direct or indirect result of acts of war,'' said one
letter Panamanian insurance companies were mailing Wednesday to
their clients.
   Conservative estimates by insurance brokers and store owners put
the damage and losses between $750 million and $1 billion,
according to Alfredo Maduro, president of the Panamanian Chamber of
Commerce.
   Maduro said Panamanian businessmen will now ask the United
States for direct assistance to try to recover losses and resume
operations.
   ``This is a bomb worse than the ones of last Wednesday. The
insurance companies are saying that in an invaded country there is
no insurance coverage,'' insurance broker Gilberto Jimenez said in
an interview.
   Businessmen have estimated that more than 90 percent of the
shops were looted on Via Espana and Central Avenue, two commercial
streets in downtown Panana City.
   Thousands of looters raided everything from food, furniture,
televisions and appliances. Only bookstores survived.
   Lazaro Gago, owner of the Gago supermarket chain, said six of
his nine establishments had been looted and added his company was
``in ruins.''
   Eight of nine of the Arrocha pharmacies also were looted.
   A car company said it lost $4 million to looters. Avis and other
rental companies still were looking for cars taken from their lots.
   Television stations ran ads from car distributors offering
rewards for information leading to the recovery of new vehicles.
   Looting damage in El Dorado, a shopping center for upper middle
neighborhoods, was estimated at $25 million.
   Maduro said the chamber would ask for direct U.S. assistance
``in the form of equipment, technology and interest-ree loans,
something like a Marshall Plan for Panama.''
   ``It is our responsibility to rebuild the economy,'' Maduro
said, ``but we do not have the capacity at this time.''
   Both Maduro and Jimenez regretted the damage was done mostly by
Panamanians.
   ``We have committed a grievous mistake,'' Maduro added. ``We
attacked our own business establishments while the Americans were
attacking military targets only.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>