<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0130 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1355EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Zimbabwe-War     12-20 0512</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Zimbabwe-War,0531</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mozambique Rebel Offensives a Dilemma for Mugabe</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN EDLIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MUTARE, Zimbabwe (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ten years ago, guerrilla chieftain
Robert Mugabe put pen to paper in London to end a bloody seven-year
war for control of his homeland, Britain's last colonial outpost in
Africa known as Rhodesia.
   That all-party peace pact signed on Dec. 21, 1979, silenced the
guns and led to the birth of black-governed Zimbabwe four months
later.
   A decade later, as president of Zimbabwe, Mugabe is on the
receiving end of offensives across the eastern border by rebels
based in Mozambique.
   While Mugabe was able to lead Rhodesia to peace as Zimbabwe
through talks, he is opposed to similar direct negotiations with
the insurgents, who have threatened to bring their war into
Zimbabwe.
   Alfonso Dhlakama's Mozambique National Resistance seeks to
undermine Mozambique President Joaquim Chissano's socialist
government.
   The 12-year-old war has left an estimated 500,000 to 700,000
dead and created about 1 million Mozambican refugees. Almost half
of Mozambique's 15 million people require some food aid.
   The guerrillas also sabotage roads and railways vital to
landlocked Zimbabwe's economy, and Mugabe has stationed 12,000
troops in Mozambique at a crippling cost of $450,000 a day.
   Dhlakama's rebels now routinely cross the scrub-studded plains
and pine-carpeted mountains into Zimbabwe to raid tea and coffee
plantations, native villages and state schools.
   Hundreds of Zimbabweans have been slain or abducted in these
forays, and tens of thousands have been herded into state-guarded
villages, upsetting life all along the 800-mile frontier.
   ``The Rhodesians forced many people into so-called protected
villages when they were fighting Mugabe's guerrillas,'' said a
Roman Catholic missionary, who spoke on condition of anonymity.
``So there are villagers today who are suspicious that they're
being placed in similar settlements by the government they
support.''
   But missionaries back the government's contention that
Zimbabweans are better off behind wire and under guard because of
the rebels.
   The guerrillas, known also by their Portuguese acronym Renamo,
have been accused of widespread atrocities, including the killing
of children, mutilating of victims, rape, and destruction of entire
communities.
   The rebels were founded in 1977 by former Rhodesian Prime
Minister Ian D. Smith to hound Mugabe's guerrillas in their
Mozambican bases.
   Mugabe ended aid for Renamo when he came to power and no
government currently acknowledges assistance.
   Mugabe and Kenyan President Daniel arap Moi have been acting as
intermediaries in indirect talks in Kenya between the rebels and
the Mozambique government. There have been no breakthroughs since
the talks began in July.
   Mugabe has long said he opposes direct formal peace talks for
Mozambique, insisting Renamo disavow violence and lay down its arms
first.
   Renamo, in turn, demands Zimbabwe withdraw its troops from
Mozambique before face-to-face negotiations can be considered.
   Renamo also demands that Mozambique's government allow it to
take part in elections as a legal party.
   The Mozambican government says it will not accept a second party
but is considering a proposal that would allow people who are not
in the ruling party to run for Parliament.
</TEXT>

</DOC>