<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0256 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 2115EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f BC-Britain-Water Adv26   12-22 0724</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Britain-Water, Adv 26,0751</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv26</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Tuesday Dec. 26</HEAD>
<HEAD>Financial Watering Hole: Britain's Privatized Water Companies</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserGraphic</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By COTTEN TIMBERLAKE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Like nomads at a desert oasis, investors here and
abroad are gulping shares of Britain's newly privatized water
industry, lifting prices to unexpected highs but raising fears of
foreign control over a necessity of life.
   The government sold 10 water utilities in England and Wales for
$8.4 billion earlier this month. It was the latest in a series of
privatizations and surprisingly successful in an otherwise sluggish
stock market.
   The government offered 2.183 million shares at the equivalent of
$3.84 each. The shares, which began trading Dec. 12, quickly rose
in price and by Friday were worth about 50 percent more on the
London Stock Exchange.
   ``They have done fairly well,'' said Stephen Doe, a water
industry analyst at the London investment firm Smith New Court PLC.
   British investors weren't the only ones to perceive the water
industry as an opportunity. Foreigners including a French water
company also were aggressive buyers of the stock.
   Within less than a week of the trading launch, the French group
Lyonnaise des Eaux announced it acquired stakes in three water
companies _ 9 percent in Anglian Water, 6 percent in Wessex Water
and 2 percent of Severn Trent.
   France's two other big water companies, Generale des Eaux and
Societe d'Amenagement Urbain et Rural, also are expected to be big
buyers of the British shares.
   There's no immediate takeover threat to the big water utilities
because the government retained ``golden shares'' limiting holdings
in them to 15 percent for five years.
   However, Trade Secretary Nicholas Ridley recently has expressed
reservations about this limitation, suggesting it might be lifted.
   The French water companies are keen to invest because they
believe the British water companies are undervalued and offer good
prospects for earnings growth, analysts said.
   The French companies have the expertise and technology to
capitalize on the opportunities, which aren't available in other
European countries where the water industries are mostly
state-controlled.
   But some Britons oppose foreign control on their sources of
water, particularly if the owners are French, an historical British
rival.
   The resentment has been suggested in Britain's financial press,
which has quoted critics of the water privatization as portraying
the French water companies as raiding opportunists.
   But the Times of London wrote in an editorial: ``While the
government might have preferred to see British rather than French
predators, it can hardly object when it is committed to a level
playing field in the takeover game in Europe. We are all good
Europeans now.''
   The water shares are popular with other investors for other
reasons. They are considered recession proof because water is a
vital commodity. Built-in price increases in the form of rate hikes
virtually guarantee good profits for at least the next few years.
   Nigel Hawkins, water industry analyst for Security Pacific-Hoare
Govett Ltd., said the water shares' average yield is attractive at
7 percent, a 50 percent premium on the average market yield.
   The shares have been boosted by speculation about the French
companies' buying intentions.
   There had been concerns that the water sale would fail because
it followed the sharp drop in world stock markets a few months ago.
But demand for the shares greatly exceeded the supply.
   ``We have proved our critics wrong,'' Environment Minister
Michael Howard said.
   The water sale is the first privitization since the government's
divestment of its one-third stake in British Petroleum Co. PLC,
which was a failure because it coincided with the October 1987
stock market crash. Many brokers suffered severe losses from the BP
fiasco.
   The water privatization also faced stiff opposition from critics
who believed such a vital utility should remain in state hands for
reasons of security and water quality.
   Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher's critics said she was becoming
too extreme during her third term, taking a privatization program
too far. But she is proceeding.
   The government also plans to sell the country's electricity
industry by mid-1992. That sale could raise more than $32 billion,
dwarfing the other privatizations.
   Mrs. Thatcher's Conservative government has sold $53 billion
worth of state-owned companies in the past decade as part of a
broader economic policy of encouraging private enterprise and
investment by British citizens.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End adv for Tuesday Dec. 26</NOTE>

</DOC>