<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0020EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-ThirdWorld     12-25 0608</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Third World,620</SECOND>
<HEAD>Third World Gains in Quality of Life</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CARL HARTMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Third World countries, though struggling with
poverty, violence and debt, have made big strides in schooling
their children and prolonging people's lives in recent years,
according to figures assembled by the World Bank.
   The World Bank is the biggest source of aid loans to the Third
World. It collects data on 185 countries and territories in ``The
World Bank Atlas.'' The 1989 edition was published recently.
   Take Sri Lanka, the island republic off the coast of India, torn
by ethnic conflict among a population with an average income of
only $420 a year.
   Between 1970 and 1988, the country increased life expectancy for
newborn children from 64 to 71 years, not far from this country's
75 years.
   The number of children a Sri Lankan mother could expect to have
dropped to 2.6 in 1988 from 4.3 in 1970. Reducing the size of the
future population is important in a country that crowds more than
16 million people into an area smaller than the state of Maine.
   By 1986, the date of the most recent figures, 84 percent of Sri
Lankan children were in school, up from 71 percent in 1970.
   India too, a country much more populous than Sri Lanka and even
poorer, had built schools for 60 percent of its children in 1986,
compared with 49 percent in 1970. Parents of an Indian baby born
last year could expect it to live until age 55 _ instead of only 48
in 1970.
   Between 1965 and 1986, food supplies went down in some of the
poorest areas _ Ethiopia, Chad, Zaire and Nigeria, Africa's most
populous country. But many of the 42 areas in the bank's ``low
income'' group showed an increase in food supplies, including
Indonesia, Nepal, Laos, Malawi and Tanzania.
   The average Indonesian, for example, had a daily average of only
1,800 calories available in 1965. By 1986, that had risen to 2,579
calories, though the average citizen was earning only $500 a year.
Americans have an average daily supply of 3,645 calories.
   Even Africa has progress to show, though incomes have gone down
in many countries since they emerged from colonial rule in the
1960s. Togo, for example, claimed to have 78 percent of its girls
in elementary school in 1986, up from only 32 percent in 1965. Togo
got its independence from France in 1960. Incomes have been
dropping throughout the 1980s, averaging $370 last year.
   In 1965, Togo had one physician for 23,240 people. Yet by 1984,
the average had improved to one doctor for 8,720 people. That was a
long way from this country's 470 prospective patients per doctor,
but still a considerable improvement.
   Many Latin Americans are especially proud of progress in
education, although otherwise they speak of the 1980s as a ``lost
decade.'' Incomes have declined in many areas, wealthy citizens
have sent much of their wealth abroad and the burden of foreign
debt has increased greatly.
   For instance, a poor country like Bolivia was educating 87
percent of its children in primary school in 1986 _ 93 percent of
the boys and 82 percent of the girls _ compared with 73 percent in
1965. It also increased the number of young people in higher
education, to 19 percent from 5 percent.
   Countries where women traditionally have been at a disadvantage
were giving them more education. The number of girls in secondary
schools rose from 5 percent in 1965 to 27 percent in 1986 in
Morocco, and from 15 percent to 54 percent in Egypt in the same
time span.
</TEXT>

</DOC>