<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0093 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1507EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Navy-Safety Bjt   12-19 0521</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Navy-Safety, Bjt,550</SECOND>
<HEAD>Navy Chief Rips Lax Safety Procedures</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSANNE M. SCHAFER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Military Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Navy's top admiral, criticizing lax safety
procedures and an attitude of complacency, told his commanders they
must do better to prevent the deadly accidents that plagued the
service in recent months, the Pentagon said Tuesday.
   ``The level of effective supervision on the scene was often
inadequate when accidents occurred,'' Adm. Carlisle A.H. Trost said
in a letter sent Monday to all Navy commanders.
   ``Taking safety for granted is never acceptable,'' Trost wrote.
``Safety springs from a command attitude and set of priorities that
require an every-day, building-block approach and self-discipline.''
   Trost's findings stem from his evaluation of the Navy's
unprecedented two-day freeze, or stand-down, on routine operations
last month.
   Trost and Navy Secretary H. Lawrence Garrett III ordered the
pause in operations in mid-November after 10 accidents at sea and
in the air within three weeks killed 10 Navy personnel and injured
at least 71.
   Under the stand-down order, all Navy units worldwide halted
normal routine and concentrated on safety inspections, reviews and
lectures.
   Afterward, commanders relayed their findings to Trost.
   Pentagon spokesman Pete Williams, releasing a statement about
the Navy's study, said Defense Secretary Dick Cheney was confident
the service would address the problems.
   ``I'm sure they'll take steps to correct it,'' Williams said.
   Trost ``referred to complacency'' in his letter, and faulted
commanders for exercising poor supervision during the Navy's many
dangerous operations. He told commanders there was no single
element to link the accidents, which ranged from men washed
overboard to plane crashes to ship fires to the accidental bombing
of a cruiser.
   Trost complained that sailors had not been properly taught to do
their jobs, that supervisors lacked safety training and established
safety procedures were not adequately followed. He said those were
all areas where improvements were needed.
   ``The bottom line is that safety of our personnel is a
fundamental obligation and responsibility of leadership,'' Trost
told his commanders. ``One life lost is an unacceptable price. We
simply must do better.''
   During the safety review, naval commanders found problems with
proper planning of their operations, a lack of qualified senior
leaders during operations, proper 24-hour-a-day supervision and
compressed at-sea schedules that precluded proper training for
junior personnel, the Pentagon statement said.
   Attention should be paid to the constant review of all safety
procedures, the proper use of safety publications so sailors don't
have to constantly re-learn safety procedures and the use of
established inspections to reveal improper stowage of dangerous
materials, the statement said.
   The stand-down revealed that there should be increased emphasis
on safety during all training courses, improvement in the quality
of instructors at Navy schools and better use of such safety
instruction techniques as training videotapes.
   There have been 75 major accidents and 104 fatalities this year.
However, that includes the 47 sailors killed in the April 19 gun
turret explosion aboard the battleship USS Iowa.
   According to Navy figures, 1988 was the safest year on record
with 63 fatalities. In comparison, there were 118 major accidents
reported with 64 fatalities in 1984.
</TEXT>

</DOC>