<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0125 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 2035EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania-Timisoara     12-26 0561</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Timisoara,0571</SECOND>
<HEAD>RETRANSMITTING a0577 to include in introduction that account was
filed Tuesday.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Soviet News Agency's Account of Fighting In Timisoara</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The following is an account of fighting in Timisoara filed on
Tuesday by Anatoly Bocharov, a special correspondent for the Soviet
news agency Tass:
 
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   TIMISOARA, Romania _ Shots can still be heard in Timisoara, a
city in the western part of Romania. There are killed and wounded.
Supporters of the overthrown dictator Nicolae Ceausescu, mostly the
personnel of the former security service Securitate, continue to
offer armed resistance to the insurgents.
   In an attempt to hide from popular indignation, the extremists
try to flee the city. As a rule, they take these desperate steps at
night, firing at random at passers-by. We learned from our own
experience that the insurgents had a good reason, when taking
measures for ensuring the safety of work and travel of foreign
journalists in Timisoara and in the area around it. Eight
journalists were wounded. Danny Huwe, a Belgian journalist, was
shot dead by extremists on Monday. His car in which he was driving
together with his three colleagues was fired at by anti-insurgent
sharp-shooters.
   Army units are combing Timisoara districts and separate
buildngs. They are acting in close cooperation with the democratic
committee which assumed the duty to bring the situation in the city
back to normal.
   Facts show that they are facing a strong and treacherous enemy
trained in advance to stage repressions against the population. For
example, a regular arms cache was found in the house of one of the
heads of the security force. It is believed that there are many
such arms caches in the houses of security officers. This is the
explanation for continuing armed clashes in the streets of the city.
   Members of the democratic committee told Tass that the
Securitate had been created to serve as the mainstay of the ousted
regime. It had included well-equipped specialized units and a large
network of informers.
   One should see the eyes of the people looking at the arrests of
extremists. They are full of tears, of grief over the death of
defenseless people during the shooting of the demonstration and
hatred for the totalitarian regime.
   There is no doubt that the last hotbeds of resistance will soon
be suppressed. The situation in the city is getting back to normal
with difficulty and step by step. Residents met with satisfaction
the order of the National Salvation Front of Romania that all the
armaments should be urgently handed over to the authorities. People
heeded the appeal of the democratic committee to return to their
working places. Some grocery shops were opened. Tram, trolleybus
and bus traffic was resumed.
   Victor and Victoria are now the most popular names in the city.
To commemorate the victory of the people, they were given to its
youngest residents, a boy and a girl, who were born after the
overthrow of the regime. A proposal is being discussed in Timisoara
to make Dec. 22, the day when the revolutionary rejuvenation of
Romania was started, a national holiday.
   On our way from Timisoara to Yugoslavia, we saw trucks carrying
the Red Cross flag. They were transporting to Romania food,
medicines and clothes. Aid to the Romanian people that suffered
from the ousted regime is coming from many countries.
</TEXT>

</DOC>