<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0214 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1851EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Argentina-Economy     12-28 0480</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Argentina-Economy,0499</SECOND>
<HEAD>Interest Rates Soar to 600 Percent a Month</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ED McCULLOUGH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUENOS AIRES, Argentina (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Interest rates skyrocketed to 600
percent a month Thursday amid continuing economic turmoil and
runaway inflation.
   Banks paid their biggest depositors the 600 percent rate to
retain funds that otherwise may have been withdrawn and converted
to U.S. dollars.
   Investors have bought dollars heavily for two months, driving
down the austral, Argentina's national currency, to a value of
1,950-1 on Thursday from 728-1 on Nov. 1, a devaluation of 63
percent.
   The monthly interest rates amounted to six times the rates
quoted two days ago. It is impossible to predict what rates might
be next Tuesday, when banks open after yearend holidays Friday and
Monday.
   Virtually no one can afford to borrow except the government,
which pays that much and more on the reserves it requires banks to
set aside. Reserves average about 63 percent of banks' total
deposits.
   As the austral has lost its value, prices have soared.
   A survey by the Federation of Commercial Centers indicated that
in Buenos Aires medicine prices soared by an average 334 percent in
December; food, 210 percent; hardware items, 240 percent; clothing,
200 percent.
   Pharmacies reported their distributors were refusing to deliver
goods, particularly imported medicines, for fear of charging too
little and not being able to resupply.
   A quart of milk cost 470 australs, or 24 cents, on Thursday, up
from about 170 australs earlier this month. A movie ticket cost
2,100 australs, $1.07, up from about 900 australs.
   Since November, one economy minister and two Central Bank
presidents have been sacked, two stabilization plans launched and
financial institutions closed four times by government order.
   ``Did someone tell you they see a light at the end of the
tunnel? I don't, not now or in 1990,'' said a Central Bank official
speaking condition of anonymity.
   Analysts attribute the financial turmoil to a lack of public
confidence in President Carlos Menem's ability to carry out a
proposed program of economic reform in the face of opposition by
unions, businesses that sell to the state and his own Peronist
Party.
   Menem won national elections in May and took office in July.
   The core of the program is the reduction of state expenditures
that contribute to chronic inflation and the sale of public
companies that annually ring up huge deficits.
   Wages are linked to the government's calculation of inflation
but have failed to keep pace. Many public and private employees
received raises of 6.5 percent in early December to compensate them
for the cost of living in November.
   Economy Minister Antonio Gonzalez predicted that inflation in
December may top 50 percent.
   Inflation for the first 11 months of 1989 increased by 3,731
percent, according to the National Institute of Statistics and
Census, including 114 percent in June and 197 percent in July.
</TEXT>

</DOC>