<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0927EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-MenorahSuit 1stLd-Writethru a0492 12-29 0426</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Menorah Suit, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0492,0432</SECOND>
<HEAD>Supreme Court Allows Menorah on Steps of Public Building</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS one graf after 3rd graf with `PLO' written on menorah
sign. Picks up 4th graf pvs, `The menorah...'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Supreme Court has rejected Pittsburgh's
request for authority to bar a menorah from the steps of the
City-County Building.
   By a 6-3 vote Thursday, the court rejected an emergency request
by the city aimed at having the menorah taken down before
Saturday's conclusion of Hanukkah. Chief Justice William H.
Rehnquist and Justices John Paul Stevens and Antonin Scalia were in
the minority.
   City officials had asked the full court to set aside an order
Justice William J. Brennan issued last Friday letting Chabad, a
Jewish organization, erect the menorah. The menorah and a sign
saying ``Salute to Liberty'' were put in place Tuesday.
   Late Thursday, someone wrote ``PLO,'' the initials of the
Palestine Liberation Organization, on the sign. The vandal, if
caught, could be charged with criminal mischief, ethnic
intimidation and desecration of a venerated object, police Officer
Thomas Koral said.
   The menorah is a candelabrum symbolizing the eight-day Jewish
holiday.
   Earlier Thursday, the court had said it would take up the city's
request Jan. 5, during its next regularly scheduled conference _
virtually assuring that the 40-foot menorah would remain alongside
a 45-foot Christmas tree until it is taken down by Chabad members
on Saturday.
   Later in the day, the justices decided to take up the city's
request in a more timely manner.
   City officials argued that the Jewish group shouldn't have the
power to determine what will be displayed on the steps of a public
building. They argued that the area isn't a ``public forum'' open
to various messages by private citizens.
   U.S. District Judge Barron P. McCune ruled last week that the
city couldn't prevent display of the menorah, but the 3rd U.S.
Circuit Court of Appeals in Philadelphia on Friday postponed the
effect of McCune's ruling.
   Brennan then set aside the 3rd Circuit order.
   The same menorah and a Christmas Nativity scene located at the
Allegheny County Courthouse in Pittsburgh was the subject of a
Supreme Court decision last summer.
   The court ruled that the menorah's display was constitutional
because it, unlike the Nativity scene, was accompanied by a
non-religious symbol, the Christmas tree.
   City officials said that ruling didn't obligate them to allow
display of the menorah, but Judge McCune ruled that the steps of
the City-County Building have become a public forum open to various
types of expression.
</TEXT>

</DOC>