<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0147EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-MercyShooting     12-26 0313</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mercy Shooting,0328</SECOND>
<HEAD>Authorities: Retired Police Officer Shoots Chronically Ill Wife</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHARLES J. GANS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A retired policeman who was facing major heart
surgery fatally shot his ailing wife because he was afraid he
couldn't take care of her and didn't want her to suffer anymore,
authorities say.
   Gerald Williams, 67, was charged with first-degree murder in the
death of his wife, Alice, who suffered from multiple sclerosis,
said Police Sgt. Ronald Palmer
   Williams was released on personal recognizance into his
daughter's custody after a Christmas Day hearing.
   The prosecutor agreed with a defense lawyer that Williams, who
retired six years ago, posed no threat to society.
   ``Good luck and Merry Christmas,'' Circuit Court Judge Sheldon
Garber told Williams at the close of the hearing.
   Williams was scheduled to appear for another hearing today.
   Mrs. Williams, 64, apparently died instantly Christmas Eve when
her husband of 44 years shot her in the head with a .38-caliber
revolver as she sat in her wheelchair, Palmer said.
   Williams then called police and handed over the gun when
officers arrived at the home, Palmer said.
   ``It's a sad thing to happen on any day, and it just seems to be
embellished by the fact that it's Christmas Eve,'' said Palmer.
   Williams told the officers that ``all his wife did was complain
about how much she was suffering and she begged him to end it,''
Palmer said.
   Williams' doctor recently told him he needed a second major
heart operation and he wouldn't be able to care for his wife,
according to an account given to police by Williams' daughter.
   Mrs. Williams suffered from multiple sclerosis, a degenerative
disease of the nervous system, for 20 years, and had heart and
kidney problems, Palmer said.
   ``His health wasn't the best and hers was deteriorating,''
Palmer said. ``I'm sure the guy is overwrought.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>