<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0244 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2258EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Panama-Wounded 1stLd-Writethru a0849 12-20 0275</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Wounded, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0849,0281</SECOND>
<HEAD>Planes Bring Wounded Servicemen Back From Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: UPDATES throughout with second plane arriving, details, updated
casualty count, third plane expected, other details; no pickup.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KELLEY SHANNON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN ANTONIO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two transport planes flew 108 servicemen
wounded in the U.S. invasion of Panama to military hospitals
Wednesday, but three were dead on arrival and another died later,
officials said.
   The first C-141 landed at Kelly Air Force Base in San Antonio at
11:37 a.m. with 43 soldiers aboard, including the three dead and
the one who died shortly after arrival.
   The 39 wounded were taken to Wilford Hall Medical Center at
adjacent Lackland Air Force Base, said Lt. Dave Ebner, a spokesman
at Kelly. Some were well enough to take buses, and others were
taken by ambulance, said Lackland spokeswoman Dolores Schroeder.
   The second C-141 arrived at Kelly around 5:30 p.m. with 65
soldiers with ``serious to very critical'' injuries, said Lt. Col.
Johnny Whitaker, another Lackland spokesman.
   ``The biggest and the most extensive injuries are gunshot-type
wounds, schrapnel-type wounds, leg wounds, broken bones, this sort
of thing,'' Whitaker said.
   Forty-one of the soldiers on the second flight were taken across
town to Brooke Army Medical Center, Whitaker said. The rest went to
Wilford Hall.
   Another transport was expected later Wednesday, said Whitaker,
who was unsure how many wounded would be aboard.
   Kelly officials were told their base would be the sole reception
point for wounded from Panama.
   Pentagon officials said 15 U.S. servicemen and a female civilian
dependent were killed, one serviceman was missing and more than 100
were wounded.
</TEXT>

</DOC>