<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0720EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AmtrakAccident     12-20 0625</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Amtrak Accident,0644</SECOND>
<HEAD>Authorities Probe Cause Of Truck-Train Crash That Killed 3, Injured
55</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY27</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEVE GEISSINGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>STOCKTON, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Passengers said it felt ``like a
nightmare'' when a collision between a truck hauling chocolate
syrup and the Amtrak train in which they were riding killed three
people and injured 55.
   John Bruno, a passenger from Seattle, said Tuesday's crash
``felt like somebody had dead-stopped us. Then we hit three times.
... My head was clobbered each time.''
   ``I was collecting tickets and then all hell broke loose,'' said
conductor Gary Burke. ``I wound up flying into the next car.''
   California Highway Patrol spokesman Bob Whitmire said Tuesday
that investigators were trying to determine the accident's cause,
including the dense fog which was blamed for a couple of multi-car
pileups in the region.
   The crash killed the truck driver and two train crewmen.
   Amtrak spokesman Arthur Lloyd said the truck driver seemed to be
responsible for the crash. ``Evidently the vehicle ignored the
lights and went right in front of train,'' Lloyd said.
   But Gov. George Deukmejian, who toured the scene, said the three
people killed in the crash may be the only ones who really know
what happened.
   The 70-mph speed of the train was within the limit for the area,
according to federal transportation officials.
   People aboard the train, which carried at least 142 including
five Amtrak crew members, described nightmarish conditions during
the crash and its aftermath. No one said they had seen the truck or
warning devices at the crossing before the collision.
   ``It was like a nightmare,'' said passenger Phyllis Ferguson of
Stockton. ``I was sitting there reading the paper and then crash,
fire. I was thrown to the floor. Seats crumpled ahead and behind
me. Everybody was screaming and yelling. One woman was yelling for
her baby.''
   Several passengers said the train and ground were so covered
with chocolate from the truck that they slipped as they tried to
leave the train.
   ``It hit hard, harder than anything I've ever felt,'' said
Angela Price, who was in third of five passenger cars behind the
engine. ``I was thrown forward.
   ``I was looking out the window and I could see the flames (of
the burning truck and train engine wreckage) coming toward us. .. .
I just braced myself and watched it, but it stopped, thank God.''
   The 34-year-old Berkeley woman said she was not going on to Los
Angeles. ``I don't want to get on another train,'' she said.
   The San Joaquin County coroner's office identified the dead
truck driver as David Haskell, 47, of Pomona. The other two victims
were identified only as the train's engineer and fireman, pending
notification of relatives.
   Of the 55 injured, 24 seriously injured people were taken by
ambulance to hospitals, Whitmire said. Buses took 31 others to
various medical facilities for examination and treatment of minor
injuries.
   Whitmire said 87 uninjured people were taken by bus to the
Riverbank Amtrak station, about 20 miles south of the crash site.
   The train was southbound from Oakland to Bakersfield on Amtrak's
San Joaquin route when the crash occurred at 9:38 a.m., about nine
minutes after leaving the Stockton station.
   The Amtrak locomotive overturned and burst into flames, which
took more than an hour to extinguish.
   The truck was demolished, broken into hundreds of small pieces,
and carried 300 feet down the tracks by the train's engine. The
truck's load of chocolate syrup coated two of the train's five
passenger cars.
   The investigation into the cause of the crash by transportation
officials continued Tuesday night as Amtrak crews pulled luggage
from the wreckage.
   Cleanup and repair of 900 feet of damaged track was expected to
take several days.
</TEXT>

</DOC>