<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0138 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1726EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Burma     12-29 0396</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Burma,0407</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Prime Minister Nu Barred from Elections</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: One name correct for Nu</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RANGOON, Burma (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The ruling military junta has barred
Burma's last democratically elected prime minister from running in
the May general elections, the government said Friday.
   Kyaw Sann, spokesman for the military rulers, said former Prime
Minister Nu was disqualified for his refusal to dissolve a parallel
government he declared at the height of last year's national
uprising for democracy.
   The spokesman told a weekly official news briefing that Nu also
would face legal action, but that he would not be imprisoned.
   Nu announced his 26-member government Sept. 9, 1988, saying he
was still the country's rightful prime minister because the 1962
military coup that ousted him was illegal.
   Gen. Saw Maung's State Law and Order Restoration Council seized
power and brutally crushed protests nine days after Nu declared his
government. Saw Maung declared the rival Cabinet illegal and
demanded its dissolution as a condition for Nu to run in the
election scheduled for May 27.
   The election will be the first multiparty balloting in Burma
since Nu was elected in 1960.
   But diplomats say the military junta has arrested and harassed
thousands of dissidents since it seized power, raising doubts the
election will be free and fair.
   At a Christmas Day news conference, the 82-year-old Nu rejected
the government demand, saying he was ``prepared to face any
consequences.''
   In a Dec. 7 letter to Saw Maung, Nu said he would disband his
government only when Ne Win, the general who ousted him, made a
public apology.
   Kyaw Sann said members of Nu's party who were part of his
government and refused to disown it also were barred from the
elections. But those who withdrew from the parallel government
would be allowed to run, even if they remained members of Nu's
League for Democracy and Peace, he said.
   In reply to a reporter's question, Kyaw Sann said Aung San Suu
Kyi, considered the most popular opposition figure, would be
allowed to run providing she did not violate any provisions of the
election law.
   Ms. Suu Kyi has been under house arrest since July 20, accused
of trying to divide the people from the army. A week ago, Gen. Tin
Oo, chairman of her National League for Democracy party, was
sentenced to three years in prison on the same charge.
</TEXT>

</DOC>