<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0633EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-RecruitmentInvestigations     12-18 0306</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Recruitment Investigations,0312</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Many Armed Forces Recruiters Use Fraud to Sell the Service</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARTFORD, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Military recruiters are resorting to
fraud as they try to meet quotas and sell the armed forces to a
shrinking pool of applicants, according to a published report.
   Interviews with former recruiters and documents and statistics
obtained through the Freedom of Information Act show that
recruiters are luring prospects with promises that cannot be kept,
The Hartford Courant reported Sunday.
   The recruiters enlisted unqualified recruits by helping them
fake educational credentials, cheat on aptitude tests and conceal
criminal records and medical problems that could otherwise
disqualify them, the newspaper said.
   Overall in the 1988 fiscal year, the Army, Navy, Air Force and
Marines investigated a total of 4,128 allegations of fraudulent
recruiting. The four services substantiated 701 of the allegations
and disciplined 992 recruiters _ about 7 percent of the total
recruiting force. There are slightly more than 14,000 recruiters,
according to figures supplied by the services.
   In addition to attracting recruits, the system is supposed to
screen applicants, requiring them to pass aptitude tests and
physical examinations and to undergo police checks.
   But one in seven recruits doesn't make it through the first year
of service and one in three never finishes the term of enlistment.
The cost to taxpayers is hundreds of millions of dollars each year,
the newspaper said.
   ``Every time we recruit somebody that doesn't make it through a
first term and we have to replace them, it costs us $18,000,'' said
Wayne S. Sellman, the civilian director of the Pentagon office
responsible for recruiting policy.
   More than 42,000 of the 294,000 volunteers recruited by the
Pentagon during 1988 were discharged before the end of their first
year. Using Sellman's $18,000 figure, the cost of replacing them
would be more than $750 million.
</TEXT>

</DOC>