<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0116 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1550EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-NATO-Soviet     12-18 0653</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-NATO-Soviet,0672</SECOND>
<HEAD>NATO Reports Sees Beginning of Cuts in Soviet Defense Spending</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SALLY JACOBSEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRUSSELS, Belgium (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Soviet Union appears to have begun
cutting its defense expenditures, including in the critical area of
conventional forces, according to a new NATO study released Monday.
   The analysis by the North Atlantic Treaty Organization offers
new evidence that Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev is trying
to pare the nation's massive military industry.
   ``While NATO remains highly skeptical regarding Soviet claims
for their defense expenditures, it appears that the Soviet Union is
indeed beginning to trim its defense outlays,'' said the study, a
copy of which was approved last month by the ambassadors of the 16
alliance nations. It was made available by the U.S. mission to NATO.
   A year ago, Gorbachev went before the United Nations and
promised to cut unilaterally Soviet military forces by 500,000
troops and reduce conventional arms substantially. A month later,
he called for a 14.2 percent cut in military spending and a 19.5
percent reduction in military production.
   The nations of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization and those
of the Soviet-led Warsaw Pact are negotiating in Vienna to reduce
tanks, armored personnel carriers and other conventional weapons in
Europe. The West wants to slash what it sees as the Soviets'
enormous superiority in these arms.
   In the report, NATO analysts said that in line with Gorbachev's
U.N. speech, ``the Soviet Union is reducing the size of its
conventional forces.''
   ``A number of major procurement programs, particularly in the
land armaments area, are being scaled back,'' it said. It added,
however, that it was too early to tell whether all of Gorbachev's
promises would be carried out.
   The report did not give specific figures for defense cutbacks.
   Soviet officials say their military budget for next year will be
$114.8 billion, off 8.2 percent from 1989's reported spending plan.
   The NATO report, based on defense spending through 1988, said
the budget outlays reported this year by the Kremlin appeared too
low to cover the cost of Soviet military activities.
   It estimated that the Kremlin spent $210 billion to $258 billion
in 1988.
   That sum, it said, would amount to about 15 percent to 18
percent of the Soviet economy's total output. In comparison, NATO
estimates that U.S. defense spending last year accounted for about
6.1 percent of the gross national product.
   Most of the differences in budget estimates was due to
artificially low prices the Soviets maintain for some defense
efforts, the report said. It also said the Soviets do not appear to
include some costs added to Western budgets.
   Defense spending grew at a seasonally adjusted annual rate of
about 2 percent to 3 percent in the 1985-88 period, a bit ahead of
the pace in the first half of the decade, the report said.
   ``Underlying the estimate of defense spending growth is a fairly
rapid increase in procurement expenditures, which approach 40
percent of total outlays,'' the report said.
   ``This increase in growth has been driven by the production of
several new generations of weapon systems, the development of which
predates Gorbachev,'' it said.
   It said expenditures on operations and maintenance grew by about
2 percent annually. Spending on research and development gained but
little rise was found in personnel expenditures.
   The report noted Gorbachev's drive to restructure the economy so
that some of the money spent for defense would be channeled into
consumer goods. But it said the conversion campaign ``still appears
to lack an integrated plan.''
   It said it would be difficult to estimate Soviet defense
spending in the next decade because of the dramatic political,
economic and military changes likely to take place.
   ``Although pressure to reduce military spending will continue,
the Soviet leadership will remain determined not to let Soviet
military capability fall below the level that it judges necessary
to protect the security of the state,'' the report concluded.
</TEXT>

</DOC>