<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0143 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0751EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv05   12-26 0456</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv05,0475</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv05</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Friday, Jan. 5</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Tayloe is cq, 8th graf</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is Friday, Jan. 5, the fifth day of 1990. There are 360
days left in the year.
   Today's highlight in history:
   On Jan. 5, 1896, an Austrian newspaper (``Wiener Presse'')
published the first public account of a discovery by German
physicist Wilhelm Roentgen _ a form of radiation that became known
as ``X-rays.''
   On this date:
   In 1589, Catherine de Medici of France died at the age of 69.
   In 1781, a British naval expedition led by Benedict Arnold
burned Richmond, Va.
   In 1895, French Captain Alfred Dreyfus, convicted of treason,
was publicly stripped of his rank. (He was later declared innocent.)
   In 1925, Nellie Tayloe Ross became the first female governor of
a state as she assumed her duties as chief executive of Wyoming to
finish out her late husband's term.
   In 1933, the 30th president of the United States, Calvin
Coolidge, died at his home in Northampton, Mass., at the age of 60.
   In 1943, educator and scientist George Washington Carver died in
Tuskegee, Ala., at age 81.
   In 1949, in his State of the Union address, President Truman
labeled his administration the ``Fair Deal.''
   In 1970, Joseph A. Yablonski, an unsuccessful candidate for the
presidency of the United Mine Workers, was found murdered with his
wife and daughter at their home in Clarksville, Pa.
   In 1981, police in England arrested Peter Sutcliffe, a truck
driver later convicted of the ``Yorkshire Ripper'' murders of 13
women.
   In 1983, President Reagan announced he was nominating Elizabeth
Dole to succeed Drew Lewis as secretary of transportation, making
her the first woman to head the Department of Transportation.
   Ten years ago: At the request of the United States and 49 other
countries, the U.N. Security Council opened debate on the Soviet
Union's intervention in Afghanistan.
   Five years ago: Soviet President Konstantin U. Chernenko said
the Soviet Union was ready for ``urgent and effective measures'' to
curb the arms race, and called on the U.S. to adopt Soviet arms
control proposals.
   One year ago: Lawrence E. Walsh, the special prosecutor in the
Iran-Contra case, asked for a dismissal of two charges against
Oliver North, citing the Reagan administration's refusal to release
material sought by North.
   Today's birthdays: Former Vice President Walter F. Mondale is
62. Actor Robert Duvall is 59. Pittsburgh Steelers coach Chuck Noll
is 58. King Juan Carlos of Spain is 52. Actress Diane Keaton is 44.
Actress Pamela Sue Martin is 37.
   Thought for today: ``Wisdom is divided into two parts: (a)
having a great deal to say, and (b) not saying it.'' _ Anonymous.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Fri Jan 5</NOTE>

</DOC>