<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0031EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RollingStones     12-20 0372</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rolling Stones,0385</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stones Pay Per View Concert Tops North American Tour</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HENRY STERN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTIC CITY, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Rolling Stones capped the
next-to-last show of their 32-city North American tour with a guest
appearance by British blues guitarist Eric Clapton for the band's
pay-per-view concert Tuesday night.
   The capacity crowd of 16,000 at Convention Hall roared when the
bearded Clapton stepped to center stage for two bluesy solos during
``Little Red Rooster.''
   The Stones' lead singer, Mick Jagger, in turquoise shirt, black
jeans and silver-studded belt, then joined the Clapton on harmonica.
   Clapton, wearing a black leather jacket and white T-shirt, was
making his first appearance with the Stones on the current tour.
   The pay-per-view concert Tuesday night was to be seen in 13.5
million homes and heard on about 150 radio stations, promoters said.
   The concert, the second of three scheduled at 16,000-seat
Convention Hall, also featured appearances by vocalist Axl Rose and
guitarist Izzy Stradlin of Guns 'n' Roses and by 71-year-old
Southern blues guitar legend John Lee Hooker.
   Rose and Stradlin, introduced by Jagger as having come ``all the
way East to get their tattooes touched up,'' sang, ``Salt of the
Earth'' with the original bad boys of rock 'n' roll.
   Jagger seemed more animated Tuesday night, playing up to the
television cameras, leading middle-aged fans through the new lyrics
of ``Terrifying'' and swaying to ``Ruby Tuesday'' with fans born
after it was first recorded in 1967.
   Tickets for each of the Stones' concerts Sunday, Tuesday and
Wednesday in Atlantic City cost $38.50, $150 and $250.
   The Stones, who have been performing since 1962, opened the tour
Aug. 31 at Veterans Stadium in Philadelphia.
   The group took off Monday to celebrate guitarist Keith Richards'
46th birthday.
   Scott Kurnit, the president of Set Pay Per View, the show's
distributor to cable companies, said the suggested retail price for
the concert was $24.95, but added that some cable companies were
charging $19.95.
   Jagger said the live televised performance would inject just the
boost needed for the Stones at the end of their first tour since
1981.
   ``You get wound up for live TV ... especially at the end of a
tour,'' said Jagger, 46.
</TEXT>

</DOC>