<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0100 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1543EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Royals-Hamlet     12-19 0369</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Royals-Hamlet,0403</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prince Charles Goes From Bard to Worse</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Royals</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prince Charles used Shakespeare's ``Hamlet'' to
illustrate the decline of the English language into what he called
impoverished, sloppy banalities and cliches.
   The prince said English had been the medium for some of the
greatest literature in the world, including that of William
Shakespeare, whom he called probably the greatest playwright that
ever lived.
   But the state of modern English led the prince to wonder how
Shakespeare's Hamlet would have delivered his famous ``To be, or
not to be'' soliloquy in today's language.
   This is what Hamlet says in Act III, Scene 1, of the play,
``Hamlet, Prince of Denmark.''
   To be, or not to be: that is the question:
   Whether 'tis nobler in the mind to suffer
   The slings and arrows of outrageous fortune,
   Or to take arms against a sea of troubles,
   And by opposing end them? To die: to sleep;
   No more; and, by a sleep to say we end
   The heart-ache and the thousand natural shocks
   That flesh is heir to, 'tis a consummation
   Devoutly to be wish'd. To die, to sleep;
   To sleep: perchance to dream: ay, there's the rub;
   For in that sleep of death what dreams may come
   When we have shuffled off this mortal coil,
   Must give us pause.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Here is Prince Charles' version of how the soliloquy would be
written in today's English:
   Well, frankly, the problem as I see it
   At this moment in time is whether I
   Should just lie down under all this hassle
   And let them walk all over me,
   Or, whether I should just say: `OK,
   I get the message,' and do myself in.
   I mean, let's face it, I'm in a no-win
   Situation, and quite honestly,
   I'm so stuffed up to here with the whole
   Stupid mess that, I can tell you, I've just
   Got a good mind to take the quick way out.
   That's the bottom line. The only problem is:
   What happens if I find that when I've bumped
   Myself off, there's some kind of a, you know,
   All that mystical stuff about when you die,
   You might find you're still _ know what I mean?
</TEXT>

</DOC>