<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0705EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AbortionRefugee     12-21 0509</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Abortion Refugee,0522</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Order May Help Refugee Fleeing Forced Abortions</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALAN FLIPPEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUFFALO, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Chinese man jailed after he and his
pregnant wife entered the United States illegally to flee a forced
abortion in China hopes a presidential order will bring him freedom.
   Li Jin Lin's case is one of the first in the nation to test
President Bush's directive that says fear of forced sterilization
or abortion can be considered as grounds for granting an alien
political asylum.
   The directive, though not specifically for Chinese, was part of
Bush's Nov. 30 order allowing many Chinese citizens to remain in
the United States indefinitely after the massacre of pro-democracy
demonstrators in Beijing.
   Li, 37, and his wife, Wang Sai Zhen, fled their hometown of
Fuzhou after she became pregnant with the couple's second child.
   Ms. Wang had been forced to have several abortions after the
birth of her first daughter, now 10, because Chinese law limits
most families to one child. She feared for her health if forced to
undergo another, said Patrick W.H. Wesp, Li's lawyer. The daughter
remains in China with relatives.
   The Lis entered the United States from Canada last March, but
the U.S. Immigration and Naturalization Service caught them in
Albany and returned Li, 37, to Canada. Ms. Wang, whose age was
unavailable, was allowed to remain because of her advanced
pregnancy and gave birth to a girl in New York City.
   Li and his nephew, Chun Kong Cheung, tried once more to get into
the United States, but border officers found them in the back of a
tractor-trailer at the Peace Bridge on Oct. 14, Wesp said.
   The couple now fears harassment and worse if they should be
returned to China, and their daughter could suffer even though she
is a U.S. citizen by virtue of her birth here, said Kathleen Rimar,
a lawyer representing them before the INS.
   ``Our research indicates that individuals who have had two
children face sterilization in China,'' Rimar said. ``The child
would never have any advantages in her life. She would be cut out
of schooling, any chance at a job.''
   She said Bush's directive ``doesn't grant people asylum but it
gives them a better shot if they can prove they would be forced to
abort or face sterilization.'' She added that it should apply even
though the Lis were caught before the order was issued.
   John J. Ingham, acting district director of the INS, said the
Lis are the first refugees in the Buffalo area to claim asylum
because of their country's family-planning laws. Rimar and Wesp
said that as far as they know, it is the first such case in the
country.
   Li and his nephew are in jail awaiting trial on criminal charges
of conspiracy to enter the United States illegally, Ingham said.
   He said the family should have requested political asylum at the
border, but Rimar said the Lis neither speak English nor understand
immigration law.
   ``They don't even know the word asylum,'' Rimar said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>