<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1105EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PornographyMayor     12-17 0650</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pornography Mayor,0668</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mayor Sparks Debate on Religion's Role at City Hall</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DWIGHT WOODWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RAVENNA, Ohio (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The mayor of this northeastern Ohio city
has been using city stationery to wage a religious battle against
pornography, a tactic critics say violates the principle of
separation of church and state.
   Mayor Donald J. Kainrad is a 37-year-old Roman Catholic and a
self-described born-again Christian who was elected in 1983. He
also heads a local citizens' group against pornography, and has
been sending letters to a national convenience store chain seeking
the removal of Playboy, Penthouse and other adult magazines from
four city stores.
   ``God cannot and will not bless the Dairy Mart corporation or
other businesses that willfully violate his commandment,'' Kainrad
wrote in a Sept. 28 letter to Charles Nirenberg, chairman of
Enfield, Conn.-based Dairy Mart Convenience Stores Inc.
   Nirenberg wrote back, informing Kainrad that a statewide survey
of people entering Dairy Mart stores showed they overwhelmingly
supported customers' rights to buy the magazines.
   The debate intensified after Nirenberg forwarded Kainrad's
letters to Simon, Porteous &amp; Associates Inc., of Great Barrington,
Mass. The non-profit company publishes The Freedom Writer, a
nationwide, 21,000-circulation newsletter that describes itself as
``the national newsletter that defends the separation of church and
state.''
   The newsletter's publisher, Skipp Porteous, a former Pentecostal
minister, threatened Kainrad with a federal lawsuit if Kainrad
continued to use city stationery for his anti-pornography campaign.
   ``He's using his elected position to endorse a religion. A
number of Supreme Court decisions say it's a clear violation of
church and state,'' said Porteous, who said he founded the
newsletter after his Christian zeal ebbed and he became worried
over fundamentalist Christians putting ``the Bible above the Bill
of Rights.''
   Kainrad said in an interview last week that he will stop using
city stationery to write to Dairy Mart and has asked Citizens for
Decency in Portage County, of which he is chairman, to print
stationery.
   However, he added, ``I have a very strong personal relationship
with God, with Jesus Christ. If someone asks me what I think of
pornography, I will respond on city stationery.
   ``As mayor, I'll continue to address my office as a Christian,''
Kainrad said. ``There is not a separation of church and state; I
don't believe that.''
   Kainrad, who displays the 23rd Psalm on his desk, waved a batch
of letters he said were from supporters and said he has received
numerous phone calls as well.
   The mayor also said he similarly wrote Revco, another national
drugstore chain, a few years ago. The chain was one of several that
withdrew adult magazines from its stores in 1986 after
letter-writing campaigns from religious and anti-pornography groups.
   City Councilman Eric Hellekson said Kainrad's mixing of his
personal views with his role as a mayor could set a bad precedent
for this quiet, rural town of 12,000 that lies just beyond Akron's
outer suburbs heading toward Amish country.
   ``My concern is the use of city facilities to support a group
not backed by the city,'' Hellekson said. ``The argument I have is
the use of city personnel making copies of letters. We don't know
if he's been doing a lot of copies and mailing them out around the
country.''
   At the Dairy Mart on Main Street, cashier Robin McElhiney, 19,
said of selling adult magazines: ``The people who buy them are
responsible. If somebody looks too young, we won't sell it.''
   Porteous said Kainrad's remarks that he will use non-city
stationery for future mailings is enough for him to drop his plans
for a lawsuit. He intends to feature the issue in the next edition
of Freedom Writer.
   However, Porteous said he will monitor Kainrad in November when
the mayor traditionally declares Thanksgiving week ``Bible Week.''
   ``I've made a note in my 1990 appointment book so we can head
him off at the pass,'' Porteous said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>