<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0224EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-ExciseTaxes     12-19 0437</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Excise Taxes,440</SECOND>
<HEAD>Excise Tax May be Sought on Recreational Gear, Vehicles</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bush administration's tentative plan to
seek new excise taxes on some recreational gear and vehicles can be
defended as a user fee _ not a new tax _ because the money would be
earmarked for a specific purpose, sources say.
   The revenue from such a tax would be used to pay for
conservation initiatives, administration sources said Monday night.
   President Bush on Monday told a group of reporters he expects
his 1991 budget proposal will let him keep his ``no new taxes''
pledge for a second year.
   Sources who sought anonymity told The Associated Press that some
officials opposed the idea of a recreational excise tax as a
violation of the president's pledge of ``no new taxes.'' One
source, however, argued that, ``These are true user fees.''
   Several sources said the tax could qualify as a user fee because
it is dedicated to a specific purpose.
   Quoting an Office of Management and Budget memorandum, The
Washington Post reported today the tax would range from 1 percent
to 2.5 percent on recreational and off-road vehicles, camping
equipment and pleasure boats, and would raise $275 million a year.
   Among the programs to receive funds from the initiative would be
new purchases of land for national parks and other protected areas,
and for the planting of trees, the newspaper said.
   One non-government source said he expected excise taxes to form
only part of a ``shopping list'' of financing for environmental
measures from which Congress could pick and choose.
   That source, Derek A. Crandall, president of the American
Recreation Coalition, said, ``We've been assured that any new taxes
... would be proposed only in conjunction with the recreation
community and in a cooperative venture,'' and that had not been
done.
   An existing excise tax of 10 percent on the import or wholesale
price of fishing tackle and pleasure boat fuel, with revenues going
to state fish and game departments, ``has worked very well,''
Crandall said.
   ``We've suggested this model might work in certain other
cases,'' he said.
   Sport firearms currently carry an 11 percent excise tax.
   The last such tax on vehicles, however, expired in 1971, a 7
percent levy on both cars and light trucks.
   Steven Goldstein, spokesman for the Interior Department, whose
National Park and Fish and Wildlife services would spend much of
the money, said Monday night, ``We are still working with OMB to
develop our budget for the 1991 fiscal year and it would be
inappropriate for the department to comment'' before the president
submits his budget on Jan. 22.
</TEXT>

</DOC>