<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1028EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Romania-China 1stLd-Writethru   12-27 0294</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-China, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0498,0300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chinese Leaders Congratulate New Romanian Government</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Inserts 1 graf after 4th pvs, `Thousands of...' to UPDATE with
portrayal of Romanian uprising in Chinese press. Pickup 5th, `Chinese President...'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chinese leaders today congratulated the new
leaders of Romania and expressed hope for good relations between
the countries.
   China on Tuesday effectively recognized the provisional
government that overthrew and executed President Nicolae Ceausescu
of Romania.
   Ceausescu was one of the few world leaders to praise China's
military crackdown of a pro-democracy movement in the spring, in
which hundreds and possibly thousands of people died.
   Thousands of people were killed in Romania last week after
Ceausescu deployed the military to crush anti-government
protesters. Ceausescu and his wife, Elena, were executed Christmas
Day.
   China's official press failed to report Ceausescu's overthrow
for more than a day, and it has since depicted the turmoil as a
struggle between pro- and anti-Ceausescu forces. It has provided
details of Ceausescu's execution and the establishment of a new
government but has not mentioned the extent of the popular uprising
or the depth of popular hatred for Ceausescu and his family.
   Chinese President Yang Shangkun, in a message to Ion Iliescu,
chairman of Romania's governing National Salvation Committee, said:
``On behalf of the government of the People's Republic of China and
in the name of myself, I congratulate you on your election as
chairman.''
   ``May the friendship between the people of China and Romania and
the friendly relations between the two countries continue to
develop,'' he added.
   Premier Li Peng sent a similar message to Romania's new premier,
Petre Roman.
   The Foreign Ministry said it would not interfere in Romania's
internal affairs and respects the choice made by the Romanian
people.
</TEXT>

</DOC>