<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1443EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Powell-TrialByFire 1stLd-Writethru a0550 12-23 0794</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Powell-Trial By Fire, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0550,760</SECOND>
<HEAD>Powell Steps Into New Leadership Role</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: SUBS 17th graf pvs, bgng: Powell was, to CORRECT Harlem to NYC
to conform to style</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSANNE M. SCHAFER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Military Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After an all-night vigil in the Pentagon ``war
room'' as last week's Panama invasion began, Defense Secretary Dick
Cheney and Gen. Colin Powell emerged at 7:45 a.m. to explain the
still-unfolding operation.
   Standing before a packed room of reporters and cameras, Cheney
laid out the reasoning behind President Bush's decision and then
stood aside to watch the youngest-ever chairman of the Joint Chiefs
of Staff provide a half-hour, detailed breakdown of the most
massive military operation since the Vietnam War.
   Speaking at length without notes about the complex influx of
soldiers and their varied missions, Powell made sure to offer the
cameras a ``sound bite,'' colorfully pronouncing Gen. Manuel
Antonio Noriega's supporters ``thugs and rabble rousers'' and
declaring, ``This reign of terror is over.''
   Even though the deposed dictator had eluded his military
opponents, the 52-year-old Powell vowed, ``We will chase him and we
will find him.''
   ``It's been some years since Mr. Noriega ... has been living in
the jungle. ... I'm not quite sure he's up to being chased around
the countryside by Army Rangers, Special Forces and Light Infantry
Units,'' the four-star general said.
   Powell, the first black to hold the post as the nation's highest
military officer, had shied away from media attention during his
first four months as the new chairman of the Joint Chiefs, telling
his associates, ``I need to get to know my job.''
   Then at Bush's order he organized the shipment of 26,000 troops
into Panama _ and the spotlight couldn't have been more intense.
   By all accounts, Powell has won the applause of his Pentagon
colleagues.
   The praise has been so constant, in fact, that when a senior
Pentagon official was asked to say something negative about the
four-star general, the civilian jokingly replied, ``He's Army.''
   Powell has appeared a bit weary and puffy-faced in recent days
as he has met with reporters _ usually with Cheney at his side _ to
explain the military action that toppled Noriega from power.
   Pentagon spokesman Pete Williams, who has sat in on many of
Cheney's meetings with Powell, says the general ``has a good public
relations sense.'' Powell honed those skills as the top military
aide to one-time Pentagon chief Caspar Weinberger, and during his
White House years as the deputy national security adviser to Frank
Carlucci, whose post he later held.
   The chairman ``has been good about letting his staff speak,''
Williams said, pointing to the near-daily briefings held by Lt.
Gen. Tom Kelly, the director of operations for the Joint Chiefs and
Rear Adm. Ted Sheafer, the JCS chief of intelligence.
   But Williams said that when the general ``makes a decision,
that's it, he's unequivocal.
   ``He doesn't let things get out of hand,'' Williams said,
adding, ``I don't think I've ever heard him yell _ let alone raise
his voice.''
   Powell is regarded among his fellows as thoughtful and precise,
as well as an officer who shows little favoritism toward his own
branch of service, the Army.
   ``Colin not only is smart, he thinks smart,'' said a senior Navy
official. ``He may be career Army, but he is the least biased
toward his own service than anybody I know.''
   Powell was born in New York City, the son of Jamaican
immigrants. He distinguished himself as the best infantry
instructor at Fort Benning, Ga., in the mid-1960s and won a bronze
star and purple heart in Vietnam.
   He became a White House fellow and later became Weinberger's
senior military assistant.
   Powell was chosen for the nation's highest military post by Bush
this fall, shortly after he had been put in charge of Forces
Command at Fort McPherson, Ga., overseeing the nation's 1 million
U.S.-based troops.
   The president, impressed with Powell during their frequent White
House contacts, picked Powell over many other military men with
broader military experience and advanced age.
   The chairman played a major role in urging Bush and the Joint
Chiefs to adopt the maximum military option for dealing with the
Panamanian situation, one longtime Pentagon official said.
   ``He really has switched roles,'' the Powell acquaintance said,
noting that Powell in his National Security Council days was loathe
to take up State Department demands for more military involvement
in Central America.
   The break-point in the administration's approach to Noriega came
after the shooting of an unarmed Marine last Saturday, and Powell
began preparing to offer the president a range of military options
shortly thereafter, one of the senior Pentagon official's said.
   ``He was in on it from the very first,'' the official said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>