<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0267 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1609EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Dollar-Gold     12-22 0560</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dollar-Gold,0579</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar Lower; Gold Mixed</HEAD>
<HEAD>Precede LONDON-BC</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dollar tumbled Friday in abbreviated
pre-Christmas foreign-exchange trading, weighed down by continuing
demand for the West German mark and expectations that U.S. interest
rates are headed lower.
   Gold prices edged higher in New York after turning in a mixed
performance overseas. Republic National Bank in New York quoted an
after-hours bid for a troy ounce of gold at $413.75 as of 1 p.m.
EST, up from $412.20 late Thursday.
   Traders said the dollar was little affected by the continuing
U.S. intervention in Panama and the fall Friday of Nicolae
Ceausescu, the long-time Romanian leader.
   The currency markets finished the trading day at around midday,
several hours earlier than normal as traders got a headstart on the
three-day holiday weekend.
   ``The dollar traded in a range early and fell off late in the
session,'' said Jeff Mondschein, managing director of foreign
exchange for Continental Bank in Chicago.
   But he cautioned against reading much into the decline, saying
trading was so light that a few orders were all that was needed to
move the market.
   The underlying factors that have affected the dollar for the
past few days _ a weakening U.S. economy and the expectation that
interest rates are headed lower _ continued to depress the
currency, Mondschein said. Falling interest rates hurt the dollar
by cutting yields foreigners can get on dollar-denominated
investments.
   In Europe, dealers said the dollar was hurt by the strength of
the mark and said that as the dollar fell below the 1.7250-mark
level, dealers who had instructions from some customers to sell
dollars at that level began executing those orders.
   But trading activity also was curtailed in Europe, as most major
banks cut the trading day short in advance of the Christmas holiday.
   In Tokyo, the dollar fell 0.10 Japanese yen to close at 143.67
yen. Later, in London, the dollar was quoted at 143.05 yen. In New
York, the dollar fell to 142.35 yen from 143.65 yen late Thursday.
   The dollar also lost ground against the British pound. In
London, the pound rose to $1.6205 from $1.6125 late Thursday.
Sterling rose to $1.62425 in New York from $1.6145 late Thursday.
   Selected dollar rates in New York, compared with late rates
Thursday, included: 1.7070 West German marks, down from 1.7260;
1.5490 Swiss francs, down from 1.5580; 5.8345 French francs, down
from 5.8910; 1,277.75 Italian lire, down from 1,285.50; and 1.1592
Canadian dollars, down from 1.1597.
   Other afternoon dollar rates in Europe, compared with late rates
Thursday, included: 1.7090 West German marks, down from 1.7250;
1.5475 Swiss francs, down from 1.5575; 5.8385 French francs, down
from 5.8955; 1.9330 Dutch guilders, down from 1.9560; 1,277.75
Italian lire, down from 1,287.50; and 1.1585 Canadian dollars, down
from 1.1605.
   On New York's Commodity Exchange, gold for current delivery rose
$1.30 a troy ounce to $413.20.
   Earlier, gold fell to a late bid of $412.25 a troy ounce in
London, down from $412.75 late Thursday. In Zurich, Switzerland,
the metal finished at $413 an ounce for the third session in a row.
   Gold rose 33 cents in Hong Kong to close at $411.69 an ounce.
   Silver rose 1.7 cents a troy ounce to $5.560 on the Comex in New
York. Silver rose in London to a late bid of $5.58 a troy ounce
from Thursday's $5.57.
</TEXT>

</DOC>