<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0221 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2019EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-President     12-20 0657</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-President,0676</SECOND>
<HEAD>May Winner Becomes December President, Leader of Uneasy Coalition</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALINA GUERRERO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Guillermo Endara, sworn in Wednesday
as Panama's president after a U.S. invasion, remains a gentle,
unassuming law professor despite his long struggle with his enemy,
Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   Endara's eight-party opposition coalition united to oppose
Noriega in elections held on May 7. Noriega supporters first tried
to steal the election for his handpicked candidate, Carlos Duque,
then annulled it.
   When the vote count was halted Endara's Democratic Opposition
Alliance ticket had a 3-1 lead over Duque, according to
international observers who included former President Jimmy Carter.
   ``Our aspiration is justice, democracy and liberty,'' said
Endara in a Wednesday broadcast on a clandestine radio network. He
said that President Bush had promised U.S. troops would be removed
as early as possible.
   Opposition party officials persisted in calling Endara ``Mister
President-elect,'' maintaining that the annulment was illegal.
After Sept. 1, when Endara would have taken office, he was referred
to as ``Mister President,'' and U.S. officials followed suit.
   The staying power of Panama's opposition has always been
questioned _ Noriega said they just wanted to make money in peace
and would fold under serious challenge.
   Endara, of the Liberal Authentic Party, and his two running
mates, Ricardo Arias Calderon of the Christian Democratic Party and
Guillermo Ford of the National Liberal Republican Movement, formed
an uneasy alliance whose only unifying theme was the defeat of
Noriega.
   Arias was by far the most popular in Panama, but he was also the
most disliked by others. He clearly felt he deserved the
presidential domination but swallowed hard and took the first
vice-presidential slot.
   Second vice-presidential candidate Ford, a businessman, turned
out to be the most charismatic of the three, showing an earthy,
common touch despite his wealth as he developed a showman's style.
   One problem the three will have to surmount is the way they took
office. Many who disapproved of Noriega will also disapprove of
open, massive United States intervention, and critics say depending
on ``Big Brother'' to solve all problems is a sign of weak
character.
   The three stayed out of sight all day Wednesday. Their
statements were broadcast on a radio network anchored by Bosco
Ricardo Vallarino from ``a strategic point in Panama.'' It was
thought the point had to be on a U.S. base because Vallarino is a
well-known Noriega opponent and faced censure from Noriega
supporters.
   It was still uncertain how the tensions and compromises will
work in practice, but Endara and his running mates established
their willingness to sacrifice when men wearing Noriega's ``Dignity
Battalion'' T-shirts beat them during a May 10 protest
demonstration.
   The spectacle of Endara, Arias and Ford being beaten bloody by
pipe-wielding thugs flashed around the world in a scene that
stamped Noriega as the leader of a brutal regime. Endara spent his
53rd birthday in a hospital bed.
   ``They were not battalions and they have no dignity,'' Endara
said in a hospital interview as supporters held up his bloodied
guayabera, a short-sleeved, smock-type shirt favored by many Latins.
   He staged a hunger strike that occasioned brutal jests about
diets from pro-Noriega newspapers because of his heft.
   Endara's opposition activities date back more than two decades,
to when he served in the National Assembly under Arnulfo Arias
Madrid, Panama's grand old man of the opposition.
   He was Arias' spokesman in Panama until Arias died in Miami in
1988 in self-imposed exile. He used to speak, almost dreamily, of
the day when Arias would return ``as a sign of providence'' to lead
the country.
   Endara's wife, Marcella, died earlier this year. They had a
daughter, also named Marcella.
   Arias, 52, is president of the Christian Democratic Party. He
was a professor of philosophy at the University of Panama; he and
his wife Teresa have three children.
   Ford, 53, and his wife Dora have two children.
</TEXT>

</DOC>