<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1109EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-MoscowEmbassy 2ndLd-Writethru a0465 12-21 0753</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Moscow Embassy, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0465,680</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Expects Cooperation From Soviets for a New Embassy in Moscow</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Inserts graf 11, Critics of, with allegation location of Soviet
embassy would be good spot to monitor communications.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BARRY SCHWEID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Diplomatic Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The State Department, citing ``changing
conditions'' in the Soviet Union, is giving high priority to
constructing a new U.S. Embassy in Moscow to replace the one to be
razed after years of indecision.
   The job could cost up to $500 million. Nicholas Salgo, a former
U.S. ambassador to Hungary, was assigned Wednesday to hold formal
negotiations with the Kremlin. In the meantime, the Soviets will
continue to be shut out of their new embassy in the Mt. Alto
section of Washington and relegated to an older mansion near the
White House.
   Ever since U.S. intelligence 10 years ago detected what was said
to be a network of sophisticated listening devices in the Moscow
embassy, U.S. officials have pondered what to do with the $95
million building.
   Finally, on Wednesday, Secretary of State James A. Baker III
notified key members of Congress the embassy will be torn down and
a new one constructed in its place.
   Baker, who sent Salgo and Ivan Selin, the undersecretary of
state for management, to Moscow on an inspection trip in April,
passed up the option of saving millions of dollars by demolishing
only floors believed to be infested with ``bugs'' and salvaging
others.
   He also rejected the option of constructing an annex for
top-secret business. That would have involved at least two
problems: finding the space and creating an assumption that whoever
entered the annex was involved in sensitive operations.
   ``The decision was taken after a careful review of the
alternatives for dealing with the bugged new building,'' the State
Department said in a press release Wednesday night.
   ``The review showed that, among the realistic alternatives, the
teardown-rebuild option offered the optimum combination of
security, space, cost and time required for rebuilding,'' the
statement added.
   The embassy was built under a 1972 agreement made by the Nixon
administration that allowed the Soviets to prefabricate off-site
the concrete slabs for the building. U.S. officials did not insist
on a right of inspection.
   The agreement also provided for a new Soviet embassy in the Mt.
Alto section of Washington, one of the highest points in the U.S.
capital. It was built, but the Soviets were kept from occupying it
while a decision on the Moscow embassy was pending.
   Critics of the arrangement said Americans gave away valuable
real estate that also put the Soviets in a good spot to monitor
communications through listening devices. The Soviets, however,
have not been able to occupy their new building until the problems
with the Moscow embassy are solved.
   ``Soviet occupancy of their new chancery building at Mt. Alto
remains linked to our occupancy of a new building in Moscow,'' the
statement said.
   It said there was progress in preliminary talks with Soviet
officials and added, ``We look forward to working with the Congress
and getting on with the project.''
   ``The changing conditions in the Soviet Union have made
resolution of this issue very high among our foreign policy
priorities,'' it said.
   In April, Salgo and Selin reported to Baker that building an
annex would be cheaper than the estimated $500 million cost of
building a new embassy.
   Former President Reagan last year advocated razing the building,
saying the United States had ``no choice.'' But he left a decision
to Bush.
   The State Department said it will ask Congress in the next
budget for $270 million for initial building costs. It also said
the United States will press claims against the Soviets to recover
damages for implanting eavesdropping devices in the building and
for shoddy workmanship.
   Meanwhile, a trade group headed by Dwayne O. Andreas, chairman
of Archer Daniels Midland Co., offered to buy the building for use
as business offices.
   Andreas is co-chairman of the U.S.-USSR Trade and Economic
Council, which promotes trade between the two superpowers. He made
the offer on behalf of a consortium of U.S. companies, which would
have used the building as a Moscow headquarters.
   Baker's decision surfaced first on Capitol Hill where it was
disclosed by the office of Rep. Olympia Snowe, R-Maine.
   ``I am extremely pleased that the Bush administration has given
final approval to the total reconstruction of our bugged embassy
building in Moscow,'' Snowe's office said. ``Our goal now must be
to move quickly to build a secure facility.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>