<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0143EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-NoriegaandCeausescu Bjt   12-29 0681</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Noriega and Ceausescu, Bjt,680</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON TODAY: Two Tyrants, Eerie Parallels</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   On the surface, Panama's Manuel Antonio
Noriega and Romania's Nicolae Ceausescu had little in common aside
from the heavy-handed way in which they ran their respective
countries.
   One was a tropical tyrant for whom ideology meant nothing. The
other, irreverently described as the ``butcher of Bucharest,''
viewed the world in terms of the Marxist philosophy he had embraced
as a teen-ager.
   But there are some eerie parallels between the two, not the
least of which was the way the ups and downs in their relations
with the United States reflected the fluctuations of U.S. policy
between expediency and morality.
   One historical oddity was that both Ceausescu and Noriega had
their definitive falling out with the United States on the same day
_ Feb. 26, 1988. Last week, their tyrannical rules ended within two
days of each other.
   When both were riding high, there were periods in which the
United States overlooked their more disreputable qualities in
pursuit of its anti-Soviet policies. In the end, once their
usefulness had been squandered, both were widely reviled in
Washington for the way in which they had brutalized their
respective peoples.
   Ceausescu had been an admired figure in Washington during the
1970's. President Nixon visited Bucharest early in his first term
and Ceausescu was given a red carpet welcome by President Carter at
the White House in 1978.
   All this was Washington's way of showing gratitude to a man
viewed as a maverick in the Warsaw Pact for his willingness to
adopt stands independent of the Soviet Union.
   He denounced the Soviet invasion of Czechoslovakia, maintained
normal ties with Israel at a time when no other Pact member did,
refused to take part in alliance military maneuvers and extended
the hand of friendship to China when Moscow and Beijing were at
loggerheads.
   The United States offered Romania trade concessions and export
credits as part of a strategy to encourage other alliance members
to show independence from Moscow. Ceausescu's Stalinist internal
policies were a secondary consideration.
   Noriega, meanwhile, also was being cultivated by the United
States during the latter part of the 1970s when he was Panama's
chief of military intelligence.
   He was viewed as an intelligence asset, providing the United
States with information on Cuban activities in Central America. In
the 1980s, Noriega was considered a potential asset for the Reagan
administration in its effort to topple Nicaragua's leftist
government. How much assistance he actually provided is not clear.
   U.S. officials were aware that Noriega was involved in
drug-smuggling activities but felt he was minor figure before
becoming head of the Defense Forces in August 1983. In that same
year, then-Vice President George Bush met with Noriega during a
visit to Panama.
   The deterioration in relations with Panama accelerated after
Noriega's indictment by two Florida grand juries on drug smuggling
charges in early February 1988. The definitive break occurred Feb.
26, when his allies in the Panamanian legislature impeached
President Eric Arturo Delvalle just hours after he attempted to
fire Noriega as defense chief.
   Hours later on that same day, the State Department disclosed
that Ceausescu had unilaterally renounced the trade privileges
Romania had had for more than a decade. If Ceausescu had not taken
the action, Congress would have done so, primarily based on
Romania's tight restrictions on emigration.
   In any case, Romania's usefulness as a Warsaw Pact maverick had
steadily diminished with rise of Mikhail Gorbachev in the Soviet
Union and the waning of the Cold War. When Ceausescu fled last
Friday, on the morning following the calendar's longest night of
the year, he was increasingly looked on as an anachronism.
   A final parallel between Ceausescu and Noriega: at the precise
moment Ceausescu was fleeing the presidential palace, across the
Atlantic, the Organization of American States, after an all-night
session, was expressing regret by an overwhelming vote over the
U.S. decision to oust Noriega by force.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   George Gedda has covered foreign affairs for The
Associated Press since 1968.
</TEXT>

</DOC>