<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 0036EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-JudgeConvicted 2ndLd-Writethru a0674 12-17 0774</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Judge Convicted, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0674,0796</SECOND>
<HEAD>County Judge Convicted of Bribery, Acquitted of Lewdness</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: ADDS 2 grafs after final graf pvs with juror denying he disagreed
with verdict. No pickup.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID S. MARTIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EBENSBURG, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A suspended county judge accused of
running the rural courthouse like a fiefdom was convicted of
bribery and official oppression Saturday but acquitted of open
lewdness and three other counts.
   Suspended Cambria County Judge Joseph F. O'Kicki, who rose from
poverty to win his first judicial election 18 years ago, showed no
emotion as the verdicts were read after 16{ hours of deliberations
over two days.
   O'Kicki faces a maximum term of 26 years and $57,500 in fines.
No sentencing date has been set. On sentencing, he will lose his
$80,000-a-year job and his pension.
   O'Kicki said he will appeal.
   ``This verdict today is a sad day for the justice system in
Pennsylvania,'' O'Kicki said. ``The sad day for O'Kicki was Oct. 8,
1988, when he was suspended.''
   Prosecutors said the 59-year-old judge used fear and favors to
rule the elegant 19th-century courthouse in the foothills of the
southern Allegheny Mountains in eastern Pennsylvania.
   O'Kicki maintained that the charges were prompted by his feud
with a Johnstown political power broker who has family ties to the
lieutenant governor.
   The judge was convicted of six counts involving the acceptance
of $500 from a court employee for a promotion that never came;
asking a Johnstown attorney for $500 after a favorable ruling; and
demanding a favorable settlement on a bank loan.
   Charges included official oppression, demanding property to
secure employment, criminal coercion and bribery. All are felonies.
   He was acquitted of charges of requiring court employees perform
personal chores for him on county time, of open lewdness for
allegedly asking two secretaries into his office while he was
wearing only his underwear, of using inside information about an
estate in a money-making scheme and of seeking a bribe from a
Johnstown strip-mining company.
   O'Kicki also faces a second trial on 16 additional charges
focusing on private business dealings. No date has been set for
that trial.
   The prosecution and defense called 82 witnesses and introduced
nearly 200 pieces of evidence. Testimony began Nov. 7.
   O'Kicki, who prided himself on streamlining the county's civil
court system, was suspended by the state Supreme Court in June 1988
and was indicted in March.
   During two days of testimony, O'Kicki blamed his legal troubles
on Johnstown millionaire W.E. Schonek, the politically influential
father-in-law of Lt. Gov. Mark Singel.
   According to O'Kicki, the millionaire was angry at him for
encouraging Schonek's brother, Rudolph, to make a stock gift worth
more than $200,000 to St. Francis College in Loretto.
   O'Kicki said Schonek yelled threats at him about the gift in
1987 at a Johnstown-Cambria County Airport restaurant.
   Schonek and Singel have denied influencing the investigation.
   Northampton County Judge Richard Grifo, who presided over the
seven-week trial, told the jury that the investigators' motives
were irrelevant.
   O'Kicki sat impassively through the testimony with his second
wife, Sylvia, at his side, but he said the trial was physically,
emotionally and intellectually devastating.
   On the stand, O'Kicki denied the charges as his attorney asked
him about them one by one, answering many of the allegations, ``No,
absolutely no.''
   He broke down in tears once when he referred to his empty home
following his divorce from his first wife, Theresa, in 1986.
   After unsuccessful bids for district attorney's office and
Congress, O'Kicki, a Democrat, was elected judge in 1971 by
defeating the endorsed Democratic candidate in the primary and then
winning the general election.
   He won a retention election for a second 10-year term in 1981
and was elected president of the Pennsylvania Conference of Trial
Court Judges two years later.
   O'Kicki reached the pinnacle of his success in June 1988 by
becoming president of the five-judge county court but a state
investigation into his dealings already was under way.
   Defense attorney Richard Galloway indicated that in the appeal,
he will make an issue of the trial judge's refusal to declare a
mistrial after an unusual development.
   When jurors were asked to state their verdicts individually,
James C. Miller of Johnstown said he disagreed with the other 11
jurors on three of the six convictions. Although an unanimous
verdict is required, Grifo rejected Galloway's mistrial request,
saying he didn't hear any discrepencies.
   Miller, reached at home afterward, said he agreed with the other
jurors' conclusions, although it appeared to courtroom witnesses he
had disagreed when the jury was polled.
   ``I absolutely did,'' he said when asked if he concurred in the
guilty verdicts.
</TEXT>

</DOC>