<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0134 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1353EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-Panama-Marriott 1stLd-Writethru a0688 12-20 0469</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Marriott, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0688,430</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hotel Officials Pressing U.S. Government for Protection</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: CORRECTS spelling to Conner sted Connor in grafs 4, The remainder,
and 8, Conner said</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Officials of the Marriott Corp. said today
they were pressing the U.S. government to ensure the safety of
guests at a luxury hotel in downtown Panama City after several
people were taken from the building by Panamanian troops.
   The 400-room Marriott Hotel, which employs 300 people, was about
42 perce Tuesday when Panamanian military troops
came to the facility, according to Roger Conner, a spokesman for
Betent occupied lathesda, Md.-based Marriott.
   Although Conner said details were sketchy, it was his
understanding that ``Panamanian military forces had come into our
hotel and seized an undetermined amount of people.'' He said a
handful of journalists, as well as several employees, were taken
from the hotel early this morning by Panamanian troops.
   The remainder of the guests were accommodated in the hotel
ballroom, Conner said.
   Pentagon spokesman Pete Williams said U.S. forces in Panama were
aware of hostages taken from the Marriott Hotel and that some
Americans were still at liberty in the building.
   ``We will make efforts to take care of that,'' said Williams.
But he declined to say whether American troops were moving guests in a
situation that was ``just like when an earthquake hits ... Everyone
makes do.''
   ``Operations are not normal,'' he said, but he did not think the
hotel guests were under guard by Panamanian military officials.
   The hotel's general manager, Sapinder Palta, was at a meeting in
Fort Lauderdale, Fla., today but had been in touch with the hotel
by telephone, Conner said. Other hotel officials, including
Marriott Hotels President Bill Tiesel, were trying to get through
to the hotel, but having little success, Conner said.
   But the hotel officials had been in touch with the U.S.
government. ``From Marriott's standpoint, we are taking every
effort to have the U.S. military troops secure the hotel so that
guests can be protected,'' he said.
   The hotel, the Panama Marriott Caesar Park, is owned by Aoki
Construction Inc., a Japanese company, but it is managed by
Marriott. Opened in 1982, the hotel is adjacent to the Atlapa
Convention Center five minutes from the banking center of Panama
City.
   At the time of the U.S. invasion of Panama, most of the guests
were journalists and airline crews, Conner said. There were few
businessmen in the hotel, he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>