<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0172 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1936EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Shevardnadze 1stLd-Writethru a0626 12-18 0702</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Shevardnadze, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0626,0722</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Union Signs Major Agreement to Expand European Trade</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: 7 grafs SUB for 5th graf, He said ... UPDATING with banquet,
quotes. Picks up 6th, `French Foreign ... with minor editing to trim, conform</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Czechoslovakia, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SALLY JACOBSEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRUSSELS, Belgium (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard A.
Shevardnadze signed a far-reaching trade agreement with the
European Community on Monday, a major step toward getting needed
Western help for his nation's ailing economy.
   On Tuesday, Shevardnadze will pay an unprecedented visit to the
North Atlantic Treaty Organization, the center of the Western
military alliance.
   He called the 10-year accord _ the first between Moscow and the
12-nation trading bloc _ ``truly innovative.''
   ``Its nature reflects the dynamism of the process of renewal in
Europe,'' he said.
   He later had what was described as a relaxed dinner with the 12
EC foreign ministers. ``He was like a colleague we have known for
many years,'' said Belgium's foreign minister, Mark Eyskens.
   Hans van den Broek, the Dutch minister, said Shevardnadze
discussed the upheaval in Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union's own
economic reform program, among other issues.
   ``His message was: `We do not deny the (economic) situation is
difficult, but grant us more time,''' Van den Broek said.
   On Eastern Europe, ``he was so far as to say that had the
reforms occurred a few years ago, it could have happened with fewer
shocks,'' he added.
   Van den Broek said Shevardnadze lauded Western leaders for
insisting that change must come in Europe but not at the expense of
stability. West German sources said the same point was made at a
separate meeting Shevardnadze had with Foreign Minister
Hans-Dietrich Genscher of West Germany.
   The Soviet minister said the trade and economic cooperation
agreement he signed at a ceremony at EC headquarters would help
overcome the division of the European continent.
   He said it ``gives food for collective thinking'' about creating
an ``economic complex on our Continent.''
   French Foreign Minister Roland Dumas, whose country holds the
community's rotating presidency, hailed the arrangement as
``facilitating the integration of the Soviet Union into the world
economy.''
   Frans Andriessen, the community's top-ranking trade official,
cautioned that the pact's success depended on Soviet efforts to
achieve a more market-oriented economy.
   The agreement will gradually get rid of most import quotas on
agricultural and industrial products from the Soviet Union and set
out closer cooperation in areas including nuclear energy and
safety, financial services, environmental protection and management
training.
   In return, the Kremlin has promised to give Western European
businesses greater access to its potentially enormous consumer
market.
   ``Now the agreement is to be put into practice,'' Shevardnadze
said. ``We are ready for it and we intend to continue to work in
earnest, keeping up the high tempo and the spirit of creative
cooperation.''
   He said he did not request the meeting with NATO
Secretary-General Manfred Woerner, but ``simply raised the
question'' of whether there would be a chance to visit the alliance.
   ``We have to take the first step even if the fleets are facing
each other,'' he said.
   He said he had ``no particular hidden thoughts visiting NATO.''
   Questioned about whether the Kremlin intended to join the
Western alliance, he joked he would take a look Tuesday and
``decide whether it's worth joining up now.''
   He made a pitch for dismantling the Western group of 17 nations
formed to keep sensitive technology out of the hands of the East
bloc nations. But he said easing its restrictions was up to the
United States, the key partner in the Western drive.
   The accord is the fourth the community has negotiated with
Eastern European countries since it established in June 1988 formal
ties with the socialist economic bloc, the Council for Mutual
Economic Assistance.
   The community has trade and economic cooperation accords with
Poland and Hungary and a smaller one with Czechoslovakia. It is
discussing pacts with Bulgaria and East Germany.
   The Soviet Union imported about $11 billion in goods from the
community in 1987, while the trading bloc bought nearly $16 billion
from Moscow. Total trade between the community and Eastern Europe
amounted to about $56 billion in 1987.
</TEXT>

</DOC>