<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0322EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-SocialistMaverick 1stLd-Writethru   12-20 0704</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Socialist Maverick, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0463,670</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romanian Unrest May be Beginning of End for Ceausescu, Analysts Say</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 8th graf, bgng: The current xxx to CORRECT that Brasov
is not near Timisoara or Arad.</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRYAN BRUMLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The unrest in Romania may be the beginning of
the end for strongman Nicolae Ceausescu, who was hailed 24 years
ago as a Soviet bloc maverick but is increasingly denounced for his
repressive policies.
   ``We are definitely in the twilight of the Ceausescu era,'' said
F. Stephen Larabee, vice president of the Institute for East-West
Security Studies in New York.
   The Soviet foreign minister and the White House both condemned
Ceausescu's use of violence to crush demonstrations in the Romanian
city of Timisoara, where according to some reports as many as 400
people died.
   But Ceausescu, who has ruled Romania with an iron hand since
1965, ``is going to be a harder nut to crack'' than communist
leaders swept from power in the Soviet bloc nations of Poland, East
Germany, Hungary, Czechoslovakia and Bulgaria, said James Brown, a
specialist in East European affairs at the RAND Corp. in Los
Angeles.
   Romania has been a maverick in the Soviet camp for decades _
boycotting Warsaw Pact exercises, trading with the West against
Kremlin wishes and most recently balking at the democratic reforms
of Mikhail S. Gorbachev.
   Although Ceausescu may be able to survive in the short term, his
days seem numbered, said Larabee, Brown and other analysts.
   ``This incident or some other might open up an explosion of
popular dissent, or some group in the leadership, such as the
military, may decide to get rid of him. Sometime or another,
something has to give,'' said Raymond Garthoff, a former U.S.
ambassador to Bulgaria and now a senior scholar at the Brookings
Institution in Washington.
   The current unrest in Romania began as a reaction to repressions
against the Hungarian minority in the nearby cities of Timisoara
and Arad, along with the more distant city of Brasov, but reports
indicate that ethnic Romanians may have joined the demonstrations.
Experts say that is bad news for Ceausescu.
   Ceausescu was once a favorite of U.S. leaders because he refused
to allow Romanian troops to join Warsaw Pact military maneuvers,
was the only Soviet bloc leader to maintain full relations with
Israel and traded with Western nations against the wishes of
Moscow. In 1969, then-President Richard Nixon went to Romania in
the first U.S. state visit to a Soviet bloc nation.
   Ceausesu's widely reported human rights abuses chilled
U.S.-Romanian relations, however, and the United States last year
withdrew trade favors from Romania, costing that nation as much as
$250 million annually.
   White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater harshly criticized
Romania on Tuesday.
   ``The United States condemns the brutal use of police force by
the Romanian government against protesters in Timisoara and other
cities,'' Fitzwater told reporters.
   Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard A. Shevardnadze said that if the
reports of bloodshed were true, ``I can only express my very
profound regret. We are categorically opposed to the use of force.''
   Romania has been a maverick since the late 1950s when
Ceausescu's predecessor rejected a Kremlin plan to more closely
integrate the Romanian economy into Soviet bloc by selling Moscow
and its allies oil and other natural resources. Instead, the
Romanians sold their oil to the West and used the money to
industrialize.
   Ceausescu became party leader in 1965 and refused to allow
Romanian forces to take part in Warsaw Pact exercises.
   He was the only Warsaw Pact leader to refuse to take part in the
1968 Soviet-led invasion of Czechoslovakia. He denounced the Soviet
invasion of Afghanistan in 1979 and refused to join the Soviet bloc
boycott of the 1984 Olympic Games in Los Angeles.
   Throughout that period, the Romanians took advantage of the
Sino-Soviet dispute, playing Moscow off against Beijing. As reforms
have swept Eastern Europe, Ceausescu has kept close ties with
conservatives in Beijing and counts as his closest allies hardline
communist leaders in China, North Korea and Cuba, Brown said.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Bryan Brumley, a former Associated Press
correspondent in Warsaw and Moscow, writes on national security
affairs from Washington.
</TEXT>

</DOC>