<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0152 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0528EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DigestBriefs     12-27 0716</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Digest Briefs,0740</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Justice Department is moving to freeze the
foreign assets of Manuel Antonio Noriega, as U.S. officials press
for custody of the deposed Panamanian dictator hiding in the
Vatican Embassy in Panama City.
   David Runkel, a Justice Department spokesman, said attorneys
today would ask officials in about a half-dozen countries,
primarily in Europe, to freeze the cash that Noriega took out of
Panama.
   ``The papers will be filed with the respective agencies of
government which control the financial institutions,'' he said.
   He refused to identify the countries where Noriega is believed
to have hidden more than $10 million in ``illegal drug money.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The provisional government today set
up military tribunals to try members of the vicious security police
of Nicoleau Ceausescu, who denied right up until a firing squad
executed him that he ruled by terror.
   State television, headquarters for the mix of dissidents,
disaffected government officials and army commanders who are
running the country, on Tuesday night broadcast footage of
Ceausescu at his secret military trial.
   The 40-minute videotape showed an unrepentant man refusing to
acknowledge either the severe hardship he forced on the Romanian
people or the massacre of thousands of people by his security
forces.
   ``Everything that was said here is false, and I don't want to
talk anymore,'' the man who ruled Romania for 24 years told his
accusers. He insisted he was still in power.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Securities and Exchange Commission,
catapulted into the headlines by its pursuit of multimillion-dollar
insider trading scandals, is putting out the word that it intends
to be just as aggressive in protecting small investors.
   SEC Chairman Richard Breeden is creating a new fraud unit at the
SEC designed to police the sale of securities by savings and loan
institutions.
   Investigators have charged that some small investors lost their
life savings when they bought securities sold by S&amp;L branches in
the mistaken belief that their investments were protected by
federal deposit insurance.
   ``We intend to see to it that when people are sold securities,
they are provided all the necessary information,'' Breeden said.
   Breeden also announced Tuesday that he had selected William R.
McLucas, a 12-year SEC veteran, to be the new director of
enforcement at the SEC. He will succeed Gary Lynch, who resigned in
July after supervising such landmark insider trading cases as the
investigation of Ivan Boesky and the Wall Street firm of Drexel
Burnham Lambert Inc.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>ORLANDO, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Orange juice prices leaped on the futures
market after a weekend freeze overwhelmed Florida and Texas citrus
groves, but experts said consumers may escape big price increases
because of a bumper crop in Brazil.
   However, Big Chill '89 likely will drive up vegetable prices in
the Northeast because the cold wiped out thousands of acres of
carrots, cauliflower, broccoli and other crops in Florida,
agriculture officials said.
   Experts assessing the damage Tuesday said it was too early for
definite predictions about prices. U.S. Agriculture Department
economist Ralph Parlett in Washington said price increases were
likely, but he hadn't changed his earlier forecast of a 3 percent
to 5 percent overall rise in food prices in 1990.
   In Florida, where the citrus industry is worth an estimated $3.5
billion a year, the Christmas cold wave struck with about 80
percent of the citrus crop still on the trees, and there was heavy
icing of oranges and grapefruit. In Texas, an estimated 65 percent
of the crop _ or $55 million worth wholesale _ was still on the
trees, according to growers and farm officials.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>ROLFE, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Penny Hollis left New Hampshire last summer
and bought a home in this farm belt town so fast that she didn't
notice the major landmark: a grain elevator.
   ``I thought, `Elevator, what's so special about an elevator?
Isn't that what goes up and down in department stores?''' she
recalled.
   Hoping to save its businesses and its school, Rolfe put out a
national invitation two years ago, offering a free lot and $1,200
cash to anyone who builds a house worth $30,000.
   About 70 people have accepted the invitation, increasing the
population by almost 10 percent. Their 20 children padded school
enrollment to 190.
</TEXT>

</DOC>