<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0148 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1747EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-PentagonSpending 1stLd-Writethru a0609 12-29 0899</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pentagon Spending, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0609,880</SECOND>
<HEAD>Navy `Robbing Peter to Pay Paul' For 1991 Budget</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS one graf after 19th pvs, ``The '91, to add that source
did not idenfity which battleships should be retired</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSANNE M. SCHAFER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Military Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Navy is proposing to put two of its four
battleships in mothballs and limit purchases of the $1.2 billion
Trident submarine to every other year, a senior Pentagon official
says.
   But the service, studying proposals for the new fiscal-year
budget, is fighting to spare at least 14 aircraft carriers from
White House pressures to trim the military's most favored weapons
programs.
   President Bush, who is slated to deliver his budget to Congress
on Jan. 22, may be called upon to make the final decisions on any
suggested cuts, given their controversial nature.
   ``We're robbing Peter to pay Paul,'' the Pentagon official said
of the current budget-juggling exercise. He spoke on condition of
anonymity.
   The fiscal 1991 spending plan will be a key barometer of the
Pentagon's ability to respond to pressures from budget cutters on
Capitol Hill and in the Office of Management and Budget.
   White House budget planners have told Defense Secretary Dick
Cheney he can spend a little more than $292 billion in the new
budget year, which begins next Oct. 1. That means Pentagon spending
won't keep pace with inflation, which the administration has
projected will increase at an average rate of 4.1 percent.
   The Navy, like other services, is being forced to trim programs
it holds to be successful _ such as the Trident _ in order to meet
these goals, said the senior official.
   The official said the service is ``seriously considering''
stretching out the annual purchases of the strategic Trident subs
to every other year.
   The sub's billion-dollar price tag has made it easy prey for
lawmakers advocating less lavish spending on strategic nuclear
weapons programs amid the warming of relations with the Soviet
Union.
   In November, the Electric Boat Division of General Dynamics
Corp. in Groton, Conn., won a contract to build the 17th Trident
submarine.
   But due to its high cost and complexity, funds for the submarine
are stretched out over several years.
   Navy Secretary H. Lawrence Garrett III has told Rep. John G.
Rowland, R-Conn., that he expects to request full funding for the
18th Trident submarine in the fiscal 1991 budget.
   But the letter made no mention about long-term procurement funds
for additional submarines.
   ``I'd put my money on some type of stretch-out,'' said another
Defense Department official, asked about the future of the Trident
program.
   The official said it was ``premature'' to talk about an end to
the program, and said that if an every-other-year purchase policy
is finally adopted, ``it may not even compromise the long-term
number'' of submarines, widely exepted to be 24.
   The service's World War II-era battleships also have become
targets of budget cutters on Capitol Hill, particularly in the
aftermath of last spring's explosion aboard the USS Iowa, which
claimed 47 sailors' lives. The tragedy spawned a series of
congressional hearings, where lawmakers voiced sharp criticism of
the huge ship's safety procedures and personnel practices.
   Even the chief of naval operations, Adm. Carlisle A. Trost,
admitted at one hearing that the future of the four warships was
``up for grabs'' in the budget debate. But the Navy leadership is
loathe to let the warships go, the senior official said.
   ``Nobody _ not the Army, not the Marine Corps, not the Navy,
wants to give those ships up,'' the official contended, arguing
that their mobile firepower offers a major boost when a president
calls for a little ``gunship diplomacy.''
   ``The '91 (budget) plan calls for putting two in mothballs. But
we'd still have two and we want to hang on to those,'' he said.
   He did not identify which battleships would be retired.
   The official argued against putting all four 58,000-ton vessels
in mothballs again, citing the high costs and problems that arose
during their remodernization in the early 1980s.
   The Navy was forced to ``call up old, retired sailors'' to help
in the rebuilding of the ships, the official said.
   ``When it came to taking the propellers off the darn things,
there was only one retired chief petty officer who knew how to do
it _ and you had to use special explosive charges to do it,'' the
official said.
   The second DOD official noted that congressional pressure may
work against mothballing the battleships, since their home ports
were to be dispersed among four states under a revised program.
   ``Our phones rang off the hook'' from lawmakers unhappy about
Trost's suggestion of the ships' possible demise, the official said.
   The senior official said that the Navy is fighting to save at
least 14 aircraft carriers during the next fiscal year.
   One carrier _ the World War II-era Midway _ is scheduled for
retirement next year, which would bring the fleet from 15 to 14.
   ``Tell me, which commitment are we supposed to walk away from?''
the official asked, pointing out that the U.S. commitment to sail
the Indian Ocean and keep tabs on the potentially explosive Persian
Gulf haven't changed.
   The official also said the requirements of the Navy most
probably will increase as the service is asked to place more power
on the high seas to advance the nation's war against illicit
narcotics traffickers.
</TEXT>

</DOC>