<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0162 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1859EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Colombia     12-22 0542</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia,0557</SECOND>
<HEAD>Drug Traffickers Slain in Colombia, Turf War Feared</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STAN YARBRO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The slaying of a cocaine lord last week
may have touched off a bloody war by mid-level traffickers fighting
to take his place in the notorious Medellin cartel, police were
quoted Friday as saying.
   The national police investigations chief, Col. Oscar Eduardo
Pelaez, said Thursday six men were found dead at a south Bogota
dump. At least four of the victims, who were found Wednesday,
belonged to the slain cocaine boss' group, the official said.
   Four other bodies were found in a resort town late Thursday, and
five men died in a Bogota prison earlier in the week in a turf
fight between prisoners of rival drug organizations.
   Some officials had been predicting violence between rival cartel
factions since police shot and killed Gonzalo Rodriguez Gacha in a
Dec. 15 gunfight on the country's northern coast.
   Rodriguez Gacha, the Medellin cartel's No. 2 leader, died with
his 17-year-old son, four bodyguards and another trafficker.
   Bogota's El Tiempo newspaper Friday quoted police sources as
saying that Rodriguez Gacha's organization of about 2,000 men had
been thrown into chaos by their leader's death.
   ``Some of them have given up their arms, others have fled, and
others have returned to their normal activities,'' said an
unidentified police official quoted by the paper.
   However, El Tiempo added that some officials fear that mid-level
traffickers are trying to take control of the dead drug lord's
operation and reorganize it.
   The six men whose bodies were found at the dump were apparently
killed as a result of internal power struggles in the cartel, said
Pelaez. He told reporters at a news conference the victims had been
gagged and shot, and their bodies showed signs of torture.
   One of the bodies matched witnesses' descriptions of a man who
drove a bus bomb into the secret police headquarters in Bogota on
Dec. 6, Pelaez said. The bus, loaded with about 1,100 pounds of
dynamite, exploded moments later, killing 63 people and injuring
about 1,000.
   Gen. Miguel Maza Marquez, the secret police chief, had accused
Rodriguez Gacha of ordering the attack with the No. 1 man in the
Medellin cartel, Pablo Escobar. He remains at large.
   Police found four more bodies late Thursday along a road leading
from the capital to the resort town of Melgar, 55 miles to the
south. El Espectador newspaper, citing police sources, reported
Friday that the deaths were the result of battles between feuding
criminals groups.
   A police spokesman told The Associated Press by telephone that
he could not say whether the victims had worked for Rodriguez Gacha.
   Five men died Tuesday when two bands of prisoners battled with
knives at a Bogota jail. Police said Rodriguez Gacha's men attacked
a group of prisoners of a rival group that had been fighting with
the drug trafficker for control of emerald mines in central
Colombia.
   The family of Rodriguez Gacha issued a statement to the news
media Friday saying his ``battles, political ideals, and
convictions had been buried with him.''
   The statement, signed by two brothers of the trafficker, said
the family had no ``dark desire for vengeance or retaliation'' and
wanted peace for the country.
</TEXT>

</DOC>