<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0196 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0851EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APonTV-NormanLloyd Adv19   12-18 0756</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP on TV-Norman Lloyd, Adv 19,0775</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv19</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Tuesday PMs, Dec. 19, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Norman Lloyd Brings Intellectual Power To Washington Heavy on `Wiseguy'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LA1 of Dec.16</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JERRY BUCK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Television Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The role of Washington manipulator Gen.
Leland Masters on CBS' ``Wiseguy'' was written to be a big,
imposing American Caesar.
   The producers had in mind Gregory Peck, who portrayed Gen.
Douglas MacArthur in the movie ``MacArthur.'' After considering it,
Peck turned it down. The producers then considered Kirk Douglas,
Richard Widmark and others before turning to Norman Lloyd, who was
cast in the role.
   Lloyd, who spent six years on ``St. Elsewhere'' as the saintly,
cancer-stricken Dr. Daniel Auschlander, brings a new aspect to the
role. In a way, Masters is more dangerous, more cunning because of
Lloyd's benign appearance.
   ``I saw him instead as a man of some intellectual power,'' Lloyd
said of the fictional general.
   ``One of our best generals ... was an intellectual: Vinegar Joe
Stillwell. He was a small, wiry man. He'd been a schoolteacher. He
would not have thought the way Masters did, however. Masters would
have been closer to Chiang Kai-shek than Stillwell.''
   In the current five-week arc on ``Wiseguy,'' Vinnie Terranova
(Ken Wahl) comes out of cover at the instance of Masters to
investigate a scheme to undermine the economy of Japan.
   ``Somebody wants to flood Japan with counterfeit money and he
wants Vinnie Terranova to work on it,'' said Lloyd. ``As it
unfolds, we see that Masters is the heavy and he's setting up
Vinnie to be the patsy.
   ``Their antagonism goes back several years ago when Vinnie
stymied Masters' pet project, the invasion of Isle Pavot. Masters
pretends to uncover this plot, but it's all to frame Vinnie to get
his revenge.''
   Early in his career, Lloyd usually played villains. He was the
bad guy who fell from the Statue of Liberty in Alfred Hitchcock's
``Saboteur'' in 1942. That spectacular scene is often studied in
film schools.
   ``When I see that I mourn for my lost hair,'' said Lloyd. ``It
was red.''
   Lloyd was in Hitchcock's ``Spellbound,'' which starred Gregory
Peck and Ingrid Bergman, and in 1957 Hitchcock brought him out from
New York to produce ``Alfred Hitchcock Presents.'' He spent eight
years on the series and directed 25 episodes.
   In ``Dead Poets Society,'' he was not a villain, but he
represents the establishment in his conflicts with Robin Williams
and the students.
   ``Gen. Masters is a political power behind the scenes,'' Lloyd
said. ``His power reaches right into the White House. He's on the
National Security Commission. He's a very dangerous fellow. The
writers threw in some wonderful throwaway lines. I have a line, `I
told them we needed more helicopters in the desert.' You know right
away it refers to the attempt to rescue the hostages in Iran.
   ``I think this show gets into some controversial issues in a
dramatic way. It has energetic, gutsy stories.''
   Lloyd said he found the role a refreshing change from Dr.
Auschlander, who had a long remission from cancer. Apparently, in
the beginning Auschlander was not meant to stay around, but the
producers had a change of heart. He was still working at the end of
the series.
   ``As a heavy, you're always in conflict,'' he said. ``You're
into the energy of the piece. When you play a hero you have to
create situations of interest to the audience that aren't just
white bread. It's easier to play a heavy. It's more dramatic.
   ``The new-found freedom of television helps. You don't have to
say `gee whiz.' You can say words that are closer to reality.''
   Lloyd has a book coming out based on his oral history for the
Directors Guild. It tells of his work with such directors and
filmmakers as Jean Renoir, Charlie Chaplin, Orson Welles, Bertolt
Brecht, Lewis Milestone and Alfred Hitchcock.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Elsewhere in television:
   ENCORE _ Susan Seaforth Hayes will return to her role as Julie
Williams on the NBC soap opera ``Days of Our Lives'' in February.
She had played the role for 16 years until leaving the show in
1984. After that, she spent five years on the CBS soap opera ``The
Young and the Restless.'' Her husband, Bill Hayes, also starred
with her on ``Days of Our Lives'' as her husband, Doug. He left
when she did and later returned to the show for a brief period.
Hayes also appeared on ABC's ``General Hospital.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Tuesday PMs, Dec. 19</NOTE>

</DOC>