<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0522EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Taiwan     12-25 0409</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Taiwan,0421</SECOND>
<HEAD>2,000 In Noisy March For Political Reform</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto TPE2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SHIRLEY LAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TAIPEI, Taiwan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 2,000 opposition supporters marched
downtown today in a noisy but peaceful demonstration on
Constitution Day to demand swifter political reform.
   About 2,000 riot policemen backed by water cannon trucks guarded
the National Assembly building from behind barbed-wire barricades.
   Earlier, 11 legislators from the opposition Democratic
Progressive Party scuffled with guards at the National Assembly who
tried to prevent them from carrying protest banners into the
building.
   Three assemblymen said they suffered bruises in the brief
scuffle before they were allowed to take the banners into the
National Assembly where President Lee Teng-hui appealed for greater
tolerance toward dissent.
   ``In a more open society we need to have the magnanimity to
tolerate dissent,'' Lee told the assembly. ``As our society faces a
transition, we need to build a new political culture and strengthen
psychological reconstruction.''
   As Lee and Premier Lee Huan addressed the assembly, Taiwan's
electoral college, the opposition assemblymen unfurled their
banners which demanded ``Aging Assemblymen Step Down,'' ``We Want
Universal Suffrage For The Presidency'' and ``Please Proclaim
Taiwan an Independent State.''
   Both the Nationalist government in Taiwan and the rival
Communist government in Beijing are opposed to independence for
Taiwan, which they say is a Chinese province. Both say they are the
sole legitimate government of all China, and Beijing has indicated
it may use force to prevent Taiwan from gaining independence.
   The 780-member National Assembly, which meets every six years to
elect the president, is dominated by aging members, many in their
70s, who were elected on the Chinese mainland before the
Nationalists fled to Taiwan in 1949 after losing a civil war to the
Communists.
   Most of the aged assemblymen are Nationalist supporters and they
have been frozen in office to support the Nationalist claim to be
the legitimate government of China.
   The opposition has demanded the retirement of the aged
assemblymen. The government has offered them handsome pensions if
they step down, but has refused to force them to retire.
   ``The old members did not face re-election for 40 years (and
they) cannot represent Taiwanese people,'' said Chou Ching-yu, a
Democratic Progressive Party assemblywoman. ``They don't have the
right to elect our president.''
   Lee, who is expected to be re-elected president in March, told
opposition assemblymen at a meeting last week that political
reforms must be introduced slowly to maintain Taiwan's stability.
</TEXT>

</DOC>