<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0333EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Panama-Aid     12-30 0332</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Aid,320</SECOND>
<HEAD>Recovery Plan Expected Next Week</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The new Panamanian government plans to present
economic recovery proposals to the United States next week that
will cover damages including looting that occurred when U.S. troops
overthrew dictator Manuel Antonio Noriega, says the new ambassador
to the United States.
   The new ambassador, Carlos Rodriguez, said Friday night that
Panamanian experts working with an inter-agency U.S. team ``have
not quantified anything, and we are not demanding anything.''
   Asked about reports that war damage would amount to $3 billion
to $10 billion, he replied, ``It is not possible to quantify
matters with that degree of precision.''
   The economic recovery proposal ``was designed, prior to the
military action, to restore Panama's economy, but it has been
updated to reflect the military action,'' Rodriguez said in an
interview.
   ``There were damages, including the Chorillo area, and merchants
who suffered looting from the interruption in police services,'' he
said.
   Reports from Panama say supporters of Noriega set fire to the
Chorillo area, inhabited by many poor people near his old
headquarters. Some 13,000 people took shelter in a nearby athletic
complex.
   The Chamber of Commerce in Panama City has estimated damages
from looting alone in that city at $2 billion.
   A team of U.S. experts already has gone to Panama and hopes to
``make a presentation to the press on Tuesday of the same
proposals'' being put forward to the United States government,
Rodriguez said.
   U.S. sanctions against the Noriega regime over the past two
years have caused that nation's economy to shrink by an estimated
10 percent to 15 percent annually, some analysts have said.
   Some estimates put unemployment above 20 percent, and the
country of around 2\ million people has a foreign debt estimated at
$5.6 billion.
   Cash totaling $50 million was flown into Panama on Friday from
the United States, part of frozen assets now released. Panama has
no national currency of its own and uses U.S. dollars for all its
transactions.
</TEXT>

</DOC>