<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0287 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1641EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Bloomingdale'sBidders     12-20 0524</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bloomingdale's Bidders,0542</SECOND>
<HEAD>Developer Trump Reportedly Has Eye on Bloomingdale's</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Billionaire Donald Trump reportedly is among
bidders weighing a possible purchase of Bloomingdale's but the
department store chain's troubled owner, Campeau Corp., declined
Wednesday to confirm Trump's interest.
   Campeau spokeswoman Carol Sanger said the company intends to
maintain silence for the duration of the sale process. The identity
of the bidders will not be disclosed and all negotiations are
confidential.
   The only thing the company has been willing to say in the past
is that no more than five or six parties would advance to the
second stage of the bidding. No word on who will acquire the
17-store upscale chain is expected until sometime in February,
Campeau said on Dec. 8, the day the initial stage of the sale
process was concluded.
   Susan Heilbron, a spokeswoman for the Trump Organization, also
declined to comment on a report Wednesday in The Wall Street
Journal that said Trump is one of the bidders who will advance to
round 2.
   Trump is known primarily as a property developer. Included in
his vast holdings are an airline and a stake in a New York
department store chain, Alexander's.
   Alexander's announced on Wednesday that, at the urging of Trump
and another stockholder, the retailer had hired the investment
banking firm Morgan Stanley &amp; Co. to ``consider strategic
alternatives to maximize stockholder value, including the possible
sale of the company.''
   The retailer said there was no assurance that any transaction
would occur.
   Ms. Heilbron dismissed speculation that Trump might favor a sale
of Alexander's to raise money to help pay for Bloomingdale's. She
said Trump and Steven Roth, who each own 27.2 percent of
Alexander's, have been advocating changes for years in the way
Alexander's has been run.
   She said she wouldn't rule out the possibility that Trump might
pursue a takeover of the share of Alexander's he doesn't already
control. Alexander's operates 11 stores in the New York
metropolitan area.
   Besides Trump, the bidders for Bloomingdale's include shopping
center owner JMB Realty Corp. based in Chicago, Japan's Tokyu
Department Store Co. and a group led by Joseph E. Brooks, chairman
of the Ann Taylor stores, the Journal said, citing unidentified
sources.
   An investment group headed by Bloomingdale's Chairman Marvin
Traub also is among the contenders, a spokeswoman for the chain,
Katie Locke, said.
   Ira Millstein, an adviser to Traub and a senior partner with the
law firm Weil, Gotshal &amp; Manges, told the Journal that the Traub
group is trying to arrange financing for a possible bid. He said
the group is engaged in serious discussions with potential
financial partners.
   A sixth bidder, possibly Japanese, also is believed to be
involved in the bidding, the Journal said.
   Campeau, a Canadian real estate company with extensive retail
holdings in the United States, was forced to put Bloomingdale's up
for sale in September as part of a plan to cope with a severe cash
squeeze and an enormous debt load.
   Among the stores besides New York-based Bloomingdale's under
Campeau's corporate umbrella are: Abraham &amp; Straus, Burdines,
Lazarus, Rich's, The Bon Marche, Jordan Marsh and Stern's.
</TEXT>

</DOC>