<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1217EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Romania 6thLd-Writethru a0527 12-18 1200</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania, 6th Ld - Writethru, a0527,1237</SECOND>
<HEAD>Source Reports Deaths in Romania; Unconfirmed Report of Hundreds
Dead</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 29 grafs to move up background on Ceausescu, UPDATE
with action in Yugoslavia today, reaction from exiled king, British tourists
detained; Picks up 26th graf, `The unrest ...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROLAND PRINZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Romanian police opened fire on protesters
during weekend anti-government riots, and at least two people were
killed, including a child, a person traveling in the region said
today.
   In West Germany, Radio Bremen quoted William Totok, an ethnic
German author who emigrated from Romania to West Germany, as saying
that eyewitnesses told him as many as 300 to 400 people were
killed. The report could not be independently confirmed.
   Several sources reported Sunday and today that they heard
gunfire in the streets of Timisoara, Romania's fourth-largest city,
following the largest protests against the hard-line Communist
government in two years.
   Romania sealed its border with Yugoslavia today to all but
official traffic and tanks were reported patrolling Timisoara and a
nearby city.
   President Nicolae Ceausescu, the East bloc's longest-ruling
leader, traveled to Iran on a state visit. He has crushed
opposition, rejected the reforms being adopted elsewhere in Eastern
Europe and imposed harsh economic measures on Romania.
   Romanian emigres said thousands of demonstrators enraged with
the hardship and repression under Ceausescu clashed with security
forces in Timisoara. Police reportedly fired shot and also used
water cannon against the demonstrators.
   Romania's strictly controlled state-run media made no mention of
the unrest, but Bucharest radio on Sunday warned citizens to stay
calm, indicating security forces were worried about protests
spreading, as occurred in East Germany and Czechoslovakia.
   Popular revolts in those countries led to the downfall of
hard-line leaders and ended the Communists' monopoly on power.
   Elsewhere in the East bloc today:
   _East Germany's Communist leaders resumed talks with opposition
factions on how to run the country until the first free elections
are held in May.
   _Czechoslovakia's Communist Party chief, Karel Urbanek, said his
party likely will try to form a coalition with other parties before
free elections planned next year. The party's official Rude Pravo
newspaper apologized for past articles that criticized opponents of
the government.
   _Yugoslavia's Premier Ante Markovic proposed a new convertible
currency unit as part of a sweeping reform plan to save the
Communist nation from its worst economic crisis.
   The traveler in Romania, a Yugoslav who refused to give his
name, told The Associated Press that other Yugoslav tourists
reported seeing more dead in Timisoara after security forces
intervened to break up the protests.
   Those reports also could not be independently confirmed, and
Romania has refused to allow Western journalists into the country.
   ``Police and troops moved in quickly,'' the traveler said after
leaving Romania today. He said only police, but not troops, were
seen firing at the demonstrators.
   ``I saw two dead, including a child, on the streets,'' the
source said.
   Western diplomats contacted by telephone in Romania said
security forces guarded Otopeni international airport and refused
to allow a plane carrying about 200 Western tourists to land.
   It also refused to allow a group of 28 British schoolgirls,
three teachers and two parents who were on a ski vacation. They
were detained at Bucharest Airport on Sunday, the British Foreign
Office said in London.
   Hungarian border officials also reported that entry to Romania
by Hungarian visitors was severely curtailed following the weekend
demonstrations.
   Zoltan Kiraly, a Hungarian parliamentarian, told legislators
tanks were on the streets of Timisoara, where a protest over an
ethnic dispute evolved into a violent demonstration against
Ceausescu.
   Kiraly said tanks also patrolled Arad, 40 miles north of
Timisoara, where unrest was reported over the weekend.
   Timisoara, with a population of 350,000, is in the region of
Transylvania, about 30 miles from the Yugoslav and Hungarian
borders.
   Protest in Romania has generally originated in Transylvania and
the northern areas near Soviet Moldavia, where people can
understand broadcasts from neighboring Hungary and the Soviet Union
and learn of reforms sweeping the East bloc but rejected by
Ceausescu.
   Hungarian Premier Miklos Nemeth told reporters in Budapest that
he had been told Romanian armed forces were put on a state of
alert, but this could not be confirmed.
   Budapest radio, quoting unidentified witnesses, reported that
Romanian security forces sealed off Timisoara.
   Romanian emigres who contacted friends and relatives abroad said
anti-government demonstrations also were staged in Brasov, another
Transylvanian city that was the site of a major anti-Communist
rally in 1987.
   The Western diplomats said the Romanian capital, Bucharest,
appeared calm.
   Ceausescu, 71, rarely travels abroad, and his departure for Iran
indicated he wanted to appear unruffled by the demonstrations. His
wife Elena, the second most powerful person in the country, stayed
behind.
   In Geneva, exiled King Michael of Romania today condemned the
crackdown on anti-government protests and said he was deeply moved
by the demonstrators' ``courageous action.''
   The unrest in Timisoara began Saturday after demonstrators
formed a human chain to prevent officials from evicting an ethnic
Hungarian clergyman from his church. Transylvania's ethnic
Hungarian minority has long complained of harassment by Romanian
authorities.
   Some news reports said the government planned to deport the
Protestant minister, the Rev. Laszlo Toekes, a Reformed Church
clergyman who has championed the rights of ethnic Hungarians.
   Toekes had been confined to the church since masked assailants
attacked him in his adjoining apartment Nov. 2, said Steve Toekes,
the minister's brother, in a telephone interview today from his
home in Montreal.
   The Hungarian state-run MTI news agency, said a crowd of
Hungarians and Romanians ``tried to prevent the eviction of their
clergyman when hell broke loose and the human chain changed into a
demonstration of thousands against Ceausescu and his regime.
   ``Riot police tried to suppress the demonstration, and a bloody
brawl started,'' the agency said. MTI said it took police nearly
two hours to regain control. It said Toekes' fate was not known.
   ``Eyewitnesses saw bloodied young people in the streets of
Timisoara and Ceausescu pictures floating on the Bega Canal. They
said many of the demonstrators were arrested,'' MTI said.
   Yugoslav travelers returning from Timisoara told The Associated
Press in Belgrade that tens of thousands of people were milling in
the streets Sunday morning. The Yugoslavs said that ``the entire
city seemed on the streets.''
   They said that when they left the city at 2 p.m. Sunday, cordons
of soldiers, three-deep, were blocking traffic at main
intersections.
   The Yugoslav witnesses said on Saturday night, protesters
smashed the window of a bookstore, threw Ceausescu books into the
street and burned them.
   A Yugoslav customs official at the Vatin crossing to Romania
told the AP in Belgrade that Romania stopped letting through all
private cars early today.
   MTI said that on Sunday morning Romania closed its border for
Hungarians, but other travelers were apparently allowed to enter
Romania.
   Ceausescu was elected Romanian Communist Party chief on March
22, 1965.
   This is the biggest challenge to his leadership since an
anti-government march in the town of Brasov in 1987.
   That protest was quashed by the massive secret police force that
has helped Ceausescu, the longest-serving Soviet bloc leader, to
silence virtually all dissent.
</TEXT>

</DOC>