<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0232 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0124EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-GiftCertificateFraud Bjt   12-22 0604</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Gift Certificate Fraud, Bjt,0625</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gift Certificate Fraud Popular During Holiday Season</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HELEN J. SIMON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEWARK, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Talented con artists won't be stopping at
forged checks and stolen credit cards this holiday season,
retailers and security experts say. Gift certificates have become a
hot new tool of the trade.
   ``The economic criminals are getting away from buying hard
merchandise and they're buying gift certificates,'' said Jack
Scott, director of loss prevention for JBS Associates of Ringwood,
one of the country's largest check guarantee companies.
   ``They realize it's a weakness in the merchants' system,'' he
said.
   The thieves use stolen credit cards or bogus checks to buy the
certificates because they are more difficult to trace, more
flexible and can be resold.
   ``Once they get the gift certificate it's like money in their
pocket,'' said Ray Watson, a loss prevention detective for Sears,
Roebuck and Co. Inc.
   Some certificates are redeemed for merchandise, which also can
later be resold. Thieves may also buy an item with the certificate
and later take it back, asking for a cash refund.
   Scott, whose company guarantees the credit-worthiness of checks
for merchants, estimates the going rate for gift certificates on
the street is 70 to 75 cents on the dollar compared to 35 cents on
the dollar for merchandise.
   In one case, Scott said, a con artist was able to pass more than
$50,000 in counterfeit gift certificates in less than two weeks
before he was caught.
   Gift certificates are easy targets because few merchants keep
track of them by serializing them or recording numbers of documents
that have been redeemed, he said. Gift certificate purchases are
often rung up as cash, making it difficult to later trace them.
   In addition, they often are printed on regular paper instead of
on paper with watermarks or other means of preventing reproduction
by increasingly sophisticated laser copiers, he said.
   Lewis Shealy, vice president of loss prevention for the
Chicago-based Marshall Fields department stores, said his company's
25 stores had gift-certificate losses of about $10,000 last year
even though they serialized their certificates.
   ``They were using photocopy machines to counterfeit them and
they looked very, very good,'' he said. ``During a busy Christmas
season your chances of passing them are 100 percent.''
   This year, the store hired a company that designs federal bank
notes to create a system under which the word ``void'' appears on
photocopies of gift certificates, he said.
   Officials from federal and state agencies and the National
Retail Merchants Association said they had no figures on gift
certificate fraud.
   ``That's not an area we've been called into at all,'' said
association spokesman John Gary.
   Richard Adams, a spokesman for the U.S. Secret Service in
Washington, D.C., said the agency does not keep statistics to
distinguish certificate fraud from other fraud like credit card
misuse.
   Scott estimated the use of stolen checks or credit cards to buy
gift certificates is up by about 20 percent this year.
   Scott said the extent of the problem was brought home to him
this summer through interviews with the arrested heads of a
national ring estimated to have cashed more than $35 million worth
of stolen checks in the last three years.
   ``They predicted there is going to be a major loss to retailers
this holiday season because of the popularity of gift certificate
fraud among economic criminals,'' Scott said.
   Not all stores are victims of gift certificate fraud.
   ``I don't have any known fraud in my gift certificate areas,''
said Ed Barclay, director of loss prevention for Saks Fifth
Avenue's 46 stores, which serialize their certificates.
</TEXT>

</DOC>