<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0094 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1050EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Panama-PoolReport     12-20 0474</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Pool Report,460</SECOND>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   EDITOR'S NOTE: The following dispatch is from a pool report
filed by reporters Steven Komarow of The Associated Press, Robert
Kearns of Reuters and Dick Thompson of Time magazine, who
accompanied U.S. forces in the invasion of Panama
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By STEVEN KOMAROW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FORT CLAYTON, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   John Bushnell, the highest-ranking
U.S. official in Panama, said today that there will be fear among
Panamanians until Gen. Manuel Noriega is captured or otherwise
removed from the scene.
   ``Having him loose does raise the potential that he might raise
more mischief,'' said Bushnell, the U.S. charge d'affaires. ``I
have the concern that until he is in custody, there is still going
to be a great deal of concern and fear among the Panamanians.''
   Bushnell made his comments to a group of reporters at a heavily
guarded fort on the outskirts of the city.
   ``Noriega may take to the hills and be very hard to find ...
(but) he wouldn't have a significant force to actually do
anything,'' Bushnell said. ``He will get very little support from
the people.''
   The news group from Washington was shuttled to the fort by
helicopter from Howard Air Force Base only 10,000 yards from where
the briefing was held because the military considered it unsafe to
drive.
   The reporters were given six copies of a videotape of the
swearing-in of Panama's newly elected leadership.
   The officials themselves were in hiding because it was still too
risky for them to appear anywhere in public, Bushnell said. He
would not disclose their whereabouts.
   The three Panamanian leaders _ considered by the United States
to have won an election last May _ met with Bushnell on Monday
evening and were told of the U.S. military plan. They approved of
it in a letter to President Bush, Bushnell said.
   The officials _ President Guillermo Endara, and Vice Presidents
Ricardo Arias Calderon and Guillermo Ford _ were sworn in at an
undisclosed site early Wednesday as the military action was getting
under way.
   The oath was witnessed by two officials of Panama's human rights
association, because no Panamanian government official could be
enlisted to participate.
   Bushnell raised the possibility that Noriega could slip into
Nicaragua or Cuba. ``He may be in the embassies right now,
hiding,'' he said.
   The U.S. Embassy was hit by one or possibly two rounds believed
from a rocket-propelled grenade launcher in Wednesday's fighting.
   The new Panamanian government was hoping to go soon to the
presidential house once the fighting is over. The leaders were
welcoming U.S. help they had eschewed earlier because of the
experience and aftermath of the Oct. 3 coup attempt against Noriega.
   ``There weren't too many Panamanians left with guns who were
willing to do it,'' Bushnell said. ``When Noriega is captured,
there will be an immense sigh of relief.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>