<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0711EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-RomanianPrincess 1stLd-Writethru a0474 12-27 0549</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romanian Princess, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0474,0559</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romanian Princess-Turned-Nun Says Prayers Answered</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 5th graf, `He was...' to CORRECT style on Antichrist.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCIA DUNN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Romania's Princess Ileana, now a nun at an
Orthodox monastery in rural western Pennsylvania, said her homeland
was saved ``in the nick of time'' by a revolution she never thought
she'd live to see.
   ``I always believed my prayers would be answered,'' the Rev.
Mother Alexandra said Tuesday.
   The 80-year-old daughter of King Ferdinand and Queen Marie, and
great-granddaughter of England's Queen Victoria and Czar Alexander
II of Russia, said her European contacts told her ousted President
Nicolae Ceausescu had to die.
   Ceausescu and his wife, Elena, were executed by a firing squad
Monday following conviction by a secret military tribunal. The
former Communist leader and his wife had been captured Saturday, a
day after a popular uprising forced him from power.
   He was denounced as the ``Antichrist'' and accused of killing
60,000 people.
   ``They said 60,000 is enough ... and it (execution) had to be
done because it would have gone on and on and on,'' Mother
Alexandra said in a telephone interview from the Orthodox Monastery
of the Transfiguration near Ellwood City. ``They had to do it, so
they tell me. I personally have no opinion.''
   Mother Alexandra's father was king from 1914 until his death in
1927. Her nephew, King Michael, was forced to abdicate by the
communists in 1947 and lives in Switzerland.
   ``I didn't expect the whole thing, I must say. I've lived with
it so long. It's been 42 years since I left,'' she said.
   ``The strength of the country has always been in its peasantry.
That's what Ceausescu was destroying. I hope there is enough of
them left and enough intellectuals left to be able to build again.''
   Princess Ileana was exiled from Romania with the rest of the
royal family soon after King Michael's abdication in December 1947.
   She immigrated with her husband, an archduke of Austria, and
their six children to Switzerland and then Argentina before
settling in 1950 in the United States. The move ultimately led to
divorce.
   She ended a second marriage to become a postulant, or a
candidate for the religious order, in 1961. Six years later, she
took her monastic vows and put up a trailer outside Ellwood City to
began building an English-speaking monastery for Orthodox women of
all ethnic backgrounds.
   Mother Alexandra said she has spent much of the past week on the
telephone with friends and relatives in Europe, keeping abreast of
developments and consoling friends of the many who died in the
uprising.
   She said that even with the changes elsewhere in Eastern Europe
she did not expect such quick, drastic moves in her homeland.
   ``Quite honestly, I was feeling very depressed about it,'' she
said. ``I thought everybody was doing something but nothing was
moving in Romania at all. And suddenly, it blew up.''
   Mother Alexandra said she is working with the Romanian Orthodox
Episcopate of America in Jackson, Mich., to organize a Save Romania
Fund. She also plans a special service at the monastery this week
for Romania's dead.
   She said she would consider returning to Romania ``if I could be
of use.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>