<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1733EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Drive-inAttack     12-17 0493</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Drive-in Attack,0509</SECOND>
<HEAD>Couple in Kidnap, Rape and Murder Appeared to be Randomly Picked</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CARSON, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three men kidnapped a couple at a drive-in
theater, raped and killed the woman and viciously beat her
boyfriend before dumping him in an alley, authorities said.
   There were no arrests in the case Sunday, and Los Angeles County
Sheriff's deputies said the attackers apparently picked their
victims at random.
   ``They're animals,'' sheriff's Detective Joe Barnes said of the
assailants. There was no sign that drugs or gangs were involved, he
added.
   ``That's the scary part,'' he said. ``It can be you and your
wife. You and your girlfriend.''
   Detectives on Saturday found the body of Irene Franco, 20, who
was kidnapped at gunpoint with boyfriend Jesus Martinez, 26, from a
six-screen complex about 17 miles south of Los Angeles.
   Martinez, who was left bloodied and bludgeoned in an alley,
called authorities from a pay telephone after the men drove off
with his girlfriend, sheriff's Deputy Dean Scoville said.
   Martinez told authorities he and Ms. Franco were watching a
movie at the theater late Friday when a man wielding a pistol
walked up to the car and ordered the couple into the back seat as
two other men hopped in. Martinez said neither he nor his
girlfriend knew the assailants.
   The men tied up the couple and ordered them to keep their heads
down, authorities said. The gunmen drove the car to an alley and
beat and raped Ms. Franco as they took turns beating Martinez,
using a board they apparently found nearby, Scoville said.
   ``When they weren't assaulting the girl they were assaulting
(Martinez),'' Scoville said.
   Martinez, a construction worker from the Los Angeles suburb of
Gardena, was bound with electrical cord before the men drove off
with Ms. Franco.
   They shouted something like, ``Don't worry about your
girlfriend. we'll drop her off in a few minutes,'' Scoville said.
   Ms. Franco, a Mexican immigrant living in Wilmington, died of a
gunshot wound to the back of the head, Scoville said.
   A 13-year-old boy playing with a cousin spotted the woman's
badly beaten body Saturday morning in a field several miles from
the drive-in. Authorities did not identify her body positively
until 5 p.m., Scoville said.
   Martinez was taken to a hospital, treated for numerous injuries
and released. The couple's car was found abandoned at a third
location, where it had been set afire, he said.
   Detectives were trying to locate witnesses from the drive-in but
had been unable to find anyone who saw the assault, Scoville said.
   The murder shocked members of Ms. Franco's parish in Wilmington,
where the Rev. Luis Valbuena worked to arrange for her relatives in
Mexico to come to Los Angeles to make funeral arrangements.
   ``Nothing makes sense,'' Valbuena said. ``This is the time
before Christmas. It has to make you think, `Where are we going?' ''
   He described Ms. Franco, a regular churchgoer, as ``very
beautiful, very religious.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>