<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0638EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AtlanticCityProbe     12-20 0546</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Atlantic City Probe,0562</SECOND>
<HEAD>Grand Jury Indicts 11 in Atlantic City Corruption Case</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM KRATTENMAKER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TRENTON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four top Atlantic City officials are among
11 people under indictment in a broad corruption probe in the
gambling resort, but the grand jury was silent on the mayor, who
had been arrested in the case.
   ``It's an active, ongoing investigation,'' the state attorney
general's spokesman, Christopher Florentz, said Tuesday. ``It does
not conclude with today's indictments. The charges at this time
have not been dropped.''
   Atlantic City Mayor James Usry had no comment, said Rosalind
Norrell-Nance, an aide.
   ``City government can continue to march,'' said business
administrator Carl Briscoe, who runs the resort's everyday affairs.
   Among those indicted Tuesday were City Council President Walter
Collette, Councilman Gene Dorn and Zoning Board Chairman Kaleem
Shabazz, who are all accused of accepting bribes to use their
positions to obtain zoning breaks and other benefits for private
businesses.
   Another councilman, Arnold Orsatti Jr., was charged with
participating in the conspiracy.
   A state police sting hit the top echelon of Atlantic City's
government with arrests and corruption charges on July 27. Besides
the 11 indicted, Usry and two others were arrested in the sweep
that culminated an eight-month investigation.
   Usry, 67, was led away from his home by police in a roundup of
suspects. Authorities said $6,000 in cash was found in his home,
but the mayor's attorney said the money was a contribution from a
businessman that Usry was to relay to a children's charity.
   The arrest was an embarrassment to state Republicans, including
Gov. Thomas H. Kean, who had helped put Usry in office and make him
one of the most prominent black Republican officials in the nation.
   Including Usry _ who was elected as a reformer _ four of
Atlantic City's last seven mayors have been arrested.
   The indictment also named W. Oscar Harris, former director of
the city's housing authority; Robert McCurdy, a former jockey and
partner in a liquor store; Harold Mosee, an aide to Collette and a
former councilman; and Jack Wolf, a consultant for Pan Am World
Services.
   State Police Superintendent Col. Clinton Pagano said Collette is
charged with accepting a $1,000 bribe in May by Albert Black, who
was cooperating as an undercover agent for the state police.
   Authorities said the investigation began when Black approached
them with reports that Harris had solicited a bribe from him.
   Black became a key source for investigators, but his account of
the complex of alleged bribes and influence was questioned by one
suspect Tuesday.
   ``Al Black has altered the facts and corrupted the truth beyond
recognition,'' Wolf said. ``The Salem witch hunts prove that in the
end, truth will win out.''
   Authorities suspect Collette accepted the bribe in exchange for
influencing a zoning variance that would enable Black to operate a
car wash.
   Dorn was accused in the indictment of taking a $7,500 cash bribe
from Black to obtain a zoning variance for a gas station.
   Dorn and Wolf were also charged with soliciting and accepting
$3,500 in bribes from Black for influencing Pam Am to give Black a
gift shop concession at Atlantic City International Airport.
   All 11 defendants will be arraigned in January in Superior Court
in Trenton.
</TEXT>

</DOC>