<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0207 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1159EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--Crime-BustingPsychology Adv25   12-21 1113</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Crime-Busting Psychology, Adv 25,1144</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv25</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Monday, Dec. 25, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Psychological Techniques Can Help Solve Crimes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MALCOLM RITTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At first, the woman couldn't remember if the
suspicious-looking man she saw near the murder scene wore any
jewelry.
   But a few minutes later, as she concentrated on her recollection
of him turning his head to the side, she remembered a gold earring.
   That memory helped solve the case, says psychologist Ronald
Fisher, who interviewed her at the request of police. The payoff
came from an experimental technique called the cognitive interview,
aimed at getting crime victims and witnesses to remember more than
under standard police questioning.
   The technique is one of several contributions psychology
researchers hope will help solve crimes and convict criminals.
   Much of this work has been done only in laboratories. But the
cognitive interview recently showed promise in a real-world test
with detectives at the Metro-Dade Police Department in Miami.
   It ``proved to be real fruitful,'' said police Sgt. Jim Wander.
``The guys who took part in it are appreciative of the results, and
I think they're probably better detectives overall as a result of
it.''
   Results were reported in the October issue of the Journal of
Applied Psychology by Fisher and Michael Amador of Florida
International University and R. Edward Geiselman of the University
of California, Los Angeles.
   By analyzing interviews with robbery victims and witnesses, they
found that seven detectives trained in the technique elicited 47
percent more information than before training, and 63 percent more
than did nine untrained detectives.
   The technique involves asking fewer questions than a standard
interview, putting more burden on the witness to actively generate
information rather than simply respond to queries, Fisher said.
   Among its strategies is to discern the witness' job or hobby
interests, which might indicate details he is more likely to
recall. A clothing designer might be able to describe in detail
what a suspect was wearing, for example.
   The witness is also asked to recall his emotions and thoughts at
the time of the crime, because studies suggest that will help
recollection.That can be tricky in the case of a victim who was
frightened by the crime, Fisher said.
   The interviewer also asks the witness what happened, not so much
to get information as to determine the witness' vantage point in
seeing the crime and the ``mental pictures'' he has of it. The meat
of the interview lies in asking the witness to recall the event,
one mental picture at a time, and probe each picture for detail as
it unfolds.
   For example, if a suspect initially approached the witness and
then walked away, the witness should be asked about the suspect's
face only while recalling the approach. Questions about the back of
the suspect's jacket should wait until the witness has moved on to
recalling the departure.
   The technique has ``a lot of promise,'' said Gary Wells,
chairman of the psychology department at Iowa State University and
the author of a handbook on eyewitness identification for police.
   But he and Elizabeth Loftus of the University of Washington have
some reservations. For example, the interview combines several
techniques, and it is not clear which produces the results. Finding
that out might help researchers determine when to use the interview
and when not to, Wells said.
   Loftus also questioned whether the extra details recalled during
the cognitive interview are important. ``Some of them are
important, some of them are not,'' replied Fisher. ``I go for all
the information I can get.''
   Wells said more tests of the technique are needed.
   Another line of memory research deals with the risk that a
victim or witness will falsely identify an innocent person. Several
hundred people a year may be falsely convicted of felonies in the
United States through erroneous identification, said Ken
Deffenbacher, a psychology professor at the University of Nebraska
at Omaha.
   Laboratory experiments have shown two strategies useful in
reducing the risk of false identifications in police lineups, Wells
said. Lineups include a person suspected by police and several
people who generally resemble him.
   In one strategy Wells studied, the witness is shown a ``blank''
lineup which, unknown to him, does not contain any suspects. If he
fingers somebody, he is discarded as unreliable.
   In the other strategy, the witness is shown one person at a time
and asked if it is the right person. In the laboratory, this
technique reduced false identifications by 20 percent to nearly 40
percent, Wells said.
   But Lt. Ron Lewis of the robbery-homicide division of the Los
Angeles Police Department said he considered the ``blank'' lineup
unnecessary because a regular lineup can already expose an
erroneous witness if the witness fails to choose the suspect. He
also said the district attorney generally will not file a complaint
against a person identified by only one witness; corroborating
evidence or multiple witness identifications are generally needed.
   On another aspect of eyewitness reliability, studies show that
people do more poorly in identifying people of a different race
than of their own, said Florida State University psychologist John
Brigham. His recent analysis of 14 studies involving blacks and
whites found the problem affected each race about equally. ``A lot
of people had assumed that whites would do worse with blacks than
blacks would do with whites,'' Brigham said.
   The reason for the problem is not clear. The observer's degree
of racial prejudice doesn't seem to make a consistent difference,
and evidence suggesting the cause is lack of exposure to people of
a different race is ``pretty weak,'' he said. Maybe scientists need
a better measure of exposure, including types of exposure, to
demonstrate such a relationship, he said.
   Brigham suggested that in appropriate cases, jurors be told of
the hazards of cross-racial identification. He also recommended
that lineups be arranged by an officer who is the same race as the
suspect and may be better able to choose people who resemble the
suspect, providing a fairer test of the identification. Police
departments do not appear to do that generally now, he said.
   Gerald Arenberg, executive director of the National Association
of Chiefs of Police, said he doubts such a practice would be widely
used because of the logistics of having enough officers of the
proper race available.
   Wells said that when he describes his lineup techniques and the
cognitive interview while giving workshops to police, ``they are
quite impressed with the kinds of findings that we're coming up
with.
   ``I really think this is one of the areas of applied psychology
that is making a real contribution and a real difference.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Dec. 25</NOTE>

</DOC>