<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1134EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-NoBubbly Bjt   12-30 0603</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-No Bubbly, Bjt,0616</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviets Tough it Through New Year's Parties Champagne in Short Supply</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAREY GOLDBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Professor Iosif Nikolaevsky, standing in line for
some cherry wine at a Moscow food store, doubted he'd be able to
get hold of champagne for his New Year's Eve toast.
   He shrugged and said, ``If I can't get champagne, I'll drink
tea.''
   For most Muscovites, shopping for the traditional New Year's Eve
family feast is the toughest it has been in memory, and what hurts
most is the shortage of champagne, geese, chocolates and other
holiday delicacies.
   ``It's the hardest this year,'' sighed pensioner Lydia
Sergeyeva, handling the jar of murky fruit compote she had just
bought in the Gastronom on central Moscow's Kutuzovsky Prospect,
and recalling past years when she could purchase meat and sausage
easily.
   Like a dozen other shoppers interviewed in the store, she blamed
supply problems on perestroika, Mikhail S. Gorbachev's program of
reforms, but accepted them with equanimity. ``It's a transitional
period. It's natural for there to be breakdowns,'' she said. ``But
we're optimists.''
   Nearby, a young man walked up to the display of dirt-encrusted,
withered carrots, picked-over cabbages and giant jars of pickled
tomatoes and shook his head. ``It's a nightmare,'' he said. ``What
to do?''
   The prospect of toasting the new year without the old bubbly so
concerned the official news agency Tass and government newspaper
Izvestia that they launched investigations into the champagne
shortage.
   ``Not to raise a glass of champagne at New Year's _ such a thing
was not demanded even during the toughest time of the campaign of
total sobriety,'' Tass complained Saturday.
   Gorbachev brought in an anti-alcohol campaign soon after coming
to power in 1985, but it faded after bootleg brewing mushroomed and
state income shrank from lost vodka sales. This year's champagne
shortage was clearly not engineered by government teetotalers.
   Tass reporters went from store to store in search of the sparkly
stuff but encountered only embattled salespeople, angry customers,
wine factory workers who claimed to have fulfilled their production
plans, and store managers who maintained they had never received
shipments.
   The baffled reporters finally explained the shortage with
typical Moscow accusations: Much of the champagne went to the
privileged elite, and shoppers from out of town snatched up the
rest.
   Izvestia, however, went deeper in its search. In an article
headlined ``Will we have champagne on New Year's Eve?'' it
determined that the Soviet Union, for all its fame as an exporter
of vodka and ``Golden'' champagne, produces yearly only about one
bottle of champagne per person.
   Glass factories, using technology unchanged since 1926, put out
less than half the bottles needed each year, further limiting
champagne producers, the newspaper said.
   The Izvestia report echoed the government line on the reason for
widespread shortages. Gorbachev and other party leaders say the
``period of stagnation'' under past leaders left the country's
industrial base in dangerous disrepair, made people lose their
taste for work and left them indifferent to quality.
   Delicacies and gifts are freely available in the markets, where
farmers, craftsmen and private cooperatives sell their wares at
prices they set themselves. But free-market prices tend to horrify
Soviets used to state subsidies on most food and small necessities.
   Slaughtered piglets at one of the capital's 28 farmer's markets
were going for 100 rubles, or $160 each, the labor daily Trud said,
and cucumbers and tomatoes cost about $15 a pound.
   ``If it keeps on like this, then in order to buy food for a
holiday, we'll have to save money all year,'' the newspaper said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>