<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0156EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Cuba-Salvador     12-26 0570</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Cuba-Salvador,560</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cuba Believed Sending Weapons to Leftists by Remote Mexican Route</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Cuba is believed to be using a remote Mexican
land route to send weapons to leftist rebels in El Salvador, U.S.
officials say.
   Cuba is believed to have started using the alternate route some
time ago, and indications are that use of the route _ beginning in
the Yucatan Peninsula _ has increased recently, said the officials,
who asked not to be identified.
   Cuba has traditionally used Nicaragua as its primary transit
point for weapons deliveries to its allies in El Salvador.
   It was not clear whether Mexican officials have been approached
by U.S. diplomats about the alleged shipments. There was no
immediate comment from the Mexican government.
   Historically, Mexico has been sympathetic to the Salvadoran
rebels but that support has been more muted since President Carlos
Salinas de Gortari took office a year ago.
   Much of the weaponry sent to the Salvadoran insurgents is
supplied by the Soviet bloc and delivered via Cuba, according to
officials. Recent administration statements indicate that it sees
Cuba _ not the Soviet bloc _ as the principal villain in these
activities.
   As described by officials, the Cubans ship the weapons across
the narrow channel that separates Cuba from the Yucatan Peninsula.
From there, the equipment is sent by truck to El Salvador via
Guatemala although the precise route is not clear.
   Nicaragua's leftist government has been criticized
internationally for its alleged collaboration with Cuba in
supporting the Salvadoran rebels.
   As U.S. officials see it, Cuba's apparent search for new ways to
help the Salvadoran rebels _ without relying exclusively on
Nicaragua _ may be an effort to limit the chances that the
Sandinista role will be exposed more than it has been.
   Nicaragua has denied that its territory has been used for
subversive activities in El Salvador. Such interference is a
violation of Central American agreements signed by Nicaraguan
President Daniel Ortega.
   The Sandinista government has been in the forefront of the
international effort over the past week to have the Bush
administration condemned for its invasion of Panama. Cuba's
response also has been indignant.
   The administration views Cuba's purported use of the route
through Mexico as a supplement to the support the Nicaraguans are
providing as a transit point for Cuban-supplied weapons.
   As evidence that the Sandinista connection has not been
abandoned, the administration has cited the discovery of weapons by
Honduran officials aboard a truck said to have been headed to El
Salvador from Nicaragua.
   The driver of the truck involved in the Oct. 18 weapons seizure
told authorities he had been making the run between Nicaragua and
El Salvador monthly since August 1988.
   According to officials, a more revealing incident occurred on
Nov. 25 when a plane carrying surface-to-air missiles crashed in El
Salvador. The plane had taken off from Nicaragua and its
destination reportedly was rebel-held territory in El Salvador.
   The officials contend Cuba and Nicaragua are intent on providing
assistance to the Salvadoran rebels during the current period
because it may be more difficult in the coming months. One reason:
peacekeepers from the United Nations are being assigned to Central
America to ensure that provisions of regional agreements are being
kept.
   The Bush administration has been pressing U.N. officials to
ensure that the peacekeepers, among other duties, are on the
lookout for deliveries to the Salvadoran rebels from outside the
county's borders.
</TEXT>

</DOC>