<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0802EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Cold 2ndLd-Writethru a0461 12-23 0835</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Cold, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0461,0856</SECOND>
<HEAD>White Christmas _ in Tampa?</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 5 grafs to UPDATE with North Carolina snow record
and for minor editing. Picks up 5th graf, `In Nebraska....'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto DN1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARTHUR ALLEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The arctic air that strained power supplies, threatened orange
trees and brought misery to the homeless today delivered an encore
of polar blasts and record low temperatures, and what could be a
white Christmas in Tampa, Fla.
   ``There was supposed to be global warming, but I don't think
anybody's seen it this month,'' weather service forecaster Edward
Yandrich said in New York. ``The greenhouse effect took a hiatus.''
   The coldest dawn on record broke over some U.S. cities but the
``Siberian Express'' that whistled over the pole through the Yukon
and stalled in the Midwest should be jump-started over the weekend
by a warm front trickling over the Rockies.
   Snow was falling or forecast from central Florida to the
Carolinas and west fo Mississippi, but in other areas east of the
Rockies today's lows should be followed by a pre-Christmas respite.
   Wilmington, N.C. had more than 4 inches of snow on the ground
this morning and up to 8 inches was forecast by afternoon, far
surpassing the record for the date. The snow closed the coastal
city's airport.
   In Nebraska, the weekend forecast called for Christmas Day
temperatures in the 40s, seemingly tropical compared with the
40-plus below recorded Friday morning.
   The cold snap has caused at least 67 weather-related deaths
around the country.
   Snow flurries whitened the Florida Panhandle cities of
Pensacola, Tallahassee, Apalachicola, Milton and Crestview early
today, said Brian Maher of the National Weather Service.
   Up to 4 inches of snow were forecast for Jacksonville, where the
all-time record is 2 inches. Southern Florida, which has escaped
the cold until now, was due for a snap, with a freeze forecast
Sunday in Miami.
   ``People are pouring in,'' said Jeanetta Pratt of the City
Rescue Mission in Jacksonville. ``We don't turn anyone away. ... We
will find a place for them.''
   Citrus growers were nervous, jogged by memories of the $3
billion in damages from hard freezes in 1983 and 1985.
   ``The timing is not good. We have a lot of fruit on the trees
and a lot of concerned growers,'' said Dick Whalley of Florida
Citrus Mutual in Lakeland.
   Texas' $30 million citrus industry was also threatened.
   A sheet of ice and up to 2 inches of snow today covered
Georgia's Golden Isles, normally a holiday haven of winter golf
among the palm trees. Officials closed ice-covered causeways,
cutting off three of the islands from the mainland.
   Cold records were snapped in more than 125 cities Friday. A low
of 23 degrees below zero made it the coldest day ever in Kansas
City, Mo.
   At Rochford, high in the black hills of South Dakota, the
unofficial reading was 60 degrees below zero. The weather service's
official low was 47 degrees below zero at Broadus and Hardin, Mont.
   The all-time record low in the United States is 80 below at
Prospect Creek, Alaska, on Jan. 23, 1971. And in New York City,
where it was a brisk 8 Friday morning, a Soviet emigrant said he
wasn't impressed.
   ``This is nothing,'' said Dora Romadinov. ``In Moscow it's much
colder. Look, there's no snow! The sun is out!''
   The rags-and-riches atmosphere of midtown Manhattan took on a
particularly poignant air, with many of the city's 80,000 homeless
people crowding into shelters and train and subway stations to keep
warm, cheek by jowl with well-dressed Christmas shoppers bustling
from boutiques.
   A homeless man in tennis shoes fished for spare coins in a
fountain; across the street families traipsed into Radio City Music
Hall for the Christmas show.
   Outside City Hall, demonstrators erected four tombstones to mark
the deaths of four homeless people who died of exposure while
sleeping in subways last weekend.
   ``These tragic deaths have gone virtually unnoticed, and we more
affluent New Yorkers seem to have let our hearts grow colder and
more hardened than the bitter winter,'' said David Beseda of the
Coalition for the Homeless.
   Around the country thousands were without heat or power because
of outages caused by overdrawn current, ice on the power lines and
other problems. Heating oil shortfalls were reported at terminals
throughout the Northeast.
   At the Southeast Kansas Branch Experiment Station near Parsons,
the cold was making it difficult to keep water for the cattle from
freezing. Luckily none of the cows at the station were about to
give birth.
   ``It would be a rude awakening to come into the world now,''
said station head Lyle Thomas. ``That would be quite a temperature
drop.''
   Records lows Friday included Pittsburgh at 12 below; Tulsa 6
below; Oklahoma City at 4 below; Denver at 18 below, and
Scottsbluff, Neb., at 42 below.
   ``Records are nice, but who the hell wants to stick around when
they're there?'' said George Matuella of the weather service in
Omaha, Neb.
</TEXT>

</DOC>