<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0205 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1916EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-WallStreet 2ndLd-Writethru   12-26 0597</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Wall Street, 2nd Ld-Writethru,0620</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stocks Closed Narrowly Mixed Amid Interest Rate Concerns</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 18th, `Exxon, forced ...,' to CORRECT location of refinery
to Louisiana sted Texas. Picks up 19th graf pvs, `Bank of ...'.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOYCE M. ROSENBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prices closed narrowly mixed on Wall Street
Tuesday as rising oil prices triggered concerns about inflation and
interest rates.
   Stocks tracked the credit markets for much of the session,
declining in early trading as Treasury prices slumped. Wall Street
later shook off the drop in bonds and moved moderately higher, but
in late afternoon the credit markets continued to fall in response
to a surge in oil prices and stocks gave up their gains.
   The Dow Jones average of 30 industrials closed 2.13 lower at
2,709.26 after rising as high as 2,728.88 earlier in the day.
   Advancing issues were slightly ahead decliners in nationwide
trading of New York Stock Exchange-listed stocks, with 712 up, 664
down and 552 unchanged.
   Volume on the floor of the Big Board came to a slim 77.61
million shares, down from 120.98 million in the previous session.
Many traders were extending their Christmas holiday weekend.
   Nationwide, consolidated volume in NYSE-listed issues, including
trades in those stocks on regional exchanges and in the
over-the-counter market, totaled 99.09 million shares.
   Treasury prices skidded first because of an increase in Japan's
discount rate, which raised the specter of interest rates rising in
the United States to keep up with Japanese yields.
   Bonds continued to drop in later trading because of a surge in
oil prices after several oil companies reported refinery shutdowns.
   Rising energy prices are considered a harbinger of higher
inflation and, in turn, higher interest rates. The Federal Reserve
is less likely to relax credit and allow interest rates to drop
when inflation is accelerating.
   The January price for a gallon of home heating oil jumped nearly
10.74 cents to 92.48 cents on the New York Mercantile Exchange,
while the Treasury's 30-year bond was down about 1\ point, or
$12.50 per $1,000 in face amount, in late afternoon. The bond's
yield soared to 7.99 percent from 7.88 late Friday.
   ``The bond market finally put the chill into traders,'' said
Michael Metz, a stock market analyst with Oppenheimer &amp; Co.
   Stock prices had risen as bargain hunters entered the market but
by late afternoon ``the bargains were resistable and they walked
away,'' Metz said.
   As measured by Wilshire Associates' index of more than 5,000
actively traded stocks, the market fell $2.784 billion, or 0.08
percent, in value.
   The NYSE's composite index of all its listed common stocks fell
0.23 to 191.72.
   Standard &amp; Poor's industrial index slipped 0.70 to 395.65, and
S&amp;P's 500-stock composite index was off 0.61 at 346.81.
   The NASDAQ composite index for the over-the-counter market rose
0.69 to 445.26. At the American Stock Exchange, the market value
index closed at 370.80, down 0.04.
   The most active issue on the NYSE was Bank of New England, which
fell [ to 7].
   Exxon, forced to shut down a major Louisiana refinery following
a weekend fire, was off { at 50[.
   Bank of Boston picked up 1] to close at 18[ after it was
disclosed that a group led by CBS chief executive Lawrence Tisch
held a 6.6 percent stake in the company.
   UAL surged 7\ to 170\ amid continued speculation that the parent
of United Airlines might go private in an employee-led buyout.
   Among other big-name stocks, IBM was down ~ to 94{, AT&amp;T was
unchanged at 44}, and Philip Morris fell \ to 40.
</TEXT>

</DOC>