<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1343EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Romania-Future     12-24 0812</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Future,770</SECOND>
<HEAD>Post-Ceausescu Romania Still Has Tough Rough Ahead</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRYAN BRUMLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The ouster of Romanian strongman Nicolae
Ceausescu is proving to be the bloodiest phase so far in the
revolution that has ended all six hardline communist regimes in the
Warsaw Pact since the summer.
   Security forces loyal to Ceausescu battled rebels through the
weekend, in contrast to neighboring nations, where reform forces
have come to power relatively peacefully.
   The conflict was part of the heritage of Ceausescu's
quarter-century rule, which virtually destroyed the nation's
economic and political fabric, and makes Romania's future cloudier
than those of other Eastern European countries emerging from the
darkness of dictatorship.
   ``The fact that Ceausescu is gone in itself is fantastic, but we
are not out of the woods by any means,'' said Juliana Geran Pilon,
who was born in Romania and now directs the National Forum
Foundation, a conservative Washington lobbying group.
   When the fighting ends, Romania promises to be in worse shape
than the other Soviet nations.
   ``Romania more than any other of the Eastern Europe countries
needs direct Western help in the form of food,'' said James Brown,
a specialist on the region at the RAND Corp. in Santa Monica, Calif.
   Winters can be harsh in Romania, which is as far north as Maine
or Minnesota, and the land is desperately short of food and heating
fuel, Brown said.
   Moreover, thousands of Romanians reportedly died in fighting
before and after Ceausescu's ouster, in contrast to the nearly
bloodless revolutions in Poland, East Germany, Czechoslovakia,
Bulgaria and Hungary.
   Ceausescu was replaced by the National Salvation Committee
transitional government, composed of civilian and military leaders,
some of whom had fallen into disfavor or been jailed under the old
regime.
   The leading figure in the new government appeared to be former
Foreign Minister Corneliu Manescu, 73, who has been under house
arrest in Bucharest since he and seven other top communists wrote a
highly critical letter to Ceausescu last March.
   Another civilian in the leadership was Ion Iliescu, who was
ousted as secretary of the Communist Party Central Committee in
1971 and is reputed to be a strong advocate of reforms. Iliescu
attended Moscow State University with Soviet leader Mikhail S.
Gorbachev, according to Ms. Pilon and another Romanian emigre,
Michael Radu.
   ``He is the closest you can get to a reformer of the Gorbachev
type in the Romanian Communist Party,'' said Radu, who is now a
resident scholar at the Foreign Policy Research Institute, a think
tank in Philadelphia.
   Manescu already has promised elections, although it was not
clear when or under what circumstances they would be held, or who
would run.
   Ceausescu eliminated not only the two former political parties,
the National Liberals and the Peasants, but rival communists as
well, said Petre Nicolae, a former Romanian Communist Party member
who emigrated in 1981.
   Equally pressing for the new government will be the economic
recovery of Romania, which ``is by natural resources the richest in
Eastern Europe, but under Ceausescu developed the worst economy,
with the lowest living standard,'' said Brown. Only Albania, a
communist nation not allied with Moscow, is poorer, he said.
   Ceausescu collectivized once-productive Romanian farms, driving
peasants into the cities to work on heavy industry, which he was
simultaneously building, said Radu.
   Romania was forced to import raw materials for its industry,
however, building up a huge foreign debt that Ceausescu paid off
through austerity that forced the people to live on a
``semi-starvation diet'' with inadequate heating oil and
electricity, said Radu.
   Another rock may lie hidden on Romania's course to recovery,
said Brown and Pilon. The population of the neighboring Soviet
republic of Moldavia is composed 65 percent of ethnic Romanians,
and the republic, one of 15 in the Soviet Union, was seized by the
Soviet Union in one of the Nazi-Stalin pacts at the dawn of World
War II.
   Any popular movement to reunite Romania and Moldavia could cause
friction with the Soviet Union.
   ``Romania is the last domino to fall of the Soviets' East
European allies,'' said Brown. The demise of Ceausescu means that
``all of Eastern Europe is farther along on the path to democracy
than the Soviet Union.''
   That could inspire ethnic groups in the Soviet Union to increase
their campaigns for greater freedom.
   ``The leaders of the national front in Moldavia have been rather
shy of seeking to rejoin Romania as long as Ceausescu was alive.''
But the greater freedom in Romania may embolden them, and ``that
will present a problem for the integrity of the Soviet Union,''
said Brown.
   For the time being, however, ``any new regime that emerges in
Bucharest will have other things on its mind.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Bryan Brumley, former Associated Press
correspondent in Moscow, writes on national security issues from
Washington.
</TEXT>

</DOC>