<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0150 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2026EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-EastGermany 2ndLd-Writethru a0718 12-19 0993</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0718,1024</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kohl, Modrow Meet; Brandenburg Gate to Reopen by Christmas</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with two grafs to CORRECT that reopening is by Christmas
Day, that news was misread on state TV. Picks up 3rd `Modrow, Kohl ...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos DRE3,5,29</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NESHA STARCEVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DRESDEN, East Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Brandenburg Gate, a towering
monument to unity that became a symbol of discord, will reopen by
Christmas after being closed by the Berlin Wall for a generation,
the government said Tuesday.
   State television reported the date after Premier Hans Modrow and
Chancellor Helmut Kohl of West Germany held a summit and said the
gate would be opened on Christmas Eve but its editors late Tuesday
said the announcer had misread his text and that the date for
reopening was by Christmas Day.
   Modrow, Kohl and the mayors of East and West Berlin will preside
Sunday, the television report said.
   On Tuesday, West Berlin police began setting up crowd-control
barriers in front of the wall at the gate, which is in East Berlin.
   At their summit, Modrow and Kohl agreed to negotiate closer ties
between the two Germany's created at the end of World War II. The
Berlin Wall was built in 1961.
   Modrow said that visa-free travel between East and West Germany
will begin Christmas Eve and his government will free all political
prisoners.
   In a joint statement, the German leaders said ``a
good-neighborly relationship between the two states ... is of great
importance for stability in Europe and represents a contribution to
the new European architecture.''
   At a news conference after their meeting, Modrow would not be
specific about the Brandenburg Gate pedestrian crossing, but Kohl
said: ``We will all be able to take a walk across to the
Brandenburg Gate before Christmas.''
   The Brandenburg Gate was built 200 years ago and opened the road
to the region of Brandenburg in Prussia, but its six battle-scarred
sandstone columns became a symbol of division after the wall was
built in 1961. The gate, the size of a five-story building,
remained on the eastern side.
   In 1963, Communist soldiers dropped huge red drapes over the
gate to prevent President John F. Kennedy from looking into East
Berlin when he visited West Berlin.
   With the political upheaval that has ended Communist domination
in East Germany and opened the country's once-locked borders, the
gate is viewed by millions as the symbol of German unity.
   The issue of how to bring the nations closer dominated the first
meeting of Kohl and Modrow, and the public reaction highlighted the
debate raging over possible reunification after more than four
decades.
   Workers in hard hats left their jobs and joined thousands of
others to catch a glimpse of Kohl as he rode to the meeting in his
motorcade of black Mercedes limousines.
   ``Helmut! Helmut!'' and ``Germany, united fatherland!'' they
shouted.
   But posters in the city center read ``Kohl Go Home.''
   ``A Fourth Reich _ Is that why you stayed behind?'' said one,
referring to East Germans who have declined to emigrate to wealthy
West Germany, choosing instead to stay behind and help rebuild
their troubled socialist state.
   East German TV reported 5,000 people demonstrated against
reunification in East Berlin, shouting ``Nazis out!''
   Modrow opposes reunification, and Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard
A. Shevadrdnadze reiterated the Kremlin's opposition to
reunification during a speech Tuesday to the European Parliament.
   ``It is necessary to proceed on the basis of the postwar
realities, namely, the existence of two sovereign German states.
... A retreat from that is fraught with destabilization in
Europe,'' he said.
   Elsewhere in Eastern Europe:
   _ Shooting and fires were reported in western Romania, where
there were reports that security forces have killed hundreds of
people who protested the harsh Communist regime of President
Nicolae Ceausescu.
   _ Former Czechoslovak dissident Vaclav Havel received an
endorsement for the presidency from the Communist premier, Marian
Calfa, who urged that he be elected before the end of the year.
   _ The Soviet Parliament pushed through an economic reform plan
that retains heavy central planning, in a no-confidence vote that
Premier Nikolai I. Ryzhkov and his ministers easily survived.
   _ Lithuania's Communist Party leader urged a united political
front with other parties to press for sovereignty and protect the
Baltic republic from Kremlin pressure. Algirdis Brazauskas avoided
calling for an immediate, direct break with the Soviet Communist
Party or for Lithuanian indepenence, but he left open both
possibilities.
   The German summit began with the signing of an economic
cooperation agreement and pacts to boost cultural and travel ties.
   A significant development is the planned treaty to improve
cooperation and relations. Negotiations will start immediately,
Modrow said, with Kohl saying he hoped the treaty could be signed
by spring.
   The leaders planned a second summit in late January or early
February.
   Perhaps the most striking aspect of the summit was the welcome
Kohl received.
   Later, at an evening rally, a crowd of 20,000 burst into rounds
of wild cheers and applause as the West German leader addressed
them as his ``countrymen'' and promised not to abandon them.
   ``God bless our German fatherland,'' he said.
   Some, however, carried signs supporting East German sovereignty.
   Kohl spoke near the ruins of the Frauenkirche (Church of Our
Lady), destroyed during World War II. There Kohl laid a bouquet in
memory of war victims before addressing the flag-waving crowd.
   ``Unity! Unity! Unity!'' they shouted as he began to speak.
   Kohl promised West German aid for the economic recovery,
assuring the crowd: ``We will not desert our countrymen.''
   But mindful of warnings from East German leaders, the
superpowers and European neighbors that a reunited Germany could
threaten peace, Kohl promised East Germans: ``We will respect what
you decide for the future.''
   The last such summit was Sept. 7-8, 1987, in Bonn, when Kohl met
Honecker. The last time a West German chancellor visited East
Germany was in December 1981, when Helmut Schmidt met with Honecker
in Werbellinsee.
</TEXT>

</DOC>