<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0225 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 2126EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-ViolinMaker-PhotoPkg Adv28   12-22 0317</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Violin Maker-Photo Pkg, Adv 28,0323</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv28</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Thursday, Dec. 28, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Violin Maker Says Carving a Violin Similar to Rearing a Child</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY306,307,308,309,310,311 on schedule for Dec. 23</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAROL PUGH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Severin Schurger spends weeks perfecting a violin,
days just carving and eyeing the scroll of his creation to ensure
its curves are even.
   ``Something I would like to achieve would be to make a nice
scroll quickly,'' says Schurger, who studied playing and making
violins in Japan, where his mentors could carve two perfectly
shaped spruce scrolls a day.
   So carefully does he work that he carves just two or three
violins a year out of spruce and maple, making about 25 violins,
six violas and three cellos in 18 years. The instruments sell for
about $6,000 each.
   ``I just sort of stopped practicing and I wanted to devote my
life to repairing and making violins so other people can play. I
had a passion for it. It's something I really enjoy.''
   In addition to that passion, Schurger brought to the craft his
experience as a cabinetmaker on sailboats. ``There's a big
similarity between a sailboat and a violin,'' he says, likening a
violin's bridge to a sailboat's mast, its scroll to the sailboat's
decorative stem.
   Watching a violin take form is enjoyable, he says, but ``when I
put the varnish on, that's when it comes alive. That's a real big
turn-on.''
   For fun, Schurger spends his free time with voice lessons and
singing in a Miami opera company. But violins are his first love,
and he equates each of his finished instruments to a child that's
ready to leave home.
   ``I don't really get attached to one _ you can't. ... This thing
you are making is going out on the world stage. It's like a part of
yourself.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Dec. 28</NOTE>

</DOC>