<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0096 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1707EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     12-23 0472</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0493</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright and Brief</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: RETRANSMITTING a0601 to fix category code.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>YORK, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A York holiday tradition will be enjoyed across
the country this Christmas, with National Public Radio broadcasting
a local rendition of Christmas carols.
   But don't turn the volume up too high.
   The instrument being played is the steam whistle at the New York
Wire Co.
   ``You can hear it 10 miles outside of York, depending on the
wind irection,'' said Don Ryan, of York.
   At one time the whistle marked the beginning and end of the work
day at the 101-year-old company, which makes screens for the window
and door industry and industrial screens.
   For the past 56 years, the whistle has been blowing Christmas
carols every holiday season, and for 34 of those years it's been a
Ryan family project.
   Ryan, 43, an assistant project director at Motter Printing of
East York, picked it up from his 73-year-old father, Marlin Ryan.
Ryan's son, Scott Ryan, 23, and his daughter, Lisa Ryan, 22, also
help.
   NPR, whose programs are carried by about 400 radio stations
across the country, will broadcast part of a performance recorded
Friday on Christmas morning along with an interview with Marlin
Ryan.
   The NPR team recorded the whistle performance _ ``Silent
Night,'' ``The First Noel,'' ``Oh, Come All Ye Faithful'' and ``Joy
to the World'' _ from a block away, not because of the volume but
to avoid the sound of machinery in the plant.
   In the midst of a rehearsal, 5-year-old Joshua Flickinger of
York, whose mother is an aquaintance of the Ryan family, walked
over to Scott, reached up and tapped him on the elbow.
   ``Are you going to blow it?'' Joshua asked.
   Scott nodded affirmatively.
   ``Don't blow it,'' Joshua shouted. ``It hurts my ears.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   You, too, can join the search for Noriega _ from
the comfort of your desk chair or couch.
   A new computer game called ``Find Noriega'' has hit the market
just days after the U.S. military began looking for Panamanian
strongman Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega in Panama.
   Developed by Eugene, Ore.-based Abracadata, the game sends the
player on a chase that features Noriega look-alikes, an
interrogation of Tammy Faye Bakker, and the interception of top
secret-coded messages from the CIA to President Bush.
   It also includes fighting off fans at Graceland with a Noriega
look-alike disguised as Elvis.
   When news of the Panama invasion broke early Wednesday, Nancy
West, project manager for the company's Adventure of Learning
division, held a brainstorming session with her staff.
   Using a previously written program, they wrote a different,
topical scenario that was ready for shipment by Friday.
   ``A player can change the game as the news changes,'' West said.
   The game runs on any Apple II series or fully compatible
computer and retails for $89.95.
</TEXT>

</DOC>