<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0031EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-LymeDisease     12-22 0610</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lyme Disease,0626</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lyme Disease Test Results Vary Widely in New Jersey</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By A.J. HOSTETLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Wide discrepancies surfaced in results of
Lyme disease tests last year, indicating a crying need for
standardization to help in diagnosis and research, a new study says.
   ``The low agreement among laboratories has many implications for
the diagnosis of Lyme disease and for future research in this
field,'' researchers say in an article appearing Friday's issue of
the Journal of the American Medical Association. ``Finally, the
economic implications are of concern and need to be addressed.''
   In an accompanying editorial, Louis Magnarelli of the
Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station in New Haven says
commercial test kits should be evaluated and state or federal
proficiency testing for laboratories is ``critically needed.''
   The study focused on tests performed on New Jersey residents.
About 90,000 tests for Lyme disease were performed last year in the
state at a cost of $3.5 million, the researchers reported. Patients
were charged $35 to $63.
   ``As the test is increasing in use, it's important to take a
step back and see how the laboratories are agreeing on those
tests,'' said the study's lead author, Dr. Brian Schwartz, formerly
of the University of Pennsylvania and now with Johns Hopkins
University.
   Lyme disease, named for the Connecticut town where it was first
documented in 1975, can cause rashes, headaches and sore muscles,
and if not detected early, arthritis and heart irregularities. It
can be treated with antibiotics.
   The disease is spread through tiny deer ticks and is most common
in suburban and rural wooded areas.
   According to the Centers for Disease Control, 4,572 cases of
Lyme disease were reported in 1988, almost double the 2,368 in
1987. The CDC said only nine states, all west of the Mississippi
River, have not reported Lyme disease.
   For the study, blood specimens from 132 workers of the New
Jersey Department of Environmental Protection were sent to four
laboratories _ a state Department of Health laboratory, one large
commerical lab near Philadelphia and two research centers. The
researchers compared results among the four labs and among samples
sent to the same laboratory.
   All participants had at least two tests, 105 had at least three
and 100 had at least four blood samples taken. The laboratories
used one of two common types of tests.
   The laboratories had a ``low to moderate'' level of agreement
and the results from different samples sent to the same lab showed
similar discrepancies, according to the study.
   The researchers said the discrepancies arose from subjective
interpretations of results, differences in how blood specimens were
prepared, the non-standardized tests and the unreliability of tests
adminstered shortly after a person shows the first symptoms of Lyme
disease.
   The lack of standardized tests harms not only humans who may be
infected, but impedes research on the disease, according to Dr.
Daniel Cohen, associated dean of Penn's veterinary school.
   ``There is a real need for the U.S. government to step in and
standardize the tests,'' Cohen said. ``It's very difficult to pass
judgment'' on comparing research based on different standards.
   The study shows physicians should not rely only on current
laboratory tests, which do not always diagnose the disease in its
early stages, according to Magnarelli.
   ``The clinical picture should come first,'' followed by
laboratory testing for confirmation, Magnarelli said Thursday,
   ``We now have antibody tests of varying sensitivity and
specificity values, and it is not surprising that interlaboratory
comparisons of test resuls often show poor agreement,'' he wrote.
``When one considers the health-care dollars spent on serological
testing, these discrepancies do not rest well with the medical
community or the public.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>