<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1007EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-PauleyFarewell     12-29 0378</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Pauley Farewell,0388</SECOND>
<HEAD>Last `Today' for Jane Pauley</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Holding back tears with her ``precautionary
Kleenex,'' Jane Pauley said farewell this morning after 13 years as
a co-host of NBC's ``Today'' program.
   She said ``1989 is a year nobody is likely to forget'' for
reasons other than a cast change of a television program, but added
that ``next year promises to be pretty interesting, too, and I'm
anxious to get on with it.''
   She promised to keep up friendships with each of her colleagues
on the show, Bryant Gumbel, Gene Shalit and her replacement,
Deborah Norville, as they said their goodbyes at the conclusion of
the last program of the year.
   Recalling Frank McGee, a former ``Today'' regular, Pauley said,
``Frank never said goodbye, but at least 1,000 times he said,
`Don't go far.'''
   Much of the final half-hour of the two-hour show was taken up
with highlights of Pauley's past, including clips of her changing
hairstyles since 1976, and the comments of an anthropologist on the
deeper meanings of her coiffure.
   Tom Brokaw, co-host for the first five years of Pauley's run,
said in a film clip that she was ``the young woman you'd like to
have as your daughter.''
   Weatherman Willard Scott summed her up as ``a class act.'' A
statistician said she'd logged 3,000 shows, conducted 12,000
interviews, asked 88,000 questions and traveled 200,000 miles for
the program.
   ``I look like Alice in Wonderland,'' a maturer and more assured
Pauley said after seeing a clip of her first appearance, Oct. 11,
1976, as she told viewers that ``one and a half years ago I was a
second-string news reader in Indianapolis. ...''
   Pauley became co-host of the top-rated network morning program
when she was 25, stepping into the shoes of the trail-blazing
Barbara Walters.
   Pauley has said her own decision to leave ``Today'' grew out of
her feeling that NBC News President Michael Gartner and NBC Sports
President Dick Ebersol, who also was overseer of ``Today,'' were
not thinking about her future.
   Ebersol said bringing in Norville and other changes were done to
``position the show for the '90s.''
   Pauley was seen in prime time on Wednesday, as co-host of ``The
Eighties'' retrospective with Tom Brokaw. Other prime-time
assignments are planned.
</TEXT>

</DOC>