<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0303EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-US-Panama Bjt   12-22 0862</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-Panama, Bjt,850</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Vows to Hunt Noriega `As Long as it Takes'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WX6</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HARRY F. ROSENTHAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush says the United States will
hunt for deposed dictator Manuel Antonio Noriega for ``as long as
it takes'' to bring him to justice, at the same time thousands of
U.S. troops settle in on Panamanian soil to help restore order in a
chaotic country.
   ``This operation is not over, but it's pretty well wrapped up,''
Bush said Thursday at a news conference that coincided with return
of the first bodies of U.S. soldiers killed in the massive strike
in Panama.
   ``General Noriega is no longer in power. He no longer commands
the instruments of government or the forces of repression that he's
used for so long to brutalize the Panamanian people,'' Bush said.
   At the same time, the president said the U.S. military operation
was ``open-ended as far as going after Noriega, open-ended as far
as restoration of order in Panama,'' where looters were hauling
away goods from virtually every shop in Panama City. Defense
Secretary Dick Cheney said a sizeable troop presence would remain
until a ``condition of normalcy'' had returned.
   The Pentagon said 21 troops were killed in the first two days of
battle, 208 were wounded and one was missing. American military
aircraft were bringing the bodies of the dead back to Dover Air
Force Base in Delaware, their coffins draped with American flags.
   Bush, Cheney and other key administration officials hastened to
claim success for the military strike force at the same time the
United States came under criticism from Latin American nations for
its armed intervention. The Organization of American States held
backstage meetings on a resolution condemning the action, and Peru
withdrew its ambassador from Washington.
   U.S.-backed Panamanian President Guillermo Endara, in a
telephone interview from Panama City with ABC's ``Nightline,'' said
Thursday night he hoped to organize a new police force to take over
from the U.S. military within a month.
   Some congressmen called for the troops to be brought home
quickly, though one _ Rep. Les Aspin, chairman of the House Armed
Services Committee _ said some might have to remain as policemen
until ``Christmas eve a year from now.''
   Said White House press secretary Marlin Fitzwater: ``We
certainly aren't willing to give a timetable to it. But everyone
recognizes this is not going to be a case of going in Wednesday and
coming out Thursday.''
   The president readied a formal report today for Congress
justifying his use of military force, as envisioned under the War
Powers Act.
   Asked at his White House news conference whether the potential
capture of Noriega was worth the cost in American lives, Bush
replied:
   ``No way can you do an operation this large and not have
American casualties. Every human life is precious. And yet, I have
to answer: yes, it has been worth it.''
   Military casualties, he said, ``are a burden which a nation must
endure and all presidents have to face up to, but which we can
never accept.''
   U.S. officials said 59 Panamanian soldiers were killed and 66
wounded. Army Lt. Gen. Tom Kelly said U.S. troops had taken 1,500
prisoners, most of them regulars from the Panamanian Defense Force.
   An American civilian, Candy Helin, 43, was killed by stray fire
from the Panamanian Defense Forces, officials said.
   Speaking a day after ordering 9,500 fighting men into Panama to
join more than 13,000 already stationed there, Bush said that
helping provide a stable environment for Endara's government helps
ensure the integrity of the Panama Canal.
   At one point, he used the word ``invade'' to refer to the U.S.
operation in Panama but caught himself and changed it to ``send in
those troops down into Panama.''
   Bush said that with Noriega on the run and Endara in office,
``The government is beginning to function and the man (Noriega)
controls no forces. And he's out. But, yes, I won't be satisfied
until we see him come to justice.''
   Meanwhile, Fitzwater said Bush still anticipates attending a
Feb. 15 drug summit with Latin American leaders in Cartagena,
Colombia, even though Peru's president, Alan Garcia, pulled his
ambassador from Washington in protest of the Panamanian
intervention and called for postponing the summit.
   Noriega is under indictment in the United States on
drug-smuggling charges and the president has offered a $1 million
bounty for him.
   ``His picture will be in every post office in town,'' said the
president. ``He's a fugitive drug dealer and we want to see him
brought to justice. And if that helps, if there's some incentive
for some Panamanian to turn him in, that's a million bucks that I
would be very happy to sign the check for.''
   The president acknowledged he had changed course from October,
when he was criticized for not supporting or joining the effort by
Panamanian officers to overthrow Noriega.
   ``I think what changed my mind was ... the death of the Marine,
brutalizing, really obscene torture of the Navy lieutenant and the
threat of sexual abuse and the terror inflicted on that Navy
lieutenant's wife, the declaration of war by Noriega,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>