<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0149 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1755EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Poland     12-29 0528</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland,0543</SECOND>
<HEAD>Parliament Votes to Change Name, Rewrite Constitution</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH G. SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Parliament voted to change the country's
official name Friday and to eliminate the constitutional provision
guaranteeing the Communist Party's leading role in the goverment.
   The constitutional changes were adopted 374-1 with 11
abstentions. The majority of the lawmakers immediately rose and
began to sing the national anthem.
   The move changes the nation's Communist-imposed name, the
People's Republic of Poland, to the pre-World War II Republic of
Poland.
   The amendments incorporate into the constitution the reforms won
by the Solidarity-led opposition movement, which won partially free
elections in June and assumed dominance of the government in August.
   Soviet-backed Polish communists changed the country's name to
the People's Republic of Poland when they proclaimed a new
government on July 22, 1944, while the country was still ravaged by
war.
   Both Communist President Wojciech Jaruzelski and Prime Minister
Tadeusz Mazowiecki, head of the Solidarity-dominated government,
were present for the evening debate on the constitutional
amendments.
   The amendments eliminated the phrase that mandated the leading
role of the Communist Party in state affairs and changed a phrase
that called Poland a ``socialist society'' to a ``citizens'
society.''
   The pre-war crown that graced the head of the eagle on the
national emblem also was restored. The crown symbolizes Polish
sovereignty and unity.
   The amendments also introduced a provision giving citizens the
right to create political parties and other organizations. Until
now, the Communist Party, the Democratic Party and the Peasant
Party were officially the only legally recognized parties in Poland.
   Also introduced was a clause guaranteeing protection of private
property.
   The amendments were adopted following a daylong debate, with
lawmakers often haggling over one or two words.
   Earlier, Cardinal Jozef Glemp wished lawmakers strength Friday
for the hard tasks ahead. It was the first visit by a Polish
primate to Parliament in the country's Communist history.
   Glemp met with senators and members of all political
orientations in the Sejm, as the lower house of Parliament is
called, during a midday break in debate over amendments to the
constitution and a possible change in the country's national emblem.
   The lawmakers sang traditional Polish Christmas carols as Glemp
entered the building. ``I address all gathered here with great
respect and I would like to express my frank, patriotic and hearty
wishes,'' Glemp told the lawmakers.
   ``I wish you enough strength for the coming year and that the
link between the nation and the parliament will become stronger and
meet with greater understanding. Please accept those best wishes
from the church of which I am an abject servant,'' he said.
   Solidarity leader Lech Walesa used a series of strikes to force
the Communists to the bargaining table this year, winning
guarantees for a role in the government in exchange for cooperation
on Poland's economic problems.
   But popular support for Solidarity among the masses and
repudiation of the Communists forced them to ultimately grant the
opposition a dominant role in the government. Reform movements
subsequently swept the rest of the East bloc, toppling the old
guard Communist governments in Hungary, Czechoslovakia, East
Germany, Bulgaria and Romania.
</TEXT>

</DOC>