<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0142 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0748EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv04   12-26 0422</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv04,0437</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv04</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Thursday, Jan. 4</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is Thursday, Jan. 4, the fourth day of 1990. There are 361
days left in the year.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
      Today's highlight in history:
   On January 4, 1885, Dr. William W. Grant of Davenport, Iowa,
performed what is believed to have been the first appendectomy. The
patient was 22-year-old Mary Gartside.
   On this date:
   In 1809, Louis Braille, inventor of a reading system for the
blind, was born in Coupvray, France.
   In 1821, the first native-born American saint, Elizabeth Ann
Seton, died in Emmitsburg, Md.
   In 1896, Utah was admitted to the Union as the 45th state.
   In 1948, Britain granted independence to Burma.
   In 1951, during the Korean conflict, North Korean and Communist
Chinese forces captured the city of Seoul.
   In 1960, French author Albert Camus died in an automobile
accident at the age of 46.
   In 1965, poet T.S. Eliot died in London at the age of 76.
   In 1965, President Lyndon B. Johnson outlined the goals of his
``Great Society'' in his State of the Union Address.
   In 1986, Senator Gary Hart, D-Colo., announced he was not
running for re-election, and strongly hinted at a possible run for
president in 1988.
   In 1987, 16 people were killed when an Amtrak train bound from
Washington to Boston collided with Conrail engines approaching from
a side track in Chase, Md.
   Ten years ago: President Carter announced a sharp curtailment in
U.S. grain sales to the Soviet Union and other actions in response
to the Soviet intervention in Afghanistan.
   Five years ago: Ethiopia condemned the evacuation of Ethiopian
Jews to Israel, one day after Israel reluctantly acknowledged it
had mounted the relocation effort in previous months.
   One year ago: Two U.S. Navy F-14 fighters shot down a pair of
Libyan MiG-23 fighters in a clash over international waters off the
Libyan coast.
   Today's birthdays: Actor Sterling Holloway is 85. Actress Jane
Wyman is 76. Former CIA director William E. Colby is 70. Actor
Sorrell Booke is 60. Miami Dolphins football coach Don Shula is 60.
Former heavyweight boxing champion Floyd Patterson is 55. Actress
Dyan Cannon is 53. Opera singer Grace Bumbry is 53. Maureen Reagan
is 49.
   Thought for today: ``Very few men are wise by their own counsel;
or learned by their own teaching. For he that was only taught by
himself, had a fool to his master.'' _ Ben Jonson, English
dramatist and poet (1572-1637).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Thur Jan 4</NOTE>

</DOC>