<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1102EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania-Timisoara     12-23 0474</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Timisoara,0490</SECOND>
<HEAD>Residents Reclaim Streets as Rebel Soldiers Appear to Control Timisoara</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DANISZEWSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TIMISOARA, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rebel soldiers appeared the take
control of Timisoara on Saturday and residents armed with knives
and sharpened sticks roamed the streets of the city, the cradle of
Romania's revolution.
   Medical personnel reported at least two people killed and six
wounded from midnight Friday to midmorning Saturday in fighting
between the army and holdout units of Securitate, the feared
special police force of deposed leader Nicolae Ceausescu.
   Scattered gunfire continued in Timisoara, the nation's
fourth-largest city.
   At the military hospital, doctors spent the night anxiously
listening to the crackle of automatic machine-gun fire and barrages
from tanks. The sound of gunfire surrounded the building, but the
shooters were not seen.
   ``They are here, they are there, they are somewhere in the park.
We don't know where they are, and that's why it's so frightening,''
said a doctor.
   The physician said she had been working without letup since Dec.
17, when police and army units machine-gunned thousands of
civilians.
   Two days earlier, a brutal police crackdown on Timisoara
pro-democracy demonstrators sparked protests that spread across the
nation, leading to Friday's revolt against Ceausescu by citizens
and sympathetic army soldiers.
   Romanian radio said more than 12,000 people had been killed in
Timisoara alone since the uprising began. As in other Soviet bloc
countries seeking reform, the protesters sought an end to
dictatorial one-party rule.
   Among the dead were 7,614 people detained by pro-Ceausescu units
and executed, said the report, which like others was impossible to
verify.
   Tearful residents on Friday congregated at freshly unearthed
mass graves believed to contain the bodies of thousands of
summarily executed victims _ some mutilated.
   The streets on Saturday appeared to be controlled by bands of
citizens wearing armbands of the national colors of blue, yellow
and red. They were armed only with knives, clubs and sharpened
sticks. Open trucks carrying army troops were a frequent sight.
   Buildings were decorated with Romanian flags with their
communist coat-of-arms cut out and with pictures of Ceausescu
behind bars.
   A wounded man undergoing surgery for a bullet hole in his leg
asked for military aid for the anti-Ceausescu rebels.
   ``We need guns and airplanes, all fighting for us and not
against us,'' he said through a translator.
   ``Send Rambo,'' he said grimacing as the surgeon explored his
wound.
   Another victim was a 33-year-old doctor whose leg was shattered
by a bullet as he was coming toward the hospital. It appeared he
would lose his leg.
   ``You come to the hospital to help people, and here I am as a
patient,'' he said.
   He and other Romanians asked a Western reporter for anonymity,
in a reflection of the widespread anxiety that the revolution could
be squelched and repression could return.
</TEXT>

</DOC>