<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0197 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1757EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-CommodityRdp     12-27 0682</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Commodity Rdp,0708</SECOND>
<HEAD>Heating Oil Up Sharply Again; Gold, Silver Plunge</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID DISHNEAU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Heating oil futures rose dramatically again Wednesday on the New
York Mercantile Exchange as speculation continued that supplies
would be tight amid continued cold weather.
   On other commodity markets, gold and silver prices plummeted as
investment buying dried up; orange juice futures were widely mixed;
livestock and meat were mixed; and grains and soybeans were mostly
lower.
   With temperatures slowly warming, oil traders focused on reports
of reduced production capacity at the Gulf of Mexico, where several
refineries were forced to shut down because of cold-weather damage
to equipment.
   The spot January heating-oil contract again led the gainers but
analysts said the market could become extremely volatile in the
next two sessions as the January contracts approach expiration on
Friday.
   ``The risk-to-reward at these price levels dictates a lot of
prudence and probably profit-taking,'' said William O'Neill,
research director with Elders Futures Inc. in New York.
   Wholesale home heating oil settled .36 cent lower to 7.23 cent
higher with January at 99.71 cents a gallon, a six-year high.
   In other energy futures, West Texas Intermediate crude oil
finished .13 cent lower to .16 cent higher with February at $21.78
a barrel and unleaded gasoline was .09 cent lower to 2.45 cents
higher with January at 60.85 cents a gallon.
   Gold futures settled $6 to $7 lower on New York's Commodity
Exchange with the spot contract for delivery in December at $400.80
a troy ounce, a five-week low.
   Silver futures fell 27.2 cents to 30.8 cents with spot December
settling at a seven-week low of $5.24 a troy ounce.
   Market analysts said the investment buying that drove precious
metals up sharply in October and November had dwindled with the
easing of international tensions.
   That development, compounded by typically thin holiday trading
conditions, caused a dearth of willing buyers when commercial
traders turned sellers early in Wednesday's session.
   ``There was nothing on the other side,'' said Stephen Platt, an
analyst with Dean Witter Reynolds Inc. in Chicago. ``As the market
started breaking through chart support, you started seeing some
computer-fund selling, which was not easily absorbed by speculators
so the market pretty much got hammered.''
   The recent bull move had carried spot gold to almost $420 an
ounce and spot silver to nearly $5.90.
   Most orange juice futures soared the permitted daily limit of 5
cents a pound on the New York Cotton Exchange but the January
contract fell 2.95 cents to $1.5015 a pound amid profit-taking
after Tuesday's strong gains.
   Florida officials said they still could not estimate the damage
from the weekend freeze in the orange groves, but an increasing
number of experts said Brazilian imports and stockpiled Florida
juice should prevent a sharp rise in cash prices.
   Cattle futures fell on the Chicago Mercantile Exchange amid
profit-taking after steep gains on Tuesday. Hog futures rose and
pork belly futures fell in light trading ahead of the Agriculture
Department's monthly cold storage report.
   The report showed 68.7 million pounds of bellies in cold storage
as of Dec. 1 compared with 39.8 million pounds a month earlier and
93.3 million pounds a year ago.
   Live cattle settled .15 cent to .48 cent lower with February at
77.45 cents a pound; feeder cattle were .05 cent to .43 cent lower
with January at 84.82 cents a pound; hogs were .08 cent to .35 cent
higher with February at 49.25 cents a pound; frozen pork bellies
were .57 cent lower to .15 cent higher with February at 49.20 cents
a pound.
   Grain and soybean futures prices ended mostly lower on the
Chicago Board of Trade, led by a drop in the soybean market that
analysts attributed mainly to technical factors.
   Wheat futures settled \ cent to 3} cents lower with March at
$4.06\ a bushel; corn was unchanged to { cent higher with March at
$2.39 a bushel; oats were { cent lower to { cent lower with March
at $1.52{ a bushel; soybeans were 1} cents to 4 cents lower with
January at $5.64{ a bushel.
</TEXT>

</DOC>