<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0121 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1343EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     12-22 0652</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0675</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BIG TIMBER, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   NBC News anchorman Tom Brokaw says he
has bought an interest in a 4,000-acre ranch as a mountain retreat.
   Brokaw said he has been looking for Montana property since 1981,
when he came to the state to film an NBC special and became
enchanted.
   ``I think the world of Montana and I've always wanted to be a
part of it,'' he said. He now is honorary chairman of Friends of
Montana, a program of the Nature Conservancy.
   ``Of course, one of the reasons I bought it was to be able to
get away from the frantic life I lead and to have some privacy,''
Brokaw told the Billings Gazette in an interview published Friday.
   ``I don't want to get involved in a lot of controversy there,
but I do want to support some of the things I think are
important,'' he said. ``One of those is certainly protecting the
wide open areas that make Montana so attractive.''
   Brokaw's ranch is near the north flank of the Absaroka-Beartooth
Wilderness Area in an area known for its spectacular peaks and
blue-ribbon trout streams. Actres-model Brooke Shields, actor
Michael Keaton and novelist Tom McGuane are other local landowners.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>REDONDO BEACH, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Times have mellowed for Ron Kovic,
the former Marine whose life is depicted by Tom Cruise in ``Born on
the Fourth of July.''
   Once the angry man who rallied the Vietnam Veterans Against the
War, Kovic is now occupying himself with artwork and other creative
undertakings. He co-wrote the script for the autobiographical film
directed by Oliver Stone. Stone collaborated on the script.
   The film outlines Kovic's nightmarish passage from all-American
boy and superpatriotic soldier to wheelchair activist against the
war.
   In a recent interview, he described his joy that Stone, a friend
and fellow Vietnam veteran, undertook bringing his life story to
film.
   Kovic, 43, said he was at first skeptical about Cruise. Now, he
says he is astonished at his performance.
   ``Many people wondered, `Could Tom Cruise do it? Could he pull
it off?''' Kovic said. ``When he did, it was just so exhilarating.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CHARLOTTE, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 10-year-old Fort Mill, S.C., girl
waiting for a heart transplant was given permission to go home for
Christmas, but not before she got a stellar sendoff from actor Tom
Cruise.
   ``When he came in the room, her heart monitor showed her heart
rate went up to 170 beats a minute,'' Ginger Mason said. ``She was
absolutely so excited she couldn't stand it.''
   Cruise, who was filming Paramount Pictures' ``Days of Thunder''
at Charlotte Motor Speedway, brought Brandi Mason a hat and shirt,
autographed her pillowcase and then visited some of the other
children at Charlotte Memorial Hospital on Thursday.
   Doctors said they don't know when a heart will be available for
Brandi, who was found to have myocarditis, a rare viral infection
of the heart, in July.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Christmas is a special time, a time when one
politician can spend tax money sending special holiday greetings,
and another politician can complain about it.
   Mayor Andrew Young sent jumbo Christmas cards this year to 1,500
area reporters, ministers, supporters and public officials,
including Lt. Gov. Zell Miller _ who just happens to be a candidate
for governor next year, just like the mayor.
   The 9x14 cards, featuring a montage of Atlanta accomplishments,
Young's smiling face and the legend ``Municipal Leader of The Year
1989,'' cost the city a little more than a buck apiece to print,
and 65 cents to mail.
   ``I think it is inappropriate to spend $1 apiece to send a
Christmas card out at the city's expense,'' Miller said Thursday.
``If the man is elected governor, what will he send out in 1991 _ a
billboard?''
   The response from the Young camp? ``What a Scrooge,'' said press
secretary Lee Echols.
</TEXT>

</DOC>