<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0091 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1541EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ClevelandMayor     12-30 0715</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cleveland Mayor,0736</SECOND>
<HEAD>White Ushers in New Decade for Cleveland</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KRISTI UMBREIT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Michael White takes over as mayor this week,
beginning the task of pursuading developers to give as much
attention to neighborhoods in the 1990s as they did to rebuilding
the downtown in the past decade.
   Some of the city's neighborhoods ``look like Germany in 1945,''
he said.
   White, 38, says he has been dreaming of being mayor since he was
a teen-ager.
   ``I've sought this prize for 24 years,'' said White. ``The
things I've done ... have basically been designed to get me where
I'm going to be Monday,'' he said in an interview last week.
   White resigns as a state senator effective Sunday, before being
sworn in Monday. He also has been a Cleveland councilman and
Columbus housing director.
   As mayor, he succeeds George Voinovich, who has held the post
since 1979. Voinovich has been credited at least partly with
steering Cleveland out of financial default and sagging esteem. His
is now seeking the GOP nomination for governor.
   White beat a fellow Democrat, City Council President George
Forbes, in a non-partisan race in November after a bruising
campaign during which White was called a slumlord. He acknowledged
he had rental properties that need repairs.
   Early in a five-man primary _ the city's most heavily contested
mayoral race in more than a decade _ White was considered a long
shot.
   Forbes chose the mayoral race over seeking re-election to City
Council, where he had reigned as president for 16 years. He is
returning to private law practice.
   During the Voinovich and Forbes era, the Cleveland skyline
expanded with office towers, a Lake Erie harbor project and the
start-ups of two bank skyscrapers, hotels, a shopping mecca and a
Rock and Roll Hall of Fame. There's also talk of a new baseball
stadium.
   Voinovich said pointedly that he and Forbes ``are leaving with
the lights on and the cranes hanging.''
   But White says the downtown renaissance hasn't improved the
quality of life in many of Cleveland's neighborhoods. He promised
that his administration would foster growth on both sides.
   ``I think that what I bring to the office is kind of a view of
balance,'' he said. ``Our neighborhoods are falling apart. Some of
them look like Germany in 1945.
   ``You cannot have a great town with only a great downtown. There
has to be a balance.We will continue to lose people in this town if
we do not restore the quality of life at the neighborhood level.''
   In the past 20 years, the city's population has declined to
550,000 from 800,000.
   Other problems include a nearly 50 percent dropout rate in the
city school system, 40 percent of the population living below the
federal poverty level, shabby public housing with maintenance so
poor that the city had to name a new housing authority director to
get federal aid, and drug peddling and other crimes common in big
cities.
   One of White's goals is to add about 240 officers to bring the
city's police force up to 2,000.
   Others are establishing a better environment for small
businesses, building more housing, and continuing to encourage what
he sees as improvement in race relations in a city where the
black-white population is roughly even.
   White also said he favors tax abatement to encourage economic
growth, but said he would wring from developers as many
stipulations beneficial to the city as he could, such as certain
percentages of jobs given to Clevelanders and funding for
neighborhood improvements.
   More than $200 million in tax abatements have been granted to
developers of downtown in the past two years.
   ``If we build 100 new buildings but six or seven out of 10 of
those jobs continue to go to suburbanites, then we haven't made any
progress,'' he said. ``And today, six out of 10 jobs in Cleveland
go to people who don't live here. That's why we have so much
poverty.
   ``I've said to the business community, yes, I will help them
with economic development, but they must help me with the creation
of new jobs.''
   With White's swearing-in comes a wave of fresh faces. One-third
of the 21 council members are new, and a new council president was
named after Forbes' departure.
</TEXT>

</DOC>