<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0135 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1941EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-ColdRdp 1stLd-Writethru a0606 12-27 0781</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cold Rdp, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0606,0798</SECOND>
<HEAD>South Suffers After-Effects of Cold Wave</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 13th graf, `That ravaged..., with 4 grafs to UPDATE with
experts predicting rise in supermarket produce prices, record heating oil
price in New Hampshire. Picks up 14th graf pvs, ``It's a...</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROGER PETTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Plumbers worked overtime across the South on Wednesday to repair
thousands of water pipes that burst when they froze in record low
temperatures, and frozen waterways are slowing shipping and
devastating some commercial fishing.
   Temperatures have eased since record lows late last week and
during the Christmas holiday weekend, with temperatures in the 40s
and 50s Wednesday in Georgia.
   Homeowners and plumbers in Houston were working as fast as they
could to repair thousands of pipes broken during three days of
record-setting lows.
   ``We're so busy I can't believe it,'' said Charles Rumsey,
general superintendent at Crown Plumbing. ``We're trying to hold
the men's working days down to 12 hours, but some of them are
getting 15 or 16 hours.''
   Houston officials said that by midday Wednesday, water pressure
in the city was up to 80 percent as leaks were gradually plugged.
   Residents of some Houston apartment complexes had been without
water since Friday. ``They're dipping water from the pool and
carrying it to their apartments to flush their toilets,'' said Jean
Williams, manager of Regency Arms apartments.
   In Jackson, Miss., Mayor Kane Ditto said it was impossible to
say when the city's water problems might be over.
   Ditto said crews working to restore service to the remainder of
60,000 homes and businesses that had been without water were still
finding new problems. He said there were 33 breaks in Jackson's 900
miles of water lines Wednesday morning, up from 10 the night before.
   Non-essential federal, state, county and city government workers
stayed off the job in Jackson.
   ``Our guys are working 'til they drop. I don't know how much
longer they can keep up this pace,'' said Bennie Payne, owner of
Central Plumb It Yourself Supply in Baton Rouge, La., which also
sends plumbers on house calls.
   The 50,000 residents of New Orleans' public housing projects
have had little or no water. City officials said water pressure
dropped from a normal 65 pounds per square inch to about 47 because
of pipe breaks.
   The Louisiana freeze, called the harshest of this century by
meteorologists, sent temperatures below 32 degrees for almost 82
hours in New Orleans and below 15 degrees for 15 hours.
   While water pressure plunged, the economic pressures of the
freeze pushed produce prices higher at the wholesale level. Prices
were expected to climb soon in supermarkets as well, experts said
Wednesday.
   ``The pipeline stays filled for three to seven days in advance
of any major prices change in the marketplace,'' said Reggie Brown,
spokesman for the Florida Fruit and Vegetable Association in
Orlando. ``You'll start seeing it showing up probably within a
week.''
   Heating oil prices continued to climb as well. In New Hampshire,
the cost per gallon of home heating oil hit a record high $1.37, up
from 81 cents on Oct. 5, Jonathan Osgood, director of the
Governor's Energy Office, said Wednesday. The previous high was
$1.29 in March 1981.
   The freeze ravaged the citrus industry in Louisiana's
Plaquemines Parish for the second time since 1983. Unlike growers
in Florida and Texas, Louisiana orchard owners got most of the
fruit picked before the freeze, but the trees were damaged.
   ``It's a disaster second only to a big hurricane,'' said Luke A.
Petrovich, president of the Plaquemines Parish Council. ``We've
lost our entire citrus industry, all our truck farms are wiped out,
and the fishing industry will be hit real hard.''
   ``Not only are there thousands of frozen fish in the marshes,
but we also have oysters frozen in their shells. The seafood has
been totally spoiled, ruined,'' said Joe Buras, president of the
Delta Commercial Fishermen's Association of Plaquemines Parish.
   In the East, this is turning out to be the iciest winter on
Chesapeake Bay, with foot-thick ice in places, since the winter of
1976-77 when much of the estuary froze.
   The Coast Guard has been hampered in its efforts to clear
shipping lanes because of the four ships it used for ice-breaking
are in for repairs, said Lt. Cmdr. Steven Waldmann.
   Farther north, up to a half-foot of ice on Pittsburgh's three
rivers has brought barge and boat traffic to a virtual standstill.
Ice covers 70 percent to 100 percent of the Allegheny, Monongahela
and Ohio rivers.
   ``The river people I talk to are saying this is the worst
they've seen since the winter of 1977-78,'' said Coast Guard Cmdr.
Anthony Regalbuto.
</TEXT>

</DOC>