<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0159EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Santa Bjt   12-19 0593</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Santa, Bjt,0618</SECOND>
<HEAD>Santa Warned of Promising Too Much</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto DC1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VAL CORLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   If your child tells you Santa promised
something outrageous, I know the reason: Santa doesn't always hear
so well.
   I should know. I was Santa. For a few hours, anyway.
   ``Did she tell you what she wants for Christmas?'' the mother
asked, hurrying over after her youngest and shyest child had her
turn with St. Nick.
   ``I didn't understand her,'' Santa replied.
   ``Oh, well. She won't tell us and we had hoped ...'' The mother
trailed away, smiling and accompanied by a laugh that wasn't a
ho-ho-ho.
   To help me catch the children's words, I kept a small tape
recorder at my side. Playing back the tape, the only speaker always
clear was the one on the mall intercom: ``Will the owner of the
blue Ford parked ...''
   The little blond girl spoke softly, and Santa couldn't make out
her name. Asked what she wanted for Christmas, she said, ``A
ball.'' Or was it, ``a doll?''
   Sunday was Santa's busiest day of the week at the Southridge
Mall. Tracey Bruner Rayhons, the mall's marketing director, agreed
to let me sit in for the regular Santa to hear childrens' dreams.
   Ms. Rayhons had one condition. ``Don't promise them anything. We
had one Santa last year, we never did find out which one it was,
who promised the kids anything they wanted. Boy did we have some
parents angry,'' she said.
   When I tried on a Santa suit, I found my doctor hadn't lied: No
padding was needed. Mike Wiley, one of four Santas working at
Southridge, had some pointers before I left for Santa's seat.
   The children will be well behaved, he said.
   ``I've had a couple who like to pull the beard, but I don't
think any of us have been wet on yet. I think we've all been real
lucky.''
   He said children ``are a lot more mellow this year. They don't
ask for a whole lot. ... What they're asking for is for one gift
that's expensive, like a Nintendo, bicycle, VCR, television, like
they're asking for one thing and that's all.''
   In my hour and a half as Santa, I found he was right.
   But I also found out more.
   Most children were eager to sit on Santa's knee. The only
beard-pullers were a couple of toddlers looking for something to
hang on to.
   Some young ones liked the idea of seeing Santa from a distance.
Up close was a different matter. It was just hang on to Mommy and
... maybe next year.
   There were times when management's advice came in handy.
   With Don on my left knee asking for ``a real puppy'' and sister
Misty on my right knee asking for ``a bicycle and a ... real kitty
cat,'' it may have been best not to promise anything.
   When a petite brunette named Allison sat on my knee, her father
piped in, ``She hasn't been cleaning her room like she should.''
   She confirmed that, but promised, ``I will when I get home.''
   Not only that, but she said she would keep her room clean until
Christmas and even after Christmas. All she wants is ``a dolly that
cries.''
   And there was Elizabeth, who also asked for a doll that cries,
and a puppy. She also gave something back.
   ``Want to hear a secret?'' she suddenly asked, looking at Santa.
   She whispered in Santa's ear: ``I love you Santa Claus.''
   ``Ohhh, Santa Claus loves you, too.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>