<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0149EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Romania Bjt   12-30 0744</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania, Bjt,0770</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Romania Leaders End Restrictions But Invite Communist Help</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERRY LEONARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The country's revolutionary leadership
scrapped harsh food and gasoline rationing rules enforced by
executed dictator Nicolae Ceausescu but invited other Communists to
join in reshaping Romania.
   The governing council of the National Salvation Committee, which
took power Dec. 22 during a popular uprising backed by the army,
moved to take full control of the country Friday and to prepare it
for free elections set for April.
   It also promised to remain in the Soviet-led Warsaw Pact
military alliance and to honor other international commitments.
   Meanwhile, the army said it had begun to try Ceausescu loyalists
who waged fierce battles against army forces and citizens during
the revolt.
   Romania's interim president, Ion Iliescu, signed decrees to lift
rules allowing motorists only 8 gallons of gasoline a month and
another that eliminated food rationing that kept people from eating
meat for months at a time.
   The government also halted food exports _ a key part of
Ceausescu's harsh economic policies _ and citrus fruits, coffee and
other items have appeared on store shelves for the first time in
ages.
   Iliescu also did away with a rule that banned private citizens
from meeting with foreigners or from offering them board and
lodging.
   Earlier in the day, the revolutionary government changed the
country's official name from the ``Socialist Republic of Romania''
to just ``Romania'' and removed the Communist symbol from the flag.
   However, Budapest radio in Hungary quoted Iliescu as saying in
an interview that members of the Communist Party will have a role
in a new democratic Romania.
   ``We are in a situation in which we have to ask all of our
society's forces to act in unity and to join forces,'' Iliescu said.
   ``Many Communist Party members are indispensible,'' he said.
   Ionescu told a news conference that several thousand forces
loyal to Ceausescu had surrendered or been captured.
   However, several hundred other members of Ceausescu's dreaded
Securitate remained in hiding, defying an order to surrender or
face execution, said Cazimir Ionescu, a vice president in the
National Salvation Committee's 145-member governing council.
   The council had ordered the Securitate holdouts to surrender by
5:00 p.m. Thursday or face death.
   The Military Council, which takes orders from the fledgling
government, issued a ``last call'' for surrender by
anti-revolutionary forces. It said those who refuse to do so will
face trial and be ``summarily sentenced.''
   An army statement said its forces were ``in full control in all
parts ... of the country'' and that military tribunals set up to
try the special police forces had begun their work ``and will
continue to try all acts of terrorism.''
   It gave no indication of how many trials had been held.
   Romania's uprising began on Dec. 15 with demonstrations in
Timisoara. The protests spread and Ceausescu and his wife, Elena,
fled their palace in Bucharest on Dec. 22 after the army sided with
the citizens.
   The couple was captured a day later, then shuttled about in a
constantly moving armored car for the last three days of their
lives, Britain's Independent Television News said. It quoted Capt.
Mihail Lupoi, identified as a senior army official, as saying that
Ceausescu was kept in the moving car to prevent rescue attempts.
   The Ceausescus were executed Monday after they were convicted at
a secret trial of crimes against the state during his 24-year rule.
   Romania's former defense minister was given a hero's funeral on
Friday. Gen. Vasile Milea died of a gunshot wound Dec. 22, senior
officers have said.
   Before fleeing, Ceausescu had denounced Milea and claimed he had
committed suicide. But Romania's new leaders say he was executed
for refusing to order army troops to fire on demonstrators.
   Milea's funeral in a small hall at the Military Academy was
shown on national TV.
   The new leadership received support and recognition Friday from
several Western countries, including the United States. A special
envoy of President Francois Mitterrand of France met with first
deputy president Dumitru Mazilu.
   Romania's new leaders are likely to meet the leaders of the six
other Warsaw Pact countries for the first time in Sofia, Bulgaria,
on Jan. 9.
   The Soviet-led Eastern trading bloc Comecon also meets for its
annual congress on that day.
   It will be the first time that the leaders of the seven Warsaw
Pact countries will gather since all of their nations embraced
democratic reforms.
</TEXT>

</DOC>