<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0242 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0511EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-SPE--Bride&amp;Groom:Demographics     12-18 0853</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-SPE--Bride &amp; Groom: Demographics,0869</SECOND>
<HEAD>RETRANSMITTING b1341; changes coding.</HEAD>
<HEAD>SPECIAL EDITION</HEAD>
<HEAD>Bride &amp; Groom: Demographics</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BARBARA MAYER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Newsfeatures</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Social scientists will tell you that the October, 1989, wedding
of Susan Parsons, 28, and Donald Waite, 48, is an good example of
demographic trends affecting marriage in the United States.
   According to demographer Arlene Saluter, U. S. Census Bureau
statistician, people are older at first marriage than they once
were. The median age for women is 23.6 years; for men, 25.9. These
1988 statistics are the latest and represent a trend.
   ``Young adults are postponing marriages until later to pursue
education and careers. The high cost of housing is also a factor,
as is the acceptability of alternative arrangements, such as
sharing households,'' says Saluter. Most people _ at least 90
percent _ will marry eventually, she adds. Statistics show that the
chance of divorce is lessened by advanced education, so by waiting
longer, couples may have a more stable marriage.
   At 28 for the bride and 48 for the groom, there is a 20-year age
difference between bride and groom. Though unusual, this is part of
a slight trend toward age differences of eight years or more
between partners, according to U.S. National Center for Health
Statistics demographer Barbara Foley Wilson.
   Comparing 1976 and 1986, Wilson found that in 1976, the groomrecently
married couples whom she interviewed for
her book, problem areas included combining possessions, lifestyles
and close relationships and adult friendships they had with
individuals other than their spouse. Another important issue is
that women come to marriage committed to careers.
   McDonough, whose own recent marriage was to a man 16 years older
and of a different religion, says that there are more marriages
between individuals of different religious or cultural traditions
who may have vastly different sets of experiences and expectations.
``The families have a lot more work to do to assimilate this new
union.''
   The differences can be either problems or opportunities.
Depending on how they are handled, ``they can lead to a stronger
marriage between partners who bring more to a relationship.''
   Unexpressed fears about differences can lead each partner to
doubt the wisdom of the step they are about to take. When unvoiced,
the worries become a generalized anxiety which becomes attached to
the wedding event itself.
   ``Almost everyone I interviewed experienced a great deal of
turmoil about small details of the ceremony and reception,'' she
says. Becoming overwrought over such issues as where people sit or
the color of the napkins is usually a cover for other emotional
issues.
   ``There is almost always a question of whether the couple will
satisfy themselves or their parents.'' Since they are older and
more self-assured and often paying for the wedding themselves, the
couple are more likely to make decisions in keeping with their own
wishes. However, how to do this tactfully, without alienating the
parents, is often a central issue of the wedding.
   ``My parents were divorced very acrimoniously 15 years ago, and
I wanted them both to attend my wedding. It took a lot of work. I
had it at a friend's home rather than at my mother's so my father
would feel comfortable, invited my father's new wife and made sure
to invite my mother's close friends, too,'' says McDonough.
   ``The attempts I made were helpful, although at times my husband
and I thought about simply eloping. I am glad I had the wedding I
always wanted.''
   She advises others to verbalize their fears because ``it is more
fun to plan a wedding if you are aware of the emotional issues and
try to do something about them.''
   ``In the 1950s we had a little box we all called marriage. The
'60s threw it out and everyone said no more boxes for me,'' says
Barbara Tober, editor of Bride's magazine.
   In the 1970s many people realized marriage could be reshaped to
fit their needs, and in the 1980s many became comfortable with the
idea that their marriage could be different from others.
   Tober says that ``the key to '90s attitudes will be that
marriage is something you mold, a freeform sculpture, a work of art
in progress that you can do anything you want with.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>