<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0227 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1802EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Bonds     12-29 0461</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bonds,0482</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bond Prices Close Lower</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bond prices fell moderately Friday after a
survey of Chicago purchasing executives indicated strength in the
manufacturing sector of the economy.
   The Treasury's 30-year bond fell 5-32 point, or about $1.56 per
$1,000 face amount. Its yield edged up to 7.97 percent from 7.96
percent late Thursday.
   Analysts said an initial report that Chicago purchasing managers
were reporting a slowdown in the economy gave the market a lift,
but when the report was corrected, showing strength among
industrial firms, bond prices turned downward.
   Traders believe the Federal Reserve is more likely to relax
credit and allow interest rates to fall if the economy is slowing.
The report of a pickup in the economy led them to believe the Fed
would not push rates downward.
   The National Association of Purchasing Management will issue its
monthly survey on the economy next week. Traders are looking to
that report and the government's unemployment figures for possible
signals on how the Fed might act.
   Trading was extremely light Friday as most traders had closed
their books for the year.
   The federal funds rate, often an important reflection of the
Fed's credit policy, fell dramatically as the central bank added
funds to the system to help banks meet their yearend needs.
   The rate, which closed at 9} percent on Thursday, fell to 7{
percent.
   Analysts said the extra reserves were needed by banks for the
long weekend.
   In the secondary market for Treasury bonds, prices of short-term
governments were unchanged to 1-32 point lower, intermediate
maturities were off 1-16 point and long-term issues were down about
3-16 point, according to Telerate Inc., the financial information
service.
   The movement of a point is equivalent to a change of $10 in the
price of a bond with a $1,000 face value.
   The Shearson Lehman Hutton Daily Treasury Bond Index, which
measures price movements on all outstanding Treasury issues with
maturities of a year or longer, fell 0.93 to 1,188.41.
   Yields on three-month Treasury bills fell to 7.82 percent as the
discount dropped 9 basis points to 7.58 percent. Yields on
six-month bills rose to 7.99 percent as the discount picked up 7
basis points to close at 7.59 percent. Yields on one-year bills
rose to 7.75 percent as the discount rose 1 basis point to 7.24
percent.
   A basis point is one-hundredth of a percentage point. The yield
is the annualized return on an investment in a Treasury bill. The
discount is the percentage that bills are selling below the face
value, which is paid at maturity.
   In the tax-exempt market, the Bond Buyer index of 40 actively
traded municipal bonds rose 1-16 point to 93 14-32. The average
yield to maturity was unchanged at 7.25 percent.
</TEXT>

</DOC>