<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1057EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Scandinavia-Smoking     12-25 0730</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Scandinavia-Smoking,0754</SECOND>
<HEAD>Facing Tough Restrictions, Scandinavian Smokers Fight Back</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARTHUR MAX</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>STOCKHOLM, Sweden (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Shoved into corners, banned from local
flights and excluded from some hotel floors, smokers in Scandinavia
say they have had enough and are beginning to fight back.
   Smokers have banded together in Sweden, Norway, Finland and
Denmark to combat perceived discrimination, to lobby against new
anti-smoking laws and to share tricks to sneak a smoke against the
rules.
   ``We want to protect smokers' rights. We don't want to encourage
people to smoke, especially not young people,'' said Bengt Oste,
chairman of the Swedish lobby Smokepeace.
   ``Too many smoking bans were coming from all over the place. It
was about time somebody did something about it,'' said Tore Dinesen
of the Danish smokers' organization, Henry.
   In their latest action, the pro-smoke groups published a
pamphlet on how to avoid the smoking bans on local flights by
Finnair and SAS, the Scandinavian Airlines System. The rule was
extended Nov. 1 to any international flight less than 100 minutes
long on these airlines.
   The ``Smokers' Guide To Smokers' Flights in the Nordic Area''
lists flights by other airlines with smoking sections that have
stopovers in the region.
   To get to Copenhagen from Helsinki, the pamphlet says, a
traveler can fly Pan Am to Stockholm and transfer to a Soviet
Aeroflot aircraft to the Danish capital. A heavy smoker might have
time for two cigarettes on each leg.
   Finnair claims it was the first airline to introduce non-smoking
seats more than 20 years ago.
   Smokepeace, which adopted the symbol of an Indian in feathered
headdress puffing a peace pipe, says it just wants a fair deal for
smokers and non-smokers.
   In 10 months it has drawn 1,500 members. Some are non-smokers
offended by discrimination, Oste said, and 53 percent are women.
   ``Smokers have to back down a bit, so as not to harm or irritate
non-smokers,'' said Oste, an anchorman for Swedish TV news who says
he has been a pipe smoker for 45 years.
   At the same time, fair provision should be made for smokers, he
said. ``Too often, company managers and politicians are making
decisions without asking workers,'' Oste said.
   Henry, launched two years ago by a Danish wine and tobacco
merchant, enlisted Denmark's pipe-smoking Foreign Minister Uffe
Ellemann-Jensen in an advertising campaign last spring to plead
that ``tolerance and consideration are the basis of living
together.''
   Although it doesn't release financial figures, Henry reportedly
gets part of its finances from the Danish tobacco industry.
   Norway has enacted some of the world's toughest anti-smoking
laws, which critics say make lighting a cigarette indoors illegal
almost everywhere except at home.
   Sweden's parliament is in the early stage of drafting a new
comprehensive law, which many legislators want to fashion on the
Norwegian model. Steps toward a similar bill in Denmark were
interrupted by an election and have been dropped for now.
   Among Norway's regulations is a ban on smoking in any office
occupied by more than one person, even if everyone in the room is a
smoker.
   Smoking was outlawed in schools, hospitals, theater lobbies and
public transportation. Selling tobacco to youths under 18 is
illegal.
   Many Scandinavian hotels have no-smoking rooms, and some have
barred tobacco from entire floors.
   Most work places have set aside smoking areas. The Stockholm
daily Aftonbladet banned smoking anywhere in its new nine-story
building except in a few glassed-in rooms by the coffee machines on
each floor. They are so poorly ventilated that workers refer to
them as ``the gas chambers.''
   High tobacco taxes also are meant to deter. In Norway cigarettes
cost about $4 a pack, slightly more than in the other countries.
Roll-your-own tobacco is becoming more popular in Denmark, where
pipe tobacco has less tax.
   One dodge from smoking bans is snuff, a plug of tobacco that
many Scandinavians stick under their upper lip.
   The government in Oslo adopted an ambitious and, critics say,
unrealistic target of making Norway smoke-free by the end of the
century.
   The critics note that although tobacco has not been advertised
since 1973, four out of 10 Norwegians smoke and consumption is
rising by 500 tons of tobacco a year.
   The other governments have gone no farther than to endorse the
World Health Organization's goal to reduce smoking by 25 percent in
the next 10 years.
</TEXT>

</DOC>