<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0201 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1907EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-Panama-KellyText 3rdAdd   12-20 0831</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Panama-Kelly Text, 3rd Add,a0844 et. seq.,700</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHN: would choose.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Q: Did you go to the _
   Q: So, you said that was where heavy fighting was, so you think
you got _ got rid of a lot of them there?
   ADM. SHEAFER: We've been trying to track each of the hostage
reports, and we have probably almost a dozen. And we have great
difficulty with the information we have in corroborating any of
them. They vary in numbers ranging from the lows of two or threes,
to the highs in the teens.
   Q: But Admiral, there was a CBS news producer taken captive at
one hotel with an ABC producer, and that ABC producer has been
released. How can you say that's not a credible report?
   ADM. SHEAFER: If that's true, I'm unaware of it.
   Q: General, do you have any information about _
   Q: What role is the military playing playing in the search for
General Noriega?
   GEN. KELLY: Pardon?
   Q: What role is the military playing in the search for General
Noriega? And how is that going?
   GEN. KELLY: Every role we can. We have every spigot turned on
that we can turn on to find the fugitive, Mr. Noriega, and we
expect we eventually will.
   I _ let's start with this gentleman _
   Q: Just following that up, General, if I might. You said at the
outset, or at least we were told this morning, one of the aims was
to capture General Noriega. Can you walk us through why that
apparently failed, at least in its initial stages. Were you in the
right place? Was he in the wrong place?
   GEN. KELLY: Ahhh. He was obviously in the right place. He's a
crafty devil, as you know. He grew up in a very tough academy, so
he's been used to this for many years. He allegedly changes his
place of residence about four times a night. We had him spotted
several times during the day. We thought we had a pretty good idea
where he was last night. We went there and he wasn't there.
   Q: Where was that?
   GEN. KELLY: I would _ I'd prefer not to say because he may go
back there and we may want to go back there again. But, we're
looking for him very hard. Of course, that's all contingent on
intelligence. And what I meant to say when ``we had all the spigots
turned on'' is, we are turning on all our looking, listening, and
hearing devices to see if we can't pick him up.
   Q: When you say _ excuse me for interrupting you, General. When
you say that you spotted him several times today, are you
suggesting to us _
   GEN. KELLY: Not today _ I said yesterday.
   Q: Yesterday. You're suggesting to us, though, that you're not
far away from him, that you expect to capture him. Can you make
that kind of commitment?
   GEN. KELLY: No, I can't. You would probably have to ask my boss
for that kind of commitment. But, I'd just tell you we're going to
try as hard as we know how to try to help Mr. Noriega get a plane
ride up here.
   Q: General _
   Q: Sir, have you spotted him at all today _ since this attack
began?
   GEN. KELLY: Have we spotted him today? No, we have not. He has
gone underground.
   Q: General, one of the other missions _ stated goals for this
mission was to provide greater safety for Americans in Panama.
Especially in view of what you just said, you all don't where some
of these PDF forces have gone _ off into the jungles, or they may
re-emerge in urban areas. How exactly has this operation improved
safety for Americans? And what kind of safety are you going to
provide on the streets of Panama?
   GEN. KELLY: First, I had also said, we know of no American yet
who has been injured as a result of this operation with the
exception of one American dependent which I think you know about
who was killed yesterday.
   Second, we said we have a concern that they have gone off into
the jungle. We don't know for a fact that that's what they've done.
If they have gone off into the jungle, I think there's every chance
that we'll go off after them.
   I think that by tomorrow you'll begin to see a greater presence
on the streets of Panama City. One of the main reasons that we went
down with the size force we're going down with, and it's very
substantial, is to protect life and property. And our goals, when
we went to Panama, was to keep the Canal open, to protect American
lives, to protect American property, and to prepare _ to help the
Panamanians re-achieve democracy.
   Q: Do you think Americans there now are safe today?
   GEN. KELLY: In the main, yes, I do. None of them have been hurt.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>