<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0181 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2118EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Argentina-Economy     12-18 0530</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Argentina-Economy,0552</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Economy Minister Lifts Exchange, Price Controls</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ED McCULLOUGH</BYLINE>
<HEAD>Associated Press Writer</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUENOS AIRES, Argentina (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government Monday announced
it is lifting controls on foreign exchange and most prices it has
unsuccessfully tried to set for years.
   The move came as President Carlos Menem struggles to carry out a
tricky program of privatization of state-run businesses,
deregulation and reduced government spending to remedy decade-long
inflation and related economic problems.
   When banks reopen after a government-ordered banking holiday
that began Friday, the value of the austral, the beleaguered
national currency, will be determined by market forces, new Economy
Minister Antonio Erman Gonzalez said.
   Most prices will also be set in the marketplace.
   However, the holiday will continue at least through Tuesday,
said the spokesman for the Economy Ministry, Miguel Alurralde.
   Erman Gonzalez announced the new measures Monday in a 10-minute
speech that followed his swearing-in to replace Nestor Rapanelli.
Rapanelli resigned Friday after a plunge in the value of the
austral on the black market.
   The importance of the measures was underlined by the fact that
the speech was broadcast nationwide from Government House. In
attendance were the president, vice president, Cabinet ministers,
business and union leaders, and top brass of the armed forces.
   In his own short speech, Menem insisted his economic program
would continue. He said it is the only hope for remedying the
country's economic problems.
   ``On this flight, we are all on board, absolutely everyone, and
this plane has no parachutes,'' Menem said. ``Anyone who wants to
jump may jump, knowing the consequences.''
   Erman Gonzalez, the third economy minister in Menem's
5-month-old government, takes over amid economic distress that
threatens to become a political crisis for Menem.
   The president risks losing public support he needs in the short
run until his reforms produce long-term benefits. A wide segment of
organized labor, a powerful force in Argentina, and business have
attacked his plans.
   Even Menem's own labor-based Peronist Party has shown only
lukewarm support for the reforms.
   Inflation that moderated to 6.5 percent in November from 197
percent in July is projected to top 30 percent in December.
   One of the causes of economic deterioration the past week was
massive buying of dollars. Analysts said the buying was triggered
by the government's unexpected decision to suspend repayment of
principal on internal bonds for two years and raise taxes on
exports.
   Erman Gonzalez instead annulled the unpopular tax hikes and said
the government would try to repay the principal on time.
   While price controls for food and many consumer and industrial
products will be lifted, Erman Gonzalez said the government will
continue to regulate rates for gas, electricity, water, telephones,
bus and commuter train fares, and other public services.
   To help Argentines pay for the rates, Erman Gonzalez authorized
a monthly pay increase for public and private workers of about $20.
   Lifting controls on the austral means exporters may convert
their dollars at the Central Bank at a much higher rate. The move
is intended to induce them to turn in dollars it has been hoarding
from overseas sales of beef and grain.
   The Central Bank has previously been regulating the exchange
market.
</TEXT>

</DOC>