<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1438EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DarkChristmas     12-24 0611</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dark Christmas,0632</SECOND>
<HEAD>Disabled Miner Wants No Tree at Tough Christmas</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KELLY P. KISSEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MAN, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   There's no Christmas tree to brighten Jesse
Crabtree's living room, and the disabled coal miner has no holiday
cheer this season.
   ``He says, `Why get a tree if we don't have any gifts to put
under it?''' said Crabtree's wife, Edith.
   Crabtree, 68, suffers from black lung disease _ caused by
breathing coal dust _ and has been hospitalized for two heart
attacks and prostate gland surgery. He also was hurt in a 1976
mining accident and now spends his retirement money on medicine
rather than Christmas.
   ``Now, Jesse just sits there in the bedroom, day in and day out,
looking out the window. That's his life,'' Mrs. Crabtree said.
   Crabtree blamed their economic plight on the bitter battle
between the United Mine Workers and the Pittston Coal Group Inc. A
union poster is taped to the wall near his bed.
   Nearly 1,700 miners struck Pittston's coal subsidiary in
Virginia, West Virginia and Kentucky on April 5, after working 14
months without a contract. The walkout was prompted by Pittston's
refusal to participate in an industry agreement on how to fund
costly miners' retirement and health plans.
   The UMW and Pittston failed Saturday in a last-ditch effort to
reach a pre-Christmas settlement. Negotiations recessed with an
agreement that both sides would return to the bargaining table
Wednesday.
   Mrs. Crabtree said she and her husband get $911 a month through
retirement benefits and black lung program payments. Their mortgage
and medical bills alone exceed that.
   ``We're making it from hand to mouth. We're poor but we're
proud,'' Mrs. Crabtree said. ``We had a little bit of savings put
away.''
   For a while, the couple's Christmas dinner was uncertain.
   ``I don't even know if I'm going to have a turkey or a ham,''
Mrs. Crabtree said just before the president of a UMW local arrived
with a 15-pound turkey.
   ``She said she needed a turkey for Christmas. I told her it
would be no trouble,'' said Bethel Purkey from UMW Local 5815.
   Crabtree is upset Pittston changed its pensioner health policy.
After the old contract ran out, the policy began providing 80
percent coverage after a $200 deductible. It had been 100 percent.
   ``Pittston owes him and should pay his medical bills. They are
the ones that caused his problems,'' his wife said.
   Pittston spokeswoman Susan Copeland said 80 percent coverage is
a nationwide standard.
   Cheryl van Tilburg, a spokeswoman for Blue Cross-Blue Shield in
Chicago, the nation's largest health insurer, said ``80-20 is
definitely the norm for group coverage.''
   Crabtree, a union miner for more than 37 years, also is upset
the UMW worked for Pittston for 14 months without a contract. He
said it's possible the company would have continued full coverage
for pensioners if a contract had been reached.
   ``If they had gone on strike then, they'd have a contract now,''
Crabtree said. ``No contract, no work. If a fellow (strike breaker)
wanted to go on in, you keep him from going. You can't have anyone
going in while others are staying out.''
   Mrs. Crabtree said a 100 percent health plan would give her one
less thing to worry about.
   ``I'm 4 feet, 11 inches tall. He's 230-some pounds and I handle
him alone,'' she said. ``I take him to the doctor alone, pull the
car up to the garage. Don't ask me how I do it.''
   One way she does it is by letting Christmas pass virtually
unnoticed.
   ``He needs me and he knows I'll be there,'' Mrs. Crabtree said.
``Mister, I'll never let him down.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>