<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 2334EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Thornburgh-Gray 2ndLd-Writethru   12-29 0661</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Thornburgh-Gray, 2nd Ld-Writethru,a0703,640</SECOND>
<HEAD>No Prosecution, Discipline in Rep. Gray Leak Case</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS last graf with two grafs to give Gray comment</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By W. DALE NELSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Attorney General Dick Thornburgh said Friday
he has decided against prosecution or disciplinary action over a
news leak about a Pennsylvania Congressman because the department
can't identify the leaker.
   In a letter to Sen. Joseph Biden, D-Del., chairman of the Senate
Judiciary Committee, Thornburgh said investigators had been
``unable to identify with certainy the original source'' of
unauthorized disclosures to CBS reporter Rita Braver about the
office of Rep. William H. Gray III, D-Pa.
   Thornburgh said the investigators also told him that ``the
nature of the confirmations alleged to have been forthcoming to Ms.
Braver'' were ``uncertain.''
   Consequently, he said, the investigators told him that ``it
would be futile and impossible to pursue a prosecution based on the
available evidence.''
   ``Therefore, I have accepted the recommendation of the
investigators and prosecutors that this matter be closed without
prosecution,'' the attorney general said.
   ``Furthermore, since the investigation has not produced
sufficient evidence to enable me to ascertain that any present
employees of the Department of Justice was responsible for the
disclosure, I have determined that no termination of employment or
other disciplinary action is justified in this matter at this
time.''
   The leak occurred while Gray was seeking election in the House
as majority whip, prompting accusations from Democratic lawmakers
that Thornburgh's aides were the source of a political leak.
   Two weeks after Ms. Braver's broadcast that Gray's office was
being investigated, the Justice Department stated that Gray was not
a target of the investigation and was cooperating with the probe.
   Gray, who was elected whip, said the day after the broadcast he
had been told by FBI agents from the Philadelphia office in a
Memorial Day interview that he was not a target and that they were
looking into the possibility that one of his employees held a
no-show job. Nothing more has been heard of that investigation.
   Thornburgh said he wrote to Biden because the Judiciary
chairman, at a committee hearing June 2 at which Thornburgh
testified, ``raised questions with regard to my concerns over
unauthorized disclosure of information.''
   Biden said in a statement that Thornburgh wrote him that the
department's Office of Professional Responsibility concurred with
all conclusions and recommendations of the Criminal Division in the
matter. But the senator said committee staff members had checked
with the Office of Professional Responsibility and though that
office had been consulted, ``It has never seen the criminal
division report or any of its conclusions, and therefore could not
have an has not concurred in those conclusions.''
   Normally, the Office of Professional Responsibility would be
responsible for recommending disciplinary action against department
employees.
   Thornburgh's spokesman, David Runkel, said, ``I don't know whom
Sen. Biden or his staff has been talking to, but that statement is
clearly at odds with what the attorney general was told by the
criminal division.
   The head of the Office of Professional Responsibility, Michael
E. Shaheen, does not have a listed telephone number.
   Thornburgh told the senator that 11 FBI agents devoted
approximately 385 days to the investigation, interviewing members
of the U.S. attorney's office in Philadelphia, the Philadelphia
division of the FBI, FBI headquarters, the criminal division of the
Justice Department and the attorney general's office.
   He said about 30 other persons were also interviewed, including
members of Congress, aides to Gray, confidential sources and
several reporters. Ms. Braver ``declined to be interviewed or
otherwise cooperate with this investigation,'' he said.
   Gray said in a statement from Philadelphia: ``The failure of
this investigation raises the white flag of surrender to those in
the Department of Justice who use false leaks to defame innocent
citizens. The leaks in this case were designed to harm me, but
their real victim was the integrity of our criminal justice
system.''
   CBS said Ms. Braver was on vacation.
</TEXT>

</DOC>