<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0136 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1919EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-WhiteHouse-Pamphlets     12-18 0298</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-White House-Pamphlets,300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Leaflet Regulation Declared Unconstitutional</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETE YOST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal judge Monday declared
unconstitutional a 1976 regulation barring people from passing out
leaflets in an area around the White House.
   U.S. District Court Judge John Pratt issued the ruling in the
case of a Carol Ann Fennelly, charged with illegally distributing
pamphlets June 21 along East Executive Avenue between the White
House and Treasury Department.
   The material urged passers-by to write members of Congress in
favor of housing for the homeless.
   The judge said the regulation is an unconstitutional limitation
on First Amendment rights.
   National Park Service regulations approved in 1970 were part of
an effort to protect White House security by restrictions on
demonstrations. The 1976 amendments were drafted to preserve an
atmosphere of calm and tranquility at memorials and buildings
associated with past presidents.
   In 1976, ``nothing was said about the underlying purpose of
presidential security which was the overriding purpose of the
comprehensive regulations issued in 1970,'' Pratt said. The 1970
regulation allowed distribution of pamphlets and leaflets by not
mentioning them.
   ``In contrast, the 1976 revision ... for the first time banned''
distribution of material in the White House Park area, the judge
said.
   Pratt noted that Fennelly ``would violate the regulation by
passing out a leaflet,'' but ``could convey the same identical
message by word of mouth without fear of arrest.''
   ``A ban on the free distribution of leaflets and pamphlets in
those remote areas far removed from the White House itself has no
conceivable governmental interest,'' Pratt said in his opinion.
   ``It's distressing that the government continues to try to
impose these ridiculous limitations on free speech in the nation's
capital,'' said American Civil Liberties Union lawyer Arthur
Spitzer, who handled the case.
</TEXT>

</DOC>