<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0357EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Judge-Profile     12-18 0558</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Judge-Profile,0576</SECOND>
<HEAD>Black Political Leaders Say Vance Led Fight Against Segregation</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Judge-Explosion, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BIRMINGHAM, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Assassinated Federal Judge Robert S.
Vance was praised upon his death for helping blacks overcome the
onetime segregationist politics of George Wallace.
   Vance, a 58-year-old judge on the Atlanta-based U.S. 11th
Circuit Court of Appeals, was killed by a mail bomb that went off
at his home Saturday afternoon. His wife was seriously injured.
   ``Bob Vance led the fight to integrate the state Democratic
Party. We are very much saddened by his death,'' said state Rep.
Alvin Holmes of Montgomery. ``He was a great friend to the black
people of this state.''
   Vance, a Talladega native, entered the University of Alabama at
age 15. When he was a senior, he was elected student body
president. He graduated from the university's law school in 1952,
spent two years in the Army and in 1955 received a master's of law
degree from George Washington University Law School in Washington.
He then returned to Birmingham.
   Vance first gained statewide attention with his efforts to get
the Legislature to redraw legislative districts to reflect changes
in population in the early 1960s.
   At that time, the State Democratic Executive Committee was
controlled by a staunchly conservative coalition of states rights
advocates and Dixiecrats loyal to then-Gov. Wallace.
   Vance, then a young lawyer, became the champion for Democrats
who were afraid that Wallace's growing influence would cause a
split with the national Democratic party.
   He was elected state party chairman in 1966 and won re-election
twice during the next 11 years. He soon began the political
wrangling necessary to fully integrate the all-white Democratic
party.
   ``He ushered in a new era,'' said Joe Reed, chairman of the
state party's black political caucus. ``Bob Vance was a healer and
a builder for the Democratic Party and because he lived, the
Democratic Party is alive today.''
   Under Vance's leadership, Reed and Mobile attorney Arthur D.
Shores became the first blacks from Alabama to attend a national
Democratic convention _ the 1968 Chicago convention.
   At that convention, when Wallace, Vance and John Cashin of the
now-defunct National Democratic Party of Alabama were trying to
seat delegates, the delegates chose Vance's integrated group.
   One of Vance's first moves as state party chairman was to bring
about the removal of the white rooster _ a symbol of white
supremacy with the slogan ``For the Right'' _ from atop the party's
election ballots.
   ``He felt like we had to move forward out of the racial unrest
we were in,'' said Sen. Howell Heflin, D-Ala., who met Vance more
than 30 years ago when they were young trial lawyers. ``He believed
we ought to approach these things, not draw a line in the dust.''
   Wallace unsuccessfully challenged Vance's leadership many times.
``He ran someone against him every year,'' said Executive Director
Al LaPierre.
   ``Vance had to be very courageous to take a stand against
Wallace,'' said Holmes, who was appointed with other blacks by
Vance to the party's executive committee.
   Vance invited blacks to his home in the exclusive Birmingham
suburb of Mountain Brook during the 1960s and `70s ``when blacks
weren't allowed out in Mountain Brook unless they had on a maid
uniform,'' Holmes said.
   ``He understood the suffering and discrimination that black
people had endured in the state of Alabama.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>