<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0150EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-NuclearContracts Bjt   12-28 0684</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Nuclear Contracts, Bjt,680</SECOND>
<HEAD>Companies, Not Taxpayers, to Pay for Nuclear Arms Mistakes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government will stop reimbursing operators
of nuclear weapons plants for their own criminal fines,
environmental penalties, fraudulent losses and other questionable
costs, officials say.
   The decision, spurred by growing congressional criticism of the
weapons program, marks the most fundamental change in the Energy
Department's weapons contracting system since companies were
recruited to build the first atomic bombs in the 1940s.
   The companies traditionally have been allowed to recover
virtually all their costs, even those resulting from their own
negligence. The logic was that weapons production was so
specialized and vital to national security that the government
could not afford to risk losing a plant operator over money matters.
   The new thinking, under Energy Secretary James D. Watkins, is
that the weapons contractors will perform better if they are held
accountable for their mistakes.
   Under the new system, the government will continue paying
contractors' normal operating expenses, but for the first time all
costs resulting from negligence will be borne by the companies
instead of the taxpayers, Stephen A. Wakefield, the Energy
Department's general counsel, said in an interview.
   Wakefield said a formal proposal to amend the department's
regulations to end the practice of reimbursing all contractor costs
will be announced in January, and it could become official policy
by late spring. Detailed application would be made in the annual
negotiations with each contractor that normally set the terms under
which bonuses are awarded in the coming year.
   Private companies run all 17 major facilities in the nuclear
weapons complex. The Energy Department spends about $11 billion a
year on the arms program.
   The issue of liability is important because the plants have
billions of dollars in environmental problems, and some continue to
violate environmental laws. The Rocky Flats plutonium processing
plant in Colorado is under FBI investigation for possible criminal
violations of federal hazardous waste laws.
   In exchange for assuming a bigger share of the financial risk of
operating the weapons plants, the contractors will be offered
bigger bonus payments for excellent work, Wakefield said.
   Wakefield declined to say how much extra bonus money would be
made available, but he said ``it would not be unreasonable'' to
think current fees might be doubled.
   The companies typically can earn several million dollars a year
for operating the plants. For example, Westinghouse Electric Corp.,
which holds contracts to run several of the plants, earned $3.9
million in bonus fees from April through September for operating
the Savannah River nuclear facility near Aiken, S.C.
   Wakefield said ``there are varying levels of concern'' among the
companies which have been briefed on the outlines of the contract
changes.
   ``A couple of them have said, `Well, this is one more thing we
have to consider in ... deciding do we want to be in this
business,''' Wakefield said, adding that none so far has indicated
it would withdraw as a result of the changes.
   Wakefield cited several examples of circumstances under which
the department no longer would reimburse the contractors:
   _Environmental fines and related legal costs stemming from
actions by the contractor that could reasonably have been avoided.
Last month the General Accounting Office, the investigative arm of
Congress, reported that the department had reimbursed two plant
contracts for $295,000 in fines levied for violations of hazardous
waste laws _ plus $529,000 in the companies' legal costs.
   _Damage to government property as a result of negligence.
Wakefield said that if the new contract provision had been in place
in January, E.I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Co., which then was operator
at Savannah River, would have been liable for damage to several
nuclear reactor valves caused by improper testing procedures. The
department has estimated the valve damage at $20,000.
   _Damage to third parties, including people and property outside
the plant, due to negligence by the contractor. Wakefield said this
could, under some circumstances, mean the contractor instead of the
government would have to pay for environmental or health damage
resulting from the spread of radioactive contamination.
</TEXT>

</DOC>