<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1623EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-OldJustice     12-24 0613</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Old Justice,0630</SECOND>
<HEAD>Challenge To Mandatory Retirement Provision Continues</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER GRAFF</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MONTPELIER, Vt. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   State Supreme Court Justice Louis Peck
turned 71 on Sunday, putting him a year beyond the state
constitution's retirement age for judges. But he still sits on the
bench, making decisions and waging his battle against a rule he
says is age discrimination.
   Peck's case, which goes before a federal appeals court next
week, pits him against the state of Vermont, which argues that a
federal anti-discrimination law cannot supersede a state's power to
choose its judges. On his side are others who believe that people
should be judged on their ability, not on the calendar.
   ``The right of an able person to work regardless of his or her
age is among the most basic in our society,'' the American
Association of Retired Persons, which has more than 30 million
members, said in its legal brief siding with Peck.
   ``It is the people of each state who establish the state's
judiciary,'' the state of New Mexico countered in a brief filed on
the side of Vermont.
   Peck won the first round of his case last July when a federal
judge, also 70, ruled that the federal age-discrimination law
protects appointed state judges. But federal judges in neighboring
Massachusetts have ruled the other way.
   The federal law exempts elected officials and top appointed
policy-makers, but does not specify whether appointed judges fit in
the latter category.
   The state has appealed the ruling favoring Peck to the 2nd U.S.
Circuit Court of Appeals. Oral arguments are scheduled for Jan. 5
in New York.
   Peck, who was appointed to the bench in 1981, said he never
expected his fight to attract such attention, and has said he would
consider retiring after proving his point in court.
   ``When this first started, I didn't want any publicity. I just
wanted this to be settled quietly,'' he said recently. ``I must
admit the publicity it has received has stimulated my own interest
in the case and my determination to see it through.''
   Under the Vermont Constitution, Peck should have retired last
Dec. 31, at the end of the year in which he turned 70. But he
stayed on, refusing an order to step down.
   The state attorney general sided with Peck, but a series of
rulings in federal judges in neighboring Massachusetts supported a
state's right to impose mandatory retirement on state judges. The
state court administrator placed Peck on retirement status
effective June 30.
   Peck filed an age discrimination charge with the federal Equal
Employment Opportunity Commission challenging the retirement order.
The EEOC picked up Peck's case and filed a complaint in federal
court that resulted in the ruling in favor of Peck last July.
   The state's rights argument, however, found favor with the 1st
U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals in a ruling on Massachusetts'
mandatory retirement provision. The court ruled it could not find
``a sufficiently clear statement by Congress that it intended to
overrule the clear intent of the people of a state in an area
intimately and fundamentally related to that state's
self-governance.''
   The 1st Circuit ruling has meant judges in Massachusetts must
retire at age 70.
   With the conflicting rulings, lawyers on both sides are eager to
see a decision by the U.S. Supreme Court.
   ``I think that's what we hope for,'' said Peck. ``Until we get
that, you are going to have courts ruling different ways.''
   Rep. Peter Smith, a Vermont Republican, has introduced
legislation designed to amend the Age Discrimination in Employment
Act to clarify that appointed state judges are covered under the
act.
   His bill, if enacted, would not be retroactive.
</TEXT>

</DOC>