<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0088 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1441EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Royals     12-19 0672</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Royals,0690</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prince Deplores `Calamitous Decline' of English Usage</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GRAHAM HEATHCOTE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prince Charles on Tuesday lamented the
``calamitous decline'' in literacy in Britain and the degeneration
of the English language into a ``dismal wasteland of banality,
cliche and casual obscenity.''
   In June, the heir to the British throne had complained English
was taught ``so bloody badly'' that he had to correct all the
letters written by his staff before they were sent out.
   His criticism Tuesday was more elegantly phrased but equally
biting in singling out the teaching profession for discarding the
idea that English is a precious legacy to be handled with care.
   ``We have seen the abandonment of learning the rules of grammar
and the parts of speech as boring and irrelevant,'' he said.
   Past attacks by the 41-year-old prince on the state of language,
modern buildings, inner cities and urban sprawl, have made him
respected and feared.
   In the packed London church of St. James Garlickhythe, he
presented prizes to children for their memorized recitations from
the Book of Common Prayer, attributed to Archbishop of Canterbury
Thomas Cranmer, to mark the 500th anniversary of his birth.
   He then deplored the ending in schools of learning poetry by
heart and the idea of English as something really to be learned, by
effort and application.
   The prince also denounced what he called ``banal'' modern
versions of Cranmer's Prayer Book and the 17th century King James
Bible. The originals were commanding and poetic, he said.
   ``Poetry was for everybody. But banality is for nobody. It might
be accessible for all but so is a desert,'' he said.
   ``Is it entirely an accident that the defacing of Cranmer's
Prayer Book has coincided with a calamitous decline in literacy and
the quality of English?'' he asked.
   He said Britain had produced the world's most successful
language, which had been the medium for some of the greatest
literature, ``yet a great many people today look in dismay at what
is happening to that language in the very place where it evolved.''
   ``Looking at the way English is used in our popular newspapers,
our radio and television programs, even in our schools and our
theaters, they wonder what it is about our country and our society
that our language has become so impoverished, so sloppy and so
limited _ that we have arrived at such a dismal wasteland of
banality, cliche and casual obscenity,'' the prince said.
   He said his stand for England's heritage had led to accusations
of nostalgia for an irrelevant past.
   ``The fear of being considered old-fashioned seems to be so
all-powerful that the more eternal values and principles which run
like a thread through the whole tapestry of human existence are
abandoned under the false assumption that they restrict progress,''
he said.
   The prince had his audience laughing when he declared:
   ``Well, I'm not afraid of being considered old-fashioned, which
is why I am standing here wearing a double-breasted suit and
turn-ups _ pant-cuffs _ to my trousers, ready to declaim the fact
that I believe the Prayer Book is a glorious part of every English
speaker's heritage and, as such, ought to be a grade one listed
edifice'' _ the English phrase for a state-protected building.
   After the speech, Doug McAvoy, general secretary of the National
Union of Teachers, said teachers of English had not given up
standards but they had an exhausting task in state schools.
   The Rt. Rev. John Taylor, Church of England bishop of St.
Albans, said Cranmer's language was magnificent and beautiful but
the church's new liturgy enabled modern congregations to use a
language reflecting their hopes and prayers.
   A government-appointed committee reported last year that
although English is the first language of 320 million people around
the world and spoken daily by about 1 billion people, the teaching
of English had been neglected in its country of origin. The
committee recommended that every school employ a teacher whose sole
job is to ensure the language is used properly.
</TEXT>

</DOC>