<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0151 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 2344EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HughesLawsuit     12-27 0391</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hughes Lawsuit,0403</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Employee Says Firm Covered Up Microchip Defects</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FULLERTON, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A former Hughes Aircraft Co. engineer
has filed a $9.6 billion lawsuit against the company charging that
it concealed a potential defect in computer chips used in defense
systems.
   The lawsuit was dismissed as mostly ``fantasy'' by a Hughes
official.
   Metallurgist Michael C. Denlinger, a former senior staff
engineer at a Hughes division here, filed the lawsuit in U.S.
District Court in Santa Ana last June, but it remained sealed until
it was served on Tuesday.
   Denlinger claims that more than 4 million computer chips used in
national defense systems may corrode because Hughes took a shortcut
in a soldering process that can cause cracks in what should be
airtight surfaces.
   ``We think our national security is compromised,'' his attorney,
Frank Barbaro, said Tuesday.
   Denlinger, who worked for Hughes for 14 years and was most
recently responsible for testing strengths of materials, brought
the action under the federal False Claims Act, which allows
whistleblowers to share in damage awards in defense fraud cases.
   Damages in false claims cases are usually triple the value of
the products. Denlinger's attorneys claim the company sold $3.2
billion worth of systems using the allegedly faulty computer chips.
   The U.S. Department of Justice must decide whether to join such
false claims lawsuits, which usually are sealed while the
department investigates.
   The department told the federal court that its research of the
Hughes case was complete, and court papers indicated the department
would make a decision on the case within 60 days.
   Denlinger alleges that defective chips installed since 1984
caused two failures in the Navy's submarine-launched Advance
Capability torpedo system.
   While routine screening found two defective chips in torpedoes,
the lawsuit's allegations are wrong, said Dan Reeder, a spokesman
for Hughes' Ground Systems Group in Fullerton.
   ``Most of the stuff is just fantasy,'' he said. ``We have never
had any failure of the test torpedoes due to hardware problems
during any of the hundreds of runs we have gone through.''
   Denlinger said in the lawsuit that he repeatedly wrote memos
about possible cracking of the chips but they were ignored. He
resigned in November 1988.
   Hughes said Tuesday that it has inspected every chip since
becoming aware of a cracking problem in 1985, and said it was an
industry-wide problem.
</TEXT>

</DOC>