<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0018EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Obit--Wedemeyer     12-20 0326</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit--Wedemeyer,310</SECOND>
<HEAD>World War II Planner Dead at 92</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FORT BELVOIR, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gen. Albert C. Wedemeyer, who drafted
the ``Germany first'' strategy under which the allied coalition led
by the United States and Britain won World War II, is dead. He was
92.
   Wedemeyer, who had Alzheimer's Disease, died Sunday at the
Fairfax Retirement Center at Fort Belvoir.
   Wedemeyer was a temporary lieutenant colonel when the United
States entered the war in December 1941. His first major assignment
came earlier that year when President Franklin D. Roosevelt asked
the then War Department for suggestions as to how to win the war
that the nation was surely going to have to enter.
   Gen. Wedemeyer, at that time the only American officer to have
graduated from the Germany Army general staff college, drew up what
became known as the ``Victory Program,'' advocating the defeat of
German armies on the continent of Europe by allied ground troops.
   After the U.S. entry into the war, a refined version of the plan
was adopted by Roosevelt and British Prime Minister Winwston
Churchill, and, despite a few detours, led to the invasion of
Normandy in June 1944 and the defeat of Germany.
   Wedemeyer stayed with the War Department until October 1943 when
he was made deputy chief of staff to British Adm. Lord Louis
Montbatten, the commander-in-chief of the Southeast Asia Command.
   After returning to the United States in 1946, he took on a
fact-finding mission in China, racked by civil war between
Communist and Kuomintang forced, for President Truman, and held
stateside posts until his retirement in 1954.
   His decorations included the Distinguished Service Medal with
Oak Leaf Cluster and the Distinguished Flying Cross.
   In retirement, he served as director of several corporations,
published his memoirs and settled on a farm in Boyds, Md. He moved
into the Fairfax Retirement Home earlier this year.
   Wedemyer is survived by his wife, Elizabeth; two sons, six
grandchildren and nine great-grandchildren.
</TEXT>

</DOC>