<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0152 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1832EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Bulgaria     12-29 0608</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bulgaria,0631</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gov't Will Allow Turks to Take Back Moslem Names</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SLOBODAN LEKIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SOFIA, Bulgaria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government will allow Bulgaria's
Turkish minority to take back Moslem names they were forced to
abandon during an anti-Turk campaign that began in the early 1980s,
an official said Friday.
   Word of the policy change came at the end of a one-day meeting
of the Communist Party's policy-setting Central Committee. It was
confirmed by Politburo member Alexander Lilov at a news conference.
   ``We adopted (today) a policy based on guaranteeing all freedoms
starting with the free choice of names, religion and schools
without any restrictions,'' Lilov said.
   The name change campaign, which gathered momentum in 1984,
affected hundreds of thousands of people, including Pomaks, or
Moslem Slavs, living in southern Bulgaria.
   The forced change and increasing curbs on ethnic and religious
rights of the 1.5-million-strong Turkish minority earlier this year
prompted more than 300,000 to emigrate to Turkey after Bulgarian
authorities gave them passports.
   Lilov blamed longtime Communist leader Todor Zhivkov for the
name change, which he said had harmed Bulgaria's reputation abroad.
   Zhivkov was ousted last month as part of the wave of reform that
has swept across Eastern Europe.
   ``The Central Committee has determined that no documents exist
in the files of the Politburo (to prove) that such a decision was
ever formally adopted,'' said Lilov, who was not a member of the
Politburo at the time the name change was ordered.
   ``This represents one of the peaks of Zhivkov's
irresponsibility,'' Lilov told reporters.
   While the Central Committee was still in session, about 2,000
journalists gathered in front of the party headquarters demanding
freedom of the press.
   At the rally, a speaker of Moslem faith said the first birth
certificate with a Moslem name in the past 10 years _ that of
one-month-old Osman Bajram Husseinov _ had just been issued by the
municipal registrar.
   In Ankara, Turkish Foreign Minister Mesut Yilmaz said Turkey was
pleased by the decision to revoke the name change.
   Earlier Friday, thousands of ethnic Turks and Pomaks braved a
blizzard to stage a noisy but peaceful demonstration through
downtown Sofia for the second straight day, chanting ``Unity'' and
``Give us back our names.''
   About 6,000 of the protesters circled the parliament building,
vowing not to disperse until their ``problems are resolved once and
for all.''
   ``We will remain here whatever happens, until persecution is
stopped and our demands are met,'' said Milen Rusev, one of the
protesters.
   He said that in 1980 he had been forced ``at gunpont'' to change
his Turkish name of Mehmet Refatu.
   At the Central Committee meeting, the date of an extraordinary
party congress was moved up from March 19 to Jan. 30.
   The official news agency BTA quoted Andrei Lukanov, the No. 2
man in the Politburo, as saying the decision was prompted by ``the
dynamic development of the political situation in the country and
the need to speed up the renewal process in the party.''
   Lukanov reportedly also called for ``a complete and final
de-Stalinization of the party,'' adding that ``the party shall be
one of dialogue and social consensus.''
   At the news conference, Lukanov was asked if the Communist Party
would concede defeat if it lost in free elections scheduled for May
1990.
   ``In a democracy the possibility of losing elections is always
present _ this should be respected by all political forces,
including the Communist Party,'' Lukanov said.
   An end to the party's guaranteed monopoly on power is one of the
main demands of the Union of Democratic Forces, an umbrella forum
of independent political groups, trade unionists and
environmentalists.
</TEXT>

</DOC>