<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0301EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Bush-ChinaUproar     12-20 0720</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bush-China Uproar,710</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON TODAY: A Double Standard on China and Rest of World</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERENCE HUNT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP White House Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush's secret dealings with the
repressive government in Beijing suggest a double standard in the
way the administration views China and the rest of the world in
terms of human rights and aspirations for democracy.
   With the Soviet Union, for example, the United States demands
that human rights stand as a centerpiece of the superpower
relationship.
   Yet with China, Bush is moving to resume business with its
aging, hardline leaders even though they remain doggedly
unrepentant about the June massacre of pro-democracy demonstrators
and continue to suppress their citizens.
   On Tuesday, Bush approved the export of three communications
satellites expected to be launched by China, and he moved to end a
ban that kept the U.S. Export-Import Bank from aiding companies
doing business with China.
   Winston Lord, the U.S. ambassador to China until last April,
says the United States would not have reversed course so swiftly if
the killings had occurred in Eastern Europe.
   Breaking with the administration because of its secret
diplomatic missions to Beijing, Lord said the U.S. overtures were a
sign of ``cultural, if not racial, bias.''
   Bush has been an outspoken champion of democratic reforms that
are toppling hardline communist regimes from power in Eastern
Europe.
   Along those lines, the White House on Tuesday denounced the
``systematic denial of human rights'' in Romania and called on its
government to cease the ``brutal repression'' that some witnesses
say has left hundreds dead.
   It is a message that could be aimed just as easily at China.
However, Bush has muted his criticism of Beijing and he only
reluctantly accepted sanctions imposed by Congress against China.
   An old China hand, Bush has taken the position he knows better
than his critics. It's hard to judge exactly what Bush is doing
since he refuses to talk about it publicly.
   ``You see,'' Bush explained to reporters, ``I still believe that
sometimes to effect change, you talk in confidence to people.''
   He insists his secret dealings do not amount to condoning the
repression in China. ``That is not a good rap and it is not true,''
Bush said.
   As for the secrecy of Bush's actions, White House press
secretary Marlin Fitzwater says the president's conduct of foreign
relations ``will, from time to time, involve him in making trips,
making contacts, talking to people and keeping it secret.''
   The administration's actions have sharpened tensions between the
White House and Congress on foreign policy and are sure to be an
issue of contention when lawmakers return to Washington.
   There probably will be congressional hearings on U.S. policy
toward China.
   The flash point of dispute is the two secret missions to China
by presidential emissaries Brent Scowcroft, Bush's national
security adviser, and Lawrence Eagleburger, his deputy secretary of
state.
   Reluctantly, the White House revealed that Scowcroft and
Eagleburger had traveled to Beijing barely a month after the
crackdown. The purpose, Fitzwater said, was to tell Chinese leaders
face to face that the United States found their conduct
unacceptable.
   The news provided fresh ammunition for opponents of Bush's
policies.
   ``To have sent two of our highest level officials to Beijing
only weeks after announcing a ban on such exchanges makes the
president look like a wimp in Beijing and a hypocrite in
Washington,'' said Rep. Stephen Solarz, D-N.Y.
   Senate Majority Leader George Mitchell, D-Maine, demanded that
the administration make a full disclosure of its contact with China.
   Even before disclosure of the July trip, Democrats were up in
arms about an announced visit by Scowcroft and Eagleburger to China
in December.
   Toasting Chinese leaders with words approved by Bush, Scowcroft
said the United States wanted to bring ``new impetus and vigor'' to
the relationship.
   In language soothing to the Chinese government, Scowcroft said,
``In both our societies, there are voices of those who seek to
redirect or frustrate our cooperation. We both must take bold
measures to overcome these negative forces.''
   Fitzwater, asked to identify the negative forces in the United
States, said Tuesday, ``I don't know.'' He suggested that the
question should be directed to Scowcroft.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   EDITORS NOTE: Terence Hunt has covered the presidency since 1981
and is the AP's chief White House correspondent.
</TEXT>

</DOC>