<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0323EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-BackyardDishes Bjt   12-30 0605</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Backyard Dishes, Bjt,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>FCC Probing Claims that Companies Overcharge Satellite Dish Owners</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAY ARNOLD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Federal Communications Commission is
investigating claims that some companies are charging backyard
satellite dish owners as much as 20 times more than cable systems
for the same TV programs.
   The FCC said Friday it had ``disturbing evidence'' that cable
operators were receiving preferential treatment from satellite
carriers for the programs cable operators provide by coaxial cable
to their subscribers.
   ``Because this evidence raises serious concerns about the
competitive nature of this market and the impact on consumers,''
the commission said it would conduct an inquiry into the matter to
determine if remedies were needed to protect the nation's 2.5
million dish owners.
   ``This is a great victory,'' said Larry Helland, attorney for
the Valhalla, N.Y.-based American Home Satellite Association.
Helland said the new FCC inquiry finally would force satellite
companies to justify their rates to backyard dish owners.
   The FCC's decision for an inquiry grew out of an investigation
of possible discrimination by satellite companies against
distributors of TV network and so-called superstation programming.
Congress, in the 1988 Satellite Home Viewer Copyright Act, ordered
the FCC study, which the commission completed Friday just before
its Dec. 31 deadline.
   The commission said that, based upon the information it had
gathered from nine companies, the prices satellite carriers charged
distributors did vary, but the FCC could not determine that there
was ``unjust or unreasonable discrimination.''
   It added, ``We do not foreclose the possibility that cable
operators are exercising undue market power to the detriment of
earth station owners and distributors'' and that its new inquiry
would look into that issue and take remedial action, if necessary.
   The FCC cited comments from the dish owners association and the
National Rural Telecommunications Cooperative, an organization of
550 rural electric cooperatives and small telephone systems in 47
states that distributes a package of TV programming known as
``Rural TV'' to 30,000 backyard dish owners.
   According to the telecommunications cooperative, Eastern
Microwave proposed to charge NRTC $1.34 per month per subscriber
for the signal of WWOR, New York, and WSBK, Boston. The cooperative
told the commission that Eastern charges cable systems 18 cents to
20 cents per month for WWOR and WSBK.
   Eastern Microwave, in a letter to the cooperative, said the 1988
satellite act applied only to discrimination among distributors to
earth station owners and that rates charged to ``other classes of
users are irrelevant,'' the commission said.
   The cooperative also told the commission that Southern Satellite
Systems charges NRTC 79 cents per subscriber per month for
superstation WTBS, Atlanta, while offering the same service to
cable systems for 4 cents to 10 cents per month per subscriber.
   The cooperative said Netlink charges $3.25 a month per
subscriber for five Denver network and superstation signals, while
Denver cable systems get Netlink's feed for 58 cents per subscriber
per month.
   ``Our inquiry suggests that cable operators are paying
substantially less than distributors to home earth stations for the
same programming,'' the FCC said. ``The limited evidence that is in
this record does not support a conclusion that the wide disparities
between distributor and cable operator rates have been justified.''
   Bob Phillips, chief executive officer of the National Rural
Telecommunications Cooperative, said he was ``anxiously awaiting a
further inquiry so we can establish the discrimination between the
home dish market and the cable market, and we can gain some
relief.''
   Backyard dish owners may pay from $3 to about $20 a month for TV
programs, and the average cost of the dish and descrambling
equipment is about $2,500.
</TEXT>

</DOC>