<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0236 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1811EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-TWAFuture 2ndLd-Writethru   12-19 0788</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-TWA Future, 2nd Ld-Writethru,0811</SECOND>
<HEAD>Airline May Be On Its Way From Major to Minor Carrier</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS grafs 10-11 to CORRECT that TWA not recently headquartered
in St. Louis; picks up 12th graf pvs bg'ng, ``There is ...</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RANDOLPH PICHT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Employees have been living with uncertainty at
Trans World Ailines Inc. ever since Carl Icahn bought the carrier
in 1986, but now they believe the handwriting on the wall is
becoming clearer.
   TWA, which began the decade as one of the nation's largest
airlines, is in serious danger of disappearing in the early 1990s,
industry analysts and workers say.
   The airline is saddled with $2.7 billion in debt, its 218
airplanes are among the oldest used by major carriers, and pilots,
mechanics and flight attendants are frustrated and disillusioned
about their future.
   On Monday, TWA announced plans to sell its Chicago-to-London
route and four gates and a dormant maintenance facility at
Chicago's O'Hare Airport to American Airlines for $195 million, a
move that shocked and angered workers.
   The sale is subject to regulatory approval.
   ``It's very difficult to see how selling a route to a competitor
can be beneficial,'' said Herb Johnson, president of the Machinists
union's Local 1650 in Kansas City. ``Selling the London route just
doesn't compute.''
   Johnson, who heads the airline's largest union local, said
workers can't help but wonder if they're going to have a carrier to
work for in 1990. And it's particularly upsetting to see the route
go to a fierce rival like American.
   ``American is a tough competitor. Everyone knows that once they
get in your markets, they'll blow your doors off,'' Johnson said.
``Market share is everything in this business and when you start
reducing that you're in trouble.''
   Icahn said the proposed sale will help restore profitability at
TWA, which has already lost $117 million for the first nine months
of 1989 and is expected to lose between $230 million to $300
million for the year.
   TWA is headquartered in Mt. Kisco, N.Y., but has one of its
largest hub operations in St. Louis.
   Icahn, who took the company private last year, said the company
will need the money from the sale to make it through a slump in
business that's already under way and to survive an industry
consolidation in the mid-'90s.
   ``There is a time to invest and a time to be cautious, and now
is the time to be cautious,'' Icahn told employees in three-page
letter on the state of TWA.
   But no one at TWA or in the airline industry seems to believe
that caution is what prompted the sale to American.
   Some analysts believe Icahn is trying to raise more money to buy
additional stock in USX Corp., a company he's been rumored to be
interested in buying for years.
   In fact, on Tuesday, Icahn received permission from the Federal
Trade Commission to acquire a bigger stake _ at least 25 percent _
of USX, a Pittsburgh-based steel and energy company.
   Icahn currently owns 34 million, or 13.6 percent, of USX's
outstanding common shares.
   There's also speculation that Icahn has found an airline that
wants to buy TWA and Icahn is now trying to streamline the airline
to help avoid any antitrust violations.
   ``This sale could be consistent with a lot of different theories
about what's goig to happen to TWA,'' said Paul Turk, an analyst
with Avmark, Inc., an aviation consulting firm based in Arlington,
Va.
   Kent Scott, chairman of the TWA unit of the Air Line Pilots
Association, said he believes Monday's proposed sale is the
beginning of the complete liquidation of the airline.
   ``I think he's testing the water of opposition in the regulatory
agencies and if he gets this one through he can use it as a
precedent when he proposes others,'' said Scott, who is based in
St. Louis.
   The next routes for sale may be the coast-to-coast flights _ New
York to Los Angeles and San Francisco _ Scott said. Meanwhile,
Scott said he expects the three Boeing 747 airliners used by TWA to
fly from Chicago to London to be up for sale once the American deal
goes through.
   The pilots' union will encourage federal regulators to quash the
deal, Scott said.
   Whatever the reason for Monday's proposed sale, analysts agree
with Icahn that the airline industry has been struggling recently
with higher costs and slackening demand for air travel.
   ``TWA hasn't been performing well and the whole industry hasn't
been doing too well either,'' said Mark Daugherty, a stock analyst
at Dean Witter Reynolds in New York. ``This (Monday's sale)
surgically removes a route that wasn't that important, but it's
hard to say what it means.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>