<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0240EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-JewishSchoolVandalized     12-28 0315</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Jewish School Vandalized,300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Vandals Ransack Jewish School Closed for Holiday</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SILVER SPRING, Md. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Repairs are being made at a Jewish
secondary school in this Washington suburb, which was ransacked by
vandals in a ``hate-violence incident'' while it was closed for
Hanukkah, officials say.
   Police said the 12-room school, Yeshiva of Greater Washington,
apparently was invaded late Tuesday, the fifth night of the Jewish
festival of Hanukkah.
   Lockers were ransacked, ceiling panels ripped out, windows and
doors smashed and books strewn all over the floors.
   The school, which has 85 students in grades 7 through 12, was
closed this week, and officials said they were not sure they could
make repairs in time to re-open on Tuesday.
   ``Driving here, I was prepared for the worst,'' said Rabbi Zev
Katz, assistant principal. ``But this goes beyond anything I could
prepare myself for.''
   The vandalism was classified as a ``hate-violence incident''
because of messages left by the vandals, officials said. The word
``Satan'' was written in chalk on the blackboard of one classroom.
In the hallway, across six lockers, the words ``Roman Catholics
rule'' were scribbled.
   In 1977, when the school was located in a different building
nearby, the building was defaced with swastikas, anti-Semitic
slogans and obscenities, and later was damaged by arson.
   The school is located in the Kemp Mill neighborhood, where many
Orthodox Jews live and which was the target of burglaries and
vandalism last summer. After those incidents, about 300 residents
of the neighborhood sought aid from Montgomery County police.
   However, police said they believe the incidents were isolated
and not the work of any organized group.
   In one incident, swastikas were painted on cars; in another
anti-Semitic act, epithets were painted on a sidewalk.
   Jerry Pasternak, president of the Kemp Mill Civic Association,
said residents were pleased with increased police patrols and there
had been no incidents since September.
</TEXT>

</DOC>