<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0172 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0229EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-ColdWarAds Bjt   12-28 0531</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Cold War Ads, Bjt,0549</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Networks Decline To Run Ads Featuring Bush, Gorbachev</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCY GORDON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   CBS and ABC have rejected a commercial for a
cold medicine that features the leaders of the superpowers in a
play on the term ``cold war.''
   The two television networks said Wednesday they would not run
Schering-Plough Corp. commercials for the cold remedy Drixoral
featuring President Bush and Soviet leader Mikhail S. Gorbachev
unless the company obtains permission from the two heads of state.
   Schering is using pictures of Bush and Gorbachev at their recent
summit talks in Malta in a television and newspaper advertising
campaign that starts today.
   But CBS and ABC notified the company's ad agency Wednesday that
they would not run the ads without government permission, said Kent
Roman, an account supervisor for the agency, Messner Vetere Berger
Carey Schmetterer. NBC still plans to run the ads and Schering is
considering placing them on cable television channels, he said.
   In the past, the White House has sent stiff cease-and-desist
warnings to companies using the president's picture to make him
appear to endorse a product.
   Schering did not ask Bush's permission before making the ads,
company officials said.
   Presidential aides with Bush in Texas were unavailable for
comment Wednesday, a secretary in the White House press office said.
   Several principals of the ad aency worked on commercials for
Bush's 1988 presidential campaign.
   ``They (Schering) should obtain the consent of the White House''
and Soviet authorities, said Matthew Margo, a vice president for
program practices at CBS. It is ``not appropriate'' to use the
presidency to sell products, he said.
   Margo said, however, that CBS would run the commercials if the
leaders gave their permission.
   ABC officials couldn't be reached for comment late Wednesday on
their refusal to run the ads.
   Tom Feitel, a senior brand manager of Schering, said NBC plans
to air the commercial and newspapers will run the ads.
   ``It is extremely tasteful,'' he said in a telephone interview.
``We feel there's no attempt to make it appear that either of the
individuals involved are exponents for the product.''
   Schering also is shipping boxes of Drixoral to the heads of
state of East Germany, Poland, Hungary, Czechoslovakia, Romania and
Bulgaria ``to help ease the effects of their treacherous winter,''
the pharmaceutical company said in the news release.
   ``In the new year, may the only cold war in the world be the one
being fought by us,'' say the ads for the antihistamine and nasal
decongestant.
   Schering, which is spending more than $200,000 on the campaign,
claims it is the first time Bush and Gorbachev appear in an ad
promoting a product.
   Among the newspapers scheduled to run the ad is Novoye Russkoye
Slovo, a Russian paper published in the United States.
   Other U.S. companies ranging from Pepsico to American Telephone
&amp; Telegraph Co. have capitalized on the Cold War thaw to promote
themselves in television commercials. But these ads have not shown
any political leaders appearing to endorse a specific product.
   Schering is a leading pharmaceutical and health-products maker
based in Madison, N.J., with sales of nearly $3 billion in 1988.
</TEXT>

</DOC>