<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0184 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1015EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f BC-CanadianShoppers Adv01   12-28 0872</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Canadian Shoppers, Adv 01,0899</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv01</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Monday Jan. 1</HEAD>
<HEAD>Canadians Drawn By Low Prices, Strong Dollar Flood U.S. Stores</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALAN FLIPPEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NIAGARA FALLS, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Canadian shoppers have made this
holiday season jolly for U.S. retailers, but some residents are
feeling a lack of goodwill toward fellow shoppers from across the
border.
   Low U.S. prices and a comparatively strong Canadian dollar have
caused Canadians to throng grocery stores, liquor marts and factory
outlets throughout this border city.
   ``The prices _ check it out,'' said Manny Hilario, 23, who drove
100 miles from Brampton, Ontario, to shop at the Factory Outlet
Mall one recent Saturday. Outside, in an overflowing parking lot,
Ontario plates outnumbered New York plates more than three to one.
   The crowded lots, long checkout lines and delays entering Canada
on the area's three international bridges have caused tempers to
rise at times.
   A group of six Niagara Falls residents announced recently they
were forming a group called ``People Against Canadian Shoppers'' to
press local merchants to deal with the problems.
   ``We have nothing against them (Canadians) personally, but we do
think something could be done to improve the situation for
everyone,'' Steve Hughes, a spokesman for the group, told The
Niagara Gazette.
   Hughes said his group is circulating petitions blaming Canadians
for everything from litter and rudeness to unsafely transporting
gasoline across the border in extra tanks.
   That effort, in turn, has prompted U.S. business and tourism
officials to hasten to assure Canadians that they are still welcome.
   ``It's easy to blow this out of proportion and make out that
there's a major war going on,'' said Ray Wigle, spokesman for the
Niagara Falls Convention and Visitors Bureau.
   The convention and visitors bureau and the Niagara Falls Area
Chamber of Commerce have urged businesses to clean up the trash and
expand checkouts. Local governments have been asked to increase
traffic control in order to reduce the complaints.
   Local Canada Customs officials have asked the agency that
operates the international bridges to expand the customs facilities
and are trying to persuade Ottawa to allocate more staff.
   Same-day shopping traffic across the Rainbow and Whirlpool
bridges has increased by almost 60 percent over the past four
years, and at the Lewiston-Queenston bridge, the main route to
major Canadian cities such as Hamilton and Toronto, traffic is up
107 percent over that period, said John Johnston, district manager
for Canada Customs operations in Niagara Falls.
   Theories abound over why the number of shoppers has multiplied,
though the year-old U.S.-Canada free trade pact isn't considered a
direct cause. The agreement has reduced wholesale tariffs on
several categories of merchandise but has not yet affected the
duties paid by individual shoppers at the border.
   Still, free trade may have subtly boosted cross-border shopping
by helping to strengthen the Canadian dollar. The Canadian dollar
trades at about 85 U.S. cents these days after falling as low as 70
cents earlier in the decade.
   Niagara Falls, N.Y., also has a built-in price advantage because
western New York is one of the cheaper regions of the United States
while Niagara Falls, Ontario, is an extension of the pricey Toronto
metropolitan area, said Wigle.
   Price is not the only attraction of the United States, some
Canadian shoppers said.
   ``In groceries, anything new they come out with (in the U.S.) is
in Canada the year after,'' said Lisa Morrice of Hamilton, Ontario.
   ``You just don't have the choices (in Canada),'' agreed a
Toronto woman who declined to give her name. ``You see different
things down here.''
   U.S. grocery chains began advertising heavily across the border
in the past few months after seeing the stronger dollar and the
increased willingness of Canadians to cross the bridges.
   ``Their money is worth a lot more than it was two years ago,''
said Ralph Meranto, manager of a local Tops supermarket. ``It
wasn't even worthwhile before.''
   Canadian merchants say they can't compete with U.S. prices, but
are not calling for stronger government action to protect them.
   Turkeys that cost 69 cents a pound in the United States sell for
the equivalent of $1.28 to $1.49 a pound in Canada, said Justin
Sauve, manager of Hy and Zel's Supermarket in Niagara Falls,
Ontario.
   ``A lot of people I know buy a case of beer for 10 bucks (in the
U.S.) and over here it's $22 or $23,'' Sauve said. ``People go over
there to gas up and they go to the stores while they're there.''
   Canada, unlike the United States, has no duty-free allowance for
shoppers who have been out of the country less than 24 hours. Sauve
said a lot of Canadians are escaping the duty and federal sales
tax, which can add up to 19.8 percent to the cost of a purchase,
but declined to fault customs officials for letting them through.
   ``If you take everybody who you could pull over, you'd be
pulling everybody over,'' he said. ``You'd be there all day pulling
them over.''
   Johnston, the customs manager, said his agency's penetration
rate was ``reasonable'' given the need to keep traffic flowing.
   ``When we have to take enforcement action, it tends to slow
things down,'' he said.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End adv for Monday Jan. 1.</NOTE>

</DOC>