<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0195 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1834EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-Panama-KellyText 1stAdd   12-20 0666</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Panama-Kelly Text, 1st Add,540</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHN: back up.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Q: General, can you try and talk into the microphones?
   GEN. KELLY: Yeah, sure. I'm sorry. Why don't you move that map
back a little? The map is my security symbol and my lesson plan.
   Of interest is that the Canal is functional. There has been no
endeavor that we've uncovered to try to destroy it. We have forces
out along it, and we intend to protect it. It was actually worked
somewhat today. Some ships were moved out. And we are hoping as
early as tomorrow we'll be moving other ships through the canal, so
that's a real plus for the effort to date.
   I would say things up in the Task Force Atlantic area are in
pretty good shape.
   We'll skip Task Force Bayonet now and go out to what we're
calling Task Force Pacific, and that's the one that's built around
the 82nd Airborne Brigade, which jumped in last night. They have
gotten organized, moved out. They have attacked the cav squadron at
Panama, Viejo, or engaged the cavalry squadron, and reduced it;
there is no longer any resistance there. They have engaged the
infantry company at Finajitas and reduced it; there is no
resistance there. They have engaged the Battalion 2000, another
anti-coup unit from the 3rd of October, and found nothing when they
got there.
   Actually an R&amp;S team out along the bridge on the Pacora River
last night called in airplanes, AC-130s, and they knocked out nine
of their vehicles, which I think is a pretty good portion of their
vehicles. And the rest fled.
   And we've been seeing the PDF fleeing from our troops in most of
the engagements, with some exceptions: the naval infantry up here,
at least initially the two companies at Rio Hato, although
eventually they fled. So it looks like the organized resistance in
these areas is pretty much a thing of the past.
   The organized resistance in the Task Force Bayonet area is also
a thing of the past. We were going into the Comandancia this
afternoon with a Ranger company to go through it room by room, and
we found it empty. We have completed sweeping all of the buildings
at Fort Amador, and Fort Amador is now secure, although there is
some shooting down in this area. We have established a refugee
collecting point at Balboa, and as of mid-afternoon, had about
1,000 people in there. And refugees are becoming a problem.
   But I think it's fair to say that the _ and our plan was to go
after the organized combat forces of thePDF first in this area from
Rio Hato on out to Fort Cimarron _ Rio Hato in the West, Fort
Cimarron in the East. That's where the preponderance of them are.
   That's where the preponderance of the power of the PDF is. We
went after them first. We have reduced them. And there is no
organized resistance left in those areas, although there are people
left in those areas. There are also a number of Dignity Battalions
in those areas, primarily in Panama City, and that has got to be
our next priority, to get in there and to begin to clean that out.
   Panama City, as you know, is a city of almost a million people.
Urban operations are possibly the most difficult kind. They might
compete with the relief in place in the dark, but they're right up
there in the degree of difficulty in terms of military operations.
   It's a large city to sweep through. It's going to take a lot of
people. That's why we are anxious to get the 7th Infantry Division
brigade in tonight and anxious to get the 16th MP Brigade
Headquarters and those two companies in.
   Two companies doesn't sound like much, but that goes _ they go
with the other MP companies already in Panama. I believe there's
five of them. So it'll represent about a brigade of MPs.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>