<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 2258EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Romania-Americans 4thLd-Writethru a0855 12-24 0681</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Americans, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0855,0700</SECOND>
<HEAD>Demonstration, Mass in Honor of Romanian Victims</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 8th graf, `Romania's massive ...,' with 4 grafs to UPDATE
with Portland gathering; picks up 9th graf, `The revolt ...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID ROCKS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of bundled-up but jubilant
demonstrators, chanting ``Freedom'' and ``Victory,'' rallied in a
downtown plaza Sunday to show their support for democratic change
in Romania.
   ``Death to the communist regime and the security forces and all
the rest of the bandits,'' said Ionel Mikleu, who emigrated from
Romania 20 years ago. ``They ruled Romania for 40-some years. It's
enough.''
   The crowd, estimated by police at 500, waved Romania's flag with
the communist emblem torn out, burned portraits of deposed dictator
Nicolae Ceausescu, and sang the country's national anthem.
   Earlier Sunday, hundreds more Chicagoans with Eastern European
roots wore black armbands at church services for victims of the
turmoil in Romania.
   In New York, about 200 people demonstrated across the street
from the Romanian Mission to the United Nations.
   Princess Margaret, daughter of exiled King Michael, told the
crowd in English of her support for the popular movement in
Romania, then said ``Thank you'' in Romanian, according to the Rev.
Aurel Radulescu, head of the coalition Romania 21.
   Romania 21 has organized daily demonstrations outside the
mission since the uprising in Romania began, more recently to
celebrate and appeal for international aid.
   In Portland, Ore., more than 125 people gathered in downtown
Pioneer Square to sing Christmas carols and light Christmas
candles. Three men held high a Romanian flag.
   ``We want to express our joy at the freedom,'' said John Pirva,
who has lived in Portland for the past eight years.
   One man held a sign with a picture of Ceausescu captioned
``Wanted for Mass Murder,'' referring to the massacre of thousands
of protesters in Timisoara, Romania, last weekend.
   Romania's massive protests began Dec. 15 in Timisoara. The
protests spread to Bucharest, forcing Ceausescu to flee his palace
Friday.
   The revolt was sparked when ethnic Hungarians in Timisoara
rallied to the defense of Presbyterian-Calvinist minister Laszlo
Tokes, who was about to be deported for preaching in his native
Hungarian tongue.
   During the afternoon rally in single-digit temperatures at
Chicago's Daley Center Plaza, demonstrators carried signs reading,
``Make my day _ kill a dictator today'' and ``Ceausescu = Murder.''
Others called for U.S. military aid to partisans battling with
security forces loyal to Ceausescu.
   ``If the State Department would permit us to go there we would
have a battalion ready,'' said Mikleu, a history professor at
Oakton College in suburban Des Plaines.
   Speakers attempting to address the rally could not be heard
above the chanting crowd.
   At the morning mass at St. Stephen King of Hungary Church,
parishoners mourned the deaths of ethnic Hungarians and others in
the violence that has engulfed Romania since last weekend.
   ``I hope that this will bring about a more democratic society
with freedom of speech and religion where people can practice their
own culture and language,'' said Gabriel Pataky, a member of the
congregation.
   The 250 worshipers expressed hope that any new regime in Romania
would respect the rights of the 2 million ethnic Hungarians in the
country.
   ``To replace one repressive regime with another repressive
regime doesn't benefit anyone,'' Pataky said.
   The Hungarians were joined by representatives of other East
European ethnic groups, including Romanians, Poles and Ukrainians,
who pledged their support for democratic change.
   ``We're here as proof of our intentions of cooperation among our
peoples,'' said Vasile Bouleanu, a Romanian.
   Chicago Alderman Roman Pucinski, a leader of the Polish
community, praised the Romanians who stood up to Ceausescu's
security forces.
   ``What we are witnessing today is that people power is the
greatest power in the world,'' Pucinski said. ``We are hopeful that
it won't be long before all the nations in the world will be able
to live in freedom and dignity.''
   One man held a sign with a picture of Ceausescu, captioned
``Wanted for Mass Murder,'' referring to the massacre of thousands
of protesters in Timisoara, Romania, last weekend.
</TEXT>

</DOC>