<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1754EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Portugal     12-17 0404</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Portugal,0417</SECOND>
<HEAD>Opposition Scores in Portuguese Local Elections</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LISBON, Portugal (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The opposition Socialist Party claimed
major victories in local voting Sunday with the election of its
leader as mayor of Lisbon and the capture of other large cities and
government strongholds.
   The governing, center-right Social Democrats of Prime Minister
Anibal Cavaco Silva received most votes nationwide when initial
results were announced, winning an estimated 40 percent of the
vote, according to state RTP television.
   However, the loss of Lisbon, Oporto in the north, the major
cities of Coimbra and Faro, and Social Democratic strongholds on
Madeira and in the Azores islands were hailed as triumphs by the
opposition.
   ``This is a clear defeat for the government and the Social
Democratic Party on a national scale _ and the Lisbon result shows
the capital doesn't even trust the ministries it houses,''
Socialist Party leader Jorge Sampaio told a news conference at his
party headquarters.
   Three hours after polling stations closed, about 35 percent of
the vote was reported as having gone to the Socialists, 11 percent
to the conservative Democratic Social Center and 9 percent to the
Communists. No vote totals were available.
   Sampaio won in Lisbon as candidate of an unprecedented alliance
between Socialists and Communists that won from 48 to 50 percent of
the city vote.
   His conservative opponent, Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa, admitted
defeat after hearing first estimates.
   Shortly after initial results were announced, Socialist Party
spokesman Antonio Lopes Cardoso said Sampaio would not join forces
with the Communists in the next legislative elections slated for
1991.
   The Social Democrats had warned that a leftist victory in Lisbon
could tempt the Socialists to maintain the alliance in general
elections and so let the Communists into the federal government by
the back door.
   The government has slipped in popularity since winning
Portugal's first absolute majority in 1987 on the promise of
free-market economic policies and rapid modernization.
   A consumer boom and big foreign investment have brought
prosperity to some, but annual inflation of more than 12 percent
has squeezed low-income budgets.
   Persistent rumors of high-level corruption also plagued the
Social Democrats.
   About 8 million Portuguese were eligible to vote in elections
for 55,000 local authorities.
   Voting in Cunha Alta in the northern region of Mangulade was
postponed until Sunday, Dec. 24, after strong winds ripped roofs
off houses and injured at least two people, the Portuguese news
agency Lusa reported.
</TEXT>

</DOC>