<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0628EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-NoAccess     12-28 0380</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-No Access,0392</SECOND>
<HEAD>Homeowners May Be `Landlocked' if Private Road Closed</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LANSING, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Russell Oberman doesn't much care for ``you
can't get there from here'' jokes, ever since a squabble over a
railroad crossing began threatening the only access he and five
other homeowners have to their homes.
   ``We are legally landlocked,'' Oberman, a village police
officer, said Wednesday. ``I can put my truck into four-wheel drive
and drive across some guy's field _ but my wife doesn't have a
four-wheel drive.''
   Oberman and others who live nearby get to their homes by driving
down a narrow gravel road across a set of railroad tracks _ but
there's the rub.
   Detroit-based Grand Trunk Western Railroad Co. has always asked
the road's residents to sign an agreement stating they will not
hold the railroad liable for any accident at the unmarked crossing.
Residents have done so.
   The railroad also has asked that residents maintain a private
insurance policy to cover any claims filed because of accidents at
the crossing. They've done that, too.
   But after a 1986 accident at the crossing that left three people
dead and resulted in several lawsuits _ one of them against the
insurer _ the insurance company canceled its coverage.
   Residents called a number of insurers, but were unable to secure
new coverage.
   To complicate matters, some residents have decided because of
the lawsuits that they will no longer sign the agreement with the
railroad.
   Oberman said the railroad has threatened to erect barricades to
keep residents from crossing the tracks, but a spokesman for the
railroad said Wednesday that Grand Trunk would like to avoid that.
   ``That's an option they would prefer not to use,'' spokesman
Chuck Ragains said. ``They're not ruling it out, but they prefer
not to use it.''
   Another possible solution: converting the road to a public
thoroughfare, thus shifting liability from the residents. But that,
too, is problematic.
   Village officials say to upgrade the road to make it public,
they must charge residents for at least 40 percent of the
improvements _ at a cost of between $15,000 and $20,000 per
household.
   The railroad is behind it, but residents say they can't afford
it.
   The issue is expected to come up again at next month's Village
Board meeting.
</TEXT>

</DOC>