<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0140 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 2135EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Australia-Quake 1stLd-Writethru a0556 12-28 0647</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Australia-Quake, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0556,0672</SECOND>
<HEAD>Australia Quake's Toll: $1 Billion in Damages, 9 Dead</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS throughout to UPDATE with officials saying nine dead,
garage parking lot collapsed, details. No pickup. ADDS byline</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto SYD1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD BILL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEWCASTLE, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rescuers crawled through the rubble
of a workers' club Friday seeking victims of Australia's first
fatal earthquake, which killed nine people, injured 107 and
devastated sections of the nation's sixth largest city.
   State police headquarters in Sydney, 75 miles south of
Newcastle, revised the death toll in Thursday's quake from 11 to
nine, but said more people may be trapped in the wreckage of the
Newcastle Workers' Club.
   A preliminary estimate put overall damage from the quake at $1
billion.
   The army was sent in to stop looting.
   The temblor toppled buildings, crumbled walls, damaged pipes and
knocked out power.
   From Texas, President Bush sent a message of condolence to Prime
Minister Bob Hawke.
   Britain's Queen Elizabeth II also sent quake condolences.
   Two floors of the workers' club collapsed into the parking
basement, where 24 cars lay under broken concrete slabs, police
said. Six bodies were taken from the club. Most were elderly women
who met Thursdays to play bingo after getting their pension checks,
a police officer said.
   He spoke on condition of anonymity.
   Three other victims were killed by falling debris and shop
awnings as the quake, measuring 5.5 on the Richter scale, hit at
10:28 a.m.
   Cave expert David Rothbury said he climbed into open spaces in
the rubble but found no bodies.
   ``There are some spaces big enough to get into, but there was no
one there,'' he said. ``We asked for the machines to be quiet so we
could hear any cries for help, but we didn't hear anything.''
   Elsewhere in this industrial city of 500,000, residents were
surveying the damage and waiting for the predicted aftershocks.
   Police cordoned off the debris-littered central business
district until high-rise office builings could be inspected for
damage.
   Army Maj. Brian Jordon said up to 150 buildings, including
homes, were so badly damaged they may have to be demolished. He
heads a 200-member unit ordered in by Hawke to help police.
   The city council met in emergency session Friday to gauge the
damage and plan relief programs for homeless residents.
   Water and telephone services were gradually being restored, a
council officer said.
   Scientists at Canberra-based Australian Seismological Center
said the quake was one of the most severe on record and the first
to cliam lives.
   Its epicenter was eight miles west of suburban Hamilton,
occurred at a depth of slightly more than six miles, and lasted 29
seconds.
   Australia's biggest earthquake was at Meeberrie, in remote,
sparsely populated Western Australia in 1941 and measured 7.7 on
the Richter scale.
   Thursday's quake was felt throughout New South Wales state _
including Sydney, where it struck like a sharp jolt _ and police
said it was the first in Australia to hit a heavily populated area.
   Newcastle is the most populous city in New South Wales after
Sydney. The city on the southeast coast is a major shipping port
and coal-mining center.
   Hawke, grieving over the Christmastime death of his 92-year-old
father, cut short holiday plans to visit the disaster site.
   The army was called in to patrol streets. Police spokesman Simon
Latimer said there were reports of looting in the business district.
   A vast number of homes across the state lost electricity and
emergency services were stretched thin. Crews were flown from
Sydney to help.
   The Richter scale is a gauge of of the energy released by an
earthquake as measured by the ground motion recorded on a
seimograph. A quake measuring 5 can cause considerable damage and a
quake measuring 6 can cause severe damage.
   The earthquake that hit Northern California on Oct. 17 killed 67
people and measured 7.1.
</TEXT>

</DOC>