<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0092 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1642EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-Endara     12-23 0605</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Endara,0626</SECOND>
<HEAD>Endara Got Three Hours Warning of U.S. Invasion</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY A. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Panama's new president said Saturday
he had only three hours warning of the U.S. attack that toppled
Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega and has been scrambling ever since
because his government had to ``start from point zero.''
   President Guillermo Endara said in an interview that the news of
the U.S. invasion at midnight Tuesday was ``like a kick in the
head. It was not the best thing I would have thought.''
   ``We were not really consulted,'' said Endara, who said he was
``very diplomatically'' told of President Bush's plans only two or
three hours before it was launched.
   Endara said Saturday he had named a Cabinet but was not making
the names public yet to protect its members. One of Endara's vice
presidents, Ricardo Arias Calderon, survived an assassination
attempt Friday.
   ``We are keeping them confidential, but they will be announced
soon,'' Endara told a group of reporters.
   Endara and his two vice presidents were sworn in one day after
the U.S. invasion. They assumed office Friday.
   A few hours later, fighters loyal to Noriega raked Arias' car,
wounding two of his bodyguards.
   ``It is a shaky government. I took over a government of a
country invaded by another country. There was total anarchy. This
is the first time a government has to start from point zero. But we
are working hard,'' Endara said.
   Endara said he was trying to get one of Panama City's two
airports open to allow food and medicine to be flown in.
   Endara said his government is also trying to organize a police
force to replace the one that fell apart with Noriega's downfall,
setting off a massive looting spree.
   ``We swore in the first 20 members (of the force) yesterday,''
he added. The new force will be commanded by Col. Roberto Armijo, a
former Noriega loyalist who switched sides.
   Asked how he felt about the American invasion, Endara replied:
``I have lots of work to do. I have no time to think about the bad
things. Noriega destroyed everything when he fell. Everything was
back to zero.''
   ``I would have been happier without an intervention. I could
have gone into a depression over the invasion,'' he said.
   ``I probably would have worked out some details in advance, like
the matter of public order,'' he added.
   But he said he could work with the Americans.
   ``The gringos have their defects, but I am used to ... them. I
wish it would have been different, but we have to work with what we
have,'' Endara said.
   He denied reports that he was sworn in before a judge at a U.S.
military base.
   ``I was sworn in on Panamanian territory, in a Panamanian home
after 1 a.m. Then in the morning we went to (the U.S. military base
at) Fort Clayton,'' he said.
   Endara and vice presidential candidates Arias and Guillermo Ford
were elected by a landslide in May 7 elections, according to U.S.
and other foreign observers. Noriega declared the election void.
   All three were scheduled to have been sworn in Sept. 1, but
instead Noriega named a provisional president and ended up having
himself elevated to ``chief of government'' before the U.S. attack.
   ``Everybody would be more at ease if Noriega were in custody,
but Noriega is not essential now. He is out of power forever. He is
not so popular among the people,'' Endara said.
   ``He never was. People are sad because of the price they had to
pay for (all) this,'' he added.
</TEXT>

</DOC>