<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1153EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Philippines     12-25 0462</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines,0475</SECOND>
<HEAD>Aquino Calls For Unity, Filipinos Light Candles For Peace</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT H. REID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Corazon Aquino called on
Filipinos in a Christmas message to join together to help the
country recover from the most recent coup attempt. Thousands of
people lighted candles in a plea for peace.
   ``The candles we will be lighting as one symbolize the longing
of the ordinary citizen for peace and tranquility and his
repudiation of violence as an instrument of power,'' The Manila
Chronicle said in a front-page editorial.
   Mrs. Aquino said the Dec. 1-9 coup attempt tarnished the
country's reputation and stalled efforts to improve the economy
still suffering from 20 years of rule under former President
Ferdinand Marcos.
   ``What we need to do today is to join hands so that we can
regain the momentum that we lost, so that we can heal the wounds
that were inflicted upon us,'' Mrs. Aquino said.
   Marcos was ousted in a February 1986 military-civilian uprising
that propelled Mrs. Aquino to power. Marcos died in September in
exile in Hawaii.
   In another statement Monday, the Central Committee of the banned
Communist Party of the Philippines blamed the December coup attempt
on Mrs. Aquino's failure to solve the country's economic, social
and political problems.
   The party claimed the country was drifting toward a new era of
repression because of the growing influence of the military faction
that has quelled six coup attempts during the Aquino administration.
   The December coup try was the worst, leaving at least 113 people
dead.
   ``The recent upsurge of popular unrest owing to the worsening
political and economic crisis, the military rebellion in December,
and the shameless manner in which the Aquino regime asked for U.S.
succor to quell the rebellion have dramatically ... exposed its
ineptitude to rule,'' the party said in a statement distributed to
news organizations.
   The statement was issued to mark the 21st anniversary of the
Communist Party of the Philippines, founded Dec. 26, 1968.
   Thousands of candles flickered in front of homes, businesses and
military camps across the politically troubled land.
   The nationwide candle-lighting ceremony was organized by
entertainer Danny Javier in a bid to forge national unity in the
wake of the coup and amid insurgencies by Marxist and Moslem rebels.
   People were urged to place one candle in front of their home for
each member of the household as a gesture of peace and national
reconciliation. Hundreds of thousands of Filipinos also crowded
churches in Asia's only predominately Christian country to pray for
peace.
   In his Christmas message, Roman Catholic Cardinal Jaime L. Sin
said violence had drowned out the ``song of peace and good will
that was sung by the heavenly choir over Bethlehem on that first
Christmas.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>