<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0193 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2309EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Summit     12-18 0311</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Summit,0319</SECOND>
<HEAD>Leader at Gulf Summit Asks U.N. Moves for Peace</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NEIL MACFARQUHAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MUSCAT, Oman (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sultan Qaboos of Oman opened a summit
meeting of Persian Gulf states Monday with a call for the United
Nations to redouble its efforts to arrange a peace treaty between
Iran and Iraq.
   He also noted that recent reforms in Eastern Europe provide new
opportunities for cooperation with this region.
   Other participants in the four-day summit of the Gulf
Cooperation Council were sheiks Isa bin Salman al-Khalifa of
Bahrain, Jaber al-Ahmed al-Sabah of Kuwait, Khalifa bin Hamad
al-Thani of Qatar and Zayed bin Sultan al-Nahyan of the United Arab
Emirates and King Fahd of Saudi Arabia.
   The regional leaders were expected to focus on how trade can
boost their national economies now that the Iraq-Iran war is over
and oil prices are inching up.
   A U.N.-brokered cease-fire in the war took hold in August 1988.
However, talks have failed to produce an agreement on exchanging
prisoners of war, withdrawing troops to international borders, and
other sticking points.
   The summit probably will issue a statement stressing the need
for a firm peace treaty. However, the bloc's influence is weakened
by Iranian accusations that it is biased toward Iraq, diplomats say.
   Participants were also expected to discuss setting up a common
tariff structure and coordinating development plans.
   Qaboos noted that the recent reformist wave in Eastern Europe
toward economic and political freedom means new opportunites for
cooperation and for the conservative gulf states to gain a
``progressive role and effective presence in this changing world.''
   He said such moves would require new policies but did not spell
them out.
   He also asked the people of Lebanon to carry out an Arab
League-sponsored peace plan to end Lebanon's 14-year-old civil war
and said Israel must be pressured to solve the Palestinian problem.
</TEXT>

</DOC>