<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0169 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0540EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DigestBriefs     12-19 0562</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Digest Briefs,0582</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government had clear evidence shortly
after the first nuclear bombs were built in the 1940s that weapons
workers were being exposed to potentially dangerous amounts of
radiation, according to a congressional report.
   Despite this information, including some not previously made
public, officials overseeing the bomb factories recommended not
informing workers of the possible health risks they faced at the
secretly operated facilities, the report said.
   ``The U.S. nuclear weapons program was exposing large numbers of
workers to potentially dangerous health risks but did nothing to
warn them,'' said Sen. John Glenn, D-Ohio, in releasing the report
on Monday.
   The report was prepared by the majority staff of the Senate
Governmental Affairs Committee, which Glenn chairs. The panel is
investigating the health research programs of the Energy
Department, which owns the 17 major facilities that design and make
nuclear arms.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bush administration is telling regulators
to begin selling real estate and other assets from failed savings
and loans even before the government officially closes the
institutions.
   Regulators ``should ... immediately begin shrinking such
institutions' balance sheets in a coordinated and orderly manner,''
instructs a document obtained Monday by The Associated Press.
   The administration, in a 91-page strategic plan, also is telling
regulators to discourage influence-peddling by keeping a public log
of all attempts by ``senior public officials'' or their staffs to
influence their decisions.
   The plan, scheduled for release by the end of the year, was
prepared by the Resolution Trust Corp. Oversight Board, an
administration panel headed by Treasury Secretary Nicholas F.
Brady. The board sets policy for the Resolution Trust Corp., a new
entity run by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corp., an independent
regulatory agency.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>INDIANAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dan and Kathy Blackburn began taking in sick
and abandoned children while serving as missionaries in Haiti, and
came to love them so much they've brought all 28 home to adopt.
   ``It turned into a family and snowballed,'' Blackburn said as
the couple arrived to a rousing welcome Monday night at
Indianapolis International Airport. The Blackburns and their
children _ ages 3 to 14 _ headed for a church camp where they'll
stay in a dormitory until they find a home.
   The arrival of the Christian Evangelical missionaries and the
children culminated two years of efforts by Christian groups in
this country to bring the family to the Blackburns' home state.
   The Blackburns fled Haiti for the neighboring Dominican Republic
in 1987 during the turbulence that followed the 1986 ouster of
dictator Jean Claude Duvalier. This month, they won special holiday
parole status from the Immigration and Naturalization Service to
bring the children to the United States.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For the 20th time since the founding of the
republic, your government is setting out to learn something about
each of you _ and quite a lot about many of us.
   Where do you live? How old are you and what's your race? Are you
single, married or living with an ``unmarried partner''? How big is
your house, what's it worth and is it paid for?
   Yes, it's time once again for a new decade and another census.
   Even now, massive printing presses are churning out the more
than 100 million forms that will be needed to count over 250
million Americans April 1.
</TEXT>

</DOC>