<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0095 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1323EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Brazil-Profile     12-18 0730</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil-Profile,0754</SECOND>
<HEAD>Collor de Mello, From a Bloody Political Tradition to President</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Brazil, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER MUELLO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIO DE JANEIRO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fernando Collor de Mello, a young
and wealthy state governor reared in a tradition of bloody
political feuds, ran for the national presidency on a platform of
``Christian reform'' and clean government.
   He was born Aug. 12, 1949, into a powerful clan in Alagoas, a
poor northeastern coastal state dominated by sugar barons and known
for violent politics.
   His father, Arnon de Mello, who served as governor and senator,
shot and killed a colleague in 1963 during a dispute on the Senate
floor. His grandfather, Lindolfo Collor, was labor minister under
dictator Getulio Vargas, who ruled from the 1930s until the early
1950s.
   Collor de Mellow spent his childhood in Rio de Janeiro, then the
family moved to Brasilia, the new inland capital, where he became
city karate champion in 1969.
   Later, he returned to Alagoas to run the family's Gazeta media
group, which includes a newspaper, a television station, three
radio stations and a publishing house.
   In 1975, he married Rio heiress and socialite Lilibeth Monteiro
de Carvalho, with whom he had two children. They divorced, and in
1984 he married Rosane Malta, from another wealthy Alagoas family.
   His political career began in the 1970s, when he joined the
Arena Party of the military regime that governed Brazil from 1964
to 1985.
   Largely because of his father's connections, Collor de Mello was
appointed mayor of Maceio, capital of Alagoas state, in 1979. He
was elected to Congress three years later for the Social Democratic
Party, the new name taken by Arena.
   He surprised party colleagues in 1984 by supporting a
constitutional amendment for direct presidential elections, after
millions of Brazilians demonstrated in favor of it. The amendment
lost.
   Collor de Mello backed the military party's candidate for
president, Paulo Maluf, in 1985. Maluf lost to opposition candidate
Tancredo Neves, who died before taking office, and vice president
elect Jose Sarney became president.
   In 1986, Collor de Mello switched to Sarney's Brazilian
Democratic Movement party and was elected governor of Alagoas. He
split with Sarney last year, quit the party and began his run for
president after forming the National Reconstruction Party.
   To describe himself, Collor de Mello uses the terms ``Christian
reformer'' and ideologically left of center. Opponents call him
``the new face of the right'' and a ``test-tube candidate''
manufactured by conservative media interests.
   Conservatives were attracted by Collor de Mello's pro-business
ideas, but he also captured the mass imagination.
   While serving as governor, he gained national attention by
refusing to pay the high salaries of an elite group of civil
servants, popularly known as ``maharajahs.'' Although they seldom
showed up for duty, some had been collecting $10,000 a month by
holding two or three government jobs at once.
   His decision struck a chord with Brazilians, most of whom were
earned the equivalent of about $25 a week.
   The clean-government crusade was the heart Collor de Mello's
presidential campaign. He also was a fierce critic of Sarney, whom
many Brazilians blame for corruption in high places and annual
inflation of 1,500 percent.
   At one point, Collor de Mello called Sarney a ``corrupt,
second-rate politician.''
   As a candidate, he made crowd-pleasing promises to sell the
limousines of high officials and Brasilia mansions of government
ministers, and to close the feared National Intelligence Service.
   On many issues, however, Collor de Mello was vague.
   He described Brazil's $110 billion foreign debt, largest in the
Third World, is ``unpayable'' but said he would merely limit annual
payments to foreign banks, not stop them.
   Collor de Mello said one way to bring the debt under control was
to withdraw government guarantees on loans for state-run companies
and state governments.
   ``I don't intend to welsh or declare a moratorium,'' he said.
``I want to play within the rules. Withdrawing federal guarantees
will send a signal to creditors that will promote a broad
renegotiation.''
   Critics say Collor de Mello's record belies his claims of
fighting corruption.
   As governor, he made a settlement considered overly generous in
a tax dispute with Alagoas sugar barons, and appointed thousands of
people to state jobs just before resigning to run for president.
   The Justice Ministry ordered federal police to investigate. No
progress in the case had been reported by election day.
</TEXT>

</DOC>