<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0235 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0303EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Rothschild-Bankruptcy     12-29 0614</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Rothschild-Bankruptcy,0637</SECOND>
<HEAD>Parent of Wall Street Brokerage Reaches Reorganization Plan</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEFAN FATSIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   L.F. Rothschild &amp; Co., the Wall Street firm
devastated by the 1987 stock market crash, is reforming as a
smaller brokerage as its parent company seeks to restructure more
than $100 million in debt in bankruptcy court.
   Creditors of the 90-year-old firm's parent company, L.F.
Rothschild Holdings Inc., approved a plan to issue new bonds to
replace those defaulted on last June, when the company sought
bankruptcy court protection.
   ``We've gone about trying to intelligently refocus the
broker-dealer, which was never part of the bankruptcy,'' Rothschild
Chief Executive Joel E. Miller said in an interview Thursday.
``We're small and lean and well-capitalized for what we do.''
   Since its parent sought protection from creditors under Chapter
11 of federal bankruptcy law in June, Rothschild &amp; Co. has shuffled
its management and scaled down its businesses in an effort to stay
alive.
   Founded in 1899, the brokerage has 45 workers, up from a low of
about 35 earlier this year but a shadow of its peak employment of
2,200 before the Oct. 19, 1987, stock market crash.
   After suffering substantial losses in the crash, Rothschild
systematically sold or abandoned its retail brokerage, public
finance and municipal bond sales and trading operations.
   It also ceased over-the-counter market making, arbitrage and the
selling and trading of government, mortgage-backed and high-grade
corporate securities.
   Miller said the restructured brokerage would re-enter the retail
brokerage and investment banking businesses. In November, the firm
entered municipal securities trading and the capital markets
business.
   Miller said the brokerage is contacting old clients and would
increase advertising in January to twice a week in The Wall Street
Journal and Investors Daily in an effort to find new customers.
   Rothschild Holdings in early 1988 became a subsidiary of
Franklin Financial Services, which itself is a subsidiary of
Ottawa, Kan.-based Franklin Savings Association.
   On Thursday, Franklin Savings said it would sell Rothschild next
year. The thrift has blamed the brokerage company for its recent
losses.
   Franklin Chairman Ernest M. Fleischer said that a group of
Rothschild employees, led by Miller, ``expressed an interest'' in
buying the company and that the group ``are the most likely
buyers.''
   As of Jan. 1, 1987, Rothschild ranked as the 18th largest U.S.
securities firm with capital of $289 million. By the end of the
year, Rothschild posted a $129 million annual loss, $56 million of
which resulted from arbitrage and over-the-counter trading
positions held during the Black Monday crash.
   Miller said the firm now has a net worth of about $20 million.
   For the quarter ended Sept. 30, Rothschild Holdings showed
losses of $3.81 million on revenue of just $235,000. That compared
with losses of $5.59 million on revenue of $65.0 million a year ago.
   Rothschild Holdings issued a statement Thursday saying its
committee of unsecured creditors had approved the restructuring
proposal. The brokerage subsidiary was not included in the
bankruptcy filing.
   Under the debt restructuring, Rothschild Holdings plans to swap
existing debt for zero-coupon debt in an attempt to cut current
interest payments. Zero-coupon bonds are sold at a discount and
redeemed at maturity at face value, and do not provide periodic
interest payments.
   Rothschild Holdings plans to issue zero-coupon notes worth $29.8
million to replace the defaulted bonds valued at $101 million, the
company said.
   In its bankruptcy court filing, Rothschild Holdings said its
major creditors were Citicorp Investment Bank (Switzerland) with a
$48 million claim, Morgan Guaranty Trust Co. with a $24.9 million
claim and Cede &amp; Co. with a $39 million claim.
   L.F. Rothschild is not connected with the New York investment
bank Rothschild Inc.
</TEXT>

</DOC>