<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0606EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-QuakeTrail     12-25 0403</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Quake Trail,0413</SECOND>
<HEAD>Quake Epicenter Lures Hikers</HEAD>
<DATELINE>APTOS, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A trail through Aptos Canyon has become a
tourist attraction, drawing hundreds of hikers eager to stand at
ground zero of the deadly and devastating October earthquake.
   ``It's awfully crowded ... it's swamped,'' said senior park aide
Barbara Louck on Sunday, adding that the crunch of curious
sightseers were creating problems for parking and access to the
six-mile round-trip trail.
   ``It's an exciting place to be,'' said Bud Getty, superintendent
of Forest of Nisene Marks State Park. ``This was the major quake of
people's lifetimes, and it really captures your imagination to walk
out to the epicenter. You can really see the power of the earth.''
   A sign posted by Ranger Jerry Waggoner marks the spot about 50
miles south of San Francisco that was calculated by latitude and
longitude. The site has 4-foot-diameter redwood trees snapped off
at the ground, and a 150-foot wide landslide nearby. Just beyond
the epicenter, the trail is closed because of danger from new
landslides.
   ``That's enough to convince me,'' said Pat Wagner, 62, of
Burlington, Iowa. ``I've never been in an earthquake _ and I never
want to be.''
   ``Can you imagine what it took to rip these trees out?'' asked
Julie Dawson of Milpitas during a hike to the epicenter last week.
``And can you imagine the sound it made? Snap, crackle and pop!''
   Dawson said she understands why the previously obscure park site
has become so popular since the 7.1-magnitude on Oct. 17 that
killed 67 people and resulted in $10 billion in damage.
   ``I stayed away from San Francisco because I didn't want to be a
rubble necker. I wouldn't want that in my neighborhood,'' she said.
``But there's no one to bother out here.''
   The walk to the site takes about an hour. Most of the trail is
in a deep forest where sunlight rarely penetrates.
   In addition to Nisene Park, other San Francisco Bay area
locations are experiencing renewed interest from temblor tourists.
   At Point Reyes National Seashore, the 0.6-mile Earthquake Trial
leads to the epicenter of the 1906 San Francisco quake and visitors
can see a fence displaced by fault movement of 16 to 20 feet.
   And in Hollister, meeting place of the San Andreas, Calaveras
and Hayward faults, a self-guided earthquake walk wanders past
curbs offset by fault creep and buildings damaged in the Oct. 17
earthquake.
</TEXT>

</DOC>