<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0035EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Romania-FirstPerson Bjt-2Takes   12-27 1153</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-First Person, Bjt-2 Takes,1199</SECOND>
<HEAD>AP Correspondent Shot 3 Times in Early Throes of Romanian Revolt</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   One of the near-victims of the Romanian revolt
against their hated longtime dictator was John Daniszewski, chief
of the Warsaw bureau of The Associated Press, who had gone to the
Balkan nation to report the momentous events there. Here is his
first-hand account, filed from his hospital bed in Belgrade, of the
hellish situation in Romania and his brush with death.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DANISZEWSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Assoicated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BELGRADE, Yugoslavia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The uprising against dictator
Nicolae Ceausescu gave rise to fierce resistance by his secret
police, turning Romania into a land of fear, suspicion and
retribution. I know, I became a victim of that chaos Saturday night.
   I was shot three times, narrowly escaping death. One bullet
grazed my skull, and two more lodged in my left arm.
   Thanks to some dedicated doctors in District Hospital No. 1 in
Timisoara, and the friendly intervention of Yugoslav diplomats in
the city, I survived and was evacuated within two days to
Yugoslavia's capital Belgrade.
   It is hard to describe the mood of pure panic and paranoia that
pervaded Timisoara, a petrochemical center in western Romania with
about 350,000 inhabitants.
   The events that led to Ceausescu's fall and execution began a
week before Christmas. Demonstrations to prevent a Protestant
minister from being evicted swelled into anti-government protests.
Unarmed civilians were gunned down by state security troops, the
dreaded Securitate, in the main square.
   No Westerner has been able to verify the number of fatalities,
but doctors with whom I spoke said more than 4,000 died. After the
slaughter, the bodies were gathered in trucks and taken to a mass
grave at the city cemetery.
   The blood that flowed that day on the square sparked a popular
thirst for revenge.
   Residents responded with a general strike, and the army declared
itself with the people and against Ceausescu.
   After state TV in Bucharest fell to the opposition Friday, the
borders opened for the first time in four days to Western
journalists.
   I flew to Belgrade from Warsaw late Friday, rented a car at the
airport, and started driving to Romania's border.
   Just before entering Romania, I met a Yugoslav journalist, Ljuba
Pajic, who was to be my companion in the days that followed.
   Although I arrived at the border with no visa, the slightly
drunken border guards wearing armbands in the national colors of
red, blue and yellow let me in with little formality.
   ``American? You are with us,'' one guard whispered out of
earshot of his superior.
   On the two-hour drive to Timisoara, we were repeatedly stopped
by groups of peasants waving the Romanian flag _ with the Communist
emblem cut out of it.
   ``Ceausescu kaput! Ceausescu finito!'' they shouted to the
foreigners.
   But once entering Timisoara, tension replaced jubilation. A
siren wailed and young people on the street talked fearfully of an
air raid.
   Ceausescu's forces were going to bomb the city, they claimed.
   So, with car lights off, fearing the bombs that never fell and
avoiding the black silhouettes of tanks at many street corners, we
began to look for the main hotel, where I thought we would find
other journalists.
   Ljuba and I ended up at the Hotel Timisoara, near the Opera
Square.
   Inside the darkened lobby, we were frisked by nervous young
people carrying knives, clubs and sharpened sticks.
   A young woman who spoke English gave me an account of the
massacre:
   Children peacefully praying the previous Sunday, Dec. 17, were
mowed down by automatic weapons, she said. When their mothers ran
to them, they too were shot.
   It was also in the lobby, less than an hour after arriving in
town, that I met my first casualty.
   French photographer Jean Langevant hobbled in holding his
buddy's arm, a bullet hole in his leg.
   He was bleeding badly, but the rat-a-tat-tat of gunfire growing
nearer outside made everyone reluctant to go for help.
   Finally, a ``machina'' _ a car _ rolled up to the front door and
Langevant was bundled inside. Ljuba and I decided to follow in our
car.
   Headlights still off, we raced through the deserted streets,
afraid to stop. We screeched into the courtyard of District
Hospital No. 2.
   The photographer was taken to the operating room and we spent
the night huddled in the doctors' lounge.
   The hospital, like the other buildings in Timisoara at night,
was kept in eerie darkness whenever possible.
   ``They shoot at the light,'' one physician said, drawing a
curtain closed when the flicker of a television set dimly lighted
the lounge.
   Doctors said they had been working with a constant stream of
shooting victims since Dec. 17. They too were afraid, cowering on
the floor when the noise of gunfire came too close. Red tracers
arched over the hospital roof.
   It was a hairy night, but at last, by midmorning Saturday, the
shooting had died down enough to go outside.
   Saturday we spent trying to locate an outside phone line to tell
the story.
   In the evening, I returned to Hotel Timisoara, where we talked
to the leader of the pro-democracy forces, headquartered there.
   Their chief was an automotive engineer, a tall and dignified
young man dressed in a black beret and trenchcoat who spoke some
French.
   The hotel was again in total blackness and he led us through the
empty restaurant to a small cafe off the kitchen, where he pushed
together two tables and fed us a Romanian feast _ sliced sausages
and salty cheese, washed down with grapefruit soda. A Romanian
soldier with a Soviet submachine gun and several rebels looked on
politely.
   I asked them what kind of country they wanted. Democracy and
free elections was the reply. And the Ceausescus? Killing was too
good for them, the group agreed. Maybe torture.
   After a short drive around downtown, where the fighting had been
the heaviest, all appeared quiet. I made one outside phone call and
left the building,
   Outside, the scene had suddenly changed. Gunfire erupted very
close by as soon as we left. Retreating to the car, we backed away
in the opposite direction. Two Italian journalists who had left the
consulate with us followed in another car.
   What followed was a nightmare of running with nowhere to hide.
Every turn in the strange city seemed to lead to another firefight.
We tried to make our way back to the hotel, going in ever wider
circles because of the fighting.
   Finally, luck ran out. Driving into an intersection, somebody
flashed a light on us and shouted in Romanian.
   Before we could answer or get out of the car, I saw the flash of
a gun and realized in an instant they were shooting at us.
   Immediately, I felt something slam into my arm and what felt
like warm water being poured on my head. My own blood.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>