<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 2149EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ColombianCandidate     12-17 0440</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombian Candidate,0455</SECOND>
<HEAD>Colombian Presidential Candidate Asks For American Support</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CLIFF EDWARDS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Colombian presidential candidate on Sunday
called on Americans to step up the war on illegal drug trafficking
while his South American country increases the pressure on drug
barons.
   Colombia is pursuing its war on drugs with renewed vigor
following the death last week of Rodriguez Gacha, the country's
second-most wanted drug trafficker, Cesar Gaviria said here on the
second day of a three-day U.S. visit.
   But Americans need to help by swearing off illegal drugs, said
the presidential candidate, who was in Chicago to enlist the
support of an estimated 50,000 Colombian-Americans.
   ``Not only President Bush, I think every American can do much
more to fight the war on drugs,'' Gaviria said. ``It's a program
for every person in society.''
   ``We are talking about fighting this problem to the end ...
until it is solved,'' he said.
   Gaviria spoke at a news conference at a downtown hotel where he
was meeting with Colombian-Americans.
   Several attempts have been made on his life in Colombia, and the
hotel was heavily guarded by U.S. Secret Service agents,
bomb-sniffing dogs and Gaviria's bodyguards.
   Gaviria, who was Sen. Carlos Galan's presidential campaign
manager, became a leading Liberal Party contender after Galan was
assassinated at a political rally Aug. 18. The Colombian government
accused drug traffickers of arranging the killing.
   The Conservative Party, weakened by internal division, is given
little chance of winning the presidential election in May,
political analysts say.
   Gaviria reiterated support for a treaty to extradite drug
traffickers to the United States, saying Colombia's justice system
cannot effectively prosecute the drug lords.
   ``We don't have the capacity to punish these people'' because of
terrorist activities and the assassination of federal judges, he
said.
   Since Colombian President Virgilio Barco declared war on
traffickers and enacted emergency extradition measures this summer,
traffickers have retaliated with a wave of bombings and
assassinations of public officals, including two federal judges and
a leading leftist politician.
   The administration has extradited 10 middle-level traffickers to
the United States as part of its crackdown, but had failed to track
down any top targets until Rodriguez Gacha's death.
   Dr. Luis Yarzagaray, a Colombian-born American citizen, said
Chicago's Colombian community will work to enlist more U.S.
economic support to accomplish those goals in the South American
country.
   ``I want to give a legacy for my children,'' said Yarzagaray, a
Loyola University professor. ``I simply want the right thing.''
   Gaviria was scheduled to return to New York City on Sunday,
where he began his visit, before returning home on Monday,
Yarzagaray said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>