<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0292 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 2015EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Eastern     12-22 0507</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Eastern,0523</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eastern Airlines Reducing Schedule</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAN SEWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eastern Airlines, which just sold its Latin
American routes, also is cutting back some domestic flights, the
company said Friday.
   In the first announced reduction of its flight schedule since
Eastern began rebuilding from a crippling strike, the carrier said
it will reduce daily flights from 830 to 803 on Jan. 31.
   Among the reductions are cuts in nonstop service from Miami to
Boston, Philadelphia, Orlando, Tampa and several Caribbean cities.
That will reduce Eastern's departures from its Miami home base from
78 to 51, with deeper cuts ahead next year when the sale of Latin
American routes to American Airlines is completed.
   In a message to employees this week, Eastern said ``some
furloughs may be necessary as we reduce operations.''
   ``It's a reflection of the revamping we're in the process of
doing on the current operation, which is going to involve a return
to the basics of the business plan that was presented in April,''
company spokesman Robin Matell said Friday. ``We're trying to
develop the best possible schedule that opens the most potential
for profitability.''
   Hobbled by the strike of its three unions that began March 4,
Eastern filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection five days later
and in April said it would rebuild as a carrier about two-thirds
its pre-strike size. Negotiations to sell its Central and South
American routes to rival American stalled in August, and Eastern
officials said they would keep that service and build back to 90
percent of Eastern's pre-strike size.
   However, projected cash shortfalls displeased some Eastern
creditors, and the company and its parent Texas Air Corp. this week
sold the Latin routes and other assets to American.
   Eastern will continue operating the routes until the deal
obtains approval from the Department of Transportation and U.S.
bankruptcy court, expected to take as much as six months.
   However, the carrier is going ahead with other adjustments back
to the plan for operations two-thirds that of its pre-strike size,
Matell said.
   Eastern had more than 30,000 employees and 1,040 daily flights
before the strike.
   The company has about 20,000 workers, mostly non-union, now.
Matell said no layoffs of pilots, flight attendants or mechanics
are anticipated.
   American, the nation's largest airline, has said it will absorb
Eastern's employees in Latin America when it takes over the routes.
   Officials of the Machinists union, the lone union still striking
against Eastern, said Eastern's planes are flying at less than half
capacity, despite the carrier's sharp fare discounting in hopes of
luring back passengers. Matell said Eastern's flights have been at
about 50 percent for the first half of December, but were picking
up for the holidays.
   At Machinists Local 702, strikers and their families gathered
Friday evening for a Christmas party, with Santa Claus handing out
gifts donated from the AFL-CIO and several other national unions,
local President Frank Ortis said.
   ``We're going to have a happy Christmas after all, despite the
Scrooge (Chairman) Frank Lorenzo,'' Ortis said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>