<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 1119EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Portugal-Discoveries Bjt   12-31 0830</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Portugal-Discoveries, Bjt,0854</SECOND>
<HEAD>Is Small Beautiful For Portugal's 500-Year Discoveries Celebrations?</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TONY SMITH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LISBON, Portugal (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Spain's plans to stage a
headline-grabbing 500th birthday party for America in 1992 have
stirred up a storm of controversy over how Portugal is celebrating
its own discoverers, who were charting the Atlantic before
Christopher Columbus was born.
   Spain and Portugal were archrivals in the push in the 15th and
16th centuries to sail off the end of known maps and find new
worlds. Both succeeded.
   But now, many Portuguese fear their neighbors are stealing the
limelight for the 1992 fiesta.
   At the center of Spain's celebrations is Seville's Expo '92, a
530-acre international fair that is set to end a six-month run Oct.
12, 1992, 500 years to the day after Columbus reached the Caribbean
island of San Salvador.
   Also making Spain hot property in 1992 will be the excitement of
the Summer Olympic games in Barcelona. And the European Economic
Community has chosen Madrid as its cultural capital on the eve of
the trading bloc's deadline to create a single European market.
   Compared with all that, Portugal's 1992 celebrations seem
lackluster.
   Lisbon's government-appointed National Discoveries Commission is
promoting research, exhibitions and the publishing of more history
books about the era.
   It has commissioned American composer Philip Glass to write an
opera for 1992 release, based probably on the Lusiads _ an epic
poem about Vasco da Gama's voyages that was written by Portugal's
16th century roving bard, Luis de Camoes.
   But the Spaniards got there first by casting Catalan soprano
Montserrat Caballe and tenor Jose Carreras in Cristobal Colon, an
opera based on trials and tribulations of the Genoese captain. It
sold out when it premiered in Barcelona in September.
   News media, executives and even historians here have called for
more glamour to promote Portugal's past glories and to show that it
is a rapidly modernizing European country.
   ``I'm ashamed at how my country is celebrating the
discoveries,'' said Waldemar de Abreu, a Lisbon publisher and
editor of ``The Portuguese Christopher Columbus _ Secret Agent of
King Dom Joao II,'' a 600-page book that claims proof the explorer
was Portuguese.
   ``Portugal could easily have pooled resources with Spain and
staged an Iberian discoveries exhibition in 1992,'' de Abreu said.
   While admitting Spain ``is pegging all the force of its
modernization on 1992,'' Vasco Graca Moura, head of the
Commission's executive board, makes no apologies for not going
overboard in that year.
   ``The main difference is that Spain is only commemorating one
date and a short journey _ Columbus' voyage in 1492 to the West
Indies,'' he said.
   ``Our celebrations began last year with Bartolomeu Dias and will
only end in 2000, with Pedro Alvares Cabral.''
   Spurred by their pioneering Prince Henry the Navigator's studies
of astronomy and cartography, Portuguese seafarers had claimed the
island of Madeira and the mid-Atlantic Azores archipelago by 1430.
   Dias took his ship around the Cape of Good Hope in 1488, leaving
da Gama to open up the sea route to India 10 years later.
   Cabral discovered Brazil in 1500, the Portuguese went east of
India to Japan, and Fernao de Magalhaes _ better known as Magellan
_ closed the Discoveries circle in 1520 by commanding the first
expedition to sail around the world.
   ``Our commemorations match our dimension _ we're smaller than
Spain, so honestly we can't be as elaborate,'' said the
commission's Antonio Mega Ferreira, though adding Portugal still
has a few tricks up its sleeve.
   Lisbon last week submitted its candidacy to the Paris-based
International Exhibitions Bureau, to hold Expo '98 _ a three-month,
international fair, only about a tenth the size of Seville.
   Instead of trying for the Olympics, Portugal is expected to bid
in January to hold soccer's World Cup in 1998.
   Expo '98's theme will be East meets West, its hero _ Vasco da
Gama. Graca Moura argues da Gama's trips to the Orient were as
important as Columbus' discovery in the West.
   Mega Ferreira's plans for Expo '98 include a subway train
connecting the undeveloped left bank of the Tagus estuary with
Lisbon's historic Belem district.
   Belem is already the site of three ornate monuments to the
discoveries _ Belem tower and Jeronimos monastery, and former
dictator Antonio Oliveira Salazar's colossal, caravel-shaped
``Padrao'' _ a pillar that navigators used to leave behind them on
land to mark the spread of the Portuguese empire.
   Salazar in 1940 organized an exhibition called ``O Mundo
Portugues'' _ the Portuguese world, that glorified the country's
discoveries and African empire to distract attention from its
isolation in Europe and World War II that was going on around it.
   ``The (center-right) government has a complex of being linked to
Salazar. They're frightened they'd be accused of nationalism, if
they did more to glorify our history,'' de Abreu said. ``But
nobody's accusing Spain's socialist government of anything, and
what is Seville if not a glorification of Spain's colonial past?''
</TEXT>

</DOC>