<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0653EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     12-30 0586</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0606</SECOND>
<HEAD>Winter Weather Slaps Southwest, Northeast</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A Southwest winter storm that dumped nearly a foot of snow on
parts of central Arizona lingered today and snow mixed with
freezing rain and sleet glazed the Northeast from Lower Michigan to
Long Island.
   Snow advisories were in effect for central Arizona and winter
weather advisories were posted over much of New Mexico today.
   By mid-afternoon Friday, Arizona snowfall included 11 inches at
Flagstaff, 8 inches at Sunset Crater and Pinetop, and 7 inches at
Walnut Canyon.
   A snow advisory was posted for Southern California's San Gabriel
and San Bernardino mountains. Advisories for strong winds were
posted over the northern deserts and Owens Valley of Southern
California.
   In addition to Arizona, snow extended today from Washington
state through Montana and Wyoming to the Dakotas, south to Nebraska
and northern parts of Illinois and Iowa across much of Wisconisin
and Michigan to southern New England and New York state.
   In the Midwest today, a weak low-pressure trough in the central
Mississippi Valley was expected to drift northeast, bringing light
snow as cold air regrouped over Wisconsin.
   Upper-level winds were forecast to shift to the northwest
Sunday, allowing another surge of cold air to descend into the
Great Lakes region.
   A cold front over Indiana and Missouri will slide southeast
today, to be replaced by an upper disturbance from south-central
Canada.
   The front should spawn freezing drizzle and flurries over parts
of Kansas, Iowa, Missouri, Illinois, Nebraska, Pennsylvania,
southern New Jersey, Delaware, Maryland, West Virginia and northern
Virginia.
   Colder air was expected to sock the nation's midsection today.
The cold, combined with the Canadian disturbance, should continue
the threat of light precipitation.
   By tonight and Sunday, northwest winds will push clouds and
flurries out of the Midwest.
   Friday was the 23rd day this month the temperature at
Pennsylvania's Williamsport-Lycoming Airport failed to rise above
32 degrees, setting a record for December cold in the area.
   Three California cities enjoyed record high temperatures Friday.
Oakland's 65 degrees, Sacramento's 72 and San Francisco's 68 melted
old marks.
   Friday's high temperature in the nation was 81 degrees at
Kingsville and McAllen, Tex.
   Other reports at 3 a.m. EST today:
   _East: Atlanta 51 cloudy; Boston 16 snow; Charleston, S.C. 47
partly cloudy; Chattanooga 47 rain; Cincinnati 38 foggy; Cleveland
32 foggy; Detroit 24 cloudy; Hatteras 46 partly cloudy;
Jacksonville 41 foggy; Key West 66 fair; Knoxville 42 cloudy; Macon
55 partly cloudy; Miami 64 fair; New York 30 snow; Philadelphia 33
rain; Pittsburgh 34 drizzle; Portland, Maine 8 snow; Richmond 40
rain; Tampa 54 fair; Washington, D.C. 33 cloudy.
   _Central: Bismarck 18 cloudy; Chicago 32 foggy; Denver 20 fair;
Des Moines 27 freezing drizzle; Indianapolis 34 foggy; Kansas City
30 freezing drizzle; Little Rock 56 drizzle; Louisville 48 drizzle;
Memphis 59 foggy; Nashville 55 foggy; New Orleans 61 foggy; North
Platte 26 cloudy; Rapid City 25 cloudy; St. Louis 41 drizzle;
Minneapolis-St. Paul 19 snow; Sault Ste. Marie 8 fair; San Antonio
62 foggy.
   _West: Anchorage 3 cloudy; Boise 16 fair; Casper 24 snow;
Fairbanks 15 fair; Great Falls 29 cloudy; Honolulu 74 fair; Las
Vegas 50 fair; Los Angeles 52 fair; Medford 26 smoke; Pendleton 29
fair; Phoenix 49 fair; Portland, Ore. 39 foggy; Reno 20 fair; Salt
Lake City 24 hazy; San Diego 52 fair; San Francisco 44 fair;
Seattle 44 cloudy; Spokane 27 cloudy.
   _International: Montreal 14 hazy; Ottawa 14 fair; Regina 18
fair; Toronto 12 snow; Winnipeg 1 partly cloudy; Mexico City 50
fair.
</TEXT>

</DOC>