<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0168 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 2328EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Liu-Taiwan     12-29 0645</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Liu-Taiwan,0664</SECOND>
<HEAD>Taiwan Found Liable for Official Who Ordered Murder</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BOB EGELKO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government of Taiwan is legally
responsible for the acts of a military official who ordered the
1984 killing of a Taiwanese-American journalist, a federal appeals
court ruled Friday.
   The decision by the 9th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals not only
reinstates a $200 million suit by the widow of journalist Henry Liu
but also links the Taiwanese government to the actions of its
defense intelligence chief, Vice Admiral Wong Hsi-Lin, who has been
convicted in Taiwan's own courts.
   ``Wong's act was committed within the scope of his employment as
director of the DIB (Defense Intelligence Bureau),'' the court
said. ``We conclude that the ROC (Republic of China) is liable.''
   The ruling, if upheld, would virtually guarantee that Taiwan
would be found liable for the murder itself, leaving only the
question of damages to be resolved.
   ``I read the decision to say that the Republic of China is
liable under California law for the murder of Henry Liu,'' said
Gerard Harper, a lawyer for Helen Liu, who sued for her husband's
death.
   ``It's the first time, to my knowledge, that in a contested case
a foreign state has been held liable for a murder in the United
States.''
   ``My intention was to find the truth of this case, because the
trial held in Taiwan was orchestrated,'' Mrs. Liu said Friday.
   ``The reasons why they had to kill Henry, they didn't ask in the
(Taiwanese) court. ... I want people to know the real reasons, the
mentality of the Taiwan regime. He (her husband) was trying to get
Taiwan to be a more democratic country.''
   John Martel, a lawyer for Taiwan, said he had not seen the
ruling and could not say whether it would be appealed. But he said
any implication that the government was responsible for the murder
was false.
   The ruling is one of several recent decisions allowing lawsuits
against foreign officials for allegedly ordering crimes in the
United States.
   Earlier this month, a jury in Seattle found the estate of former
Philippine dictator Ferdinand Marcos liable for the 1981 killings
of two Philippine-American dissidents and labor union activists.
   Liu, 52, a Taiwanese-born U.S. citizen and author of a critical
biography of Taiwan President Chiang Ching-Kuo, was shot to death
in October 1984 at his home in Daly City, south of San Francisco,
by gunmen who were later traced to the United Bamboo Gang in Taiwan.
   Military courts in Taiwan convicted five men of responsibility
for the murder, including Admiral Wong, who was found to have
ordered the gangsters to silence Liu. He was sentenced to life in
prison. A sixth man was convicted of murder in a California court.
   While finding that Wong was motivated by Liu's criticism of the
government as well as a personal grudge, the Taiwanese courts
concluded that Taiwan's government was not responsible for Wong's
unauthorized actions.
   U.S. District Judge Eugene Lynch cited that conclusion in
September 1987 when he dismissed Mrs. Liu's suit against the
government.
   Lynch said Wong was acting outside the scope of his employment.
A U.S. court could not authorize a further inquiry into the
conclusions of the Taiwanese courts, Lynch said, without involving
the judiciary in sensitive areas of a foreign government's national
security and intelligence affairs, causing potential embarassment
to U.S. foreign policy.
   The appeals court, in a 3-0 ruling, disagreed with both of
Lynch's conclusions.
   The opinion by Judge Robert Boochever said the relationship of
Wong's actions and his job as intelligence chief was shown by the
factual findings of the Taiwan courts.
   As for the Republic of China, although the suit may affect its
government financially, ``it does not affront its sovereignty and
can cause no more embarrassment than the exposures already made by
the ROC courts,'' Boochever said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>