<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0195 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1324EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Rexene     12-28 0368</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Rexene,0382</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dallas Firm Announces Common Stock Dividend Suspension</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Plastics-maker Rexene Corp. says it will suspend
its quarterly common stock dividend, citing ``current industry
conditions, changes in the financial markets and other operating
factors.''
   The suspension of the quarter-per-share dividend comes less than
six months after Dallas-based Rexene borrowed $500 million to pay a
special $7 per share dividend to stockholders. The company, which
has forecast improved fourth quarter earnings, also is selling off
assets to pay off debt.
   Rexene was taken private in a $456 million buyout in April,
1988, financed through high yield, or junk, bonds sold by Drexel
Burnham Lambert Inc.
   Four months later, Rexene went public again, selling stock at
$21.50 per share. The stock has fallen dramatically since then,
standing at $3.75 a share at mid-day Thursday, down 50 cents from
Wednesday, when it fell $1.87{ in composite trading on the New York
Stock Exchange.
   Almost half of the company's new stock is held by partnerships
controlled by current or former Drexel employees, the Wall Street
Journal reported Thursday.
   In the past year, Rexene has announced a 10-percent work force
reduction, plus sales of manufacturing facilities in Bayport and
Odessa, Texas, where more than half of its employees are located.
   The Bayport facility, which includes polypropylene and
polyethylene plants, was sold to Lyondell Petrochemical Co. for $88
million. Analysts had anticipated it would bring about $100 million.
   The Odessa Styrene plant also is on the block, and the company
said Wednesday it still is looking for buyers.
   Other asset sales need to occur soon, analysts said, because an
anticipated downturn could cut their value.
   ``We are in for another shakeout so their timing in getting on
with it is rather critical,'' said Peter Savage, a vice president
at consulting firm DeWitt &amp; Co. in Houston.
   Rexene said the dividend suspension will be reviewed quarterly.
   In the latest quarter, Rexene lost $9.1 million, or 29 cents per
share, compared with a profit in 1988 of $35.5 million.
   The company, formerly known as El Paso Products Co. and based in
Odessa, makes thermoplastic resins and petrochemical products used
in the manufacture of such items as plastic milk cartons and other
containers.
</TEXT>

</DOC>