<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0098 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1106EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-EastGermany 2ndLd-Writethru   12-20 0707</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-East Germany, 2nd Ld-Writethru,a0595,0731</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kohl Says No Need to Fear Reunification</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE with Kohl news conference. No pickup.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NESHA STARCEVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DRESDEN, East Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chancellor Helmut Kohl of West
Germany tried to reassure opponents of German reunification today
and said their fears of an evil German empire based on past horrors
are ``absurd.''
   Kohl, during a news conference closing a triumphant two-day
visit, also said he expects a treaty expanding East and West German
ties to be completed by May.
   Kohl met with Communist Premier Hans Modrow on Tuesday, and the
two later announced plans for the treaty and a number of other
changes:
   _The famed Brandenburg Gate, isolated in East Berlin since the
Berlin Wall was built in 1961, will be reopened by Christmas.
   _Germans will be allowed to travel without visas between the two
states beginning Christmas Eve.
   _East Germany will free all political prisoners, with many to be
released before Christmas.
   Kohl pledged to take into account the concerns of other European
countries as the two German states, created after World War II,
move closer together.
   ``It's the most natural thing that Germans want to live
together,'' Kohl said.
   Kohl pledged to avoid ``destabilization,'' a reference to the
power vacuum in East Germany that has followed the virtual collapse
of Communist Party control here since a popular revolution began in
the fall.
   Kohl added: ``Fears based in the past are understandable, but
there is nothing to be feared from the future. It's absurd to talk
about a Fourth Reich.''
   East German Communists and other opponents of reunification have
said joining the two states could create a ``Fourth Reich,'' and
have reminded people of the atrocities of Nazi dictator Adolf
Hitler's Third Reich.
   In meeting with several opposition groups, including New Forum,
Democratic Awakening, and others, Kohl said he heard none of them
voice opposition to eventual reunification.
   New Forum representative Arnold Vaatz told the official news
agency ADN he found ``broad agreement'' with Kohl and that his
group was ``thankful'' for the results of the summit.
   Earlier today, Kohl met with the Roman Catholic bishops of
Dresden and Berlin, Joachim Reinelt and Georg Sterzinsky.
   Sterzinsky said he and Reinelt explained their views on future
cooperation with West Germany in the meeting with Kohl.
   Sterzinsky said he expects West Germany to ``treat us as a
partner and help with our renewal.'' He viewed the visit by Kohl, a
conservative Christian Democrat, as ``entirely positive,'' the
official news agency ADN reported.
   West Germany's Bild newspaper quoted unidentified officials in
Dresden as saying Berlin's Brandenburg Gate will be open to
pedestrians Friday. The newspaper said its report would appear in
Thursday's editions. It was sent in advance to other news media
today.
   The Brandenburg Gate is a symbol of German unity to millions and
was a centerpiece of a major Berlin thoroughfare before the wall
was built 28 years ago.
   Under the pressure of massive pro-democracy demonstrations
starting in October, openings have been made in the wall, two sets
of Communist leaders have been ousted, and free elections are
scheduled in May. At the same time, West Germany has warmly
accepted all East German refugees and offered to help revive its
neighbor's struggling economy.
   At a joint news conference after their summit, Kohl and Modrow
said their talks had made progress toward what the two nations
refer to as a ``treaty community.'' Such an arrangement would
safeguard the sovereignty of both states.
   Talks leading up to the planned bilateral treaty could focus on
improving traffic connections, telecommunications and pollution
problems, Kohl said.
   Both leaders agreed to meet again in late January or early
February in West Germany.
   While Kohl stressed the ``right of self-determination'' for
citizens in both Germany on the issue of reunification, Modrow
called for the continued existence of two German states.
   Kohl joined his host in counseling caution and patience.
   Later, Kohl received an emotional welcome from a crowd of about
20,000 at an outdoor evening rally.
   People repeatedly burst into wild cheers, applause and chants of
``Unity!'' ``Unity!'' as Kohl addressed them as his ``countrymen.''
   Many waved West German flags, outnumbering those carrying signs
insisting on East German sovereignty or attacking Kohl.
</TEXT>

</DOC>