<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0834EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Panama 1stLd-Writethru   12-23 1037</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama, 1st Ld - Writethru,a0463,1069</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Sending More Troops to Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 12 grafs to UPDATE with plane bombing resistance
position, U.S. troops moving against looters in port city. Pickup 4th,
`The Red...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos WX9,10,PAN12, LaserColor NY9</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CANDICE HUGHES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Air Force plane bombed a
resistance position today, and the U.S. military reportedly decided
to reinforce its troops after its headquarters were attacked by
forces loyal to Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   Anarchy ruled the streets, and residents set up vigilante squads
to protect homes and businesses from looters and from the
paramilitary ``Dignity Battalions'' loyal to Noriega.
   The U.S. plane repeatedly bombed a hilltop position at 4 a.m. in
the working-class district of San Miguelito, site of the Panamanian
military garrison of Tinajitas. Witnesses said the bombing run
lasted about five minutes, and the plane apparently did not draw
ground fire.
   An observation plane and a helicopter conducted lengthy patrols
over the area before the raid.
   Civilians manned street barricades overnight to prevent the
Dignity Battalions from sacking homes and stealing cars. In some
areas Friday, the paramilitaries went door to door to demand car
keys and loot homes.
   U.S. troops moved into the port city of Colon on Friday to quell
widespread looting, and 200 members of the Defense Forces
surrendered, Lt. Col. Johnny Brooks, told a group of Pentagon pool
repoorters.
   He said the soldiers fought a small group of snipers but that no
Americans were wounded.
   A local businessman, Esteban Jimenez, told reporters that 55
people had been killed in the days of looting.
   Brooks said that in one case troops shot the tires of a forklift
to prevent it from carrying a luxury automobile down the street.
``Have you ever seen a BMW on a forklift?'' he said.
   Leopold Benedetti, a former mayor of the city, said residents
needed medical supplies. The U.S. invasion began midnight Tuesday.
   Members of the Dignity Battalions fired at the car of the
U.S.-installed first vice president, Ricardo Arias Calderon, as he
left the National Assembly on Friday. He was not hurt, but two
aides were wounded, another aide said.
   The Red Cross appealed for food for thousands of refugees of the
fighting and hospitals were short of medical supplies.
   Rumors were rife about Noriega's whereabouts but the general who
stubbornly resisted two years of U.S. political and economic
pressure remained elusive.
   The Bush administration said it launched ``Operation Just
Cause'' to bring him to the United States to face federal drug
trafficking charges, restore democracy and protect the 35,000
Americans living in the country.
   The government that was sworn in Tuesday night requires U.S.
protection and has no police or army to back it, indicating it may
be some time before a working democracy is built in Panama.
   The Dignity Battalions, joined by an unknown number of Noriega's
once 15,000-strong Defense Forces, were putting up a tougher battle
than U.S. officials anticipated.
   Gen. Maxwell Thurman, chief of the U.S. Southern Command, said
he was ``surprised'' by the strength of the remaining Noriega
forces. The fighting is ``a little bit greater than I expected at
the onset.'
   He said the estimated 1,800 members of the Dignity Battalions
had broken up into groups of 10 to 12.
   ``It is organized, clearly organized,'' he said.
   A Pentagon source said Friday night that 2,000 more U.S.
soldiers would be flown to Panama to augment the 24,000 already in
the country. The stiff Panamanian resistance was extending an
operation originally planned for three days. Military officials in
Washington said it would take 10 more days.
   On Friday, Noriega loyalists attacked Quarry Heights, the
Southern Command headquarters on the western edge of Panama City,
for an hour at midday.
   Mortars thundered from the railroad tracks below, shaking the
hillside building as they struck the ground nearby. Helicopters and
machine gunfire chattered overhead.
   About a dozen fighters attacked U.S. soldiers occupying
Panamanian secret police headquarters by the railroad below and
gunfire hit a warehouse and other buildings near the Panama Canal
Commission headquarters a few blocks away.
   There were no reports on casualties.
   In the first three days of fighting, 21 American soldiers and
127 Panamanian soldiers were killed, the Pentagon said. It reported
221 Americans and 66 Panamanians wounded, and two American soldiers
and one civilian missing. Two civilian U.S. dependents were killed
and 1,663 Panamanians detained.
   But Dr. Elmer Miranda, deputy director of Santo Tomas Hospital
in Panama City, said there were 200 bodies there. He said a
colleague said there were 60 more in Gorgas Hospital, run by the
U.S. Southern Command.
   The Supreme Court, about a mile to the southeast, was set ablaze
Friday and planes made occasional bombing runs on San Miguelito, a
center of resistance.
   Sporadic gunfire continued into the night.
   American troops seized 10,000 weapons in three separate caches
in Panama City, primarily East bloc weapons. Lt. Gen. Tom Kelly,
director of operations for the Joint Chiefs of Staff, called the
discovery ``little short of astonishing.''
   He said U.S. forces have made some progress, such as taking the
legislative building, the presidential palace, central bank, and
several ministries.
   Military intelligence officers pored over papers from Noriega's
offices but said they found few clues as to the general's
whereabouts.
   Glass, trash and toppled light poles littered the streets of
Panama City, a flourishing international banking center just two
years ago. Columns of smoke darkened the sky where gunfire and
mortar attacks were launched.
   Thousands of people of all ages and incomes looted supermarkets,
department stores and boutiques.
   Snipers were reported in many areas of the city. Gunshots, many
of them fired by shopowners and private armed guards trying to
prevent looting, rang through virtually every neighborhood.
   With no police protection, residents took the law into their own
hands.
   Many Panamanians were too frightened to come out of their homes.
   Latin American countries have protested the intervention, with
Peru acting most decisevly on its objections by suspending joint
anti-drug operations with U.S. agents in the Huallaga Valley, a
major cocaine producing region.
   President Alan Garcia said Thursday that he would not attend a
Feb. 15 drug summit with President Bush and leaders of Colombia and
Bolivia.
</TEXT>

</DOC>