<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1607EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Church     12-25 0353</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Church,0363</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man With A Grenade Interrupts Christmas Mass in Bucharest</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DUSAN STOJANOVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man armed with a hand grenade was
captured outside Bucharest's main Mitropolia cathedral during
Christmas service Monday after worshipers shouted that he was a
terrorist.
   The patriarch of the Romanian Orthodox Church, Teoctist Arapasu,
was preparing to address hundreds of worshipers who braved sporatic
gunfire to attend the service when the man, who carried an
identification card from the hated Securitate secret police, was
spotted.
   A woman and some other people started shouting, ``We know this
man, he's a terrorist.''
   Two soldiers and a group of civilians who acted as security in
front of the church jumped on the man, opened his raincoat. They
showed he was wearing a bulletproof vest and was armed with a hand
grenade.
   The man, taken away by soldiers armed with automatic rifles, did
not resist. The soldiers took the documents from the man and a
Securitate identification card.
   In the church, Arapasu thanked about 500 worshipers for coming
to the service despite the battles between a new government and
forces loyal to deposed Communist dictator Nicolae Ceausescu.
   Ceausescu was reported captured Saturday with his wife, Elena,
as the tried to flee a popular uprising. State radio announced the
Ceausescus were executed Monday after a secret trial at which they
were convicted of genocide and plundering of $1 billion in public
funds.
   The partiarch asked people to pray for ``the brave young people
who have given their lives in the struggle against Ceausescu's
terrorist regime.''
   ``We must thank God, who gave us freedom after 25 years of
terror,'' the patriarch told the congregation. ``Many of our church
services were banned by the terrorist regime. We must not let this
happen again.''
   The patriarch also thanked hundreds of people who brought
presents and food to the church in memory of the dead.
   ``I have been waiting 40 years for this. Now I can openly go to
church,'' said Ion Ganescu, a dissident who spent 10 years in
prison for his opposition to Ceausescu.
</TEXT>

</DOC>