<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0180 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1250EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-YE--Deaths1989 Adv00-1stAdd   12-19 0553</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-YE--Deaths 1989, Adv 00 - 1st Add,0579</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv00</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release in Year-End Editions</HEAD>
<HEAD>UNDATED: street shooting.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   DIANA VREELAND, flamboyant arbiter of the fashion world who
edited two leading women's magazines and coined the phrase ``the
beautiful people.'' Exact age unknown, but believed to be about 86.
   IRVING STONE, whose biographical novels of Vincent Van Gogh,
Michelangelo and Sigmund Freud brought history to life for millions
of readers. Age 86.
   JOSEPH ALSOP, longtime political columnist. Age 78.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>SEPTEMBER</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   A. BARTLETT GIAMATTI, baseball lover and former president of
Yale University whose short tenure as baseball commissioner was
dominated by the investigation and banishment of Pete Rose. At age
51 of a heart attack.
   GEORGES SIMENON, prolific writer of more than 200 novels,
including 80 featuring the popular Inspector Maigret. His books
were translated into 55 languages and sold more than 500 million
copies worldwide, making him perhaps the most widely read author of
the 20th century. Age 86.
   ROBERT PENN WARREN, the nation's first poet laureate, winner of
three Pulitzer prizes for fiction and poetry rooted in his native
South. Age 84.
   IRVING BERLIN, whose songs such as ``Cheek to Cheek,'' ``Easter
Parade,'' ``White Christmas'' and ``God Bless America'' were the
essence of American popular music. Age 101.
   FERDINAND E. MARCOS, ruled the Philippines for more than 20
years but became an unwanted exile after being ousted in 1986. Age
72.
   AUGUST A. BUSCH, JR., patriarch of the world's largest brewing
dynasty and president of baseball's St. Louis Cardinals. Age 90.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>OCTOBER</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   GRAHAM CHAPMAN, a founding member of the zany British comedy
group Monty Python's Flying Circus. At age 48 of cancer.
   BETTE DAVIS, two-time Oscar winner whose toughness, huge eyes
and haughty cigarette-smoking style made her a Hollywood legend.
Age 81.
   ANTHONY QUAYLE, veteran actor-director. Known to film audiences
for his roles as a fighting man in such films as ``The Guns of
Navarone,'' he also was honored with British knighthood as a
mainstay of the classical theater. Age 76.
   MARY McCARTHY, critic and novelist whose ice-clear observations
of politics and literature made her one of America's longtime
literary stars. Age 77.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>NOVEMBER</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   VLADIMIR HOROWITZ, titan of the keyboard who brought
``controlled thunder'' to the piano, dazzling the world for 60
years. Age 85.
   CHARLES BECK, comic book artist who created Captain Marvel, the
superhero who came to life at the word ``Shazam.'' Age 79.
   CLEMENT F. HAYNESWORTH JR., whose nomination to the Supreme
Court in 1969 was rejected by the Senate because of his business
practices and his views on minorities. Age 77.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>DECEMBER</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   ALVIN AILEY, dancer and choreographer whose dynamic style
introduced black American music and traditions into modern dance
and helped transform it into a popular art form. At age 58 of a
blood disorder.
   SAMMY FAIN, Oscar-winning composer whose classic love ballads
included ``Love Is a Many Splendored Thing'' and ``I'll Be Seeing
You.'' Age 87.
   JOHN PAYNE, leading man who starred in Hollywood musicals with
Alice Faye and Betty Grable and in dramas such as ``Miracle on 34th
Street.'' Age 77.
   ANDREI SAKHAROV, Soviet dissident, Nobel Peace Prize winner and
brilliant scientist who built the Soviet hydrogen bomb. Risked his
status as a national hero to openly challenge the government on
behalf of disarmament and human rights. Age 68.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Release in Year-End Editions</NOTE>

</DOC>