<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0228 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1607EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-TelephoneRates 2ndLd-Writethru   12-19 0420</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Telephone Rates, 2nd Ld-Writethru,0432</SECOND>
<HEAD>AT&amp;T to Reduce Long Distance Rates</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: CORRECTS ``weekend'' to ``weekday'' in 5th graf: ``This would,''</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By W. DALE NELSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   American Telephone &amp; Telegraph Co. announced
today it will reduce rates by $300 million a year on interstate and
international long-distance services used primarily by residential
and small business customers.
   The price reductions will take effect Jan. 1, AT&amp;T said The
company said they would apply to its basic long-distance service
plus international calls and the AT&amp;T ``Reach Out America'' and
optional long-distance plans.
   The reduction would be the company's 10th since 1984 and would
bring total rate decreases to 40 percent in the six years since the
breakup of the Bell System, the company announcement said.
   The company said a 10-minute call, at any time of day to
anywhere in the United States, will cost $2.50 or less after the
decrease takes effect. At night or on a weekend, such calls will
cost $1.32 or less, it said.
   This would be a reduction of 1.3 percent on weekday calls and 2
percent on evening calls, the company said.
   AT&amp;T said price cuts, filed today with the Federal
Communications Commission, reflect reduced expenses, mainly from
lower fees that the company will pay in 1990 to local telephone
companies for access to customers' lines.
   Under FCC guidelines, those costs savings lower the price cap on
AT&amp;T long-distance services.
   The proposal includes:
   _A 1.3 percent drop in prices for basic long-distance service
during the weekday calling period, which is 8 a.m. to 5. p.m. local
time Monday through Friday, and a 2 percent drop during the evening
period, 5 p.m. to 11 p.m. Sunday through Friday.
   _Increasing discounts for subscribers to the Reach Out America
24-hour plan from 5 percent to 10 percent on weekday calls and from
20 to 25 percent on evening calls, 5 p.m. to 10 p.m. Sunday through
Friday.
   _A $104 million price slash on international calls from the U.S.
mainland to 25 of the most frequently called countries and overseas
areas, with the reductions varying by country and time of day.
Countries include Canada, Mexico, Japan, the United Kingdom,
France, Italy, Israel, Brazil, Australia, the Philippines, Taiwan
and Korea.
   _Reductions in the price of service to 39 countries by AT&amp;T
World Connect, which gives frequent international callers a
discount on direct-dialed calls from the U.S. mainland.
   _A reduction in basic long-distance prices from Puerto Rico and
the U.S. Virgin Islands to 95 countries and territories.
</TEXT>

</DOC>