<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0200 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0710EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e AM-APArts:AmericaEats Adv27   12-21 0997</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-AP Arts: America Eats, Adv 27,1023</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv27</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Wednesday AMs, Dec. 27, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Form and Function Meet in Edible Folk Arts</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY MacVEAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When William Woys Weaver picks up an old, red
clay stewpot or a wooden cookie press, it's the nicks and cracks
that draw his practiced eye.
   ``The form is what I look at first. I like to pick up and see
where it was used, where the scratches are. That's first and
foremost. If I can figure that out, it makes me happy,'' said
Weaver, guest curator for the exhibit ``America Eats: Forms of
Edible Folk Art'' at the Museum of American Folk Art.
   There are no Styrofoam boxes, microwave-ready trays or juice
boxes, but there is a lovely rolling pin of whalebone and mahogany
made by an American sailor around 1850. There's a batter jug
decorated with blue swirls, with two handles and a spout for
pouring onto a griddle. There is an eagle-shaped cookie cutter, and
an intricate cider jelly mold. Many pots are glazed inside to
withstand the acids of pickling or preserving.
   ``America Eats'' traces folk cookery, mostly in the East,
through 135 objects from the 1600s to 1920s. A book of the same
name from Harper &amp; Row looks more deeply into cooking history and
includes 42 recipes adapted to today's kitchens and ingredients.
   The food is functional, hearty, simple: ``Foods that no longer
serve a purpose are quickly forgotten,'' Weaver writes.
   He celebrates the simple: ``Toast, properly done, was one of the
unsung accomplishments of American folk cookery. It was a culinary
art form reduced by its very nature to the perfection of classic
simplicity. It represented a craftsmanship in folk cookery that has
little to do with ornament.''
   An original recipe for Maryland biscuits directs: ``Beat the
dough with an ax for half an hour, until the dough is soft or until
it breaks when pulled.'' The modern version still requires beating,
but with a rolling pin.
   The exhibit inludes a wooden roller contraption called a break,
which cuts the beating time in half, for either recipe.
   Little has been written about folk cooking, so there are plenty
of misconceptions, such as the labeling of many old stewpots as
chamber pots.
   ``We always assumed people cooked everything in these old cast
iron boilers. But a lot was done in ceramics,'' said Weaver, who is
trained as an architect and found himself working increasingly on
kitchens and food.
   Iron cookware came into vogue as cooks had to deal with the more
intense heat of iron stoves.
   ``More than any other single force, the cookstove brought a
radical change to the art of cookery,'' Weaver writes. ``The rules
that applied in the past, the techniques and oral tradition that
had been relied on for centuries, were suddenly obsolete.''
   And toward the end of the 19th century, the tin can made food
available away from its source. ``There was a mysterious virture, a
sense of impending progress, once Americans discovered that they
could put folk culture into a can,'' Weaver writes.
   Folk art has enjoyed a new popularity today, and folk cooking
has benefited from that as well as from a heightened interest in
food.
   ``We are looking at the kitchen a lot today because there is an
immense interest in cooking, regional cuisines, women's studies.
All of this has given it a respectability it hasn't had before,''
Weaver said.
   Many people, he said, are attracted by the sense of nostalgia;
others, perhaps fed up with today's quick food, are drawn by the
craftsmanship.
   ``Things are so rootless today. These are kind of touchstones.
It reminds people of their backgrounds, their grandmothers,
great-grandmothers,'' giving the sense of connectedness that is a
major theme of Weaver's book.
   Food plays an essential role in the search for connectedness, he
said.
   ``If I moved away, I could still make my Pennsylvania Dutch food
in Seattle, or wherever. It's inside me like my spirit. I don't
think anything comes as close as food.''
   And connections are on several levels. A folk cook is connected
to the fuel and water supply, aware how much effort it takes to
keep water hot for washing, said Alice Ross, an expert in hearth
cooking from Long Island. The cook also is connected to the
regional foods available to her, to her family or community.
   Food also connected people to major events, and Weaver writes of
funeral biscuits, Election Day cakes and New Year's cakes, as well
as to the seasons. And it connects people over time, from ``Indians
using corn right down to popcorn and Fritos. There's a
continuity,'' Weaver said.
   ``There is a great interest in ethnicity,'' Ross said. ``As
things have disappeared more, you get to the third and fourth
generations of families, they don't really want to have lost all
that's been lost.''
   One reason folk cooking has been of interest to professionals
only for the last 20 years or so was that it was woman's work,
Weaver and Ross said.
   ``It wasn't something that was professional. It was in the
home,'' Weaver said. With one exception, ``I found nothing that I
could honestly say had been made by women for their own use. I
could not find any women tinsmiths or potters.''
   He included in his exhibit a basket made by black women in South
Carolina _ the only item made by blacks.
   But while the nation was polarized over slavery, many people
refused to use ingredients produced by slave labor, a boycott,
Weaver noted, not unlike modern-day protests. Boycott recipes, such
as Wisconsin cake made without molasses or sugar, became part of
the folk repertoire. ``This kind of current is always there in
food,'' Weaver said. ``And it's helpful to know why there was no
molasses or sugar in that honey tea cake.''
   ``America Eats: Forms of Edible Folk Art'' runs through Feb. 4.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Wed AMs, Dec. 27</NOTE>

</DOC>