<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0110 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1418EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Panama-Funerals 1stLd-Writethru a0455 12-29 0685</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Funerals, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0455,0702</SECOND>
<HEAD>Families Bury Soldiers Killed in Panama Invasion</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 6 grafs to update with service today, picking up
2nd graf pvs, `Among those....'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A 19-year-old Illinois soldier killed in the U.S. invasion of
Panama was remembered today as a man who ``believed in what he was
doing,'' as his family and friends gathered for his funeral.
   More than 250 mourners attended a service at Moline, Ill., for
Army Pfc. Scott Lee Roth, one of 23 U.S. servicemen killed in the
invasion to oust Panamanian leader Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   The service for Roth was held one day after six soldiers killed
in the Panama action were buried in services around the country,
with mourners honoring their dedication to an effort that
``silenced an evil regime.''
   More than 40 military men in uniform attended today's service
for Roth.
   ``This is a man who wanted to be a soldier, loved being a
soldier and he believed in what he was doing,'' said Army Lt. Col.
Robert C. Pearson, a chaplain at the Rock Island Arsenal.
   Roth's wife, Mary _ his high school sweetheart who enlisted with
him after graduation _ attended the service with her family and a
military escort.
   Among those buried Thursday was Spec. Alejandro L.
Manriquelozano, the first of the dead from the invasion to be laid
to rest in Arlington National Cemetery.
   Manriquelozano, 30, was buried with military honors _ including
three rifle volleys and the playing of ``Taps'' _ in snow-covered
ground at Arlington within sight of the Capitol and Washington
Monument.
   Manriquelozano, a naturalized American citizen from Peru who
lived in Lauderhill, Fla., was an anti-tank gunner with D Company,
2nd Battalion, 504th Infantry, of the Army's 82nd Airborne Division.
   Manriquelozano's sister, Luz, who flew to Washington for the
funeral with other family members from Lima, Peru, told reporters,
``We are proud of him, because he always wanted to be an American.
His desire is fulfilled.''
   Col. James D. Weiskopf, public affairs officer of the Army
Military District of Washington, said Manriquelozano was the first
of the 23 servicemen listed as killed in Panama whose family had
requested burial at Arlington, although all are eligible.
   In Great Falls, Mont., Gov. Stan Stephens was among the nearly
300 mourners at the funeral of Pvt. 2 Vance Troy Coats, who died
when a grenade exploded in a Panama City neighborhood Dec. 20.
   ``His courageous commitment has silenced an evil regime,''
Stephens said. ``Thank you Troy Coats. Farewell son of Montana.
Rest in peace.''
   In the northern Wisconsin logging community of Conover, hundreds
of friends and relatives honored Pfc. John Mark Price, an Army
paratrooper from the 75th Rangers who would have turned 23 on
Christmas Eve.
   In a tear-filled eulogy attended by about 400 people at the
Evangelical Free Church, Tom Dillahunt, a close friend of Price,
held up a snapshot of the soldier.
   ``He was the gung-ho type, the energy behind any plans that were
made,'' Dillahunt said. ``He died doing what he loved best, being a
soldier. He died to protect us.''
   Another Army Ranger, 19-year-old Pfc. Roy Brown Jr., was buried
in Orange, Calif., and mourners were asked to lay the blame for his
death on Manuel Antonio Noriega, the deposed Panamanian dictator.
   ``Let us criticize the Noriegas, let us criticize the drug lords
... and let us criticize those that would endanger our freedom,''
Pastor Wiley Drake told more than 250 mourners.
   In Pennsylvania, several hundred mourners overflowed the United
Methodist Church of Hallstead for the funeral of a third Ranger,
Staff Sgt. Larry R. Barnard, 29.
   ``He was a guy who really believed in what he was doing,'' said
the Rev. Keith Benjamin, ``and believed in doing it right.''
   Barnard formerly belonged to the 82nd Airborne Division and
served in the U.S. invasion of Grenada.
   In Abilene, Texas, hundreds of relatives and friends turned out
for the funeral of native son Pfc. Martin D. Denson, 21, an
infantryman.
   Denson was buried at Elmwood Memorial Park with full military
honors and a 21-gun salute.
</TEXT>

</DOC>