<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0211 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1537EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a PM-BusinessMirror Adv19   12-18 0573</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Business Mirror, Adv 19,0585</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv19</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release PMs Tuesday, Dec. 19</HEAD>
<HEAD>Developing The Savings Habit</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN CUNNIFF</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Analyst</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Subtle advertising, constant sales, periodic
discounts and rebates, and an abundance of consumer goods helped
make big spenders of many Americans in the decade of the 1980s.
   Now, as if the abundance of choices were insufficient, ordinary
folks are likely to be presented with still another decision in the
1990s: They will be asked to decide between spending and saving.
   It won't be easy after a 15-year addiction to the retail
marketplace, a period in which the subtle arts of marketing, along
with plentiful credit and tax incentives, helped produce a
live-for-now mentality.
   Uncle Sam will be trying to break that habit in the 1990s, and
the government is preparing the first of its incentives, a Family
Savings Account that would allow $5,000 a year to be saved tax-free.
   That's a big incentive, but one many Americans will find
difficult to exploit because, as envisioned, those savings would
lose their tax exemption if not maintained for a decade, an
eternity for those used to immediate gratification.
   In this and other ways the Bush administration hopes to
accomplish two ends: Promote savings, which are necessary for
industrial development and job creation, and spur Americans to seek
greater financial rewards by investing for the long term.
   The consequences are enormous for individuals, the general
economy and government.
   For individuals, saving for the long term rather than immediate
spending might provide the means to buy even more tomorrow.
Investments grow; the value of purchases often falls.
   Money saved generally means a sounder economy, since it is
invested in research and development of plant and equipment that in
turn enhance productive efficiency _ more goods at lower cost _ and
create jobs.
   For government the return might not be immediate. In fact, tax
exemptions can have the short-term effect of reducing revenues. But
over the longer term, a larger, healthier economy inevitably means
an increase in revenues.
   Whether the goals can be accomplished is made uncertain by many
factors. For one thing, the Family Savings Plan would involve a
10-year period of time, an ambitious endeavor in a nation
accustomed to making tax changes each year.
   Individual Retirement Accounts, for example, were originally
meant to spur savings by allowing $2,000 a year to be invested and
deducted from current tax liability. But after several years the
deductibility feature was removed.
   That action, in the opinion of critics, all but emasculated an
otherwise strong incentive to save rather than spend. It probably
left a legacy of doubt about government promised that could impact
the Family Savings Plans.
   However, some of the other tax changes in recent years have been
more in line with the need to save rather than spend. Most consumer
debt, for example, no longer is tax deductible, thus removing at
least one incentive to spending.
   Americans accepted that action with amazing calmness, even
though it proved to be enormously costly to them. However, it
didn't stop them from taking on debt, and in that respect it failed
to make a dent in the buy-now philosophy.
   It leaves this question: If people feel so strongly about buying
that they will pay higher taxes in order to continue buying, will a
program that rewards them for savings instead of buying be any more
successful?
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv PMs Tuesday, Dec. 19.</NOTE>

</DOC>