<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0914EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Panama-NoriegaEscape     12-22 0325</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Noriega Escape,310</SECOND>
<HEAD>Troops Believe They Almost Caught Him</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDITOR'S NOTE: The following is based on a pool dispatch from Panama
by Steven Komarow of The Associated Press and Robert Kearns of Reuters.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEVEN KOMAROW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. troops storming the ``Witch
House'' quarters of Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega found cigarettes
smoking in ashtrays and believe they missed the Panamanian fugitive
by minutes, military sources say.
   The Witch House, one of Noriega's residences, was filled with
bizarre black magic paraphernalia. Another of the ousted dictator's
quarters was decorated with portraits of Nazi dictator Adolf
Hitler, American servicemen told reporters on Thursday.
   The Witch House is on the sea coast near Panama City, close to
several U.S. military bases.
   Military investigators believe that the house may have been
booby-trapped and would not allow reporters and photographers
inside until it could be made safe, said Gen. John Huston.
   Soldiers on the scene some six hours after the fighting started
said they thought Noriega may have made a narrow escape.
   ``The cigarettes were still smoking in the ashtray and the women
left their purses, which no woman would ever usually do,'' said a
soldier familiar with the house.
   Troops who saw the house spread word that the room in which the
purses were found was apparently devoted to the occult, with signs
of animal entrails and ``vats of blood,'' the soldier said.
   Military officials could not immediately confirm the soldier's
account. He declined to permit use of his name.
   Sgt. 1st Class Joseph Torregrossa said there were some bizarre
trappings in Noriega's private office in the No. 8 building of
Panama's military barracks at Fort Amador.
   ``When we went inside, there were all of these expensive prints,
but he also had a portrait of Adolf Hitler and a lot of expensive
weapons, mostly automatic,'' Torregrossa said.
   ``He had German Lugers, Israeli Uzis (and) all sorts of real
sophisticated stuff.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>