<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0109 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1548EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Jews Bjt   12-21 0502</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Jews, Bjt,0515</SECOND>
<HEAD>Refusenik Cases to be Resolved, American Jewish Leaders Told</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANDREW KATELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Foreign Ministry officials Thursday told American
Jewish leaders at the first national congress of Soviet Jews in
nearly 70 years that most of the estimated 100 remaining refuseniks
will be allowed to emigrate.
   Martin Wenick, executive director of the U.S. organization
National Conference on Soviet Jewry, said the news about the
refuseniks _ those Jews repeatedly refused permission to emigrate _
came from Anatoly Adamishin, a deputy foreign minister.
   Adamishin told Wenick and other representatives of the U.S.
group a ``substantial'' number of the refuseniks who had been
barred from emigrating because of access to state secrets would be
told soon they could leave.
   A Western diplomat who follows the refusenik issue said he had
heard the same report but cautioned that the Soviets had not
officially notified the refuseniks of the news. ``We hope it's true
but let's wait and see,'' said the diplomat.
   Emigration of Soviet Jews has reached record levels under
President Mikhail S. Gorbachev's liberalized policies. An all-time
high of 55,465 Soviet Jews were registered at a transit center in
Vienna between January and November. More Jews left via Romania and
Hungary.
   Refuseniks remain, however, and problems of emigration have been
a central topic at the conference of Soviet Jews that began Monday
and ends Friday.
   A draft resolution to be voted on Friday welcomes progress made
so far in emigration but says the number of refuseniks has remained
stable at about 250 families, 100 of them refused on secrecy
grounds. The resolution also criticizes a draft law on emigration
and travel as overly vague and says it contains ``infringements on
the political, economic and social rights of citizens.''
   The meeting was organized by more than 160 Jewish organizations
in 75 cities and marked the first time since 1920 that Jewish
leaders were allowed to openly congregate to establish a national
organization.
   The country's biggest Jewish group, the Jewish Bund, was founded
by Jewish socialists in 1897 but disbanded in 1920.
   Former refuseniks now living abroad, deputies from the Soviet
parliament, and about 150 Jewish leaders from the West were among
the 650 people attending the conference.
   But Soviet officials denied a visa to Jewish activist Natan
Sharansky, who spent nine years in Soviet labor camps before
emigrating to Israel in 1986.
   The conference also was scheduled to adopt a resolution saying
anti-Semitism is growing in the Soviet Union, and delegates
expressed concern about two protest groups that have been
demonstrating outside the Cinema Center.
   As the conference opened, about 60 jeering members of the
Russian nationalist Pamyat Society jostled delegates as they tried
to enter the hall.
   They waved signs saying, ``Zionists Out of the U.S.S.R.'' and
``Jews, Get Out of the Union.''
   On Thursday, several dozen Palestinian students demonstrators
marched outside. They carried a picture of Palestine Liberation
Organization chief Yasser Arafat and signs that read, ``P.L.O.
Israel No'' and ``Zionism Won't Go Through.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>