<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0171 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1617EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-Soviet 1stLd-Writethru a0753 12-20 0666</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Soviet, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0753,0681</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Union Condemns U.S. Invasion of Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs to UPDATE with TV news coverage. Pickup 8th
pvs, ``Bush said...''</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN IAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Soviet Union on Wednesday branded the U.S.
military attack in Panama ``gunboat diplomacy'' and a violation of
international law. It called for an immediate end to the operation.
   However, a Soviet official played down any impact the U.S.
action might have on improved superpower relations, and the
Kremlin's rhetoric was far milder than its denunciations of the
1983 U.S. invasion of Grenada.
   Foreign Ministry spokesman Vadim P. Perfiliev told a news
briefing the sending of U.S. troops to Panama, ``whatever its
motivation, has provoked a feeling of serious concern in the Soviet
Union.''
   He said the U.S. action violated the U.N. Charter and recognized
rules of international relations and ``should be condemned by the
international community.'' The United States, he said, ``must
immediately stop its armed intervention in Panama.''
   Millions of Soviets saw dramatic footage of the attack on the
nightly TV newscast ``Vremya.''
   Commentator Igor Fyesunenko: ``Again, the world hears the loud
voice of `gunboat diplomacy' and understands perfectly well that
the anger of Washington is caused not by the American concern about
Panama, but by the wish to disrupt the process of transferrence of
the ownership rights of the (Panama) canal ... and to preserve the
complex of American military bases on the territory of this
country,'' he said.
   Tass said none of the arguments put forth by President Bush to
justify the military operation stands up to scrutiny.
   ``This action is an example of notorious `gunboat diplomacy'
which has been used for decades by the United States in an attempt
to turn Latin American and Caribbean nations into its backyard,''
the official news agency said.
   Bush said the troops were sent to protect U.S. lives and
apprehend Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega, who stands accused by
Washington of setting up a succession of puppet regimes while
running a military empire that purportedly trafficked in Colombian
cocaine.
   Perfiliev dismissed the allegations of drug trafficking as a
pretext to intervene in Panamanian affairs.
   The Soviet Union is steadfastly against international drug
trafficking, he said, reflecting the Soviets' greater attention
under leader Mikhail S. Gorbachev to global problems that were once
dismissed as symptoms of capitalist decay.
   ``We have something else here,'' Perfiliev said. ``We are
commenting on the intervention of the United States in a sovereign
state. No matter what the motivation, this is something we are very
concerned about.''
   Despite Soviet concern, Perfiliev indicated the U.S. action
would not reverse the direction of improved Soviet-U.S. relations.
   ``We are now in a situation where an event in the East or in the
West is not perceived, is not evaluated, in terms of confrontation
between East and West,'' the Soviet spokesman said.
   But, he said, ``I think both the Soviet Union and the United
States would stand to gain if a situation could be achieved where
there is not interference in the affairs of others.''
   Tass, however, said sending U.S. troops to Panama did not
involve just another regional conflict. ``It is a dangerous
encroachment on the unsteady equilibrium that has been achieved in
the world arena,'' it said.
   The United States, it said, ``has challenged the entire
international community and is acting against universal human
interests.''
   Official Soviet reaction to the U.S. actions in Panama was
markedly more restrained than when former President Ronald Reagan
ordered the invasion of Grenada in 1983.
   At that time, the government newspaper Izvestia accused the
United States of carrying out ``a stinking show.'' It also said
Reagan was ``obsessed with the ideas of world domination.''
   Perfiliev said all countries would benefit from policies of
non-interference, which the Soviet leadership under Gorbachev has
repeatedly professed to be its policy.
   ``All states would stand to gain when all peoples of all
countries decide their own destinies,'' Perfiliev said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>