<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0155EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     12-20 0373</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0388</SECOND>
<HEAD>On The Light Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It was a big bull, but it didn't sit well
outside the New York Stock Exchange.
   The 3-ton bronze bull sculpture, which turned up uninvited
Friday outside the exchange, is being moved to a park in the Wall
Street area, said city Parks Department spokesman Skip Garrett.
   The city yanked the sculpture from its spot outside the market
last week, but it has changed its mind. Parks Commissioner Henry
Stern was scheduled to dedicate it today.
   ``It's our custom to allow sculptors to display their works in
city parks. Henry's found the bull a temporary home,'' Garrett said
Tuesday.
   The sculptor, Arturo DiModica, was ecstatic about the city's
reversal.
   ``I feel fantastic,'' said DiModica, who spent two years and
$300,000 on his work, ``The Charging Bull.''
   DiModica brought the bull to the stock exchange under cover of
darkness Thursday, but within 24 hours the unlicensed art work was
hauled off. Garrett said the bull's home will not be permanent,
although Garrett didn't have a time frame for its departure.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>TALLAHASSEE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A private yacht navigator has won
enough money to buy a yacht of his own after claiming a $13.6
million Lotto prize.
   Hagne Murray of Fort Lauderdale and his wife, Theresa, were
celebrating their wedding anniversary Saturday night and didn't
even look at their tickets until late Sunday after hearing the
winning ticket had been sold in Fort Lauderdale.
   Mrs. Murray, 32, was already in bed when her husband told her
about the winning tickets. ``I thought he was kidding,'' she said.
   Murray, 39, who bought 20 tickets for the drawing, had played
the same numbers for weeks.
   On Dec. 10, he matched four numbers on one pick, winning $127.
   ``When I matched four numbers, I felt like the marlin was
tugging a little bit on my line,'' Murray said Tuesday. ``So I
played those numbers again and landed the big one.''
   By matching the winning numbers, 01-06-22-23-34-47, the Murrays
will receive $684,000 before taxes annually for the next 20 years.
The Murrays have four children, ages 12 to 19. They have no plans
for the money yet, but will go ahead with a planned vacation this
week.
</TEXT>

</DOC>