<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1420EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Noriega'sHouse     12-24 0507</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Noriega's House,0522</SECOND>
<HEAD>Noriega's Home, An Ordinary Upper-Middle Class House</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DORALISA PILARTE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega allegedly
earned millions helping Colombia's cocaine lords launder drug
profits, but if that's true he didn't put too much of it into his
house.
   Compared to the extravagant mansions customary among Latin
American dictators, the Noriega house is modest _ a two-story
affair in a neat, upper middle-class neighborhood. Its walls are
painted white and topped by a red tile roof, classic tropical
architecture.
   ``He would only say `Hello,' very respectfully,'' said German
Sanchez, 53, who was the military leader's next-door neighbor 16
years but was never formally introduced to him.
   ``You may think what you like of Noriega, but we can't say he
was anything but respectful toward his neighbors,'' he said.
   Sanchez's house is between Noriega's and a smaller house on a
corner that Noriega also owned. ``The servants and guests stayed
there,'' Sanchez said.
   Reporters allowed into the house Saturday did not find any
evidence of voodoo or black magic, which Noriega was rumored to
have practiced.
   But the general apparently admired Napoleon Bonaparte and hung
two pictures of the French emperor in his second-story study.
   The house wraps around three sides of a 45-square-foot courtyard
where a stone fountain was bubbling water.
   A small room had been converted into a chapel. A six-foot
crucifix hung on a wall behind an altar. An oil painting of St.
George slaying the dragon hung on another wall.
   Noriega seemed to be in the Christmas spirit. An eight-foot
Christmas tree trimmed with stuffed dolls and other adornments
stood in a back terrace, next to a manger.
   About two dozen cardboard boxes and black plastic garbage bags
were stuffed with toys, games and gifts for children.
   U.S. troops stormed the Noriega family home Wednesday, using
stun grenades that shattered glass jalousies and hand-painted vases
and flowerpots.
   All the windows in Noriega's bedroom were blown away, as was
most of the ceiling over his king-size bed.
   One of two walk-in closets held a combination safe and a locked
metal strongbox. The safe was open and empty, with two plastic bags
of dehumidifying crystals inside. A bullet destroyed the keyhole of
the metal cabinet.
   A U.S. soldier assigned to guard the house picked up a wooden
plaque with ``Battalion 2000'' painted on it. That is the elite
unit Noriega named in honor of the year Panama is to take over the
Panama Canal.
   It is not clear how much Noriega used the house recently. He was
reportedly sleeping in different locations every night, fearing
coup attempts. Little is known of his personal life.
   Sanchez, a lawyer and member of the board of directors of the
Panamanian Chamber of Commerce, said he had just arrived home from
a cocktail party early Wednesday when the U.S. attack began.
   ``About five minutes before that, two small cars with armed men
inside rode up to the house and then everybody left right away,''
Sanchez said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>