<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0653EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-MailBombs     12-30 0621</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mail Bombs,0641</SECOND>
<HEAD>Letter Claiming Mail-Bomb Responsibility Appears Authentic, FBI Says</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Diader Rosario is cq in 12th graf.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SONYA ROSS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The FBI believes a letter claiming responsibility
for bombings that killed a federal judge and a lawyer is authentic,
but agents still know nothing about the organization that sent it.
   The letter was sent to Atlanta television station WAGA and
disclosed Thursday.
   ``We believe the letter received by WAGA is authentic because it
contained information which has not been made known to the public
and which is known only to someone closely associated with the
construction and mailing of the bombs and to law enforcement,''
said William L. Hinshaw, special agent in charge of the FBI
investigation.
   The Atlanta Journal and Constitution, quoting unidentified
sources, reported Friday that the letter contained an identifying
code identical to that in follow-up letters sent to the bomb
targets. The newspaper didn't elaborate.
   NAACP Southeastern regional director Earl Shinhoster said a
letter sent to his office after a tear-gas bombing, postmarked Aug.
21, also contained that numerical code. He said other letters
associated with the bombings also have that code.
   ``They're all the same,'' he said. ``If you see one, you can
rest assured that if there's another one, it also has a code.''
   The letter to WAGA referred to the case of Julie Love, a white
Atlanta woman who was abducted in July 1988 and whose body was
found last summer. Two black men were arrested; one has pleaded
guilty to murder and other charges, and the other is awaiting trial.
   The letter said U.S. Circuit Judge Robert S. Vance and Savannah
lawyer Robert Robinson were ``assassinated'' in reprisal for Ms.
Love's death. It said ``two more prominent members of the NAACP''
also would be killed in reprisal.
   Vance was killed at his Alabama home on Dec. 16; Robinson was
killed in Savannah two days later.
   The letter said that any time a black man rapes a white woman in
Alabama, Florida or Georgia _ the states served by the 11th U.S.
Circuit Court of Appeals, on which Vance sat _ a federal judge, an
attorney and an officer of the National Association for the
Advancement of Colored Persons would be killed.
   The FBI in Atlanta asked anyone with information on the group,
calling itself Americans for a Competent Federal Judicial System,
to call a hotline established for tips in the case.
   Agency spokesman Diader Rosario said Friday that some calls had
been received since news of the group's letter broke Thursday. The
information received so far, however, was ``nothing exciting,''
Rosario said. He refused to provide details.
   ``Certainly it (the group) is something brand new for us, and
another link in the chain,'' Rosario said.
   The letter also condemned the 11th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals
for ``granting the blacks' demand for white teachers for their
children,'' leading FBI agents to re-interview the lead plaintiff
in a 21-year-old school-desegregation case.
   ``They showed me some of the letters that had been written, and
they asked me for names of people that I know who would send
letters like that,'' said the plaintiff, Roger Mills, who also is a
member of the DeKalb NAACP's executive committee.
   Mills said he would review his stockpile of hate mail to see
whether any of it is similar to the letter sent to WAGA.
   Benjamin Hooks, the NAACP's executive director, said the
threatening letter is intended to intimidate the group, ``to strike
fear in our hearts.''
   ``It will not succeed. We intend to go about our business, but
we will most certainly be taking precautions,'' Hooks said from the
NAACP national headquarters in Baltimore.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Eds: Atlanta hotline is 404-361-1092.
</TEXT>

</DOC>