<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0098 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1346EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Sheriff-RacialSlur 1stLd-Writethru a0544 12-29 0449</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Sheriff-Racial Slur, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0544,0455</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sheriff Urged to Apologize or Resign</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 1st graf to clarify by adding ``chief.'' SUBS 7th graf
to add that reported comment was in an interview. Note language in 7th
graf.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>COLUMBIA, S.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sheriff Allen Sloan should either
apologize for a racial slur a newspaper said he made and hire a
black chief deputy, or resign, business and civic leaders say.
   The Richland County sheriff has denied making the remark
attributed to him by The State newspaper on Dec. 22 and said
Thursday he would take neither action recommended by the Greater
Columbia Community Relations Council.
   The council prefers that Sloan stay in office, said its
chairman, Paul Beazley.
   Sloan said he was shown the council's statement shortly before
its release and was appalled to hear that its conclusions and
recommendations were unanimous and backed by the executive
committee of the Greater Columbia Chamber of Commerce.
   ``As for the apology, I have already made an apology numerous
times through the media and would like to take this opportunity as
well to say that anything that was said to cause embarrassment to
the black community or the white community, that I am truly sorry
and apologize for it,'' Sloan said.
   ``I am everybody's sheriff,'' he said. ``I was elected by the
whites and the blacks.''
   The State reported that when asked in an interview in his office
how safety could be improved at Columbia Mall, where four shootings
have occurred in the past six months, Sloan replied: ``Keep the
niggers out.''
   Sloan has maintained he did not make the racial slur and said no
one on the council consulted him before concluding that he had.
   The Community Relations Council said Thursday that if Sloan
stays in office he should hire a black second-in-command, partly to
advise him on race relations.
   The sheriff said he would not do that.
   ``There is no way that I'm going to let any group of citizens
tell me how to hire or promote in this office, especially in
stepping over the bounds in thinking it had to be someone black,''
Sloan said. ``I am not going to fire my chief deputy simply to hire
someone because of a color. That's racial discrimination in its
purest form right there.''
   The Community Relations Council wichland County Council.
   Sloan, elected in 1988 to a four-year term, is the chief law
enforcement officer in Richland County. The county, where the
capital city of Columbia is located, is the third-most populous
county in the state with 285,000 residents.
</TEXT>

</DOC>