<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0245 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0557EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DigestBriefs     12-20 0530</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Digest Briefs,0549</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III says he
regrets possibly misleading the American public about a secret trip
to China taken by two high-level Bush administration officials.
   Baker said through a spokeswoman Tuesday night ``he felt
obligated to protect the secrecy of a mission the president wished
to have classified.''
   Speaking for Baker, spokeswoman Margaret D. Tutwiler added: ``He
regrets that he may have misled some...''
   It was the first acknowledgement of error since the White House
announced on Dec. 9 that national security adviser Brent Scowcroft
and Deputy Secretary of State Lawrence Eagleburger were visiting
Beijing. Their trip was roundly condemned in Congress as a friendly
gesture to China and a cancellation of the ban President Bush
imposed on high-level exchanges after pro-democracy students were
massacred in early June in Tiananmen Square.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Eds: Embargoed for release noon EST; time set by source</NOTE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Requests for help from the homeless and hungry
increased during the past year _ particularly among families with
children _ and many cities were unable to meet the need, according
to a survey released today.
   Many cities were forced to turn away families and others needing
shelter and food, the U.S. Conference of Mayors said.
   Increases in hunger, homelessness and poverty are ``one of the
most dramatic changes that swept across our country'' in the 1980s,
said Boston Mayor Ray Flynn, chairman of the conference's task
force on hunger and homelessness.
   Requests for emergency shelter in 1989 increased by 25 percent
in the cities surveyed, said the mayors' annual report on hunger
and homelessness in urban America. Requests for emergency food
increased by 19 percent.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End embargoed material</NOTE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Social Security Commissioner Gwendolyn King is
supporting a plan under which the government early next year would
mail monthly refunds to millions of elderly people overcharged for
Medicare premiums.
   If the plan goes through, Social Security beneficiaries who
unavoidably will be overcharged by about $5.30 a month for their
Medicare coverage early in 1990 will be simultaneously issued
monthly refund checks.
   The overcharges are the result of Congress' late action in
repealing Medicare's catastrophic health-care program. Social
Security contends its computers can't be adjusted by January to
halt withholding of the extra Medicare premium for catastrophic
coverage.
   As a result, nearly 27 million Social Security beneficiaries who
have Medicare premiums deducted directly from their benefit checks
are expected to be overcharged from January through May.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Many long distance telephone rates to points
in the United States and abroad will be going down after the first
of the year, the three major long distance companies say.
   American Telephone and Telegraph Co. filed reductions with the
Federal Communications Commission Tuesday. MCI Communications Corp.
and U.S. Sprint said they will take action to remain competitive.
   AT&amp;T says it has about 70 percent of the long distance market,
as measured by interstate and intrastate revenues. MCI is No. 2
with more than 10 percent. U.S. Sprint claims 7 to 8 percent.
   The AT&amp;T reductions will take effect Jan. 1, barring an unusual
action by the FCC to block them.
</TEXT>

</DOC>