<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0157 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1654EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-NoriegaEscape 2ndLd-Writethru a07J3-e 12-22 0721</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Noriega Escape, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0735,680</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Troops Come Upon a Bizarre Scene</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDITOR'S NOTE: The following is based on a pool dispatch.    </HEAD>
<HEAD>EDs: CORRECTS 1st graf to make witches Brazilian instead of Panamanian;
subs 3rd graf, Snell said to add detail; inserts 6th graf, bgng: Other</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEVEN KOMAROW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. soldiers who stormed one of Gen.
Manuel Antonio Noriega's guest houses here narrowly missed
capturing four Brazilian voodoo witches who performed rituals for
his protection, officials said Friday.
   The so-called ``witch house,'' a fortified structure specially
built for Noriega, contained an estimated 50 pounds of cocaine, a
bucket of blood, voodoo artifacts and a brewery for making
concoctions and potions, Col. Mike Snell, the officer in charge of
the area, said.
   Snell said it was not known whether the blood was human or
animal or for what the potions were used. Officers said some of the
cocaine had been wrapped in a banana leaf and placed in the freezer.
   Gen. Maxwell Thurmand, commander of the Panama-based Southern
Command, said at a press briefing that Noriega's ``voodoo
practitioners ... practiced rituals for Noriega's protection.''
   Lt. Curtis Vinyard said the house had apparently been occupied
until shortly before it was stormed by U.S. troops.
   Other military officers said the house was where Noriega ``kept
his Brazilian withces.''
   ``There was still a candle burning,'' he said.
   Some of the soldiers who stormed the house said there were
smoldering cigarettes in ashtrays and women had left their purses,
and they believed they might have come close to capturing Noriega
himself.
   In any event, Noriega was still at large.
   The house, on the seacoast near here and close to several U.S.
military bases, was stormed by U.S. soldiers on Tuesday, about six
hours after the U.S. invasion began.
   An American soldier who would not give his name but was familiar
with the incident said troops who saw the house spread the word
that one room was apparently devoted to the occult, with blood and
entrails.
   Reporters were also shown odd trappings in two offices used by
Noriega. His office in Panama's military barracks at Fort Amador
had two display cases full of plastic frogs, framed pictures of
Adolf Hitler, Mother Theresa and Moammar Ghadafi, and dozens of
electronic toys such as a video wristwatch. U.S. officials showed
reporters Christmas trees, more electronics and more frogs at his
former headquarters office downtown.
   Snell said collections of pornography wre found in both offices
and the Fort Amador house was stocked with Noriega's private brands
of cigars and champagne.
   U.S. intelligence officials scoured the offices in the hope of
finding records would help trace Noriega's assets.
   Sgt. 1st Class Joseph Torregrossa said the Fort Amador office
also contained expensive prints and ``a lot of expensive weapons,
mostly automatic. He had German Lugers, Israeli Uzis, all sorts of
real sophisticated stuff.''
   Thurmand told reporters, ``He was clearly dedicated to
outfitting a substantial force, outfitting dignity battalions,
which in the long run would have given us a tremendous challenge in
this area.''
   Travel restrictions, including a nighttime curfew, were still in
effect Friday, and new fighting was reported with men loyal to
Noriega attacking the headquarters of the U.S. Southern Command.
   A two-hour tour through a bombed-out shopping district that once
was a Noriega stronghold showed scenes of near chaos as thousands
of looters seized refrigerators, microwaves, automobile tires,
gasoline and other goods.
   They cheerfully stopped, however, to shout ``Viva Bush, Viva
Bush'' or ``Bush, Bush, Bush'' as they waved to soldiers and
journalists. One held up a knife sharpener and joked, ``It's a
present from Bush.''
   Noriega's nine-building headquarters was a smouldering hulk, its
windows blown out by tank and artillery fire. It was closely
guarded by dozens of U.S. troops.
   Less than a mile away, the body of a man, face down and
shirtless, lay trapped in the crushed wreckage of a sedan. A U.S.
infantry sergeant said an armored personnel carrier rolled over the
car after the driver was seen passing out AK-47 rifles.
   An old section of the city around Noriega headquarters contained
many of Panama City's poor and homeless, but they had largely
abandoned it, taking refuge in quarters provided by U.S. military
at the American-owned Balboa High School in the suburbs, U.S.
officials said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>