<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0094 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1439EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Poland     12-21 0746</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland,0766</SECOND>
<HEAD>Communists Say Party Losing Touch With Workers</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DRUSILLA MENAKER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Poland's Communist Party is losing touch
with a critical constituency: the workers, its leaders said
Thursday.
   So few actual workers were elected as delegates to the party's
crucial national congress set for next month that the leadership
may issue special invitations, said Janusz Bisztyga, the central
committee spokesman.
   ``The share of workers is disquietingly low,'' Bisztyga said.
``We have called on all party groups to work out a different
solution.''
   The percentage of workers has not been calculated while delegate
elections continue, but the spokesman offered two examples of the
problem: the Baltic province of Slupsk, with only one worker and
two farmers among the 22 delegates, and the central area of Kielce,
with only four blue-collar workers among the 44 delegates.
   The situation is dire for the party, created for the
proletariat, said Wieslaw Veitz, a sociologist and party member,
during a news conference called to discuss the congress, which
meets Jan. 27.
   ``It is not that the party leadership is losing touch with the
base. In fact there is no contact with the base, because if we had
contact, the situation would not be as it is now,'' he said.
   The Communists' iron grip on Poland's government and economy
broke in the last year. First, they turned to the independent
Solidarity movement they had sought to crush, seeking help with the
economic crisis and social unrest. Then they suffered a stinging
popular rejection during unprecedented democratic parliament
elections, leading to the East bloc's first non-Communist prime
minister and a Solidarity-led cabinet.
   Now huge government budget subsidies and tax exemptions that
funded Communist Party activites are ceasing Jan. 1, while economic
reform is radically reducing the role of the party in state-run
industries. And within four years, the party will have to face
fully free elections.
   The party congress, the 11th since the Communists consolidated
power in postwar Poland, may be its last in its current form.
Struggling to retain a place in the nation's political future, the
party is expected to adopt a new name and a program that will cast
it as broadly leftist supporting parliamentary democracy.
   ``Today the party's future is being discussed by a narrow group
of intelligentsia, and lacks participation from the workers,'' said
Zbigniew Sobotka, an alternate Politburo member from the Warsaw
steel works.
   ``If we are to discuss the future of the party, we should give
the floor to the people who have been most identified with the
party so far,'' he said.
   ``We do not want a situation where after the congress there is
no base of membership to support the reformed party.''
   A Workers Congress Forum was created at factories in Warsaw to
generate interest in party issues among the workers who Sobotka
described as frustrated by slow party reform and the leadership.
   In preparation for the congress, new rules were established for
more democratic election of the 1,500 delegates. Previously,
participants were approved by party leaders.
   But Sobotka said that in the elections, ``members of the
intelligentsia have an advantage. ... They are more eloquent than
the workers.''
   Among the alternatives being considered to bolster worker
representation at the congress are inviting delegations from
factories to speak to the session, allowing factories to elect the
guests and making them full delegates to the congress of any new
party that is formed, Sobotka said.
   Also, said Zenon Szoda, a Polish Academy of Science professor,
``We do not confine ourselves to the working class, we mean people
who are gainfully employed. We do not reject people who have
production means _ private farmers, private entrepreneurs.''
   The party has a membership of just under 2.1 million in a nation
of 39 million, down 1 million in the last decade and 35,000 in the
first half of 1989, according to an August report.
   About 37.5 percent of the members are workers, compared with
52.1 percent who are members of the intelligentsia: managers,
teachers and others whose jobs require higher education. The rest
are in agriculture.
   The Central Committee reported in October that 72 percent of
members favored changing the name, charter and program of the party
that was formed in 1948. The report said there were 70 proposals
for a new name.
   Polish Communists have been studying their Hungarian
counterparts, who voted Oct. 7 to scrap the old party and replace
it with a socialist one.
</TEXT>

</DOC>