<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0172 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 2037EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WKD--Brock Adv05-07   12-26 0786</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--Brock, Adv 05-07,0814</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv05-07</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Weekend Editions, Jan. 5-7, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WEEKEND ENTERTAINMENT AND ARTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Nashville Sound: Jeff Brock's Music Is All Over Television</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOE EDWARDS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jeff Brock has never recorded a hit
song, but people who watch TV frequently hear his music.
   The 39-year-old Brock is president of a ``music house,'' a
company that provides tunes for TV commercials. Brock Music, his
company, has won or shared five Clios or ADDYs, national awards for
excellence in advertising.
   Some of his best-known music accompanied these spots:
   _ Actor Richard Farnsworth posing in a desert eating chips with
the tag line, ``the flavor's a legend.''
   _ Fast-food hamburger containers open their lids and talk to
each other.
   _ A bleach with the hook line, ``Don't just get 'em clean, get
'em vivid.''
   Brock provides music to advertising agencies that have contracts
with major corporations. He comes up with original music or
arranges a well-known song that already has been chosen for an ad.
   Brock, who supervises a staff of four plus several free-lance
music writers and arrangers, says music is important to the overall
content.
   ``I think music plays an immense role in the memorability of a
spot. When you have 5-year-old kids running around singing jingles
all day, you know it has a lot of impact on people's minds,'' he
said.
   He estimates that 70 percent of his work is ``post scores'' _
seeing the ad without music and writing a tune to emphasize what's
happening visually.
   ``The music is supposed to be poignant and jump out,'' Brock
said.
   The guidelines vary.
   ``They will say they want something appealing to kids age 12 to
young adults age 25. In that age group, you go for something hard
hitting, something a little more rock 'n' roll.
   ``Sometimes they say they want music like ... and they name the
artist. I come up with something similar to that artist or that
style,'' he said.
   ``Sometimes we go out on a limb and say we don't think it will
work and here's what we suggest.
   ``And in other cases, they say they have no earthly idea what
they want. But they know it when they hear it. Those are the
toughies. You may come up with something you think is incredibly
good, but the client doesn't.''
   For a recent spot about food to be taken to work, he was
instructed to come up with music that sounded ``classical, English,
very proper.''
   ``When I wrote those scores, I wrote from an acoustical
standpoint with strings and woodwinds and light, fun,
British-sounding music. It came out beautifully and they are airing
nationally.''
   He writes some lyrics, but most of the time they are written by
the ad agency. ``We sort of pick up the ball and run with it
wherever they decide to pass it off to us,'' Brock said.
   He always knows the client, but sometimes it is top secret.
   ``We're not supposed to let out what we're doing or the
campaign, and this can be painful because you've just done a
wonderful session for someone and they are not going to break the
campaign for three months and you can't even play it for anybody.''
   In most cases, the spots are 30 seconds long, some only 15
seconds.
   ``You don't get a chance to say much in 15 seconds,'' he said.
   The companies and products he has worked with include General
Mills, Century 21, K mart, the Walt Disney Co., CBS News, Folgers,
McDonald's, Long John Silver's and Ralston Purina.
   Brock Music is one of about 15 Nashville companies doing music
for jingles.
   ``Our value is our versatility,'' Brock said. ``We do all
musical styles. We do a lot of different things well.''
   Brock was raised in Anderson, Ind., and worked as a jingle
singer in Dallas before he began writing jingles in 1975. He moved
to Nashville the next year. Ten years ago he wrote the music for
political advertising, including the music for Dan Quayle's first
campaign for the U.S. Senate in Indiana.
   ``We helped to elect a lot of candidates,'' said Brock, who also
was a judge in the 1989 Miss America Pageant.
   He turned to jingle writing because he didn't want to continue
doing political ads.
   His office complex has a small studio in the rear where most of
the ad music is created. He plays keyboards himself as needed.
   ``I think when you have some leeway, and the agency allows you
to be creative and do the job you feel is needed for that project,
and it comes out wonderful, it's very satisfying.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Weekend Editions, Jan. 5-7</NOTE>

</DOC>