<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0125 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1526EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CounselorArrested     12-29 0382</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Counselor Arrested,0396</SECOND>
<HEAD>School Drug Counselor Arrested on Drug Charges</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FORT WORTH, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police arrested a school drug counselor
found with apparent cocaine residue, as well as glass pipes and
other items considered drug paraphernalia, in his pickup truck, a
police spokesman said.
   Clyde Tillman, 56, was arrested Wednesday on suspicion of
possession of narcotics paraphernalia, said Dee Anderson of the
Arlington police.
   Tillman, a former high school football coach and longtime
employee of the Fort Worth school district, was released Thursday
from the Arlington City Jail on a personal recognizance bond, a
jail spokeswoman said.
   Police will seek a felony charge of possession of a controlled
substance if tests show the residue is cocaine and is a usable
amount under state law, Anderson said.
   Phone calls Friday to Tillman's residence were not answered.
   ``I am kind of in shock here,'' his supervisor, Billy Whitworth,
said after learning Thursday about Tillman's arrest. ``He has been
a good employee.''
   Tillman works in the district headquarters, dealing with
students who are chronically absent and break drug rules, Whitworth
said.
   ``If the student has broken the drug policy, they are referred
to him and he refers them to a drug counselor,'' Whitworth said.
``He talks to them first about their problem.''
   Tillman was arrested in Arlington, which is just east of Fort
Worth, after a police officer spotted his pickup under a tree by
Lake Arlington in an area known as a dumping ground for stolen
cars, Anderson said. The officer noticed Tillman shuffling things
around on the pickup's floor.
   Tillman told the officer he had come to the lake to ``drink a
beer and enjoy the scenery,'' Anderson said.
   The officer noticed a mirror and razor blade on the seat,
Anderson said. The officer also found a cloth bag under the seat
that contained glass pipes commonly used to smoke crack cocaine.
   A propane torch, which cocaine smokers sometimes use to heat
hardened cocaine, was found on the floor along with an empty
miniature plastic bag, police said.
   Schools Superintendent Don Roberts said Tillman probably will be
suspended with pay until the case is decided.
   ``There are about 7,800 employees in this district and they are
subject to a lot of things that society in general is exposed to,''
Roberts said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>