<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0203 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0831EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-FrostFighter     12-19 0496</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Frost Fighter,0513</SECOND>
<HEAD>Inventor of Engine Heater Appreciated in Winter Months</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto GRF1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JEFF MEYER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FARGO, N.D. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The electric cords that dangle from the
fronts of cars on the northern Plains are an oddity to strangers
but a lifeline to residents.
   The cords run to engine heaters that help cars start on brutally
cold mornings. Folks on the Plains have been known to call the
device's inventor, Andrew Freeman, a saint.
   ``I had a guy come up to me in a store the other day and thank
me for inventing the heater,'' the 80-year-old Freeman said Monday.
``He said he never would have gotten his car started that day
without it. I get a kick out of things like that.''
   Strangers to the region point to the heater cords showing
through the grillwork and ask whether they belong to electric cars.
   But Mark Ewens, a National Weather Service forecaster in Fargo,
said the heaters have become necessary equipment in North Dakota
and other Midwestern states.
   ``We all have them, we all use them,'' Ewens said. ``When the
air temperature is 33 degrees below zero when you get off work at 7
a.m., there's no way you'd get the car started if you didn't have
it plugged in.''
   Freeman, a North Dakota native who lives in Grand Forks, created
his first heater out of necessity. He got a patent on the device in
1947.
   Tired of being unable to start his car in the winter, he devised
a heater that consisted of a brass cylinder about the size of a
finger. It contained a heating element attached to the end of a
bolt.
   The bolt replaced one of the headbolts in the engine and the
cylinder, with the heating element extended into the engine water
jacket. A cord attached to the top of the bolt plugged into an
electrical outlet.
   As cars changed, Freeman invented two other heaters _ a frost
plug heater that attached to the side of the engine and an external
tank heater.
   Drivers who want to make certain their cars start simply can go
to a service station and have an engine heater installed for
roughly $50. Its cord is plugged into an outlet at night, and the
car is warm and ready to go in the morning.
   Freeman's invention should get plenty of use in the coming days.
The temperature is not expected to climb above zero for the rest of
the week.
   Ewens said December's cold weather is not that unusual.
   ``I think people have really poor meterological memories,'' he
said Monday. ``We've just had a few years of really mild winters.
Now we're back to normal.''
   And despite the cold, Freeman gets a warm twinge of pride when
he sees all those cars with heater cords.
   ``You walk around town and you see a lot of cars with plugs
hanging out of them, and you realize you're the guy who got that
started.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>