<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0133 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 2336EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Judge-Explosion 1stLd-Writethru a0630 12-23 0844</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Judge-Explosion, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0630,0865</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bomb Was Sent Through Mail, Postal Inspectors Confirm</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 2 grafs to UPDATE with postal inspectors confirming
bomb was sent through mail; picks up 2nd graf, `Washington County ...'
SUBS 13th graf, `Investigators interviewed ...,' with 4 grafs to UPDATE
with inspection service spokesman comment; picks up 14th graf, `The carrier
...'; DELETES outdated grafs 17-20, ```We're relatively ... ' picks up
21st graf, `Doctors said ...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEB RIECHMANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HAGERSTOWN, Md. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police on Saturday interviewed neighbors
of a county judge and a letter carrier who delivered a package to
his apartment, but found no leads into the bomb attack that wounded
the judge, authorities said.
   Postal inspectors confirmed Saturday night that the pipe bomb
was delivered through the mail.
   Washington County Circuit Judge John P. Corderman's condition
was upgraded to good at Washington County Hospital, one day after a
pipe bomb sent shrapnel into his hand and groin and damaged his
eardrums.
   Dr. Charles Chaney said the judge's ears were still ringing from
the blast, but his hearing had improved. Corderman now suffers a 25
percent hearing loss in both ears, down from a loss of as much as
75 percent initially, Chaney said.
   ``His sense of humor remains intact,'' the physician said. ``
When told of the holes in both eardrums, he quipped, `There goes
scuba diving.'''
   Postal inspectors, agents of the FBI and the federal Bureau of
Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms, and Hagerstown police investigating
the bombing believe it wasn't related to four parcel bombs
delivered in the Southeast in the past week, Police Lt. Robert
Frick said.
   Two of those bombs exploded, killing a federal judge in a
Birmingham, Ala., suburb Dec. 16 and an alderman who was also a
civil rights attorney in Savannah on Monday.
   Bombs were found and defused last week at the Jacksonville,
Fla., chapter of the National Association for the Advancement of
Colored People and the federal courthouse in Atlanta. Investigators
are focusing on a possible racial motivation in those cases.
   Frick said investigators didn't have a lead theory in the
Hagerstown bombing. ``It's so early in the investigation,'' he
said. ``We haven't fixed our investigation on a particular track.
   ``From what I know, (Corderman) doesn't have any idea who may
have wanted to do this to him,'' he said.
   Frick said investigators were reviewing Corderman's cases.
   Authorities said they saw no link with the Southeast bombings,
but said the attack could have been a copycat crime.
   Authorities believe a second unexploded bomb found in the
apartment was delivered in the same package as the pipe bomb. That
bomb was disarmed, and Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms officers took
it and other evidence to the agency's laboratory in Rockville.
   The U.S. Postal Inspection Service confirmed that the pipe bomb,
packaged in a Christmas food gift box, was sent through the mail
and not through some other delivery service, said spokesman Paul
Griffo in Washington.
   ``It basically changes the picture of the investigation,''
Griffo said. ``Now the Postal Inspection Service will be the lead
agency in the investigation because we've determined that the bomb
arrived through the mail and not through a delivery person.''
   The inspection service stopped short, however, of naming letter
carrier Robert L. Miller Sr., the only carrier on Corderman's
route, as the person who delivered the bomb.
   Earlier Saturday, investigators interviewed Miller, who said he
delivered a flat, rectangular box to Corderman's downtown apartment
about 12:45 p.m. Friday, nearly two hours before the 2:30 p.m.
explosion. Miller said he left the box leaning against the door
when no one answered.
   The carrier said he believed the box contained perishable food
because the cardboard had a waxy, oily texture.
   ``They showed me a picture of a blown-up Hickory Farms box with
his name on it, but I don't know if I delivered a Hickory Farms box
or not. It just looked like a normal package that came from a
business,'' said Miller, 42.
   ``They keep asking me about postage and return addresses. I
don't know. I think there was a return address, but I'm not sure,''
he said.
   Doctors said the judge, who had been in stable condition after
surgery Friday to remove shrapnel, could be released from the
hospital as early as Christmas Day.
   Chaney said doctors removed pieces of lead-colored pipe from
Corderman's groin and right hand and reconstructed the top half of
the middle finger on the judge's right hand, which had lost its tip.
   Several judges and other officials visited Corderman along with
members of his family, who have declined to comment. Corderman also
refused interviews.
   ``He's in very good spirits ,'' County Circuit Judge Daniel
Moylan said. ``He's very grateful that he's alive.''
   Corderman, who had been a judge for 12 years, was known as one
of the toughest judges in the county. He was known for handing down
harsh sentences, especially in drug-related cases. He also has been
an outspoken advocate of gun control and has spoken out on
controversial issues such as club gambling.
</TEXT>

</DOC>