<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0206 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1719EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-WallStreet 1stLd-Writethru   12-28 0482</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Wall Street, 1st Ld-Writethru,0502</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eds: Updates with closing prices throughout.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHET CURRIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Stock prices inched ahead Thursday, continuing
their tentative yearend rally in the next-to-last session of 1989.
   Much of the activity appeared to be devoted to final maneuvering
by investors for tax and yearend portfolio reporting purposes.
   The Dow Jones average of 30 industrials rose 7.90 to 2,732.30,
bringing its gain over the past two trading days to 23.04 points.
   Advancing issues outnumbered declines by about 5 to 4 in
nationwide trading of New York Stock Exchange-listed stocks, with
842 up, 673 down and 475 unchanged.
   Volume on the floor of the Big Board came to 128.03 million
shares, down from 133.73 million in the previous session.
Nationwide, consolidated volume in NYSE-listed issues, including
trades in those stocks on regional exchanges and in the
over-the-counter market, totaled 164.12 million shares.
   Analysts said money managers at many investing institutions had
pretty well closed their books on 1989, and thus were making few
waves in the marketplace.
   The government is due to report Friday on the index of leading
economic indicators for November.
   Advance estimates call for a flat to slightly higher showing by
the index, which would presumably do little to resolve the
questions in investors' minds about the economic outlook for the
first half of 1990.
   With only Friday's trading left in 1989, the Dow Jones
industrial average sports a gain of 563.73 points, or 25.99
percent, since the end of last year.
   Germany Fund ranked among Thursday's volume leaders, up 1} at
19. The stock of the closed-end investment company has soared in
recent days on expectations of big benefits to West German business
from the opening up of Eastern Europe.
   Among other overseas funds, Austria Fund gained 2{ to 19{; Spain
Fund 3 to 31{, and Templeton Emerging Markets Fund 1 to 14}.
   Campbell Soup gained 4] to 57] on word that some members of the
company's founding Dorrance family want to find a buyer for their
stock.
   Actively traded blue chips included American Telephone &amp;
Telegraph, up 1 at 45|; Philip Morris, up ~ at 41[; Exxon, down ]
at 50[, and International Business Machines, down | at 94[.
   Rexene Corp. sustained the biggest percentage decline among NYSE
issues, down ~ at 3] on top of a 1~-point loss Wednesday, when the
company suspended its dividend.
   As measured by Wilshire Associates' index of more than 5,000
actively traded stocks, the market increased $14.87 billion, or
0.44 percent, in value.
   The NYSE's composite index of all its listed common stocks
gained .90 to 193.59.
   Standard &amp; Poor's industrial index rose 2.34 to 400.50, and
S&amp;P's 500-stock composite index was up 1.86 at 350.67.
   The NASDAQ composite index for the over-the-counter market added
1.17 to 449.98. At the American Stock Exchange, the market value
index closed at 373.90, up .94.
</TEXT>

</DOC>