<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1120EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Panama 3rdLd-Writethru a0538 12-19 0782</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0538,0802</SECOND>
<HEAD>US, Panama Trade Accusations on Shootings</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS lead to CORRECT Army to Marine officer; SUBS 9th graf,
`Tensions already ...' to UPDATE with ID of dead American officer; SUBS
14th graf, `Panama says ...' with ID.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Panama today accused the United
States of ``arrogance'' in two recent confrontations that left an
American Marine officer dead and a Panamanian policeman wounded.
   The latest incident occurred Monday, when a U.S. Army lieutenant
shot and wounded a Panamanian police officer. At the time, U.S.
forces were on high alert following a Saturday shooting, with
President Bush refusing to rule out military action against the
government of Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   The general's Defense Forces on Monday called the shooting of
the policeman an ``ever more reckless aggression'' by the United
States and accused U.S. officials of twisting the facts of the case.
   The American involved was leaving a laundry in western Panama
City when the policeman motioned to him to stop and approached him,
according to the U.S. Southern Command. It said the policeman
appeared to reach for a gun.
   ``The American responded defensively by pulling a weapon and
fired two shots,'' the U.S. statement said. ``The Panamanian went
down, then got up and left the scene.''
   Panama, however, said the American was traveling in a vehicle
that ``never stopped and on the contrary, accelerated.''
   One of the two shots hit policeman Cesar Tejada in the left
forearm, a Defense Forces communique said.
   The civilian laundry, under contract to clean U.S. military
uniforms, is near Southern Command headquarters and less than a
mile from Panamanian Defense Forces headquarters.
   Tensions already were high over Saturday's fatal shooting of
Marine 1st Lt. Robert Paz, 25, of Dallas, and the reported beating
of a Navy couple who U.S. officials say witnessed the shooting.
   The government-owned newspaper Critica today called the two
incidents ``epileptic arrogance'' by the United States and lashed
out at the ``cynicism to blame the Defense Forces for the criminal
actions of Saturday when four U.S. soldiers fired on civilians and
defenseless women.''
   U.S. forces stayed on maximum alert but took no public action
other than to patrol their bases in battle gear. Traffic and
business in Panama City was normal today.
   Since Noriega was indicted on cocaine trafficking charges in
Florida in February 1988 the United States has tried through
economic, diplomatic and political pressure to drive him from power.
   The Panamanian leader claims the U.S. drug charges, which he
denies, are part of a plot by Washington to renege on the 1977
Panama Canal treaties, which cede control of the waterway at the
end of the century.
   Panama says Paz _ and three others with him Saturday _ ran a
checkpoint and wounded a Panamanian soldier and two civilians. The
Southern Command said they were fleeing a crowd of Panamanian
soldiers and people in civilian clothes when the Panamanians opened
fire.
   Photographs viewed by The Associated Press of the 1981 Chevrolet
with Michigan plates in which the Americans were riding showed
bullet holes, including two on the driver's side and one through
the trunk.
   U.S. officers said the shots came from Soviet-made AK-47 rifles.
   ``This is the most serious incident we have had,'' a U.S.
Command spokesman said. ``This involved a loss of life. No course
of action is being ruled out as a response.''
   ``We are trying to be rational in our response. We are going to
take a calculated plan of action. The U.S. government does not
respond without thinking results through.''
   He spoke on the condition of anonymity.
   White House press secretary Marlin Fitzwater said the Noriega
government's recent declaration of a ``state of war'' with the
United States ``may have been a license for harassment and threats
and in this case murder.''
   Lt. Col. Arnulfo Castrejon Garcia, the Panamanian navy chief,
said the two military forces were communicating by messenger about
the incidents. A U.S. military source said there had been no
``negotiations.''
   He said Maj. Gen. Marc Cisneros, commander of the U.S. Army
South, had demanded an explanation of the American officer's death
and threatened to invade Panama.
   A Southern Command spokesman declined to comment on Castrejon's
version.
   Panama's Defense Forces sent U.S. military officials a letter
that did not explain the shooting but demanded that U.S. forces
``exercise maximum prudence to avoid unfortunate incidents.''
   Castrejon also denied that the U.S. Navy couple was mistreated,
but confirmed they were arrested.
   ``At no time any of our defense forces threaten, intimidate or
much less torture any citizen, much less if he is a foreigner or an
American,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>