<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1556EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Elena-Sketch     12-25 0586</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Elena-Sketch,0604</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dictator's Wife a Pitiless Ruler</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Elena Ceausescu, the textile worker
who rose to virtual second-in-command, was praised by her husband's
regime as ``the best mother of Romania,'' but insiders say she
derided her people as ``worms.''
   During the years of her husband's draconian rule, she also
developed a taste for furs and jewelry, and was honored for
scientific expertise she did not possess. She had bugs planted to
spy on her children.
   Official biographies shaved two years off her age, to make her
one year younger than her husband, Nicolae Ceausescu. Mrs.
Ceausescu actually was 72, a year older than the deposed dictator.
   Bucharest Radio said she and her husband were put on trial
secretly and executed Monday for genocide and other crimes against
the Romanian people.
   Mrs. Ceaucescu was born in Petresti, a village in southern
Romania, in 1917. She married her husband when both were teen-age
revolutionaries and joined the Communist Party in 1937 in Bucharest
where she worked in a textile factory.
   After Ceausescu's takeover in 1965, she rapidly rose in the
party hierarchy. She was named a member of the party executive
committee in 1973, and also was a member of the Politburo and first
vice premier.
   She once was elected ``queen'' of a workers' parade on May 1,
1939, and she lived like one in the last two decades.
   Elena and Nicolae Ceausescu acted much like a royal family,
traveling abroad, conducting well-staged visits to farms and
factories, and making a regal promenade at state receptions.
   Romanian TV on Sunday showed footage from one of the Ceausescus'
residences, displaying some of her jewelry and Western currency
allegedly prepared in a bag for escape.
   One of her many expensive fur coats was found at the Communist
Party headquarters Friday and paraded in front of photographers
after she and her husband fled the capital by helicopter.
   Mrs. Ceausescu was said to be a trained chemist and was praised
as a ``scientist of world fame.'' Her works filled Romanian
bookstores and were translated into foreign languages. But they
were believed to be ghost-written by other scientists.
   As chairman of the national council for science and education,
Mrs. Ceausescu was in charge of all curricula, from elementary
schools to higher education.
   Her celebrated competence in science was less than genuine.
During her time as director of the Central Institute of Chemical
Research, she took the floor at several national conferences and
meetings but spoke on general matters.
   Whenever a specific scientific theme arose, she deferred to a
``Comrade Engineer'' who then had to explain the details.
   Gen. Ion Pacepa, chief of Romanian intelligence operations
abroad until 1978 when he defected to the United States, said in a
book published last year that his duties included collecting
classified technological information to be used in the books by
Mrs. Ceausescu.
   Pacepa said he was also ordered to ensure Mrs. Ceausescu could
shop for jewelry whenever she wanted.
   He said he reported to her once a week with tapes secretly
recorded at the residences of their children _ two sons and a
daughter _ and other high officials, so she could keep tabs on them.
   Sources close to her entourage said she was cynical and paid no
attention to the real needs of the 23 million Romanians, whom she
despised.
   ``The worms never get satisfied, regardless of how much food you
give them,'' she was once overheard saying, referring to their
complaints about food shortages that plague Romania.
</TEXT>

</DOC>