<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0100 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1955EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Panama-Occult     12-25 0300</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Occult,0309</SECOND>
<HEAD>Investigators Show Evidence Of Noriega's Occult Interests</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FORT AMADOR, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.S. Army said Monday it found
idols, potions and other evidence that Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega
practiced a form of occult worship.
   At a house at Fort Amador on the edge of the capital,
specialists with the Army Civilian Investigation Command showed
reporters items indicating that Noriega practiced ``santeria.''
   Noriega, meanwhile, was waiting in the Vatican mission for word
on his plea for asylum after U.S. troops invaded Panama last week
and drove him from power. He fled to the mission Christmas Eve.
   Army agent James Dibble, a specialist in the occult, defined
santeria as a worship of saints usually used as appeasement of God,
but which can be used for malevolent purposes as well.
   Various potions and colored ribbons contained names, pictures
and documents belonging to Noriega's political enemies, including
President Bush, former President Ronald Reagan and the new
Panamanian president, Guillermo Endara.
   Endara's photo was found in a ball of what appeared to be corn
dough wrapped in colored ribbons.
   A tray of unidentified red slime contained the government
identification card and original birth registration of Roberto
Eisenmann, co-founder of the opposition newspaper La Prensa.
   The items included a maggot-infested cow's tongue that had nails
driven through it. It was in a bowl covered with corn and rotten
eggs and wrapped in a cloth. The name of the person, written on a
slip of paper, was not legible.
   Dibble said the ribbons and potions represent specific saints.
   Army specialists said they think Noriega brought in a prominent
santeria practitioner from Brazil.
   Spirit cults, which originated in Africa, are popular throughout
the Caribbean, Brazil and much of South America. Among cult
followers are people from all social and economic classes.
</TEXT>

</DOC>