<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1212EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Judge-LegalDrugs     12-23 0744</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Judge-Legal Drugs,0765</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge's Advocacy of Legalized Drugs Prompts Criticism, Support</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VERA HALLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In June, a man convicted of selling nearly a
half kilogram of crack went before U.S. District Judge Robert
Sweet. He spoke of his family and his wish to lead a productive
life, and he pleaded for mercy.
   Sweet, who this month became the first federal judge to publicly
advocate drug legalization, reluctantly sentenced the defendant to
20 years in prison. Bound by federal sentencing guidelines, his
frustration was evident.
   ``I know of no basis upon which I could accede to your plea,
though I think it is entirely reasonable, and I regret that
intensely,'' he said.
   ``It is a mechanical task. I am a clerk,'' the judge complained.
   His frustration festered, along with the perception that the
judicial system was being overburdened by ``a social phenomenon.''
   And so, in a speech Dec. 12, Sweet declared the war on drugs was
``bankrupt.'' The lifelong Republican and former federal prosecutor
suggested that drugs like marijuana, crack and heroin be legalized
and treated like alcohol _ taxed, regulated and made illegal for
minors.
   ``I suggest it is time to abolish the prohibition - to cease
treating indulgence in mind-alteration as a crime,'' Sweet said in
his speech. ``More money, more prisoners, more addicts _ these
numbers demonstrate to me our present prohibitive policy has
failed, flatly and without serious question.''
   The reaction was instantaneous. The president's drug czar,
William Bennett, condemned Sweet's remarks as ``stupid'' and
``morally atrocious.'' Vice President Dan Quayle denounced him;
Gov. Mario Cuomo said he considered legalization ``a sellout.''
   But others came to his defense.
   ``I think he's a courageous man,'' said Baltimore Mayor Kurt
Schmoke. ``All he's trying to do is get our country to admit the
failure of current policy and to persuade national policy-makers to
consider a more efficient alternative to controlling drug abuse and
drug-related crime.''
   ``Judge Sweet has learned a great deal and is everywhere honored
as a wise man and experienced jurist. What he said needs thinking
about,'' wrote conservative columnist William F. Buckley.
   Both Schmoke and Buckley had previously supported legalization _
Schmoke set off a firestorm in April 1988 when he suggested the
idea to the U.S. Conference of Mayors. Others who have broached the
proposal range from former U.S. Attorney General Ramsey Clark to
economist Milton Friedman to former Secretary of State George
Shultz. Each has been targeted by critics.
   ``Sometimes at a reception or party I advance these views and
people head for somebody else. They don't even want to talk to
you...,'' said Shultz, in an October speech to alumni of Stanford
Business School. ``No politician wants to say what I just said, not
for a minute.''
   Sweet's remarks were especially provocative because of his 11{
years on the federal bench. To lawyers and judges who know him,
Sweet is a thoughtful, intelligent and fair judge whose opinion
should not be easily dismissed.
   ``The man is obviously in the eye of the hurricane,'' said David
Breitbart, an attorney who has represented clients before Sweet.
``If he says the war on drugs is a failure then he has seen it on a
firsthand basis in the courts.''
   Sweet did not answer numerous requests for an interview.
   Sweet's experience with the drug problem dates back to the late
1960s when as a deputy New York City mayor, he helped supervise
treatment programs for addicts. Recent sentencings reflect his
continued belief in rehabilitation.
   In October, Sweet imposed a one-year prison term, the lightest
sentence allowed by the guidelines, on a 29-year-old man who
pleaded guilty to taking part in a conspiracy to distribute cocaine.
   Noting that it was the first conviction for the employed father
of two young children, the judge said in a sentencing memorandum
that any longer sentence would interfere with, rather than
facilitate, rehabilitation.
   Sweet also ordered the defendant to undergo drug testing and
treatment during three years of probation following his prison term.
   His colleagues said Sweet's public stand for drug legalization
would not affect his work as a judge.
   Chief Judge Charles L. Brieant of the Southern District of New
York said Sweet would continue to be assigned narcotics cases.
   ``The judges of the court are confident that Judge Sweet will
honor his oath of office and administer the law as it stands,''
said Brieant. ``A judge doesn't lose his First Amendment rights by
becoming a judge.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>