<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0239 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0321EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Freeze-Disaster     12-29 0448</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Freeze-Disaster,0463</SECOND>
<HEAD>Governor Declares Florida a Disaster Area From Freeze</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Frozen Profits, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CURT ANDERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TALLAHASSEE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Low-interest federal loans could be
made available to Florida farmers who lost crops in the Christmas
freeze after Gov. Bob Martinez declared the state a disaster area.
   Martinez sent a letter Thursday to U.S. Secretary of Agriculture
Clayton Yuetter asking for approval of the Farmers Home
Administration loans. The governor also signed an executive order
declaring the disaster following several visits to freeze-damaged
farms.
   ``From what I have seen, there is no question that Florida has
suffered devastating losses and that our state is a disaster
area,'' Martinez said. ``We must now do everything we can to help
those whose lives and livelihoods have been ravaged by the
unmerciful weather.''
   The governor's order affects all 67 Florida counties and opens
the door to a possible disaster declaration by President Bush once
the full extent of the losses is known. A presidential declaration
would make unemployment assistance, direct grants and other
assistance as well as FHA loans available to growers.
   The hard freeze Saturday and Sunday nights damaged Florida's
700,000-acre citrus belt as well as winter vegetable crops, many of
which would have gone to markets in the Northeast. The state's
tropical fish industry, sugar cane crops and plant nurseries also
suffered heavy losses.
   Higher vegetable prices have already been reported, but the
impact on citrus prices could be minimal because of a large juice
reserve and the quick processing of frost-bitten fruit into
concentrate.
   Reaction from growers was mixed, with some industry
representatives saying the programs could throw the delicate
supply-and-demand balance of the food business into disarray,
driving down some prices.
   ``It can extend the disaster beyond its time,'' said Reggie
Brown, spokesman for Florida Fruit and Vegetable Association in
Orlando.
   Ernie Neff, spokesman for Florida Citrus Mutual in Lakeland,
said not all growers could benefit from disaster programs, but they
could keep some from going deeply into debt.
   ``When you're in a disaster area, you look for all the options.
Not every grower can use them, but it will certainly help some,''
Neff said.
   State agriculture officials will assess the damage in each
county to find the exact losses, which would be needed before a
federal declaration is made. That could take two or three weeks.
   Jon Peck, the governor's press secretary, said it will take time
to ascertain just how much of the citrus crop was lost because some
damaged fruit can still be turned into concentrate for juice.
   Martinez earlier declared a statewide emergency that waived
truck weight restrictions so growers can quickly haul their
products to processing plants.
</TEXT>

</DOC>