<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0158 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1552EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-Symposium-FarEast Adv31   12-26 0741</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Symposium-Far East, Adv 31,0755</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 31, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WORLD SYMPOSIUM '90s: Far East _ Even More Growth in Economic
Power</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LARRY THORSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At the dawn of a new decade, key Far East nations
are growing economically stronger, pulled along by the mighty Japan.
   Japan's economy is predicted to hum along at an annual growth
rate close to 5 percent, the best among the big industrial
democracies and the powerful engine helping other fast-growing
economies like South Korea, Taiwan, Hong Kong and Singapore _ the
``Little Dragons.''
   The only real problem Japan faces as the 1990s begin is in the
political realm. The governing, pro-business Liberal Democratic
Party, beset by scandals and an unpopular tax, is heading for a
crucial election, most likely in February.
   The Japanese electorate will have a chance to pass judgment on
whether the cozy government-business relationship that has helped
make Japan rich is too corrupt to continue. The result is hard to
predict, though it seems likely that a political stalemate will
harden, doing nothing to change Japan's postwar reputation for
sterile politics.
   Japan and the Little Dragons harnessed well-educated, dedicated
work forces to the aim of exporting, with the huge U.S. market as
the target. Their success, however, has finally stung the American
giant into demanding reciprocal export markets.
   The old formula for economic success in the Far East thus is in
question, and countries are increasingly looking to each other as
markets. With Washington's backing and initial membership, a
conference of Asia-Pacific nations was held in Australia in 1989 to
improve economic coordination.
   Japan's overall trade surplus has declined but the troublesome
surplus with the United States seems stuck around $50 billion a
year. American demands for quality Japanese consumer products,
machinery and high-tech gear are unlikely to abate.
   Trade negotiators will be busy for the foreseeable future as
Washington seeks greater sales in Japan's market. The U.S. strategy
now is to change fundamental ways of doing business in Japan, and
U.S. officials can expect tough slogging.
   Traveling right behind the negotiators are businessmen from the
United States _ and many other countries _ seeking niches in
Japan's lucrative market.
   Other countries in the region will be similar targets of the
international businessman, and, like Japan, the explorer will find
in them vibrant local markets and complex political situations.
   Hong Kong, for instance: the British colony is to revert to
Chinese rule in 1997, and the question now is how many of the 5.6
million people will still be in Hong Kong then. The colony's morale
slumped in June when the Chinese army stamped out the pro-democracy
movement, and the future of Hong Kong depends on developments in
Beijing and London.
   China casts a shadow over other Far Eastern economies. It had
become a key source of cheap labor and land for businesses
searching for lower overhead costs. The stunning political
repression in Beijing set back many plans for investment in China.
   While South Korea and Taiwan moved forward with democratic
political reforms, the Philippines' young democracy took a heavy
shock in December with a bloody military coup attempt. The
mutineers probably shot as many holes in the country's chances for
strong economic growth as they shot in the high-rises of the Makati
district of Manila where the coup sputtered out.
   Elsewhere in Southeast Asia, Malaysia, Thailand and Indonesia
are bidding to follow the region's other new economic powers.
Cambodia is in perpetual civil war and Vietnam is so poor that its
citizens are still fleeing almost 15 years after the Indochina War
ended.
   Vietnam, however, may be a new entry in the region's
economic-growth stakes if it is able to shed the pariah status it
earned by invading Cambodia.
   The Vietnamese occupation officially ended in September after 10
years, an indication of how long it can take to make a political
change in the region. Burma, for instance, remains stuck with an
authoritarian government.
   And North Korea's communist regime, still under the helmsmanship
of Kim Il Sung after 44 years, was not steering to East
European-style political changes as the decade ended. The leader's
son and possible successor, Kim Jong Il, said the North Korean
party ``must on no account admit heterogeneous ideas into it. In
party activity, the unity of action based on a single ideology can
be realized through monolithic leadership.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Sunday, Dec. 31</NOTE>

</DOC>