<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0242 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2244EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Panama-Military 2ndLd-Writethru a0832 12-20 0937</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Military, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0832,880</SECOND>
<HEAD>Attackers Melded Paratroopers, Tank Units, Foot Soldiers</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 4th graf: `Fifteen American,'' to raise total of injured
to more than 100</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRYAN BRUMLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.S. attack force captured or drove most
regular Panamanian Defense Forces from their bases on Wednesday and
planned to begin clearing the streets of Panama City on Thursday of
troops loyal to their fugitive leader, Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega,
top Pentagon officials said.
   ``It looks like the organized resistance is a thing of the
past,'' said Lt. Gen. Tom Kelly, the director of operations for the
Pentagon's Joint Staff.
   U.S. troops reported seeing Noriega several times on Tuesday,
but on Wednesday he and an undetermined number of loyal troops
eluded capture, Kelly told a Pentagon briefing.
   Fifteen American servicemen were killed, more than 100 were
wounded and one was missing, Pentagon officials said. An American
female dependent also died in the fighting.
   The U.S. forces captured 250 members of Noriega's army. Sporadic
fighting was reported late in the day, but most Panamanian units
had dispersed and may have fled into the jungle, Kelly said.
   ``We have a concern that they have gone off into the jungle,''
he told reporters. ``There is every chance that we will go off
after them.''
   The main operation on Thursday will be moving military police
and other units into Panama City, a city of 1 million where nine of
Noriega's 18 so-called Dignity Battalions were spotted Wednesday,
said Rear Adm. Ted Shaefer, an intelligence specialist.
   The Dignity Battalions, which beat civilian candidates during
elections last spring, are poorly armed and organized and are not
considered a major military threat, said Shaefer.
   U.S. officials expect ship traffic to resume Thursday through
the Panama Canal, said Kelly.
   ``The canal is functioning. There has been no endeavor that we
have discovered to destroy it,'' he said.
   The more than 20,000 American troops sent against Panamanian
military bases Wednesday moved in relative secrecy and carried out
simultaneous, pre-dawn attacks using paratroopers, infantry and
light tank units, top Pentagon officials say.
   ``It is among the most professionally executed operations that I
have seen in 33 years of military status,'' Kelly told a Pentagon
briefing. But he said without elaborating that ``we have
information that human beings in Panama have made mistakes.''
   The identities of the dead and wounded had not been released by
late afternoon; casualties were being flown to Kelley Air Force
Base in San Antonio, Texas.
   The U.S. forces failed initially to capture their prime target,
Noriega. Hours after the 1 a.m. invasion, American troops continued
to encounter sniper fire and pockets of resistance, said Defense
Secretary Dick Cheney.
   Nevertheless, Gen. Colin Powell, the chairman of the Joint
Chiefs of Staff, proclaimed ``Operation Just Cause'' a success.
   ``This reign of terror is over,'' he proclaimed.
   Powell, in a breakfast-hour briefing, said Noriega was ``not
running anything, because we own all of the bases he owned eight
hours ago.''
   The U.S. operations, involving Ranger paratroopers, Marine Corps
and Army infantrymen and light tanks, were launched simultaneously
against Panamanian military bases and Noriega's heaquarters, the
Commandencia.
   ``I hope you recognize how complicated an operation this was,
and how competently it was carried out,'' Powell said.
   In addition to the 13,000 U.S. troops stationed in Panama, the
United States sent 7,000 troops there overnight and was airlifting
an additional 2,500 over the course of the day, for a total of
22,500, said Powell.
   U.S. forces stationed in Panama before the invasion included the
193rd Infantry Brigade, reinforced with Marine Corps units; a
battalion from the 7th Infantry division at Fort Ord, Calif.; a
mechanized battalion from the 5th Infantry Division at Fort Polk,
La., and Military Police units, Powell said.
   The decision to invade was made Sunday night. The next night,
the of additional forces from the United States began, including a
brigade from the 82nd Airborne Division at Fort Bragg, N.C., two
Ranger battalions, and selected Special Operations units. Units
headed for Panama Tuesday included the 16th Military Police brigade
from Fort Bragg.
   Powell said the units were concentrated into four main groups.
They are:
   _Task Force Atlantic, made up of the 82nd Airborne and 7th
Infantry divisions, which occupied the Electrical Distribution
Center, the Madden Dam and the Gamboa Prison, where they liberated
47 Panamanian officers taken prisoner after the abortive Oct. 3
coup attempt against Noriega.
   _Task Force Semper Fidelis, made up of Marines and a light
armored infantry company, which attacked the area around the Bridge
of the Americas and the U.S. Howard Air Force Base, and ``completed
their missions successfully,'' he said.
   _Task Force Red, which attacked two Panamanian Defense Forces
units that had been loyal to Noriega in the Oct. 3 coup, the 6th
and 7th Infantry Companies. Some Noriega loyalists were captured
but others escapted, he said.
   _Task Force Bayonet, made up of the 6th Mechanized battalion,
light tanks, and the 5th battalion of the 87th Infantry, which
attacked Noriega's headquarters, the scene of the heaviest fighting.
   Asked whether Noriega might form a guerrilla army, Powell said:
   ``He can do that, and we will chase him and we will find him. He
is a very canny individual. He's demonstrated incredible ability to
survive catastrophe, and we'll see over time whether he survives
this catastrophe.
   ``It's been some years since General _ Mister _ Noriega, the
fugitive, has been seen in the jungle. He's used to a different
kind of lifestyle. I'm not quite sure he would be up to being
chased around the countryside by Army Rangers, Special Forces and
light infantry units.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>