<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0128EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-MoonRace     12-18 0665</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Moon Race,0686</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviets Reveal Never-Used Lunar Spacecraft from 1960s</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DANIEL Q. HANEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Twenty years after the United States put men on
the moon, the Soviets have admitted they raced to get there first,
U.S. scientists say.
   The Massachusetts Institute of Technology released photographs
of a landing craft and a module built _ but never used _ to put
cosmonauts on the moon and bring them back to Earth.
   The pictures were taken last month by one of a group of U.S.
aeronautics engineers who were shown the equipment while touring
the Moscow Aviation Institute.
   ``We are almost positive that we are the first Westerners to
have seen this,'' said Edward F. Crawley of MIT.
   While many believed that the Soviets wanted to reach the moon
first, they long denied that they were in the race.
   ``What's newsworthy is they are just now admitting that they
were trying to get to the moon. They always denied it,'' said Lee
Saegesser, archivist at the National Aeronautics and Space
Adminsitration in Washington, D.C.
   The Soviets first acknowledged the lunar program in October,
when the newspaper Pravda published an interview with Vasily P.
Mishin, its chief designer.
   The Soviets told the American professors that the spacecraft was
ready to fly the year before the U.S. Apollo 11 mission reached the
moon in 1969. But the project was abandoned because of difficulty
perfecting the rocket booster that would have carried some of the
equipment into space.
   The Americans said the Soviets were nonchalant about showing off
the hardware.
   ``It was off hand,'' said Jack L. Kerrebrock, MIT's acting dean
of engineering, who snapped the pictures.
   ``They took us into the room that houses this hardware to show
it to us as part of their educational program. Indeed, this is how
it's used by students. They crawl around it and make drawings of
it.''
   The Americans said the equipment resembled the U.S. landing
craft except for two major details: The Soviet setup required two
rockets rather than one to carry it into space. And it would have
have carried one man rather than two to the lunar surface.
   The Americans were shown the equipment by their Moscow host,
professor Oleg Alifanov. The Americans _ five from MIT and one from
California Institute of Technology _ were in the Soviet Union to
help set up an exchange program with the Soviet aerospace institute.
   Crawley said the Soviets showed a ``mixture of pride that they
had built it and sorrow that they had never used it and concern
that no one had ever heard about it.''
   Americans Neil Armstrong and Edwin Aldrin were the first to set
foot on the moon on July 20, 1969. The era ended three years later
when Apollo 17 astronauts made the sixth and final lunar landing.
   The Americans said the Soviets told them the lunar lander part
of the mission was ready to go in 1968, and they were under
pressure to hurry because of the Apollo successes. However,
setbacks in the development of the Soviet's N1 booster rocket
delayed the mission.
   They said the moon program was put on hold in 1972 and canceled
two years later. The Soviets then gave priority to their space
station project.
   The Americans saw the Soviet equipment on Nov. 27, and MIT
released Kerrebrock's photos Sunday.
   The N1 booster would have carried the lunar landing craft into
space, while a Proton rocket would have lifted a spacecraft
intended to bring the cosmonauts back to Earth.
   The Americans said the Soviet landing craft, complete with
extendable landing legs, was designed much like the U.S. version.
   ``There is a lot of similarity due to form and function,'' said
Crawley. ``It's the natural form that something that would land on
the moon with men on it would have.''
   Besides Kerrebrock and Crawley, others who saw the equipment
were Lawrence R. Young, Leon Trilling and Daniel E. Hastings of MIT
and Frank Marble of Caltech.
</TEXT>

</DOC>