<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0242 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1902EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-BoeingUnion     12-19 0397</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Boeing Union,0411</SECOND>
<HEAD>No Talks in Sight for Boeing Engineers After Contract Rejection</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Boeing Co. faced a new labor threat Tuesday from
the engineers and scientists who play a crucial role in designing
its planes, less than a month after a crippling Machinists strike
ended at the aerospace giant.
   In ballots counted Monday night, those members of the Seattle
Professional Engineering Employees Association voted 69 percent to
reject a three-year contract offer from the world's largest
commercial airline builder.
   Although members also voted by 52 percent not to authorize their
negotiators to call a strike, the union said it might be well into
1990 before the contract talks resume.
   ``Our executive director has been in touch with the director of
labor relations at Boeing and we've made known our availability at
any time,'' said Dan Mahoney, union general counsel.
   ``However, it appears the rejection was quite a surprise to
company negotiators and they weren't prepared for it, so they have
to assemble their negotiating team.''
   Company negotiators apparently had made commitments to other
activities and face a logistical problem in getting them all back
together, Mahoney said.
   ``Right now, if I had to guess, it would be after the first of
the year'' before negotiations will resume, Mahoney said.
   Boeing officials were meeting to discuss the situation, but
there was no indication when talks might resume, company spokesman
Paul Binder said.
   The engineering union's other unit, which represents Boeing
technical and support workers, ratified a separate three-year pact
by nearly 2 to 1. Both contracts expired Dec. 1.
   The offer rejected by engineers, who now make an average of
nearly $40,000 a year, included a 3 percent wage increase, a
productivity bonus of 10 percent of gross pay in the first year and
no further general increases.
   Technicians, with average pay of about $28,000, accepted wage
increases of up to 3 percent and bonuses of up to 10 percent.
   Mahoney said the union was sending a survey to its engineer
members ``so when we do go to the table we'll know what to ask
for.''
   He added, however, that ``the engineers feel the money offer
undervalued their services. I do believe they (company negotiators)
will have to offer more money.''
   Members of the International Association of Machinists and
Aerospace Workers voted Nov. 18 to end a 48-day strike and accept a
three-year pact.
</TEXT>

</DOC>