<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1328EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany     12-30 0565</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany,0581</SECOND>
<HEAD>Germanys Join Forces to Prevent Neo-Nazi Mayhem on New Year's</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAROL J. WILLIAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Germanys have joined forces to keep
rallies by neo-Nazis from ruining the first New Year's that Germans
on both sides of the border can celebrate together.
   East Germany on Saturday opened new border crossings to make it
easier for Germans to cross over into their neighboring country to
mark the end of a momentous year and the beginning, perhaps, of a
new era of closeness.
   West German Chancellor Helmut Kohl, in a televised New Year's
message to be aired Sunday, credited the reform movements in the
Soviet Union, Poland and Hungary for making the democratic
revolution in East Germany possible.
   ``This past year has brought the unity of our fatherland a good
deal closer,'' Kohl said. ``After decades of division, awareness of
the unity of our nation is alive.''
   In another interview to be published Sunday, West German
President Richard von Weizsaecker said a joint head of state for
East Germany and West Germany is ``conceivable.''
   But in the interview with the Hamburg-based newspaper Bild am
Sonntag, Weizsaecker cautioned that Germans in both states must be
patient in bridging the divisions.
   Kohl and other conservatives have fueled a confrontation between
those who support reunification and those who feel East Germany
should remain independent.
   Ultra-right activists planned to use the more relaxed border
procedures during the weekend to infiltrate East German border
towns and demonstrate for reunification, according to officials in
the West German city of Fulda.
   Viking Youth, a neo-Nazi group fashioning itself after the
Hitler Youth, has appealed to radical sympathizers to cross into
East Germany from Hesse state with flashlights and fireworks to
stage a noisy demonstration, the Fulda officials said.
   Erwin Maisch of the West German border patrol in Fulda and
regional police chief Karl Ball told reporters West and East German
authorities agreed to increase patrols in the area.
   East German officials warned last week of an increase in
neo-fascist incidents during the past year because of the dizzying
pace of reforms. Massive protests in East Germany ousted the
hard-line leadership in a matter of weeks.
   A New Year's Eve gathering of the Viking Youth has been
forbidden by Fulda regional council chief Fritz Kramer, who warned
that right-wing demonstrations could lead to ``violent
consequences.''
   Several hundred women from both sides of divided Berlin
demonstrated along East Berlin's famed Unter den Linden
thoroughfare Saturday to protest fascism.
   The demonstrators, led by Eva Rohmann of the East German state
women's organization, denounced vandalism by right-wing extremists,
who last week targeted a Soviet war memorial in the suburb of
Treptow.
   Neo-Nazi desecrations have reportedly been on the rise in East
Germany in recent months, but officials claim most of the
disturbances are created by radicals from West Germany.
   Participants in the peaceful pro-democracy rallies held in
Leipzig each Monday contend that many banners pressing for
reunification are the work of West German ultra-rightists.
   West German border authorities said Saturday they were informed
of at least 20 temporary pedestrian crossings opened along the East
German border with Bavaria state to facilitate the heavy traffic
expected on the holiday weekend.
   More than 350,000 East Germans arrived in West Germany in the
two days prior to noon Saturday, and more than 50,000 West Germans
crossed into northern East Germany, authorities said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>