<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0174 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0544EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DigestBriefs     12-29 0546</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Digest Briefs,0566</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A group claiming responsibility for bombs that
killed a federal judge and a civil rights lawyer threatened in a
letter full of racial invective to assassinate two NAACP officials
``as part of the same reprisal.''
   In a letter to WAGA-TV, an organization calling itself Americans
for a Competent Federal Judicial System also threatened to kill
lawyers, judges and members of the National Association for the
Advancement of Colored People ``any time a black man rapes a white
woman.''
   The threatened reprisals led black leaders to bolster security
plans for the Jan. 15 celebration of slain civil rights leader
Martin Luther King Jr.'s birthday.
   Precautions were being taken at the 600 southeastern branches of
the NAACP, said Earl Shinhoster, the organization's regional
director. He declined to say what those precautions were.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government, making its annual forecast of
winners and losers in American business, says jet aircraft and
other high-technology areas will be strong in 1990, but automakers
and construction firms will not fare as well.
   The Commerce Department assessed the prospects of 350 U.S.
industries for its 31st edition of the ``U.S. Industrial Outlook.''
   On the industrial side, it predicted that three-fourths of the
193 manufacturing firms it reviewed should enjoy rising shipments
next year while 18 percent will suffer declines and the rest will
have stagnant shipments.
   It predicted a median growth rate in manufacturing shipments of
2 percent next year, after removing the effects of inflation. That
would compare with estimated growth of 2.2 percent this year and
2.5 percent in 1988.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The news media shuttered by the
regime of Manuel Antonio Noriega are rushing to resume operations
just days after the general's overthrow by U.S. forces.
   Even employees of those media that loyally followed a
pro-government line under Noriega are celebrating the installation
of the civilian government of President Guillermo Endara.
   The Noriega closed three opposition newspapers, three radio
stations and a television channel in 1988, shortly after the United
States began demanding the general's ouster. His regime
expropriated another TV station this year.
   In some cases, broadcast or publishing licenses were revoked,
equipment confiscated and offending reporters houned into exile.
The new government announced Thursday that all news media can
resume operations without any restrictions.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Six soldiers killed in the U.S. invasion of Panama were buried
in services around the country, with mourners honoring their
dedication to an effort that ``silenced an evil regime.''
   Among those buried Thursday was Spec. Alejandro L.
Manriquelozano, the first of the dead from the invasion to be laid
to rest in Arlington National Cemetery.
   Manriquelozano, 30, was buried with military honors _ including
three rifle volleys and the playing of ``Taps'' _ in snow-covered
ground at Arlington within sight of the Capitol and Washington
Monument. Manriquelozano, a naturalized American citizen from Peru
who lived in Lauderhill, Fla., was an anti-tank gunner with D
Company, 2nd Battalion, 504th Infantry, of the Army's 82nd Airborne
Division.
   His sister, Luz, who flew to Washington for the funeral with
other family members from Lima, Peru, told reporters, ``We are
proud of him, because he always wanted to be an American. His
desire is fulfilled.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>