<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0130EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CashCrop Bjt   12-23 0572</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Cash Crop, Bjt,0591</SECOND>
<HEAD>In Western Massachusetts, Farmers Design Their Own Futures Market</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHELLE LOCKE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SHEFFIELD, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two farmers in the Berkshire Hills are
selling stock in a piece of summer, marketing $10 notes redeemable
in fruit and vegetables at their produce stands starting in June.
   The ``pay now, eat later'' approach is more or less the same one
employed by the Chicago futures markets _ only on a tiny scale.
   The notes will give farmers a short-term loan over the winter
when business is slow and costs, such as heating greenhouses, are
high, said Susan Witt of Share, a non-profit group that works to
improve the region's economy.
   They also will help build the customer base for the stands owned
by Don Ziegler and Dan Tawczynski, she said.
   The dollar-bill-sized Berkshire Farm Preserve Notes, which went
on sale Thursday, are green and decorated with hand-drawn fruit and
vegetables and the slogan ``In Farms We Trust.''
   They cost $9 but will be worth $10 when redeemed in June, July
and August at the Ziegler and Tawczynski stands in western
Massachusetts.
   ``It's really being used as a self-financing tool,'' Witt said.
``It's a way of saying, `No, we don't have to be dependent on
federal loan programs, state loan programs. We the customers can
support the businesses that we shop at ourselves.'''
   In October, Share was involved in a similar project. Great
Barrington delicatessen owner Frank Tortoriello made a successful
issue of Deli Dollars, certificates worth $10 in future food at his
establishment. He needed to raise money to move the delicatessen.
   Agriculture Commissioner August Schumacher Jr. launched the
farmers' issue by buying two notes Thursday. With the notes came
promotional literature calling on consumers to ``invest now in your
summer cravings for Berkshire-grown plants and veggies.''
   ``I'm intrigued with it,'' Schumacher said. ``I think we
certainly want to support the community's efforts to support their
local farmers. I'm looking forward to seeing how it turns out.''
   At the Tawczynski stand, called Taft Farms, about $700,000 in
sales were rung up last year, said Martha Tawczynski. But winter
costs are high, with 3,000 gallons of oil burned this year already
to keep the greenhouses warm.
   Turning to the community, rather than to a bank, to raise spring
seed money came naturally to the farm families, Mrs. Tawczynski
said.
   ``These are just local people ... they're our friends,'' she
said. ``We get to know people across the counter.''
   Ziegler and Tawczynski had been discussing the idea for some
weeks, but the it took on urgency when a severe fire destroyed part
of Ziegler's stand earlier this year.
   His stand, the Corn Crib, is operating again, but money has been
tighter than it usually is during the non-productive winter months,
Ziegler said.
   ``You're always spending more money than you're beginning to
make,'' he said.
   If the farm notes work for the two farmers, Share hopes to
extend the program to other local operations, Witt said.
   ``The idea seems right for this area. It's a flexible idea and
other people have taken it up and seen how they could use it and
that is encouraging,'' she said.
   The concept may be limited to tightly knit areas such as the
Berkshire Hill communities, she said.
   ``It's a rural New England area that likes to help out itself,''
she said. ``Its local connections are very strong and that's why it
works.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>