<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0132 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1854EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Baltics     12-19 0412</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Baltics,420</SECOND>
<HEAD>Source Says Bush Warned Gorbachev on Baltic Violence</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRYAN BRUMLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush told Mikhail S. Gorbachev at
the Malta summit that using force to block non-violent independence
movements in the three Baltic Republics would damage U.S.-Soviet
relations, a senior administration source said Tuesday.
   ``I think the Soviet leadership understands our position on this
very clearly,'' said the U.S. official, who spoke on condition of
anonymity.
   Meanwhile, an emigre Baltic diplomat who was briefed by U.S.
officials on the discussion said he was told that Gorbachev
responded that violence would not be used under his reform.
However, Gorbachev made no specific promises on the Baltics, whose
independence he has opposed, the diplomat said.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III received similar
assurances from his Soviet counterpart in September. The
conversation at Malta was significant because the independence
movements are gaining strength.
   The United States never recognized the Soviet annexation of
Lithuania, Latvia and Estonia after World War II.
   Under Gorbachev's reforms, those three republics, with a
combined population of 7 million, have been striving for
independence. Gorbachev has said that post-war Soviet borders
cannot be changed.
   Bush's conversation with Gorbachev was not disclosed in the days
immediately after the Dec. 2-3 summit, but representatives of the
three emigre Baltic governments were briefed Monday by Assistant
Secretary of State Raymond Seitz.
   By warning Gorbachev against the use of force, Bush assisted the
Baltic independence movements, said Stasys Lozoraitis, charge
d'affaires at the Washington legation of the Lithuania. The exile
governments of the three republics have maintained legations in
Washington since they lost their independence.
   ``If they do not use violence, we can slowly and carefully do
what we need to do,'' Lozoraitis said.
   Leaders of the Lithuanian popular front Sajudis are predicting a
victory in February elections to the republican parliament and plan
to use their majority to secede from the Soviet Union, a step that
is legal under the Soviet constitution.
   The administration source said that Bush and ``the secretary of
state have made clear our legal position, that we do not recognize
the incorporation, and that their status ought to be a matter of
self-determination. We have no particular view as to the outcome.'''
   A key point of the U.S. position, said the source, was that the
process ``should be peaceful.'' The exchange on the issue at Malta,
the source said ``wasn't really a dialogue. It was a presenting of
views.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>