<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0202 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2124EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Sentencing     12-20 0449</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Sentencing,0462</SECOND>
<HEAD>Life Terms for Three Palestinians in Fire Bomb Deaths</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARIEH O'SULLIVAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A military court sentenced three Palestinians
to life prison terms Wednesday for a firebomb attack on an Israeli
bus that killed a rabbi's daughter, her three children and an
Israeli soldier, the army said.
   After sentencing, Israeli soldiers tried to assault the
prisoners and turned on journalists as they left the court, Israel
radio reported. No injuries were reported.
   Last week, the court in Ramallah found Ahmad Takruri, 22; Jumaa
Adam, 20, and Mahmud Abu Harbish, 19, guilty of causing the deaths
by throwing firebombs at the bus as it passed through the biblical
town of Jericho in the occupied West Bank.
   It found the attack to be premeditated, and also convicted the
men of preparing firebombs in three prior instances. Adam was given
two years beyond life because of a two-year suspended sentence for
an earlier conviction.
   The attack occurred on Oct. 30, 1988, two days before national
elections. It was thought to have given a last-minute boost to
rightist parties such as Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir's Likud
bloc, which urged tougher action against the Palestinian uprising.
   There had been expectations the three would be sentenced to
death after military Judge Lt. Col. Yosef Shapira said last week
the court was not bound by the prosecution's request for life
sentences.
   The army prosecutor, Capt. Moshe Bachar, said at the time a
request for the death sentence was rejected in consultations with
high-ranking authorities.
   The only person ever executed in Israel was Nazi war criminal
Adolf Eichmann, who was hanged in 1962.
   Chief of Staff Dan Shomron said at the time of the attack that
it was ``spontaneous'' and ill-planned.
   ``It was a group of guys who were sitting around at night
playing cards and decided to throw a firebomb at a passing bus,''
he said.
   The three were said to have hidden in a banana grove and hurled
firebombs through the open windows of the passenger bus traveling
from Tiberias to Jerusalem.
   Rachel Weiss, a 27-year-old school teacher, and her sons
Netanel, 3, Rafael, 2, and 9-month-old Efraim were burned to death.
David Delarosa, a soldier who tried to rescue the family, suffered
severe burns and died later.
   On Oct. 30, a Jerusalem court handed down the stiffest sentence
of the 2-year-old uprising against Israeli rule, giving a
Palestinian 16 life terms for forcing a passenger bus off a cliff
and killing 16 people.
   At least 631 Palestinians have been killed by Israelis during
the revolt, and 43 Israelis have been slain. Another 161
Palestinians have been killed by their fellow Arabs as suspected
collaborators with Israel.
</TEXT>

</DOC>