<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0160 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 2018EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Sharpshooters 2ndLd-Writethru a0686 12-29 0315</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Sharpshooters, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0686,0320</SECOND>
<HEAD>Holdout Sharpshooters Said to be Aiming for Revolutionary Leaders</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS final 2 grafs, `Brucan is...' with 2 grafs to change attribution
from Tass to Le Monde.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Holdout loyalist sharpshooters with infrared
telescopic sights are trying to pick off Romania's revolutionary
leaders, a member of the new leadership was quoted Friday as saying.
   Silviu Brucan of Romania's ruling National Salvation Front was
quoted in the independent daily newspaper Le Monde as saying most
members of the feared Securitate, or security police, had given
themselves up.
   ``It's only a few fanatics with some telescopic sights who
threaten us now,'' he was quoted as saying. ``They now have only
one goal: try to decapitate the movement by assassinating us.''
   In an office at the Romanian Foreign Ministry with the curtains
drawn, Brucan said the security police were able to use their
better equipment to devastating effect, even in total darkness, Le
Monde reported.
   ``They have rifles with infrared scopes. I saw with my own eyes
12 soldiers killed in front of the Central Committee building, at
night, with a bullet right in the middle of the forehead,'' he was
quoted as saying.
   ``In those days, we only moved around in armored vehicles. And
each time, our vehicle was hit by their gunfire. They knew we were
inside. They were everywhere,'' he was quoted as saying.
   Brucan also defended the decision to try and quickly execute
deposed Communist dictator Nicolae Ceausescu and his wife, Elena,
the newspaper said.
   ``If the Securitate had freed them, Romania would have seen a
bloodbath, an atrocious internal war,'' he was quoted as saying.
``We had no choice.''
   He said the military tribunal conducted the trial of the
Ceausescus on Christmas Day, Monday morning, and executed them at
midday.
   Brucan is the former Romanian ambassador to Washington who broke
with Ceausescu.
</TEXT>

</DOC>