<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0616EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Israel-Harari     12-29 0569</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Israel-Harari,0589</SECOND>
<HEAD>Top Aide to Noriega is Former Israeli Intelligence Agent</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LOUIS MEIXLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Israeli who served as a top adviser to
deposed Panamanian leader Manuel Antonio Noriega reportedly led a
famous bungled mission as chief of special operations for Israel's
spy agency.
   The mission set out to catch the Palestinians who carried out
the massacre of Israeli athletes at the 1972 Munich Olympics but
wound up killing a Moroccan-born waiter in Norway in a case of
mistaken identity.
   Michael Harari, whose arrest in Panama was reported Thursday,
was a security adviser to Noriega and an instructor for Panamanian
Defense Forces, according to a U.S. Embassy official in Panama who
spoke on condition of anonymity.
   Spokesmen for the Israeli foreign and defense ministries refused
comment today on the arrest, saying Harari was a private citizen.
   But the exploits of the 62-year-old former Israeli army colonel
have been described extensively in Israeli newspapers.
   The daily Yediot Ahronot said Harari helped Noriega recruit
Israeli mercenaries as his personal bodyguards over the last year.
   The newspaper also said a second Israeli, Eliezer Ben Giton,
surrendered to U.S. troops outside the Vatican mission in Panama
City and identified himself as ``responsible for the personal
security of Gen. Manuel Noriega.''
   U.S. troops invaded Panama on Dec. 20 to seize Noriega and take
him to the United States to stand trial on drug-trafficking
charges. But he eluded capture and took refuge in the Vatican
mission on Sunday.
   The independent Haaretz daily said Israel, under strong U.S.
pressure to cut contacts with Noriega, convinced Harari to leave
Panama last year.
   But the former agent with the Israeli Mossad spy agency later
returned. Haaretz reported that Harari told Israeli officials that
if he did not work with Noriega, his role would be filled by Cubans
or Nicaraguans.
   Israel's ambassador to Panama, Reuven Ben-Eliezer, told Israel
army radio in an interview from New York that he had no contact
with Harari.
   ``I don't know who Harari is, I didn't see him, I didn't meet
him, I didn't get orders from him, and he also didn't receive''
orders from Israel's embassy in Panama, Ben-Eliezer said in an
interview recorded Wednesday but first broadcast today.
   ``He is a private Israeli. I don't know what he did there. He
did business and he was appointed by Noriega as honorary general
counsul for Panama in Israel,'' Ben-Eliezer said.
   Yediot described Harari as the former chief of Mossad's special
operations and said his best-known case was the bungled effort to
kill the leader of the Palestinian Black September group that
massacred 11 Israeli athletes at the 1972 Olympics.
   The case is also described in the book ``The Quest for the Red
Prince'' by Israeli authors Michael Bar-Zohar and Eitan Haber.
   Haber, now spokesman for Defense Secretary Yitzhak Rabin,
refused to comment on the case.
   In the book, the team leader is referred to only as ``Mike,''
but sources familiar with the case have said it was Harari.
   According to the accounts, Harari led a 15-member Mossad hit
squad to kill the Palestinian group's leader, Ali Hassan Salameh.
But the chase ended on May 23, 1973, when agents shot and killed a
waiter in Lillehammer, Norway.
   The incident embarrassed the Mossad and the service's image was
further tarnished when six agents and other Israelis involved in
the mission were arrested by Norwegian police.
</TEXT>

</DOC>