<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0210 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1933EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Judge-Explosion     12-20 0397</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Judge-Explosion,400</SECOND>
<HEAD>Anonymous Letters Examined</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES ROWLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Investigators probing mail bombs that killed a
federal judge and a civil rights lawyer are examining anonymous
letters mailed last summer that threatened the federal judiciary,
the FBI said Thursday.
   The letters, which surfaced in Jackson, Miss., Milwaukee,
Minneapolis and an undisclosed location in California, may be an
important clue in the FBI-led probe of the two fatal mail-bombs in
the South, said FBI spokesman Greg Jones.
   ``We are examining those letters to try to determine whether or
not there is a link between those threats in August and the matters
at hand today,'' Jones said.
   The bombs killed Judge Robert S. Vance of the 11th U.S. Circuit
Court of Appeals and Robert E. Robinson, a Savannah, Ga., alderman
and civil rights lawyer. Other parcel bombs were found at the 11th
Circuit court in Atlanta and the Jacksonville, Fla. NAACP office.
   The FBI says it believes all four similarly packaged bombs were
mailed from locations in Georgia. The bombs were similarly
constructed of nails and explosives, authorities say.
   Television stations in Jackson, Miss., and Milwaukee received
letters bearing Aug. 21 Atlanta postmarks. That was the day before
a tear-gas cannister was thrown into the NAACP headquarters in
Atlanta, injuring eight people.
   Jones refused to discuss the contents of the letters but he said
they were similar in content.
   The ones received by WAPT-TV in Jackson and WITI in Milwaukee
were titled ``Declaration of War'' against the 11th Circuit Court
of Appeals. according to copies made available by the stations.
   They threatened poison gas attacks on heavily populated areas
``until widespread terror forces the court to adopt the impartial
and equitable treatment of all as its highest priority.''
   The Justice Department said Tuesday that the investigation is
concentrating on racial motivations for the killings and the bomb
incidents.
   FBI Director William Sessions said investigators are checking
Vance's court docket. The director said he wouldn't be surprised if
a decision Vance once made motivated the killing.
   Vance ruled in favor of the Jacksonville NAACP on Sept. 15 in a
school desegregation case.
   Jones said all four letters were examined last summer by the FBI
crime laboratory in Washington but yielded no physical clues such
as fingerprints. U.S. Marshals in the various jurisdictions where
the letters were received were told of the threats, he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>