<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0133 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1858EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-KGB 1stLd-Writethru a0662 12-19 0679</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-KGB, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0662,0694</SECOND>
<HEAD>KGB Chief Says Sakharov Exile an `Injustice'</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 8 grafs for 5-12 pvs bgng `Sakharov, winner...' to ADD
dates of exile, meaning of KGB; pickup graf 13 `Kryuchkov...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANN IMSE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   KGB chief Vladimir A. Kryuchkov said Tuesday it
was an ``injustice'' to exile Andrei D. Sakharov to Gorky for
nearly seven years _ a period of physical hardship and KGB
harassment for the late human rights activist.
   In a wide-ranging news conference with a group of female
journalists, the KGB head also predicted Soviets will be less
fearful of his agency after new laws are passed defining its
actions in investigations, including the use of informers and
wiretaps.
   ``I think criminals should be scared of the KGB but innocent
people shouldn't,'' he said. But he acknowledged ``there is
reason'' for ordinary citizens to be scared after years of
repression of supposed internal enemies.
   ``I think that when we pass a law on the KGB, it will do a lot
to calm the situation,'' Kryuchkov said.
   Sakharov, winner of the 1975 Nobel Peace Prize for his protests
of human rights violations in the Soviet Union, was buried Monday
with the pomp and respect due a national hero, three years after he
was released from his exile of January 1980-December 1986.
President Mikhail S. Gorbachev and half the Politburo attended a
memorial service. Kruchkov was not among them.
   Many mourners blamed the KGB for Sakharov's poor health.
Sakharov, 68, had been drugged and force-fed during a hunger strike
while in Gorky, and a doctor warned him, ``We won't let you die,
but we will make you an invalid.''
   Kryuchkov on Tuesday said, ``Our activities should be aimed at
defending human rights.'' Of the treatment given Sakharov, he said
``it was an injustice.''
   Still, the amiable KGB chief's line was not quite consistent. In
written answers to questions, he said, ``We have tightened
requirements for observation of laws,'' and ``alternative
applications'' of laws have been eliminated.
   Yet in verbal responses, he exonerated previous KGB
administrations and much of his current staff. ``The law was
imperfect, but people were abiding by it,'' he said.
   Security forces, he said in another statement, ``fought not
against different-mindedness but against specific illegal acts.''
   Thousands of Soviets were imprisoned for their political beliefs
under a law banning ill-defined ``anti-Soviet activities.'' The law
was rescinded last spring.
   The three-hour meeting with Kryuchkov was the latest sign of the
KGB's greater attention to its image, both at home and aboard. He
met the journalists at KGB headquarters in downtown Moscow, a site
that still strikes fear into many Soviets. KGB stands for
``Committee for State Security.''
   Kryuchkov, a member of the Communist Party's ruling Politburo,
also gave a clear indication that the leadership is leaning toward
acceptance of Sakharov's last call, a demand for removal from the
Constitution of Article 6, which guarantees the party's monopoly on
power.
   ``There is nothing eternal under the sun,'' he said. ``I'm
talking about politics. The leadership is not going to hold onto
Article 6.''
   ``If our Congress decides to abolish or leave out this article,
there will be no tragedy,'' he said.
   The Congress of People's Deputies heeded arguments from
Gorbachev and voted 1,139 to 839 last week against placing the
issue on the agenda of its current session. Only months ago,
Sakharov was one of the few Soviets who dared mention the question
publicly. But as one country after another in Eastern Europe
abolished similar provisions under pressure of massive
demonstrations and strikes, Gorbachev's position has softened.
   The Lithuanian parliament voted two weeks ago to eliminate a
similar article from its constitution and substitute a multiparty
system.
   The KGB chief noted the Constitution now treats the Communist
Party as the leading organization, ``though it may not be true.''
He predicted the party would have to fight for its position in the
future.
   Later, he added, ``We are analyzing what is going on in Eastern
Europe. We are trying to learn from these mistakes and from these
events.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>