<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0260 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1747EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-SearsSuit     12-21 0671</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sears Suit,0695</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sears Denies Sale Price Distorting Charge</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Sears, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN F. BONFATTI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUFFALO, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sears, Roebuck and Co. was accused in a
lawsuit filed Thursday by New York's attorney general that the
retailer's ``everyday low prices'' policy is a fraud. Sears denied
the charges.
   Under the pricing policy announced in March, Sears said it would
cut back drastically on the number of sales it conducts but would
offer many items at lower prices every day.
   But Attorney General Robert Abrams said Thursday that a shopping
survey by his office in many of Sears' 42 New York stores indicated
that isn't the case.
   ``In fact, when consumers went to make purchases, they were
paying essentially the same price'' as under the old system, he
said. ``And in a number of instances, they were actually paying a
higher price.''
   Abrams said he believes the problem may not be limited to Sears'
operations in New York.
   ``We believe that this is a nationwide practice that is being
conducted by Sears in all their stores throughout the United
States,'' said Abrams. ``I'm alerting my colleagues _ the attorneys
general of the other states _ of this investigation so that Sears
might be facing similar action by others.''
   Michael Bozic, chairman and chief executive of Sears
Merchandising Group, denied the company was misleading the public.
   ``We are shocked by the distorted and untrue statements the New
York state attorney general made to news media today regarding
Sears everyday low pricing,'' Bozic said in a news release.
   ``We have a valuable reputation for trust and integrity with
American consumers and we intend to prove these malicious charges
are false,'' he said.
   Sears, the nation's largest retailer, has 847 stores in the
United States.
   In the lawsuit filed in state Supreme Court in Buffalo, Abrams
alleged that Sears portrayed the ``everyday low price'' policy as a
perpetual sale, creating the false impression that the new prices
represented cut-rate discounts from Sears' previous prices.
   For instance, he said, a canister vacuum which sold most
frequently at a sale price of $199.99 under the old system was
listed at an ``everyday low price'' of $219.99.
   Similarly, a living room set which most often sold at $899.94
before March cost $979 under the ``everyday low price'' system.
   Abrams said his office received information on Sears' prices and
number of units sold by monitoring advertisements and obtaining
actual sales figures from the company.
   ``(Sears advertised) that in effect every day, virtually every
item would be on sale,'' he said. ``We have found that they have
deceived consumers; that the prices that people pay are not
substantial sale bonus discounted prices.''
   About 20 items were priced, Abrams said. Bozic said that's too
small a number to accurately reflect all of the items Sears sells.
   ``While we have not yet reviewed his lawsuit, we believe that it
is based on an investigation of only 14 items out of the more than
100,000 items we sell,'' he said. ``This, in itself, is
misleading.''
   Thursday's action marks the second time in three years Abrams'
office has had problems with Sears' marketing.
   In 1986, Abrams' office and Sears reached a settlement where the
company paid a $75,000 fine to settle a complaint that it engaged
in false advertising.
   In that case, the state accused Sears of claiming that items
were discounted from regular prices when, in fact, the items almost
never sold for the ``regular price.''
   ``We caught them doing that, they were fined $75,000 and they
pledged never to do it again,'' said Abrams. ``We have shopped in
the store on a weekly basis over an 18-month period and we caught
them doing the same thing again.''
   The suit filed Thursday also charged that Sears violated its
1986 agreement.
   The state asked the court to fine Sears, stop it from engaging
in such practices in the future and order restitution for consumers
``who were induced to buy items because of the fraudulent
advertising and sales practices.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>