<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0194 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1225EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-WallStreetNoon     12-28 0307</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Wall Street Noon,0323</SECOND>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Stock prices held very close to Wednesday's
closing levels today, marking time in the next-to-last session of
the year.
   The noon Dow Jones average of 30 industrials stood at 2,724.40,
unchanged from Wednesday.
   Gainers and losers ran about even in nationwide trading of New
York Stock Exchange-listed issues, with 670 up, 662 down and 529
unchanged.
   Much of the activity appeared to be devoted to last-minute
maneuvering by investors for tax and yearend portfolio reporting
purposes.
   Analysts said money managers at many investing institutions had
pretty well closed their books on 1989, and thus were making few
waves in the marketplace.
   The government is due to report Friday on the index of leading
economic indicators for November.
   Advance estimates call for a flat to slightly higher showing by
the index, which would presumably do little to resolve the
questions in investors' minds about the economic outlook for the
first half of 1990.
   Germany Fund ranked among the volume leaders, up 1~ at 19[. The
stock of the closed-end investment company has soared in recent
days on expectations of big benefits to West German business from
the opening up of Eastern Europe.
   Campbell Soup gained 3{ to 56{ on word that some members of the
company's founding Dorrance family want to find a buyer for their
stock.
   Among actively traded blue chips, American Telephone &amp; Telegraph
rose } to 45]; International Business Machines dropped ] to 94];
Philip Morris added ] to 40|, and Eastman Kodak was down [ at 40|.
   The NYSE's composite index of all its listed common stocks rose
.29 to 192.98. At the American Stock Exchange, the market value
index was up .05 at 373.01.
   Volume on the Big Board came to 59.80 million shares at
noontime, against 58.95 million at the same point Wednesday.
</TEXT>

</DOC>