<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0134 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1554EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Vietnam-Refugees 1stLd-Writethru a0570 12-29 0675</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Vietnam-Refugees, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0570,0693</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Clash With Boat People During Search For Weapons; 40 Injured</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 4 grafs after 15th graf, `According to ...' with reaction
from British opposition, Foreign Office; Picks up 16th graf, `About 44,000
...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CINTY LI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HONG KONG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police raided a Vietnamese refugee camp Friday
and clashed with stone-throwing boat people who reportedly feared
they would forced to return to their Communist homeland. Officials
said 40 people were injured.
   Police fired tear gas after the Vietnamese set fire to blankets
and threw rocks to prevent a search for homemade weapons, said
government spokesman Timothy Li. Twenty-seven Vietnamese were
arrested and more than 700 weapons seized, police said.
   Television showed police equipped with helmets and shields
firing tear gas, and smoke from the fires could be seen rising
above the center on outlying Lantau island, which houses more than
3,000 Vietnamese.
   ``The boat people, in order to make the operation more
difficult, pushed their women and children to the front,'' said
Security Secretary M. Geoffrey Barnes.
   The violence came only one day after clashes broke out between
Vietnamese at another center in which one person was killed and 10
others injured.
   The government-funded radio reported the resistance may have
been prompted by reports that some of those in the center may be in
the next group of boat people forced to return to their
impoverished homeland.
   Earlier this month, the government returned 51 Vietnamese to
their homeland against their will in the first such repatriation.
   Although officials refused to say how many police joined in the
operation, the radio put the number at about 300.
   Police said Friday night that said 14 Vietnamese and 26 guards
and policemen were injured in the camp.
   The officials said five hours of counseling by staff of the U.N.
High Commissioner of Refugees and voluntary agencies failed to
persuade the Vietnamese to cooperate.
   Police reported two clashes Thursday night between Vietnamese
armed with homemade weapons at the Shek Kong Detention Center in
which one person died and 10 others were injured..
   Police said they were investigating the cause of the brawls
between two rival groups from Quang Ning. About 100 people were
involved in the fighting.
   Police have classified the case as homicide. The injured at Shek
Kong ranged in age from 16 to 28, and one was hospitalized in poor
condition, police said.
   No arrests were made at Shek Kong but police found homemade
weapons such as swords and lances in the detention center after the
battles.
   According to police, five people have died this year in
factional fighting that erupts frequently in the crowded and
squalid Vietnamese camps.
   ``This latest violence is a further manifestation of the unrest
in the camps caused by the threat of forced deportation,'' said
George Foulkes, of Britain's opposition Labor Party. ``I fear that
it is a foretaste of worse to come unless the government abandons
its policy.''
   Foulkes also accused the British government of delaying
deportations at the request of the U.S. government.
   ``While they are dithering and delaying, the situation in the
camps is reaching boiling point,'' he said.
   A Foreign Office spokesman, who requested anonymity, said in
response: ``The facts are that considerable assistance is being
given through our reintegration package to the boat people ... We
are not waiting for Washington.''
   About 44,000 boat people who have sailed into Hong Kong since
mid-June 1988 and are considered illegal immigrants unless they can
prove they fled persecution.
   Those who are denied refugee status and have their appeals
rejected can volunteer to go home or face forced repatriation.
   The 12,000 boat people in Hong Kong who arrived before the
screening program took effect were automatically granted refugee
status and are awaiting resettlement overseas.
   Meanwhile, the eighth batch of boat people to volunteer to
return to their Communist homeland flew back to Hanoi Friday.
   The 111 people who took the chartered flight bring to 874 the
number of boat people who have returned home voluntarily since
March.
</TEXT>

</DOC>