<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1200EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-Borders     12-24 0495</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Borders,0510</SECOND>
<HEAD>East Germans Welcome West Germans as Visa Restrictions Dropped</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH G. SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of West Germans passed through the
Berlin Wall on Sunday after East Germany marked the holidays by
lifting visa and currency requirements on visitors from the West.
   A spontaneous festival erupted on the East side of the wall's
Brandenburg Gate shortly after midnight as West Berliners poured
through the border crossing.
   The East German government, forced to give in to a pro-democracy
uprising, opened the Berlin Wall on Nov. 9 and lifted most
restrictions on East Germans who want to travel to the West.
   Earlier this month, the government lifted currency exchange and
visa requirements on West Germans traveling to the East, fully
opening the border between the nations.
   The new rules went into effect at midnight Saturday, and there
was no shortage of West Germans curious about the East.
   East Berliners tried to return the warm welcome they had
received in West Berlin in November, when bars and cafes stayed
open all night in a riotous celebration of freedom.
   Six weeks later, smiling East Germans rolled out a large keg of
beer, others passed out cognac in the cold drizzle and still others
served as guides for West Berliners, many of whom had crossed into
East Berlin for the first time.
   They strolled down Unter Den Linden, the most elegant boulevard
in East Berlin.
   Berliners from both sides of the crumbling wall broke out in a
chorus of old songs, and couples twirled around to the steady beat
of an organ grinder winding his way around the Brandenburg Gate.
Merrymakers handed flowers to police who grinned in response.
   Others shook metal cans to collect money for medical supplies
for battle-stricken Romania, while the familiar clink of souvenir
seekers chipping away at the wall continued in the background.
   Until Sunday, West Germans were required to obtain a visa to
travel into East Germany and were obliged to change 25 marks, about
$15, each day, a hefty sum for young people and the elderly.
   Now, West Germans simply must show an identity card and fill out
a short form so that the East Germans are able to keep track of the
number of visitors.
   West German border police reported that East Germans greeted
their West German neighbors with flowers and a welcome drink in
numerous villages along the border even before the new rules became
official.
   At many border crossings, East German border guards simply
ignored the rules and allowed West Germans in before the new
regulations went into effect.
   Still, border police reported Sunday morning that the number of
East Germans heading West outstripped the number of West Germans
using their new travel freedoms in the other direction.
   But the number of East Germans traveling to West Germany had
fallen sharply in comparison with previous Sundays. Border police
attributed the drop to the fact that the stores were closed for
Christmas.
</TEXT>

</DOC>