<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0176 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1817EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-MailBombs 1stLd-Writethru a0757 12-22 0640</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mail Bombs, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0757,670</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Says Evidence Links Threatening Letters</HEAD>
<BYLINE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with court members receiving threatening
letters. ^By JAMES ROWLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Colleagues of a federal appellate judge who
was killed by a parcel bomb similar to one that fatally injured a
civil rights lawyer have since received threatening letters,
sources said Friday.
   The Justice Department, meanwhile, said four threatening letters
delivered this week bore physical evidence linking them to the
bombs.
   The letters to the judges were among those that surfaced after
parcel bombs killed 11th Circuit Court of Appeals Judge Robert S.
Vance on Dec. 16 and Savannah, Ga., alderman and attorney Robert E.
Robinson two days later, said the sources.
   A letter addressed to Vance was also among those delivered, said
the sources, who spoke on condition of anonymity.
   Justice Department spokesman David Runkel said he was unaware
that letters had been delivered to judges on the 11th Circuit.
   But he said there was ``solid evidence'' on four threatening
letters delivered this week linking them to the parcel bombs that
killed Vance and Robinson as well as two others found this week.
   Parcel bombs were also found at the the Jacksonville, Fla.,
chapter of the NAACP and the 11th Circuit courthouse in Atlanta.
Both were defused without incident.
   Runkel declined to describe the common characteristics of the
letters and the parcel bombs.
   But stamps, typing or other markings on the packages and letter
envelopes may give FBI crime lab specialists important clues.
   Comparing the typing on the letters and packages may enable the
FBI to determine if the same typewriter was used to address the
parcels and write the letters.
   Runkel said the physical evidence may also provide a link to
four other letters sent in August that declared war on the 11th
Circuit.
   The earlier letters, sent from Atlanta, threatened poison gas
attacks on population centers until ``widespread terror'' forces
the 11th Circuit to ``adopt the impartial and equitable treatment
of all.''
   Before Vance's death, the 11th Circuit had 10 active judges. The
Atlanta-based court considers appeals from federal district courts
in Florida, Georgia and Alabama.
   While the FBI continued its investigation of the bombings in the
deep South, a state judge was seriously injured by a parcel bomb in
his apartment in Hagerstown, Md.
   The FBI sent agents to assist local police and the Bureau of
Alcohol Tobacco and Firearms to investigate the blast that injured
Circuit Judge John Corderman.
   The FBI-led investigation has been concentrating on possible
racial motivations for the killings in Georgia and Alabama.
   Agents have been combing Vance's docket to determine if any of
his decisions, particularly in civil rights cases, may have
motivated the slaying.
   In September, Vance wrote an opinion in a Jacksonville school
desegregation case that was a victory for the NAACP. A three-judge
panel of the 11th Circuit unanimously reversed a lower court's
ruling that Jacksonville could stop busing students because the
school system was racially integrated.
   Robinson had represented the NAACP on an unrelated school
desegregation case involving Savannah schools.
   Investigators have found physical evidence linking the bombs,
which were made with nails and explosive material. The bomb parcels
all were mailed from towns in Georgia.
   Vance was killed in his suburban Birmingham, Ala., home after
opening a package. Robinson was fatally injured by a bomb that
exploded when he opened a similar package sent to his law office.
   Meanwhile, Savannah police said that security would be tight for
Robinson's funeral Saturday.
   Benjamin Hooks, director of the National Association for the
Advancement of Colored People, is expected to speak at the service.
   The Justice Department said Deputy Attorney General Donald B.
Ayer, James P. Turner, acting head of the civil rights division,
and William Lucas, director of the department's Office of Liaison
Services would attend the funeral.
</TEXT>

</DOC>