<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0232 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1707EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-WallStreet 1stLd-Writethru   12-19 0473</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Wall Street, 1st Ld-Writethru,0492</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eds: Updates with closing prices throughout.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHET CURRIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Stock prices continued to sag Tuesday amid
persistent worries about the future course of the economy.
   The Dow Jones average of 30 industrials slipped 1.92 to
2,695.61, extending its loss over the past four sessions to 65.48
points.
   Declining issues outnumbered advances by about 2 to 1 in
nationwide trading of New York Stock Exchange-listed stocks, with
513 up, 1,021 down and 479 unchanged.
   Analysts said the latest economic reports from the government
hadn't done much to pull the market out of its recent slide,
induced to a great extent by worries about the real estate market
and mortgage debt.
   The Labor Department reported that the consumer price index rose
0.4 percent in November, or at an annual rate of 4.9 percent. That
appeared to put a new obstacle before any fresh moves by the
Federal Reserve to relax its credit policy.
   Separate government figures showed a 4.7 percent decline in
housing starts last month.
   Brokers said that left stocks in the grip of recession fears and
of talk that a slump in business conditions might be exacerbated by
a weak market for homes and other real-estate properties.
   A few recently depressed mortgage and regional banking stocks
staged a rebound. Federal National Mortgage rose 1] to 32{, and
Bank of New England gained { to 8.
   But elsewhere among the regional bank stocks, First Fidelity
Bancorp dropped { to 21]; First Interstate Bancorp ] to 42};
Citytrust Bancorp | to 14, and Fleet-Norstar Financial { to 23}.
   Money-center bank stocks were mixed. Citicorp rose [ to 27;
Chase Manhattan added \ to 32[; J.P. Morgan lost ] to 40\, and
Bankamerica was up | at 24{.
   The battered technology sector also attracted
``bargain-hunting'' buyers. International Business Machines gained
1[ to 94}; Digital Equipment 2[ to 84]; Hewlett-Packard 1 to 45{,
and Unisys \ to 14[.
   Unisys said it expected to post a ``significant'' profit in
1990, in large measure because of cust-cutting steps taken this
year.
   Volume on the floor of the Big Board came to 186.06 million
shares, against 184.79 million in the previous session. Nationwide,
consolidated volume in NYSE-listed issues, including trades in
those stocks on regional exchanges and in the over-the-counter
market, totaled 224.98 million shares.
   As measured by Wilshire Associates' index of more than 5,000
actively traded stocks, the market lost $13.98 billion, or 0.42
percent, in value.
   The NYSE's composite index of all its listed common stocks
dropped .77 to 189.40.
   Standard &amp; Poor's industrial index lost 1.14 to 392.46, and
S&amp;P's 500-stock composite index was down 1.23 at 342.46.
   The NASDAQ composite index for the over-the-counter market fell
1.68 to 434.35. At the American Stock Exchange, the market value
index closed at 367.95, down 2.91.
</TEXT>

</DOC>