<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 2121EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PUREXPlant     12-17 0374</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-PUREX Plant,0384</SECOND>
<HEAD>DOE Reopens Plutonium Processing Plant For Limited Operations</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHLAND, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A key plutonium production plant at the
Hanford nuclear reservation reopened Sunday to process spent
nuclear fuel that has been stuck in the plant since it was shut
down a year ago, the government said.
   Energy Secretary James D. Watkins authorized the reopening
Friday based on a review by the department and the need to improve
safety at the facility, said Department of Energy spokesman Tom
Bauman.
   The Plutonium-Uranium Extraction Plant takes nuclear fuel rods
from Hanford's N Reactor and dissolves them to extract plutonium
and uranium. The plutonium must be processed further at another
facility for use in nuclear weapons.
   The N Reactor has been closed since late 1986, but PUREX
continued to operate until last December to reduce a large
stockpile of irradiated fuel.
   Westinghouse Hanford Co., which operates the nuclear production
complex for the government, said it shut the plant down because
operators did not follow procedures in handling a loss of steam
pressure.
   DOE officials have said previously that the shutdown of the
PUREX plant would not hurt the country's ability to make nuclear
weapons.
   A review of safety requirements and procedures, along with
retraining of about 500 PUREX workers, was completed in March.
Equipment repairs and improvements to waste treatment systems at
the 33-year-old plant delayed the resumption of operations, Bauman
said.
   PUREX is expected to remain open for four to six weeks to finish
processing material that was in the plant when it was shut down,
Bauman said.
   Then, the plant will be shut for another year to make additional
modifications and improvements before resuming the processing of
spent fuel in storage at Hanford, Bauman said. Processing that
inventory is expected to take until 1995.
   From PUREX, plutonium is sent to Hanford's Plutonium Finishing
Plant, which has been operating only periodically for the past
year. Bauman said that plant will gear up eventually to handle the
additional plutonium from PUREX, but he could not say when that
might occur.
   The nation's only other plutonium extraction operation is at the
Savannah River Plant in South Carolina, but it has little to do
because reactors at that site have been closed for safety reasons.
</TEXT>

</DOC>