<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0098 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1454EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Czechoslovakia     12-27 0398</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Czechoslovakia,0415</SECOND>
<HEAD>20 Prisons Affected in Strikes for Amnesty, Better Conditions</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Inmates demanding better living
conditions and amnesties staged hunger strikes or other protests in
at least 20 prisons across the country Wednesday.
   Opposition leaders, many of them former prisoners themselves,
said they were working with the Justice Ministry in reviewing
inmate grievances and would propose an amnesty for some prisoners.
   Any amnesty would have to be granted by the president, who is to
be elected Friday. Vaclav Havel, a leader in the opposition Civic
Forum, is the only candidate.
   The prisoners' demands vary widely but focus on living
conditions. Petr Pospichal, a Civic Forum spokesman, said many of
the demands were legitimate.
   ``Many of us have experience in this situation personally,'' he
said, referring to several members of Czechoslovakia's reform
government, including Havel, who once were imprisoned for dissident
activities.
   The non-violent protests began Friday when 2,500 inmates at
Leopoldov Prison east of Prague began a hunger strike demanding a
general amnesty.
   By Wednesday, the hunger strike had spread to 16 prisons in the
Czech republic and four in the Slovak republic, according to the
Justice Ministry and the Communist Party daily Rude Pravo.
   Some prisoners waved banners advocating non-violence.
   ``The protest is spreading so fast it's impossible to monitor,''
said Pospichal.
   He said Civic Forum would ask that some sentences be reduced and
some prisoners released.
   All political prisoners were released from Czechoslovak jails
under an amnesty granted by hard-line Communist President Gustav
Husak before he resigned Dec. 9. That amnesty covered 800 to 2,000
inmates.
   Popsichal said he did not know how many prisoners might be
affected by a future amnesty but said six inmates sentenced in
secret trials for espionage would be included on Civic Forum's list
of those deserving amnesty.
   ``The president is the only one who can decide about whether to
grant amnesty, and the scope is his decision,'' Pospichal said.
   The Czechoslovak government, meanwhile, announced plans for
lavish inaugural festivities, including an outdoor ball, following
Parliament's presidential vote Friday.
   Havel, a playwright and former dissident, is the unchallenged
candidate and would be Czechoslovakia's first non-Communist
president in 41 years.
   The election is the crowning victory of a peaceful revolution
that began Nov. 17 and ended four decades of Communist domination,
ousted hard-line Communist leaders, and installed a reformist
government to plan for free elections next year.
</TEXT>

</DOC>