<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0116 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1449EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MercuryContamination     12-29 0287</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mercury Contamination,0295</SECOND>
<HEAD>Martinez Creates Task Force to Examine Mercury</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CURT ANDERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TALLAHASSEE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gov. Bob Martinez signed an executive
order Friday setting up a task force to coordinate study of the
mercury contamination that is threatening the state's rural
environment.
   Elevated levels of the toxic metal have been found in wildlife
such as Florida panthers, alligators, largemouth bass and turtles
throughout the state, said Forrest Ware, chief of the research
bureau of the Florida Game and Fresh Water Fish Commission.
   ``Mercury contamination could pose a very real, very dangerous
threat to public health, and we can't sit back and just hope for
things to get better,'' the governor said.
   The task force is to report to Martinez by March 1 with a plan
to deal with the contamination, including possible solutions.
   ``Basically, we're just identifying problems right now. Then we
can get to the how and why,'' he said.
   Health officials have warned people of possible contamination in
at least eight rivers across the state, including the St. Johns,
Suwanee and Yellow, as well as Lakes Kissimmee and Tohopekaliga.
   In the Everglades, mercury was blamed for the death of a
4-year-old Florida panther earlier this year.
   ``We haven't even looked at the birds yet or the marine life,''
Ware said. ``This has to be investigated.''
   One possible source of contamination could be natural. Peat
contains mercury that could be released through contact with acid
rain or after drought-triggered fires. Coal-fired power plants and
insecticides also are possible mercury sources.
   Task force members are the heads of the state departments of
Health and Rehabilitative Services, Agriculture and Consumer
Services, Environmental Regulation, Natural Resources, Marine
Fisheries Commission and the game commission.
</TEXT>

</DOC>