<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0246 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0629EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a w PM-WalterMears ADV21   12-20 0779</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Walter Mears, ADV21,0796</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv 21</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release PMs Thurs Dec 21 and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Quayle Making the Most of Favorable Publicity</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WALTER R. MEARS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A year into his vice presidency, Dan Quayle is
making the most of any favorable publicity that comes his way, his
wry smile an acknowledgement that it has been scarce. There is no
comparable shortage of advice _ he gets that all the time.
   He's been told to raise his profile, and to lower it; to be more
relaxed, and to be more guarded against gaffes. He has been advised
to specialize on a few, chosen trademark issues, and to be a
generalist so as to display a grasp on the whole catalogue of
issues. Through it all, Quayle has one set answer: he works for
President Bush and he will keep doing what the boss wants done.
   His assignment in 1990 will include a heavy political campaign
schedule, a traditional vice presidential role in off-year
elections. For Quayle that job could be a way to overcome old image
problems and prove that he's not out of his depth, perceptions that
haunt him in the public opinion surveys.
   Vice presidents tend to be underemployed; as Nelson A.
Rockefeller said in shunning the post he later filled, they are
standby equipment. They usually get specialized assignments _
Quayle's include space issues and efforts to enhance U.S.
competitiveness in world markets. But other officials have primary,
day-to-day responsibility. It's always difficult for the No. 2 man
to put his own imprint on government actions or decisions. As
Ronald Reagan's vice president, Bush headed a task force on
regulatory reform, a popular topic in the deregulation decade. It
looked like a promising role, but not much happened.
   That's not uncommon for understudies.
   A vice president is a dependent. His official standing depends
entirely on the boss. Bush has helped on that score.
   Quayle sees Bush every morning when both are in town, and says
he has full access to the president. ``This has been a very
comfortable, important relationship that we have worked out in
these early morning sessions,'' Quayle said this week in a C-Span
television interview.
   That well-advertised access provides a sort of power.
   ``When I'm on Capitol Hill ... senators, congressmen say `would
you please give this to the president?' or `tell the president
this,' or `I don't like this particular policy, I want you to do
something about it,''' Quayle said in the TV interview.
   Bush has publicly promised Quayle renomination for a second term
as vice president and top Republicans consider the commitment to be
absolute.
   But neither job security nor presidential praise has done much
for the performance ratings, despite what Quayle considers a good
first year in office. So he relished a Dec. 15 Wall Street Journal
column praising his performance.
   ``After 12 months in this job I will take any favorable
publicity I can possibly obtain, and I will pocket it,'' he said.
``And I think I'll take that editorial and make sure that it's
reprinted and perhaps sent out to some of my friends.''
   Republican Party leaders say that Quayle can raise both his
profile and his standing in 1990 in the off-year campaign role that
has become traditional for vice presidents. He already gets good
ratings for his work for party candidates and causes. The party
counts about $7 million in proceeds from GOP fundraising events
featuring Quayle.
   Bush will be out campaigning for chosen Republican candidates
next year, as he has at fundraising events for two GOP Senate
challengers. But the heavy schedule of sustained campaigning is
assigned to the vice president. It was Bush's role in the two
off-year elections of his vice presidency, and it will be Quayle's
in 1990.
   He'll have help. In January, E. Spencer Abraham, the Michigan
Republican chairman, will become his deputy chief of staff,
concentrating on political liaison and supervising speech writing,
travel planning and the like.
   The vice president says he'd like to spend more time outside the
Washington beltway, in ``the real America.'' He'll have ample
opportunity in the coming campaign, in a role that can help him
shape a new image or cement the old one.
   Quayle said his sometimes shaky performance in the 1988 campaign
was due in part to traveling consultants who over-coached him to
the point of stifling him. In 1990 he can do it his way.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Walter R. Mears, vice president and columnist
for The Associated Press, has reported on Washington and national
politics for more than 25 years.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>For Release PMs Thurs Dec 21 and Thereafter</NOTE>

</DOC>