<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0453EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WilbergMine     12-18 0774</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Wilberg Mine,0794</SECOND>
<HEAD>Five Years After Mine Disaster, Lessons Remain</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PEG McENTEE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SALT LAKE CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The labyrinthine passages of the Wilberg
Mine, their rich coal seams exhausted, are mostly silent now. But
the harsh lessons of the inferno that claimed 27 lives five years
ago have not been forgotten.
   ``It changed the industry,'' said J. Brett Harvey, vice
president for fuel resources at mine owner Utah Power &amp; Light Co,
which has instituted sweeping changes in safety and technical
procedures.
   ``I think government as well as mine operators look at safety
from a new angle, mostly because of the tragedy.''
   But for Rick Boyle, president of United Mine Workers Local 2176,
even the strictest precautions can't mitigate the dangers of
two-entry longwall mining, in which two passages lead to and from
the coal seam.
   Utah Power and other western underground mine operators insist
the system is the only way to support the weight of the mountain
above as massive machines cut coal from panels hundreds of feet
long.
   The union counters that, as in the case of the Wilberg fire,
miners could be trapped without a third way out.
   On Dec. 19, 1984, extra workers had been summoned to one section
of the mine, the Fifth Right, more than an mile underground to make
a run at a 24-hour production record. There were 28 people where 13
or 14 usually worked for Emery Mining Co., which operated Utah
Power's mines at the time.
   Smoke first was spotted in the roof of the main tunnel system
near Fifth Right's entrance, and soon began snaking along a loop of
ventilation up one passage and down the other.
   Boyle, a diesel mechanic working elsewhere in the mine, was
among those who aimed extinguishers and water hoses at the hot spot
until someone on the surface ordered the power killed, cutting off
the underground pumps for nearly two hours. Meantime, nearly 80
people in other areas were evacuated as firefighters and rescue
teams assembled.
   Kenny Blake, the only miner to escape Fifth Right, has said he
and several others donned emergency breathing devices and groped
through the darkness and smoke toward the main tunnel. Finally,
separated along the way, Blake emerged unharmed.
   Most of the others died of smoke inhalation or carbon monoxide
poisoning in the two entries. One man made his way thousands of
feet deeper into the mine until he apparently was overcome by
carbon monoxide. Three bodies were found in a connecting tunnel
partially blocked by a cave-in.
   That passage was not designated an escapeway, and an inspector
with the federal Mine Safety and Health Administration had issued a
variance allowing the blockage to remain.
   Within three days, officials worried about explosions evacuated
the mine and left the bodies behind, to be retrieved nearly a year
later. With flames visible at the surface Dec. 26, the Wilberg was
sealed.
   In October 1986, an MSHA investigation concluded the fire began
at an air compressor rigged to operate with its heat sensor and
on-off switch disconnected and left running, all but unnoticed, for
nearly 70 hours.
   The UMW later issued its own report, bitterly denouncing the
two-entry system, the variance on the blocked tunnel and ``the
failure to provide escape routes that were safely ventilated and
the failure to protect miners from a fire that killed them.''
   Utah Power was sued by most of the victims' families and
eventually reached a $22 million out-of-court settlement. The
utility took over operation of all its coal mines in 1986, and a
year later it and Emery were fined a record $113,944 for 41 alleged
violations, including nine MSHA said directly contributed to the
fire.
   Emery paid $7,115 for 17 citations, but Utah Power contested the
rest. A hearing is scheduled for March, said MSHA spokeswoman
Katharine Snyder. Also scheduled are trials involving insurance
issues and product liability.
   Utah Power has installed computerized air and equipment
monitoring systems and above-ground, high-power water pumps and
revised ventilation practices in all its mines. Its 650 employees
also are required to undergo annual hands-on training with
breathing apparatus, Harvey said.
   MSHA also analyzed two-entry longwall mining and ventilation
systems and is using the results to revise federal regulations,
Snyder said.
   But for his opposition to the two-entry longwall system now in
place in all Utah Power's coal mines, Boyle commends the utility's
innovations and its willingness to work with the union.
   ``Everybody that works up there lost somebody in that fire that
was a good friend or a partner,'' he said. ``The consequence of
what can happen becomes a vivid reality. And that changes people's
attitudes.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>