<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0166 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1907EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     12-18 0336</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0347</SECOND>
<HEAD>Snow Falls Across Northern Tier Of States, More Record Lows</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Snow fell Monday from Washington state to Maine and winter-like
weather threatened the Southeast, and more low temperature records
were set across the Midwest.
   Balmy Miami beckoned with a record high of 87 degrees.
   Elsewhere, record lows were 1 below zero at Binghamton, N.Y.; 5
below at Cleveland; 3 below at Cincinnati; 7 below at Columbus,
Ohio; 3 below at Detroit; 5 below at Fort Wayne, Ind.; 1 below at
Lexington, Ky.; 3 below at Mansfield, Ohio; 4 below at Parkersburg,
W.Va.; 7 below at Pittsburgh; and 8 below at Youngstown, Ohio.
Elsewhere Redding, Calif., hit a record low of 24.
   At midday, light snow fell from eastern Washington into
northwestern Montana and over parts of Idaho, Colorado, South
Dakota, Nebraska, Kansas, Missouri, Iowa, Michigan, upstate New
York, Vermont and Maine.
   In the Southeast, bitter cold and slippery roads closed hundreds
of schools. Ice was believed to blame for an accident outside
Atlanta in which one man was killed.
   A winter storm warning was posted through the night and into
Tuesday over the mountains, foothills and piedmont of South
Carolina.
   Snow and winter weather advisories were in effect into Tuesday
for parts of Kentucky, Ohio, North Caroline, and Georgia.
   New snow accumulations at Colorado ski resorts included 16
inches at Vail, 10 inches at Steamboat, 9{ inches at Breckenridge,
and 8 inches at Loveland and Mary Jane, the National Weather
Service reported.
   Steamboat Springs has received 99 inches of snow in nine days, a
spokeswoman said.
   Rain was scattered over central Texas and the upper Texas Gulf
Coast, southern Louisiana, southern Mississippi, the Florida
Panhandle, northeastern Florida, eastern Georgia and southern South
Carolina.
   Freezing rain extended from central Arkansas across central
Louisiana.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EST ranged from 13
degrees below zero at Havre, Mont., to 87 at Miami. Monday
morning's low for the Lower 48 states was 31 below zero at Warroad,
Minn.
</TEXT>

</DOC>