<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0088 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1704EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-CitrusFreeze-FoodPrices     12-26 0429</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Citrus Freeze-Food Prices,390</SECOND>
<HEAD>Not Much Expected By Way of Price Increases</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Citrus Freeze, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The freeze that struck Florida citrus and
vegetable crops should drive up food prices somewhat, but not very
much, an Agriculture Department expert said Tuesday.
   The expert, Ralph Parlett of the department's Economic Research
Service, said an earlier forecast that food prices generally may
rise 3 percent to 5 percent next year is still valid.
   Overall food prices are up an average of about 5.7 percent this
year, the largest annual gain since a 7.8 percent jump in 1981.
Much of this year's increase was due to lingering effects of the
1988 drought and poor weather early in 1989.
   ``I'm not worried about my overall forecast (for 1990) at this
point,'' Parlett said in a telephone interview. ``But there'll be
some impact, and possibly higher prices in the first quarter.''
   Parlett said he and other agency analysts are ``still trying to
assess the damage'' to citrus and vegetable crops in Florida.
   ``The main thing is oranges,'' he said. ``Vegetables _ tomatoes,
bell peppers, celery _ they're some of the big volume things that
would be coming out of Florida now.''
   Parlett said 90 percent of the Florida oranges are for
processing and that a lot of them can be salvaged for juice. The
main source of ``fresh market'' oranges is California.
   ``There will be some (retail) price impact,'' he said. ``But
since we do have decent supplies in California this year ... the
supply impact will be minimal.''
   With the supply of Florida orange juice reduced by the freezing
weather, Parlett said imports from Brazil will probably rise
sharply.
   ``We've got super supplies in Brazil this year, but the price
has been fairly low because of the higher supplies,'' he said.
``But now that we probably will be importing, that will push the
price up some.''
   Parlett said he had not seen damage reports from Texas, where
state officials have estimated losses of 70 percent of the citrus
and 80 percent of the winter vegetables.
   Vegetable losses are ``a more temporary kind of thing'' because
those crops can be replanted, he said. Growers were just starting
to harvest Florida's main supply of winter vegetables when the cold
weather struck.
   California is still producing vegetables, however, and ``this
time of year we start getting produce out of Mexico, too,'' Parlett
said.
   ``There's no doubt that some of the supplies will be cut short,
and we'll probably see higher prices'' at produce counters, he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>