<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1243EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-US-China 2ndLd-Writethru a0468 12-19 0865</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-China, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0468,800</SECOND>
<HEAD>White House Defends Secret Missions</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Top 8 grafs with new defense of mission; picks up at pvs 6th
graf, it was, and edits Fitzwater reference in pvs 11th graf, However,
White</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERENCE HUNT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP White House Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The White House today defended President
Bush's secret dealings with China, insisting he has been forthright
with the American people but saying he feels free to send
emissaries on unpublicized missions.
   The statement from White House press secretary Marlin Fitzwater
came amid criticism from a congressional leader that Bush ``misled
the American people'' by sending high-level officials to Beijing
barely a month after the bloody crackdown on pro-democracy
demonstrators.
   The secret mission in July, kept hidden from the public and
Congress until Monday, was carried out by national security adviser
Brent Scowcroft and Deputy Secretary of State Lawrence Eagleburger.
   The two officials visited Beijing on Bush's orders even as the
United States was saying that high-level U.S. exchanges had been
cut in protest of the crushing of the pro-democracy movement.
   ``We've been forthright,'' Fitzwater said today. ``The
forthrightness is in saying we are going to have these kinds of
contacts.
   ``We have and will have (such trips) and they will be secret,
and it is not misleading to tell you about everything he's doing.
The president's up there in the Oval Office doing things all day
long that you don't know and won't know about, and that's not
misleading,'' the spokesman said.
   He refused to say whether there have been any other high-level
contacts with China that have been kept secret.
   Speaking generally about Bush's foreign policy, Fitzwater said,
``There have been trips you don't know about and there will be
more.''
   It was Scowcroft and Eagleburger who also quietly traveled to
China this month expressing hopes to ``bring new impetus and
vigor'' in Sino-American relations.
   In Beijing today, China's Foreign Ministry issued a statement
saying the government had received Scowcroft last July at the
Unites States' request.
   ``Such high-level contacts between China and the United States
are useful and conducive to enhancing the mutual understanding,''
the statement from Beijing said.
   Senate Majority Leader George Mitchell, D-Maine, said in a
statement he was ``astonished'' to learn of the July meeting,
saying the trips to Beijing ``make a mockery of our profession of
concern for human rights and the stated ideals of our democratic
system of government.''
   Mitchell called on the Bush administration to disclose all U.S.
contacts with the Chinese government.
   However, Fitzwater said Monday that he could not rule out the
possibility that Scowcroft and Eagleburger, or other top officials,
had made other, still-secret trips to China.
   The Dec. 8 visit was announced after the two officials arrived
in Beijing. The July visit was acknowledged only after it was
reported by the Cable News Network, and the White House refused to
provide any details, even the date of the trip.
   Rep. Sam Gejdenson, D-Conn., chairman of a House Foreign Affairs
subcommittee on trade, said Bush ``misled the American people and
the Congress.''
   ``How does the White House square that (earlier trip) with their
statements at the time that high-level contacts with the Chinese
were cut off?'' Gejdenson said. ``The sad reality is that the
president confuses his personal relationship with the Chinese
leaders with what is good national policy.''
   Fitzwater said Bush felt it was essential to hold quiet
diplomatic discussions with China outside ``the public glare''
regarding its crackdown.
   ``The president has had years of experience with China and he
knows that face-to-face declarations are important to them, and
felt it was important that they knew privately and from someone on
his immediate staff just how strongly the United States felt about
this,'' Fitzwater said.
   A White House statement said the July mission was undertaken to
underscore U.S. ``shock and concern about the violence in Tiananmen
Square and to impress upon the Chinese government the seriousness
with which this incident was viewed in the United States.''
   Even before the July trip to Beijing was disclosed, Bush was
defending his China policies, insisting that the United States
should not isolate a country with a population of more than a
billion people.
   Bush refused to say whether China's hardline leaders offered any
concessions in exchange for his gesture of taking the first step to
repair relations.
   ``I'm not going to discuss what I did or didn't get,'' the
president said.
   ``You see, I still believe that sometimes to affect change, you
talk in confidence to people,'' Bush said, who has been accused by
Democrats of ``kowtowing'' to China.
   ``And I notice now,'' Bush said, ``that some of the critics who
were so opposed (and) using this fantastically, diabolically
anti-me language, they come up now in saying, `Well, if you get a,
b and c, then it will be all right, or then we'll understand. Let
them just stay tuned.''
   Bush also said he does not know when Chinese dissident Fang
Lizhi will be able to leave the U.S. embassy in Beijing, where he
has taken refuge since the crackdown. Quoting Scowcroft, Fitzwater
denied there were any negotiations with China about an acceptable
country where Fang might go.
</TEXT>

</DOC>