<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0283 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1808EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Columbia-MovieAds     12-22 0395</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Columbia-Movie Ads,0409</SECOND>
<HEAD>Columbia Pictures Moves Tri-Star Pictures Ad Account to McCann-Erickson</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SKIP WOLLENBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Columbia Pictures Entertainment Inc. said Friday
that it had decided to put McCann-Erickson Worldwide in charge of
placing domestic advertising for both its Columbia Pictures and
Tri-Star Pictures movies.
   The decision could mean an extra $70 million to $75 million in
annual billings for the giant New York-based agency, which had
previously held the assignment only for Columbia Pictures ads.
   The loser is AC&amp;R Advertising, a unit of Saatchi &amp; Saatchi Co.
PLC, which had been responsible for placing the Tri-State Pictures
advertising.
   Among Tri-Star's recent films have been ``Steel Magnolias'' and
``Look Who's Talking,'' while Columbia's recent films have included
``When Harry Met Sally ...'' and ``Ghostbusters II.''
   Calls were placed to both agencies, but went unanswered Friday
afternoon. Many businesses closed early Friday in advance of the
three-day Christmas holiday weekend.
   The move comes a month after Columbia Pictures Entertainment was
acquired by Japan's Sony Corp. in a $3.4 billion buyout, but a
Columbia spokesman who asked not to be identified said the decision
was unrelated to the buyout.
   The Columbia and Tri-Star studios merged their marketing
departments last March and had reportedly been reviewing ad agency
assignments for several months.
   In response to inquiries, the Columbia Pictures spokesman in
Burbank, Calif., said the decision to consolidate North American
media placement for the two studios was the next step in the merger
of the marketing departments.
   The spokesman declined to disclose how much the studios spend on
advertising their films.
   But industry sources said that annual spending came to between
$140 million and $150 million this year evenly divided between the
two studios.
   McCann-Erickson, whose total U.S. billings amounted to $1.3
billion in 1988, has handled media placement for Columbia Pictures
for about two years.
   Among its other clients are Coca-Cola Co.'s soft drinks, General
Motors Corp.'s Buick division, American Telephone &amp; Telegraph Co.'s
business-to-business advertising and Exxon Corp.'s gasoline and
motor oil products.
   It recently won a $25 million assignment for Taster's Choice
coffee from Nestle, a $25 million job for unspecified new products
from RJR Nabisco and a $10 million account for Fidelity Investments.
   AC&amp;R Advertising had U.S. billings of $355.6 million in 1988.
Its clients include Austin Rover of North America, Fosters Lager
Beer and Regency Cruises.
</TEXT>

</DOC>