<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0275 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1335EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-Walter-Bankruptcy     12-20 0294</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Walter-Bankruptcy,0305</SECOND>
<HEAD>Parent Of Jim Walter Corp. Faces Chapter 11 Bankruptcy</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TAMPA, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hillsborough Holdings Corp., the parent
company of Jim Walter Corp., said today it was prepared to file for
Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection if its bondholders did not agree
to financial restructuring.
   Kohlberg, Kravis, Roberts &amp; Co. of New York acquired
Hillsborough Holdings as part of its $2.4 billion acquisition of
Jim Walter last year. The Tampa-based building materials company is
currently fighting a $3 billion asbestos-related lawsuit.
   The proposed bankruptcy move would be the first involving a
large company acquired by Kohlberg Kravis, the leader among
leveraged buyout firms, and could have an effect on the junk bond
market that has financed many takeovers.
   Hillsborough officials said the bankruptcy filing was expected
to be made Dec. 27 if an exchange offer for $624 million worth of
the company's bonds were not accepted by at least 80 percent of the
company's bondholders.
   Kohlberg Kravis has apparently failed to persuade a group of
Hillsborough's senior bondholders to accept a proposed financial
restructuring of the company.
   ``If the pending exchange offers are not consummated on their
current terms and conditions, Hillsborough and certain of its
subsidiaries may have no alternative but to file voluntary
petitions for reorganization under Chapter 11,'' said David
Townsend, Hillsborough Holdings spokesman.
   If the offer is not accepted, Hillsborough faces the prospect of
having to repay its notes in full, which it told bondholders at a
meeting Tuesday that it could not do.
   Hillsborough's financial problems began last summer when it was
named in the class-action lawsuit.
   Because of the suit, Kohlberg Kravis has been unable to sell off
Jim Walter's assets. And without the proceeds from the sales, the
company cannot meet its upcoming debt payments.

</TEXT>

</DOC>