<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1213EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NewLaws Bjt   12-30 1002</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-New Laws, Bjt,1029</SECOND>
<HEAD>From Elephant Abuse to Gun Control, New Laws Taking Effect</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE SILVERMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   In California, it will be a crime to abuse an elephant. In
Florida, people who want to dive for scallops will have to buy a
license. In Illinois, the Tully monster will become the official
fossil.
   These and scores of other new laws take effect around the nation
Jan. 1.
   In several states, new measures are going on the books that deal
with gun control, alcohol, drugs and smoking.
   California has a law inspired by the January attack on a
Stockton schoolyard, in which Patrick Purdy gunned down five
children with an AK-47 semiautomatic assault rifle and then shot
himself to death with a handgun. With the new law, military-style
assault weapons identified on a special list will be severely
restricted. The list contains some 55 pistols, rifles and shotguns
that will be barred from manufacture, importation or sale.
   Maryland will bar sale of handguns unless they are on a list of
weapons approved by the Handgun Roster Board. That law is aimed at
so-called ``Saturday night specials.''
   ``Nobody said we were going to stop crime if this occurred,''
said state Police Superintendent Col. Elmer H. Tippett. ``We only
said that it was a start to get some of this junk off the street.''
   Oregon gun buyers and people seeking licenses to carry concealed
handguns will face stiffer identification requirements and
background checks.
   In New York, a new law aims to curb underage drinking. Police
will be able to issue a $50 summons to people under 21 for mere
possession, instead of purchase, of alcohol.
   ``It will certainly help neighborhoods where raucous parties go
on and destroy the neighborhood's tranquility,'' said Doris Aiken,
a Schenectady woman who founded Remove Intoxicated Drivers. ``Kids
at Cornell University would stand in the street with beers in their
hand and wave at the police.''
   But Genevieve Connor, vice president for campus affairs for the
State University of New York Student Association, said ``a law like
this would make people potentially the victims of arrest just
because they're carrying a six-pack of beer.
   ``They may be going to make stew, who knows?''
   Two states are imposing new crackdowns on drunken drivers. In
Connecticut, police officers will be permitted to revoke on the
spot the license of a driver who fails a blood-alcohol test. In
California, it will be a crime to drive with a blood alcohol
concentration of .08 percent or greater, toughened from .10 percent.
   As part of the war on drugs, Connecticut is offering some young
male drug offenders ``boot camp''-style punishment. The state will
spend $10 million on the program, which will also include
court-ordered wilderness school sentencing for certain juvenile
drug offenders.
   A Florida ``drug-free workplace'' law championed by Gov. Bob
Martinez says that law enforcement officers, firefighters and
``safety-sensitive'' state employees may be tested for illegal
drugs when hired or when they undergo physical examinations. The
law does not require the testing and bans random testing.
   Illinois students will be forbidden to carry or use beepers on
school property because the devices are often associated with drug
dealing.
   New York's ``Clean Indoor Air Act,'' touted as the nation's
toughest anti-smoking law after Minnesota's, prohibits smoking in
auditoriums, elevators, gymnasiums, food stores, shared taxicabs
and limousines, and restricts it to certain areas in larger
restaurants and other public facilities.
   In Greensboro, N.C., smokers will face the toughest restrictions
in that state, the nation's No. 1 producer of flue-cured tobacco.
Voters in November narrowly approved the new ordinance, which
requires restaurants to set aside 25 percent of their seats for
non-smokers and bans smoking in retail stores that can accommodate
more than 200 people.
   The elephant law in California stems from the 1988 case of an
8,000-pound pachyderm named Dunda at the San Diego Wild Animal
Park. The animal was ``subjected to two days of beatings which
caused apparently severe injuries and trauma to the head area,''
according to a city attorney's report. Zoological society officials
acknowledged the beatings, but said the elephant needed to be
disciplined.
   Florida's first recreational saltwater fishing license is
expected to raise $6.5 million for fisheries and marine research in
its first year. It will cost $12 for Florida residents and $30 for
those from out of state.
   ``What were once unlimited natural resources are being depleted,
and I think most folks who will be affected recognize that
additonal revenue is needed to enhance the resources,'' said
Richard Healey, deputy director of the Florida Marine Patrol
support services.
   But state Sen. Vince Bruner said many fishing boat captains in
his Panhandle district fear they will lose business to neighboring
states.
   Illinois' new official fossil, known formally as the
Tullimonstrum gregarium, is about a foot long, has a snout like an
elephant's and is 300 million years old.
   ``I've handled a lot of heavier legislation in my time, but this
was one that I was delighted to do,'' state Rep. Larry Wennlund,
who sponsored the legislation at the behest of the son of
discoverer Francis Tully.
   Here is a look at some other new laws:
   ALASKA: Increases residency requirement from six months to two
years to qualify for the dividend given to each citizen from
Alaska's $10 billion oil-wealth savings account. It is expected to
eliminate about 60,000 newcomers from the list. This year's
dividend was $873.
   TEXAS: Requires anyone possessing a wild animal such as a lion,
tiger or bear, for ``breeding, exhibition, or personal use'' to
obtain a $100 permit.
   NORTH CAROLINA: Makes it a misdemeanor to take or sell a labeled
milk crate. Dairies complained that crates were being snatched by
people looking for convenient carriers or low-budget furniture.
   GEORGIA: Makes it illegal to heavily tint car windows. Law
officers worry about the risk of approaching a car without being
able to see the occupants.
   CALIFORNIA: Requires state government agencies to answer their
telephones by the 10th ring. The law contains no provision for
penalizing violators.
</TEXT>

</DOC>