<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0086 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1225EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania-Radio     12-29 0561</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Radio,0579</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S.-Funded Radio Plays Key Role in Romanian Revolt</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALISON SMALE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.S.-funded Voice of America and
Radio Free Europe played a key part in preparing Romanians for
their revolt by informing them of the changes elsewhere in Eastern
Europe, Bucharest residents say.
   RFE's broadcasts in Romanian from Munich and VOA's from
Washington have a big following among Romania's 23 million people
who have had a severely restricted access to Western media.
   Media in neighboring Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and the
Soviet Union also helped keep Romanians abreast of Warsaw Pact
change.
   Clusters of Romanians formed every time Bulgarian state-run
Balkan Airlines posted the Bulgarian TV schedule in its Bucharest
office, and Aeroflot used to display Mikhail S. Gorbachev's latest
pronouncements in Romanian in its windows.
   But East European and Soviet broadcasts often could be received
and understood only on the peripheries of the country, and rarely
carried Romanian emigre or dissident views.
   Romanians say VOA and RFE kept them abreast of news about their
own country, such as a significant letter last spring to Nicolae
Ceausescu in which six former Communist Party officials demanded
major changes and were arrested because of it.
   ``We owe thanks to the United States for the help of the VOA and
Radio Free Europe,'' said a staffer at Bucharest's main children's
hospital. ``Many people were listening to VOA and RFE.''
   Through RFE, a Western diplomat said, Romanians with little
experience of democracy know its terms and progress through the
rest of Eastern Europe.
   ``They've never done it themselves, but they are aware,'' said
the diplomat, speaking on condition he not be identified.
   Under Ceausescu, Romanian TV broadcast only two hours a night,
and up to 90 minutes of that time was devoted to the president and
his deeds.
   Radio gave a diet of similar news, and virtually the only item
anybody read in the newspapers were the meager sports report and
the weather.
   Radio and television, which were captured by the revolutionaries
who forced Ceausescu from power a week ago, have become beacons of
the revolt, spreading vital news through the country.
   Even now, however, the dissenting voices who have united against
Ceausescu can still communicate with each other _ and with the
country _ most effectively through RFE.
   Dissidents like Doina Cornea, a former university professor in
Cluj placed under house arrest for her critical letters to
Ceausescu, poet Mircea Dinescu in Bucharest and writer Dan
Petruescu in Iasi, were unable to meet under Ceausescu's
totalitarian rule. ``They `met' on RFE,'' a Bucharest resident said.
   Other still powerful remnants of totalitarianism enhance the
continued importance of the U.S.-funded radio stations, which can
draw on the expertise of many well-informed Romanian exiles.
   Two years ago, for instance, Ceausescu's wife, Elena, ordered
all Western news agencies into Romania cut, on grounds they were
not needed. Delivery has not been restored.
   Thus, VOA and RFE are still a primary source of information for
Romanians eager to know how their revolution is perceived in the
West.
   ``VOA is the most important broadcast,'' resident Valentin
Hornicar said outside Communist Party headquarters Thursday.
   ``Not only food and medicine are needed,'' said Hornicar, 26.
``We need magazines and newspapers from all over the United States
and all over Europe. We need to see what is being said about us.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>