<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0178 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2036EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-ComputerSabotage     12-18 0421</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Computer Sabotage,0435</SECOND>
<HEAD>Scotland Yard In International Hunt for Computer Saboteur</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scotland Yard has launched an international hunt
for the high-tech saboteur who sent at least 10,000 tampered disks
to individuals and institutions worldwide, officials said Monday.
   Computer users as far away as Australia and South Africa have
received the altered disks, which were packaged as an ``AIDS
Information Introductory Diskette,'' Scotland Yard said. Disks have
also been received in Britain, Norway, Sweden, Denmark and the
United States, officials and news reports say.
   Thousands of callers from British government departments, health
authorities, accountancy firms, lawyers, newspapers, magazines and
commercial institutions have telephoned Scotland Yard about the
suspect disks.
   ``We can't give a number of damaged systems. All we can say is
quite a number of recipients have actually put the disks into their
machines and therefore the machines have been damaged,'' said a
police spokeswoman on condition of anonymity.
   Scotland Yard said it now believes more than one mailing list
may have been purchased by the saboteur. A middle-aged man calling
himself Mr. E. Katema bought a mailing list from PC Business World,
a computer magazine, it said.
   Police said a letter with the disks asks for a ``license fee''
of either $189 or $378, depending on the type of license, to be
sent a Panamanian postal box.
   The letter warns that if the disk is used but no payment made,
the sender will employ programming in the disk to block normal
operation of the host computer.
   Police sources said some damage is caused as soon as the disk is
installed, but full damage is only recognized much later. They say
the disk has a counter that masks the damage until the host
computer has been switched on about 90 times.
   The disk purportedly offers information on the risk of getting
the fatal disease AIDS, or Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome.
   Experts say the disk programming does not automatically spread
to other computers, as some computer viruses have in the past.
   The alarm was first raised earlier this month by Alan Solomon,
chairman of the IBM Personal Computer User Group. He said he had
received one of the disks.
   ``It has also been established that the post office box number
in Panama does exist and inquiries are continuing with assistance
of authorities in Panama,'' Scotland Yard said.
   Detectives have determined that most of the disks were mailed
from London, the Scotland Yard statement said.
   Scotland Yard had said it was treating the case as criminal
damage and blackmail.
</TEXT>

</DOC>