<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1052EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-CoalStrike     12-23 0558</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Coal Strike,1st Ld-Writehtru, a0443,570</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mine Workers, Pittston Seek Pre-Christmas Agreement to End Lengthy
Strike</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Following tops with 4 grafs to update with talks resuming and
Dole delaying travel plans. Pickup 4th graf pvs: The two sides etc. Subs
8th graf pvs to delte Dole first reference.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN KING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Labor Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Striking miners and the Pittston Co. are
hoping to reach a pre-Christmas agreement on a contract that would
end a nearly nine-month strike.
   Talks between the United Mine Workers and Pittston resumed at
midmorning today after breaking off shortly after midnight as the
two sides sought to meet a mediator's hope that the bitter and
sometimes violent strike be settled by Christmas.
   Principals in the talks did not speak to reporters because of a
gag order, but sources said considerable progress was made Thursday
and Friday. Still, an agreement has proved elusive because of
outstanding disputes.
   Labor Secretary Elizabeth Dole, hoping an agreement was near,
delayed plans to travel to her native North Carolina for Christmas
and remained in Washington so she could participate if a settlement
is announced. It was Dole who named the supermediator for the talks.
   The two sides began around-the-clock negotiations early this
week, and word that a settlement might be imminent surfaced at
mid-week as UMW President Richard Trumka and Pittston Chairman Paul
Douglas were called into the talks.
   Mediator W.J. Usery pledged to seek a settlement by Christmas
that would allow the nearly 1,700 miners from Virginia, West
Virginia and Kentucky to return to work after the traditional
holiday shutdown of the mines.
   Although the strike involves just 1,700 miners, it holds broad
implications for the UMW and the mining industry as a whole. The
dispute between the miners and Pittston over retiree health
benefits threatens to undermine a decades-old compact between
mining companies and the UMW guaranteeing retired miners full
health benefits.
   Pittston last year refused to participate in the compact, the
Bituminous Coal Operators Association agreement, because it
objected to the new funding formula. Pittston was unable to reach
agreement with the miners on an alternate plan and had stopped
payments into union pension and medical funds.
   Usery, a former labor secretary and veteran mediator, was tapped
as supermediator by Mrs. Dole in late October, shortly after she
visited with Pittston strikers in the Virginia coal fields.
   The dispute over funding the retirement plans led the miners to
strike April 5 after 17 months of failed contract talks with
Pittston's mining subsidiary, Pittston Coal Group. The miners had
worked for 14 months without a contract when they struck.
   The union has paid the strikers about $200 a week in benefits
and is facing fines totaling $63.5 million for violating court
orders limiting picketing and other strike activities. Last week
the union said it would give each striker a $1,250 Christmas bonus,
sweetening a prior offer to give them interest-free loans.
   Pittston hired replacements to operate the mines but production
has been well below pre-strike levels, and industry analysts said
it appeared the company has been forced to buy coal to keep up with
its supply commitments.
   Pittston reported that its coal operations lost $3.6 million in
the second quarter of 1989 and $9.8 million in the third, compared
to profits of $9 million and $7.4 million in the respective
quarters of 1988.
</TEXT>

</DOC>