<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1104EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-East-Glance     12-18 0302</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-East-Glance,0324</SECOND>
<HEAD>Latest Developments in Eastern Europe</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a look at major developments in Eastern Europe:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>ROMANIA:</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   A Yugoslav traveler reports two people were killed during
weekend demonstrations against hard-line President Nicolae
Ceausescu, the largest anti-government demonstrations in two years.
   The country closes its border with Yugolavia to all but official
traffic, and security is reported tightened at the Hungarian border
following reports of violent weekend demonstrations.
   Hungarian legislators report tanks patrolling the major Romanian
city of Timisoara and nearby Arad, the sites of demonstrations.
Romanian emigres report further unrest in the city of Brasov, site
of a major uprising in 1987.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>CZECHOSLOVAKIA:</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The Communist Party chief, Karel Urbanek, is quoted as saying
his party will probably try to form a coalition with other leftist
parties before free elections planned next year.
   The party daily, Rude Pravo, prints a front-page apology for
previous articles that attacked such reformers as Vaclav Havel and
Alexander Dubcek.
   Foreign Minister Jiri Dienstbier prepares to travel to Moscow on
Wednesday for discussions on the possible withdrawal from
Czechoslovakia of about 80,000 Soviet troops installed after the
invasion that crushed a 1968 reform movement.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EAST GERMANY:</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The Communists and opposition factions resume talks on the
country's future. Angry protesters demanding a part in the
negotiations disrupt the session's first hour by banging on the
windows and shouting through bullhorns.
   The forum agrees to meet each Monday and opens talks to five
more groups.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>YUGOSLAVIA:</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   About 160,000 workers stage a half-hour ``warning'' strike in
the republic of Montenegro to pressure the Communist government to
adopt urgent measures to contain hyperinflation.
   Premier Ante Markovic proposes the introduction of a new
convertible currency unit at a key parliamentary session that is to
decide an economic and political reform package.
</TEXT>

</DOC>