<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0239 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0502EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-SPE--Bride&amp;Groom:ACateredAffair     12-18 0747</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-SPE--Bride &amp; Groom: A Catered Affair,0758</SECOND>
<HEAD>SPECIAL EDITION</HEAD>
<HEAD>Bride &amp; Groom: A Catered Affair</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY703</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BARBARA MAYER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Newsfeatures</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Offering guests a festive meal after the wedding ceremony is a
way of sharing the happiness of the bride and groom, so part of the
feast reflecting the couple's ethnic backgrounds is appropriate,
says Molly Siple, who with partner Gillie Holme catered the Sunday
afternoon country wedding of Donald and Susan Waite.
   While you do need one dish that virtually everyone will like _
in New York, chicken, turkey or poached salmon fulfill the
requirement _ other selections can be more adventurous. If
ingredients of a particular ethnic favorite are available locally,
professional caterers will enjoy the challenge of preparing these
dishes for your guests, Siple says.
   Food served can take a cue from the season and time of day. Of
course, practical considerations of budget and cooking facilities
also need to be considered in menu planning.
   The menu at the Waites' wedding was dictated by minimal cooking
facilities, the outdoor setting, autumn season and the country
locale.
   Requests for a healthful menu light on saturated fats and sugar
and dishes prepared without alcohol also were taken into
consideration. All these factors made a harvest theme natural, says
Siple.
   The menu included ham, roast turkey and condiments, New England
baked beans, a melange of seasonal squashes and cornbread on the
main buffet table. There were a separate salad station (tomatoes
with basil, marinated mushrooms and greens), a table for cheeses
and fruit and another for the wedding cake.
   The Waites' choices are part of a trend to more healthful fare
and ethnic dishes, according to Modern Bride editor Cele Lalli. The
use of several different buffet stations, making it easy to offer a
variety of dishes and serve a crowd more efficiently, also was
typical, she says.
   Lighter fare, such as a choice of fish, chicken or beef, is
being offered at many weddings around the country. Some invitations
arrive with a request for guests to indicate their main course
preference _ a practice Lalli finds unappealing. It's more gracious
to have the choice made just before the meal, she says.
   One reason for more adventurous menus is that ``more couples now
are actually planning and paying for their own event. As a result,
their tastes and budgets are taken into account,'' says Boyce
Brawley, a partner in the catering firm, New York Parties, and
co-author of a new book of the same name.
   Brawley says that when the couple plan the wedding, they're more
likely to opt for an informal event than their parents might have
been. Younger people prefer an extended cocktail party with finger
foods and passed foods and several serving stations. As a rule,
that's less costly than a sit-down meal, ``but not if you want
everything that you would have had at a dinner,'' says Brawley.
   ``Weddings of this type are not quite so formal and are more
conducive to conversation,'' he says. People have a chance to
circulate. Formalities and traditions of toasting and cake cutting,
however, are observed just as much by the young, he says.
   Late afternoon teas are increasingly popular. ``Since this is
not necessarily a period when parents are paying for the wedding,
the lesser expense of a tea is welcome.''
   Brawley says that mixing ethnic foods with more standard dishes
is becoming more common. If the bride and groom are of different
ethnic backgrounds, it's a practice to serve foods from both
traditions. ``Nothing is wrong with mixing ethnic flavors. After
all, this is a union of two families, and you want to make everyone
feel comfortable. We may even ask the couple for family recipes.''
   Brawley says that while more variety is sought in dishes, a few
foods turn up often. ``Nine times out of ten some form of salmon
will show up, and meats such as lamb, duck and quail are being
ordered far more often. People are ready to experiment.''
   Wedding planner Marcy Blum says the eclectic menu makes for a
more festive party: ``Food becomes part of the entertainment. With
six or seven buffet stations, the party flow works better at a
large wedding,'' she adds.
   Blum, who is based in New York but helps plan weddings in many
areas, says many people prefer to offer fowl rather than red meat.
She agrees that ethnic foods are popular _ and part of a trend
toward ethnicity throughout the event.
</TEXT>

</DOC>