<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0351EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-Homeless     12-26 0558</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Homeless,0577</SECOND>
<HEAD>In Tents and Shelters, Panamanian Refugees Celebrate Christmas</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PAN1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOSEPH B. FRAZIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BALBOA, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Facing an uncertain future, thousands of
people left homeless by the firepower of the U.S. troops who ousted
Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega lined up at a refugee camp for a
Christmas dinner of GI rations.
   President Guillermo Endara and his vice presidents, Ricardo
Arias Calderon and Guillermo Ford, visited the camp Monday for a
Mass celebrated by Archbishop Marcos McGrath five days after the
U.S. invasion.
   Residents swarmed around them, shouting ``Viva Endara!'' and
``Long live the civilian government!'' Endara won May elections
that Noriega annulled.
   Christmas dinners were served in makeshift plastic shelters and
large U.S. Army tents.
   ``We served more than 8,000 meals last night,'' Army Col.
William Connolly said Monday. ``The lines were longer than we or
they would have liked.''
   Many of the refugees, their arms and legs in casts or bandages,
quietly wondered what would happen to them now. They lost their
homes in fighting between Noriega supporters and U.S. forces that
attacked Wednesday to oust the military ruler.
   ``Well, you know, it's a place to stay meanwhile,'' said Pilab
Rios, 40, a store clerk. ``It is safe here and there is food. Of
course I am sad to have my home gone at Christmas, but I have my
life and they say we will leave here in a few weeks.''
   The camp is at Balboa Stadium and High School, just south of
Panama City in the former Canal Zone near the canal administration
building. The U.S. Army has erected 14 large tents and hopes to put
up 14 more.
   Many of the homeless have patched together shelter from what was
available.
   ``There are between 9,000 and 10,000 people here but you don't
see that many now,'' said Connolly, a Boston native.
   ``A lot of them leave during the day to where their homes were
and search for any belongings they can bring back here,'' he said.
``They come back in the evenings. We can estimate the population by
the number of meals we serve.''
   For many, the clothes they have on are all they managed to save.
   The camp is clean and orderly, and Connolly said it has
extensive medical facilities.
   Both the troops and the homeless consider it fortunate that now
is the start of the dry season in Panama, with no torrential rains
expected.
   Organization of the camp has been turned over to Sergio Galvez,
mayor of the Chorrillo district that surrounded Noriega's
Panamanian Defense Forces headquarters. The district was devastated
in the U.S. attack, and most of the camp residents came from there.
   ``I have been talking with presidential advisers and they are
very willing to help rebuild,'' Galvez said. ``We all want to go
back to Chorrillo. We hope the government of President Endara will
solve this problem very quickly.''
   Army Col. Jack Pryor said officials of the U.S. Agency for
International Development are looking into an urban reconstruction
program for Chorrillo.
   Galvez divided the camp into six sectors, based on people's
neighborhoods before their homes were destroyed in the fighting.
   The homeless form orderly lines for Army rations. A few cooked
rice or other staples over small fires. One family opened a small
store with a few cans of food.
</TEXT>

</DOC>