<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0321EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Thornburgh-Gray Bjt   12-30 0705</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Thornburgh-Gray, Bjt,690</SECOND>
<HEAD>No Prosecution, Discipline in Rep. Gray Leak Case</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By W. DALE NELSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Attorney General Dick Thornburgh's decision to
close an internal investigation into a news leak about an FBI probe
of Rep. William H. Gray III's office got a sharp rebuke from Gray
and from Sen. Joseph R. Biden Jr., who says the leak investigation
should continue.
   Thornburgh wrote Biden, the Senate Judiciary Committee chairman,
that investigators had been ``unable to identify with certainty the
original source'' of disclosures to CBS reporter Rita Braver about
Gray's office financial affairs and therefore will not prosecute or
fire anyone.
   The leak occurred at the end of May while Gray, D-Pa., was
seeking election in the House as majority whip, and it prompted
accusations from Democratic lawmakers that Thornburgh's aides were
the source of a political leak.
   Thornburgh said in Friday's letter to Biden, D-Del., that
investigators also told him ``the nature of the confirmations
alleged to have been forthcoming to Ms. Braver'' were ``uncertain.''
   He said he accepted the investigators' conclusion that ``it
would be futile and impossible to pursue a prosecution based on the
available evidence.''
   Therefore, he told Biden, the case would be closed without
prosecution and without firing any department employees.
   Gray said, ``The failure of this investigation raises the white
flag of surrender to those in the Department of Justice who use
false leaks to defame innocent citizens. The leaks in this case
were designed to harm me, but their real victim was the integrity
of our criminal justice system.''
   Biden, meanwhile, said Thornburgh was failing to pursue the
investigation as he had said he would when he testified last June 2
before the Judiciary Committee.
   During that hearing, Biden said in a statement, Thornburgh said
that if his department's criminal division did not turn up enough
evidence for criminal prosecution, the Office of Professional
Responsibility would ``complete the investigation and recommend
appropriate sanctions against those who can be identified.''
   In addition, Biden said that although Thornburgh wrote that he
was told the OPR concurred with the criminal division's decisions,
the Judiciary Committee staff had gotten a different story from OPR.
   ``Although OPR was consulted at various points during the
investigation, it has never seen the criminal division report or
any of its conclusions, and therefore could not have and has not
concurred in those conclusions,'' Biden said. ``Furthermore, it is
also the Judiciary Committee staff's understanding that the
criminal division did not conclude that disciplinary action was
unwarranted.''
   Biden concluded: ``The proper course ... is for OPR now to
determine if any disciplinary action is warranted.''
   Thornburgh's spokesman, David Runkel, said the attorney general
believes the findings do not justify further investigation by the
OPR, and he disputed Biden's contention that OPR had not concurred
in the criminal division's conclusions.
   ``I don't know whom Sen. Biden or his staff has been talking to,
but that statement is clearly at odds with what the attorney
general was told by the criminal division,'' Runkel said.
   OPR chief Michael E. Shaheen does not have a listed telephone
number and could not be reached for comment.
   About two weeks after Ms. Braver's broadcast that the FBI was
conducting a preliminary inquiry into allegations regarding
personnel and expenditures in Gray's office, the Justice Department
stated that Gray was not a target of the investigation and was
cooperating with the probe.
   Gray, who was elected whip, said he had been told by FBI agents
from the Philadelphia office in a Memorial Day interview that they
were looking into the possibility that one of his employees held a
no-show job. Nothing more has been heard of that investigation.
   Thornburgh told Biden that 11 FBI agents devoted approximately
385 days to the investigation, interviewing members of the U.S.
attorney's office in Philadelphia, the Philadelphia division of the
FBI, FBI headquarters, the Criminal Division and the attorney
general's office.
   He said about 30 other persons also were interviewed, including
members of Congress, aides to Gray, confidential sources and
several reporters. Ms. Braver ``declined to be interviewed or
otherwise cooperate with this investigation,'' Thornburgh said.
   Ms. Braver could be not reached for comment. The CBS Washington
bureau said she was on vacation.
</TEXT>

</DOC>