<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0151 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1613EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-FernaldSettlement     12-22 0569</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fernald Settlement,580</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government to Drop Appeal of Nuclear Plant Lawsuit</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Energy Department is dropping its appeal
of a $78 million judgment in a class-action lawsuit filed by
neighbors of an Ohio nuclear weapons plant, but doesn't know how it
will pay the 14,000 plaintiffs, the department's top lawyer said
Friday.
   ``We're not going to pursue our appeal,'' Stephen A. Wakefield
said, adding that ``the bad news'' is that the department
discovered earlier this week it cannot pay the judgment from a fund
it planned to use.
   The historic settlement came when the government, for the first
time, acknowledged that a nuclear weapons plant might have harmed
people living near it.
   The Fernald, Ohio, plant has spread uncounted tons of powdered
uranium dust into the surrounding area. Operations were suspended
earlier this year to intensify efforts to clean up the
contamination.
   Wakefield said verbal notice of the decision was given to the
plaintiffs' lawyers Thursday, but he would not say specifically why
the department changed its mind about the appeal.
   The government had never contested the amount of the judgment,
but appealed because it disagreed with a judicial interpretation of
the terms of the settlement.
   ``We think it's really past time,'' said Lisa Crawford, one of
the plaintiffs who contended in a 1985 lawsuit that releases of
radioactive material from the plant had damaged their property
values and caused them emotional distress.
   ``My question is, when are they going to put the money in the
bank?'' she said.
   In an interview, Wakefield said the Justice Department told him
earlier this week that he could not pay the $78 million from a
federal contingency fund as planned because the lawsuit was brought
not against the government but against National Lead of Ohio Inc.,
which ran the plant under federal contract until 1985.
   The Energy Department was required under terms of the operating
contract to shield National Lead against liability in the case.
   Wakefield said the department would have to ask Congress for a
special appropriation to cover the settlement and that payments
probably would be made in installments.
   ``That's terrible,'' said Paul Nemann, one of three
court-appointed trustees overseeing the settlement.
   He said the department's lawyers had said ``in no uncertain
terms'' at the time of the settlement last summer that the money
would be available by October. The department filed a notice of
appeal Oct. 17.
   Stanley Chesley, the lead lawyer for Fernald residents,
applauded the Energy Department's decision to abandon its appeal.
   ``That's encouraging. We'd like to work with them and get the
money,'' he said.
   The settlement clears the way for federal funds to pay for
long-term medical monitoring of the health of people living within
five miles of the Feed Materials Production Center at Fernald,
which processes uranium for the weapons program.
   The purpose of the medical study is to determine whether there
was an excess of cancers or other health problems that could be
traced to radiation released from the plant, which has operated for
38 years. It is 18 miles from Cincinnati.
   The department appealed the settlement to the 6th U.S. Circuit
Court of Appeals in Cincinnati because U.S. District Judge S.
Arthur Spiegel ruled in September that the deal did not prevent two
companies near the site from suing the department for environmental
damage to their property caused by the weapons plant.
</TEXT>

</DOC>