<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1306EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romanian-Diplomats     12-27 0548</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romanian-Diplomats,0566</SECOND>
<HEAD>British Diplomats Joined Romanian Revolt</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   British diplomats to Romania said they ran into
the streets and shouted rebellious slogans during the revolt
against Nicolae Ceausescu, and some envoys even joined a crowd that
stormed the television station.
   ``We were cheering with them and shouting `Down with Ceausescu.'
We were Romanians to all intents and purposes,'' said army Lt. Mike
Brown, an assistant defense attache.
   Fifteen members of the British Embassy in Bucharest and their
families arrived at London's Heathrow airport Tuesday night after
leaving Romania.
   The Foreign Office said Wednesday it had ``no problems'' with
Brown's actions in Bucharest.
   A spokesman, who was not identified in accordance with British
practice, said: ``As he made clear, he joined the crowd in order to
be able to report developments. If he had not shown some degree of
enthusiasm the crowd might have asked who he was. There were
concerns in the crowd about the activities of the security forces.''
   Brown, 40, said he went into the streets with the embassy second
secretary, Susan Laffey, to observe the uprising.
   ``We worked as a team out on the streets for a considerable
time. The most remembered part for me was when we joined in with
the students to take the television station,'' Brown said.
   ``We went along with them. We went along with the armored
personnel carriers they had captured, bedecked with civilians,
flags, flowers and Christmas trees.
   ``We drove to the television building, went through the building
and through the forbidden zone and stormed the building with them.''
   Brown said it was the diplomats' job to observe the situation
and they were ``taken along with it all.''
   ``We were swept away by the emotion of it all. It was very
exciting and we felt part of the events unfolding on the streets,''
said Miss Laffey, 28.
   When asked if he felt his action violated his diplomatic role,
Brown replied: ``I don't think we took part in it. We went along as
fairly passive observers and I think that was our job. If we hadn't
cheered and shouted slogans there might have been queries as to who
we were.''
   Brown said on another occasion he and the defense attache had
driven on an armored personnel carrier to the scene of an attack
and went through so much blood in the streets they thought it was
water.
   ``I think there was an orgy of killing,'' Brown said.
   Brown said the British diplomats worked in four groups of pairs
observing activities.
   ``I don't think any of us had come away unscathed,'' he said.
``It will certainly be on my mind for the rest of my life. I feel
tremendous affiliation with the Romanian people.
   ``They have changed from being a nation of people who walk down
the streets with their heads down. Now they are happy, they read
newspapers in the streets and have smiles on their faces.''
   Veronica Atkinson, wife of British Ambassador Michael Atkinson,
who has remained in Bucharest, said she hid in the basement of the
embassy residence when one of the security policemen fighting the
army was on the premises.
   ``We were terrified. We feared for our lives. Had we made any
noise we would probably have been killed,'' she said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>