<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 1912EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-PanamaAID     12-31 0274</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama AID,250</SECOND>
<HEAD>RETRANSMIT a0718 to fix format of summary line</HEAD>
<HEAD>Non-Profit Corporation Formed To Channel Aid to Panama</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A non-profit corporation has been formed to
channel medical supplies and other emergency contributions to
Panama, where fighting left thousands homeless and many wounded, an
official said Sunday.
   ``AID To Panama'' has been designated as the official
organization to receive funds and other contributions, said Carlos
F. Rodriguez, Panama's newly appointed ambassador to the United
States.
   ``Our task of rebuilding our beloved country has begun,'' said
Rodriguez in a statement. ``However, urgent humanitarian needs are
still unmet and all help is needed. We appreciate all offers of
assistance from our American friends.''
   Rodriguez said the need is greatest in Panama City, where a week
of fighting has left an estimated 25,000 people homeless and care
for the many wounded is urgent. Hospitals face dire shortages of
all medical supplies, he said.
   Dr. Jose Trinidad Castillero, Panama's minister of health, has
issued an urgent appeal for intravenous solutions, antibiotics,
insulin, and anaesthetics. The shortage of blood is so severe, that
doctors at Santo Tomas Hospital donated their own blood, Rodriguez
said.
   ``AID to Panama'' is working with Catholic Relief Services and
Direct Relief International, two groups organized to respond to
international health care needs. Corporate donations of supplies
and transportation already have been received but Rodriguez said
individual cash donations are urgently needed.
   Checks and other contributions should be made to ``AID To
Panama'' and sent to either:
   Catholic Relief Services, 209 W. Fayette Street, Baltimore,
21202; or, ``AID To Panama'' Sun Bank (Acct. No. 01-890-0114-0297),
777 Brickell Ave., Miami, Fla. 33131.
</TEXT>

</DOC>