<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0264 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1506EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Coca-ColaAd Bjt   12-22 0670</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Coca-Cola Ad, Bjt,0689</SECOND>
<HEAD>Coke's Admakers Went on Detective Hunt for ``Hilltop'' Reunion Ad</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SKIP WOLLENBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nearly 20 years ago, Linda Higson was working as
a teen-age nanny in Italy when she was talked into playing a
featured role in a Coca-Cola commercial that showed dozens of young
people singing on a hilltop.
   ``I'd like to buy the world a home and furnish it with love,''
the 19-year-old, blonde-haired Briton sang to open the 1971 Coke
commercial that became an industry classic.
   The ad led to some minor modeling jobs for Miss Higson, but she
eventually went home to a catering business in England, got married
and had four children.
   Early next year, television viewers are going to see her again,
this time with her 10-year-old daughter Kelly, in prominent roles
in a new version of the ad that reunites about 25 original cast
members and includes dozens of children.
   Coca-Cola has been revving up the publicity machinery in recent
weeks to stoke interest in the reunion ad that debuts Jan. 28 on
the CBS telecast of the Super Bowl, the National Football League's
championship game that usually draws a huge audience.
   The company recently flew the former Miss Higson, now 38 years
old and known as Mrs. Neary, and Stephanie Roos, another original
cast member now living in Indianapolis, to New York to talk with
reporters about the commercial.
   In one illustration of how much has changed since the first ad
was shot, the two women said they had each rejected an offer of a
flat fee for the new commercial and chose a compensation plan tied
to how often the commercial runs.
   They each declined to say how much the onetime buyout offer was
worth, and noted they were gambling that the new commercial would
be a hit in deciding to take a pay plan linked to air time.
   For the original ad, they had each been happy to get the flat
fee of about $50 and did not get any residuals based on how often
it ran.
   ``The first one was shown so much I said, `I wish I had a penny
for every time it was shown,''' Mrs. Roos said.
   The Atlanta-based Coca-Cola and its ad agency McCann-Erickson
had to do some detective work to locate original cast members for
the new commercial, which was shot on the same hill near Rome as
the original ad.
   McCann got a break when a box was found in its New York office
full of photos and ID's for some of the original cast. But many of
them had long since moved from Rome, and several women had new last
names by marriage.
   The search for the former Miss Higson was complicated by the
fact that her name had been listed as ``Hipson.'' A detective
agency was hired to search Great Britain for a woman with that last
name to no avail.
   As the shooting date approached last fall, the agency took out a
classified ad in several widely-circulated English language
newspapers in Europe.
   ``Linda Hipson, where are you? If you're the Linda Hipson who
was in a Coca-Cola commercial 20 years ago, please call (a
McCann-Erickson telephone number in New York). We'd love to hear
you sing again,'' the ad said.
   The former Miss Higson _ Mrs. Neary _ missed the ad, but a
friend spotted it while reading the International Herald Tribune in
the Stockholm airport. He contacted Mrs. Neary, who called the ad
agency and agreed to go to Rome for the reunion.
   Altogether, about 25 of the 40 principals in the original ad
appear in the new version, said McCann-Erickson executive Paul
Cappelli.
   Mrs. Neary said teaching the world to sing again ``in perfect
harmony'' _ this time with her daughter _ was an interesting
diversion from her routine.
   ``It's like being picked up out of your life and if you are a
housewife, it's a little like Cinderella, don't you think?'' Mrs.
Neary said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>