<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0111 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1556EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-Panama-Smithsonian 1stLd-Writethru a0630elowerhouseandcompletecontrolinTrenton.
12-21 0284</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Smithsonian, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0630,290</SECOND>
<HEAD>Smithsonian Employees Reported Free</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Updates in top 4 grafs with Bush saying employees are free,
picks up 3rd graf pvs, The 11</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush said today 11 people said to
have been abducted by Panamanian troops from a Smithsonian research
facility are free, though officials said the group is still waiting
to be picked up by American forces.
   Bush, speaking at a news conference, said the Smithsonian people
``have now been released.'' He said, however, he had no idea how
many other Americans were being held hostage in the Central
American country.
   Bill Schulz, a spokesman for the Smithsonian, confirmed Bush's
statement, but said the group is still at an undisclosed location.
   ``As far as we know they are not being held by anyone,'' he
said. ``They are waiting to be picked up,'' he added.
   The 11, all scientists and technicians associated with the
Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute in Panama, were abducted by
armed troops Wednesday after the U.S. invasion of the country.
   The group _ five Americans, five Panamanians and one Venezuelan
_ was on the Sanblas chain of islands off the Panamanian coast.
They were performing marine research on the coral reef.
   Madelaine Jacobs, a Smithsonian spokeswoman, had earlier refused
to identify members of the group. But she said only one American
worked for the Smithsonian. The others were affiliated with
universities or research operations.
   Members of the group had access to a radio that enabled them to
contact Smithsonian employee and the headquarters at Panama City,
the tropical institute has several other stations throughout the
isthmus. Most of the staff members, 120 of whom work full time, are
Americans and Panamanians.
</TEXT>

</DOC>