<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2350EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Salvador-Christmas     12-18 0606</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Salvador-Christmas,0626</SECOND>
<HEAD>Christmas Cheer Scarce in Ravaged Neighborhood</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Tuesday AMs report.</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DOUGLAS GRANT MINE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SOYAPANGO, El Salvador (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Glad tidings and signs of peace on
Earth are scant among the bullet- and rocket-pocked facades of the
humble homes of Conacaste.
   The family of Elpidio Verdugo set up a 3-foot artificial
Christmas tree and draped it with a string of tiny lights that
hardly ever twinkle because the electricity is on only a couple
hours a day.
   There are no presents beneath the tree and Verdugo's wife,
Gloria, doubts there will be.
   ``The country is in mourning,'' Verdugo said.
   The 45-year-old bank teller, his wife and their four teenage
children spent the better part of three days last month huddled
beneath mattresses draped over tables in the kitchen-living room of
their cinderblock house.
   Outside, the crack of fire from assault rifles and machine-guns
filled Alley 6. An acrid gauze of gunsmoke reduced visibility to 15
feet, streamed through the shattered windows and seeped through
cracks where the mattresses overlapped, stinging eyes and giving
the terrified family even more reason to cry.
   The Verdugos' neighborhood of Conacaste in Soyapango, just east
of San Salvador, was the most devastated of several working-class
districts ravaged by fierce combat last month in and around the
nation's capital.
   A guerrilla offensive launched Nov. 11 killed up to 2,000 people
and was the biggest push of a 10-year-old civil war between leftist
rebels and a succession of U.S.-backed governments.
   The Verdugos finally were able to evacuate by climbing over the
rear wall on Nov. 15. They returned after a week of refuge at the
nearby psychiatric hospital to find their home a shambles.
   The roof of the bedroom of 16-year-old son, Stanley, was blown
to bits by either a rocket-propelled grenade or a rocket fired by a
helicopter. A crater surrounded by a whorl of black marks the point
of impact on the white wall.
   The corrugated synthetic tile roofing sheet has been replaced
with cardboard, the same material covering Stanley's bedsprings.
   ``The mattresses were burned up or torn to shreds,'' said Mrs.
Verdugo.
   The yellow refrigerator has a bullet hole in the side, patched
with cloth and tape so the refrigerant doesn't leak. Two kitchen
chairs sprout foam rubber stuffing where bullets ripped through
them.
   Verdugo estimated the damage at about $600, six months of his
salary. The family has no savings.
   Officials of a government housing fund visited to evaluate
damage. They promised money to help reconstruct.
   ``But they also promised help to repair damages from the (1986)
earthquake, and that never came,'' said the father.
   ``We'll do what we can to celebrate the arrival of the Christ
child,'' said Mrs. Verdugo. She plans to prepare turkey or chicken,
pastries and homemade candies for visits of friends and relatives
on Christmas Eve and Christmas Day.
   ``Even amid so much poverty, there's always the joy of
Christmas. We've always got faith, and the hope that this won't
happen again,'' she said.
   Xiomara, the 13-year-old daughter, said she had been hoping to
receive a new dress or some other gift at Christmas. ``But I
understand why there won't be presents this year. And it doesn't
matter, really.''
   Mrs. Verdugo said she does not entertain illusions that the
Christmas spirit of good will toward men might somehow foster peace.
   ``In a moment of anguish, like in the middle of the battle,
people accept Christ in their heart. But then when things calm
down, they forget. For there to be peace, Christ has to be in
people's hearts all the time,'' she said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>