<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0165 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1547EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-BingoSuicide     12-20 0329</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bingo Suicide,0341</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tenn Secretary of State Dies of Self-Inflicted Gunshot Wound</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BILL RAWLINS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tennessee's secretary of state, whose
office has been at the center of a bingo and political corruption
scandal, died today, more than a week after shooting himself in the
head.
   Gentry Crowell, 57, died at Vanderbilt University Medical
Center, said hospital spokesman Wayne Hood. The one-time
legislative power broker shot himself Dec. 12 in a suicide attempt
on the front porch of his Lebanon home.
   As secretary of state, he was in charge of regulating bingo and
spending by lobbyists and political campaigns, all of which were
involved in a federal-state investigation that has resulted in 22
people being indicted or pleading guilty since January.
   Crowell testified in September and November before federal grand
juries investigating bingo corruption in Tennessee. He said he was
told by federal agents that he was not a target of the
investigation.
   Last week, however, the Nashville Banner quoted unidentified
sources as saying that federal investigaors were focusing on how
Crowell solicited campaign money from architects, engineers and
bingo operators.
   As a result of the probe one former Crowell aide, former chief
bingo inspector W.D. ``Donnie'' Walker, has gone to federal prison
for offenses incliding including extorting payoffs from bingo
operators; his longtime administrative assistant and secretary,
Mary Sue Wright, has been named an unindicted co-conspirator. She
admitted taking thousands of dollars from a campaign fund.
   Controversy, much of it growing out of Crowell's passionate
devotion to the Democratic Party, followed him during most of his
18 years in state government.
   He was once known as The Godfather on Capitol Hill because of
his absolute, partisan control over legislation in the dual roles
of chairman of the House Democratic Caucus and House Calendar
Committee.
   The secretary of state's office had regulated charitable bingo
since it was legalized for charity fund-raising in 1971. In 1989
the state Supreme Court ruled bingo unconstitutional.
</TEXT>

</DOC>