<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0152 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2037EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Jordan-PLO 1stLd-Writethru a0717 12-19 0666</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jordan-PLO, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0717,0685</SECOND>
<HEAD>Arafat in Jordan For Mideast Talks; Jordan Lifts Martial Law</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: ADDS 6 grafs with background on martial law being lifted. ADDS
byline.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMAL HALABY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AMMAN, Jordan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Yasser Arafat, chairman of the Palestine
Liberation Organization, came to Jordan Tuesday for talks on the
proposal by U.S. Secretary of State James A. Baker III for direct
Palestinian-Israeli negotiations.
   His two-day visit coincided with Prime Minister Mudar Badran's
announcement that Jordan was lifting martial law imposed 22 years
ago after Israel captured the West Bank from Jordan in the 1967 war.
   ``I will brief King Hussein on all that concerns our central
issue, the Palestinian issue ... and developments on the
Palestinian, Arab and international arenas because we are in one
trench,'' Arafat told reporters.
   ``Our relationship with Jordan is beyond the level of
coordination. ... We are one family and it gives me pleasure to
come to Jordan at anytime.''
   Badran and other Cabinet members met Arafat at the airport and
all drove to the Guest Palace, where Hussein was expected to join
them for talks.
   Arafat adviser Bassam Abu Sharif told The Associated Press the
talks will focus on ``concentrated efforts to open a
Palestinian-Israeli dialogue'' in Cairo and deal with ``Israeli
deviousness which tries to dampen and control all efforts for a
peaceful political solution to the Palestinian problem.''
   Baker proposed in October that the meetings between Palestinian
and Israeli delegations focus on Israeli Prime Minister Yitzhak
Shamir's election plan for the occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip.
   The election is part of a wider plan for a limited self-rule for
1.7 million Palestinians living under occupation. The Palestinians
have been waging a bloody insurrection in the occupied lands since
Dec. 8, 1987.
   The PLO says it must name the Palestinian delegation and the
agenda must be open to all topics.
   Israel regards the PLO as a terrorist organization and rejects
any direct or indirect PLO involvement.
   Badran affirmed Jordan's support for the Palestinians saying:
``We in Jordan are all Palestinians when it comes to the
Palestinian issue.''
   ``We support all the efforts of the PLO because they work for
the benefit of the Palestinian cause.''
   In July 1988, Hussein renounced sovereignty over the West Bank,
turning over reponsibility to the PLO.
   More than half of Jordan's population of 3 million is of
Palestinian origin, and Badran is known for close ties with the PLO.
   In Tunis, the Tunisian capital where the PLO is headquartered,
the organization published a statement at the end of a three-day
leadership meeting which said, ``The United States' unlimited
support for the Israeli leadership is hampering the peace process
in the Middle East region.''
   But it said it was ready to open a dialogue with the Israelis on
the basis of principles laid down in Baghdad in October at the last
meeting of the PLO Central Council _ the PLO's right to pick
members of the Palestinian delegation and following the Cairo talks
with ``an international conference on peace in the Middle East with
the participation of Egypt and Sweden.''
   The lifting of martial law was the latest in a series of moves
by Prime Minister Badran and Hussein aimed at liberalizing
Jordanian society.
   Badran also promised to crack down on corruption among public
officials, and criticized former governments for deficit spending
that swelled Jordan's $8.3 billion foreign debt.
   The newly elected, 80-member legislature adjourned after hearing
the policy statement, and a vote of confidence was set for Dec. 30.
   Badran's 23-member Cabinet, which he formed Dec. 6, needs 41
votes to be installed. Otherwise, Hussein will have to appoint a
new prime minister.
   Most candidates in last month's general elections had called for
the lifting of martial law, under which authorities can close
newspapers at any time, effectively inhibiting free criticism of
officials.
   Martial law also banned large public meetings, provided for
special courts and allowed authorities to interfere in private
business dealings and control bank transactions.
</TEXT>

</DOC>