<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 2159EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RollingStones     12-17 0432</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rolling Stones,0448</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rock 'N' Roll's Bad Boys Open Three-Night Show In Atlantic City</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Axl cq in 14th graf</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HENRY STERN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTIC CITY, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Rolling Stones' North American
tour ends here with the fortyish band taking fans through a
three-night medley of rock 'n' roll history from 1965's
``Satisfaction'' to 1989's ``Rock and a Hard Place.''
   The Stones opened Sunday night in 16,000-seat Convention Hall,
and were to play there Tuesday and Wednesday nights in their first
indoor concerts of the four-month, 32-city ``Steel Wheels'' tour.
   At a news conference before the concert Sunday, guitarist Keith
Richards said he was satisfied with the road show, but expecting a
bit of a letdown.
   ``I'm always sorry to see the tour end,'' the unshaven Richards
said. ``When I'm lying in bed, the body is saying, `Where's the
gig?'''
   Tickets sold for $38.50, $150 and $250. The show will also be on
pay-per-view TV Tuesday for $19.95 and $24.95, depending on the
cable company.
   Asked whether ticket prices to see the show in person were too
high, Richards shrugged and said, ``You can't justify it.''
   The group started performing together in 1962. Lead singer Mick
Jagger is 46 years old, Richards will be 46 on Monday, bassist Bill
Wyman is 53 and drummer Charlie Watts is 48. Guitarist Ron Wood,
who joined the Stones in 1975, is 42.
   Outside the entrance to Convention Hall, vendors did a brisk
business selling everything from $3 pins to $450 leather jackets
bearing the Stones' trademark tongue emerging from ruby-red lips.
   Laura Stevens, who drove with a friend from Virginia, said the
four-hour trip and $100 scalper tickets for $38.50 seats were worth
it.
   ``It's our last chance to see them,'' said Ms. Stevens, 19, of
McLean, Va.
   Miyano Daisuke, 21, of Tokyo topped the two Virginians in
dedication and deep pockets.
   Daisuke, pulling out his round-trip plane ticket from Tokyo,
said he and nine friends had bought $150 tickets for all three
shows from a broker in Japan.
   ``They're very famous in Japan,'' Daisuke said. ``Every Japanese
guitarist plays the same as Keith Richards.''
   Guests expected to appear with the Stones Tuesday include
guitarists Eric Clapton and John Lee Hooker, as well as vocalist
Axl Rose and guitarist Izzy Stradlin of the group Guns 'N Roses.
   Guns 'N Roses has been criticized for lyrics offensive to
blacks, homosexuals and immigrants.
   But Jagger dismissed a question about whether he was concerned
about appearing with the group.
   ``We're trying to appeal to the black, gay market,'' he said
with a laugh.
</TEXT>

</DOC>