<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0085 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1030EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-ColdRdp 1stLd-Writethru a0510 12-22 0971</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Cold Rdp, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0510,0995</SECOND>
<HEAD>Deadly Cold Continues: `Not a Fit Night Out for Man or Beast'</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 14 grafs to UPDATE with morning record lows, power
outages, cutbacks, snow in Houston, other details, remove outdated material.
Picks up 9th graf, `Natural gas...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto DC1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARTHUR ALLEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A record-breaking cold snap caused power outages today in at
least three states, posed perils for the citrus industry and
threatened the lives of the homeless and impoverished elderly from
the Rockies to the East Coast.
   Thursday night, the longest of the year, was ``one not fit for
man or beast,'' said Hugh Crowther of the National Weather Service
in Kansas City.
   Temperatures sank even lower today _ the first full day of
winter _ following a day that saw wind chill readings of 89 degrees
below zero at Dickinson, N.D., the mercury steady at 40 below at
noon in Havre, Mont., and temperatures about zero as far south as
Tennessee and Alabama.
   Record lows set this morning included 29 below at Rapid City,
S.D., 13 below at Syracuse, N.Y., and 3 below in Memphis, Tenn.
   Light snow was falling in Houston this morning for the first
time since January 1985.
   Thousands were without power today in Texas, West Virginia and
Ohio.
   The weather service was predicting bone-chilling weather at
least until Sunday.
   As for a white Christmas, ``We've got it already,'' said John
Hart of the weather service in West Virginia, where wind-chill
readings reached 40 below early today and the snow was squeaky dry
underfoot. ``It's certainly not going anywhere.''
   Storm systems had dumped up to 1{ feet of snow early today
across the Great Lakes from Indiana to upstate New York. The cold
was forcing homeless into packed shelters and was blamed for more
than 50 deaths.
   Oil companies said Thursday that the cold had drained heating
oil supplies, causing temporary shortages in some areas of the
Northeast and driving up prices. Exxon USA, Mobil Corp. and Star
Enterprise, a Texaco Inc. affiliate, reported temporary oil
depletions at their terminals.
   Utilities in several states reported record demands for power.
Most of the power outages reported were caused by system overloads
from the increased demand or cold-related equipment failure.
   In Texas, an estimated 12,500 homes were without electricity in
the Fort Worth area early today because of such demand, and a TU
Electric spokesman predicted it would take several hours to restore
power. The temperature dropped to 5 and the wind chill index was
minus 26 at the time of the outage.
   About 10,000 customers in Kentucky, 2,300 in several Ohio
counties and about 500 in the Charleston, W.Va., area lost power at
least temporarily, utilities spokesmen said.
   Potomac Electric Power Co., which serves the District of
Columbia and the Maryland suburbs, cut voltage by 5 percent this
morning due to extremely heavy demand, said spokesman Tom Welle.
   Natural gas and electricity delivery problems were reported in
Missouri and Texas.
   The National Weather Service predicted a possible repeat of the
killer freeze of December 1983, which destroyed the citrus crop in
the Rio Grande Valley and parts of Louisiana.
   If the predicted freeze today through Sunday is as bad as 1983,
citrus growers ``will suffer the same consequences _ go broke,''
said Jerry Walzel of the Texas Citrus and Vegetable Association.
   ``When it gets down below 20, (citrus trees) just explode _
they're evergreen trees and are full of water, and they split,''
Walzel said. ``You can actually hear it _ it sounds like a .30-.30
rifle cracking.''
   About a third of the $30 million crop was picked, and the
weather service urged farmers to pick as much as they could
Thursday.
   The cold front brought snow early today to the mountains of
northern Georgia, and record lows Thursday of 12 below in Kansas
City and 22 below in Sault Ste. Marie, Mich., where an 18-foot deep
wall of brash _ broken ice left by passing ships _ mired the
Canadian freighter Travailleur in the St. Marys River.
   On a day where the mercury rarely reached zero, those
unfortunate enough to be working outside had to devise tricks to
save extremities from frostbite.
   ``We rotate,'' said Rick Kiolbasa, an assistant manager for
Cablevision In Lincoln, Neb., where the cold knocked out service to
20,000 households. ``There are three guys in the truck. One guy
goes out for five minutes, gets cold, and then the next guy goes
out.''
   Bad as it was to work outside, it was worse to be living there.
   In New York City, where an estimated 80,000 people live on the
streets, 9,140 people were in the city's shelters Thursday morning,
up 1,200 over last year at this time, officials said.
   At least 15 weather-related deaths have been reported in Chicago
since the cold snap began, according to the Cook County Coroner's
office.
   Some homeless were itching for a fight so they could be jailed
through the worst of the cold.
   ``It's pretty typical this time of year for homeless and needy
people to act intentionally _ or unintentionally _ so they can be
locked up,'' said Dale Davis, executive director of the Michigan
Sheriff's Association.
   But Michigan jails are too crowded for inmates who aren't
dangerous, Davis said, so most of the idlers are held only briefly.
``If we can get them shelter elsewhere, we will,'' he said.
   The Christmas holiday came early in Nebraska, Kansas, Missouri,
North Dakota, New York, Iowa and Minnesota, where schools were
closed Thursday by officials worried at the thought of youngsters
waiting for buses that might break down in the cold.
   In Farmington, Maine, hundreds of townsfolk _ most wearing
earmuffs _ turned out to celebrate Chester Greenwood Day, in honor
of the man said to have created the muffs in 1873.
</TEXT>

</DOC>