<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0215EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-AviationSecurity     12-19 0610</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Aviation Security,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Senator D'Amato Says FAA Covered Up Knowledge of Terrorism Warnings</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID BRISCOE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A senator on the presidential commission
investigating air terrorism is accusing Federal Aviation
Administration officials of covering up knowledge of terrorism
warnings posted only for government employees.
   Sen. Alfonse D'Amato, R-N.Y., lashed out the FAA during a
commission hearing Monday, saying they've ``flunked'' in protecting
air passengers.
   At the second hearing of the President's Commission on Aviation
Security and Terrorism, D'Amato produced a cable showing the FAA
knew of warnings issued to U.S. Embassy employees in Moscow prior
to the Dec. 21, 1988, bombing of Pan Am Flight 103 over Lockerbie,
Scotland, which killed 270 people.
   State Department and FAA officials say posting of the terrorist
alert in Moscow on Dec. 13 was an error which went against a policy
of not warning government officials without issuing general public
warnings of a terrorist threat.
   D'Amato, one of seven members of the commission looking into the
Flight 103 bombing and air terrorism issues, praised embassy
officials in Moscow for posting the warning.
   ``Thank God the ambassador published it because he saved some
lives,'' D'Amato said.
   FAA security director Raymond Salazar said it has never been
shown that any embassy personnel canceled reservations on Flight
103 because of the warning.
   ``You either are incredibly incompetent or you covered up,''
D'Amato told Salazar, who said he could not recall seeing the Dec.
13 message from Moscow until a copy was sent two months after the
Dec. 21 bombing.
   The cable acknowledged receipt of an FAA advisory of a threat
against Pan Am flights between Frankfurt and New York, which U.S.
officials later said proved to be a hoax even though the threat fit
details of the Pan Am bombing. Flight 103 began with a different
plane in Frankfurt and was en route from London to New York when it
blew up.
   ``Since a number of people from this post will be flying out of
Frankfurt in the next two weeks,'' the cable said, ``post plans to
issue an internal administrative notice warning employees of the
threat.... No recommendation will be made as to course of action to
be followed by travelers.''
   Monte Belger, FAA associate administrator, said the agency did
nothing to stop the embassy from warning government employees even
though such a selective warning is against government policy.
   Belger told the commission that, in retrospect, he wishes that
someone in the FAA had focused on the message and called the State
Department to stop the posting of the warning, ``but we didn't.''
   FAA senior intelligence analyst Claude Manno, who acknowledged
receiving the original message on Dec. 13, said he ``probably
shredded it.''
   D'Amato said studies by the General Accounting Office indicate
that ``the FAA and the present system have flunked when it comes to
providing basic security systems that anyone can have confidence
in.''
   Transportation Secretary Samuel Skinner, in an interview on
Cable News Network, denied the assertion, saying, ``The FAA has
done a very good job in implementing a number of programs in the
last year to enhance our protection.''
   Skinner noted a program to install sophisticated bomb detection
equipment at key airports, fines against airlines for security
lapses and new FAA personnel added to foreign posts.
   D'Amato said problems with the FAA suggest there may be a
conflict between its role of promoting aviation and that of
ensuring passenger safety.
   The GAO report said stepped-up security measurers since the
disaster may be ineffective at high-risk foreign airports due to a
lack of training standards.
   Earlier reports found problems with passenger screening, airport
security controls and security inspections.
</TEXT>

</DOC>