<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0190 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1818EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania 2ndLd-Writethru a0811 12-20 0969</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0811,0997</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romania Declares State of Emergency in Timisoara Region</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 9 grafs with more Ceausescu quotes; picks up 9th,
`Few foreigners'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALISON SMALE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Romania declared a state of emergency
Wednesday in the western region around Timisoara, where security
forces may have killed thousands of people in crushing
anti-government protests.
   Tens of thousands marched through the city to demand the bodies
of protesters, chanting ``Give us our dead!''
   Reports said protests of President Nicolae Ceausescu's iron rule
had spread to at least eight more cities since the bloody weekend
at Timisoara, which is in Transylvania only 30 miles from the
Yugoslav and Hungarian borders and about 500 miles from the capital
Bucharest.
   Ceausescu, the last autocrat in the Soviet bloc, declared the
emergency hours after returning from a three-day state visit to
Iran, Romanian state radio reported.
   It said an 11 p.m. curfew in the city of 350,000 and surrounding
region applied to everyone except workers on factory night shifts
and banned gatherings of five or more people.
   Soldiers, police and members of special militias were placed on
alert, the radio said, without specifying what that meant.
   In a broadcast speech earlier, Ceausescu ignored international
condemnation and said fascists and foreigners were fomenting unrest
in his Stalinist land.
   He said soldiers fired warning shots Sunday in Timisoara when
threatened by ``hooligan elements,'' but did not mention casualties.
   ``The military units ... were compelled to defend themselves,''
he said, but were ``very patient'' and ``did not respond, even when
soldiers and officers were hit.''
   Few foreigners and no journalists could get into Romania.
Reporters already there, including those from allied nations, were
not allowed to travel freely.
   Eastern European reporters who tried to reach Timisoara from
Bucharest were turned back 30 miles away, the Soviet, Yugoslav and
East German news agencies reported.
   Timisoara remained inaccessible to foreign travelers and
telephone callers Wednesday. It also was impossible to telephone
Bucharest from Vienna.
   A Yugoslav trucker said he saw graffiti daubed on walls in a
Timisoara suburb early Wednesday, calling for ``an uprising ...
against the Ceausescu regime on Dec. 24.'' He reported sporadic
gunfire and from the direction of downtown Timisoara.
   A Pole who reached Budapest, Hungary, from Timisoara on
Wednesday told the daily Mai Nap it was ``like a city under siege.
I saw them tossing dead into the river. People told me over 1,000
people were killed.''
   Dispatches from the Yugoslav and Hungarian news agencies said
Timisoara was full of police and soldiers Wednesday, but that
50,000 people went into the streets nonetheless. Western
businessmen who crossed into Yugoslavia said Wednesday's protest
began at a factory in the morning.
   The businessmen said the people went to a stadium where they
apparently believed authorities were keeping the bodies, chanting
``Give us our dead!''
   No police intervention was reported by the businessmen or the
Yugoslav news agency Tanjug, which quoted the Yugoslav consul
general in Timisoara. MTI, the Hungarian news agency, said some
soldiers joined the demonstrators in chanting slogans against
Ceausescu.
   In a dispatch quoting Romanians working in East Germany, the
official East German agency ADN said unrest had spread to at least
eight other Romanian cities and the death toll in Timisoara could
reach 3,000 or 4,000.
   Casualty estimates have risen daily since Sunday. No independent
confirmation is possible because of Romania's isolation.
   Large numbers of soldiers and police were reported in the
streets of Bucharest and other major cities, according to a
Hungarian who telephoned five cities, and dispatches from Eastern
European journalists in the Romanian capital.
   Mihnea Berindei, Paris spokesman for a group called Defense of
Human Rights in Romania, said some policemen entered hospitals to
arrest wounded protesters. Belgrade radio said police burst into
the Yugoslav consulate, the only diplomatic building in Timisoara,
and seized demonstrators who took refuge there.
   Yugoslavia's Foreign Ministry would not confirm or deny the
incident, which would be a violation of diplomatic conventions.
   In a report from the Yugoslav border with Romania, Tanjug said
there was no more room in Timisoara hospitals.
   The Hungarian Red Cross appealed for international help in
searching for victims of the crackdown.
   Ceausescu, who has ruled Romania since 1965, delivered a
25-minute broadcast address after his return home, with his entire
government and wife Elena, the second most powerful person in
Romania, lined up behind him.
   He sought to blame Hungary, which he has accused of wanting to
reclaim Transylvania, where most of Romania's 1.7 million ethnic
Hungarians live. Hungary ruled the region for centuries, but it was
given to Romania in 1920 by the Treaty of Trianon.
   Foreign Minister Gyula Horn said earlier that Hungary was not
involved in the unrest.
   In his speech, the 71-year-old Romanian leader blamed the
trouble on fascists cooperating with ``reactionary, imperialist
circles and espionage centers.''
   ``The aim of these anti-national, provocative actions was to
provoke disorder and to create the conditions for the territoral
dismemberment of Romania, of its independence and sovereignty,'' he
declared.
   Ceausescu has governed with increasing harshness in recent
years. He has ignored international criticism of his human rights
policies and enforcing industrialization and debt repayment
programs that caused rationing and other hardships.
   Because none of his remarks dealt with those problems, which
have created widespread discontent, it appears he will continue to
rely on the army and legions of uniformed and secret police to
perpetuate his regime.
   Tanjug reported from Bucharest, quoting unofficial sources, that
``a state of full alert has been introduced across Romania as
protests and unrest continue in Timisoara and other towns.''
   ADN said unrest had spread to the other Transylvanian cities of
Brasov, scene of a large anti-government protest in 1987; Cluj, and
Sibiu, to the Black Sea port of Constanta and at least four other
cities.
</TEXT>

</DOC>