<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1106EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-SEALTeams     12-22 0477</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-SEAL Teams,0489</SECOND>
<HEAD>SEAL Members Died While Capturing Panamanian Airfield</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NORFOLK, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four Navy SEAL members whose bodies were the
first to return home from Panama died while capturing an airfield,
Pentagon officials said.
   The men were part of an assault against an airfield used by
ousted Panamanian dictator Gen. Manuel Noriega, said Lt. Gen. Tom
Kelly, director of operations for the Joint Chiefs of Staff. U.S.
intelligence had feared Noriega would use the field to flee the
country, but he did not, Kelly said Thursday.
   Atlantic Fleet officials in Norfolk identified the four Sea, Air
and Land commandos as Lt. j.g. John Patrick Connors, 25, of
Arlington, Mass.; chief engineman Donald Lewis McFaul, 22, of San
Diego, Calif.; boatswain mate Christopher Tilghman, 20, Kailua,
Hawaii; and torpedoman Issac George Rodriguez III, 24, of Missouri
City, Texas. Their bodies were flown Thursday from Panama to Dover
Air Force Base in Delaware.
   The team was part of the Naval Special Warfare Group Two based
at the Little Creek Amphibious Base in Virginia Beach.
   ``He was a fine fellow; he was doing exactly what he wanted
to,'' said Tilghman's father, Taylor Tilghman.
   Tilghman enlisted in the Navy after he graduated from the
Kalaheo High School in Kailua, Hawaii, in 1979.
   ``He was following in my footsteps. He joined right after high
school,'' his father said in a telephone interview from his home in
Kailua. Taylor Tilghman was in the Navy for 15 years and the Coast
Guard for another 15.
   Paul Bennett, former executive officer of Connors' college
military training program, said Connors ``was a quiet kid, not the
kind of kid who walks around with `Soldier of Fortune' in his back
pocket. But he loved his country, and had a strong sense of value
and freedom.''
   Connors was a graduate of Worcester Polytechnical Institute, in
Worcester, Mass., which he attended on Naval ROTC scholarship.
   The SEAL teams are trained to undertake intelligence, hostage
rescue, and other operations needing a small, nearly invisible
force to succeed. Their training includes underwater demolition,
courses at the U.S. Army's Special Forces and Ranger schools, and
electronics and communications courses.
   Organized in 1962, the SEALs were used extensively in the Mekong
Delta area of Vietnam for anti-guerrilla warfare and secret
intelligence gathering operations during the Vietnam War. In 1965
and again in 1984, SEAL teams led the way for the invasions of the
Dominican Republic and Grenada.
   During the Reagan administration, a special unit was formed
within the SEALs that was believed to have been trained in hostage
rescue and covert intelligence gathering. The team reportedly was
put ashore by submarine in Libya in 1987, where team members
sabotaged communications and gathered information on coastal
defense.
   The Navy has two SEAL teams, one in California and the other at
Little Creek, with about 2,000 men in all.
</TEXT>

</DOC>