<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0204 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0717EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-Disasters-Christmas Adv22-24   12-21 0525</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Disasters-Christmas, Adv 22-24,0538</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv22-24</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Weekend Editions, Dec. 22-24, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Christmas Spirit Tested In Disaster-Stricken Spots</HEAD>
<HEAD>With BC-Hugo-Christmas</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Outwardly, it's been Christmas as usual: shops filled, trees
flocked, lights strung. But for many people in places scarred by
disaster, this has not been an ordinary holiday season.
   This Christmas will be more deeply felt and longer remembered by
those who were touched by the northern California earthquake, the
Alaska oil spill and the tornado that killed nine schoolchildren
near Newburgh, N.Y.
   _In San Francisco, the Rev. Cecil Williams of Glide Memorial
Methodist Church said this holiday season presents special
challenges to those who suffered losses in the October earthquake.
   ``No one should be homeless on Christmas Eve and Christmas
Day,'' he said. ``And we've decided anyone who needs a place, we're
going to put them up.''
   Glide has been raising money to pay for rooms at local
residential hotels to house up to 1,000 people. The church also
planned to hand out more than 9,500 bags of groceries and 5,000
toys, and feed more than 6,000 people on both Christmas Eve and
Christmas Day.
   Some Bay Area charities complained that the surge of giving
after the quake has subsided, even while the need remains strong.
At the Volunteer Bureau of Santa Cruz County, spokeswoman Maria
Norena said collections have been meager for new clothing and toys.
And, she said, ``This year we need it more than ever.''
   _In Alaska's port city of Valdez, site of the nation's worst oil
spill last March, a dreary, rainy summer has given way to a dreary,
slushy winter.
   The community's population ballooned to about 13,000 people from
its normal 3,000 during the summer's cleanup frenzy. This winter,
the number has shrunk to about 4,000.
   ``I think there's kind of a letdown after a busy summer,'' said
City Manager Doug Griffin. ``I don't think that is necessarily bad.
I think after all the activity, people need to catch their breath.''
   City Councilman Dennis Holtz, who owns the Food Mart, said his
sales have been strong. ``But I'm sensing the community is not
upbeat,'' he added. ``I think people are tired from the long
summer, and the spirit, the Christmas spirit, is not present. I
just think everybody's beat.''
   _In Newburgh, the Rev. Ted Bechtel of First Reformed Church said
people are beginning to put the tragedy at East Coldenham
Elementary school behind them, ``although we all realize it's going
to be with us a long time.''
   ``For a lot of the families involved and others in the
community, it's going to take a lot of the edge and joy off of
Christmastime,'' Bechtel said. ``But kids get caught up in the
season and the time of year and are generally doing well.''
   One of those killed, 8-year-old Peter Orsino, had attended
Sunday school at Bechtel's church.
   Peter's family is ``handling it pretty well,'' Bechtel said.
``They have other children and they're trying to celebrate a normal
Christmas. But I know another family, they don't want to decorate,
they don't want to celebrate Christmas at all.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sun AMs, Dec. 24</NOTE>

</DOC>