<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0186 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0902EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-LeadingIndicators 2ndLd-Writethru f0011 12-29 0627</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Leading Indicators, 2nd Ld-Writethru, f0011, f0314,0641</SECOND>
<HEAD>Forecasting Gauge Up Slightly in November</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Combines pvs files</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN CRUTSINGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Economics Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government's main forecasting gauge of
economic activity edged up a modest 0.1 percent last month, the
Commerce Department said today in a report that analysts took as a
sign the economy will slow in 1990 but not topple into a recession.
   The small rise in the department's Index of Leading Economic
Indicators for November followed a revised 0.3 percent decline in
October.
   In all, the index, which is designed to forecast economic
activity six to nine months in the future, has exhibited a sawtooth
pattern this year, rising in six of the past 11 months and falling
in the other five months.
   Through November, the index was down by 0.3 percent for the
year, compared with an increase of 3.9 percent for all of 1988.
   To economists, this provided evidence that economic activity in
1990 will be more sluggish than in 1989.
   Many analysts are predicting that the economy, as measured by
the gross national product, will expand at a modest annual rate of
2 percent or less in 1990, compared with expected growth of 3
percent this year.
   However, analysts generally expect the economy will be able to
escape a recession. That belief based in part on the fact that the
leading index has not yet declined for three consecutive months,
the traditional _ though not infallible _ sign of a downturn.
   The 0.1 percent rise in November, which was right in line with
expectations, was led by a strong jump in orders for consumer
goods. The other four indicators providing strength were a drop in
weekly unemployment claims, an increase in plant and equipment
orders, a rise in the money supply and an increase in the backlog
of manufacturers' unfilled orders.
   Six other indicators acted as a drag on the index last month,
with the biggest negative coming from a drop in the price of raw
materials. While such a decrease is considered good news for
inflation prospects, it is counted as a negative in the index
because it also can reflect declining demand.
   Other negative factors were a decline in stock prices, a drop in
consumer confidence, a decline in the average manufacturing work
week, a decline in building permits and a speedup in business
delivery times.
   The various changes left the index at 144.7 percent of its 1982
base of 100.
   The gross national product grew at an annual rate of 3 percent
in the July-September quarter, but economists believe the growth
rate slowed dramatically in the current October-December quarter.
   Frank McCormick, senior economist at the Bank of America in San
Francisco, said the GNP probably expanded at an annual rate of just
1.2 percent in the fourth quarter. The government will not release
its own estimate of this growth rate until next month.
   Some analysts are even more pessimistic, fearing that the GNP
may not have expanded at all and instead registered a small
negative number. The most pessimistic say the economy may suffer a
small recession with negative growth in both the fourth quarter and
the first quarter of next year.
   But McCormick discounted this minority view, contending that the
Fed's easing efforts have come in time to keep alive the expansion
following the 1981-82 recession, a recovery which already has
lasted a peacetime record of seven years.
   ``We think we have gone through the slowest growth already this
quarter and the economy will be gradually picking up through next
year,'' he said.
   That forecast would be good news for the Bush administration,
which is counting on continued growth to boost government revenues
and help reduce the federal deficit without a tax increase.
</TEXT>

</DOC>