<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0251 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1101EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f BC-CreditMarkets Adv25   12-22 0738</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Credit Markets, Adv 25,0770</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv25</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Monday, Dec. 25</HEAD>
<HEAD>New Muni Bond Rules Effective Jan. 1 Should Help Inform Investors</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BART ZIEGLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Starting Jan. 1, investors should have more
information available to make an informed decision when dabbling in
the municipal bond market.
   That's when federal disclosure rules for municipal bonds take
effect. The rules, released earlier this year by the Securities and
Exchange Commission, are designed to prevent such debacles as the
1983 bond default by the Washington Public Power Supply System.
   The $2.25 billion worth of bad WPPSS bonds _ the largest default
in municipal bond history _ led to these first-ever disclosure
rules for municipal bonds. Many brokerages that underwrote WPPSS
bonds later said they never were told by the utility consortium of
its financial problems.
   Muni bonds were exempt from the disclosure requirements placed
on other securities when the SEC was established in 1934.
   The new rules require brokerages underwriting municipal bond
issues of more than $1 million in value to obtain extensive
information about the projects financed by the bonds.
   Brokerages also must obtain information on the credit history of
the state or local government or agency issuing the bonds and any
foreseeble risks to investors.
   Brokerages must release this information to all potential buyers
in the form of official statements, which resemble the prospectuses
that companies are required to issue before they sell shares of
stock.
   Most muni bond issuers have been putting out official statements
for years, but the SEC rules make them mandatory and also tighten
the time frame in which they must be issued.
   Under the rules, a muni bond underwriter must make sure an
official statement is available within seven business days of a
bond issue's first selling day.
   Currently, it is common for a 30-day lag before an official
statement is released, said Christopher Taylor, executive director
of the Municipal Securities Rulemaking Board, the industry's
self-regulatory body established by Congress.
   ``We found that the problem with disclosure documentation was it
was produced but it wasn't disseminated in a timely fashion,''
added George Brakatselos, a vice president of the Public Securities
Association, a trade group for the municipal bond industry.
   Since the rules require brokers to describe potential risks of
bond issues, they could make it easier for investors to sue
investment houses in the event of a default.
   However, the rules don't apply to the billions of dollars in
municipal bonds now in investors' hands.
   The SEC rules also promote the creation of a central repository
to store and update the official statements.
   Under the rules, a brokerage must make official statements
available for 90 days after the end of a bond's underwriting
period. But if the statements are filed with a central repository,
the brokerage only has to make them available for 25 days after the
end of the underwriting period.
   The creation of a central repository could mark a turning point
in the municipal bond industry.
   The hope is that municipal bond issuers take it upon themselves
to update their disclosure forms periodically so that the
repository is viewed as the source of current information on
municipal issues that have been on the market for some time.
   If such a system develops, official statements could begin to
resemble the quarterly financial reports that corporations are
required to issue for their stock and bondholders.
   ``Issuers have long said, `Gee, I'd like to let the world know
how I'm doing but I have nowhere to send the information,'' Taylor
said last week.
   Four companies have said they want to set up a central
repository. In addition, the Municipal Securities Rulemaking Board,
which originated the idea, is devising plans for a computerized
repository of its own. The SEC has yet to select which group or
groups will be designated as official repositories.
   Under the rulemaking board's plans, it would make the statements
available to anyone for a nominal fee.
   Taylor said he envisions private companies repackaging
information from the rulemaking board's library and reselling it in
a form that may be more useful to bond traders, brokers and
investors.
   The Public Securities Association says it's pleased with the
government's new rules, especially those encouraging a central
repository.
   ``I think it will benefit everybody because right now there is
no single place you can go to get an official statement,''
Brakatselos said.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Monday, Dec. 25</NOTE>

</DOC>