<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0118EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Panama-Democracy     12-27 0719</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Democracy,710</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lack of Democratic Tradition in Panama Stymies US Efforts, Scholars
Say</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RUTH SINAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. presidents since Teddy Roosevelt in 1903
have talked about the need to install democracy in Panama. Some
sent troops under the banner of shoring up democratic rule.
   But all have been stymied by the lack of democratic tradition in
the strategically placed isthmus and by their overriding desire to
protect U.S. rights of passage through the Panama Canal, scholars
say.
   When President Bush went on television Wednesday morning to
explain why he dispatched troops to remove Panamanian strongman
Manuel Antonio Noriega from power, he cited the Panamanian people's
desire for democracy and peace. ``The people of the United States
seek only to support them in pursuit of these noble goals,'' he
said.
   ``The rhetoric about favoring democracy is no more than that.
It's a pretense,'' said John Peeler, who heads the Center for the
Study of the Americas at Bucknell University in Pennsylvania.
   The real U.S. desire is ``for democratic government, read
reliable government, one that won't threaten our control of the
canal,'' Peeler added.
   The few times in their 86-year history of independence when
Panamanians have supported a truly democratic government, ``We
weren't willing to accept their choice,'' Peeler said.
   That includes Arnulfo Arias, a populist leader elected president
twice in the 1940s and again in 1968. Arias' left-leaning views did
not sit well with the United States, which was not sorry to see him
ousted after several days in office by National Guard commander
Gen. Omar Torrijos.
   But Torrijos proved an even bigger problem for the
administration, with his pro-Cuban policies and strong nationalism
which opposed the U.S. right under the 1903 treaty to use the canal
``in perpetuity.''
   Increasing friction with the United States led to the
ratification of a new treaty in 1978 ceding the canal to Panama in
the year 2000 but reserving the right to intervene if shipping
through the waterway were threatened.
   Threats to U.S. use of the canal were what prompted the first
dispatch of military force to Panama. When Colombia, which ruled
Panama in the 19th Century, refused to approve the 1903 canal
treaty with the United States, Roosevelt sent warships to help the
growing Panamanian secessionist movement.
   But the warships only stood by as the secessionists launched a
bloodless revolt and declared independence.
   In August 1914, the same month World War I broke out, the first
ships passed through the canal. But political chaos reigned and the
United States sent troops to register voters and supervise
elections.
   Each time that happened _ in 1908, 1912 and 1916 _ the losing
side blamed U.S. interference.
   By the 1930s, ``there was growing U.S. frustration with the
attempts to instill democracy in Panama,'' said Frank Gerome, a
professor of history at James Madison University in Virginia.
Gerome has written extensively about U.S. efforts to organize the
1912 elections.
   Panama's strategic importance grew immensely in World War II,
when the U.S. military presence rose sharply to defend oil
shipments from Venezuela to the United States against German
interception. The hitherto limited U.S. military presence, which
had been centered mostly around the canal, spread to other parts of
the country.
   Panama in the 1950s and 1960s was ruled by a succession of
families from among a thin elite. While not a military state,
neither was it truly democratic.
   Torrijos' rise to power in 1968 transferred power to the
military, with a nominal role for civilian governments. Such was
the setup under Noriega, too, after Torrijos died in a 1981 plane
crash.
   ``Various American presidents hoped the roots of democracy might
grow,'' said Gerome. ``What they failed to understand is that you
can't export democracy.''
   Noriega, abhorrent though he is now to the U.S. administration
which nurtured him in the 1970s, enjoyed strong popular appeal
among Panama's poor.
   Guillermo Endara, who was installed at a U.S. military facility
as Panama's president on Thursday based on the results of last
May's elections, does not enjoy Noriega's popular appeal. His main
support comes from middle-class merchants.
   ``Support for him is weak, not passionate,'' and being propped
up by the United States can only be a liability, said Peeler,
adding, ``People aren't celebrating democracy, they're looting.
Doesn't Bush see that?''
</TEXT>

</DOC>