<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0222EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-HUDEthics     12-20 0506</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-HUD Ethics,500</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kemp Vows Swift Action to Improve Ethics Oversight</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN KING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Housing and Urban Development Secretary Jack
Kemp says he is moving quickly to correct problems that caused a
congressional study to say HUD has an ``extremely weak'' ethics
review system.
   Kemp's pledge came Tuesday following the release of a General
Accounting Office study that said HUD was failing to make sure
consultants filed financial disclosure forms and was not reviewing
the ones filed by employees.
   ``We found that HUD's system for obtaining and reviewing
disclosure statements is extremely weak, for its own employees as
well as for experts and consultants,'' GAO said.
   ``The fact that the problems we are reporting have existed for
so long demonstrates to us that the HUD secretary has not held the
(ethics officials) sufficiently accountable for developing and
administering an effective financial disclosure system.''
   GAO said there have been three HUD workers who have filled in as
the agency's chief ethics officer since Kemp took over early this
year, and said there has not been a staff and resource commitment
to policing for conflicts of interest.
   ``It appears that to a large extent it is business as usual at
the Department of Housing and Urban Development,'' said Sen. David
Pryor, D-Ark., who requested and released the report. ``I am
faulting Secretary Kemp.''
   Kemp, through HUD General Counsel Francis Keating, acknowledged
the problems.
   Keating said Kemp would hire a new chief ethics officer by
year's end and would soon fully staff an expanded ethics department.
   A new ethics manual also will be published by the end of the
year and all HUD employees are being required to attend ethics
seminars, Keating said.
   ``There are still things that need to be done but they are being
done,'' Keating said. ``No one is having to make a convert at this
department on the subject of ethics.''
   The GAO said it reviewed the files of 62 consultants hired by
HUD from 1986 to 1989 and that 52 had not filed required financial
disclosure forms.
   The agency, the investigative arm of Congress, also said that
HUD received 62 disclosure reports from employees who are required
to file them but that the agency had not reviewed any of them more
than 100 days later. Ethics law requires that the reports, designed
to uncover possible conflicts of interest, be reviewed within60
days.
   Keating said most have since been reviewed and the rest would be
scrutinized by Jan. 15.
   GAO said the problems date back at least seven years and persist
despite Kemp's promises to rid the agency of mismanagement,
political influence and other problems blamed for a number of
agency scandals during the Reagan administration.
   It is the second time Kemp's administration has come under some
criticism in a study of agency management. The department's
inspector general issued an earlier report praising Kemp's plans to
reform the oversight of agents HUD contracts to sell properties but
said the department's regional offices were slow in implementing
the changes.
</TEXT>

</DOC>