<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0321EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-JapaneseConstruction     12-20 0289</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Japanese Construction,260</SECOND>
<HEAD>Construction Companies Pay in Bid-Rigging Settlement</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.S. government is being paid $32.7
million by 99 Japanese companies to settle bid-rigging charges that
officials say raised construction costs of a U.S. Navy base by 25
percent.
   The cartel of 140 companies had bid on construction of the base
at Yokosuka, the Justice Department said Tuesday.
   Japan's Fair Trade Commission, which administers that country's
antitrust laws, earlier had fined 69 companies 1.5 percent of the
value of each company's contract, for a total of $2.2 million, and
had warned 70 unsuccessful bidders not to continue in the
bid-rigging arrangement.
   Some companies offered to negotiate a settlement as a result of
threats of a U.S. government lawsuit in the Japanese courts and
also in the U.S. courts against 26 companies also doing business in
the United States, the department said. The settlement, which
involved 99 firms, was negotiated in November, the agency said.
   Japanese construction companies frequently collaborate on bids
in a system called ``dango'' where the bidders decide who gets the
winning bid. The 140 companies bidding for U.S. Navy contracts at
Yokosuka formed an association in 1984 that called itself
``Seiyukai,'' or ``Friends of the Stars,'' a reference to the
American flag.
   The association dissolved in 1987 when the companies became
aware that they were under investigation by the Navy.
   Stuart M. Gerson, assistant attorney general in charge of the
civil division of the department, said the U.S. government would
pursue ``available remedies,'' including possible lawsuits in
Japan, the United States or both countries, against construction
companies that did not join the settlement.
   ``We are pleased to have been able to reach a just result
through the Japanese legal process,'' Gerson said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>