<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1921EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Pope-Christmas     12-24 0365</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pope-Christmas,0375</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pope Heralds Christ's Birth in Midnight Mass</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VATICAN CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pope John Paul II heralded the birth of
Jesus in a Christmas Eve midnight Mass in St. Peter's Basilica
beamed to millions on television.
   ``I bring you good news of a great joy,'' John Paul said,
opening his homily quoting from Luke. ``To you is born this day a
Savior.''
   Pilgrims and tourists packed St. Peter's, the largest church in
Christendom, and the pope greeted ``all people, on every
continent'' who listened on radio or watched on television.
   The Vatican said it expected the Mass to be televised to about
50 countries, including John Paul's native Poland, the Soviet
Union, Hungary and _ for the first time _ East Germany.
   Earlier, in an interview broadcast by Italy's state-run RAI-TV,
the pope praised the wave of democracy sweeping Eastern Europe,
lamenting only that the bloodshed in Romania at Christmas time was
a ``sad and painful'' exception.
   ``But it's a step in the same process. (It is) the past and the
future of our continent.''
   He called the European events ``extraordinary'' and said Eastern
Europeans who suffered as a result of World War II were ``finally
emerging as winners.''
   John Paul began his Christmas activities blessing a
100-foot-high tree from Austria and a nativity scene with life-size
figures in the center of St. Peter's Square at noon on Sunday. He
said Christmas eve was a ``wait full of hope as we prepare to
welcome Christ who comes to us as savior of the world.''
   In brief remarks, he said that while wars, rivalries, arrogance
and selfishness were obstacles to peace, ``the optimism of hope is
not naive.''
   Later, in his homily, the pope said, ``On this Bethlehem night
all of us are called _ once again _ to rejoice in the work of
creation.''
   ``The church, which on this night proclaims `a great joy,' knows
that this joy comes completely from God. It is the gift of his
love,'' the pope said.
   On Christmas, the pope will celebrate another Mass in St.
Peter's and then deliver his traditional message ``Urbi et Orbi'' _
Latin for ``to the city (of Rome) and the world.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>