<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0187 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2320EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-Hospital     12-21 0483</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Hospital,480</SECOND>
<HEAD>Medical Facility Treats All</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   EDITOR'S NOTE: The following is a pool report by Kathy Lewis of
The Houston Post, Bill Clayton of the Houston Chronicle, Kevin
Merida of The Dallas Morning News and Dick Thompson of Time
Magazine.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The medical facilities set up in the
converted classrooms of Balboa High School have been treating
civilians as well as soldiers.
   They have tended everything from a 2-year-old girl with an
amputated foot to a 73-year-old woman looking for insulin.
   They have patched up a large number of gunshot and shrapnel
wounds and delivered one baby which was said to be healthy.
   However, Col. Michael McConnell _ who is the Southern Command's
command surgeon _ said Wednesday's military injuries were
``significant'' in terms of seriousness, but he said they had been
able to stabilize everyone.
   ``I'd be surprised if any of them died,'' he said.
   One of the Panamanian civilians, a tiny, gray haired woman
wearing sandals cried that her home had been destroyed by the
fighting. ``I don't have a thing,'' she said, ``just what I have
on.''
   Still the woman, who declined to give her name fearing
retaliation, did not condemn the American action, said ``God bless
America. The America fed my father. The America gave me everything.
God bless America.''
   Pfc. Doc Jurkiewicz, a 22-year-old who is from Dallas, Texas,
was being treated for shrapnel in the left leg. He said he was
injured as they were clearing buildings near the comandancia. The
area already was on fire and apparently a gas tank blew.
   Though he was hurt last night, he stayed on and did not come in
for treatment until Thursday morning. He said there were ``a lot of
people'' still fighting.
   Jurkiewicz was the only soldier who was being treated during a
tour by reporters Thursday morning.
   One or two of the military injuries had been very serious he
said, ``The flack jackets saved many.''
   Across the hall from where the soldier was being treated,
several Panamanians were receiving medical attention. Some appeared
to have serious injuries.
   Susana Rivero, an older woman, who got bumped into barbed wire
was being treated for a cut on her left foot. She said her home in
Chorrillo, a poor neighborhood near the PDF's headquarters was lost.
   ``Everything was bombed,'' she said.
   However, she said she was glad the Americans came and wants
deposed Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega killed. She spoke of him as
still in office even though she had heard on the radio that
President Guillermo Endara had been sworn in.
   ``He has destroyed everything,'' she said of Noriega. ``He did a
lot of harm.'' She said he ought to be ``caught and killed.''
   Asked if she were glad the Americans came even though she lost
her home, she said, she was ``satisfied and calm'' and that the
Americans had never done any harm.
</TEXT>

</DOC>