<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0240 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0325EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Campbell-Dorrance Bjt   12-29 0660</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Campbell-Dorrance, Bjt,0682</SECOND>
<HEAD>Investor Group Pushing for Campbell Soup Sale</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MELANIE BURNEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAMDEN, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dissent appears to be growing among members
of the founding family of Campbell Soup Co. as three heirs to the
fortune put their 17 percent stake up for sale and threatened to
oust board members who oppose a plan to sell the food company.
   The group, composed of three nieces of Campbell's late chairman,
John T. Dorrance Jr., and their husbands, said in a Securities and
Exchange Commission filing Thursday that it plans to seek ``a price
per share significantly in excess of current market value.''
   The filing ``magnifies and brings to actuality the discord we've
been hearing about among the family,'' said Mary Harden, an
industry anaylst with Duff &amp; Phelps Inc. in Chicago.
   ``It's not particularly surprising,'' said Pavlos M.
Alexandrakis, an analyst with Argus Research Corp. in New York.
   Campbell shares have been driven higher in recent weeks by
increasing speculation of dissent within the Dorrance family. On
the New York Stock Exchange, Campbell shares closed Thursday up
$4.37{ to $57.37{ in active trading.
   ``They would seem over the last many months to not have
agreed,'' said Roderick Rumreich, an assistant vice president at
Moody's Investors Service Inc. in New York. ``For any group to
reach an agreement given the recent filings seems somewhat
improbable.''
   James H. Moran, a spokesman for Camden-based Campbell, said the
company had no comment on Thursday's SEC filing.
   Heirs of John Dorrance Sr., the chemist who invented condensed
soup in 1897, control about 59 percent of Campbell's 129.6 million
outstanding common shares, including the three nieces of Dorrance's
son who hold a 17.4 percent stake.
   The group pushing for a sale said it would encourage Campbell's
board of directors to do the same and consider ousting members who
opposed a sale.
   ``They've become much more aggressive about managing their
assets,'' said Rumreich.
   Last week, three children of Dorrance Jr., who died last April
and whose great uncle founded the company, issued a statement
saying they intended to maintain their ownership in Campbell and
keep the company independent. The three recently received control
of their father's 31.3 percent stake in the company.
   Ms. Harden said about 11 percent of the company's stock is in
hands ``friendly'' to the Dorrance children, including Robert J.
Vlasic, chairman of the board, who also opposes a sale.
   Those who want to sell ``are outvoted _ it looks like,'' Ms.
Harden said.
   But Alexandrakis said the family members pushing for a sale
could recruit others if the price was right.
   None of the descendants of Dorrance Sr. have played as active a
role in the company as his son Dorrance Jr. did.
   Alexandrakis described Campbell as a laggard in the food
industry, slow to update facilities and products. The company's
dominance in the retail soup market has dropped in recent years and
Campbell has had trouble gaining an upper hand in the fast-growing
dry soup market.
   Campbell's fiscal 1989 earnings totaled $13 million, or 10 cents
per share, down sharply from a profit of $274.1 million, or $2.12 a
share, the previous year.
   The most recent results were reduced by $343 million as a result
of a restructuring in August that included the closing of
manufacturing plants in Camden, Maryland and Tennessee with a loss
of 2,800 jobs.
   In November, R. Gordon McGovern stepped down as Campbell's chief
executive officer and president after heading the nation's largest
soup maker for nine years. A two-man interim management team was
appointed to oversee day-to-day operations, but a replacement has
not been named.
   Ms. Harden said the dissenting family members may have
difficulty finding a prospective buyer willing to pay top price for
Campbell.
   ``They're assuming it's somebody out there with deep pockets,''
she said. ``I'm not certain in this investment environment that
they're going to find an investor ... willing to pay the kind of
prices they're looking for.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>