<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1218EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-Navy-Safety 1stLd-Writethru a0552-a0554-a0556 12-19
0541</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Navy-Safety, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0552-a0554-a0556,520</SECOND>
<HEAD>Navy Chief Orders: `We Simply Must Do Better' On Safety</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Combines pvs files; minor editing</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSANNE M. SCHAFER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Military Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Navy's top admiral has told commanders
they ``must do better'' to improve the service's safety record
following evaluation of the unprecedented two-day freeze on routine
operations last month, Navy sources said today.
   Adm. Carlisle A. H. Trost, chief of naval operations, faulted
commanders for exercising poor supervision during the Navy's many
dangerous operations, saying the level of effective supervision on
the scene was often inadequate when accidents occurred.
   Trost offered the critique in a letter Monday that summed up his
findings in light of the mid-November ``safety stand-down'' he had
ordered after a string of serious accidents killed 10 sailors.
   The Associated Press obtained the contents of Trost's letter
from Navy sources.
   The admiral told commanders that he found the stand-down was
executed professionally at all levels, and that there was no single
thread that tied the string of accidents together.
   But he said, ``One life lost is an unacceptable price. We simply
must do better.''
   A Navy source, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said Trost
complained that sailors had not been properly taught to do their
jobs, that supervind boning utility 1-3, 50.00-55.00, high
dressing 55.00-57.00, low dressing 47.00-50.00. Breaking utility
and commercial 2-4, 49.00-54.00. Canner and low cutter 1-2,
47.00-50.50, shelly or lightweight 43.00-47.00.
   Slaughter bulls: Yield grade 1-2, 1400-2200 lbs 59.00-65.00,
individual exotic 2120 lbs 67.50; 1000-1400 lbs 55.00-60.00.
   Hogs: 3,000. Barrows and gilts compared with Monday moderate to
slow, steady.
   U.S. 1-3, 220-250 lbs 50.50; 250-260 lbs 50.00-50.50.
   U.S. 2-3, 260-280 lbs 48.50-50.00.
   Sows: Moderate. Under 500 lbs steady; over 500 lbs mostly 1.50
lower.
   U.S. 1-2, 300-500 lbs 41.50, few 42.00.
   U.S. 1-3, 500-650 lbs few early 46.50, later 45.00.
   Boars: 300-700 lbs 39.00.
   Sheep: 900. Compared with Monday, all classes steady to weak.
Supply near 30 percent slaughter lambs, 60 percent feeder lambs,
balance mostly slaughter ewes.
   Slaughter lambs: Shorn: Choice and prime 100-110 lbs with no.1
and 2 pelts 58.00-60.00. Wooled: Choice and prime 100-110 lbs
56.00-58.00; 110-120 lbs 54.00-56.00; 120-130 lbs 50.00-54.00.
   Slaughter ewes: Utility and good 22.00-26.00. Cull 18.00-22.00.
Few aged bucks 16.00-18.00.
   Feeder lambs: Choice and fancy 60-75 lbs 70.00-74.00; 75-90 lbs
65.00-70.00; 90-100 lbs 60.00-65.00.
</TEXT>

</DOC>