<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0176 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1331EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s e BC-BroadwayTix Adv23-24   12-19 0812</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Broadway Tix, Adv 23-24,0837</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv23</HEAD>
<HEAD>$adv24</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Weekend Editions of Dec. 23-24 and thereafter</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Broadway's new and current shows.
Ticket supply as of Dec. 22 is indicated as Difficult or Available.
Credit card holders can order tickets by phone or by calling
Telecharge or Ticketron.
   Telecharge's number is 212-239-6200 unless otherwise indicated.
Ticketron is 212-246-0102.
   For 24-hour information on theater, dance and music
performances, call the Theater Development Fund's New York City-On
Stage, 212-587-1111.
   When calling theaters directly, use New York area code 212.
Advance inquiries should be made, as ticket availability is subject
to change.
   _``A Chorus Line,'' the longest-running musical in Broadway
history, is about the hard life and struggles of chorus-line
members. Shubert, 239-6200, same number as Telecharge. Ticketron.
Available.
   _``A Few Good Men,'' Tom Hulce stars in Aaron Sorkin's play
about two Marines on trial for murder. Music Box, 239-6200, same
number as Telecharge. Ticketron. Available.
   _``Artist Descending a Staircase,'' a Tom Stoppard comedy about
three artists and the woman they loved. Helen Hayes, 944-9450.
Ticketron. Available. Closes Dec. 31.
   _``Black and Blue,'' Ruth Brown, Linda Hopkins and Carrie Smith
star in a musical revue celebrating blues songs and the art of tap
dancing. Minskoff, 869-0550. Ticketron. Available.
   _``Cats,'' musical based on T.S. Eliot's cat poems, music by
Andrew Lloyd Webber. Winter Garden, 239-6200, same number as
Telecharge. Ticketron. Available.
   _``City of Angels,'' a musical by Cy Coleman and Larry Gelbart
about a writer of detective novels in Los Angeles of the 1940s.
Virginia, 977-9370. Ticketron. Available.
   _``Grand Hotel,'' Tommy Tune directs a musical based on the
Vicki Baum novel about the goings-on at a posh hotel in post-World
War I Berlin. Martin Beck, 246-6363. Ticketron. Available.
   _``Gypsy,'' Tyne Daly stars as Mama Rose in a revival of the
musical based on the early days of stripper Gypsy Rose Lee. St.
James, 398-0280. Ticketron. Available.
   _``Jerome Robbins' Broadway,'' a cavalcade of dance and musical
numbers from musicals directed and-or choreographed by Jerome
Robbins, including ``West Side Story,'' ``Peter Pan,'' ``Fiddler on
the Roof'' and ``The King and I.'' Winner of the 1989 Tony Award as
best musical. Imperial, 239-6200, same number as Telecharge.
Difficult.
   _``Lend Me a Tenor,'' a farce by Ken Ludwig about an opera star
who gets sick before a charity gala. Royale, 239-6200, same number
as Telecharge. Ticketron. Available.
   _``Les Miserables,'' a musical retelling of the epic Victor Hugo
novel. Broadway, 239-6200, same number as Telecharge. Ticketron.
Available.
   _``Love Letters,'' A.R. Gurney's two-character play told
entirely through the correspondence of a man and a woman. The cast
changes weekly. Timothy Hutton and Elizabeth McGovern star through
Dec. 24. Lynn Redgrave and John Clark appear Dec. 26 though Dec.
31. Edison, 302-2302. Ticketron. Available.
   _``M. Butterfly,'' Tony Randall stars in a play by David Henry
Hwang about the love affair between a French diplomat and a Chinese
opera star. Eugene O'Neill, 246-0220. Ticketron. Available.
   _``Me and My Girl,'' the 1930s English musical hit about a
cockney scamp making it big in high society. Marquis, 382-0100.
Ticketron. Available. Closes Dec. 31.
   _``Meet Me in St. Louis,'' a stage version of the classic MGM
musical set during the 1904 World's Fair in St. Louis. Donna Kane
plays the Judy Garland role. Gershwin, 586-6510. Ticketron.
Available.
   _``Rumors,'' Neil Simon's newest play, which he calls a farce,
set during a couple's frantic anniversary party. Ethel Barrymore,
239-6200, same number as Telecharge. Ticketron. Available.
   _``Sweeney Todd,'' a revival of the Stephen Sondheim musical
about a murderous London barber. Circle in the Square, 239-6200,
same number as Telecharge. Ticketron. Available.
   _``The Circle,'' Rex Harrison, Glynis Johns and Stewart Granger
star in a revival of W. Somerset Maugham's 1921 comedy of manners.
Ambassador, 239-6200, same number as Telecharge. Available.
   _``The Heidi Chronicles,'' Christine Lahti stars in Wendy
Wasserstein's play about one woman's journey from the 1960s to the
present. Winner of the 1989 Tony Award as best play. Plymouth,
239-6200, same number as Telecharge. Ticketron. Available.
   _``The Merchant of Venice,'' Dustin Hoffman plays Shylock in a
production of the Shakespeare play directed by Peter Hall. 46th
Street, 221-1211. Ticketron. Difficult. Limited engagement through
Feb. 24.
   _``The Phantom of the Opera,'' the lavish Andrew Lloyd Webber
musical about a deformed composer who haunts the Paris Opera House
and the young soprano he loves. Majestic, 239-6290, a special
Telecharge number. Difficult.
   _``The Tenth Man,'' a revival of Paddy Chayefsky's 1959 Broadway
hit by the Lincoln Center Theater. Vivian Beaumont, 239-6200, same
number as Telecharge. Ticketron. Available.
   _``3 Penny Opera,'' Rock star Sting is Mack the Knife in a new
version of the Bertolt Brecht-Kurt Weill musical. Lunt-Fontanne.
575-9200. Ticketron. Available. Closes Dec. 31.
   _``Tru,'' Robert Morse is Truman Capote in a one-man show based
on the life of the famous writer. Booth, 239-6200, same number as
Telecharge. Ticketron. Available.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Weekend Editions, Dec. 23-24</NOTE>

</DOC>