<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0423EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Mexico-ArmsSmuggling     12-27 0447</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mexico-Arms Smuggling,0460</SECOND>
<HEAD>Officials Deny Cuba Smuggles Salvador-Bound Arms Through Mexico</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD HERZFELDER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MEXICO CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   High-ranking government officials deny U.S.
allegations that Cuba has established a route through Mexico for
shipping arms to El Salvador's leftist guerrillas.
   ``Mexico has been especially careful to establish facilities in
its territory for preventing the situations described,'' a Mexican
official said Tuesday on condition of anonymity.
   In a dispatch from Washington, The Associated Press reported
Monday that U.S. officials believe Cuba is shipping weapons across
the 130-mile wide Yucatan Channel, which leads to Mexico's Yucatan
peninsula. From there, the arms are loaded on trucks and taken on
an unknown route through Guatemala to El Salvador, the U.S.
officials said.
   One top Mexican official, who spoke on condition of anonymity,
said the claim was ``irresponsible, lacking in credibility and
false.''
   The official said that the United States has never brought up
the matter officially and that the Mexican government would have no
comment on the record because the claim had been leaked.
   The Mexican government historically has been sympathetic to the
Salvadoran rebels in their decade-old war, but that support has
been muted since President Carlos Salinas de Gortari took office a
year ago.
   U.S. officials contend Soviet bloc arms are reaching Salvadoran
rebels of the Farabundo Marti National Liberation Front through
Cuba and Nicaragua, although recent administration statements
indicate they do not see the Soviet Union as the principal villain.
   The U.S. officials told the AP that Cuba was looking for new
ways to help the rebels and at the same time shield Nicaragua's
Sandinista government from further criticism.
   The Sandinistas were embarrassed in October when a truck
carrying arms was intercepted in Honduras and in November when a
plane carrying surface-to-air missiles was shot down in El Salvador.
   The Salvadoran rebels, who maintain offices in Mexico City,
refuse to confirm or deny that they receive arms from Cuba and
Nicaragua.
   ``But even if we do, so what?'' said one rebel official. ``The
United States is helping its own.''
   The Mexican official said the Mexican government has tried to
work with the United States to fight arms and drug trafficking. If
there was a problem, this official said, channels created for that
purpose should have been used.
   A Mexican law enforcement official also denied claims that his
country was being used to smuggle arms south and noted that the
shortest route would take the arms into the resort area of Cancun.
   He said there was some evidence that a route had been
established through Belize, south of Mexico on the Yucatan
peninsula.
   ``The coast is much less well guarded down there,'' said this
official.
</TEXT>

</DOC>