<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0100 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1400EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Congress     12-18 0453</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Congress,0465</SECOND>
<HEAD>Conservatives Try to Roll Back Election Reform</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANN IMSE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Conservatives on Monday tried to roll back
political reform with an attempt to restore the Communist Party's
100 guaranteed seats in the Congress of People's Deputies.
   The Congress' legislative arm, the Supreme Soviet, voted several
months ago to remove a section of the Constitution allocating
one-third of the 2,250 Congressional seats to certain social
organizations, including the Communist Party and the Young
Communist League, known as the Komsomol. Instead, all deputies
would have to face public election in a territorial district.
   The constitutional change must be confirmed by the full
Congress, however, and that is where representatives of the
organizations fought to keep their privileged position.
   If the reform wins final approval, President Mikhail S.
Gorbachev would have to run in his first election campaign in 1994
if he wants to retain the presidency when his current five-year
term expires.
   He would have to run only in one local district, like British
Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher, because the Congress elects the
president from among its members.
   Although a vote was taken on the issue Monday, many deputies
were confused, and they wound up sending the issue back to
committee overnight. Some deputies apparently thought the 1,740 to
98 decision meant social organizations would lose their seats,
while other deputies thought it meant just the opposite.
   The decision will affect both the national Congress and the
parliaments of the republics. Most republics chose direct,
territorial elections, but Byelorussia and Kazakhstan already have
begun nominations from social organizations.
   Deputy Anatoly Sobchak said the system of electing deputies from
social organizations violated ``the most important principle of
election rights _ the principle of one man, one vote.''
   Under this system, for example, a female Communist scientist
could vote for deputies representing the Communist Party, the
Academy of Sciences, the national women's society and the district
where she lives.
   Many deputies representing such organizations took the
microphone to argue the system should remain in place. Many claimed
it was necessary to guarantee representation of invalids, the Red
Cross and other relief organizations. They did not mention that the
primary beneficiary of the system is the Communist Party.
   An exasperated Sobchak responded, ``Don't make our country the
laughingstock of the world. I fear that if we take this decison,
arguing that it will help invalids, then people will begin to call
us an invalid state.''
   Deputy Ilya Zaslavsky, who walks with a cane and was elected on
a program of invalids' rights, argued that many organizations were
not even on the list guaranteed representation in the Congress.
   Therefore, he argued, all organizations should compete for seats
in territorial-based elections.
</TEXT>

</DOC>