<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1751EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     12-17 0595</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0610</SECOND>
<HEAD>Record Cold Moves Into Virginias, Heavy Snow in New York State</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Arctic air drifted further east Sunday, breaking low-temperature
records from the Midwest to the Virginias and casting frost across
northern Florida, and another wave of cold air was expected to move
into Wyoming.
   Snow was widespread, stretching from northern Maine to parts of
the Great Lakes, covering parts of the northern Plains and Rockies,
and reaching south to Arkansas and Tennessee.
   The official low temperature for the Lower 48 states Sunday
morning was 17 degrees below zero at Lewisburg, Va., but smaller
communities in West Virginia and southwest Virginia reported much
lower temperatures. In West Virginia, Greenbank reached 26 below
and Seneca State Forest hit 23 below, while Burkes Garden, Va., had
a low of 19 below zero.
   Low-temperature records for the date were set or tied in at
least 22 cities in 11 states because of the arctic air mass
centered over the lower Ohio Valley. Six new records were set in
Ohio, including 12 degrees below zero Columbus, 10 below in
Youngstown, 9 below in Cincinnati and 7 below in Cleveland.
   Other new records included minus 2 degrees in Charleston, W.Va.,
minus 7 in Detroit, 10 below in Indianapolis, 11 below in Fort
Wayne, Ind., minus 6 in Lexington, Ky., and minus 5 in Springfield,
Ill.
   The cold also persisted in Honolulu, where the early morning low
of 57 degrees tied the record for the date set in 1980.
   Northern Florida got frost and freezing temperatures Sunday
morning, with lows of 26 degrees at Crestview and Tallahassee, 30
at Pensacola and 31 at Gainesville.
   Cold weather also was expected to move into Southern California.
A frost advisory was posted for the San Diego area, with lows
expected to drop to around 27 degrees in nearby agricultural areas
Sunday night.
   Another surge of snow and lower temperatures was forecast to
move into Wyoming on Sunday night, dropping temperatures to as low
as 15 below zero. Monday's highs were expected to be between zero
and 15 degrees above zero. From 3 to 6 inches of snow was forecast
for the mountains and 1 to 3 inches elsewhere in the state.
   Early Sunday afternoon, snow was falling in sections of Maine,
New York state, Tennessee, Michigan, Missouri, Arkansas, Iowa,
Minnesota, the Dakotas, Colorado, Wyoming, Montana and eastern
Washington state.
   A snow squall warning remained in effect in parts of western New
York state southeast of Lake Ontario. Hancock has received 2 feet
of snow since Friday, and another 6 inches or more were expected.
   Heavy snow caused authorities to extend an avalanche alert in
the Rockies of northern Colorado Sunday. The area has received 2 to
5 feet of snow over the past week and there were at least two dozen
avalanches on Saturday, Nick Logan of the state's Avalanche
Information Center in Denver said.
   Skiers rejoiced, though, particularly at Steamboat Springs where
the resort reported a 59-inch snow depth. ``It's good powder skiing
_ soft powder skiing,'' said Joe Puchek of Gunnison.
   Snowfall during the 6 hours ending at 1 p.m. EST included 4
inches at Pellston, Mich., and Syracuse, N.Y., 3 inches at
Muskegon, Mich., and 1 inch at Rome, N.Y.
   Sleet and light snow was falling in north-central and west
Texas, causing hazardous road conditions, and rain was falling on
the central Texas Gulf coast.
   Temperatures at 3 p.m. EST ranged from 10 degrees below zero at
the Air Force base near Grand Forks, N.D., to 79 degrees at Miami
and Fort Myers, Fla.
</TEXT>

</DOC>