<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0106 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 2203EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama 2ndLd-Writethru 1stAdd 12-25 0483</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama, 2nd Ld-Writethru, 1st Add, a0652,0490</SECOND>
<HEAD>PANAMA CITY: City said.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Most in the capital of 1 million faced a miserable Christmas due
to the shortage of food, medicine and other goods caused by the
looting. But news Noriega turned himself in brought hundreds of
elated people into the streets.
   ``Now we can have Christmas!' said one celebrant.
   On Monday, editors of the opposition newspaper La Prensa entered
their building for the first time since Noriega shut it down Feb.
25, 1988. Much of the equipment was destroyed and they were
uncertain when they could publish.
   Also Monday in Washington, the Justice Department announced a
Panamanian officer who was indicted along with Noriega on drug
charges was flown to Miami by agents of the Drug Enforcement
Administration. Lt. Col. Luis del Cid, a loyalist who commanded a
unit in western Chiriqui province, surrendered Saturday.
   U.S. troops also arrested Mario Rognoni, a commercial minister
under Noriega, according to witnesses who saw him being taken from
his house. It was not known why he was apprehended. Earlier,
Rognoni's name appeared on a communique from a pro-Noriega party
declaring itself ``in democratic and peaceful opposition to the
government imposed by the invading forces.''
   U.S. military officials said most members of Noriega's
15,000-member Defense Forces are surrendering and the resistance of
his loyalists has died. U.S. troops arrived in David, 200 miles
west of Panama City and took the airport and a Panamanian military
headquarters.
   Helicopters dropped tens of thousands of ``safe conduct passes''
in resistance areas for Noriega loyalists who want to turn
themselves in to U.S. military headquarters.
   Lt. Col. Jerry Murguia told a Southern Command briefing in the
capital on Monday that U.S. troops captured Santiago, 120 miles
southwest of Panama City, taking 188 prisoners and seizing hundreds
of small arms.
   In the soccer stadium at Balboa next to the Panama Canal, U.S.
troops fed and assisted up to 10,000 Panamanian refugees who had
the fighting. Panama's archbishop celebrated a Christmas Mass.
   In his homily, Archbishop Marcos McGrath called for ``a new
Panama without revenge or hate'' and urged looters to return stolen
goods.
   The fighting that broke out after the U.S. invasion, launched
early Wednesday, left much of Panama City in chaos.
   The Pentagon issued new casualty figures. The death toll of U.S.
troops stood at 23, revised downward by one from Sunday because one
victim was counted by two different units. There were 303 U.S.
wounded, none missing and two dependents killed.
   It said Noriega's routed Panamanian Defense Forces suffered 290
dead, 121 wounded, and 3,780 captured or detained. Panamanian
doctors said more than 100 civilians were killed and hundreds more
injured.
   ``One single person is guilty of all this. So much death because
of one man, and that man's name is Manuel Antonio Noriega,'' said
goldsmith Ruben Camargo, whose home in the Chorrillo neighborhood
next to Noriega's headquarters was destroyed.
</TEXT>

</DOC>