<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0241EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Israel-SouthLebanon 1stLd-Writethru b0147 12-28 0835</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Israel-South Lebanon, 1st Ld - Writethru, b0147,0854</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israel Strengthens Lebanese Militia but Discipline Uncertain</HEAD>
<BYLINE>Eds: INSERTS new 2nd graf in b0147, which moved in advance 12-22,
to UPDATE with subsequent Israeli raid. Picks up 2nd pvs, `With Israeli
...' ^By NICOLAS B. TATRO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MAJDIA, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The South Lebanon Army, created by Israel
to help guard its border, has honed its fighting skills and
expanded in size. But there is no sign Israel is ready to withdraw
from southern Lebanon and leave the fighting to its allies.
   On Tuesday, Israeli ground and air attacks wiped out two
guerrilla bases of the Communist Party in central and southern
Lebanon in the largest such action in a year. Thirteen people were
reported killed.
   With Israeli advisers and reporters watching, the SLA recently
showed off its gunnery prowess in a live-fire exercise with a dozen
Soviet T-55 tanks captured by the Israelis from the Palestine
Liberation Organization.
   Gun barrels flashed and the aging tanks, painted gray, knocked
out rusty trucks on a hillside nearly a half-mile away.
   The Lebanese crews, silhouetted on a ridgeline, could be seen
jumping and waving their arms with delight.
   The exercise, Israeli advisers stressed, marked a significant
improvement in the military capabilities of the militia that helps
Israeli troops patrol a security zone that is 2.5 to 12 miles deep
just north of Israel's border.
   However, some observers see a major problem with the militia's
reliability and discipline.
   The SLA has caused Israel political embarrassment by getting
involved in shooting incidents with the nine-nation, 5,700-member
United Nations peackeeping force that patrols north of the security
zone.
   It also has stirred up anti-Israeli sentiment with
indiscriminate shellings of Shiite Moslem villages.
   The SLA commander, Antoine Lahad, 62, a retired Lebanese army
general, told reporters his force made a ``lot of improvement''
since Israel withdrew the bulk of its troops from Lebanon in 1985.
   ``The SLA was more like a militia. Now it has developed into a
small regular army,'' he said, adding the force numbered 3,000 men,
up from 2,000 a year ago, and may expand further.
   Lahad, who survived a communist-inspired assassination attempt
in November 1988, said an Israeli presence was needed until Syria
withdrew its 40,000 troops from Lebanon.
   ``The day we face Lebanese opponents only, we can do without the
backing of the Israeli army,'' said Lahad, a Christian whose
militia controls an area with a predominantly Shiite Moslem
population of 200,000.
   Israel has stationed troops in Lebanon since shortly after
Lebanon's civil war began in 1975.
   Col. Renaan Gissin, deputy spokesman for the Israeli army, said
Israel had no plans to leave but also had no interest in Lebanon
beyond protecting its 60-mile border.
   He added that the zone had proved a success because life in
northern Israel was normal and no Israeli civilian had died in an
attack from Lebanon since 1985.
   The SLA's reliability remains a major question mark, however.
   In recent years, the Christian-led force was riddled with
defections by Shiites, had its positions overrun by Iranian-backed
Hezbollah guerrillas and proved unable to stop Palestinian
infiltrations into the security zone.
   The SLA has also borne the brunt of Shiite and Palestinian
attacks, suffering 188 killed and 600 wounded in the past four
years. So far this year, the SLA came under 350 guerrilla attacks,
about half the level of the previous year.
   Despite the improvements, some experts are less confident of the
SLA's ability to restrain its militiamen from exacting revenge and
say the force is incapable of standing up to guerrilla attacks
without Israeli troops, estimated by foreign reports to number at
least 1,000.
   ``The SLA will hold on as long as Israeli army is the backbone.
Discipline is good as long as Israeli officers are there,'' said
Yoram Hamizrachi, a retired colonel who was in charge of training
the SLA from 1977 to 1980.
   ``They are improving in military skills. They can read maps and
coordinate their actions. But they have a tendency to lose their
tempers. I wouldn't trust them in anything major.''
   In early December, for example, SLA gunners retaliated for the
ambush killing of three SLA militiamen by firing sporadic barrages
at civilian areas north of the security zone. Lebanese reports said
nine civilians were killed in the Shiite town of Nabatiyeh.
   The Shiite leader, Nabih Berri, responded with a warning that
his Amal militiamen would shell Israeli settlements if the SLA
attacks persisted.
   Maj. Gen. Yossi Peled, Israel's northern front commander,
conceded in a recent interview that he had frequent arguments with
SLA commanders about the use of force.
   He said that it was normal for Lebanese militias to fire 100 to
300 shells into a small village.
   Peled said it was ``quite difficult'' to get the SLA to
understand Israel's objections but ``during the past two or three
years we succeeded to change their behavior. I don't know if it
will go back the way it was, but there has been a tremendous
change.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>