<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0040EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Vatican-Panama     12-25 0535</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Vatican-Panama,0551</SECOND>
<HEAD>Vatican Dilemma: What To Do With Noriega</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEPHEN R. WILSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VATICAN CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   While it's not the first time a political
figure has sought refuge in a Vatican embassy, Roman Catholic
officials faced a unique dilemma when Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega
showed up at the papal nunciate in Panama.
   Helping the strongman flee the country would likely pique the
United States, which invaded Panama last week to try to capture the
strongman and bring him to trial on drug charges.
   At the same time, the Vatican would not be eager to hand him
over to U.S. authorities for fear of appearing to condone the
invasion and take sides in an international dispute.
   ``It's a very complex problem,'' said a senior Vatican official
early today after learning that Noriega took refuge Sunday at the
papal nunciate, or Vatican embassy, in Panama City.
   The official, who works in foreign policy issues and spoke under
the usual ground rule of anonymity, noted that the Vatican has no
tradition or policy of accepting asylum seekers.
   ``The Vatican policy is `we're not open to taking people, we
can't take them back to the Vatican.' The Vatican needs to
negotiate with a third government to take them. This is much more
difficult,'' the official said.
   The official said the Vatican mission could seek to turn Noriega
over to the new Panama government or to arrange for safe passage to
another country.
   ``I don't think they could directly hand Noriega over to the
Americans, who are an invading army,'' the official said. ``They
would be recognizing the Americans as the local authorities.
Instead, they could hand him over to the government there on
condition of a fair trial.''
   The official said Noriega may have chosen to take refuge at the
Vatican embassy because he feels it offers the most guarantees and
is the one mission whose diplomatic immunity the United States
would not want to violate.
   Just two months ago, the Vatican embassy in Panama had sheltered
opposition leader Guillermo Endara after he was beaten by Noriega's
soldiers. Endara was later installed as president after the U.S.
invasion.
   In 1983, four Marxist guerrillas sought refuge at the Vatican
mission in Santiago, Chile, after they were accused by Chilean
authorities in the assassination of retired Army Gen. Carol Urzua,
the governor of metropolitan Santiago.
   The Holy See arranged for their safe conduct out of the country
on grounds they would have faced summary judgment in Chile by an
army war tribunal.
   Another case of political refuge involving the Vatican was that
of the late Hungarian Cardinal Josef Mindszenty, who was convicted
of treason in 1949 in what was widely regarded as a rigged trial.
   Mindszenty was freed from prison by Hungarian revolutionaries in
1956 and took refuge in the U.S. mission in Budapest when Soviet
tanks crushed the uprising. He left his asylum in 1971 under an
agreement with the Vatican and died in Vienna in 1975.
   Pope John Paul II and the local Roman Catholic Church have
expressed concern about the U.S. military intervention in Panama.
On Friday, the pope said ``there have been clashes with innocent
victims and grave discomforts to the population.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>