<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0110 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1516EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People-CriticsAwards     12-18 0297</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People-Critics Awards,0307</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Do The Right Thing' Wins Four LA Critics Awards</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: ``sex, lies and videotape'' is all lower case cq</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ``Do The Right Thing'' did just that for the
Los Angeles Film Critics Association as the controversial film
about racial tensions scored honors as best picture of 1989 and
best director for Spike Lee.
   ``Do The Right Thing,'' set on the hottest day of the year in
New York, also won awards Saturday for Danny Aiello for best
supporting actor and for the musical score by Lee's father, Bill
Lee.
   Andie MacDowell, who played the sexually frustrated housewife in
``sex, lies and videotape,'' shared the best actress honor with
Michelle Pfeiffer, the sultry lounge singer in ``The Fabulous Baker
Boys.''
   Daniel-Day Lewis won best actor for his portrayal in ``My Left
Foot'' of Irish writer-painter Christy Brown, who was born with
cerebral palsy. Brenda Fricker, who played Brown's mother, won best
supporting actress.
   Best screenplay went to Gus Van Sant and Daniel Yost for
``Drugstore Cowboy,'' about narcotics burglars in the early 1970s.
   Michael Moore's quirky ``Roger and Me,'' about Moore's efforts
to show General Motors head Roger Smith the economic devastation
his company brought to Flint, Mich., won for best documentary.
   The best foreign film honor was split between ``Distant
Voices-Still Lives,'' from Britain and France's ``Story of Women.''
Disney's``The Little Mermaid'' picked up the award for best
animation for writer-directors John Musker and Ron Clements.
   The career achievement award was given to Stanley Donen, the
musical and romantic comedy director best known for ``Singin' in
the Rain,'' and the best newcomer award went to Laura San Giacomo.
Gregg Araki got the Independent-Experimental Award for ``The Long
Weekend.''
   The awards will be formally presented Jan. 16 in West Hollywood.
</TEXT>

</DOC>