<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0603EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Japan-Travel     12-30 0314</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Japan-Travel,0326</SECOND>
<HEAD>Half-Million Japanese Traveling Abroad During Holiday Season</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By K.P. HONG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 33,000 Japanese crowded into Tokyo's
international airport as the New Year holiday exodus began, and
about 420,000 people are expected to head for Hawaii, Hong Kong and
other vacation spots.
   ``The estimated total is up 10.6 percent from the same period a
year earlier,'' said Akihiro Furukawa of the Japan Travel Bureau, a
major Japanese travel agency.
   Government officials have said travel represents one of the most
promising areas for Japan to increase its ``imports'' and offset
its trade surpluses.
   Japan's travel deficit stood at $19 billion in 1988, when the
country's merchandise trade surplus reached $95 billion, according
to Japanese figures.
   The Transportation Ministry said Friday an estimated 9.64
million Japanese have traveled abroad this year, up 14.2 percent
from a year ago.
   Hawaii is the most popular New Year destination, expected to
draw 68,000 Japanese, travel agents say. Another 49,000 are bound
for the U.S. West Coast and 13,000 for Canada, they said.
   Other popular destinations are Taiwan, South Korea, Singapore,
Thailand and the South Pacific.
   Many Japanese never take the vacations to which they are
entitled, meaning their only time off from work comes during the
New Year holiday and a string of public holidays in late April and
early May, with perhaps some vacation days used to stretch those
periods.
   Many companies remain closed this year from Friday through
Thursday, although some Japanese began their travels last weekend.
   The average Japanese will spend $2,800, if souvenir shopping is
included, on an average six-day stay abroad, Furukawa said.
   A booming domestic economy is fueling the travel surge, he said.
This country's strong currency makes foreign travel relatively
cheaper for Japanese, too. The Japanese yen has climbed from about
242 yen to the dollar in late 1985 to the current 143 yen.
</TEXT>

</DOC>