<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0102 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1240EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mandela     12-22 0448</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mandela,0459</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Says Mandela Won't Be Freed Before New Year</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID CRARY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government said Friday
that jailed black nationalist leader Nelson Mandela won't be freed
before the end of the year.
   Speculation remains strong, however, that Mandela will be freed
in January or early February.
   A broad range of black leaders say Mandela must be released
before they can accept President F.W. de Klerk's invitation to
negotiate a new Constitution that would extend political rights to
blacks.
   Rumors that Mandela would be freed before Christmas spread
earlier this week following unsubstantiated reports that British
Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher asked South African authorities to
take this step. Mrs. Thatcher's office denied that any time frame
had been added to her standing request that Mandela be freed ``as
soon as possible.''
   South Africa's Bureau for Information said Friday: ``In response
to numerous press inquiries concerning the possible release of Mr.
Nelson Mandela, the bureau would like to make it clear that there
will be no developments in this regard during the festive season.''
   The bureau said that meant Mandela would not be freed before
Jan. 1.
   Mandela, 71, is South Africa's best-known black leader. He has
been imprisoned since 1962 and is serving a life sentence for
plotting an anti-government sabotage campaign to be carried out by
his African National Congress guerrilla movement.
   Mandela lives at a staff house on a prison farm outside Cape
Town, and has been meeting frequently with anti-apartheid leaders
and government officials, including talks last week with de Klerk.
   Mandela met for six hours Friday with a five-man delegation from
the Congress of South African Trade Unions, the country's largest
and most militant labor federation.
   ``Mr. Mandela said he wants to be released into an environment
where he would be able to move freely amongst his people,'' said
one of the union leaders, John Ernstzen. ``He would like to see the
cessation of all hangings, treason trials and other methods the
state is using.''
   The mayor of Cape Town, Gordon Oliver, Friday released the text
of a letter he sent to Mandela requesting a meeting. Oliver said
the all-white City Council would like Mandela's advice on how to
carry out its goals of creating a city free of discrimination.
   The Prison Services confirmed Friday that Mandela had been
allowed the use of a telephone to confer with two of the African
National Congress's top exiled leaders. Col. Ray Gamble, a prison
spokesman, said Mandela was permitted to speak by phone Tuesday
with ANC secretary general Alfred Nzo and ANC external affairs
sectrary Thabo Mbeki while they were attending a political congress
in Zimbabwe.
</TEXT>

</DOC>