<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0537EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Marcos     12-22 0431</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Marcos,0444</SECOND>
<HEAD>Murder Investigation Reopened After Civil Verdict Against Marcoses</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The investigation of the 1981 murders of two
Filipino union leaders has been reopened after a civil trial found
the late Philippine President Ferdinand Marcos liable for their
deaths, a prosecutor said.
   The victims, Silme Domingo and Gene Viernes, worked in this
country against Marcos, and their survivors claimed they were
killed on orders from the Philippines. Police laid their deaths to
union activities and three men were convicted.
   On Thursday, after meetings with attorneys for the dead men's
families, the King County Prosecutors Office announced the probe
would be reopened.
   ``We plan on taking a very serious look at the matter,'' said
prosecutor's spokesman Dan Donohoe.
   The follow-up investigation should take about two months,
Donohoe said.
   Last week the families of Domingo and Viernes won a civil suit
in U.S. District Court here against the estate of Marcos, who died
in September, and his widow, Imelda.
   The civil jury decided that Marcoses were conspirators in the
deaths of the two men and were negligent in failing to control
their intelligence agents in the United States. The families were
awarded more than $15 million.
   After the trial, Seattle attorney Michael Withey, who
represented the families, said the survivors wanted criminal
charges filed against the man whose gun was used in the killings in
light of evidence presented in their civil suit.
   The gun belonged to Constantine ``Tony'' Baruso, 61, of Seattle,
who was never charged in the case. Baruso was president of the
Alaska Cannery Workers Union when Domingo and Viernes were gunned
down at the union's Seattle headquarters.
   Baruso and Dr. Leonilo Malabed, a San Francisco physician who
allegedly managed an intelligence fund for Marcos, also were named
in the civil suit. Baruso and Malabed waived their right to a jury
trial and U.S. District Judge Barbara Rothstein has yet to rule on
their part of the case.
   In a related matter, attorneys defending Mrs. Marcos in a
federal racketeering case in New York have discussed a plea
bargain, but are preparing for the March 14 trial anyhow.
   The talks with prosecutors were ``preliminary chitchat'' and
haven't led to any sort of deal for her to plead guilty to lesser
charges, said Mrs. Marcos's lawyer, John J. Tigue.
   The charges stem from allegations she and her late husband
siphoned more than $100 million from the Philippines treasury and
funneled it into this country for the purchase of New York real
estate and art.
   The prosecutor, Assistant U.S. Attorney Charles LaBella, refused
to comment on the negotiations.
</TEXT>

</DOC>