<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0747EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-DignityBattalions     12-21 0419</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Dignity Battalions,0434</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dignity Battalions Prepared for U.S. Invasion</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The paramilitary squads called
Dignity Battalions that comprise Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega's most
loyal supporters have been training for more than a year to fight a
U.S. invasion.
   Hundreds of the volunteers have been drilled in the handling of
M-16 rifles, jogged over rugged roads, cheered their homeland and
jeered the Yankees they predicted they would one day have to battle.
   At 1 a.m. Wednesday, when U.S. troops in armored personnel
carriers and warplanes attacked Panamanian bases, the Dignity
Battalions went into action.
   Brigades mobilized in the streets and soon after the first shots
were fired a group of men in civilian clothes carrying assault
rifles stormed the luxury Marriott Hotel and rounded up a dozen
foreign guests.
   They threatened to kill their captives but eventually released
them unharmed.
   As U.S. troops gained control of the major garrisons, many
fleeing officers of the regular armed forces _ known as the
Panamanian Defense Forces _ joined up with Dignity Battalions.
   ``We are acting as urban guerrillas, although we have lost some
positions, some garrisons,'' Enrique Thompson, second-in-command of
the battalions, told an Associated Press reporter Wednesday.
   Carrying Soviet-made AK-47 rifles, five men with him took up
positions in bushes near the Tinajitas garrison, which American
troops had seized.
   ``The people are joining the struggle for national
sovereignty,'' Thompson said.
   A national radio network broadcast called on the Dignity
Battalions to shoot at U.S. helicopters flying over Tinajitas ``and
not let them descend.''
   In another broadcast, a military officer ordered the battalions
to conduct small operations, mix with non-combatant supporters and
attack enemy positions on the edge of the city after dark.
   The paramilitary units were formed after the United States began
increasing its troop strength in the former Panama Canal Zone in
March 1988.
   Even then, the government predicted the United States would
invade to oust Noriega, who is wanted in the United States on
federal drug trafficking charges.
   Many Dignity Battalion volunteers who attended training sessions
were women. Most were in their late teens or early 20s.
   At a 1988 drill visited by a reporter, trainees shouted,
``Sovreignty, Sovreignty. Together we fight for the homeland.''
   Some battalions have been said to have more than 1,000 members,
others a few hundred. There is no reliable estimate of the total.
   ``What we are saying to North America is that when you invade,
we are ready,'' said one young man at the 1988 session.
</TEXT>

</DOC>