<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0229 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2308EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Blackbird     12-20 0442</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Blackbird,0455</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Blackbird' Spy Plane Observes 25th Anniversary of Maiden Flight</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BURBANK, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of Lockheed Aircraft Corp.
employees watched an SR-71 Blackbird thunder overhead Wednesday as
the spy plane flew toward retirement after nearly 25 years of
top-secret, supersonic service.
   Among the Lockheed workers watching the flybys near the Burbank
airport and a Lockheed research and development facility near Santa
Clarita was Clarence ``Kelly'' Johnson, 79, Lockheed's legendary
aircraft designer.
   Johnson, who is in poor health, has been living at an
undisclosed hospital, said Richard Stadler, a Lockheed spokesman.
   The black, delta-winged reconnaissance jet, which is heading for
retirement under Pentagon cutbacks, was first flown on Dec. 22,
1964, said Bill Spaniel, a Lockheed spokesman.
   Spaniel declined to give further details about the maiden
flight, saying that much information about the
intelligence-gathering aircraft remains classified.
   It was the first time many people had seen the black,
sophisticated aircraft, even among Lockheed employees, said
Stadler, who watched three flybys in Burbank from the roof of a
Lockheed building.
   ``It's amazing,'' Stadler said. ``Some of us get used to the
fact of the aircraft being around, and then you realize that a lot
of people have never seen one before.''
   The SR-71 was developed to succeed the U-2 spy plane, which came
to symbolize the Cold War after American pilot Francis Gary Powers
was shot down in 1960 during a reconnaissance flight high above the
Soviet Union.
   Like the U-2, the Blackbird was conceived by engineers working
at Lockheed's Advanced Development Projects, a highly innovative
program organized by Johnson that gained renown as the Skunk Works.
   Blackbirds on reconnaissance flights were frequently targeted by
ground-to-air missiles and jet interceptors during the Vietnam War,
Lockheed officials said.
   But attempts to shoot down Blackbirds have all failed, primarily
because the jet was able to outrun its attackers at speeds three
times faster than the speed of sound and was able to fly at
altitudes higher than 85,000 feet, officials said.
   While many of the SR-71's exact capabilities have remained
secret, it has held several speed and altitude records for nearly a
quarter century.
   One public record held by a Blackbird was a 15,000-mile flight
completed in 10{ hours, which works out to a speed of about 1,429
mph. Background material provided by Lockheed, however, says the
twin-engine jet is capable of speeds in excess of 2,000 mph.
   The capability of radar, infrared cameras and other
intelligence-gathering sensors aboard the SR-71 also is classified.
However, officials have acknowledged that the pictures produced by
such equipment are sharp enough that one can read the numbers on a
license plate photographed from 15 miles away.
</TEXT>

</DOC>