<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1216EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Romania-Diplomatic 3rdLd-Writethru   12-23 0741</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Diplomatic, 3rd Ld-Writethru,a0531,0763</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romanian Embassies in 13 Nations Support the Popular Uprising</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 9 grafs to UPDATE with 13 embassies now supporting
provisional government. Pickup 7th graf, `In Poland...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Romanian embassies in 13 countries today denounced the ousted
regime of Romanian dictator Nicolae Ceausescu and supported the new
provisional government that took power in their country.
   Embassies in the Soviet Union, France, Tunisia, Jordan, Poland,
Yugoslavia, Austria, Belgium, Turkey, Spain, Canada, Israel and
Bangladesh all supported the popular revolt that has claimed
hundreds of lives in Romania.
   As fighting continued between army soldiers who sided with
Romanian citizens and security forces loyal to Ceausescu, the
Soviet news agency Tass said the Romanian Embassy in Moscow had
sided with the provisional government.
   ``The entire staff of the Romanian Embassy in the Soviet Union
is in full solidarity with the National Salvation Committee, the
new supreme body of power in Romania, and with its platform,'' Tass
said. The news agency said it had received the statement from the
Romanian Embassy in Moscow.
   The uprising toppled the hard-line Communist leader on Friday.
The provisional government that took over promised free elections
in April.
   This afternoon, 30 Moscow dissidents and human rights activists
gathered outside the Romanian Embassy to conduct a memorial service
for the hundreds of people who have been killed in the revolt
against Ceausescu.
   The Romanian Embassy in France supported the provisional
government, and Ambassador Petre Gigea said: ``We are completely in
solidarity with the fundamental changes now going on in Romania.''
He said he was ready to meet with Romanian exiles in Paris to find
the best way to help the new regime.
   The Romanian Embassy in Tunis, Tunisia, took similar action. A
communique signed by charge d'affaires Marin Albu proclaimed that
``all the embassy personnel are with'' the new government.
   The statement said the Romanian Embassy in Jordan has taken
similar action.
   In Poland, Romanian Ambassador Ion Tesu stood outside his Warsaw
Embassy, which had been splattered with ink by anti-Ceausescu
protesters, to say he and the diplomats inside were ``in solidarity
with the heroic outburst of national bravery'' under way in his
homeland.
   The Romanian Embassy in Yugoslavia declared that it fully
supports the provisional government in Romania, the Yugoslav news
agency Tanjug reported.
   Press Attache Ion Makovei, speaking on behalf of Ambassador
Dumitru Popa and the embassy staff in Belgrade ``strongly
condemned'' Ceausescu's ``criminal actions in Romania,'' Tanjug
said.
   In Austria, Romanian Ambassador Trandafir Cocarla said he
represented the new government of his country.
   ``We are very happy that our people can at last live in freedom
and democracy,'' his spokesman said, adding that the embassy was
now called the Romanian Embassy instead of the Embassy of the
Socialist Republic of Romania.
   In Brussels, Belgium, Romanian ambassador George Ciucu said:
``We express our solidarity with ... the Romanian army who are at
the service of the people. The country does not need bloodshed, it
has suffered enough.''
   The staff of the Romanian Embassy in Ankara, Turkey, issued a
statement saying: ``We, the personnel of the Romanian Embassy,
declare that we are giving full support to the aims and the program
of the National Salvation Committee.''
   Jea Moncea, the Romanian ambassador in Spain, told Spain's
national news agency EFE that the embassy in Madrid ``totally
backs'' the provisional government in Romania and ``condemns'' the
Ceausescu regime.
   About 50 Romanian refugees demonstrated outside the Romanian
Embassy in Madrid to denounce the killings in their homeland.
   Romania's ambassador to Israel, Iulian Bituleanu, said his staff
had also decided to support the provisional government. Earlier
today, embassy workers tore the Communist emblem off the embassy
gate and draped across the building a red, black and yellow
Romanian flag with the Communist emblem ripped out.
   ``The entire staff of the Romanian Tel Aviv Embassy has joined
in identifying with the people,'' Bituleanu told journalists.
   The Romanian ambassador in Canada, Emilian Rodean, said he hoped
the uprising achieves a ``real Romania.''
   Speaking in Ottawa, Rodean said he and his staff applauded
Romanians for throwing out ``the personal dictatorship regime of
Ceausescu.''
   He said he and the staff had not received any instructions from
Romania since the hard-line Communist leader was ousted.
   Luchian Petrescu, the charge d'affaires at the Romanian Embassy
in Dhaka, Bangladesh, said in a statement that the embassy ``fully
and firmly supports the political program of the committee of
national salvation.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>