<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 1122EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-NuclearDelays Bjt   12-31 0780</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nuclear Delays, Bjt,760</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nuclear Waste Projects Fell Farther Behind in 1989</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After years of costly delay in solving
America's nuclear waste disposal problems, the Energy Department in
1989 expected to take two big steps forward. Instead it took three
backwards.
   Thus, four decades after the nation began splitting atoms to
make electricity for consumers and nuclear weapons for the
military, prospects for permanently isolating the long-lived
reactor wastes from the human environment remain in doubt.
   In 1989, the Energy Department under a new secretary, retired
Adm. James D. Watkins, was to have broken ground on an exploratory
shaft at Nevada's Yucca Mountain to study the desert site's
suitability as an underground dump for high-level nuclear waste.
Nevada resisted, and Watkins retreated to reevaluate the whole
project.
   Progress toward opening a dump, Watkins said, was crucial to
reviving the civilian nuclear power industry, which canceled more
reactors during the 1980s that it completed. Public opposition to
further expansion of the nuclear industry is based in part on
concern about a buildup of wastes at reactor sites nationwide.
   About 18,000 metric tons of high-level radioactive waste
currently are stored in cooling ponds in 41 states, and the waste
total is expected to double by 1995.
   By November, Watkins had decided the Yucca Mountain shaft would
be delayed at least two years because of Nevada's resistance and
other problems. Also, he pushed back the projected opening date of
a waste dump to 2010 _ a seven-year delay.
   To make matters worse for Watkins, Nevada in the final week of
the year told the department it would not grant state environmental
permits to study the site, and then filed suit in federal court
seeking to force the project out of the state.
   The future of the Nevada project is likely to be one of the
hottest items on Watkins' agenda in 1990. Besides the legal and
political battles with Nevada, Watkins must find someone to manage
the on-site work. The company he planned to pay $1 billion to
manage the site, Bechtel Systems Management Inc., was disqualified
by a federal judge in August who said the selection process was
unfair.
   Henson Moore, the deputy energy secretary, has sought to cast
the Yucca Mountain delays in a positive light, saying Watkins now
has ``a very doable game plan'' that will restore public confidence
in the department's ability to complete the project, which already
has chewed up about $500 million of utility ratepayer funds.
   A less dramatic but equally troublesome setback for Watkins was
his failure to open in New Mexico the nation's first permanent dump
for plutonium-contaminated wastes from government nuclear weapons
plants.
   As late as June 3, Watkins was reassuring the public that the
$800 million Waste Isolation Pilot Plant, buried in a salt cavern
near Carlsbad, N.M., would begin accepting nuclear waste in
September as scheduled. He cautioned against ``inaccurate public
alarm'' over problems that could delay the project. Three weeks
later, though, he officially abandoned the September starting date
and said the best he could hope for was an opening sometime next
summer.
   Construction of the New Mexico dump is virtually complete, but
efforts to certify its safety have been plagued by doubts that it
would contain the long-lived wastes as specified by regulations of
the Environmental Protection Agency.
   Delays in the New Mexico project in 1989 created yet a third
waste disposal problem: where to temporarily store
plutonium-contaminated wastes from the Rocky Flats nuclear weapons
plant in Colorado. Idaho, which had been accepting surplus Rocky
Flats waste, imposed a ban last September. Gov. Cecil Andrus said
he acted because the department failed to open the New Mexico dump
as promised.
   This added still another twist to the waste dilemma: Since waste
storage at Rocky Flats is approaching a limit agreed to by the
Energy Department, the plant would be forced to close in 1990 if no
alternative storage can be found early in the year.
   Watkins in October tried to persuade seven states _ Washington,
Idaho, Colorado, Nevada, New Mexico, Tennessee and South Carolina _
to accept equal portions of excess Rocky Flats waste next year in
order to keep the plant open. But all seven governors turned him
down, and the problem remains unresolved.
   Stephen A. Wakefield, the department's general counsel, said
last week the Rocky Flats waste storage limit of 1,600 cubic yards
is likely to be reached by next summer.
   Because operation of Rocky Flats is of ``paramount national
importance,'' President Bush could force states to accept waste
from the plant, Wakefield said.
   ``We have the club in the closet, but it's a last resort,'' he
said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>