<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0099 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1537EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Learnfare Bjt   12-19 0738</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Learnfare, Bjt,0763</SECOND>
<HEAD>New `Learnfare' Program Gets Mixed Reception</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL C. BUELOW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JANESVILLE, Wis. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Katie Cooper, a single parent on
welfare, says she had hit rock bottom a year ago before a state
program that tied welfare benefits to her son's school attendance
changed her life.
   Learnfare, introduced in March 1988, aims to keep teen-agers
from welfare families in school by threatening to cut the family's
welfare benefits when a child is truant.
   The program has its critics, but Ms. Cooper isn't one of them.
   Her 17-year-old son, Travis, was on drugs last year and had
missed so many days of school that the family's Aid to Families
with Dependent Children was about to be cut.
   ``Things looked so bleak,'' Ms. Cooper said. ``I thought, `How
the hell was I gonna pay the bills?'''
   AFDC benefits in Wisconsin range from $249 to $983 a month,
depending on the family's size. Learnfare cuts those benefits by
$20 to $192 a month for each month a family's child or children
fail to regularly attend school. Food stamps and other public
assistance programs are not affected.
   The threat of losing part of their benefits forced Ms. Cooper
and her son to change their ways.
   Travis, a senior, has improved his grades from F's to C's and
will graduate in May.
   Although Learnfare didn't make Travis love school, ``it kept him
there,'' Ms. Cooper said. ``That's what's important.''
   And Ms. Cooper, who battled drug addiction and an abusive
marriage before setting out on her own 11 years ago, has attended a
two-year college, while working part time as a waitress, and will
receive a degree in marketing this month.
   About 2,200 of the estimated 30,000 teen-agers whose families
receive AFDC have been penalized each month.
   Critics claim the threat of losing benefits gives troublesome
teen-agers a tool by which to hold their parents hostage.
   ``It forces families and children to lie, to commit fraud for
the money they need to live on. (It) keeps people in that vicious
circle,'' said Geneva Johnson, president of Family Service America,
a Milwaukee-based social service organization.
   Supporters, however, argue education is the first step to
breaking the cycle of welfare dependency and that Learnfare is a
strong tool to encourage students to get an education.
   Patricia Goodrich, secretary of the state Department of Health
and Social Services, which oversees Learnfare, said the program has
``brought to the attention of AFDC recipients that education is
important.''
   The state has applied to the U.S. Department of Health and Human
Services to expand the program to include children in elementary
school.
   Dorthea Harrington, a program manager for the federal agency's
regional office in Chicago, said no decision has been made on the
application and that the government has not yet evaluated Learnfare.
   Nancy Campbell, a branch chief for Health and Human Services in
Washington, said no other state has asked permission to implement
Learnfare although some have expressed an interest.
   She said Ohio has enacted a program somewhat similar to
Learnfare, but that program uses incentive payments rather than
benefit cuts to encourage welfare recipients to stay in school.
   In Wisconsin, schools are given lists of children whose families
receive AFDC and they notify Mrs. Goodrich's agency when one of
those students has three or more unexcused absences in a month.
   The agency warns the family benefits will be cut for the next
month and the deduction is made if the family does not appeal.
Families may appeal on the grounds that there were extenuating
circumstances for the absences, that the cuts will cause undue
hardship on the family or that attendance records were incorrect.
   Legal Action of Wisconsin Inc. of Milwaukee, a legal advocacy
group, recently filed suit challenging Learnfare's
constitutionality. It has handled appeals for about 200 to 250
families and won about 75 percent of the cases.
   Patricia DeLessio, an attorney for the group, said one criticism
of the program is that the welfare cuts do nothing to meet the
needs of troubled students who miss school.
   School officials ``don't sit down with the teen-agers and find
out what the problem is and try to provide services to meet their
needs,'' she said.
   Mrs. Goodrich said efforts to investigate the reasons for
truancy are part of the proposal to expand Learnfare.
   ``There's a concern that there's a real reason for the majority
of these youngsters missing school,'' she said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>