<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1239EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r k BC-EditorialRdp     12-27 0537</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Editorial Rdp,0563</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are excerpts from recent editorials in newspapers
throughout the country.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Dec. 21
   Warren (Ohio) Tribune-Chronicle on the Panama invasion:
   We can find plenty of reasons for wishing President George Bush
had not invaded Panama Wednesday to oust dictator Manuel Noriega.
Furthermore, Bush pulled the trigger on what, at first glance,
looks like flimsy pretexts.
   Noreiga did virtually declare war with the United States Friday,
and his actions in the next few days were troubling. But, while we
do not mean to belittle anyone's life, only one U.S. citizen was
killed before the invasion. ...
   And while Wednesday's well-orchestrated events began with the
swearing-in of a democratic government, our invasion made it our
government, in a sense our puppet. And yet, deep inside, we have a
gut feeling that justice just might have been served. ...
   We should be humble and perhaps even a little ashamed we had to
resort to violence. But Noriega by all accounts did deserve to be
ousted and should be brought to trial. In that light, perhaps a
more apt comparison than the invasion of Czechoslovakia may be the
killing in Romania. Would we protest if Soviet President Gorbachev
invaded Romania to put a stop to the killing there?
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Dec. 24
   The Greenwood (Miss.) Commonwealth on the Panama invasion:
   President Bush's decision to invade Panama, we're certain, will
be well received by the American people. His popularity rating will
shoot upward.
   This is the president who has been criticized for being too
cautious and too prudent _ a wimp, some have called him. Now he's
playing Rambo.
   Few nations are applauding. U.S. might does not necessarily mean
right, despite the fact that Noriega was a disreputable dictator
who pushed his luck too far and who should have been dumped.
   But many Americans do not properly appreciate the sensitivity of
the Latin Americans to intervention by Uncle Sam. The Latins have a
name for it _ gunboat diplomacy.
   The United States has no legal or moral right to intervene in
the affairs of independent nations.
   ... In this case, Noriega made it easy for Bush.
   In retrospect, we wonder why our government made it so hard for
Noriega to step down peaceably. Why did we insist that he be tried
on drug charges? ... We should have eased him out, cajoled and
persuaded him to resign, then slipped him away to exile.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Dec. 25
   The Birmingham (Ala.) News on the Panama invasion:
   Panama may have lost a tinhorn dictator last week, but in the
near future it will gain about $375 million in assets and
multi-millions more in back taxes from U.S. companies.
   Looks like a pretty good swap from here.
   The United States cut off all military and economic aid to
Panama in July 1987 in an attempt to force Manuel Noriega from
power.
   Further sanctions sharply restricted U.S. companies that do
business in Panama, froze Panamanian assets held in the United
States, held payments relating to operating the Panama Canal in
escrow and forbade American companies from paying taxes and fees to
the Noriega regime.
   But those sanctions probably hurt the poor people of Panama more
than Noriega.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>