<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0228EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Japan-Markets 2ndLd-Writethru   12-26 0414</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Markets, 2nd Ld-Writethru,a0666,0425</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stocks Hit Another Record High, Dollar Lower</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Lead with 3 grafs to UPDATE with closing Nikkei, dollar. Pickup
4th graf ``Share prices...''</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The key index on the Tokyo Stock Exchange closed at
yet another record high Tuesday, while the dollar edged down
against the Japanese yen.
   The 225-issue Nikkei Stock Average gained 257.69 points, or 0.67
percent, ending at 38,681.31. The index had gained 383.25 points
Monday as investors welcomed the third discount rate increase by
the Bank of Japan this year. The previous record was 38,586.18 on
Dec. 18.
   The dollar closed at 142.37 yen, down 0.35 yen from its finish
of 142.72 yen on Monday, when it fell 0.95 yen. It opened Tuesday
at 142.94 yen and ranged between 142.30 yen and 142.95 yen.
   ``Share prices were higher almost all across the board,'' said
Tatsuo Kurokawa, an analyst with Nomura Securities.
   Although stock investors are normally discouraged by a discount
rate hike, they boosted buy orders following the Monday
announcement by the central bank, mainly because investors were
reassured that there would be no more major changes in monetary
policy for a while, Kurokawa said.
   The Bank of Japan raised the discount rate to 4.25 percent from
its current level at 3.75 percent.
   The discount rate is the rate the central bank charges on its
loans to commercial banks.
   ``A majority of market players think all the negative factors in
the market have disappeared,'' Kurokawa said.
   In currency dealings, the market was quiet becuase many overseas
markets, including those in New York and London, were closed for
Christmas holidays, traders said.
   After the dollar hit a high at 142.95 yen, investors began to
sell the currency for profit-taking and small position adjustments,
they said.
   Toru Kanai, a foreign exchange analyst with New Japan
Securities, Co., said the dollar-yen rate remained inactive because
the market had already responded to the discount rate hike Monday.
   ``The market had been well prepared for the hike since the rumor
had come out last Tuesday,'' Kanai said. ``Everybody knew there
would be a 0.5 percentage point hike, so the hike yesterday had
little impact.''
   Also, traders said that a mere 0.5 percentage-point raise would
not boost yen-buying because Japan's discount rate is still
substantially lower than those of other industrialized nations.
   Market players were reluctant to buy the dollar as well, due to
uncertainties over whether the U.S. Federal Reserve Board will cut
its discount rate, Kanai said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>