<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0109 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 2008EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-Hostages 1stLd-Writethru a0598 12-23 0336</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Hostages, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0598,0349</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Hostages Released, Say They Were Held By Soldiers</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS thruout with quotes from hostages at press conference.
No pickup.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two Americans held hostage in Panama
were released Saturday, and they said their captors included
current or former Panamanian soldiers who indicated they might kill
them.
   But the hostages, CBS producer Jon Meyersohn and Doug Mullen, an
American businessman, said they had not been mistreated during
their captivity.
   The two were taken captive Wednesday at the Marriott Hotel in
Panama City as the U.S. assault on Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega's
forces reached its height.
   Meyersohn told a news conference in Panama City that he and
Mullen were taken to several locations during their captivity,
first to a jungle clearing, then to a farmhouse, then to an
apartment in the city.
   He said their hands had been tied, they were at one point bound
to trees, and they feared for their lives.
   They gave ``no inclination they weren't going to kill us,''
Meyersohn said.
   He said they were held in the jungle by five captors _ three men
and two women _ armed with knives, pistols, grenades, and automatic
weapons. The captors were either current or former members of the
Panamanian Defense Forces, he said.
   Meyersohn said Mullen persuaded the captors to let them make a
telephone call Friday, allowing them to contact their families and
employers. They were released Saturday at a neutral location.
   A statement by the U.S. Embassy said the embassy ``worked
diligently to secure their release.''
   Meyersohn said the captors were very disorganized and undecided
about what to do with their hostages.
   ``Once they realized they couldn't bargain for us, they held us
for their security,'' Meyersohn said. ``They just didn't know what
to do.''
   Mullen called the captivity ``a roller-coaster ride.''
   ``I was very conscious of the fact that in Panama at this time,
there were a lot of desperate people, and desperate people do
desperate things.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>