<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0129 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1715EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Hungary     12-21 0687</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hungary,0710</SECOND>
<HEAD>Parliament to Dissolve in March, to Pave Way for Elections</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALEX BANDY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUDAPEST, Hungary (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Parliament on Thursday voted to
dissolve itself on March 16, paving the way for the first free
elections in the country in more than four decades.
   Before it dissolves, however, Parliament will begin discussing a
motion at its January session calling for the complete withdrawal
of all Soviet troops from Hungary. Defense Minister Ferenc Karpati
announced plans for the continued withdrawal as part of Moscow's
unilateral troop pullout from Eastern Europe.
   Dispensing with the usual show-of-hands voting, 320 deputies
decided by roll call vote to end parliament's mandate March 16.
There were two abstentions and no votes against.
   The house also adopted the government's budget for 1990 which
foresees strict austerity measures agreed with the International
Monetary Fund.
   Negotiations with the IMF for hard-currency loans necessary to
help Hungary service its $20 billion foreign debt and revamp its
economy hinged on the adoption of the budget.
   No date was set for the elections, the first free balloting
since the Communists took power in 1948. Acting president Matyas
Sueros was to announce a date by Friday.
   Elections were due in June but there have been increasing calls
for them to be moved up.
   Hungary is one of at least four East European nations expecting
their first free elections since the communists took power more
than 40 years ago in the first half of 1990.
   In East Germany, elections are scheduled for May 6. In Bulgaria
and Czechoslovakia, plans have also been announced for free
elections before the end of June.
   The budget adopted by parliament after considerable debate, is
to lead to price rises as subsidies on consumer goods prices are
reduced and could contribute to unemployment as loss-making firms
are closed down.
   The IMF wants to see the country's budget deficit, which is
likely to reach $800 million this year, cut to $156 million in 1990
as a precondition to further loans.
   A crucial $1 billion World Bank loan hinges on the IMF agreement
as does a $1.14 billion loan from the European Community.
   Hungary is to resume its negotiations with the IMF in January.
   In presenting the budget Wednesday, Finance Minister Laszlo
Bekesi said there would be a drastic reduction of subsidies to loss
making companies by $720 million, which in turn could double or
even quadruple the number of unemployed, currently at 25,000.
   Subsidies on consumer and producer prices are also to be reduced
which will lead to price increases averaging 25 percent on foods
starting in January.
   Bekesi said the budget was designed to ``avoid economic
collapse,'' and he called it a ``crisis budget.''
   The house Wednesday adopted a new bill on housing that will lead
to an increase of average rents by 35 percent starting Feb. 1. It
also levied a home loan tax.
   Bekesi said interest payments on the country's $20 billion
foreign debt will amount to $1.5 billion in 1990 and payment on the
principle would be another $1.9 billion.
   As part of the country's ongoing economic reform designed to
introduce market forces into the economy, the government's economic
program foresees initiating bankruptcy proceedings against
unprofitable enterprises, lifting state control of wages, and
moving towards increased privatization of industry.
   Retired Brig. Gen. Janos Sebok put a motion before Parliament
for the withdrawal of the estimated 50,000 Soviet troops in Hungary
by the end of 1990, saying there was no longer any military or
political reason for them to be there.
   Karpati said a tactical missile brigade, a fighter bomber air
wing, a mechanized rifle regiment, two armored car battalions and
two contruction troops would be withdrawn next year, the state news
agency MTI reported.
   He did not say how many troops that would entail. More than
10,000 troops were withdrawn from Hungary this year.
   A year ago, Soviet leader Mikhail S. Gorbachev announced a plan
to withdraw 50,000 troops stationed in Hungary, Czechoslovakia and
East Germany.
   On Wednesday, Czechoslovakia and Moscow agreed a joint
commission should by mid-January start reviewing the presence of
80,000 Soviet troops in Czechoslovakia.
</TEXT>

</DOC>