<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1328EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China     12-28 0723</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China,0746</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Ordered to Be Alert Against Subversion; Campuses Restive</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHY WILHELM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Premier Li Peng on Thursday ordered the People's
Armed Police to keep alert against subversion, and the Foreign
Ministry vowed that political changes in East Europe won't affect
China.
   Chinese authorities are raising defenses _ with both
surveillance and by ideological work _ against any renewal of
pro-democracy protests inspired by Romania's example.
   Work units began holding political meetings to instruct their
employees not to let the ouster of Romania's hard-line president,
Nicolae Ceausescu, shake their faith in socialism.
   More plainclothes police were seen on Beijing's college
campuses, where several anonymous, illegal posters have gone up in
the past week mocking Ceausescu and urging China to learn from
Romania.
   At Beijing University, Qinghua University, Beijing Normal
University and other colleges whose students led massive
pro-democracy protests in Beijing in the spring, Romania was the
main topic of conversation, with most students expressing joy over
Ceausescu's ouster.
   Several Chinese and Western sources said students at two
colleges planned marches to celebrate events in Romania but were
found out and stopped. The reports could not be independently
confirmed.
   The Beijing city government reiterated Thursday that it or the
central government must approve any gatherings or demonstrations in
Tiananmen Square, the focal point of the spring protests. The
central government recently approved a law making most
demonstrations illegal.
   The official Xinhua News Agency said Li, party General Secretary
Jiang Zemin and top military and police officials met with the
party committee of the People's Armed Police, an armed force
separate from the army that is responsible for guarding state
installations and putting down major disturbances.
   Li paid tribute to the force for helping crush the spring
democracy movement, but added, ``China faces a long-term struggle
and we cannot afford to slacken our vigilance,'' Xinhua said.
   It said he told the force to ``firmly fight against any hostile
forces that try to subvert the socialist system in China.''
   On Wednesday, Li told a meeting of the State Council, China's
Cabinet, that ``despite the changes in the international situation,
China will maintain a firm belief in itself (and) adhere to the
socialist direction.''
   Foreign Ministry spokesman Jin Guihua reiterated the message
Thursday at a weekly news briefing.
   ``We are well-convinced that socialism will eventually overcome
the difficulties on its way ahead and continue to develop,'' he
said.
   ``With regard to what impact the situation in Romania and in
East Europe as a whole will have on China, I just want to say that
each country has its own circumstances.''
   Although China has maintained outward neutrality on the collapse
of Communism's monopoly of power in East Europe, Chinese and East
European sources say Chinese leaders privately regard the changes
as revisionist, or ideological backsliding.
   Chinese sources said authorities have issued a document setting
forth the line on Romania, stressing the need for sobriety and
faith in socialism.
   Work units have begun holding special meetings on the subject.
Teachers at the Beijing Normal University were called to such a
meeting Wednesday.
   Although students and foreign teachers said excitement over
Romania was high on campuses, they noted that students are busy
with end-of-term exams and will begin leaving for winter vacation
in a week, reducing chances for any efforts at protests.
   After initially maintaining silence on events in Romania, the
official Chinese media has reported Ceausescu's ouster and
execution, although tersely. It has not mentioned the reasons for
the uprising or the mass arrests and killings of civilians by
secret police, but many Chinese have heard such reports on foreign
radio broadcasts.
   Xinhua also reported that Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev
has sent a series of letters to Chinese leaders, with a senior
Soviet envoy presenting the latest one on Thursday.
   Xinhua did not say what was in the letters.
   The letter was given to Zemin by Valentine Falin, director of
the Soviet party's International Department.
   Xinhua said Jiang ``expressed his thanks to Falin for the letter
and to the Soviet ambassador, who had also passed on letters from
Gorbachev to Jiang and Deng Xiaoping,'' China's senior leader.
   Falin, who arrived Saturday, is the highest-ranking Soviet
official to visit Beijing since May, when Gorbachev came to
normalize state relations and restore party ties broken in the
1960s over ideological differences.
</TEXT>

</DOC>