<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0188 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1708EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-SlugKiller     12-27 0426</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Slug Killer,0440</SECOND>
<HEAD>To Kill Crop-Eating Slugs, Kill Quackgrass</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When it comes to quackgrass, a slimy,
crop-chewing slug is a dead duck, the Agriculture Department said
Wednesday.
   Weed scientist Roger D. Hagin of the department's Agricultural
Research Service said that when quackgrass is killed, it releases a
compound into the soil that acts as a nerve poison against slugs.
   ``The poison is highly specific to slugs,'' he said. ``It has
been tested with no ill effects on three species of freshwater
snails, as well as mammals in general.''
   Hagin, who works at the agency's Plant Protection Research Unit
in Ithaca, N.Y., has isolated and synthesized the quackgrass
compound. A patent on the material is in the works, which could
clear the way for commercial development of a new lethal bait for
slugs.
   Commercial poisons are available now to kill slugs, but those
also are toxic to birds and animals, he said. The quackgrass
treatment could be applied at much lower rates and at less cost.
   Hagin field-tested the compound for two years in snapbeans,
alfalfa and other crops. He said the snapbean yields were nearly
doubled as a result of reduced slug damage.
   Quackgrass is widespread and competes strongly for fertilizer
and water in crops such as corn, soybeans and forages, Hagin said.
   Slugs are especially troublesome in humid areas and have taken a
heavy toll of West Coast strawberry fields and citrus orchards.
Hagin said they also interfere with corn production on the East
Coast.
   Further, slugs are a serious problem in no-till or
minimum-tillage farming, where the soil is not cultivated heavily.
   ``We're currently looking at the possibility of using the slug
poison compound as a seed treatment in minimum-tillage
situations,'' Hagin said. ``We might be able to get the crop plants
to take this material up as a defense against slug attacks.''
   Hagin accidentally discovered the quackgrass connection in 1981
after he had used herbicides to get rid of weeds before he planted
no-till corn on land where red clover had been raised.
   ``When the corn was about six inches tall, I noticed that slugs
were attacking it heavily,'' he said. ``But there were little
islands in the field where quackgrass had been growing with the
clover, and in those areas the slugs weren't attacking the corn at
all.''
   Quackgrass is known to leave two ``allelopathic'' chemical
compounds behind in the soil that inhibit the growth of certain
other plants. But those are different from the compound that kills
the slugs, Hagin said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>