<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0192 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1935EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-PrayersAnswered     12-22 0571</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Prayers Answered,0588</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mom Says Prayers for Transplant Recipient Answered</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SARAH NORDGREN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The thoughts and prayers of people across the
country have been answered on behalf of a tiny medical pioneer who
received part of her mother's liver in a precedent-setting
operation, the girl's mother said Friday.
   Doctors tell the family that 22-month old Alyssa Smith likely
will spend Christmas with her family and may leave the hospital by
the new year.
   ``We have really been blessed by the people and their generosity
and thoughtfulness in expressing their concern,'' Alyssa's mother,
Teri, said Friday as she sat by her daughter's bedside.
   Cards and ``many, many teddy bears'' have come from around the
country. ``When we get home we're going to get a map out and mark
each town we've gotten something from,'' she said.
   Late last month, doctors transplanted part of Mrs. Smith's liver
to her daughter in the nation's first liver transplant from a
living donor.
   A second child who underwent the same operation a few days after
Alyssa, Sarina Jones, also is doing remarkably well, said John
Easton, a spokesman for the University of Chicago Medical Center.
   Both children were in critical condition, but stable, Friday,
Easton said.
   Like Alyssa, 16-month-old Sarina, of Millington, Tenn., suffers
from biliary atresia, a usually fatal congenital defect that is the
leading cause of liver transplants in children.
   Doctors have said previously that the living-donor organ
segments the children received have performed much better than the
cadaver donors previously used in such operations. Use of a living
donor also offers a possible solution to the chronic shortage of
available cadaver organs for infants.
   Alyssa, who comes from Schertz, Texas, near San Antonio, likely
will be given a ``day pass'' to spend Christmas Day with her family
at a Chicago home for relatives of ailing children, Mrs. Smith said.
   ``She'll be able to eat lunch with us and open her gifts away
from the hospital,'' said Mrs. Smith, who was released from the
hospital two weeks ago. ``We're going to be together as a family _
that's a plus.''
   Mrs. Smith, a fourth grade teacher who has been on television
and in newspaper pictures since the historic operation, went
Christmas shopping Thursday and returned with more than her
purchases, Easton said.
   ``Wherever they went, people would stop and recognize her.
People would figure out who she was and say, `Take this back for
your little girl,''' he said.
   Sarina was much sicker than Alyssa at the time of her operation,
which makes her recovery slower, Easton said.
   ``A biopsy detected some minor rejection Wednesday, and they're
watching that,''eceived part of the liver of her father, Robert, during
the operation. The transplanted liver has performed well, and
Easton said doctors are optimistic.
   ``I think everyone is real pleased,'' he said. ``Her liver began
functioning immediately (and is) for all intents and purposes, a
normally functioning liver.''
   And while Sarina and Alyssa are not completely out of the woods,
their families say they trust 1990 will be a better year than 1989
for the young transplant recipients.
   ``We feel very strongly that God's hand has been over us,'' Mrs.
Smith said. ``The thoughts and prayers of the people who responded
have definitely been answered.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>