<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0286 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2115EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-CooperativeBank     12-18 0434</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cooperative Bank,0446</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Lending Agency Fails To Serve Consumers, Nader Group Says</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A little-known government agency created 11
years ago to lend money to cooperative organizations has failed to
adequately serve consumers since it was privatized by the Reagan
Administration in 1982, a group affiliated with activist Ralph
Nader charged Monday.
   The Nader group, Center for Study of Responsive Law, charged at
a news conference that the National Cooperative Bank has in effect
used the subsidy from a low-interest $184.3 million federal loan to
provide the profits necessary pay its executives high salaries and
provide financial benefits to large cooperatives serving small
businesses rather than consumers.
   In 1988, only 5 percent of the bank's 641 member cooperatives
served businesses rather than individuals, yet 30 percent of the
bank's $199.6 milion in disbursements during the year were to the
business cooperatives, even though the law limits lending to
business cooperatives at 10 percent of the total, according to a
report prepared for the Nader group by Seyoum A. Haregot.
   The report also claimed the bank is not doing enough to serve
low-income consumers or to stimulate the formation of new
cooperatives.
   Nader, in a forward to the report, said bank has abandoned its
``one-cooperative, one vote'' principle in favor of a voting system
that gives control of the organization to large, established
cooperatives.
   He said the bank's managers drove it from ``serving ultimate
consumers and toward a commercial banking model replete with
executive emoluments, all the while enjoying its substantial
taxpayer subsidy.''
   The federal subsidy to the bank totaled $119.5 million from 1982
through 1988, according to Haregot's report. Salaries, benefits and
bonuses to the bank's nine top executives totaled $1.3 million in
1988, including $250,000 to Thomas S. Condit, president and chief
executive officer of the bank, the report said.
   In a written response, Linda R. Lewis, corporate vice president
of the bank, said the salaries were in line with the pay of other
financial institutions and said the bank has not been obligated to
keep its pay comparable to government salaries since its
privatization.
   She said the bank disagreed with Haregot's argument that it lent
too heavily to business-owned cooperatives, saying that ``we
believe a cooperative owned by a business is in fact owned by
ultimate consumers.''
   Also, the bank, at mid-1989, had a low-income loan portfolio of
$131.8 million, she said.
   Rep. Henry B. Gonzalez, D-Texas, chairman of the House Banking
Committee, said he was ``deeply concerned'' about the ``failed
promise'' of the bank and said it would be ``placed on the
oversight agenda of the committee.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>