<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1415EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Chess     12-30 0606</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chess,0628</SECOND>
<HEAD>Garri Kasparov Passes Bobby Fischer, Is Strongest Chessplayer in
History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID GOODMAN</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jan. 1 begins a new era for chess as world
champion Garri Kasparov surpasses American Bobby Fischer to become
the highest-ranked player in history.
   According to the biannual ranking list, published by the
International Chess Federation on Friday and effective from Jan. 1,
Kasparov is rated 2800.
   Fischer's highest rating, based on scores against other
internationally ranked players, was 2785.
   ``It gives me great pleasure,'' said Kasparov, the 26-year-old
Soviet champion. ``At some level it's important for the chess world
that this belongs to the current world champion, to a real player,
not a ghost.''
   Some experts had suggested Fischer could never be bettered,
Kasparov said. ``But now people can see that chess does improve.''
   Fischer overwhelmed Boris Spassky in the 1972 world championship
finale in Rekyavik, Iceland, but refused to defend his championship
crown in 1975. For more than 17 years, the eccentric genius, now
46, has lived a reclusive life in Pasadena, Calif., and has not
competed in public.
   ``It's a stupendous achievement,'' said Grandmaster Larry Evans,
a former U.S. champion who seconded Fischer during his climb to the
top, speaking by telephone from his home in Reno, Nev. ``I would
still like to see a match between Fischer and Kasparov, but it's a
vain hope.''
   ``Kasparov has maintained his level of achievement for many
years, while Fischer simply disappeared.'' Evans said.
   ``Fischer and I belong to different times,'' Kasparov said.
``You can't compare players from different epochs.''
   In 1975 former world champion Mikhail Botvinnik declared, ``In
the hands of this young man lies the future of chess.''
   Eleven years later, Kasparov defeated archrival Anatoly Karpov
in their second title duel and became, at 22, the youngest
titleholder in history.
   When Kasparov crushed Grandmaster Tony Miles 5.5-0.5 in a 1985
match, Miles exclaimed: ``I thought I was playing the world
champion, not some 27-eyed monster who sees everything in all
positions!''
   Impatient, outspoken and decisive, Kasparov publicly criticized
Soviet sports officials a year before Mikhail S. Gorbachev allowed
greater openness.
   Kasparov has a British manager to look after his business
interests, appears live on Western talk shows and has been
interviewed by Playboy magazine.
   In March, he married Maria Aratova, a 24-year-old English
translator for the Novosti news agency.
   In October, he overwhelmed Deep Thought, the world computer
champion 2-0 in a match in New York.
   His remaining ambition, he said, ``is to beat Karpov
convincingly.'' The personal and professional rivalry between the
two has already stretched over a record-breaking 131 games. The
38-year-old Karpov's rating fell back on the new list to 2730.
   Kasparov also is involved in battles away from the board.
   Following a long-running and bitter dispute with the chess
federation president, Florencio Campomanes of the Philippines,
Kasparov in 1986 created an Association of Grandmasters, known as
the GMA, to give palyers a greater say in the running of their game.
   Its aims, he said, are to ``raise the image and financial status
of chess to the highest possible level. To get real support for the
game.''
   At a meeting of the GMA in December, Grandmasters accepted by 4
to 1 a resolution from Kasparov calling for the GMA to take control
of the 1990 world championship final.
   The chess federation has given the match to Lyon, France, but if
Kasparov's move succeeds, the second half of the 10-week title duel
could be staged in the United States. Likely venues are New York,
Los Angeles, San Francisco and Chicago.
   ``There is no doubt I will play in the United States,'' Kasparov
said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>