<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0163 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1613EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-Symposium-Africa Adv31   12-26 0764</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Symposium-Africa, Adv 31,0782</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 31, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WORLD SYMPOSIUM '90s: Africa _ A `Nightmare Scenario'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By REID G. MILLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NAIROBI, Kenya (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bedeviled by wars, corruption,
mismanagement and a burgeoning population, Africa is ending a
decade of economic decline and facing what some experts say could
be a ``nightmare scenario'' in the 1990s.
   The nightmare: increased hunger, disease, poverty and conflict
on a continent already desperately poor and largely unable to
survive on its own without huge doses of foreign aid.
   While warning of possible new violence elsewhere, many observers
predict an end to war in the coming decade in Mozambique, Ethiopia,
Sudan and other embattled African countries as combatants fight to
stalemate and exhaustion.
   Namibia ended the 1980s with an election for a constitutional
assembly and will enter the world of independent nations in the
coming year. Peace also seems close at hand in neighboring Angola.
White-ruled South Africa, which has long meddled in both those
countries, appears to be changing its racial policies, albeit too
slowly for some.
   But, with the exception of South Africa, the possibility of
greater stability in those countries will not automatically bring
prosperity to them or to the vast continent as a whole, say
economists for the World Bank and other institutions.
   The 46 countries of sub-Saharan Africa _ a region of 450 million
people that includes all of the continent's nations except Morocco,
Algeria, Tunisia, Libya, Egypt and South Africa _ had a combined
gross domestic product in 1987 of about $135 billion.
   That was about the same as Belgium, with a population of only 10
million.
   That comparison, as well as any, illustrates the depths of
poverty from which most African nations are struggling to emerge,
only, in many cases, to slip deeper and deeperinto debt and
deprivation.
   The World Bank, in a study that took nearly three years to
complete and was released in late November, says there is a
solution for Africa _ one that depends largely on Africans
themselves and calls for a sharp reversal of past practices.
   The bank, a leading multinational lending institution, blames
many of Africa's problems on corruption, poor government marked by
bureaucratic bungling and misguided economic practices rooted in
Marxist-Leninist theory. All that, it said, must end.
   It was perhaps the bluntest assessment the bank has ever made of
any of the world's economies, but it may have been far easier and
faster to write than the suggested changes will be coming to a
continent whose rulers have too often equated power with plunder.
   The World Bank and others have also stressed the need for a
sharp reduction in Africa's birth rate. At 3.2 percent it is the
highest ever seen anywhere in the world and one that inexorably
accelerates pressures for land, food and jobs and threatens new
internal and cross-border conflicts.
   The population of sub-Saharan Africa in 1965 was only half the
450 million it is now and if current trends continue it will double
again to 1 billion in 20 years. The World Bank estimates that even
if fertility fell tomorrow to two children for each African family,
the continent's population would continue to grow for the next 60
to 70 years.
   ``No region of the world has ever managed to develop with so
high a rate of population growth,'' the bank said.
   Even in those countries where peace has arrived or is on the
horizon, it is likely to take most of the new decade to revive
their war-shattered economies, given optimum circumstances. Some
have fallen not just 10 years behind in the development process,
but 20 or 30.
   The World Bank's prescription for Africa called for increased
aid of about 4 percent a year through the 1990s from the developed
nations. But many African politicians and planners worry that the
East European countries emerging from behind the Iron Curtain _
Poland, Hungary, Czechoslovakia, East Germany and possibly others _
will siphon off aid dollars as they attempt to restructure their
economies with Western help.
   As if those problems weren't enough, a new peril arose in the
1980s that threatens Africa in the coming years with a catastrophe
comparable to the droughts and famines that periodically sweep the
continent.
   It is AIDS.
   Health authorities estimate that 1.5 million to 2 million
Africans, mostly young adults, will die of AIDS in the 1990s,
draining even further the continent's already shallow pool of
skilled workers and forcing many countries to spend more scarce
money on medical services.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Sunday, Dec. 31</NOTE>

</DOC>