<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0237 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0500EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-SPE--Bride&amp;Groom:StoryofaWedding     12-18 1223</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-SPE--Bride &amp; Groom: Story of a Wedding,1251</SECOND>
<HEAD>SPECIAL EDITION</HEAD>
<HEAD>Bride &amp; Groom: Story of a Wedding</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY700, NY701</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BARBARA MAYER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Newsfeatures</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   After obtaining permission in writing from her parents, Donald
Waite proposed marriage to Susan Parsons on bended knee in an open
Hansom cab in the middle of Manhattan, to the cheers of a crowd of
New York onlookers who spotted the ring and clustered around the
cab.
   Since they had been living together for about five years, Don
was pretty sure that Susan would say yes. But he had her parents'
blessing handy, just in case, when he popped the question on Oct.
31, 1988. To nobody's surprise, Susan did say yes.
   What followed was a year of intense planning by the couple for a
wedding that would be personal to them, yet involve their families
and friends.
   The story of how Susan Lynn Parsons, 28, and Donald Merrill
Waite, 48, planned this most important event for both of them is a
good indicator of the new ways of marriage in the United States,
circa 1989-90.
   Their wedding took something from the past and something from
the present, uniting tradition with life today. What was old was
the sense of joy and anticipation in melding two lives into one,
the desire to make vows in front of family and friends, and the
wish to have a wonderful party in a beautiful place, with all the
trimmings of music, delicious food, photos to commemorate the
occasion.
   What was current was their determination that the wedding
reflect their unique history and tastes and that both would play
equal roles in making the party happen.
   The care they put into arranging their wedding also reflects the
couple's determination to make a go of this, the second marriage
for Don and the first for Susan. And their story may be
increasingly typical these days when two out of five marriages
dissolve.
   The couple planned and paid for their wedding themselves,
sharing decisions equally. They held the wedding where they live _
not in the bride's home town _selecting a country farmhouse owned
by Don's brother for the party and a nearby church for the ceremony.
   The event took place on Sunday afternoon, but many guests came
for the weekend. The round of celebrations included a Friday
evening bachelor party, a Saturday afternoon decorating session at
the farm, a buffet dinner Saturday evening at a relative's home,
and a post-wedding brunch on Monday morning for those who stayed
on, when the couple opened their wedding presents.
   Susan, a dancer, and Don met when she applied for a
between-engagements job as a waitress in his Manhattan restaurant.
They had known each other for eight years when Don proposed
marriage, the night she returned from performances in the national
tour company of the show, ``Dirty Dancing.''
   The couple took just under a year to plan their Oct. 8, 1989,
wedding, throwing themselves into it with enthusiasm. Though Susan
researched wedding form in etiquette books, they felt free to
deviate from tradition. In virtually every aspect of the wedding _
from selecting the church and ceremony through menu planning,
attire, music and photography _ they personalized the traditional
choices.
   They looked at sites in New York City where they lived (they
have since moved to California) but decided early that they wanted
a country wedding. After investigating catering halls and country
clubs, they chose a church ceremony and a home party.
   After a 12:30 p.m. service at the Bedford, N.Y., Presbyterian
Church, 140 invited guests made a short drive to ``The Farm,'' the
nearby country home of Don's brother, Ralph Waite, an ordained
Presbyterian minister who is better known as the actor who played
John Walton in ``The Waltons'' television series.
   Ralph, who no longer has a congregation, donned ministerial
robes to participate in his brother's marriage ceremony. Susan was
attended by her two sisters, Don by another brother and his two
grown sons.
   Before the exchange of vows, Ralph offered some personal
reminiscences about the couple, then invited other guests to add
theirs. Don's sons and Susan's dance teacher were among those who
spoke.
   ``There were laughter and tears,'' recalls Susan, who says some
of the speakers surprised her with the depth and sincerity of their
comments.
   After pronouncing the couple man and wife, Alcorn asked all
guests to bless the marriage by responding in unison, ``I do.''
   The Waites lit a candle of unity as part of the service. Then
the scriptural reading from First Corinthians concluded the
ceremony.
   After a short pause for photos, the wedding party reconvened at
the farm for an afternoon of dining and dancing to the music of a
five-piece band. Since the house was not large enough to
accommodate the crowd, Don and Susan rented two heated tents _ one
for dining, one for dancing. The tents were set up against a
backdrop of rural splendor of meadow, trees and distant hills.
   The site set the mood for food and decor. In keeping with the
Waites' preference for an informal party and for healthy whole
foods, caterers Molly Siple and Gillie Holme created a fall harvest
buffet that included ham, roast turkey, cornbread, squashes, New
England baked beans, salads, cheese and fruit and wedding cake. As
guests assembled, hors d'oeuvres of smoked salmon, corn tartlets
filled with chili, smoked trout on endive and cheese crusts were
passed by waiters. Seasonal flowers and vegetables _ pumpkins,
squashes, autumn leaves, chrysanthemums _ decorated each table, the
tents and the grounds.
   Two bars were set up. One was for alcoholic drinks and the other
for non-alcoholic drinks, including a variety of sodas and hot
apple cider.
   ``We went on instinct when interviewing and choosing the
caterer,'' recalled Don.
   Music for dancing was furnished by members of a five-piece band,
all friends of the groom. The photographer, also a friend of the
couple, recorded the event.
   With a beautiful natural setting _ the trees were beginning
their seasonal change to brilliant autumn reds and golds _ not much
decoration was needed. Instead of hiring a florist, the couple,
some guests and their caterer embellished the setting with 35 pots
of chrysanthemums Don bought for the occasion. A wagonload of wood
chips was used to create a pathway, and items already on the
property, such as an antique tractor, were embellished with dried
grasses and leaves and seasonal fruit. A grape arbor was hung with
bunches of grapes.
   It was a wedding celebration that few guests wanted to end. At
twilight, guests slowly began to leave. Then the bride exchanged
her long white dress for jeans and the groom and his attendants
changed from morning coats and tuxedos into work clothes to clean
up the site before going home.
   Out-of-town guests were accommodated in a block of rooms
reserved for them at a nearby Holiday Inn.
   The wedding, however, was not over. On Monday morning, Ralph
hosted a brunch at which the couple opened their gifts. Then on
Tuesday, members of the family who had come from almost every part
of the country gathered once again at the farm. The occasion was a
memorial service for a beloved relative who had died after a long
illness. ``We were afraid it might be a downer,'' recalled Don,
``but it was a joyous occasion.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>