<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1520EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-TutwilerProfile     12-25 1070</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tutwiler Profile,1060</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Debutante Reigns in One of Washington's Most Visible Jobs</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY8</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also ran for AMS</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   She sits at the negotiating table with Mikhail
Gorbachev, advises James A. Baker III, travels on Air Force One
with George Bush and spars daily with the nation's foreign policy
pundits.
   But Margaret DeBardeleben Tutwiler, a Birmingham, Ala.,
debutante with a thick Southern drawl, says it's ``laughable,
ludicrous, embarrassing'' to suggest she's one of the most powerful
women in Washington.
   Others disagree.
   The 39-year-old Tutwiler, a longtime aide to Secretary of State
Baker, wears the twin hats of assistant secretary of state for
public affairs and the State Department's spokeswoman, one of the
most visible jobs in government.
   As spokeswoman _ she's the first woman to be assistant secretary
of state for public affairs _ the workaholic, unmarried Tutwiler
appears almost every day on the klieg-lighted podium to explain
U.S. foreign policy to reporters and television audiences around
the world.
   It's a long way from Finch College, Tricia Nixon's alma mater
and the New York school Tutwiler attended before she transferred to
the University of Alabama.
   While Tutwiler's face has become familiar in the last year, most
Washington insiders say her influence stems more from her access to
Baker than her sessions at the podium or her knowledge of
diplomatic nuance.
   ``Her greatest strength has always been her close relationship
with Jim Baker and her knowledge of what he is doing and
thinking,'' said John McWethy, ABC's State Department correspondent.
   Theodore Wilkinson, president of the American Foreign Service
Association, agreed.
   A career foreign service officer undoubtedly would have a
stronger grasp of policy, but probably wouldn't have Tutwiler's
``great asset'' _ her access to Baker, he said.
   So if access is power _ and in Washington it is _ Tutwiler has
it.
   Amidst the oriental rugs and antiques on the department's
exclusive seventh floor suite, Tutwiler's well-appointed cubbyhole
has a door leading to Baker's office.
   And friends and colleagues say she's not bashful about opening
it to tell her boss of nearly a decade what she thinks on subjects
ranging from sanctions against China to briefing times during the
storm-tossed U.S.-Soviet summit on Malta.
   Behind the Southern belle is a steel magnolia, say those who
have seen Tutwiler cross wires with the likes of Gennady Gerasimov,
Gorbachev's spokesman.
   ``She has good judgment and instincts about the public's
reaction,'' says V. Kim Hoggard, Tutwiler's deputy. ``She judges by
her own reaction ... that's why Baker values her advice.''
   ``Levelheaded'' is the way her childhood friend, Virginia
Scruggs, describes Tutwiler.
   Tutwiler, although reluctant to engage in self-promotion, says
her assets are her loyalty and her forthright manner.
   ``I know he thinks I'm loyal,'' she said of Baker. And in
sessions with the secretary and others in his inner circle, she
said she speaks her mind. ``I'm not playing a game with him, in
other words. Many times I say what I believe.''
   Tutwiler's relationship with Baker was forged in the 1980s when
she was his assistant at the White House, at the Treasury
Department and on the 1988 Bush presidential campaign.
   She came to the White House after working in Bush's unsuccessful
1980 presidential primary campaign. Ronald Reagan captured the GOP
nomination, but named Bush as his running mate. She counts both
Baker and Bush as her friends.
   Although Tutwiler served as an assistant secretary at the
Treasury Department, she preferred to remain behind the scenes,
rarely briefing reporters or talking in public.
   That changed at the State Department.
   ``It was very terrifying and frightening to me to grapple with,
`Can I do this job that the president and secretary of state would
like for me to try to do?,''' she said.
   Besides appearing on television, Tutwiler had to grapple with
the subject matter.
   ``I'll be honest with you. It was absolutely overwhelming,'' she
said. ``To learn all at once the United States' foreign policy in
Cambodia, in Afghanistan, in Nicaragua, in El Salvador, in arms
control ... to learn all our policies about Germany ... to learn
the world, at once.''
   In the daily press briefings, the stylish Tutwiler _ with her
fashionable clothes and streaked blonde hair _ usually reads,
verbatim, statements prepared by diplomats on issues of the day. At
times, she seems stilted, fearful of making a mistake.
   McWethy and others say she's getting better. ``Without question,
her performance at the briefings has improved and she has a better
grasp of the subject matter,'' he said.
   Tutwiler's glamorous career hasn't come without some sacrifice,
mainly her personal life.
   ``I really haven't had one,'' Tutwiler said. ``I always keep
putting my other interests on the back burner and I'm definitely
doing that here.''
   An organized perfectionist, Tutwiler keeps a grueling schedule.
She rises at 5:30 a.m., is at her desk at 6:30 a.m., and rarely
returns to her home in fashionable northwest Washington before 9
p.m. Breakfast and dinner often consist of cheese and crackers at
her desk.
   Then there is the seemingly non-stop travel _ over 126,000 miles
since February to places as far away as Australia.
   In December, she traveled to Malta for the summit, and then
accompanied Baker to London, Berlin and Brussels. Later that month,
she went to St. Martin with Baker. At Christmas, she's going skiing
with her brother and sister and their families.
   But Tutwiler's philosophy is that ``life is a tradeoff, a
compromise,'' and she doesn't know many people who would walk away
from the chance to sit at the table with Gorbachev or see the
Kremlin's inner sanctum.
   ``Money can't buy that,'' she said.
   Tutwiler said there will always be time for her other interests,
of which she has many.
   ``I grow roses, I love entertaining. I love reading. I love
biographies of women. I love histories of the South. I enjoy
cooking. I enjoy flower arranging. I enjoy the study of carpets. I
enjoy personal travel.''
   Despite her consuming job, Scruggs, who has known Tutwiler since
the first grade in Birmingham, said Tutwiler is a family-oriented
person, and a ``doting aunt'' who loves spending time with her
nieces and nephews.
   When Scruggs, the mother of two children, gets together with
Tutwiler, the two talk about how they envy parts of the other's
life.
   But Tutwiler seems happy with the choices she's made.
   ``I'm a very lucky, lucky girl,'' she says.
</TEXT>

</DOC>