<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1250EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania-Wealth     12-27 0331</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Wealth,0339</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romania Seeking Swiss Help to Recover Any Ceausescu Assets</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BERN, Switzerland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Romania's provisional governmment will
ask Switzerland for judicial assistance to try to recover any
assets Nicolae Ceausescu may have stashed in Swiss banks before he
was ousted and executed.
   Ambassador Gheorghe Dolgu, who declared his support for the
anti-Ceausescu uprising last week, delivered a diplomatic note to
the Swiss Justice Ministry on Wednesday announcing that a formal
request would follow. The new leadership has two months to detail
its request.
   In anticipation of the request, Switzerland on Sunday froze an
any assets linked to Ceausescu or his clan, addressing itself in
particular to two of its largest banks, Credit Suisse and Union
Bank of Switzerland.
   The action was taken after Moritz Leuenberger, a Social
Democratic member of parliament and lawyer, said he received
information from unidentified Romanian exile sources that Ceausescu
had transferred about $400 million, chiefly gold bullion, to
Zurich, much of it in recent weeks and months.
   Justice Ministry spokesman Joerg Kistler said a circular from
the Romanian National Bank dated Dec. 25 asked all countries to
block any Ceausescu accounts they may be spotted.
   According to a videotape of his secret trial released by the new
leadership in Bucharest, Ceausescu denied having assets in
Switzerland and refused to sign a statement authorizing the return
of any such assets to the Romanian National Bank. His wife, Elena,
rejected the military court's question about Swiss funds as a
provocation.
   In Zurich, Union Bank spokeswoman Gertrud Erismann said the
freeze had been ``superfluous because no serious bank would permit
in such a situation permit the withdrawal of funds by people who
may have obtained them illegally.''
   She declined comment when asked whether Union Bank had traced
any funds. Confirming or denying their existence would violate
Swiss banking secrecy laws, she added.
   A Credit Suisse spokesman, Helmut Reinke, said a careful check
had not produced any evidence of Ceausescu-linked assets at the
bank.
</TEXT>

</DOC>