<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1700EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Reax 1stLd-Writethru a0588 12-25 0939</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Reax, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0588,0963</SECOND>
<HEAD>World Remembers Romania, Nations Recognize New Leadership</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs to UPDATE with United States recognizing
provisional gov't, regretting manner of execution. Pick up 7th pvs, `In
at...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EDITH M. LEDERER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The world remembered Romania on Christmas Day with
candles, prayers, food and medical aid, and Bucharest's new
leadership received growing recognition as the legitimate
government.
   The United States established diplomatic relations with the
provisional government, although it expressed regret that deposed
leader Nicolae Ceausescu had not been tried in public before his
apparent execution.
   Bucharest radio said Ceausescu and his wife, Elena, were
executed after a secret military trial.
   ``The United States government pledges its support to the new
Romanian government as it struggles to achieve its announced
democratic values,'' said a White House statement.
   In Moscow, a top Foreign Ministry official said the Soviet Union
effectively recognizes the revolutionary leadership and is in
permanent contact via its embassy in Bucharest.
   However, Deputy Foreign Minister Ivan P. Aboimov repeated Soviet
disclaimers that military aid to the National Salvation Committee
was or had ever been planned.
   ``The point at issue today is humanitarian, medical and food
assistance,'' Vadim Perfilyev, a ministry spokesman, was quoted as
saying by the Soviet news agency Tass.
   The United States and France said Saturday they would not oppose
Soviet bloc intervention to support Romanians fighting police units
loyal to Ceausescu.
   At least 13 nations have recognized the National Salvation
Committee as the legitimate representative of the Romanian people.
In addition to Moscow and Washington, West Germany, Poland, Japan,
Sweden, Thailand and Yugoslavia added their recognition to a list
which already included France, East Germany, Norway, Belgium, the
Netherlands.
   In at least 27 countries, ambassadors from Romania also declared
their support for the provisional government in Bucharest. Those in
Japan and Baghdad announced their support Sunday.
   At the Vatican, Pope John Paul II prayed that the hope of
Christmas might spread through Eastern Europe, and sought a special
blessing for Romania, ``the noble land ... which is celebrating
this Christmas in fear and trembling, with sorrow for the many
human lives tragically lost and in the joy of having taken once
more the path of freedom.''
   In Britain, Archbishop of Canterbury Robert Runcie lighted a
candle for Romania and led Anglicans around the world in prayers
for the thousands who suffered and died there for freedom.
   A vast revolution had started swiftly in Eastern Europe and was
still growing, he said. ``We thought it was all in the past _ the
suffering and deaths of dissidents who never compromised. In the
blood of Romania, the price is writ large in the present.''
   The Soviet Union was evacuating 280 dependents in Romania by
train after two Soviet citizens were wounded in Bucharest and 10
Soviet motorists were hurt in the Romanian-Yugoslav border region,
Perfilyev said. Several other countries have also evacuated the
families of diplomats.
   Around the world, hundreds of groups raised money for Romania,
and governments announced new financial support. The Irish Republic
said it was contributing $45,000 for medical and relief supplies.
   The French Health Ministry said all 1,200 public hospitals in
France are being mobilized to gather and expedite humanitarian aid
to Romania.
   In a statement, the ministry said people could go to any
hospital to donate money or goods, especially medicine, canned
food, blankets and new sheets.
   West German Foreign Minister Hans-Dietrich Genscher said a
military plane carrying 25 tons of relief supplies flew from
Cologne to Bucharest on Monday. Foreign Ministry spokesman Hanns
Schumacher said it was still impossible to drive between Bucharest
airport and the city because of shooting on the road.
   Three military cargo planes carrying medical aid and blood from
the Polish Red Cross and the Defense Ministry left Poland for
Bucharest, the official PAP news agency said. Hundreds of Poles
lined up over the holiday weekend to donate blood, and hundreds of
doctors volunteered to travel to Bucharest to organize a Polish
hospital, Polish news media reported.
   Doctors Without Borders said its fifth planeload of doctors and
supplies for Romania took off from Paris on Sunday. Previous
flights landed in neighboring countries and entered by land, but it
was hoped this one could land in Bucharest.
   Britain also has sent planeloads of supplies.
   Dr. Francois Dumaine of Doctors Without Borders, who returned
Sunday from Romania, said in the city of Sibiu people feared the
water had been poisoned by security forces and were drinking only
from water trucks.
   Hungary sent aid consignments by car and truck across the border
and by military plane to Bucharest. The Bulgarian Foreign Ministry
said three ambulances with 12 medical personnel arrived in
Bucharest.
   Japan said it hopes to send emergency aid to Romania as soon as
possible, according to a senior Foreign Ministry official.
   On the diplomatic front, Genscher instructed Bonn's ambassador
to Bucharest, Klaus Terfloth, to inform the National Salvation
Committee that it was being recognized by West Germany, Schumacher
said.
   A Yugoslav government envoy, Assistant Foreign Secretary Ilija
Djukic, arrived in Bucharest on Monday to establish direct contact
with the Committee, the Yugoslav news agency Tanjug reported.
   The Solidarity-led government in Poland said it considered the
committee to be `the only reliable body representing Romania,''
according to PAP.
   In a dispatch from Beijing, Tanjug quoted unidentified
diplomatic sources as saying the Communist Party Politburo had
discussed ways of presenting the Romanian developments to the
Chinese public without ``rocking the boat.'' It said security
forces in the Chinese capital were put on first-degree alert when
news of the rebellion was finally announced.
</TEXT>

</DOC>