<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0115 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1655EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-EconomicDecisions     12-28 0660</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Economic Decisions,640</SECOND>
<HEAD>Study Says U.S. Facing Tough Economic Decisions in the 1990s</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Budget Gimmicks</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN CRUTSINGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Economics Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United States begins the 1990s facing a
host of tough decisions needed to erase policy mistakes in the last
decade that are threatening America's global economic leadership, a
congressional study concluded Thursday.
   The study, prepared by the staff of the Joint Economic
Committee, said the No. 1 economic problem facing the country was
the federal budget deficit.
   ``Eliminating the deficit will not by itself solve all of our
economic problems or put an end to our national consumption
binge,'' the study said. ``However, we will not solve our most
pressing economic problems unless we reduce the deficit.''
   The study called on President Bush and Congress to come up with
a credible package that would include a mix of both tax increases
and spending cuts to eliminate the deficit.
   The study said policymakers must abandon the budetary gimmicks
they have used in recent years to give a false appearance of making
progress in eliminating a budget deficit that has been stuck near
$150 billion for the past three years.
   ``The economic policies of the 1980s have not prepared us for a
brighter future,'' said committee chairman Rep. Lee Hamilton,
D-Ind., who directed preparation of the new report. ``We need new
economic policies for the 1990s: policies that will improve U.S.
economic performance and make us a richer nation and a fairer one.''
   The study offered a stark assessment of America's economic
prospects if policies are not altered, contending that the United
States must do more to boost savings, increase investment and spur
gains in productivity if the country hopes to compete
internationally.
   ``Our country has been driven for most of this decade not by
investment but rather by a binge of consumption that threatens our
long-run standard of living and our standing as the world's leading
economic power,'' the report said.
   It said the huge federal deficit was the biggest contributor to
this consumption binge, but it also cited a big 20 percent drop in
new business investment over the past 10 years and productivity
growth that is far below the levels of the 1950s and 1960s.
   The study, which did not have the backing of Republican members
of the committee, said it would be impossible to reduce the budget
deficit without tax increases to accompany spending cuts. This is a
conclusion that Bush has repeatedly rejected.
   His administration is putting the finishing touches on a $1.23
trillion budget proposal for next year that will meet the
Gramm-Rudman target of reducing the deficit to $64 billion without
raising income taxes.
   The study said Bush's efforts to rely on rosy economic forecasts
and elusive savings in goverment programs would prove as
unsucessful as similar policies pursued by President Reagan.
   While a tax increase alone would not be politically acceptable,
it could win approval as part of a package deal that would combine
modest tax increases with spending cuts, the study said.
   In other findings, the report predicted that economic growth
prospects over the next year were weak, in part because the effort
to reduce America's huge trade deficits had stalled out with the
trade imbalance stuck at levels above $100 billion a year.
   The report devoted an entire chapter to suggestions on how the
country can resume making progress on trimming the trade deficit,
but it warned: ``Reaching trade balance will be difficult and
painful.''
   It said efforts to boost the savings rate were essential as a
way of curbing over-consumption in the United States and reducing
Americans' appetite for foreign goods. A bigger savings pool would
also provide the capital U.S. industry needs to modernize, the
report said.
   It called for international organizations such as the
International Monetary Fund and the World Bank to devote more
efforts to resolving the Third Word debt crisis, which has severely
limited U.S. export opportunities in Latin America.
</TEXT>

</DOC>