<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0168 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2314EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-MailBombs 3rdLd-Writethru 1stAdd 12-19 0458</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mail Bombs, 3rd Ld-Writethru, 1st Add,0464</SECOND>
<HEAD>UNDATED: the bombings.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   ``He said they were very concerned about it; there are reasons
to believe that at least part of the motivation was racial,''
Lowery said. ``We're very concerned, and I was pleased (that he
called.)''
   FBI agent William Hinshaw in Atlanta said the NAACP's southeast
regional headquarters in Atlanta has been warned that the bombs
appeared to be related to a Aug. 22 tear-gas mail bomb that
exploded there, injuring eight people.
   In Montgomery, Ala., U.S. Marshal Jim Hudson said a federal
judge received a telephone death threat early Tuesday. He would not
identify the judge.
   Police in Birmingham rushed Tuesday to investigate a package
mailed to Councilman David Herring, a longtime friend of Vance. It
turned out to be a delivery from an Atlanta business.
   Meanwhile, a government source in Washington said the bomb that
killed Vance bore the return address of Lewis F. Morgan, a senior
11th Circuit judge in Georgia. Morgan is not a suspect, the source
said, but the discovery means the killer knew a great deal about
Vance's personal habits and friendships.
   Links between Vance and Robinson are not readily apparent, other
than their moderate-to-progressive politics. Vance, who was white,
became known as a racially progressive Alabama Democratic leader
before being elevated to the federal bench, while Robinson was
known as a ``moderate, reasonable'' attorney and politician in
Savannah.
   One of Robinson's biggest cases as a lawyer did go before the
appeals court. He helped represent a black group fighting
desegregation plans by the Savannah-Chatham County schools, which
were approved by the 11th Circuit Court this fall.
   But Vance was not among the three 11th Circuit judges ruling on
the case.
   ``It was a case that we lost _ it wasn't like Robinson could
have been accused of doing anything to upset the community,'' said
Lowell Johnston, the lead attorney from the NAACP Legal Defense
Fund who worked the case with Robinson.
   Earlier this year, the Jacksonville NAACP won from the 11th
Circuit a unanimous decision reinstating school busing in
Jacksonville, overruling a lower court judge who had declared the
school system was integrated. Vance wrote the opinion in that case.
   Vance, 58, ruled in at least one other major race-related case.
The 11th Circuit in 1985 overturned a lower court's ruling and
cleared the way for prosecution of 10 Ku Klux Klansmen for a bloody
May 1979 confrontation with black civil rights marchers in Decatur,
Ala. After the ruling, all 10 defendants pleaded guilty or were
convicted.
   The 11th Circuit, based in Atlanta, handles federal appeals from
Alabama, Georgia and Florida. Authorities said the Atlanta bomb was
in a mailed package addressed to the 11th Circuit court, not to a
particular individual.
</TEXT>

</DOC>