<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0185 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1717EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-UN-Panama 1stLd-Writethru   12-20 0645</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-UN-Panama, 1st Ld - Writethru,a0745,0663</SECOND>
<HEAD>Security Council Has to Choose Between Two Panamanian Governments</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: UPDATES throughout with debate delayed while Security Council
decides which government to recognize.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER JAMES SPIELMANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>UNITED NATIONS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Security Council delayed its debate on
Panama on Wednesday while trying to decide which government is
legitimate: Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega's regime or the
U.S.-installed administration.
   The United States, with the help of other Western members,
stalled the council while pressing for recognition of a new U.N.
ambassador to be appointed by the fledgling Panamanian government
of Guillermo Endara.
   Endara was widely believed to have won the presidency in
Panama's national elections May 7. But Noriega, the military
leader, canceled the balloting before results were announced.
   The overnight invasion by U.S. military forces ousted Noriega
and installed Endara as president.
   Endara was expected to appoint Eduardo Vallarino, a Panamanian
businessman in self-imposed exile in the United States, as its U.N.
ambassador, said diplomats.
   Panama has no ambassador currently accredited at the United
Nations. The previous permanent representative, Leonardo Kam, was
promoted to foreign minister, and no one had taken his place.
   Noriega's government is reportedly trying to have its ambassador
to the European Community, Merla Bellavita, accredited as its U.N.
ambassador.
   The Security Council was originally to hold its emergency
meeting Wednesday morning, said officials at the Mission of
Colombia, which currently chairs the council.
   Diplomats speaking on condition of anonymity said, however, that
wrangles over which Panamanian ambassador was representing the
legitimate government delayed the meeting. Council members held
meetings among themselves to decide how to proceed.
   The Security Council is faced with having to decide which
foreign minister represents Panama's legitimate government:
Noriega's appointee, Kam, or whomever Endara appoints.
   In an afternoon news conference in Washington, Secretary of
State James A. Baker III said Endara is moving to appoint
ambassadors to Washington and the United Nations.
   U.S. Ambassador Thomas R. Pickering said the United States acted
in self--defense when it sent its military forces to Panama to oust
Noriega.
   Alejandro Serrano Caldera, the ambassador of Nicaragua, which
called for an emergency Security Council meeting, retorted that
``the United States has no legal or ethical right to intervene in
other countries' affairs.''
   Speaking in Spanish through an interpreter, Serrano Caldera said
``We want the council to call for an immediate withdrawal of the
U.S. troops.''
   Pickering told reporters outside the council that the United
States had the right to intervene under Article 51 of the U.N.
Charter, ``which provides for the use of armed force to defend a
country, to defend our interests and our people, it's the so-called
`self-defense article.'''
   Panamanian soldiers shot and killed a U.S. Marine officer at a
roadblock on Saturday night.
   Panama's declaration last week that a ``state of war'' existed
with the United States and ``the attacks on our citizens over the
weekend are several of the things which the president has cited
which required us to move in self-defense,'' Pickering said.
   White House press secretary Marlin Fitzwater said President Bush
ordered U.S. troops to seize Noriega and bring him to the United
States for trial on federal drug charges.
   Baker informed Secretary-General Javier Perez de Cuellar of the
military moves by telephone at 2 a.m. Wednesday, said the U.N.
chief's spokesman, Francois Giuliani.
   Perez de Cuellar is ``extremely concerned'' about the crisis,
said Giuliani.
   Panama has repeatedly come before the Security Council to
complain of allegedly provocative U.S. military maneuvers that it
said were intended to lay the groundwork for an invasion to topple
the government.
   Panama claimed during council debates in April and August that
the United States is trying to provoke confrontations in order to
keep control of the Panama Canal.
   Under a 1977 treaty, the United States is to turn over control
of the canal to Panama at the end of 1999.
</TEXT>

</DOC>