<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 2055EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Bush 2ndLd-Writethru a0803 12-24 0664</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0803,650</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Says Panama Emphasis Shifting to `Humanitarian Concerns'</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: TOPS with 7 grafs to eliminate reference to Noriega surrendering,
UPDATE with news agency report that papal nuncio saying he won't turn Noriega
over to US authorities; PICKS UP 8th graf pvs bgng, `After the'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER CONNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush had just returned from a
Pentagon briefing on the situation in Panama on Christmas Eve when
he learned that Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega had sought refuge from
Vatican authorities.
   Bush had interrupted his holiday vacation to fly by helicopter
from the presidential retreat at Camp David, Md., for 90 minutes of
briefings from Pentagon officials on Panama, and he had called Gen.
Maxwell Thurman, commander of the U.S. Southern Command in Panama.
   At the time, he said he had no idea when U.S. troops might
accomplish one of the key goals for their invasion of Panama early
Wednesday, the capture of the deposed Panamanian dictator who is
under U.S. indictment on drug-trafficking charges.
   ``If I knew that, why both of us would be a lot smarter,'' Bush
told reporters after the Pentagon sessions.
   Just a few hours later, Thurman announced in Panama City that
Noriega was at the Papal Nunciate there and was seeking asylum.
   Bush, through White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater, announced
a few minutes later, ``I am pleased that the general is now under
the control of diplomatic authorities. His reign of terror is
over.''
   It was not immediately clear whether the U.S. government would
be able to bring him to the United States to stand trial. The
Italian news agency ANSA quoted the papal nuncio in Panama City,
Monignor Sebastiano Laboa, as indicating he would not hand over
Noriega to the United States or U.S.-installed government in Panama.
   After the Pentagon sessions earlier Sunday, Bush told reporters
outside the Pentagon that ``the emphasis now is on cleaning up the
last parts of resistance, seeing that civilian government take
over, (restoring) tranquility in the city and then moving on food
and medicine.''
   Noting the holiday, Bush said he wanted to express ``my
gratitude to the fine military officers and men who are taking part
in this operation. It's been outstanding.''
   ``I must say that the military, having fulfilled a major
objective _ knocking out the Panamanian Defense Forces almost
entirely _ is now putting a great deal of proper emphasis on
humanitarian concerns,'' he said.
   Bush said Defense Secretary Dick Cheney was on his way to
Panama, where the president said a ``real turnaround'' had occurred
in restoring order.
   ``It's a very good pre-Christmas report that I have received,''
Bush said after his briefing by Gen. Colin Powell, chairman of the
Joint Chiefs of Staff, and national security advisor Scowcroft.
   Bush also commented briefly on the tumult in Romania, saying he
had just spoken to the U.S. ambassador in Bucharest.
   He called the events there ``a very traumatic pre-Christmas
uprising'' but said it appeared that pro-democracy forces, which
include the nation's army, appeared to be gaining ground.
   He said the Romanian military had gained ``a little more
control'' of the country in fighting with remnants of the secret
police, who remain loyal to deposed dictator Nicolae Ceausescu.
   While at the Pentagon, Bush taped a radio message to U.S. troops
around the globe, offering a ``special salute'' to those in Panama
and a tribute to U.S. servicemen who died in the fighting there.
   ``In Panama, as in every other such test in our history,
Americans put their lives on the line for the basic values of
liberty and decency on which our nation is founded,'' he said.
   ``Our hearts and those of every American go out to the families
of those who fell. To all those who mourn a husband, a son, a
brother, a father or a friend, I can only offer the thanks of a
grateful nation. Your loved ones served a noble and just cause with
honor and distinction.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>