<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0164 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1949EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Cold 1stLd-Writethru a0686 12-21 0999</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cold, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0686,1026</SECOND>
<HEAD>Winter's Here? No Kidding!</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: UPDATES throughout with new details, more schools closed. No
pickup.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos CX5, AD1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL HIRSH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Winter began Thursday but almost no one stopped to notice. It
was still too cold.
   The arctic onslaught of record low temperatures that has plagued
much of the nation for 10 days sent another thrust across the
border, closing hundreds of schools from Montana to the Eastern
Seaboard, freezing an Amtrak train in its tracks in North Dakota
and threatening Texas' citrus crop.
   But the double wallop of frigid temperatures and high polar
winds blamed for more than 40 deaths nationwide was expected to
slacken after Friday, promising a Christmas that would be merely
seasonably cold, forecasters said.
   ``We're going to moderate right into Christmas,'' said National
Weather Service forecaster Steve Kahn in Chicago. ``Temperatures
have stopped falling _ they are going to rebound a little bit.''
   That was small comfort across the Midwest and West, where wind
chills Thursday dipped to as low as 83 below in North Dakota, more
than 70 below in Minnesota and Nebraska and 61 below in Illinois.
   In Havre, Mont., an overnight low of 43 below broke a record for
the day set 1884. Chicago set a new record with a minus 13, colder
than in 1872, when the previous record of 12 below zero was set.
   In all, at least 17 cities reported new record low temperatures
for the date Thursday morning, including 20 below zero in Omaha,
Neb.; 19 below in Dubuque, Iowa; 17 below in Des Moines; and 7
below in Topeka, Kan.
   Numerous record lows were likely to be established east of the
Rockies by Friday night, and before the cold wave is over parts of
the country may experience their coldest night of record, according
to National Severe Storms Forecast Center in Kansas City.
   Snow generated by the cold front blew across much of the High
Plains and parts of the central Rocky Mountain region, the Ohio
Valley and the central Appalachian region in the afternoon.
   Weather service officials warned that the subzero temperatures
combined with stinging wind could cause frostbite in a matter of
minutes.
   ``This is just about as bad as it can get in Iowa,'' said
National Weather Service forecaster Scott Truett in Des Moines.
``Especially this time of year.''
   Chicago police opened station doors to the homeless seeking
shelter while waiting for vans to take them to city-operated
warming centers. At least 10 people have died of exposure in the
Chicago area since the cold snap began, said a spokeswoman for the
Cook County Medical Examiner's office.
   Among the deaths elsewhere were two elderly Pittsburgh-area
women whose space heaters, their only source of heat, were not
enough to withstand the cold, officials said. ``Basically it means
they froze to death,'' Deputy Coroner James Gregris said.
   Winter officially began at 4:22 p.m. EST Thursday, but it
clearly had its own timetable. By mid-morning, hundreds of schools
had been closed in Iowa, Minnesota, Nebraska, Kansas, Missouri,
Wisconsin, Ohio and New York.
   Some school officials said they did not want young children
waiting for buses or walking to school.
   ``We thought it might be dangerous,'' said Jean Kennedy, a
spokeswoman for Mthe Parkway school district in the St. Louis, Mo.,
area.
   Business was good at towing companies and auto parts stores, as
customers sought out batteries, thermostats and engine heaters.
Tammy Collett of Council Bluffs, Iowa, said she called 10 towers
for assistance, but only one would send a truck.
   ``They said they were too busy or they wouldn't come out, and
they were all 24-hour towing companies,'' she said. ``It was not
very pleasant, that's for sure.''
   ``We haven't seen anything like this for five years,'' American
Automobile Association spokeswoman Maureen Quinn said in Madison,
Wis. ``The number of road calls for road service is seven times our
normal level.''
   Other businesses that employ outdoor workers gave employees the
day off Thursday. In Indiana, the Salvation Army issued ``take
cover'' warnings to its bell ringers.
   ``The roofers are off,'' said Louise Wolotka, a secretary with
Charles Gluth &amp; Sons roofing company in Gary, Ind. ``Even the
ground crews are off. We wouldn't do that to them. It's too
dangerous with the wind chill up on the roof.''
   ``Everybody's getting calls. I hope it stays like this for
another month,'' said Jason Grosz, a district sales manager in the
Bismarck, N.D., office of the American Automobile Association.
   In Minot, N.D., Amtrak's Empire Builder passenger train came to
a halt as fuel froze in its engine, stranding about 300 passengers
in area motels overnight Thursday.
   Forecasters in Texas and Louisiana feared a worse cold snap than
the December 1983 freeze that virtually wiped out the Rio Grande
Valley's citrus crop, killing hundreds of thousands of orange and
grapefruit trees. Temperatures were expected to drop into the lower
20s Friday and Saturday.
   That disaster crippled the Valley's economy and forced growers
to replant trees that were expected to mature this season and
produce a full crop for the first time.
   In Louisiana, citrus farmers got all hands into the groves,
picking frantically to save as many oranges and satsumas as
possible.
   ``If it gets down to 25 and stays there for five hours, which is
very possible, we would lose the fruit,'' said Gwen Becnel.
   Elsewhere, strong northerly winds produced squalls with heavy
snow in the Great Lakes region. Subzero temperatures and blowing
and drifting snow blanketed parts of upstate New York Thursday
morning. The town of Pulaski was buried under 4 feet of snow in one
night, and 2 feet of snow was reported at Barnes Corners.
   In western Pennsylvania, the arctic cold front was expected to
send the wind chill index plunging to 40 degrees below zero Friday
night.
   Sunny skies and seasonable temperatures prevailed across much of
the West, however, with the Rocky Mountain range serving as kind of
a protective barrier from the arctic invasion.
</TEXT>

</DOC>