<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0090 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1433EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Ethiopia 1stLd-Writethru a0536 12-28 0806</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ethiopia, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0536,0826</SECOND>
<HEAD>Northern Rebels Make Major Gains in New Offensive</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf to raise reference that gov't already Marxist;
SUBS 18th graf, ``The Tigrean ...'' to CORRECT second reference to Mengistu;
SUBS 25th graf ``On Wednesday ...'' to CORRECT years to 1984-85, sted 1985-85.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DIDRIKKE SCHANCHE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NAIROBI, Kenya (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rebels fighting for 14 years to turn
Ethiopia into a Stalinist state claim to have captured three key
towns and are making perhaps their biggest push yet against the
foundering government's dispirited forces.
   The rebels claim to be battling the Marxist government's troops
along the nation's main north-south highway and are fighting within
100 miles of the capital of Addis Ababa, Western diplomats said
Thursday.
   The escalating bloodshed comes as a devastating drought
threatens to bring famine to 4 million people, most of them in
northern Ethiopia, where the rebels are based.
   The rebels, the Tigre People's Liberation Front, say that in the
last 10 days they have captured the garrison town of Debre Tabor in
northwest Gonder province and the towns of Rabel and Mehal Meda in
Shoa province.
   Addis Ababa is located in Shoa province.
   Those battles, the insurgents said, have caused the government
nearly 3,000 dead, wounded or captured soldiers.
   Diplomats in Addis Ababa say the claims appear to be true and
that the rebels now are in control of the 25-mile road from Debre
Tabor to Lake Tana, source of the Blue Nile.
   They say the rebels also are continuing their southern push in
Shoa and are battling government troops along the main north-south
highway around Debre Sine, 100 miles northeast of Addis Ababa.
   ``It obviously looks like things are hotting up,'' said one of
the diplomats, all of whom spoke in telephone interviews from Addis
Ababa and requested anonymity. ``But what's going to happen, no one
knows.''
   The rebels claimed the battle for Debre Tabor, where the
government garrison has been increased to 10,000 to 15,000 troops,
was the beginning of a government counteroffensive to drive the
rebels back.
   However, the diplomats were doubtful the government could muster
much resistance.
   ``I don't think we're looking at much of a government
counteroffensive at all, if they're even capable of making one,''
said one diplomat. ``The government hasn't succeeded in pushing
them back to any degree.''
   The source said President Mengistu Haile Mariam's army,
disorganized and dispirited after a failed army-led coup attempt in
May, had been reinforced by hundreds of thousands of poorly trained
conscripts ``of dubious quality.''
   ``I think the best they might be able to do is hold the rebels
in position,'' he said.
   The Tigrean rebels began their offensive in August after joining
forces with a smaller rebel group, the Ethiopia People's Democratic
Movement.
   They control all of their home province, Tigre, and have made
significant advances into Tigre's southern neighbor, Wollo. In the
last two months they also have moved into Gonder and Shoa provinces.
   ``They've proven to be much stronger, much more coherent than
they were believed to be several months ago,'' said one of the
diplomats. ``They've basically rolled over one government position
after another.''
   The Tigrean rebels have been fighting for 14 years to topple
Mengistu's Marxist government. They themselves are Marxists who say
they want a government modeled after Albania's harsh
Stalinist-Leninist rule.
   Mengistu's government and the rebels have held two rounds of
preliminary peace talks, the last of which ended Dec. 19 in Rome
with both sides agreeing to meet in March.
   However, the peace talks ``don't appear to be going very far
now,'' said a diplomat who pointed out that the latest offensive
began immediately after the negotiating sessions ended.
   He said there was speculation that the Tigrean rebels had
launched their ``one-two'' attack in Gonder and northern Shoa in
coordination with another rebel group, the Eritrean People's
Liberation Front.
   The diplomat said sources in the capital understood the Eritrean
front was planning an offensive in their province of Eritrea and
that the Tigre rebels were effectively pinning down government
forces in preparation for that attack.
   The Eritrean rebels, who have been fighting a 28-year
secessionist battle for Eritrea, Ethiopia's northernmost province,
fought their last major offensive in mid-1988. That push also was
coordinated with the Tigre rebels and resulted in the Eritrean
rebels gaining much of Eritrea.
   In addition to the fighting, the United Nations says northern
Ethiopia is again the scene of drought and famine.
   On Wednesday, the United Nations called for an ``international
relief operation of major proportions'' and appealed for 700,000
tons of food to prevent a repeat of the 1984-85 famine that killed
an estimated 1 million.
   Relief agencies have so far unsuccessfully appealed to the
rebels and Ethiopia's government to agree on air and ground
corridors through which supplies can move, unhindered by fighting.
</TEXT>

</DOC>