<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0120 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1311EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-Panama-Congress 5thLd-Writethru a0669 12-20 1044</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Congress, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0669,1070</SECOND>
<HEAD>Most Lawmakers Support Bush, Some Criticize</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: New material, editing throughout to include critical comment.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DIANE DUSTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Members of Congress in both parties today
supported President Bush's assault against Panama's Manuel Antonio
Noriega, although one Democrat said Bush should have consulted with
allies in advance and another called him ``trigger-happy.''
   ``I support the president's decision,'' Senate Majority Leader
George Mitchell, D-Maine, said in a brief statement from Mexico
City, where he was meeting with government officials. ``It was made
necessary by the reckless actions of Gen. Noriega.''
   ``I hope that the restoration of democracy to Panama will occur
as soon as possible,'' Mitchell said. ``I deeply regret the loss of
life which resulted.''
   House Speaker Thomas S. Foley, D-Wash., also offered his
support. ``I think under the circumstances, the decision is
justified,'' he said. Bush asked him for his support in a telephone
call at about 10 p.m. Tuesday.
   ``When there is the engagement of U.S. forces in the field, it
behooves all of us to giver that support,'' Foley told reporters.
   ``My immediate reaction is: at last,'' said Rep. Les Aspin,
D-Wis., chairman of the House Armed Services Committee. ``After the
failed coup of October, the administration faced two choices _ stow
its anti-Noriega rhetoric and leave itself to the whims of events,
or take the initiative and intervene. The latter was the better
choice.''
   And Sen. Sam Nunn, D-Ga., chairman of the Senate Armed Services
Committee, said he hoped the rest of the world would take note of
``the unique circumstances'' that faced Bush. ``It is unfortunate
that the United States has been required to take these steps in
Panama'' when it is asking for restraint on the part of the Soviet
Union and China, he said.
   ``I called to tell the president, `my compliments to the
chef','' said Sen. Jesse Helms of North Carolina, the ranking
Republican on the Foreign Relations Committee.
   ``The majority of the Senate will feel good by this turn of
events,'' Helms predicted in a phone call he placed to The
Associated Press.
   However, Sen. Claiborne Pell, D-R.I., chairman of the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee, said Bush should not have sent U.S.
soldiers into action in Panama without the support and aid of other
Central American nations.
   ``Personally, unless very clear evidence emerges of a direct
threat against the Panama Canal or against American people or
installations, I would not have engaged in such unilateral or such
go-it-alone action,'' said Pell.
   But Pell said he would support the administration until the
attack aimed at unseating Noriega was completed, and he hoped for
``as few deaths as possible to soldiers.''
   Rep. Don Edwards, D-Calif., issued a harshly critical statement,
calling Bush's action ``a trigger-happy act of gunboat diplomacy
that continues our mindless 100-year abuse of small Central
American nations.''
   Edwards, chairman of the House Judiciary subcommittee on the
Constitution, said Bush had violated the provision which requires
Congress' consent to go to war. ``There was no danger to our
national security from this weak, small country, nor was the Panama
Canal in real peril,'' he said.
   And Rep. Ted Weiss, D-N.Y., interviewed on Cable News Network,
said, ``It seems to me that what the president is doing is trying
to correct for his failure to back up the insurgent forces in the
Panamanian Defense Forces back in October. And I think he was wrong
on both occasions. He didn't provide sufficient support last time
and he's doing overkill this time.''
   Sen. Richard Lugar of Indiana, a senior Republican on the
Foreign Relations Committee, called the action ``an overwhelming
success because democracy has now been inaugurated and installed in
Panama.''
   ``The canal is safe, Americans are safe,'' Lugar said, adding
that the operation was ``a very important moment in the presidency
of George Bush. It is a time when the president asserted his own
leadership and did so effectively.''
   Sen. Carl Levin, D-Mich., a member of the Senate Armed Services
Committee, endorsed Bush's decision and praised the action as a
``blow against the international drug trade.''
   ``We need to see how it plays out,'' said Senate Republican
Leader Robert Dole in a telephone interview with the AP. ``I would
guess there would be widespread bipartisan support for the
president.''
   Bush ordered the U.S. troops to Panama City to apprehend Noriega
and bring him to the United States to stand trial on drug-smuggling
charges, said White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater. The move also
was intended to protect American lives as well as the Panama Canal,
he said.
   ``I think the president has done the right thing and I suspect
he'll have pretty widespread support in Congress,'' Sen. Slade
Gorton, R-Wash., said in an interview with Seattle-based KIRO-TV.
   White House officials said top congressional leaders had been
briefed on the mission to seize Noriega by force.
   Sen. Christopher Dodd, D-Conn., chairman of the Senate Foreign
Relations subcommittee on the Western Hemisphere, also was briefed
about the operation. He said on ``CBS This Morning'' that members
of Congress he had talked to ``are standing by President Bush on
this decision.''
   Gorton called Noriega and his followers ``simply lawless bandits
who broke up a free election and are ruling as nothing more or less
than a drug cartel, and have constantly escalated their
provocations against Americans and the security of the (Panama)
Canal.''
   Sen. Pete Wilson, R-Calif., called Noriega ``a murderous thug''
who should be brought to trial in the United States for
drug-smuggling. Noriega has been indicted on narcotics smuggling
charges by grand juries in Miami and Tampa, Fla.
   ``President Bush was requested to intervene with armed force by
the duly elected president of Panama, President (Guillermo) Endara,
whose administration was denied from taking office by Noriega's
thugs after being elected,'' Wilson said in a statement his office
delivered to the AP's Los Angeles bureau.
   Dole said he met with Endara and other elected Panamanian
officials Dec. 10 and ``they were in effect pleading with us to do
something'' about Noriega.
   Rep. Henry Hyde, R-Ill., interviewed on WBBM-AM radio in
Chicago, said, ``I'm satisfied and gratified that the operation is
under way.'' After the earlier failed coup attempt in Panama, he
said, ``We looked impotent; we looked like Lilliputians.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>