<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0359EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Japan-Markets     12-20 0448</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Japan-Markets,0463</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar Up</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARI YAMAGUCHI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Tokyo Stock Exchange's main index regained its
early losses today while the dollar edged up against the yen on
news that U.S. troops had been sent to seize Panamaniam strongman
Manuel Noriega.
   The dollar closed at 144.23 yen, up 0.43 yen from Tuesday's
close of 143.80 yen. It started the day's trading at 143.92 yen and
ranged between 143.90-144.25 yen.
   Earlier trading was quiet as market players made small position
adjustments ahead of the Christmas holidays. But the dollar edged
up later in the afternoon on news that U.S. forces were attacking
Noriega's military headquarters in Panama City, said a trader with
the Bank of Tokyo, speaking on condition of anonymity.
   President Bush ordered troops into action following several days
of tension triggered by the shooting death in Panama on Saturday of
a U.S. military officer.
   ``Japanese market players were waiting to see how the New York
market reacts to the Panama situation tonight,'' the trader said.
   Participants were also held back by uncertainties over Japan's
discount rate increase, the trader added.
   ``Although the government yesterday denied a hike any time soon,
the market expects a 50 percent chance of a hike by the end of the
year,'' the trader said.
   Local news reports speculated the Bank of Japan might raise its
key lending rate to commercial banks by 0.5 percent to 4.25
percent, but the Finance Ministry and the Bank of Japan denied the
increase would happen any time soon.
   Kyodo News Service reported today that Japan's central bank will
begin negotiations with the government in an attempt to raise the
discount rate soon, citing sources from within the Bank of Japan.
   An estimated $6.3 billion traded hands in spot trading, down
from $10.8 billion the previous Tuesday.
   On the stock exchange, the 225-issue Nikkei Stock Average
regained 72.90 points, or 0.19 percent, ending at 38,512.00. It
lost 147.08 points Tuesday on the discount rate rumors.
   The index, which lost 128.57 points by the end of morning
trading, rose back toward the end of the afternoon as speculative
investors bought spot issues to collect profits from the spread
between the spot and futures markets, said Yoshio Shimoyama, a
senior dealer at Nikko Securities.
   ``The market adjusted the index's speed of increase, inspired by
the rumor of the discount rate hike yesterday, and the market
needed a rest,'' he said.
   ``Although the market was basically stable and was gradually
getting ready for the discount rate to happen, market players were
still a bit cautious,'' Shimoyama said.
   Trading was active with first-section volume estimated at 1
billion shares, up from 900 million Tuesday.
</TEXT>

</DOC>