<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0279 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1754EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f BC-Week'sBusiness Adv23-24   12-22 0717</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Week's Business, Adv 23-24,0738</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv23</HEAD>
<HEAD>$adv24</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release weekend editions Dec. 23-24</HEAD>
<HEAD>Last Christmas of the '80s Telling Retailers There Ain't No Santa
Claus</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICK GLADSTONE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Overextended consumers and a slowing economy
could combine like cheap-spiked eggnog to give many retailers a
hangover from the last Christmas season of an extravagant decade.
   From the swank gauntlet of perfume counters at cash-starved
Bloomingdale's to the kiddie departments at K mart, retailers this
past week were hoping that the most crucial days of the year would
not leave them holding vast quantities of unsold merchandise.
   Storeowners will take awhile to assess the final days before
Christmas. Historically they have been the busiest and in many
cases have helped merchants finish the year profitably. A few store
chains already say they've done well.
   But the general tone of this shopping season has been troubling,
with some big retailers trying to fend off bankruptcy and most
struggling to eke out slim sales increases over last year.
   Similar spirits were haunting other sectors of the economy
during the week. The big automakers said they would have to lay off
thousands of workers next month because of slow sales.
   Northeast banks were taking urgent steps to protect themselves
from a rapidly weakening real estate market into which they've
loaned billions of dollars.
   The real estate woes even touched off a sudden drop in the stock
market on Monday.
   The pressure on the retailers has been starkly evident on the
streets of New York _ in the racks of sale items at B. Altman &amp;
Co., the once classy Manhattan department store that is going out
of business because parent company L.J. Hooker is in bankruptcy
court, overwhelmed by creditor claims.
   It's been evident in the heavy discounting at Bloomingdale's and
other department stores owned by another retailing company bobbing
in debts, Campeau Corp., which warned that its stores might default
on their loans and might run to bankruptcy court as well.
   The pressure on Campeau intensified earlier in the week when a
leading apparel supplier and two key lenders in the retailing
industry curbed business dealings with the company for fear they
wouldn't get paid.
   To a large extent, Campeau's problems are rooted in one of the
leading causes of economic growth and consumer spending of the
1980s _ the rapid accumulation of debt.
   Campeau relied on debt for its $6.6 billion purchase of
Bloomingdale's parent, Federated Department Stores, in 1988.
   Consumers wooed by the enticements of buying with borrowed money
nearly doubled the number of credit cards in in the 1980s and
racked up a total debt of more than $700 billion.
   Debt wasn't the only deterrent to hitting the malls this past
week. Nature was a co-conspirator in the retailing industry's
troubled season, plunging much of the country into record cold that
discouraged shoppers from leaving home.
   Perhaps the largest lump of coal lobbed at a retailer came from
New York State's consumer-activist attorney general, Robert Abrams,
who sued Sears Roebuck &amp; Co. for what he called its phony policy of
low prices.
   The nation's leading department store chain, which has been
struggling in recent months to find the right recipe to compete
with aggressive lower-priced rivals like K mart and Wal-Mart
stores, said it was shocked by Abrams' accusations of false
advertising and would fight to clear its name in court.
   In other business and economic news this past week:
   _The Commerce Department said third-quarter economic growth was
revised upward to 3 percent from 2.7 percent; a Commerce survey
showed businesses plan to increase capital spending next year
despite forecasts of a slowdown; and orders for durable goods
increased sharply in November.
   _Eastern Airlines shrank and American Airlines swelled in
another repositioning that reflected the consolidation of their
industry. American bought Latin American routes and other assets
from Eastern's parent Texas Air Corp. for $471 million.
   _A well-known takeover speculator convicted of stock
manipulation was sentenced to three years' probation and a $250,000
fine, the lightest punishment doled out so far in the series of
prosecutions stemming from the Ivan Boesky insider trading scandal.
Salim B. Lewis, who had pleaded guilty to stock manipulation, was
ordered to spend the probation helping drug addicts.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End adv for weekend editions Dec. 23-24.</NOTE>

</DOC>