<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0153 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1806EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Europe-Storm 1stLd-Writethru a0636 12-18 0440</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Europe-Storm, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0636,0451</SECOND>
<HEAD>European Toll from Atlantic Storm Reaches 32</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: CORRECTS toll to 32, 12 known dead, 20 missing. Picks up 3rd
graf, Widespread damage ...</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The toll from a savage Atlantic storm rose to at
least 32 on Monday after two fishing boats sank, high winds blew
two cars into a head-on collision and a wave swept a teen-age
angler out to sea.
   Twelve people were known dead and 20 were missing and feared
dead in France, Britain, Portugal and at sea in the storm that
broke Saturday with heavy rains, lightning and winds of up to 90
mph blowing from the southwest Atlantic.
   Widespread damage was reported in western France, where
gale-force winds tore roofs from homes, toppled trees and telephone
lines, and knocked over structures.
   Rescue teams searched for 11 sailors missing in stormy seas off
the mid-Atlantic Azores islands after the fishing boat Velasco II
went down about 480 miles northeast of Sao Miguel island Sunday
night, Portuguese navy officials said. Waves were more than 25 feet
high at the time of the sinking.
   On mainland Portugal, two people died in storm-related
incidents, road and rail transport were disrupted by storms and
fire services in towns along the river Tagus were overwhelmed with
emergency calls about flooding.
   The French death toll rose to 10 with the discovery of a drowned
fisherman near the Brittany island of Brehat.
   Two people died Sunday night on the superhighway near Lille when
a gust of wind pushed a car driven by Laurent Dufour, 28, into the
path of a vehicle carrying a family of five. Dufour and Odile
Denneulin, 15, died instantly and the four others were injured.
   Near Toulon, a teen-ager drowned Sunday when a huge wave swept
him out to sea as he fished from the shore.
   In Mauleon, 230 miles southwest of Paris, Raymond Etcheberry,
43, died Saturday when a gust knocked him off the roof of a shed he
was repairing.
   Two men died when waves swept ashore and then carried them out
to sea Saturday.
   Three people near Paris died Sunday afternoon when the storm
pushed briefly into the capital.
   The captain of an Irish coastal steamer was washed overboard
early Sunday in the Bay of Biscay off France.
   All six fishermen were believed lost when a fishing boat sank
Saturday in Scotland's Firth of Clyde.
   Waves swept two teen-aged British boys out to sea in separate
incidents Sunday.
   In Greece, fog disrupted air and sea traffic. Athens airport was
closed. A spokesman for the nearby port of Piraeus said no ships
were entering or leaving the harbor.
</TEXT>

</DOC>