<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0182 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2118EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Judges-Security 2ndLd-Writethru   12-18 0657</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Judges-Security, 2nd Ld-Writethru,a0704,620</SECOND>
<HEAD>Marshals Begin Screening Packages in Wake of Attack</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf to reflect death of lawyer in Savannah</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Judge-Explosion Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES ROWLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.S. Marshals Service began screening
packages entering U.S. courthouses Monday, mindful of the mailed
bomb that killed an appellate judge in Alabama and a suspected bomb
found at an Atlanta courthouse.
   ``We're being more vigilant,'' said Flavio Lorenzoni, Chief
Deputy U.S. Marshal for the Southern District of New York. ``All
packages are being checked carefully.''
   He spoke before it was learned that another mailed bomb had
killed a lawyer in Savannah, Ga.
   Like his colleagues in other judicial districts, Lorenzoni
declined to elaborate about the security procedures that have been
invoked since the assassination of Circuit Judge Robert S. Vance.
   ``If we tell everyone what we're doing, it won't have any
effect,'' he said.
   William Dempsey, a spokesman for the Marshals Service in
Washington, said judges have been told ``to bring all packages to
the attention of the marshals so they can be screened and X-rayed
before opening.''
   All packages should be screened, even those bearing a familiar
return address because ``a return address can be faked or forged,''
he said.
   Although he said that security for judges is being stepped up
around the country, Dempsey acknowledged that it would be
impossible for the Marshals Service to provide round-the-clock
protection for every federal judge and magistrate.
   Such protection is given judges when a specific threat is
detected, usually arising from a case involving a judge.
   ``There is not a day in a year that goes by that we do not have
round-the-clock details on some judges,'' Dempsey said.
   Dempsey confirmed that extra security had given to judges in the
11th Circuit, which covers Florida, Georgia, and Alabama, following
Saturday's blast that killed Vance at his home outside Birmingham.
   In Miami, Daniel J. Horgan, U.S. Marshal for the Southern
District of Florida, called a meeting Monday of the district's
judges to inform them of the apparent bomb found in Atlanta on
Monday and the new security measures.
   Chief Deputy U.S. Marshal James Tassone said all packages and
mail entering the federal courthouses in Miami, West Palm Beach and
Fort Lauderdale were being inspected by X-ray.
   People entering the courthouses also were subjected to extra
examination. For instance, some courthouse employees who usually
pass through security with a cursory check were asked Monday to
empty their pockets as they entered.
   Not all federal courthouses changed procedures. For instance, in
Indiana, officials said security was already tight and did not need
to be improved.
   However, Deputy Marshal Jeff Whitney in Evansville, Ind., said
judges had been instructed not to open any uninspected packages
   In New York, U.S. District Judge Mark A. Costantino said federal
marshals called him at home several hours after Judge Vance was
killed and advised him to be alert for suspicious packages.
   The judge said he and his family would refuse to accept any
parcel not bearing the return address of someone they know.
   ``We may be making a mountain out of a molehill, but that shows
that someone is making an effort to create fear in the judicial
system,'' he said.
   At the White House, presidential spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said
President Bush had been in contact with Attorney General Dick
Thornburgh to ask about the status of the investigation.
   ``The attorney general advised him we have not reached any
conclusions about the source of his death. We just don't have any
answers yet as to who might have done it to him,'' Fitzwater said.
   Extra security precautions have been taken at the Justice
Department in recent months since President Virgilio Barcos of
Colombia declared war that nation's cocaine cartels.
   The Justice Department purchased an armor-plated limousine for
Thornburgh, which the attorney general uses around Washington. The
FBI agents who guard Thornburgh now carry high-powered assault
weapons in leather cases.
</TEXT>

</DOC>