<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0736EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r e BC-Theater 1stLd-Writethru a0418 12-20 0871</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Theater, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0418,0886</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dustin Hoffman stars in `The Merchant of Venice' on Broadway</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: ADDS five grafs to UPDATE with Broadway critics. No PMs planned.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL KUCHWARA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Drama Critic</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Is Shylock, the infamous moneylender of William
Shakespeare's ``The Merchant of Venice,'' victim or villain?
   Dustin Hoffman opts for mild-mannered victim in Peter Hall's
straightforward, ungimmicky production of the play which opened
Tuesday at Broadway's 46th Street Theater. Hoffman was the reason
this problematic comedy was a hot ticket in London last summer and
why it was brought to Broadway for what looks like a sold-out
12-week run.
   The star's fans won't be disappointed, but his almost genial
approach robs the play of much of its emotional depth and Shylock
of his complexity. Dressed in a flowing robe, his long hair pulled
back tightly under a skullcap, the bearded Hoffman jokes and grins
in a manner that would not be out of place in the current Lincoln
Center revival of Paddy Chayefsky's ``The Tenth Man.''
   His voice, flavored with an appropriate Jewish accent, is strong
and projects well. Shylock's impassioned speech defending his
Jewishness is delivered quietly with a somber dignity that is
Hoffman's best moment in the play.
   His Shylock is an accommodating man, especially when he agrees
to lend money to Antonio in exchange for a pound of flesh if the
borrower defaults. Shylock meekly suffers humiliation. If revenge
is on his mind, he doesn't let anyone know, at least until he
thinks he can win.
   Hall clearly sees Shylock as a survivor of persecution in a
society where antisemitism was rampant. The Venetian Christians are
the real villains of the piece, louts who spit in the Jew's face,
steal his daughter and even force him to become a Christian before
the final curtain.
   If Shylock's plight is heavily underlined in Hall's production,
his tragedy is never fully explored or realized by the star. The
loss of his daughter to Lorenzo, a Christian, and even the
forfeiture of his own faith don't seem like the devastating blows
they should be. There's no sense of tragedy when the defeated
Shylock walks out of the courtroom to the jeers and harassment of
the crowd.
   At the same time, his villainy during the famous courtroom scene
seems unemotional, almost perfunctory. Hoffman earns laughs rather
than hisses when he sharpens his knife to collect the pound of
flesh, and cheers on the judge when he appears to be winning his
case.
   Hall has better success with the lighter, more romantic aspects
of the play. The scenes in which the three suitors must pick the
right casket if they are to win the fair Portia are staged as
pageants, complete with a stage full of extras, strange music,
exotic costumes.
   Geraldine James, in the play's real star role, is a radiant
Portia, witty as well as intelligent, and with a charming
competitiveness that would endear her to the most ardent feminist.
   Her interpretation of the ``quality of mercy'' speech _ one of
the best known in the Shakespeare _ is a revelation and the heart
of the play. She speaks these lines as if she's giving a bit of
sensible advice rather than commanding the stage for a star turn.
   Leigh Lawson is a sober-sided but not morose Antonio, the
merchant whose life is nearly lost for friendship. Most of the
younger performers in the large cast perfectly capture the gaiety
of what are some of Shakespeare's best romantic scenes. Nathaniel
Parker is properly impassioned as the lovestruck Bassanio, while
Michael Siberry is a terrific Gratiano, turning the usually
long-winded boor into a funny, well-meaning best friend.
   Chris Dyer's setting is impressively adaptable, a series of
reddish-brown pillars that can turn quickly from a Venetian street
scene to idyllic Belmont to the Duke's palace by the dropping of a
curtain or the unfurling of a long red carpet.
   ``The Merchant of Venice'' makes a lot of modern audiences
uncomfortable with its episodes of virulent prejudice, alternating
with a love story that seems almost like a fairy tale. This
production captures the lighter, sunnier hues of Shakespeare's
romance, but the darker shadows of the play elude both Hoffman and
Hall.
   The play opened to general praise from Broadway critics for
Hall's production, and also for Hoffman. All said James gives the
best performance.
   Clive Barnes of the New York Post said Hoffman ``triumphed _ a
deliberately modest triumph, but his own.'' He also praised Hall's
production for being ``refreshingly simple,'' making Shakespeare a
pleasure.
   Linda Winer of New York Newsday questioned Hall's production,
saying it was difficult to understand the balance between tragedy
and comedy. But she said Hoffman was ``the best thing'' about the
play.
   The Daily News' Howard Kissel was the only critic to flatly
criticize Hoffman. He said if Hoffman were an unknown actor, he
would not have won the part. He also faulted Hall's production,
calling it abrasive.
   Frank Rich of The New York Times said the production is
unexpected because romance and comedy are restored, making it
highly watchable. He said Hall's Shylock does not dominate as would
be normal in the play, but Hoffman's performance is ``a character
actor's polished gem.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>