<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0219 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1334EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--IndianFood Adv31-1stAdd   12-18 0768</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Indian Food, Adv 31-1st Add,0788</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 31</HEAD>
<HEAD>BRIDGEWATER, Conn.: corn counterparts.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   While some chefs dismiss Indian food as dull, Weatherford
disagrees. ``Some of this is extremely sophisticated food. I think
of guacamole, for example, as a very subtle, refined dish.''
   Miller, an anthropology graduate student before becoming a chef,
agrees. The high level of aesthetics in other American Indian art
forms indicates a highly evolved cuisine, he says.
   Unfortunately, Kavasch says, ``Indian cuisine has been
trivialized. American Indian food is so unsung and misconstrued and
put down. In fact, it's as exotic as oysters and roe and smoked
salmon. There is no more colorful or unique ethnic cuisine.''
   Kavasch, whose ``Native Harvests'' was published in 1977, is
writing a new cookbook, with Dale Carson of Madison, who is Indian.
She also is working, with American Indians and food scientists, on
a line of snack foods made from wild produce.
   In her early years in Bridgewater, Kavasch's cooking wasn't the
only thing that set her apart.
   ``I treated my kids with natural remedies, resorting to
antibiotics and other prescription medicines only when necessary,''
she says. ``I've always been into farming and gardening and I've
always valued self-sufficiency.''
   She grew up during the 1940s and '50s with an appreciation for
natural things and respect for self-sufficiency rare in an era of
processed convenience foods. But on her grandparents' 100-acre farm
in Tennessee, ``We bought nothing canned. We dried and canned
everything we needed, and there was no such thing as garbage.
Everything had a use. There was great dignity in it.''
   She still forages on her land in northwestern Connecticut for
black walnuts, wild mushrooms and onion grass, and grows much of
her own produce in a carefully tended garden.
   It was her lifelong interest in health that led her to study
ethnobotany, ways in which Indians used plants to create medicines,
preservatives, heating and building materials and other goods.
   Her path led on to food and nutrition.
   ``Indians could tramp all day on a pocketful of parched corn,
the ancestor of Cracker Jacks, and outdistance the Europeans,'' she
says. ``Scientists have discovered they were taller than Europeans,
with stronger bones and teeth and longer life expectancies.''
   Clearly, the Indian way of eating held lessons for modern
society. ``Earlier people had an intrinsic sense of wellness. They
saw certain food as preventive medicine, eaten for greater mental
health and vigor.
   ``Unfortunately, information about cuisine was not passed on.
The accounts that exist were usually from a white perspective,
reflecting men's outlook on things done by women.''
   Recipes in ``Native Harvests'' are based on accounts by trappers
and missionaries, conversations with American Indians, and camping
trips during which Kavasch lived off wild foods.
   One treasured recipe came from a Catawba Indian from North
Carolina, who told her of a corn and peach soup made by his mother.
``I worked on it for years. He would come to visit and taste my
latest attempt, and I would send him pictures.
   ``It took years. When I finally got it right, he took a mouthful
and burst into tears,'' recalls Kavasch, whose own eyes fill with
tears at the memory.
   In keeping with historical accuracy, she used no salt or dairy
products in ``Native Harvests.'' But in the interest of
palatability, she says she'll probably use them in her new book.
   Among writers of American Indian cookbooks, the debate between
authenticity and taste is an old one.
   Though admirable, ``accuracy doesn't sell,'' says Jean Anderson,
whose 16 cookbooks include ``The Art of American Indian Cooking.''
   ``The big problem with Indian cooking is it's heavily adapted
for the American kitchen. You can't say, `Run out and gather the
salmon spawn.' Ladies will say `yuck.'''
   In developing recipes for her 1965 cookbook, ``we took the
things we felt would be most appealing and tried to make them into
something a lady in Garden City, Kansas, would prepare and her
family would like,'' Anderson says. ``We got dinged.''
   Los Angeles food photograper Lois Ellen Frank, the granddaughter
of a Kiowa Indian, also chose accessibility over authenticity in
``Native American Cuisine,'' due out next fall.
   She says she kept the minuscule metropolitan kitchen rather than
the open fire in mind in developing recipes for such dishes as
rabbit rolled in blue corn meal and broiled with wild mint, or
venison steaks with juniper berry and red chili sauce.
   ``When you think about it, everything's adapted, whether it's
how to make pasta or what is Southwest cuisine,'' Frank says.
``Does that ruin it? I don't think so.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>

</DOC>