<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0186 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1022EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-OilPrices 1stLd-Writethru   12-28 0801</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Oil Prices, 1st Ld-Writethru,0825</SECOND>
<HEAD>Heating Oil Prices Soar Past $1 a Gallon; Other Fuels Also In Demand</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after the 8th with early Merc trading today;
picks up 9th graf, A contract ...</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOYCE M. ROSENBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Consumers are paying more than $1 a gallon for
home heating oil in many parts of the country as cold weather
continues to deplete supplies and drive prices higher.
   But oil users aren't the only ones in a bind. Prices are rising
for other fuels and some utilities are asking natural gas customers
to limit consumption.
   In Philadelphia, a gallon of heating oil at one distributor went
from $1.35 Wednesday morning to $1.40 in the afternoon. In
Westchester County, N.Y., just north of New York City, the average
price of home heating oil was $1.35 a gallon, up 27 percent in just
a month.
   The cold weather has kept demand, and in turn, prices, running
high. Transportation problems and refinery shutdowns have
complicated the situation.
   ``The increases are incredible and they're coming just about
every day, from a penny to a nickel per gallon,'' said W. Claiborne
Coupland Jr., marketing director for Papco Oil Co., a supplier in
southeastern Virginia.
   Oil prices are high even in places where the weather has been
temperate.
   In Seattle, where temperatures have been running in the 40s,
slightly above normal for this time of the year, heating oil was
selling for nearly $1.02 a gallon. In Portland, Ore., where
temperatures ranged from the 30s to the 50s, heating oil costs as
much as $1.
   On the New York Mercantile Exchange, home heating oil for
delivery in January soared 7.23 cents Wednesday to 99.71 cents a
gallon _ 37 cents higher than the Nov. 30 price and up sharply from
53.77 cents a gallon a year earlier. On Tuesday, the contract rose
10.74 cents.
   In early trading today, the contract rose another 2.29 cents to
$1.02 a gallon.
   A contract comprises 42,000 gallons of oil, which means one
contract for heating oil would cost $41,878 at Wednesday's price.
However, the price paid by most distributors _ the people who
deliver oil by tanker truck to residential customers _ was $1.15 a
gallon Wednesday in what is known as the New York spot, or cash,
market.
   ``It's very cold outside and the inventories of heating oil got
dangerously low and it's difficult to get heating oil here prior to
the second half of January,'' said James Fiedler, an analyst with
E.D.&amp;F. Man International Futures Inc.
   Shutdowns at many refineries have worsened supply problems and
driven prices even higher.
   The most prominent shutdown was of a huge Exxon facility at
Baton Rouge, La., where a weekend explosion killed two workers. But
production at many Gulf Coast refineries has been slowed because of
frozen water pipes _ just when the oil companies were trying to
step up their output to meet the increased demand.
   ``It seems like every refinery was affected,'' Fiedler said.
``Most of the refineries have got some of their units back to
normal ... and most were talking that they'd be back to full
operation by the weekend.''
   Oil companies continued to report low heating oil supplies at
some terminals.
   At Star Enterprise, a Texaco Inc. affiliate, supplies were
tightest in the Boston area, spokesman Top Ingram said. Star has
begun limiting the amount of oil its customers can buy, he said.
   Freezing temperatures also have increased the demand for propane
and kerosene.
   In South Carolina, deliveries of the two fuels have been
hampered by icy roads and a shortage of supplies, dealers said.
Some suppliers said they were raising their prices and giving
priority to long-time customers.
   Propane prices have risen about 10 cents to $1 a gallon during
the last two weeks, while kerosene prices have risen 20 cents a
gallon, to 80 cents, dealers said.
   In Iowa, state officials said prices for liquid propane for
residential consumers have increased from under 50 cents a gallon
last month to a range of 80 cents to 95 cents a gallon.
   Natural gas customers, while not facing delivery problems of
oil, propane and kerosene users, also suffered shortages because of
increased demand.
   Philadelphia Gas Works, a city-owned system, on Wednesday asked
its 517,000 residential, commerical and industrial customers to cut
back consumption.
   PGW spokesman Don Kenley said the company's two main suppliers,
Texas Eastern Corp. and Transcontinental Pipeline Corp., cut
supplies by 28 percent because of higher demand.
   Even wood was in short supply in some areas.
   Walter Holdsworth, owner of Wakefield Firewood Inc. in
Wakefield, Va., said his wood lot was empty Friday for the first
time in 10 years. The rush began, he said, about three weeks ago
when the cold weather first set in.
</TEXT>

</DOC>