<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1404EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Panama-Deaths     12-24 0673</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Deaths,670</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pentagon List of Dead</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the names and home towns of U.S.
soldiers killed in the Panama invasion, as released by the Pentagon:
   
   _Chief Warrant Officer Andrew P. Porter, born April 20, 1964,
from St. Clair, Mich. An aviator with B Company, 1st Battalion,
123rd Aviation Regiment, 7th Infantry Division based at Fort Ord,
Calif., Porter entered the service on Aug. 24, 1982.
   _Pvt. James Allen Tabor, born Jan. 6, 1971, from Montrose, Colo.
A heavy weapons specialist from the Headquarters Company, 4th
Battalion, 325th Parachute Infantry Regiment based at Fort Bragg,
N.C., Tabor entered the service on July 5, 1989.
   _Chief Warrant Officer Wilson B. Owens, born April 25, 1960,
from North Myrtle Beach, S.C. An aviator with the B Company, 160th
Aviation Battalion based at Fort Campbell, Ky., Owens entered the
Army on Feb. 23, 1979.
   _1st Lt. John Wessel Hunter, born Jan. 29, 1959, from Victor,
Mont. An aviator with the Headquarters and Support Company from the
160th Aviation Battalion, based in Fort Campbell, Ky., Hunter
entered the Army on Dec. 6, 1976.
   _Sgt. Michael A. Deblois, of Dubach, La. Born Sept. 30, 1965,
Deblois entered the Army on Feb. 16, 1984. He is an infantryman.
   _Cpl. Garreth C. Isaak, a Marine born Dec. 28, 1966, and a
native of Greenville, S.C. Isaak entered the Marine Corps on May
29, 1985.
   _Cpl. Ivan D. Perez, 22, of Pawtucket, R.I. Perez, an Army
infantryman based at Fort Polk, La., entered the service in 1985.
   _Pfc. Scott Lee Roth, 19, of Killeen, Texas. He was a military
policeman stationed at Fort Hood, Texas.
   _Specialist Phillip S. Lear, 21, Westminster, S.C. He was an
infantryman based at Fort Lewis, Wash.
   _Lt. J.G. John Patrick Connors, born March 28, 1964, and a
native of Arlington, Mass. Connors entered the Navy on May 20,
1987, and was a member of the Navy's special operations unit known
as the SEALS, based at Little Creek, Va.
   _Chief Engineman Donald Lewis McFaul, born Sept. 20, 1957, and a
native of San Diego, Calif. McFaul entered the Navy on June 26,
1975, and was a SEAL based at Little Creek, Va.
   _Boatswain's Mate 1st Class Christopher Tilghman, born Dec. 2,
1959, and a native of Kailua, Hawaii. Tilghman entered the Navy on
Jan. 18, 1979, and was a SEAL based at Little Creek, Va.
   _Pfc. Jerry Scott Daves, born Sept. 8, 1969, and a native of
Hope Mills, N.C. Davis was a member of the 1st Battalion, 504th
Parachute Infantry Regiment.
   _Torpedoman's mate Second Class Issac George Rodriguez, born
March 22, 1965, and a native of Missouri City, Texas. He was a SEAL
who entered the Navy on Feb. 24, 1983.
   _Pfc. James William Markwell, born May 29, 1968, and a native of
Cincinnati, Ohio. He was a medic who entered the Army on Feb. 23,
1989.
   _Pvt. 2 Kenneth Douglas Scott, born May 20, 1969, and a native
of Princeton, W.Va. He was an infantryman who entered the Army on
June 15, 1989.
   _Spec. Alejandro I. Manriquelozno, born Oct. 3, 1959, and a
native of Lauderhill, Fla. He entered the Army on Jan. 20, 1988.
   _Pfc. John Mark Price, born Dec. 24, 1966, and a native of
Conover, Wis. An infantryman, Price entered the Army on July 19,
1988.
   _Pfc. Roy Dennis Brown Jr., born March 21, 1970, and a native of
Buena Park, alif. An infantryman, Brown entered the Army on Oct.
19, 1988.
   _Spc. William D. Gibbs, born July 27, 1967, and a native of
Marina, Calif. An infantryman, Gibbs entered the Army on Aug. 6,
1985.
   _Staff Sgt. Larry R. Barnard, born Dec. 8, 1960, a native
Hallstead, Pa., An infantryman and Ranger, Barnard entered the Army
June 5, 1980.
   _Pfc. Vance T. Coates, born Jan. 27, 1971, and a native of Great
Falls, Mont. An infantryman, Coates entered the Army Feb. 2, 1989.
   _Pfc. Martin D. Denson, born Sept. 12, 1968, and a native of
Abilene, Texas. An infantryman, Denson entered the Army Jan. 18,
1989.
</TEXT>

</DOC>