<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0088 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1616EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Time-Gorbachev     12-23 0305</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Time-Gorbachev,0313</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gorbachev Is Time Man of the '80s</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: For release 9 p.m. EST</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY86</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mikhail Gorbachev, whose political and economic
reforms in the Soviet Union sparked a revolution that shattered
communist control of Eastern Europe, was named Man of the Decade by
Time magazine Saturday.
   The Soviet president, previously named Time's Man of the Year in
1987, was chosen because he is ``the force behind the most
momentous events of the '80s and because what he has already done
will almost certainly shape the future,'' Time said.
   The only precedent for such a choice by the magazine was its
selection of Winston Churchill as Man of the Half-Century in 1949.
   ``This year, as world attention ricocheted from the stirrings of
democracy in the U.S.S.R. to the massacre in Beijing and the
peaceful revolts in Eastern Europe, it became clear that we were
witnessing a sequence of events that began well before 1989 and
whose impact would extend into the next decade, perhaps the next
century,'' the magazine said.
   ``Somehow confining our choice to 1989 seemed inadequate, and
thus we named Gorbachev Man of the Decade.''
   The magazine said he ``has accelerated history, making possible
the end of one of its most disreputable episodes, the imposition of
a cruel and unnatural order on hundreds of millions of people.''
   Gorbachev becomes only the fourth non-American designated twice
by the magazine. One was Churchill (1940 and 1949); the others were
Soviet leader Josef Stalin (1939 and 1942) and China's Deng
Xiaoping (1978 and 1985).
   Time has been naming a Man of the Year since 1927, choosing the
``person who, for better or worse, has had the most impact on the
year's events.'' The first award went to aviator Charles Lindbergh;
last year's winner was Earth as planet of the year.
</TEXT>

</DOC>