<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0121 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1513EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania-Clergyman     12-29 0485</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Clergyman,0501</SECOND>
<HEAD>Priest Says Execution was Right Punishment for Ceausescu</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HAMBURG, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Laszlo Toekes, the ethnic Hungarian
priest whose pending arrest unleashed the revolt that led to the
overthrew of Nicolae Ceausescu, says death was the right punishment
for the Romanian dictator.
   But Toekes, in an interview published Thursday, said it was
wrong to show the bodies of Ceausescu and his wife, Elena, on
television.
   West Germany's mass-circulation newspaper Bild Zeitung said it
interviewed Toekes on the train between Cluj and Bucharest, where
he would assume a role in the new leadership.
   ``They have proposed me for a minister (post). But I'm first of
all a priest, not a politician. However, if that's what the people
want, I will say yes,'' Toekes was quoted as saying.
   Asked if execution was the right punishment for Ceausescu and
his wife, Toekes was quoted as replying:
   ``The punishment was right. But it was horrible and disgraceful
to show both of them in such a way on television. To show their
death in full publicity, that's just not done.''
   The revolt against Ceausescu began in the western city of
Timisoara, when people linked hands around the priest's home to
prevent him from being taken away. It quickly spread into an
anti-Ceausescu uprising, with security forces opening fire on the
demonstrators. The protests spread nationwide and resulted in
Ceausescu's overthrow Dec. 22 and his execution Monday.
   Toekes described how he was tortured by Ceausescu's security
forces, the dreaded Securitate.
   ``Securitate people beat me in front of the altar of the church.
They hit me with sticks, they kicked me in front of the cross. They
dragged me off to Mineu. Fifty people watched me, floodlights shone
on the house day and night, guard dogs were in front of the door,''
Toekes was quoted as saying.
   He said his pregnant wife also was beaten by Ceausescu's
henchmen.
   The priest said he was feeling ``relatively good'' now. ``I have
great spiritual pains. Only now am I aware of the great danger that
my wife and son had been in. My life was not worth anything.''
   ``For Ceausescu, I had already been dead. .... I can only thank
God that I'm still alive,'' Bild quoted Toekes as saying.
   Toekes said he did not feel like a hero.
   ``I am a priest who had a duty. I am a very simple man. I only
did my duty conscientiously. I am not a hero,'' he said.
   Toekes said the high price in human life paid for overthrowing
Ceausescu had ``given my life some value.''
   ``Many people died because of me. That's painful. They only
wanted to help me. Securitate accused me of being responsible for
their death. My soul is destroyed,'' Toekes was quoted as saying.
   Toekes said his ``greatest wish'' was to go back to Timisoara as
soon as possible and celebrate a service with his parishioners.
</TEXT>

</DOC>