<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0115 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1925EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Bulgaria     12-26 0281</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bulgaria,0292</SECOND>
<HEAD>Round-Table Talks Next Week; General Strike Called Thursday</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SOFIA, Bulgaria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The ruling Communist Politburo on Tuesday
proposed round-table talks on the country's future with other
official and newly active opposition groups.
   The action came after an independent trade union, Podkrepa,
proposed warning strikes for Wednesday, presumably in selected
places, and a general strike Thursday to push demands for the talks.
   It was not clear whether the Politburo offer was in response to
Podkrepa's threat of the first general strike in Bulgaria since the
Communist takeover after World War II.
   It also was not clear whether the strikes would go ahead as
planned. Podkrepa is one of several opposition groups that have
been allowed to function publicly since Todor Zhivkov was ousted as
Communist leader Nov. 10.
   An initial meeting took place Dec. 15 between the ruling
Communists and representatives of opposition groups.
   Zhivkov's ouster came amid a wave of change that swept the East
bloc, beginning with Poland and Hungary and spreading to East
Germany, Czechoslovakia and Romania.
   Petar Mladenov, who took over from Zhivkov, has pledged to scrap
the Communist Party's monopoly on power, remove its guaranteed
leading role from the Constitution and hold free elections by May.
   Also Tuesday, reform Communists demanded the resignation of the
entire existing party Central Committee, elected under Zhivkov, and
announced plans to split from the party and form a faction known as
the Alternative Socialist Association.
   The group will hold a meeting Jan. 12, the state news agency BTA
reported.
   The group also wants the party to share with emerging
alternative parties the extensive property amassed over the last
four decades, its funds and printing presses, BTA said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>