<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0110 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 2307EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthKorea     12-25 0357</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Korea,0367</SECOND>
<HEAD>South Korea's Chun to Testify on Misdeeds before Parliament</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KELLY TUNNEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Disgraced former President Chun
Doo-hwan will testify before parliament on corruption, human rights
abuses and misconduct during his 7-year rule before the year ends,
the governing party said Tuesday.
   South Korean politics have been dogged by public demands to
clear the legacies of Chun's authoritarian rule so the way could be
cleared for a more open government and more democratic reforms.
   The Democratic Justice Party said Chun received a summons to
testify in the National Assembly Dec. 31, along with a 123-page
document listing questions the legislators wanted answered.
   Details of the procedure were still being discussed, a party
spokesman said.
   Chun left office in February 1988 after turning over power to
his former associate Roh Tae-woo, named president in national
voting two months earlier.
   Chun's predecessor, Choi Kyu-hah, also was expected to testify
before the assembly.
   Choi served briefly as a figurehead president in late 1979. He
was succeeded by Chun, who seized power in an internal army coup.
   Roh and the three main opposition leaders agreed on Dec. 15 on
resolving disputes over Chun's administration.
   Such compromise is rare in Korean politics, but political
leaders have been under mounting public pressure to agree on the
Chun-related issues in a bid to make a new start in 1990.
   Forty-eight people, including about a dozen Chun relatives, have
been convicted of corruption and power abuse.
   Chun went into rural exile in November 1988 after apologizing to
the nation for misrule and misconduct and surrendering $24 million
in unused political funds.
   Amopng the questions Chun was expected to answer were those
about his alleged role in using the military to quell a civil
uprising in Kwangju in 1980. By official count 200 people were
killed and more than 1,500 injured in the uprising.
   Radicals and dissidents have staged violent protests to demand
that Chun be arrested and punished. The main opposition parties
have publicly promised not to raise more Chun-related issues once
their demands are met. Dissidents have denounced the agreement as a
sellout.
</TEXT>

</DOC>