<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0236 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1025EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-WallStreet10am     12-21 0303</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Wall Street 10am,0319</SECOND>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The stock market headed higher today, rebounding
from a weeklong slide.
   The Dow Jones average of 30 industrials rose 8.96 to 2,696.89 in
the first half hour of trading.
   Gainers outnumbered losers by 2 to 1 in nationwide trading of
New York Stock Exchange-listed issues, with 689 up, 345 down and
496 unchanged.
   Volume on the Big Board came to 25.52 million shares as of 10
a.m. on Wall Street.
   Analysts said there was nothing that stood out in the economic
and business news to account for the upswing. But buyers appeared
to be nibbling at stocks that have lately suffered from worries
about a possible recession in 1990.
   Brokers also said traders remained hopeful that stock prices
might benefit from the so-called January effect, a historical
tendency for the market _ and especially smaller stocks _ to show
greater-than-usual strength in the first few weeks of a new year.
   One rationale for the January effect is the lifting of yearend
selling pressures from investing institutions cleaning losers out
of their portfolios and individual investing realizing losses for
tax purposes.
   Among actively traded blue chips, Philip Morris rose [ to 40\;
American Express gained \ to 31{; International Business Machines
added [ to 94}, and McDonald's was unchanged at 32~.
   The NYSE's composite index of all its listed common stocks
climbed .73 to 190.27. At the American Stock Exchange, the market
value index was up .41 at 368.59.
   On Wednesday the Dow Jones industrial average dropped 7.68 to
2,687.93, extending its loss over the last five sessions to 73.16
points.
   Advancing issues nosed out declines in the overall tally on the
NYSE, with 763 up, 740 down and 482 unchanged.
   Big Board volume totaled 176.52 million shares, against 186.06
million in the previous session.
</TEXT>

</DOC>