<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 1112EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Rubles-Alaska     12-31 0295</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rubles-Alaska,0308</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rubles Worth Cab Ride, Perhaps More, in Nome</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSAN GALLAGHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NOME, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three rubles will buy a cab ride in Nome as
part of a fledgling Chamber of Commerce project to let Soviets
spend their currency here.
   Jim Stimpfle of the chamber's Committee for Cooperation,
Commerce and Peace said last week the project is a way to give the
non-convertible ruble some value in the United States.
   He said he hopes that eventually acceptance of rubles in Nome
will snowball into the ruble becoming officially convertible into
dollars at a reasonable rate of exchange.
   ``It's good will, it's friendship, it's solidarity,'' Stimpfle
said.
   The ruble project grows from the opening of travel between
Alaska and the Soviet Far East during the last two years.
   Stimpfle said there were 85 flights between Nome and the Soviet
port town of Provideniya in 1989. During the summer an average of
10 Soviets a week were in Nome, either for a visit or passing
through, he said.
   Most Soviets arrive with $40 from their sponsoring organizations
in the Soviet Union, he said.
   Their government prohibits them from taking rubles from home,
but many do so anyway and make black-market swaps for dollars with
Alaskans planning trips to Provideniya.
   Stimpfle said $1 in the Soviet Union here officially brings six
rubles. In Nome, under-the-table rates for rubles vary. Under the
chamber's plan, businesses are encouraged to establish their own
rates of exchange.
   Checker Cab, which charges $3 for a ride in Nome, has agreed to
take Soviet passengers for three rubles, and Stimpfle said at least
two other businesses are willing to consider rubles.
   He's ordered stickers that say, in Russian, ``Rubles Accepted
Here'' and will distribute them to participating companies.
</TEXT>

</DOC>