<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0413EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Panama-Media     12-29 0368</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Media,0383</SECOND>
<HEAD>Panama's News Media Look to New Freedom Under Endara</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARIA VICTORIA GONZALEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The news media shuttered by the
regime of Manuel Antonio Noriega are rushing to resume operations
just days after the general's overthrow by U.S. forces.
   Even employees of those media that loyally followed a
pro-government line under Noriega are celebrating the installation
of the civilian government of President Guillermo Endara.
   The Noriega closed three opposition newspapers, three radio
stations and a television channel in 1988, shortly after the United
States began demanding the general's ouster. His regime
expropriated another TV station this year.
   In some cases, broadcast or publishing licenses were revoked,
equipment confiscated and offending reporters hounded into exile.
   The new government announced Thursday that all news media can
resume operations without any restrictions.
   ``The government's basic line is to grant an opening for all
communications media, without regard to ownership, and freedom of
expression without any type of censorship,'' said Edwin Cabrera,
director of the government's communications office.
   Cabrera also said the government is dismissing all court
proceedings against journalists accused of violating censorship or
security regulations under Noriega.
   The change in government has unleashed a wave of pent-up
resentment against the former strongman, now holded up at the
Vatican embassy.
   Only 10 days ago, a newspaper reader could scan such headlines
as ``Our Country Will Not Kneel Before Anyone, Much Less the United
States,'' and ``Gringo Soldiers Shoot 1-Year-Old Girl.''
   The newspapers Critica, Matutino and La Republica all published
anti-American appeals on Dec. 19, the day before the U.S. invasion.
Radio Nacional continued pro-Noriega broadcasts up to the moment
its transmitters were destroyed by American troops last week.
   This week, an editorial broadcast by radio station KW
Continental, which had been closed under Noriega, declared, ``The
beast must not escape'' _ a reference to Noriega's refuge inside
the Vatican embassy.
   Now, many publishers, broadcasters and editors are returning to
work.
   The newspaper La Prensa, whose offices were ransacked almost two
years ago by pro-Noriega thugs, announced it plans to hit the
streets within two weeks.
   Editors estimated damages to La Prensa's facilities during the
raid at $2 million.
</TEXT>

</DOC>