<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0292 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2031EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-TLCBeatrice     12-20 0524</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-TLC Beatrice,0541</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stock Offering Withdrawal Shows Market Weakness</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEFAN FATSIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   European food concern TLC Beatrice International
Inc.'s decision to scrap a public stock offering to raise up to
$194 million reflects a general weakness in the market for new
issues, analysts said Wednesday.
   The move also postponed what would have been two firsts: the
first former Beatrice Cos. holding to go public since a $6 billion
takeover in 1986 and the first black-owned company to be listed on
the New York Stock Exchange.
   TLC Beatrice on Tuesday canceled the offering of 18.5 million
shares of stock priced from $9 to $10.50 a share. A successful
offering would have raised between $167 million and $194 million.
   The company, controlled by investor Reginald F. Lewis, cited
weak market conditions and a lack of interest from institutional
investors in canceling the plan to offer a 35 percent interest to
the public.
   ``It's not what I would call a hot new issues market,'' said
Norman Fosback, president of the Institute for Econometric Research
in Fort Lauderdale, Fla., which analyzes new stock issues.
``Offerings tend to be overpriced.''
   ``My sense is that there is very little demand for offerings
from individual investors, and institutions are dominating the
market,'' said Fosback, who did not recommend the TLC Beatrice
issue.
   Robert Baumbach, a new issues analyst for Standard &amp; Poor's
Corp., said in a report that the TLC Beatrice shares were priced at
about 20 times what he estimated the company's 1989 earnings would
be if it already were public.
   There have been 194 initial public offerings by companies this
year through Tuesday, down from 222 in the same 1988 period and 516
in the same 1987 period, according to Securities Data Co.
   The value of IPOs rose 4.3 percent from 1988 to $5.5 billion,
but dropped 56.6 percent from $12.8 billion in the 1987 period, the
figures showed.
   A group of investors led by Lewis bought Beatrice's
international foods operations for $985 million in December 1987.
The entire company was taken private the previous year by Kohlberg
Kravis Roberts Co., the leader in debt-financed takeovers known as
leveraged buyouts.
   TLC Beatrice raised $875 million through asset sales to help pay
off debt, company officials said. They said the remaining $34
million in acquisition debt was retired this week, but the company
still has close to $170 million in long-term debt.
   As of Sept. 30, the company had assets of $624 million,
including about $154 million in cash. It expects 1989 operating
profits of $75 million on sales of $1.1 billion.
   ``The market for initial public equity offerings has tightened
up in general,'' TLC Beatrice senior vice president Everett Grant
said.
   ``We thought it was an attractive window to access the public
equity markets,'' he said. ``However, the window did not appear as
attractive as it might have been.''
   Grant said the company has not ruled out issuing the stock at a
later time.
   TLC Beatrice owns 15 companies, including Franprix, a food
wholesaler in the Paris area; Tayto, Ireland's largest snack food
company; and seven ice cream distributors in Europe.
</TEXT>

</DOC>