<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0152 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1617EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-Smithsonian     12-22 0513</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Smithsonian,460</SECOND>
<HEAD>Smithsonian Research Team Rescued by U.S. Troops</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: The following was prepared from a pool report filed by Steven
Komarow of The Associated Press, William Clayton of the Houston Chronicle
and Dick Thompson of Time magazine.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEVEN KOMAROW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A member of a Smithsonian Institution
research team rescued Friday by U.S. troops said it was a fantastic
moment when the group saw U.S. helicopters arriving.
   The 11-member research team had been abducted Wednesday from an
island research center and forced to march into the jungle by about
30 soldiers loyal to Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   The Smithsonian group, including a 4-year-old girl, eventually
was abandoned without food by the soldiers. U.S. military forces,
after a fruitless search for the researchers on Thursday, located
them on Friday as they were being taken by a friendly schoolteacher
to a nearby town.
   ``That was a fantastic moment, seeing the helicopters come,''
said Steve Travers, a marine biologist with the Smithsonian group.
   Mary Knowlton, another scientist, said the group expected
trouble because of the U.S. invasion on Wednesday. Those fears were
realized when a Panamanian patrol boat arrived at the research
center, she said.
   The research team talked the soldiers into letting them grab a
few belongings before they were hurriedly taken ashore. They
managed to sneak out three two-way radios with which they would
later guide U.S. armed forces to their location for rescue.
   Greg Summers, another member of the group, said they were taken
by boat to an airfield and then into the jungle. They walked from
11 a.m. Wednesday until 1 a.m. Thursday, he said.
   ``The worst part was walking down the main landing strip off to
the side and into the woods. Everybody thought they were going to
shoot us,'' said Travers.
   ``We really didn't know we were going to be walking halfway
across Panama,'' Knowlton said. At one point it appeared to the
hostages that their captors feared that they themselves were
isolated when word reached them that Americans were in control of
Panama City. They asked their captives to tell the American troops
that the researchers had been taken into protective custody. Then
the group was abandoned on Thursday.
   Using the radios they had hidden, the group contacted
Smithsonian officials in Panama City.
   Lt. Col. Joseph Umbarger, who coordinated the rescue, said at
first the U.S. military thought the situation might be a potential
trap but then sent three helicopters on a dangerous nighttime
search over the jungle about 20 to 25 miles north of Panama City.
Although the pilots scoured the area for hours, the initial aerial
search team was forced to return without the hostages when their
fuel ran low.
   The group received help from the school teacher Friday morning.
The teacher was taking them in a flatbed truck to the town of Chepo
when a second flight of helicopters from Fort Clayton spotted them
in transit.
   The researchers said they jumped off the truck and waved pieces
of clothing in a pre-arranged pattern to tip off the soldiers.
</TEXT>

</DOC>