<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0238 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0319EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-BigSqueeze     12-29 0375</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Big Squeeze,0390</SECOND>
<HEAD>Plants Run 24 Hours To Squeeze Freeze-Damaged Citrus</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Frozen Profits, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRADENTON, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Florida's 33 citrus processing plants are
pushing their operations to the limit to squeeze frost-damaged
oranges before they have a chance to rot.
   Truckloads of oranges are flooding plants that are running
non-stop to process the fruit damaged during a two-day Christmas
freeze.
   Industry officials fear several days of 70-degree weather would
cause the damaged fruit to decay and fall from trees if not picked
and processed quickly enough.
   At Tropicana Products Inc., the nation's largest citrus
processor, maximum plant capacity is 36 million oranges a day,
which translates into 1 million gallons of juice.
   All of Tropicana's 400-plus fruit-hauling trailers have been
mobilized to race the clock, said Tropicana Products Inc. President
Robert Soran.
   ``We'll be open 24 hours per day, seven days a week during the
salvage process,'' said Steve Caruso, assistant general manager at
Citrus World, a juice processing plant in Lake Wales that produces
about 400,000 gallons of fresh juice a day.
   The Juice Bowl plant in Lakeland also is running non-stop
indefinitely.
   Gov. Bob Martinez lifted highway weight restrictions on trucks
so citrus growers can move crops faster. And growers have pressed
all migrant farm workers into service to help harvest the fruit
from groves hit hard when the overnight temperature plunged as low
as the high teens last Sunday and Monday.
   The final freeze-damage toll won't be known for some time, but
Soran said that based on recent estimates, Florida may be able to
produce 100 million boxes of oranges this season, down from an
anticipated 130 million boxes.
   A damage estimate is due Jan. 11, said Ernie Neff, a spokesman
for Florida Citrus Mutual, which represents citrus growers.
   Florida and Brazil produce 81 percent of the world's oranges,
almost entirely for juice, and Soran said a recent increase in
Brazilian production means that the overall supply this year may
change very little.
   Juice made from a blend of U.S. and imported oranges may not
fluctuate widely in price at current supply levels, said Soran.
   However, shoppers may pay more for juices made only from Florida
oranges, such as Tropicana's Pure Premium and Minute Maid's Premium
Choice, he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>