<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0207 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1536EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-OilPrices     12-29 0557</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Oil Prices,0581</SECOND>
<HEAD>Energy Futures Rise</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Energy futures prices surged Friday as a late
rally boosted heating oil to a six-year high on the New York
Mercantile Exchange.
   Heating oil for delivery in January, which had declined Thursday
after a two-week rise, jumped 5.47 cents to finish at $1.0187,
helped by a wave of frenzied buying in the final 30 minutes of
trading.
   Heating oil last closed higher on Jan. 27, 1984, when it settled
at $1.0497, said Pat Kelly, an exchange official. The contract
traded as high as $1.10 a gallon, an all-time high, before easing
off.
   Analysts attributed much of the gains to last-minute buying
ahead of the January contract's expiration at the close of trading.
   Nevertheless, the buying spree surprised many traders, said
Peter Beutel, energy analyst with Elders Futures Inc.
   ``It came on the last trading day of the contract. That
definitely helped,'' Beutel said.
   Heating oil contracts for later delivery posted gains of between
0.60 cent and 1.27 cents a gallon.
   Meanwhile, wholesale unleaded gasoline futures also soared,
boosted by an industry report that showed a sharp drop in supplies.
The January unleaded gasoline contract, which also expired Friday,
rose 3.11 cents to end at 63.22 cents a gallon in a modified
trading session. Other contracts gained between 1.05 cents and 2
cents.
   Trading ended at 1 p.m. EST because of the New Year's holiday.
   West Texas Intermediate, the main U.S. grade of crude oil,
finished at $21.82 per 42-gallon barrel, up 32 cents on the
exchange. Later contracts advanced between 16 cents and 34 cents.
   ``The real surprise was the sharp gains in gasoline,'' said Bob
Baker, energy analyst with Prudential-Bache Securities Inc. ``The
draw on inventories simply was a surprise for the market.''
   The American Petroleum Institute, in its weekly inventory
report, said that gasoline supplies fell 4.8 million barrels last
week to 221.7 million barrels.
   Heating oil and other distillate fuel oil stocks declined 4
million barrels to 112.2 million and crude oil inventories declined
by 4.3 million barrels to 343.5 million.
   Analysts said investor concern over possible tight supplies of
oil and gasoline fueled some of the buying, even though the effects
of the record-setting cold snap that boosted the price of heating
oil in recent days was believed to be tapering off. Heating oil has
risen 45 percent since Dec. 15 when it closed at 70.42 cents a
gallon.
   While demand for heating oil and other domestic fuels remains
strong, actual shortages are not expected to occur, they said.
   Nevertheless, refinery problems in some southern states remained
a concern, observers said.
   ``People decided that if refining problems are going to be the
norm, gasoline is going to be bullish,'' said Linda Simard, energy
broker for Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc.
   Analysts said investors are expecting further refinery problems
if unseasonably cold weather persists in January and February.
   Frigid weather in the last two weeks has caused operating
problems at several Texas and Louisiana refineries. Some plants
closed temporarily and others cut back operations, while crude oil
shipments were delayed in some parts of the country.
   Heating oil prices got a boost early in the week after last
Sunday's explosion at Exxon Corp.'s Baton Rouge, La., refinery. The
plant, closed since the explosion, was expected to resume partial
operations this weekend, Exxon officials said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>