<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1417EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-US-Romania 1stLd-Writethru a0431 12-26 0462</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-Romania, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0431,440</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eds: Tops with 5 grafs to update with U.S. aid, picks up 3rd graf
pvs, A hot</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RUTH SINAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bush administration today announced an
emergency $500,000 package of humanitarian aid to Romania, after
recognizing its provisional government.
   At the same time, the United States voiced regret that the trial
of executed dictator Nicolae Ceausescu and his wife, Elena, was
conducted in secret.
   ``We would have preferred it if there had been a public trial,''
White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said.
   He said the $500,000 in aid would be made available by the U.S.
Agency for International Development to the International Red
Cross. He said further U.S. aid also was likely.
   Romania has been devastated by bitter street battles between the
army and security forces loyal to Ceausescu.
   A hot line is being set up today at the State Department to
handle the many calls from Americans and Romanians wanting to
donate food and medicine.
   ``The U.S. government today established diplomatic relations
with the new legitimate government of Romania, the National
Salvation Front,'' said a statement issued by the White House on
Monday. The National Salvation Front is the name adopted by the
reform-minded leadership, which assumed control of Romania after
Ceausescu was deposed last week.
   ``The United States government pledges its support to the new
Romanian government as it struggles to achieve its announced
democratic values,'' said the U.S. statement.
   It was issued a short while after Bucharest Radio reported that
Ceausescu and his wife were executed Monday after a secret trial
that found them guilty of killing more than 60,000 Romanians and
the stealing more than $1 billion from the country.
   ``We regret the trial did not take place in an open and public
fashion. We urge an end to all violence and bloodshed in Romania,''
the U.S. statement said.
   The statement said President Bush was informed by National
Security Adviser Brent Scowcroft of the executions when Scowcroft
went to the presidential retreat at Camp David, Md., to discuss the
situation in Panama.
   The Romanian Embassy issued a statement saying it had notified
the State Department of the executions and the charges against the
deposed couple. A State Department official, who spoke on condition
of anonymity, said that unless informed otherwise by the new
Bucharest government, the United States considers the existing
ambassador and his staff as official representatives.
   Diplomats at the U.S. Embassy in Bucharest have already been in
touch with the new government to arrange safe passage for 42
government personnel and their dependents who were evacuated Sunday
to neighboring Bulgaria, said State Department spokesman Adam Shub.
   He said the 31-car convoy of foreigners that drove to the
Bulgarian border also carried 26 other Americans.
</TEXT>

</DOC>