<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1215EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China-Army     12-28 0300</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Army,0308</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Officers Failed to Obey Orders to Crush Democracy Movement</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HONG KONG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 100 Chinese army officers and 1,400
troops defied orders or left their posts during the military
crackdown on the pro-democracy movement last spring, a newspaper
reported Thursday.
   The accusations were made in an unpublished speech by Yang
Baibing, chief political commisar of the People's Liberation Army,
at a conference on army political work in Beijing earlier this
month, the English-language South China Morning Post said.
   The only officer named by Yang for disobeying orders was Xu
Qinxian, head of the Beijing-based 38th army. The newspaper said Xu
reportedly has been court-martialled and given a stiff sentence.
   Senior Communist Party leader Deng Xiaoping called on the 38th
army to restrict the scope of the pro-democracy demonstrations as
early as April, but its failure to clamp down helped lead to the
rapid growth of the protests, the newspaper said.
   Yang reportedly said 21 officers and cadres with ranks of
divisional commander or above, 36 officers with ranks of regimental
or battalion commander, and 54 officers with the rank of company
chief ``breached discipline in a serious manner during the struggle
to crush the counterrevolutionary rebellion.''
   He also said 1,400 soldiers ``shed their weapons and ran away.''
   Unconfirmed reports of dissension among Chinese soldiers spread
after the army killed hundreds and perhaps thousands of civilians
as it shot its way through Beijing on June 3-4 to quash the
protests.
   Yang, the younger brother of President Yang Shangkun, recently
was promoted to secretary-general of the Central Military
Commission of the ruling Communist Party and is considered a rising
star.
   The newspaper report said he has been given the task of ensuring
the loyalty of military officers in case students and workers again
challenge the government.
</TEXT>

</DOC>