<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0053EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Names     12-18 0999</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Names,1045</SECOND>
<HEAD>Names in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY14</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   If anyone stole the president's wallet, it might
be a while before he noticed it was missing.
   ``You carry cash, but you don't use it much,'' President Bush
said in the year-end issue of People magazine.
   Asked how much he carried, he pulled out his wallet and counted.
   ``Let's see, there's about $53,'' he said. ``I've had it there
for quite a while. Once in a while you need something, and somebody
here will go get it if something's broken or you need some
batteries or you need something personal.''
   Barbara Bush, who was interviewed with her husband, said that
when they go out, she always whispers to him, `` `Do you have any
money?' Just in case.''
   ``For restaurants we do,'' the president said. ``We carry cash
for restaurants.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>HELENA, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At age 88, Pulitzer Prize-winning novelist
A.B. Guthrie Jr. says he still hasn't written his favorite book,
and maybe never will.
   ``I always have things in my mind,'' he said Saturday at a
book-signing session in Helena. ``Time's short, though.''
   Guthrie, who lives west of Choteau, said he considers himself a
mere ``passerby in the world'' who was lucky enough to pursue his
literary dream.
   ``I'm glad I chose the career I did,'' the former newspaperman
said. ``I've striven for a mastery of (the English language) and
yet I know it will never be mastered.''
   Guthrie won the Pulitzer in 1950 for ``The Way West,'' a novel
about the settling of the frontier, and is perhaps best known for
``The Big Sky,'' which launched his career in 1947. He has written
numerous historical novels and collections of essays and stories,
and wrote the screenplay for the 1953 movie ``Shane.''
   Guthrie was signing autographs on copies of ``Montana! A
Photographic Session,'' for which he wrote passages to accompany
104 photographs.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Comic Jackie Mason and Mayor-elect David Dinkins
say their differences over a campaign wisecrack are a thing of the
past, but Mason still got in a dig.
   Mason stirred up a hornets nest in September when he called
Dinkins ``a fancy shvartze with a mustache.'' Shvartze is Yiddish
for black.
   When he made the remark, Mason was working for the campaign of
Dinkins' opponent, Republican Rudolph Giuliani.
   At a holiday party Saturday, the comedian, with Dinkins at his
side, said he was glad Dinkins won the mayoral race.
   ``I'm on his side as much as I would've been if I'd been on his
side from the beginning,'' he said.
   ``There has never been bad blood,'' Dinkins said.
   Earlier, Mason joked with journalists about a report that
Dinkins had asked to be called ``Mr. Dinkins,'' rather than
``Dave,'' at news conferences.
   ``They called Truman `Harry.' They called Reagan `Ronnie.' Maybe
if he doesn't like his name, they could call Dinkins `Jackie' and
call me `Dave,''' Mason said.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Eds: Version moving on sports wire.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>CINCINNATI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Cincinnati Bengals football coach Sam Wyche
said he was making a point when his team ran the score up to 61-7
over the Houston Oilers.
   ``We don't like this team,'' Wyche said after Sunday's National
Football League game. ``We don't like their people. When you get a
chance to do it (run up the score), you do it. I wish today this
was a five-quarter game.''
   Wyche had his Bengals throw the football, and even executed an
onside kick with a 45-0 lead, as Cincinnati amassed enough points
to gain the most lopsided victory in its history.
   It was Cincinnati's way of repaying the Oilers for years of
perceived snubs by Houston players and Coach Jerry Glanville's
free-wheeling approach to football.
   Wyche noted his opponents' penchant for inflicting personal
fouls: ``Jerry is an unusual coach,'' Wyche said. ``Drop me a note
if you find somebody who likes this guy, will you?''
   Said Glanville: ``They played excellent. They did a great job.
There are no excuses. It's our job to stop them.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>FORT WORTH, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Getting a seat up front at the Country
Music Association's awards show was Hank Thompson's first clue that
he was about to get one of its highest honors.
   Thompson, who got his first guitar as a 10-year-old boy in Waco,
is the newest inductee into the Country Music Hall of Fame in
Nashville.
   The 64-year-old singer said last week he had a few other clues
besides the seating arrangements at October's show.
   One was that old friend Guy Clark was presenting the award and
another was that CBS had asked Thompson to appear on its morning
show live the next day.
   ``A guy told me you can usually tell who the winners are,
because you can see where they're sitting,'' said Thompson. ``So
when my seat was right up there in front, I thought, `Roy Rogers
(last year's winner) had been up there the year before, and Loretta
Lynn the year before that,' so I said, `I think I've been moved up.
I think this is gonna be it.'''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BEVERLY HILLS, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In Liza Minnelli's view, she's not
getting older _ she's getting braver.
   ``I feel the need to take risks now,'' said the 43-year-old
entertainer. ``I don't know why. Maybe it's my age ... or maybe
it's something bizarre, like the position of the planets _ who
knows?''
   Her latest album, ``Results,'' is certainly a change for the
Academy Award-winning actress best known for belting out Broadway
tunes.
   ``Results,'' co-produced and mostly composed by Britain's Pet
Shop Boys, is pop dance music.
   Sales haven't exactly taken off in this country, but Miss
Minnelli doesn't think her less-than hip image is to blame.
   ``But I am hip,'' she said, noting she likes rap and rock music.
   ``I'm not this old lady looking for her lost youth,'' she said.
``The key is doing music they can relate to. If the kids like the
music, they won't care if I'm 80 years old.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>