<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1344EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Sakharov     12-26 0448</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sakharov,0461</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sakharov Last Speech Called for Pre-Trial Rights</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK J. PORUBCANSKY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Andrei D. Sakharov, in the speech he was writing
when he died, said legislation allowing prosecutors to prolong
maximum pre-trial detention threatened society with a return to
Stalinist times, a report said.
   The respected weekly Literaturnaya Gazeta, in its Dec. 27
editions, published a text of the speech that it said the Nobel
Peace Prize winner was working on when he collapsed and died in his
study Dec. 14.
   Other Soviet publications have said a text of the final speech
of Sakharov was circulated last weekend at the Congress of People's
Deputies, where Sakharov would have given the speech, but they have
not published it.
   Literaturnaya Gazeta did not say how it obtained the text.
   Sakharov said that by trying to lengthen the amount of time
Soviets can be held before trial, the procurator general's office
was trying to ``free its hands entirely and return the country to
the stormy times of illegality of the cult of personality,
stagnation and other rather gloomy periods.''
   The ``cult of personality'' is a reference to the rule of Josef
Stalin, during which prosecutors unencumbered by legal tradition or
judicial oversight had all of Stalin's potential opponents and many
other Soviets imprisoned or killed.
   The maximum length of time a suspect may be held has been nine
months, after which only the Presidium of the Supreme Soviet could
prolong detention.
   The new law allows the deputy procurator general to extend such
detention to one year, and for the country's top prosecutor to
extend it to 18 months.
   For decades prisoners in the Soviet Union have had no access to
a lawyer during most of their pre-trial detention.
   Soviet practice has been to allow the presence of a defense
lawyer to prepare for trial only after the prosecutor has finished
questioning the suspect and building his case.
   ``This will not improve the results of the war with crime, but
only make our already sick society more cruel,'' Sakharov's text
said. ``The whole country will justly see a new lie in the new
law.''
   Sakharov cited the laws of many Western countries limiting the
amount of time suspects can be held without trial.
   He criticized Vice President Anatoly I. Lukyanov for what he
said were irregularities in conducting the Supreme Soviet
legislative session Nov. 28 at which the new law was approved.
   Sakharov, 68, was elected to the Congress of People's Deputies
in March, and during the Congress session earlier on Dec. 14 had
spoken out in favor of declaring a group of reform-minded deputies
a ``political opposition'' to the Communist Party and government.
</TEXT>

</DOC>