<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0155 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0939EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APonTV-Hargrove Adv28   12-27 0769</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP on TV-Hargrove, Adv 28,0788</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv28</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Thursday PMs, Dec. 28, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Writer Dean Hargrove Has Two New Series</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JERRY BUCK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Television Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It's an accomplishment when a writer can get
even one television series going, but Dean Hargrove has two hits on
the air and next week launches two more shows.
   ``Father Dowling Mysteries,'' previously on NBC, makes its debut
on ABC next Thursday. ``Max Monroe: Loose Cannon'' premieres on CBS
on Friday.
   Hargrove also created NBC's ``Matlock'' and CBS' ``Jake and the
Fatman.'' Earlier, he also developed the very successful series of
``Perry Mason'' movies for NBC. His frequent collaborator is Joel
Steiger.
   ``Everybody has a theory about why a show is successful,'' said
Hargrove. ``I think the audience basically is attracted by
characters, and when you have that perfect wedding of character and
performer you have a success.
   ``Most successful TV series are identified by a name: Lucy,
Archie Bunker, Columbo, J.R. Even with shows like `thirtysomething'
or `L.A. Law,' I think people tune in for the characters.
Basically, I tailor shows for the stars, like Andy Griffith, Bill
Conrad and Tom Bosley.''
   ``Loose Cannon'' stars Shadoe Stevens as Max Monroe, a police
detective whose wild and unconventional tactics have earned him the
nickname of Loose Cannon. Stevens is a rock 'n' roll disc jockey
who is host of ``American Top 40'' and a panelist on ``Hollywood
Squares.''
   ``It's a new kind of show for us,'' said Hargrove, whose partner
is Fred Silverman, former president of NBC and former head of
programming at CBS and ABC. ``The series we've done so far have
been traditional, middle of the road series.
   ``Working with Shadoe gives us an opportunity to design a show
that's offbeat and contemporary. It has a strong vein of humor. I
think almost all successful shows have had humor. I got my start as
a comedy writer and I still think of myself as a comedy writer.''
   ``Father Dowling'' stars Tom Bosley and Tracy Nelson as two
ecclesiastical snoops. He's the good father, Frank Dowling, and
she's Sister Steve. Father Dowling is always running afoul of
church hierarchy in the person of James Stephens as Father
Prestwick, the bishop's aide. The show's set in Chicago, but like
``Perry Mason,'' it's filmed in Denver.
   The next ``Perry Mason'' movie, however, has been filmed in
Paris. It's the 14th in the series since Silverman sold the project
to NBC.
   ``Fred talked to Raymond Burr, got the rights and got NBC
interested,'' Hargrove said. ``He asked me to write the script. We
thought it would be a good idea to bring in a younger character, so
we cast William Katt as Mason's investigator.
   ``My notion was to put a detective story in the middle of `Perry
Mason.' The detective gets an assignment early and goes off to
pursue it. Perry Mason carries on his mystery-solving, and the
detective works on solving another element of the case. Katt has
left, but we use the same technique with Bill Moses.''
   In the show set in Paris, Mason defends an American Marine
officer in a court-martial.
   Hargrove grew up in Iowa and began writing student films while
in college. He attended the UCLA Film School as a graduate student,
but dropped out to write professionally.
   His first job was writing for ``The Bob Newhart Show,''
Newhart's first series on NBC in 1961-63.
   ``Newhart was the button-down mind just out of Chicago,'' he
said. ``We wrote a lot of telephone routines for him. Roland Kibbe
hired me and we later worked together on `Columbo' and `Madigan.' I
also wrote for `The Man From U.N.C.L.E.' because they wanted to
bring a sense of humor to the show.''
   Hargrove wrote the pilot for ``The Girl From U.N.C.L.E'' and was
story consultant for ``It Takes a Thief.'' He wrote and produced
Gene Barry's segments on ``Name of the Game.'' He was also producer
and writer for such series as ``Columbo,'' ``Madigan,''
``McCloud,'' ``McCoy,'' ``The Family Holvak'' and ``Me and Mom.''
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Elsewhere in television:
   TRUE STORY _ NBC's ``Midnight Caller'' will look at the effects
of the Oct. 17 Northern California earthquake in a special episode
for Tuesday, Jan. 2. The cast and crew, which experienced the
earthquake while working in San Francisco, does an episode called
``Based on a True Story.'' Guest stars John Beck and Sydney Walsh
play producers trying to film a TV movie about the earthquake, as
seen from the perspective of radio personality Jack Killian, played
by Gary Cole.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Thurs PMs, Dec. 28</NOTE>

</DOC>