<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0548EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DigestBriefs     12-23 0629</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Digest Briefs,0656</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bush administration will consider aid to
the new government taking shape in Romania once it dismantles the
system inherited from ousted President Nicolae Ceaucescu and
institutes reforms, officials say.
   The White House and the State Department hailed the demise of
Ceaucescu's hard-line government Friday and expressed hope for a
peaceful transition to democracy.
   State Department deputy spokesman Richard Boucher credited the
``courageous and persistent action by the Romanian people'' who
prevailed ``in the face of great odds and despite bloody
repression.''
   Ceausescu's ouster seemed to foreshadow an improvement in
U.S.-Romanian relations, which have been under severe strain,
particularly since last weekend when anti-government uprisings
began.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   People took up arms and formed
vigilante squads to combat looting and thousands jammed churches,
stadiums and schools to flee fighting that has ravaged the capital.
Food and medicine were in short supply.
   As the U.S. military occupation entered its fourth day today,
weary and frightened residents stayed behind locked doors to avoid
street battles between fighters loyal to ousted Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noriega and American forces.
   Much of this city of 1 million people was in ruins after air
strikes by U.S. warplanes and mortar attacks by Panamanian fighters.
   Residents in many neighborhoods organized vigilante groups to
ward off the looters of homes and businesses who roamed the streets
at will.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bush administration, responding to the
stubborn resistance of Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega's loyalists, is
sending 2,000 more troops into Panama, a source said.
   Military leaders predicted the operation that began early
Wednesday would take another 10 days.
   ``The decision has been made,'' said the Pentagon source,
demanding anonymity. ``The movement will be taking place in the
near future.''
   The new arrivals will join roughly 24,000 U.S. troops already on
the ground trying to overcome the Noriega forces.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>HAGERSTOWN, Md. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A county judge described as tough-minded
and outspoken was injured by a pipe bomb delivered to his home, but
authorities said the case appeared to be unrelated to four other
recent bomb attacks.
   Washington County Circuit Judge John P. Corderman, listed in
stable condition today, isn't known to have handled civil rights
cases _ the presumed motive in the earlier attacks, one of which
killed a federal judge.
   Corderman, 47, suffered shrapnel injuries to his abdomen and
right hand, and both eardrums were ruptured in the blast in his
third-floor apartment about 2:30 p.m. Friday, said Chuck Jackson,
Maryland State Police spokesman.
   ``Apparently, the device was situated outside when he arrived
home,'' Jackson said. ``He retrieved it, entered the apartment and
a short time later it exploded. We don't know whether it was opened
or not.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Senate ethics committee says it's formally
investigating five senators who intervened with regulators for a
troubled savings and loan, and a sixth accused of influence
peddling.
   The lawmakers are using the announcement to again proclaim their
innocence.
   The committee said Friday it has begun preliminary inquiries of
the six _ the first of three possible investigative steps _ but
emphasized in a statement it ``has taken no position as to the
merits of the allegations or the weight of the evidence.''
   In the savings and loan case, the ethics panel will probe the
activities of Majority Whip Alan Cranston, D-Calif.; Banking
Committee Chairman Donald W. Riegle, Jr., D-Mich.; John McCain,
R-Ariz.; Dennis DeConcini, D-Ariz., and John Glenn, D-Ohio.
Congressional watchdog Common Cause asked for the investigation.
   Sen. Alfonse D'Amato, R-N.Y. will be the subject of the
influence-peddling inquiry, expected to focus in part on the award
of federal housing money to the senator's political contributors. A
complaint was filed by a political opponent of the senator.
</TEXT>

</DOC>