<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0315EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-StelloNomination     12-20 0593</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Stello Nomination,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stello Hearings Produce Divisions But No Clear Outcome</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three days of hearings on President Bush's
nominee to head nuclear weapons production have sharply divided the
Senate panel weighing the nomination, but yielded few signs of
whether he'll be confirmed.
   Victor Stello Jr., nominated as assistant energy secretary for
defense programs last July 24, urged the Senate Armed Services
Committee on Tuesday to act as soon as possible, but the panel is
not expected to vote until January or February.
   Stello appeared before the committee in a first round of
hearings Nov. 15 and 16.
   Three of the 11 Democratic members of the committee _ Sens. John
Glenn of Ohio, Edward Kennedy of Massachusetts and Timothy Wirth of
Colorado _ are strongly opposed to Stello, but most of their
colleagues have not publicly taken a position.
   Among the nine Republican members, Sen. John McCain of Arizona
and others have charged that the Democrats are trying to kill the
nomination by stalling and raising what they say are irrelevant and
unsubstantiated charges about Stello's professional background.
   Stello worked for the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, and its
predecessor, the Atomic Energy Commission, for 26 years before
going to the Energy Department last summer as a special adviser on
the Savannah River nuclear weapons plant.
   In a separate development Tuesday, the Energy Department
released a report showing that the new operator at Savannah River,
the Westinghouse Savannah River Co., was given $3.9 million in
federal award fees this year despite serious safety lapses,
including two instances of reactor workers sleeping on the job.
   Westinghouse was applauded for making some important
improvements at the plant since it took over last April, but the
department cited numerous ``anomalies,'' including cases of
radiation alarms being deliberately disabled by workers.
   Stello, in a final statement to the Armed Services Committee,
said ``it is our country that is suffering'' because of a
leadership vacuum in the weapons program. He described the weapons
production complex as being in ``a state of disarray.''
   Sen. Strom Thurmound, R-S.C., said Stello is well suited for the
job and that ``the real issue'' is whether opponents of nuclear
weapons will allow confirmation of a man capable of rebuilding the
production complex. Key production plants are shut down for safety
upgrades, and many private groups contend the facilities no longer
are needed for national security.
   Wirth, however, said Stello should be rejected because his
record as a staff member of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission was
spotted with evidence that he sometimes put nuclear industry
interests ahead of assuring public safety.
   The department has been without a confirmed head of weapons
production for more than a year.
   Of five former members of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission wo
testified Tuesday, three strongly endorsed Stello's nomination and
two raised serious doubts about his suitability.
   Joseph Hendrie, a former chairman of the NRC and currently a
consultant to nuclear utilities, said he has known Stello for 17
years and considers him ``a good manager and a natural leader. I
recommend him to you in the strongest terms.''
   James Asselstine, a commission member from 1982-87, said he has
``very mixed feelings'' about Stello. He called Stello technically
qualified for the Energy Department job, but said Stello at the NRC
sometimes was too easy on those he regulated.
   Asselstine cited as an example a case in which Stello ordered
his staff to rewrite proposed changes in fire protection standards
for nuclear plants to satisfy objections from utilities. Stello
later denied this allegation.
</TEXT>

</DOC>