<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0646EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     12-28 0634</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0650</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cold in Midwest, Warmer in East</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A Canadian cold front settled southward across the Dakotas,
Minnesota, Wisconsin and Iowa today, while the East and South
looked for warmer weather and the Great Lakes area braced for more
snow.
   Northeasterly winds were forecast to bring lake-effect snow
showers to the shores of lakes Superior and Michigan. Snow
advisories were called for much of Delaware, Maryland and Virginia
and in the eastern panhandle of West Virginia.
   The Coast Guard and barge operators said warmer weather expected
by Friday could help loosen ice up to 6 inches thick which covered
70 percent to 100 percent of the Allegheny, Monongahela and Ohio
rivers.
   ``The river people I talk to are saying this is the worst (ice)
they've seen since the winter of 1977-78,'' said Coast Guard Cmdr.
Anthony Regalbuto said.
   Frozen pipes and broken water lines continued to plague
residents in areas from the Carolinas to Alabama. Many communities
still report low water pressure or shortages caused by broken mains
and people leaving their faucets running to protect against frozen
pipes during the four-day cold snap.
   Forecasters were predicting some relief for the Carolinas today
_ sunshine, highs in the 50s and lows in the 30s.
   While the cold high pressure system was expected to creep into
the northern tier of states tonight and Friday, low pressure should
spread northward from Texas to the Upper Ohio Valley.
   As the cold front moves south today, snow or freezing rain may
fall on parts of South Dakota and into Minnesota and Wisconsin.
Temperatures north of the front will be in the 20s and 30s. South
of the front, the mercury should range from the 30s in Illinois to
the 50s in Nebraska.
   A weak front is expected to move out and high pressure move over
Virginia, Maryland, Delaware and West Virginia's eastern panhandle.
Temperatures today in the four-state region should be above
freezing, with the southern areas enjoying highs in the 40s.
   The nation's high on Wednesday was 77 degrees at McAllen, Texas.
   Beckley, W.Va., shattered its coldest reading for the date with
a temperature of zero. The old record of 7 degrees was set 13 years
ago. Beckley also is having its snowiest December on record,
already surpassing the old mark of 24 inches set in 1962.
   Reports at 3 a.m. EST today:
   _East: Albany, N.Y. 13 snow; Atlanta 39 fair; Boston 15 snow;
Buffalo 20; Charleston, S.C. 50 fair; Chattanooga 31 fair;
Cincinnati 35 cloudy; Cleveland 25 snow; Detroit 21 fair; Hatteras
34 partly cloudy; Jacksonville 49 fair; Key West 57 fair; Knoxville
33 fair; Macon 44 fair; Miami 52 partly cloudy; New York 22 snow;
Philadelphia 21 snow; Pittsburgh 25 snow; Portland, Maine 8 snow;
Richmond 31 fair; Tampa 46 fair; Washington, D.C. 24 cloudy.
   _Central: Birmingham 33 fair; Bismarck 29 partly cloudy; Chicago
23 fair; Denver 31 partly cloudy; Des Moines 32 fair; Fort Worth
39; Indianapolis 30 cloudy; Kansas City 31 fair; Little Rock 34
fair; Louisville 37 cloudy; Memphis 32 fair; Nashville 26 fair; New
Orleans 47 foggy; North Platte 27 fair; Oklahoma City 39 fair;
Omaha 31 fair; Rapid City 38 cloudy; St. Louis 36 cloudy;
Minneapolis-St. Paul 27 cloudy; Sault Ste. Marie 19 snow; San
Antonio 43 fair.
   _West: Albuquerque 30 fair; Anchorage 23 cloudy; Boise 22 foggy;
Casper 40 windy; Fairbanks 7 fair; Great Falls 42 cloudy; Honolulu
73 fair; Las Vegas 44 partly cloudy; Los Angeles 59 cloudy; Medford
33 foggy; Pendleton 28 foggy; Phoenix 56 fair; Portland, Ore. 37
drizzle; Reno 29 cloudy; Salt Lake City 23 snow; San Diego 60
cloudy; San Francisco 52 cloudy; Seattle 42 foggy; Spokane 26
freezing drizzle.
   _International: Calgary 34 snow; Montreal 5 snow; Ottawa 5;
Toronto 18 cloudy; Winnipeg 16 snow; San Juan 74.
</TEXT>

</DOC>