<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1145EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-SriLanka     12-17 0813</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sri Lanka,0835</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tamil Factions in Power Struggle for Supremacy</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EARLEEN FISHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>IRUTHAYAPURAM, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The frightened faces of
schoolboy militiamen barely in their teens peered from the windows
of a bus commandeered by grinning warriors no older than the
captives.
   The captives and the captors were Tamils from rival guerrilla
groups that have turned on each other in their struggle for
independence from the Sri Lankan government.
   The Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam took control of the village
of Iruthayapuram and nearby Batticaloa after a raid Tuesday in
which as many as 100 members of the so-called Tamil National Army
were killed.
   The Tigers' leaders have put away their camouflage uniforms to
negotiate with the government in Colombo for political power, and
the raid was meant to demonstrate that they are the only Tamil
force worth reckoning with in northeastern Sri Lanka, where most
members of their ethnic minority live.
   The Sri Lankan government, which gave up any claims to control
of the Batticaloa district 2{ years ago, acknowledges it is
virtually impotent to halt the Tamil power struggle.
   ``The Tamils are going to liquidate each other,'' said Foreign
Minister Ranjan Wijeratne, who is also the deputy defense minister.
   He blamed the departing Indian peacekeeping force for ``arming
to the teeth'' the Tamil National Army, which was created by
pro-Indian Tamils shortly before the Indians withdrew from the
Batticaloa area.
   India has repeatedly denied training or arming that Tamil force,
despite claims to the contrary by the Sri Lankan government,
families of teen-agers conscripted by the militia and several
longtime Batticaloa residents.
   Asked what the Sri Lankan armed forces should do to prevent the
Tamil infighting, Wijeratne replied:
   ``So do you want us to go and kill all the people? We have
deliberately restrained ourselves. Let good sense prevail.''
   Sending in the Sri Lankan army could lead to a repeat of the
ethnic war that prompted India to intervene in the first place.
   The Sri Lankan government is controlled by the island's
Sinhalese majority. The Sinhalese make up 75 percent of Sri Lanka's
16 million people and, according to Wijeratne, 99 percent of the
army. About 18 percent of the population is Tamil. Most Sinhalese
are Buddhists and most Tamils are Hindus, but there are Christians
in each group.
   It is this Sinhalese domination that touched off the Tamil
separatist revolt in 1983.
   The Tigers and an array of other Tamil militias, alternately
allying and feuding with each other, demanded a separate nation _
or at least autonomy _ to preserve the language, culture and
economic opportunities of their people.
   The guerrilla war led to terrorist attacks and massacres of
Sinhalese civilians. The Sri Lankan military, although unequipped
for all-out war, responded with heavy force that included pitching
barrels packed with explosives out of their light transport
airplanes.
   Six years later, at least 11,000 people have died in the Tamil
revolt, including 1,100 of the Indians who intervened at the urging
of their own nation's politically powerful Tamil minority.
   The Indian force, which started arriving July 30, 1987, is now
withdrawing. It set in motion a political formula to give the
Tamils a measure of autonomy, but it failed in its mission to
disarm the Tigers.
   After 2{ years of fighting the Indians, this once rag-tag bunch
of guerrillas has evolved into an experienced fighting force
determined to deny the Tamil National Army or any other Tamil
rivals the right to run the provincial government in the northeast.
   ``The armed struggle is a means to achieve a political end,''
the Tigers' chief negotiator, Anton Balasingham, said in an
interview in Colombo. ``We are not laying down our guns. We will
have our weapons as long as this problem is there.''
   In Iruthayapuram, a senior Tiger who uses the code name
Karikalan said: ``Now we are going to restore normalcy _ civilian
adminstration, transportation, everything.''
   Karikalan, who had a Czech automatic pistol on his hip, an
Italian machine gun slung over his shoulder and a spare ammunition
clip tucked in the waistband of his camouflage pants, described
himself as ``the political-wing leader'' of the Tigers in the
Batticaloa area.
   As for the frightened Tamil National Army members on the bus,
the 39-year-old Karikalan said: ``After interrogation, they will be
released.'' He would not say how long that might take.
   After Tuesday's raid in Batticaloa, fishermen scooped shrimp and
crabs from the smooth blue water as young Tigers patrolled the road
in trucks and jeeps that had been driven by local government
officials a few days earlier.
   At the Soboraj cinema, where films are shown only during the day
because most people prefer to stay off the streets after dark,
``Uncommon Valor'' starring Harrison Ford was playing. Only 39
people _ about one-fifth the ususal turnout _ bought tickets the
day after the Tigers took the town.
</TEXT>

</DOC>