<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0220EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-HomelessSanta     12-25 0300</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Homeless Santa,0306</SECOND>
<HEAD>Officers `Moved To Tears' By Homeless Man's Christmas Gifts</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two police officers were on patrol when a man
who looked like a haggard Santa Claus flagged them down from the
side of the road, saying he had something to give them.
   The white-bearded man, dressed in worn overalls and a thinning
jacket, led officers Michael Leonard and Ed McDaniel to his
makeshift home _ a clapboard hideaway tucked beneath the stairwell
of a warehouse _ and handed them two magnificently handcarved
wooden toys.
   ``I want you to give these to a boy and a girl who would
otherwise not have a good Christmas,'' Wayne Miller, 53, told the
officers.
   ``We were moved to tears,'' Leonard said Friday as he recalled
the recent encounter near the Marine Corps Recruit Depot. ``He had
several other toys in various stages (of completion), and he seemed
very disappointed that those would not be ready for Christmas.''
   Miller revealed little about his personal life to the officers
except that he has been living on the streets by his own choosing
for 12 years. One of the toys, which he began carving last July,
was an auto that could double as a jewelry box because of its
compartments. The other was a tractor-trailor loaded with logs.
   ``He collected the materials to build the toys while digging
through dumpsters for food and aluminum cans,'' Leonard said. ``At
night, he carves the wood in front of his campfire.''
   Leonard delivered the toys to the Department of Social Services
Children's Center, where assistant deputy director Sherry Paul
promised that workers would deliver the gifts to a family by today.
   The officers, meanwhile, started a collection to buy Miller a
sleeping bag or warm jacket, despite Miller's insistence that he's
doing fine.
</TEXT>

</DOC>