<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0177 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1144EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-BoardofTrade Open   12-27 0315</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Board of Trade, Open,0327</SECOND>
<HEAD>Crop Futures Little Changed in Quiet Opening</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Grain and soybean futures prices were little
changed in quiet early trading today on the Chicago Board of Trade
as export optimism offset selling linked to warmer temperatures in
the nation's midsection.
   Trading was light, which is typical for a holiday period.
   The markets opened mostly lower, extending the weaker pattern
established Tuesday due to warmer temperatures in the Great Plains
and Midwest after a two-week cold spell.
   But selling pressure waned and buying interest surfaced early in
the session, partly reflecting the Agriculture Department's weekly
grain-inspections report, which showed unexpectedly large exports
of corn, wheat and soybeans last week.
   Some buying also stemmed from Spain's overnight purchase of
180,000 metric tons of U.S. corn and from expectations that
Pakistan will tender tonight for 26,000 metric tons of U.S. soybean
oil, said Victor Lespinasse, a trader with Dean Witter Reynolds
Inc. in Chicago.
   In early trading, wheat futures were unchanged to 1 cent higher
with the contract for delivery in March at $4.10 a bushel; corn
futures were unchanged across the board with March at $2.38{ a
bushel; oats were \ cent to 1 cent lower with March at $1.52 a
bushel; soybeans were unchanged to } cent lower with January at
$5.68\ a bushel.
   Cattle futures were mostly lower while pork futures were mixed
in early trading on the Chicago Mercantile Exchange.
   Live cattle were .07 cent to .28 cent lower with February at
77.47 cents a pound; feeder cattle were .17 cent lower to .10 cent
higher with January at 85.10 cents a pound; live hogs were .05 cent
lower to .25 cent higher with February at 49.25 cents a pound;
frozen pork bellies were .27 cent lower to .03 cent higher with
February at 49.50 cents a pound.
   Livestock and meat futures settled higher on Tuesday.
</TEXT>

</DOC>