<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0128EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-PanamaPool 3rdLd-Writethru a0770 12-22 0669</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama Pool, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0770,670</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cheney Pleased with Operation of Media Pool in Dangerous Circumstances</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS new 3rd-4th grafs with more reporters arriving</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRYAN BRUMLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Defense Secretary Dick Cheney said Thursday he
was pleased with the operation of the media pool that accompanied
the U.S. invasion force to Panama, despite complaints that
reporters had been kept away from the action.
   ``I think there was adequate coverage. I think our commanders on
the scene had their priorities straight,'' said Cheney, noting that
media executives had called his office demanding that the military
protect reporters who were not in the pool.
   Later in the day, about 50 more journalists arrived in Panama
with 300 expected by early Friday.
   Lt. Col. James Swank, a military spokesman, said the reporters
would be allowed to camp out in the officers club restaurant, but
by Friday night would be expected to have their own accommodations.
   Several non-pool photographers were killed or wounded in the
action, and other journalists were taken hostage by forces loyal to
ousted Panamanian strongman Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   Pentagon spokesman Pete Williams, sitting with Cheney in an
interview with 11 newspaper and wire service journalists,
acknowledged that ``we wish we could have done a better job getting
people around'' on Wednesday.
   The chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, Gen. Colin Powell,
also said he was pleased with the operation of he pool, especially
because the news organizations involved had not leaked word of the
invasion in advance.
   ``I think it worked marvellously,'' Powell said, noting that it
had not always gone well on previous occasions. The institution was
created following the secret 1982 invasion of Grenada. News
organizations which take part in the pool agree in advance to keep
its activation a secret.
   ``We did what we promised you we would do and the media in the
pool did what they promised they would do,'' Powell said. Pool
members were collected late Tuesday night and flown to Panama with
the invasion force.
   ``There never was any concern in my mind it would break security
and it didn't,'' Powell said of the pool.
   Oddly enough, White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater earlier
Thursday had charged that a pool participant had ``divulged their
participation and departure before they left here.'' He wouldn't
say what organization had done so.
   Williams, speaking to reporters earlier, said his office had
complained to field commanders because pool members had been
restricted largely to interviews with U.S. embassy officials during
most of the first day of the invasion.
   He laid the problem to ``incompetence'' and said, ``There really
is no excuse for it.''
   Later he said he was personally responsible for the operation of
the press pool and was accepting the characterization of
incompetence for himself rather than for the officers in the field.
``They've been working day and night for five days,'' he said of
the Southern Command officers.
   Williams spoke at the close of a news conference at which top
military officers also were asked why they had not taken more steps
to protect U.S. reporters, who were not members of the pool, from
being taken hostage at the Marriott Hotel.
   The spokesman and other senior Pentagon officials said the first
objective of the invasion force had been to disperse the Panamanian
Defense Forces and occupy their base, which they said they
accomplished on Wednesday.
   The lives of American hostages became a prime concern for U.S.
forces as the fighting died down. Williams said there were reports
of an unknown number of Americans being held in three separate
incidents.
   ``We take them all seriously,'' he said. Those held were said to
include Jon Meyersohn, a CBS News television producer.
   U.S. troops evacuated 29 Americans and 35 foreigners, mostly
Panamanians, from the Marriott Hotel in Panama City late Wednesday
night, but Williams said a list of the evacuees was not available.
   Overall, 35,000 U.S. citizens live in Panama, and ``there are
Americans scattered throughout the city,'' said Williams.
</TEXT>

</DOC>