<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0149 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0941EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i PM-Japan'sGoldenAge Adv03   12-28 1004</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Japan's Golden Age, Adv 03,1030</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv03</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Wednesday PMs, Jan. 3 or Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Domestic Economy, Not Exports, Makes Japan Stronger than Ever</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSAN MOFFAT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Japanese economy heads into the 1990s riding a
boom based on spending at home. Its fundamental shift away from
export dependence may make it an even greater powerhouse in the
next century, say economists.
   At the same time, American exports to Japan have been rising.
They jumped 34 percent in 1988 and were increasing at a 19-percent
rate for 1989 by mid-December.
   The Japanese are still working overtime, but not necessarily to
send cars, TV sets or VCRs to Main St., U.S.A., or elsewhere abroad
but to satisfy their own appetites.
   ``I'm thinking of buying a new car since two of my children
graduated from school this year,'' said a middle-age man looking
over Nissans in a showroom. ``I am now living comfortably. Now I am
going to enjoy life with my wife.''
   Akihiro Nagayama, a junior at Meiji University, said he already
has a car, a stereo and a video and now was shopping for a leather
coat. He said he wasn't as conscious of brand-name products as the
older generation.
   ``I buy what I need. I have a part-time job and get some money
from my parents when I go shopping. I'm satisfied with the way
things are.''
   ``Japan is entering a long-term cycle of consumer spending like
the United States in the 1950s and 1960s,'' says Kenneth Courtis,
economist at DB Capital Markets in Tokyo.
   Economists think the present domestic-based expansion may well
outlast the export boom. In the quarter ended in September, Japan's
gross national product grew at an annualized 12.2 percent _ the
fastest of any quarter since 1973, based primarily on strong
spending on investment in plants by Japanese companies.
   The problem is, says Courtis, that ``the world hasn't
crystallized what's happening here.'' Just as the world woke up in
the 1970s to discover Japan had an automobile industry, ``in the
1990s we'll wake up and say, `Look at these companies.'''
   In 1985 exports made up 16.5 percent of Japan's GNP, the measure
of a country's production of goods and services; today they are
less than 10 percent of GNP. This ratio is lower than any major
industrial country except the United States, according to Bank of
Japan figures. Relatively sluggish export growth has actually
slowed down the Japanese economy for the past three years.
   Still, competition with Japanese exports remains a formidable
problem for countries like the United States, which suffers a
$50-billion trade deficit with Japan. But the Japanese challenge
comes from an export sector that is only one small part of Japan's
total economy.
   Japan is the most profitable market in the world, according to
more than half of the American and European companies polled by
consultants Booz, Allen and Hamilton.
   American products finding profitable niches in Japan include
Levi jeans and other apparel items; bourbon, beer, California wine,
soft drinks, instant film, razor blades, ``muscle cars'' and Jeeps,
fast food and processed foods.
   Japan is investing three times more per capita than the United
States in factories, research and development, says Courtis. Most
of that is aimed not at increasing export capacity but at reducing
labor costs and developing new technologies and products.
   Based on this investment and the restructuring of the economy
away from exports, Japan will probably be a more powerful _ and
resilient _ economic force than ever in the next century, believe
many economists.
   Ironically, the present boom was spurred by an event that some
doomsayers said would cripple the economy _ the rise of the yen
starting in 1985, pushed by governments trying to reduce Japan's
worldwide trade surplus. Exports were indeed hurt as the exchange
rate made them more expensive and less competitive. But the economy
came out stronger than ever.
   Like the discipline imposed by the oil shocks of the 1970s, the
pain of the high yen was in the end a tonic for Japan.
   ``Manufacturers started switching markets from foreign to
domestic and found (Japan) was a very profitable market,'' says
Tsutomu Tanaka, an economist at the government's Economic Planning
Agency.
   In 1987 real GNP grew a healthy 5.2 percent, in 1988 5.1 percent
and the overall level for 1989 is expected to be about 5 percent.
   ``The change is rather dramatic,'' says Tanaka. ``We used to
depend on exports for growth.''
   Anyone who visited Japan in 1985 and returns today can see the
changes wrought by the high yen.
   In 1985 a foreign car was a rare sight; most people worked on
Saturdays; people constantly complained that Japan was a ``poor
island country with no natural resources that must export to
survive.''
   Today shoppers cruise the Tokyo boutique scene in Maseratis and
Mercedes Benzes. Surfboard-laden RVs head for the beaches on
two-day weekends. Tiffany's displays jewels in the windows of a
Ginza department store that now is part owner of the luxury
retailer.
   Tokyo stores today make the typical American mall look
out-of-date.
   Every week seems to spawn a new health drink, a smaller portable
video player, wilder fashions, a new ethnic restaurant.
   Japanese need what-to-buy magazines with names like Trendy and
Goods Press just to keep up.
   Domino's Pizza scooters buzz pepperoni-and-mushroom specials to
Japanese couch potatoes playing with electronic gadgets not yet
available in the United States.
   Neighborhoods where ``rabbit hutch'' houses huddled five years
ago are sprouting solidly built condominiums. The only rub is that
prices are too high for most young families, who console themselves
with new cars and appliances and overseas vacations.
   A recruiting pamphlet for giant Nippon Steel does not feature
factories, but spiffily dressed young men enjoying life in the
flashy Roppongi nightlife district. Nowadays steel manufacturers
are building resorts and importing wine; they're also selling so
much steel to the booming domestic construction market that there
isn't enough left over to meet export demand.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Wednesday PMs, Jan. 3</NOTE>

</DOC>