<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0204 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1859EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Cattle-Beef     12-28 0421</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cattle-Beef,0436</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cattle Industry Says Beef Demand Stabilizing</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The cattle industry said Thursday that demand
for beef is stabilizing after several years of decline, in part
because farmers and ranchers have responded to consumer tastes by
producing leaner cuts.
   If bones are counted, Americans buy more chicken. If the bones
are omitted from retail weights, beef is the leader.
   The National Cattlemen's Association said it expects little
change next year in average per capita beef supplies and average
consumer prices.
   The association's president-elect, John Lacey, said the cutting
away fat from retail cuts has helped improve beef's image. He also
cited breeding and feeding advances as further boosts for the
industry.
   Topper Thorpe, general manager of Cattle-Fax, a market
information service, said no dramatic changes are expected in the
nation's cattle herd or in U.S. beef production in 1990.
   But today's total cattle herd of about 100 million head,
including dairy animals, is producing almost as much beef as the
much larger herds of the 1970s, Thorpe told a news conference.
   Cattle herds peaked at about 132 million head in the mid-1970s
and generally have fallen because of oversupply, rising production
costs, drought and other factors. Thorpe said the herd liquidation
has ended and a ``modest expansion'' has begun.
   ``Now, if weather is favorable and if financing becomes cheaper,
more producers may hold back heifers and expand their breeding
herds,'' he said. ``However, we do not see foresee rapid
expansion.''
   Using one method based on bone-in retail weights, the U.S.
Department of Agriculture says per capita consumption of beef in
1990 may drop slightly to an average of 67.8 pounds from 68.6
pounds in 1989 and 72.1 pounds in 1988. The peak was 94 pounds in
1976.
   Total poultry, which includes broilers, baking hens and turkeys,
has been setting records annually and is forecast to average 89.4
pounds in 1990, up from 84.4 in 1989 and 80.6 in 1988. Poultry
first passed beef in 1987.
   But the cattle industry says in its promotion campaign that if
you take away the bones, beef is still far ahead of poultry.
   Richard Stillman of USDA's Economic Research Service said that
on a boneless basis 1989 per capita beef consumption may average
67.1 pounds, down from 68.2 in 1988. A further slight decline is
expected in 1990.
   On the same boneless basis, he said, 1989 poultry consumption
may average 59.9 pounds, up from 57.2 pounds in 1988, with another
gain in the works next year.
</TEXT>

</DOC>