<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1013EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-PentagonText 2ndAdd   12-20 0973</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Pentagon Text, 2nd Add,1,000</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON: that situation.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   With respect to General Noriega, as you know, we're only seven
hours into this operation. We have not yet located the general. He
has a habit of changing locations in normal times four or five
times a night.
   But we will continue our efforts to locate him. But, as a
practical matter, we have decapitated him from the dictatorship of
this country and he is now a fugitive and will be treated as such.
   With respect to the embassy, the American embassy did take some
fire in the course of the evening. Nobody was injured. There was
some minor damage to the embassy. And we have US forces in strength
at the embassy to secure it.
   As you know, there is a new government in place. And I will talk
briefly about the casualty figures. As you know, this is
preliminary, and I want to reemphasize that the numbers I'm about
to give you are preliminary and are subject to change as we move in
the course of the morning and get better information.
   At the moment, the figures I have from the Southern Command
provide the information that nine Americans were killed in action.
Thirty-nine Americans were wounded in action. One American is
missing.
   Several aircraft were damaged. They include several C-130s and
some helicopters and I have no information that I'm comfortable
with PDF casualties to provide at this time.
   That concludes my briefing.
   
   Q: Gen. Powell, do you see the need to send further
reinforcements or are we seeing all of the forces that are going to
be necessary?
   Powell: The forces I mentioned that are being sent in now for
reinforcement, the Seventh Division and the MPs, I think that'll do
it. I think that'll bring it up to around 24,000 and that's really
not for sustained combat but for stability operations to make sure
that we are truly controlling the situation.
   Q: ... 24,0000, you're sending in or does that include ...
   Powell: No, that's total including those that were there to
begin with.
   Q: So that includes the ones that are in now, Gen. Powell ...?
   Powell: Yes, total.
   Q: or the ones that will be in?
   Powell: That includes all that we are planning including those
that are in the reinforcement package coming. And that is, as you
know, a number that can float around as we adjust our plans in the
course of the day.
   Q: How many have been sent in so far?
   Powell: There were 13,000 to begin with _
   Cheney: who were already there.
   Powell: who were already there as part of Southern Command
assets before the operation began overnight and so far we have
introduced close to another 7,000 and we have roughly 2,500, I
believe, on the way, from the Seventh Division and the 16th MP
Brigade.
   Q: Gen. Powell, what about members of the 82nd Airborne and some
of the Army Rangers who were brought in. I know you say you want to
get them out as quickly as possible. When can we expect that they
will be sent home?
   Powell: Well, the primary mission right now is to make sure the
situation is under control and we have satisfied our objectives and
then as soon as that is as we would like it to be and we're sure
that things are settled down, we will start to retrograde those
soldiers as quickly as possible, but I don't have a specific
timeline yet.
   Q: Gen. Powell ... Do you have any evidence that Noriega was
about to threaten the operations of the Canal?
   Powell: I have heard those reports. He has been saying this for
years and years so those reports would not surprise me. But I don't
know that I want to get into specific reports.
   Q: (Inaudible)
   Powell: Nothing that came to my attention that caused me great
concern. We had deployed our forces in a way that provided, I
believe, adequate protection of the Canal.
   Q: Gen. Powell, can you tell us where President Endara was sworn
in, who did it? I mean, tell us a little bit about that scenario.
Can you?
   Powell: He was sworn in shortly before the operation. I don't
have the details and I think I'd better _ I need to refer you to
the State Department for those kinds of answers. It was a
Panamanian. He was sworn in by a Panamanian justice of some kind
and it was done an hour before, but with respect to ...
   Q: At an American base?
   Powell: Yes. But I really need to refer you to State Department,
because it was handled by the State Department.
   Q: Gen. Powell, what assurances do you have that Noriega isn't
going to escape into the countryside and organize some kind of
guerrilla operations to keep harassing US forces down there?
   Powell: Oh, he can do that, and we will chase them and we will
find him.
   Q: Do you know that he's still in the country?
   Powell: No, I don't know that. We _ he is a very canny
individual. He's demonstrated incredible ability to survive
catastrophe. And we'll see over time whether he survives this
catastrophe.
   Q: General, now wouldn't he make life miserable for the U.S.
forces down there?
   Powell: I doubt it. No. I don't think, one, it's been some years
since General _ Mr. Noriega, the fugitive, has been seen in the
jungle, living in the jungle. He's used to a different kind of
lifestyle, and I'm not quite sure he would be up to being chased
around the countryside by Army Rangers, Special Forces and Light
Infantry units of the Joint Operations Training Center. But you
might _ I can't rule that out, but I think that's rather far
fetched.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>MORE</BYLINE>

</DOC>