<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1832EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-EastGermany 1stLd-Writethru a0709 12-17 0638</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0709,0652</SECOND>
<HEAD>Communists Call For `Human, Democratic Socialism'; Oppose Reunification</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS one graf after 12th `He said...' to ADD reform group
backing German unity; pickup graf 13 pvs `Gysi also...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BER1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH G. SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   East Germany's struggling Communists called
for a ``human, democratic socialism'' and stressed their opposition
to German reunification as an emergency party congress ended Sunday.
   The 2,700 Communist delegates scrapped their old party platform
and adopted a new one designed to guide the party until its next
regular congress in February.
   The congress ended with a new name for the discredited party,
which is trying to maintain a role for itself as elections approach
next May. Delegates changed the party's official name from the
Socialist Unity Party of Germany to the Socialist Unity Party of
Germany-Party of Democratic Socialism.
   Under pressure from mass pro-democracy protests, the party in
the past two months has ousted hard-line leaders, opened the Berlin
Wall and other borders, promised free elections and ushered in
reforms.
   In the latest change, Premier Hans Modrow announced that East
Germany's new domestic intelligence services will be under direct
control of the government. The new agency will replace the hated
Ministry for National Security, which was dissolved.
   The new Communist platform says the party roots lie in the
``Communist and social democratic workers' movement,'' a phrase
aimed at disassociating the party from 40 years of Stalinist rule
from the top.
   ``The goal is a new, human, democratic socialism'' in East
Germany, the platform said, in an echo of a phrase used by former
Czechoslovak Communist leader Alexander Dubcek. Dubcek's attempt to
create ``socialism with a human face'' was crushed by East Germany
and four other Warsaw Pact nations that invaded his country in 1968.
   ``It was the first democratic party congress we have staged in
decades,'' East German party chief Gregor Gysi told delegates.
   Gysi, a 41-year-old lawyer who has defended the rights of the
opposition, was elected to head the Communists during the first
part of the congress Dec. 9-10. The meeting resumed on Saturday.
   In a keynote speech Sunday, Gysi urged further political,
economic and military reforms.
   He reiterated the Communists' opposition to German
reunification, saying East Germany must remain ``a humanistic,
socially oriented alternative'' to its capitalist western neighbor,
the official news agency ADN reported.
   He said the existence of two Germanys is ``the guarantee for
ensuring peace and stability in Europe,'' according to ADN.
   However, in Leipzig on Sunday, delegates at the founding party
congress of Democratic Awakening, a church-led reform movement,
voted 350-35 that the right of German unity should be inscribed in
the East German constitution.
   Gysi also urged the adoption of a new national constitution and
creation of a supreme court to defend it. He urged a reduction in
the length of army service and ``an immediate freeing of military
capacities for the economy.''
   Gysi called for discussions with church leaders on a law
protecting religion in East Germany. He said the Communists favor
protecting ``Jewish religion and culture'' and urged Modrow's
government to resume diplomatic relations with Israel.
   Modrow was quoted by an Israeli newspaper Sunday as saying East
Germany is willing to change its policy of denying responsibility
for the Nazi Holocaust as a way to establish diplomatic ties with
Israel.
   ``We have approached Israel officially with a request to discuss
establishing diplomatic relations,'' Modrow was quoted as saying in
an interview in the daily Haaretz.
   While West Germany has paid billions of dollars in reparations
to Holocaust survivors, East Germany traditionally has denied
responsibility on the grounds that it did not exist as a state at
the time.
   On Saturday, meanwhile, President Bush said he would be ``very
responsive'' to any request from East Germany for emergency
wintertime food aid.
</TEXT>

</DOC>