<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0095 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1319EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-YablonskiAnniversary Bjt   12-29 0642</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Yablonski Anniversary, Bjt,0659</SECOND>
<HEAD>Union Leader's Murder 20 Years Ago Sparked Change, Son Says</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM STRADER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When three men agreed to murder a United Mine
Workers opposition leader and his family in 1969, they were told
the killings would amount to nothing more than ``local news'' in
the coal fields of western Pennsylvania.
   But in the two decades since, the New Year's Eve slayings of
Joseph A. ``Jock'' Yablonski, 59, his wife, Margaret, 57, and their
daughter, Charlotte, 25, have been a catalyst for major reform in
the coal miners' union.
   And the ``local news'' made national headlines.
   ``Basically, all the things my father had said should be done
have been done,'' said Kenneth Yablonski, now 55, who found the
bodies in the family's stone farmhouse in Clarksville almost a week
after the killings.
   In the months leading up to his death, Yablonski had waged an
unsuccessful campaign to unseat UMW President W.A. ``Tony'' Boyle.
He accused Boyle of corruption, nepotism and misuse of UMW funds.
   Yablonski also pushed for increased rights for rank-and-file
members in electing district officers and fought to clean up union
elections.
   ``All of those things were accomplished,'' said his son, an
attorney in nearby Washington, Pa. ``In the total picture, because
of what happened, I don't think anyone would say the United Mine
Workers is corrupt or its officers are totalitarian.''
   Throughout the 1969 campaign, Yablonski endured intimidation
from Boyle supporters. Until his death, he was suspicious of
strangers who approached him or his family, and with good reason.
   About two weeks before the murders, two of the gunmen had gone
to Yablonski's rural Washington County house, ostensibly asking for
help in getting mining jobs. But Paul E. Gilly and Claude E. Vealey
lost their nerve and did not shoot Yablonski that day.
   That evening, Yablonski told his son: ``Ken, I believe there
were two men here to kill me today.''
   Despite his defeat in the Dec. 9, 1969, election, Yablonski had
remained a vocal opponent of Boyle and had asked the U.S. Labor
Department to investigate possible voter fraud.
   Boyle saw himself as the hard-line heir to long-time UMW boss
John L. Lewis but couldn't match Lewis' charisma, said James A.
Craft, a business administration professor at the University of
Pittsburgh. At the same time, Yablonski was attempting to bring
about reforms.
   ``It was one of those kind of events that provided us with real
change,'' Craft said. ``Yablonski wanted to make some changes and
open things up and Boyle wanted to maintain control. And it
exploded in terms of something terrible happening.''
   Confessions and testimony revealed that Boyle ordered the
killings and other union officials embezzled UMW funds to hire the
gunmen.
   In all, nine people, including Boyle, were convicted. The three
gunmen _ Gilly, Vealey and Aubran W. ``Buddy'' Martin, all of Ohio
_ are serving life prison terms in Pennsylvania, as is the former
UMW official who hired them, Albert E. Pass. The other five
defendants either have been released or, like Boyle, died in jail.
   Although strikes, coal-field disturbances and decreased
production highlighted the ensuing administration of reformist
Arnold Miller, Craft said the union now is on more stable footing.
He called UMW President Richard Trumka a ``reasonable guy with
something on the ball'' and a vision for the union.
   Trumka has led the union in a protracted contract dispute with
the Pittston Co., a months-long strike in which miners say they are
fighting to retain hard-won health benefits.
   Kenneth Yablonski said he and his brother, Joseph Jr., who
practices law in Washington, D.C., continue to oppose parole
requests by those convicted of the killings.
   ``Twenty years hasn't diminished the horror of what happened to
our family,'' he said.
   ``Who are these people to think that 20 years has made a
difference?''
</TEXT>

</DOC>