<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0127 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1817EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-StealthMemo     12-19 0493</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stealth Memo,460</SECOND>
<HEAD>It Was Inevitable: Stealth Jet Begets Stealth Memo</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSANNE M. SCHAFER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Military Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   You've heard of the stealth bomber and the
stealth fighter, undetectable airplanes. The Pentagon has now
created the stealth memo: It can't be detected either.
   Pentagon spokesman Pete Williams, queried Tuesday about the
results of his months-long attempts to obtain more information
about the stealth F-117A fighter for reporters, acknowledged that
several memos on the subject have been lost.
   ``Even in the Pentagon, amazingly as it seems, memos get lost
and deep sixed and vanish into thin air. Stealth memos, yes. This
is a stealth memo program that we're testing,'' Williams quipped
when asked about his efforts.
   ``In fact, a memorandum to the Secretary (of the Air Force) was
written on this issue, sent to the Air Force and it vanished. ...
The Air Force's own radar couldn't detect it,'' Williams joked.
   The F-117A is the Air Force's most secret operational aircraft.
Based at Tonopah Test Range Airfield in Nevada, the jets have been
carefully screened from public view.
   But in recent months, more and more have been observed in flight
and pictures of the black, delta-winged craft have appeared in
magazines and technical journals.
   The jet, which was first test flown in 1978, uses the so-called
``stealth'' technology to provide it with low radar reflectivity
like its newer, better-known cousin, the B-2 bomber.
   The spokesman said the memo first sent to Air Force Secretary
Donald Rice about providing the press with more information ``was
subsequently found and revived'' and sent to another office ``and
it vanished into thin air again.''
   Williams stated that he was certain the Air Force had not ``deep
sixed'' the memo, or allowed it to be lost, arguing that the
service wanted to make more information about the so-called
``black'' program known.
   ``Black'' programs are the most secret in the Pentagon, with
little information released about them.
   One Defense Department source, who spoke on condition he not be
identified by name, said Air Force officials would like to release
some information about the F-117A program to show that its was
well-run, in contrast to difficulties that arose over the costly
B-2 bomber, another classified plane that now is estimated to cost
$530 million apiece.
   The spokesman said the lost memo was ``recreated in my office''
and sent to Rice again, and that he has approved it.
   ``So, there will be some effort to share more information about
the program with you,'' Williams pledged.
   The spokesman contended that the troubles arose because of the
highly secret nature of the fighter program and officials wanted to
be ``as forthcoming as we can without jeoapardizing the very
classified nature of the program. ... We don't do this a lot. We
don't embark very much on a public affairs campaign about black
programs.
   ``So we're in kind of a new area here and we are trying to make
an effort.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>