<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0139 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2110EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Haiti     12-19 0271</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Haiti,0282</SECOND>
<HEAD>Haitian Cabinet Reshuffle, Change In Army High Command</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL NORTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PORT-AU-PRINCE, Haiti (AP) _ A new Cabinet was sworn in Tuesday
after Lt. Gen. Prosper Avril replaced seven ministers, the police
chief and a top army officer in the biggest government shakeup
since he took power last year.
   Franck Paultre, the former public works minister, replaced
Leonce Thelusma as finance minister in the reshuffle, announced on
state-run TV late Monday.
   Thelusma was criticized for his foreign currency-control policy
and for having signed a controversial agreement with the
International Monetary Fund.
   Brig. Gen. Fritz Romulus, the former airport chief who was newly
promoted from colonel, replaced Brig. Gen. Acedius Saint-Louis as
defense and interior minister.
   Saint-Louis drew fire as being ineffective in fighting urban
gangsterism. Romulus, reputed to be a moderate, is the only
military man in the 13-member Cabinet.
   Serge Petit-Frere replaced Remy Zamor as education minister.
   Teachers accused Zamor of authoritarianism. They struck several
times, protesting they had not been paid. They overwhelmingly
rejected an insurance plan Zamor presented for teachers and it was
shelved.
   Also replaced were the ministers of commerce, planning,
agriculture and public administration.
   Col. Henri Robert Augustin, the police chief, was replaced by
Lt. Col. Martial Romulus, who was military attache at the Haitian
Embassy in Washington.
   Maj. Gen. Max Valles, one of Haiti's nine generals, was retired.
For six weeks in 1986, Valles was a member of the provisional junta
which took over after dictator Jean-Claude Duvalier fled into
French exile.
   Avril came to power in a bloodless coup in September 1988 that
ousted Lt. Gen. Henri Namphy.
</TEXT>

</DOC>