<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1810EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania 2ndLd-Writethru a0765 12-17 0849</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0765,0874</SECOND>
<HEAD>Human Chain Protecting Clergyman Turns Into Mass Protest</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 11 grafs to UPDATE with reports of water cannons
used, tanks seen; pickup graf 11 pvs `Earlier, a...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROLAND PRINZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Romanian security forces with tanks and
water cannons battled thousands of anti-government demonstrators
after police tried to deport a dissident clergyman, the Hungarian
news agency and other sources said Sunday.
   It was believed to be one of the largest outbreaks of
anti-government demonstrations in at least two years in Romania,
whose hard-line Communist leaders have crushed dissent and rejected
the reforms under way elsewhere in Eastern Europe.
   The Hungarian state news agency, MTI, quoting a local Hungarian
television reporter in Szeged, said an eviction order against the
Rev. Laszlo Toekes of the Reformed Church in Timisoara was to be
carried out Sunday afternoon.
   Other sources, however, said the authorities had intended to
deport the minister on Saturday. Toekes' fate was not known, MTI
said.
   MTI said Toekes and his family had been guarded for several days
by hundreds of ethnic Hungarian and other Romanian citizens who
formed a human chain to protect him. Toekes has championed ethnic
Hungarian rights.
   ``They tried to prevent the eviction of their clergyman, when
hell broke loose and the human chain changed into a demonstration
of thousands against (President Nicolae) Ceausescu and his
regime,'' MTI reported, citing eyewitness accounts.
   ``Riot police tried to suppress the demonstration, and a bloody
brawl started,'' the Hungarian report said. ``It took almost two
hours for the policemen to gain the upper hand.''
   The report did not say what day the violence broke out, but
other sources reported protest both Saturday and Sunday.
   MTI, quoting the television reporter in Szeged, said,
``Eyewitnesses saw bloodied young people in the streets of
Timisoara and Ceausescu pictures floating on the Bega Canal. They
said many of the demonstrators were arrested.''
   No number was given for those arrested. There was no immediate
injury toll either.
   MTI, quoting travelers returning from Romania, said police used
water cannons against the demonstrators in the West Romanian city.
A Czechoslovak citizen was quoted as saying he had seen tanks and
blockaded streets.
   Earlier, a source at Hungarian television in Budapest told The
Associated Press that at least 10,000 Romanians had demonstrated
Sunday against Ceausescu's authoritarian rule in Timisoara, about
30 miles from the Romanian border.
   Yugoslav travelers returning from Timisoara told The AP in
Belgrade that tens of thousands of people were milling in the
streets Sunday morning. The Yugoslavs said that ``the entire city
seemed on the streets.''
   They said that when they left the city at 2 p.m. that day,
cordons of soldiers, three-deep, were blocking traffic at main
intersections, and large detours were necessary to depart.
   According to the Hungarian television source, the angry crowd
broke display windows of bookstores and threw out books by
Ceausescu.
   According to the source in Budapest, a large part of the crowd
guarding Toekes marched downtown Sunday afternoon, shouting slogans
such as ``Down With Ceausescu!''
   Police reportedly attacked the protesters and managed to control
the crowd by late afternoon.
   Late Sunday, a caller told the Hungarian Danubiusz radio station
in Budapest that tens of thousands were still in the streets of
Timisoara. He said he got his information by telephone.
   The newspaper Die Welt in Bonn, West Germany, said hundreds of
supporters prevented Toekes' deportation on Saturday.
   According to the report in Monday editions, a crowd of 500 on
Saturday ringed the church where Toekes sought refuge after he had
been stabbed by masked, unknown assailants on Nov. 2.
   The faithful, initially only ethnic Hungarians, took turns
because of sub-zero temperatures, Die Welt reported. Later, ethnic
Romanians and members of the Romanian Orthodox Church joined the
crowd, it said.
   By midnight, more than 4,000 had come to the church to protect
Toekes, the newspaper said. It said police units left after they
were confronted with shouts of ``Away With You!'' They were
replaced by plainclothes officers, the Bonn report said.
   In Belgrade, the Yugoslav witnesses reported that around 9 p.m.
Saturday, the main square around the Continental Hotel was filled
with about 3,000 people. Their report could not be independently
confirmed.
   The Romanian state news agency Agerpres did not report on the
weekend demonstrations.
   Ceausescu, who was elected Romanian Communist Party chief on
March 22, 1965, is the longest-serving Soviet bloc leader.
   He has stamped out virtually all dissent in Romania. His crash
industrialization program and his frantic efforts to repay all of
Romania's $11 billion debt have led to perennial shortages of
consumer goods and rationing of basic foodstuffs.
   The last major demonstration was believed to be in November
1987, when at least 10,000 factory workers and other citizens
protested against his hard-line rule in Brasov, Romania'
second-largest city.
   In Budapest, hundreds of Hungarians gathered in front of the
Romanian Embassy on Sunday, chanting slogans and singing
Transylvanian songs.
   Transylvania is in western Romania, where most of the country's
1.7 million ethnic Hungarians. They have long complained of
discrimination by Romanian authorities.
</TEXT>

</DOC>