<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0214 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1724EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-TaintedMeat     12-29 0372</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tainted Meat,0385</SECOND>
<HEAD>Executives Get Prison for Adding Animal Parts to Meat</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LORI DODGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal judge Friday sentenced two meat
company executives to up to two years in prison for illegally
adding animal parts and other substances to meat and ordered
$285,000 in restitution.
   West Meat Co., president Joseph A. West and his son, processing
plant manager Jeffrey L. West, pleaded guilty in August to charges
of adulterating meat in violation of federal meat laws.
   U.S. District Judge William Hungate sentenced the elder West to
two years in prison and his son to 21 months. The two men and the
company were ordered to pay a total of $285,000 in restitution to
the state.
   West Meat, based in the St. Louis suburb Rock Hill, was charged
in a federal indictment last June with adding ``unidentified
substances previously packaged as pet food,'' to ground beef, pork
sausage and Polish sausage.
   The meats were sold to about two dozen state hospitals, schools
and prisons between October 1987 and October 1988, when the scheme
was uncovered by federal investigators, the indictment said.
   The government said that in addition to the pet food substances,
beef blood, poultry parts, bones, deer meat, water and extra fat
were added to ground beef. Pork sausage was adulterated with
several items, including adrenal and salivary glands.
   Jim Greene, a spokesman for the U.A. Department of Agriculture's
Food Safety and Inspection Service, said West Meat had voluntarily
ceased operations in May. He said the USDA would withdraw
inspection services, preventing the company from reopening.
   Earlier this month, West Meat was banned from doing business
with Missouri for 20 years. A state circuit court judge also
ordered the company to pay $20,000 to the state and invalidated
more than $40,000 in bills owed by Missouri.
   Greene said the USDA had been involved in about 160 such
prosecutions in the last five years.
   The largest penalty ever assessed a company was $2 million
against Sandy Mac Food Co. of Pennsauken, N.J., a ham processing
firm that pleaded guilty to bribing federal inspectors, selling
adulterated hams and falsifying records.
   Greene said there are about 7,000 meat slaughtering and
processing plants in the United States.
</TEXT>

</DOC>