<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0131 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 2306EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-Nicaragua-US 1stLd-Writethru a0583 12-23 0332</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Nicaragua-US, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0583,0341</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nicaraguan Troops Against Surround U.S. Embassy</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with Ortega speech. Pick up 2nd
pvs, `Several trucks...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RODOLFO GARCIA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANAGUA, Nicaragua (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nicaraguan soldiers surrounded the
U.S. Embassy again Saturday in an effort to force U.S. soldiers
searching for Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega to end their blockade of
Nicaragua's Embassy in Panama.
   President Daniel Ortega, who has repeatedly predicted a U.S.
invasion of Nicaragua, called for formation of ``a single Latin
American and Caribbean army to defend the sovereignty that is being
trampled in Panama.''
   ``War must be declared on the interventionist policy of the
United States,'' he said in a 30-minute speech in Chinandega, 80
miles northwest of Managua.
   ``A single army! A single army!'' the Sandinista crowd cheered.
   Several trucks full of troops and light artillery were in the
U.S. Embassy area in the southeastern part of the city.
   An officer in charge who refused to give his name called the
deployment ``routine movements'' and refused to say more.
   Asked about the troop deployment, the U.S. Embassy press
officer, Louis P. Falino Jr., said: ``I have no comment.''
   The standoff began Thursday, one day after U.S. forces invaded
Panama to topple Noriega and his Panamanian Defense Forces.
   In their search for Noriega, who escaped an attack that
decimated his headquarters, U.S. forces surrounded the Nicarguan,
Cuban and Libyan embassies in Panama City after rumors spread that
Noriega or his men were hiding there.
   Those embassies remained surrounded Saturday.
   In rataliation, Nicarguan troops supported by tanks surrounded
the U.S. Embassy in Managua all day Thursday, withdrawing that
night.
   Nicaraguan armored vehicles returned Friday night, but only for
15 minutes.
   Asked about Saturday's deployment around the U.S. Embassy,
Foreign Minister Miguel D'Escoto told reporters the move was in
response to the U.S. military blockade of the Nicaraguan Embassy
and that the standoff would continue until the Nicaraguan mission
in Panama City was cleared.
</TEXT>

</DOC>