<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1535EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China-Mao     12-26 0675</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Mao,0693</SECOND>
<HEAD>China Claims Mao Revival As Chairman's 96th Birthday Marked</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM ABRAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   China marked the 96th birthday of Mao Tse-tung on
Tuesday amid official claims that young people disillusioned with
Western philosophies are rediscovering truth in the works of the
late Great Helmsman.
   The official press says there is a quiet resurgence of interest
in Mao, the father of Communist China who, since his death in 1976,
has also been blamed for bringing great suffering to China with his
radical policies.
   Young people, the media report, have abandoned their Sartre and
Nietzsche and have returned to the works of Mao, Marx and Lenin.
   College students, Shanghai's Wen Hui Daily said, after traveling
the ``winding road'' of fascination with Western thought, ``have
returned to our forefathers to ask for advice. ... Is this not a
good omen?''
   The implication is that college students, after the government's
bloody suppression of their pro-democracy movement this year and
months of heavy political indoctrination, now realize that Mao and
Marx were right all along.
   Young people questioned privately said they had heard of no one
rushing out to buy ``The Selected Works of Mao Tse-tung.''
   ``Mao is a kind of cover,'' said one graduate student.
``Journalists have to perform their job, they have to write
something'' and Mao is a safe subject that adheres to party line,
he said.
   Crowds at Mao's mausoleum in Tiananmen Square, where his body
lies in state, were far smaller on his birthday Tuesday than in
previous years. A bitingly cold Siberian wind may have kept many
away, as did the continuation of martial law in Beijing that limits
access to the square to those with proper IDs.
   One vender outside the mausoleum said 10,000 to 20,000 people a
day viewed Mao's body before June. Now, the number is 4,000 to
5,000 daily.
   The overseas edition of the official People's Daily Tuesday
reported the increased popularity of Shaoshan, Mao's birthplace in
rural southern China. It said Shaoshan will receive 600,000
visitors this year, up from last year but still far below the
nearly 3 million pilgrims a year during Mao's lifetime.
   The daily also said Mao's 96th birthday was being marked with
the release of a tape titled ``A Truly Great Man of No Equal In His
Time'' on which 12 of Mao's poems are set to traditional music. A
book chronicling Mao's family line back to the Yuan Dynasty
(1271-1368) was also published.
   However, a check of several bookstores found neither tape nor
works by Mao. A clerk at one of Beijing's larger bookshops said
Mao's works had been sold out since June, but a saleswoman at a
smaller shop said, ``we haven't carried Mao's works for five
years.''
   Another clerk corrected her, saying, ``we haven't carried them
for 20 years. Every family already has his works, so there's no
need to buy them.''
   During the 1966-76 Cultural Revolution, Mao's disastrous attempt
to purge the bureaucracy and restore ideological purity to the
revolution, all Chinese were required to possess his ``Little Red
Book'' of quotations and study from it daily.
   Official reports of a revival of interest in Mao have also been
tempered by warnings against nostalgia for the personality cult
around Mao that his successor, Deng Xiaoping, has tried to eschew.
   ``Everyone knows that Mao Tse-tung was a man and not a god,''
the Beijing Daily said.
   It quoted Deng as saying Mao was a great man and ``if it were
not for Chairman Mao our country would have groped in the dark for
an even longer period of time.'' But it cautioned against ``great
mass fervor among young students'' for the Great Helmsman.
   There is little sign of that, although some Chinese embittered
by the government's corruption and harsh suppression of democratic
reform look back fondly on the revolutionary ideals represented by
Mao in the early days of the People's Republic.
   ``People prefer Mao to now,'' said the graduate student. ``The
present government is too corrupt. At least Mao was for the
people.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>