<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1806EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Professor'sDeath     12-17 0549</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Professor's Death,0566</SECOND>
<HEAD>Couple Who Committed Suicide Linked to Spiritual Guide, Paper Says</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A former professor and his wife who shot
themselves to death had consulted a spiritual guide who is facing
lawsuits in the deaths of seven associates, according to a report
published Sunday.
   David and Glenda Goodman, who killed themselves in late October,
were among a tightly knit group who followed the teachings of Terri
Hoffman, who reportedly told students she was an incarnation of
Christ, The Dallas Morning News said.
   The Goodmans' deaths bring to nine the number of associates of
Hoffman who have committed suicide or died in accidents since 1977.
   Mrs. Hoffman is accused in two Dallas lawsuits of profiting and
``mind control'' in the deaths of the seven who died before the
Goodmans: five followers and two of her husbands, the paper said.
It did not say when the lawsuits were filed.
   The suits by the victims' survivors allege that Mrs. Hoffman
used hypnosis to make her associates change their wills and
insurance policies to favor her and her metaphysical organization,
Conscious Development of Body, Mind and Soul Inc.
   Papers filed with the lawsuits allege that Mrs. Hoffman caused
her followers to kill themselves or suffer fatal accidents.
   The Goodmans had written checks to Mrs. Hoffman for more than
$110,000 in return for her showing them the ``purple realm,'' their
promised realm, the paper said, citing police sources.
   Fred Time, Mrs. Hoffman's attorney, refused to discuss specifics
of the case but told the newspaper that she was not connected with
the Goodmans' deaths.
   ``This is character assassination,'' the attorney said. ``You
have nothing to go on. ... What's wrong with giving a large gift in
return for spiritual guidance? Call up some of the big churches and
see if anybody died and left them money.''
   Mrs. Hoffman, who declined an interview with the newspaper, did
not immediately return a telephone call from The Associated Press.
   The Goodmans' badly decomposed bodies were found in their Lake
Highlands home Nov. 25. Authorities have not determined the exact
circumstances of their deaths, but have ruled that no third person
participated in the shootings.
   Goodman was a Berkeley and Yale-educated business and computer
professor at Southern Methodist University. He left teaching at the
private Dallas college in 1987 to begin an investment counseling
service and newsletters.
   Dallas police said Friday the Goodmans' deaths were still under
investigation.
   ``Even though the evidence indicates that these two deaths were
not caused by an outside agency, the unusual circumstances have
caused us to keep this case open,'' Deputy Police Chief Ray Hawkins
told the paper.
   ``When these cases were ruled suicides, we basically got out of
it,'' police Detective Bobby Hammer said when contacted by The
Associated Press on Sunday. He said they were currently not
investigating the other deaths.
   The paper said Mrs. Hoffman had about 20 followers, some of whom
were students at SMU.
   The newspaper said manuscripts police found at the Goodmans'
home show they were studying Mrs. Hoffman's teachings of gods and
spirits, rays, energy and karma.
   ``You are no longer David Goodman, son of Alice &amp; Leonard,''
said one passage addressed to Goodman in his wife's handwriting.
``That person is gone because the programming is wiped out. You are
Jupiter now.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>