<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0174 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1356EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-PRI--UntietheElderly Adv28-1stAdd   12-26 0453</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-PRI--Untie the Elderly, Adv 28-1st Add,0461</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv28</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Thursday, Dec. 28, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON: tied down.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Some nursing home officials, however, caution that there are
cases where there are no clear alternatives to restraints.
   ``While we all can agree that overuse or wholesale use of
restraints is not desirable, it is equally wrong to say no
restraints should ever be used,'' said David Mettler of Hillhaven
Corp., which runs 345 nursing homes in 38 states.
   ``This is not a black-and-white issue,'' Mettler said.
``Sometimes it may even be necessary to restrict the rights of an
individual resident in order to provide for the health and safety
of others.''
   For dramatic reduction in restraints, residents and families
must accept that ``if people have a certain amount of freedom, then
they also run the risk of getting hurt,'' said attorney Joanne
Ivancic of HFIC Management Co., which handles insurance claims for
Hillhaven.
   Benedictine has eliminated most restraints, but ``there's maybe
5 to 10 percent of the people that I can't figure out how to get
restraint-free,'' Rader said, citing as one example those who pull
out tubes unless restrained.
   Nursing home staffers who initially are skeptical about managing
residents without restraints usually find they prefer it, said
Kendal's Goldman. She quoted from a recent letter from a nurse at
Friends Hall, which in 1987 adopted a no-restraint policy: ``I
wouldn't work any other place now. I wouldn't have said that or
believed it two years ago.''
   Nine nursing homes in a Kendal demonstration program have
reduced restraint use without an increase in falls, staff or costs,
Goldman said.
   That is possible because residents who can move around generally
stay healthier and require less care, Blakeslee said. Also, it
takes a lot of time to properly apply restraints and remove them
for exercise and use of bathrooms.
   Stapeley in 1988 set a goal of untying five residents a month
and a year later removed the last restraint, said Henrietta
Roberts, executive director.
   ``I can't tell you how the families have been pleased by this,''
she said. ``The sense of humanitarianism, the sense that you are
dealing with a person ... has made a great deal of difference. The
patients are easier to care for.''
   Supporters of the change at Stapeley include Bernie Lieberman,
whose 89-year-old mother, Frances, had been routinely restrained
after she fell and broke a hip. Now, staffers help her walk and she
wears no restraints while seated.
   ``She seems much more cheerful and positive as a result of
having more freedom,'' Lieberman said. ``Even though her mind was
not working well, she was just the kind of person who wanted to get
up and walk.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Dec. 28</NOTE>

</DOC>