<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0164 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1904EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Germany-Vigil 1stLd-Writethru a0608 12-18 0730</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Vigil, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0608,0751</SECOND>
<HEAD>Marchers in Leipzig Hold Vigil for Victims of Stalin</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs to include other demonstrations; picks up
7th `Recent Monday'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NESHA STARCEVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LEIPZIG, East Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pro-democracy activists who had
marched noisily each week since early fall set aside bullhorns and
banners Monday night for a silent vigil to honor the victims of
Stalin.
   An estimated 200,000 people took part. Many carried candles
through the darkened winter streets around Karl Marx Platz for 15
minutes after a memorial service for those mistreated during what
now is called ``the intolerance of the past.''
   In September and early October, reformers were beaten and jailed
for taking part in protests.
   ADN, the official news agency, put the crowd at more than
100,000, but an Associated Press reporter in Leipzig estimated the
total at 200,000.
   Demonstrations also were reported in other East German cities.
ADN said about 30,000 people marched through Karl-Marx-Stadt, at
first silently but then with growing chants of ``Germany, United
Fatherland!''
   At Halle, opposition speakers were booed when they spoke against
reunification, the agency said. It did not say how many people
demonstrated.
   Several hundred candle-bearing demonstrators marched silently
through central East Berlin to commemorate victims of Stalinism and
about 3,000 people demonstrated for a clean environment in
Schwerin, it said.
   Leipzig church leaders and protest organizers had asked
demonstrators to be silent this week, and most marchers honored the
call for a solemn memorial.
   Recent Monday night protests aimed at keeping pressure on the
Communist-dominated government for more democratic change escalated
into shouting matches between supporters of saving a sovereign East
Germany and a growing minority seeking reunification with West
Germany.
   Isolated groups of reunification advocates disrupted the silent
march at times with shouts of ``Germany, United Fatherland.'' But
they were quickly hushed by others who whistled their disapproval
or implored them to cease chanting.
   There were no speeches by organizers at the march, another break
with a tradition that has made the Leipzig event a forum for airing
grievances and proposals.
   A few signs on the march route expressed solidarity with
pro-democracy movements in other East European nations, especially
in hard-line Romania.
   ``Freedom also for Romania,'' declared one sign.
   The discipline exhibited by most marchers was likely a result of
leaflets distributed in advance of the event by Leipzig conductor
Kurt Masur, a respected leader of the reform effort.
   ``The whole of Europe hopes along with us that the future
Leipzig Monday demonstrations after Jan. 8 will continue peacefully
as has been the case until now, and that the great idea of a united
Europe can become reality,'' Masur wrote. ``We Germans will in this
way naturally grow together and retain the trust of our neighbors.''
   Activists have decided against holding protests on the next two
Mondays because of the Christmas and New Year's holidays.
   Despite the appeals, about 200 participants tried to stir up the
gathering.
   ``Free elections'' and ``One United Germany'' were among the
political slogans hoisted by those who broke the silence.
   Some people in the crowd said they suspected the ultra-rightist
West German Republicans party had infiltrated the marches to raise
the issue of reunification.
   A young student from Dresden said she had been fearful of a
confrontation, as the demonstration last Monday was ``a little too
aggressive.''
   ``I was really afraid, but I'm very glad that this went off so
peacefully,'' said the woman, who did not give her name.
   Worries about a turn toward violence and a rift in the reform
movement mounted after last week's demonstration reached a fever
pitch, but there were no reports of incidents Monday.
   The rally's exceptional solemnity was not expected to dampen
popular sentiment for reunification.
   ``It would all have been in vain if we don`t become a unified
fatherland again,'' one elderly demonstrator told West Germany`s
ZDF television network.
   ``I am for a unified Germany. I am prepared to wait, but I
cannot wait too long,'' said another, younger participant.
   Leipzig was a hotbed of the democratic movement that forced East
Germany's Communist leaders to open the borders Nov. 9 and
relinquish much of their power.
   Among the reasons for Leipzig's role are a strong church
movement that served as rallying point for democracy activists when
authorities still had tight control over dissent, and the serious
deterioration of the city.
</TEXT>

</DOC>