<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0122 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1856EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-UMWLawsuit 1stLd-Writethru a0635 12-27 0539</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-UMW Lawsuit, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0635,0549</SECOND>
<HEAD>Company Sues Union for $60 Million, Alleges Racketeering</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: CORRECTS style on `lawsuit' throughout; SUBS 4th graf, `The
suit ... to CORRECT name of the racketeering statute to Racketeer Influenced,
Corrupt Organizations Act, CORRECT style on usage; SUBS 9th graf, `Calls
to ..., with 2 grafs to UPDATE with union comment; no pickup.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK PAXTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A strike-bound coal company sued the
United Mine Workers for $60 million Wednesday, accusing the union
and its members of attempted murder, arson and extortion as part of
a nationwide racketeering scheme.
   The lawsuit was filed in federal court in Beckley by the New
Beckley Mining Corp., which also announced it will close its nearby
Glen Daniel mine because of what it called union violence stemming
from the UMW's selective strikes.
   The UMW has been on strike against New Beckley since January,
idling 130 miners. The union also is engaged in a bitter strike
against the Pittston Coal Group Inc. in West Virginia, Virginia and
Kentucky.
   The lawsuit was filed under the Racketeer Influenced, Corrupt
Organizations Act. Although the racketeering statute was intended
by Congress primarily as a tool against organized crime, it been
used frequently against unions, including a 1988 lawsuit by the
government against the the Teamsters.
   Earlier this year, the Supreme Court upheld the use of the
statute against legitimate organizations, despite complaints by the
AFL-CIO that it had become ``a tool of harassment ... against
legitimate businesses and labor organizations.''
   The New Beckley Mining lawsuit cites alleged violence at more
than 20 coal companies in West Virginia, Kentucky and Virginia
since 1983, when the union began its selective strike strategy, in
which the UMW targeted specific companies for work stoppages.
Previous strikes were industrywide.
   The lawsuit alleges that New Beckley employees have been the
targets of vandalism, death threats, shootings and beatings at work
and at home.
   The violence ``pervades the coal industry, discouraging
productivity and inhibiting the economic well-being of individuals
living and working in coal-producing communities,'' the lawsuit
says.
   Union spokesman John Duray called the lawsuit ``ridiculous'' and
accused the company of engaging in a ``press-release lawsuit'' by
hiring a public relations company to notify the news media of the
filing.
   ``It looks to me like these guys are a lot more interested in
trying their case in the media than in court,'' Duray said.
   District 29 President Everett Acord said he knew nothing of the
lawsuit or the mine closing.
   At a news conference on the courthouse steps, New Beckley
President Jay Sasell said: ``The decision to shut down and seal New
Beckley's Glen Daniel Mine was reached because the continued
organized violence orchestrated against New Beckley by the UMWA has
reached an intolerable level of acceptability by any rational
standard.
   ``Marauding pickets continue to cause great hardship upon the
company and its families on a daily basis.''
   The lawsuit contends that the union has engaged in a pattern of
racketeering that includes 34 counts of attempted murder, 23 of
arson and 79 of extortion.
   Under the RICO statute, the company's requested $20 million in
damages can be tripled if the union and various individuals are
found to have violated the act.
</TEXT>

</DOC>