<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0424EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Union-TribLabor     12-23 0306</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Union-Trib Labor,0317</SECOND>
<HEAD>Contract Talks Break off at San Diego Newspapers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DENNIS GEORGATOS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Contract talks between The San Diego Union and
The Tribune newspapers broke off after a strike deadline passed
early today, but labor officials say they've decided against
walking out at this time.
   Discussions ended after company lawyers rejected a proposal from
the Newspaper Guild in which the union dropped its demand for a
``closed shop'' _ a key issue in the talks.
   Union leaders said a strike could be called any time.
   Representatives of the guild and the Union-Tribune Publishing
Co. met all day Friday without reaching agreement. Company lawyers
told guild officials they didn't plan further proposals at this
time, setting the stage for a possible strike, which would be the
first in the 51 years the guild has represented employees at the
two newspapers.
   Pay is less an issue than disputes over the length of the
contract and preservation of a union shop.
   The company's last proposal called for a one-year pact with
salary hikes of 8 percent to 10 percent, said Herb Klein, editor in
chief of the Copley Newspapers, a 13-paper chain that includes
those involved in the dispute.
   The guild sought a three-year contract with a 10 percent pay
hike the first year and 5 percent raises in the second and third
years.
   The labor team sought guild security under which everyone in
guild-covered positions would pay dues whether they are members or
not, said George Flynn, chairman of the guild's bargaining
committee.
   The company wants an ``open shop'' that would allow individual
workers to decide whether they want to join a union.
   The guild represents about 1,150 employees in the editorial,
photography, circulation, advertising, business, maintenance,
telephone communications and library departments.
   The old contract expired in June 1988.
</TEXT>

</DOC>