<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0252 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0159EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-AutoDefects     12-20 0444</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Auto Defects,0464</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Upgrades Beretta Investigation</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN FLESHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Federal engineers have upgraded an
investigation of a possible steering deficiency in the 1988
Chevrolet Beretta, the government said.
   The National Highway Traffic Safety Administration also said
Tuesday it was investigating reports of exploding heating systems
in Coachmen Industries recreational vehicles and of cruise control
failures in the Ford Taurus and its twin, the Mercury Sable.
   The agency said it was stepping up its Beretta probe from a
preliminary evaluation, which involves mostly paperwork, to an
engineering analysis, in which the possibly defective parts are
examined.
   Such investigations can lead to recalls or can be dismissed if
engineers decide there is no widespread safety problem.
   There have been 39 complaints of loss of steering control in the
1988 Beretta, agency spokesman Tim Hurd said. Twenty-one accidents
and 10 injuries have been blamed on the problem. An estimated
259,000 of the vehicles are on the road.
   The Chevrolet Corsica is similar to the Beretta, but the agency
did not mention any steering problems with the Corsica.
   General Motors Corp. spokesman Tom Pyden said the company would
continue cooperating with the agency in its investigation.
   ``An engineering analysis doesn't necessarily mean there's a
defect with the vehicle,'' Pyden said.
   The agency has begun a preliminary evaluation of Coachmen
Industries recreational vehicles manufactured between 1981 and
1985. There have been four reports of explosions in the vehicles'
furnaces, which burn liquified petroleum gas, Hurd said. No
injuries or accidents have been reported.
   An estimated 40,000 of the vehicles were manufactured in the
five-year period, he said.
   A spokeswoman for Coachmen Industries, based in Elkhart, Ind.,
said she was not familiar with the report and could not comment.
   The agency also launched a preliminary evaluation of the Ford
Taurus and Mercury Sable manufactured between 1986 and 1988. There
have been 15 reports of cruise controls failing to disengage, Hurd
said. No accidents or injuries have been reported.
   The investigation covers an estimated 1.25 million vehicles,
Ford spokeswoman Joy Stinson said.
   A preliminary evalution was begun of reported fuel tank
corrosion in large General Motors pickup trucks manufactured
between 1984 and 1988. There have been four complaints. An
estimated 1.7 million vehicles are on the road.
   The agency also discontinued several investigations, finding no
evidence of a widespread problem. Among them:
   _Microprocessor problems with the 1987-88 Plymouth Sundance and
its twin, the Dodge Shadow.
   _Fires under the dash in the 1988 and 1989 Ford Mustang and its
twin, the Mercury Capri.
   _Passive restraint system problems in the 1987 Hyundai Excel.
   _Safety belt failure in all Mazda models manufactured between
1984 and 1989.
</TEXT>

</DOC>