<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0161 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1331EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s w BC-WeeklyFarm Adv31   12-28 0860</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Weekly Farm, Adv 31,0884</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Sun Dec. 31 and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Other Voices Remind Yeutter of Needed Actions in 1990</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The big-ticket item in 1990 for Agriculture
Secretary Clayton Yeutter is the Uruguay Round of trade talks in
Geneva, followed by a new farm bill in Congress.
   OK, but what about other closer-to-home consumer issues such as
nutrition labeling or fish inspection? Or a sensible approach to
rural development?
   Those topics so far have been relatively muted in the
Agriculture Department's agenda, overshadowed in the Yeutter camp
by the drumbeat of global trade and farm bill strategy.
   In a recent year-end assessment, Yeutter characterized 1989 as
``one of the best ever'' years for the American farmer.
   The Yeutter list of top priority issues faced by USDA in 1989 _
his first year as secretary _ included world agricultural trade,
food safety, the environment, research and ``serving rural
America'' in general.
   ``We have worked hard this year to lay the groundwork for
enactment of the 1990 farm bill and for successful conclusion of
the Uruguay Round,'' Yeutter said. ``We now need a strong, vigorous
push if we are to open up market opportunities for the future.''
   The Geneva talks, held under the General Agreement on Tariffs
and Trade, are due to conclude in a year. If successful, they will
be a big step toward reducing and eliminating distortions in global
agricultural trade.
   Eileen Kugler of the Washington-based consumer group, Public
Voice for Food and Health Policy, was asked in a telephone
interview what kind of recommendations she had for Yeutter in the
new year.
   The federal meat and poultry inspection system in USDA should be
strengthened, she said. And microbiological criteria should be set
for meat and poultry products to help cut down on contamination by
salmonella and other harmful organisms.
   In the National School Lunch Program, Kugler said, the USDA
should ``take the leadership in reducing fat and set maximum
permitted levels of fat'' in meals served to children.
   Another item on her wish list for 1990 is better labeling on
food products to show nutrition information ``in a clear,
informative manner.''
   Kugler said she would like to see USDA take the lead in
promoting safer food supplies, to assert itself in such a way that
when Congress approves legislation for fish inspection the
department can show itself to be ``more than capable of
implementing a strong fish inspection program.''
   Overall, she said Yeutter's first year has included both pluses
and minuses.
   ``We think that in some cases he's headed in the right
direction, and his heart's in the right place,'' Kugler said.
``We've given the Bush administration a honeymoon, so to speak, and
now we'd like to see some real action.''
   Most general farm organizations and commodity groups see at
least some good things coming out of the GATT talks that occupy so
much of Yeutter's dream for a futuristic agriculture.
   No one really quarrels with gaining better foreign access for
U.S. commodities. Few would argue against the objective of getting
the 12-nation European Economic Community to open its doors wider
to U.S. goods, for example.
   There are many differences, however, on how great would be the
benefits _ or losses _ to American farmers from a global ``free
market'' arrangement, and whether the Geneva negotiations are a
major step toward the abandonment of U.S. price support programs.
   Bob Frederick, legislative director for the National Grange,
said he wishes that the EEC ``instead of talking like a world
trading leader would start acting like one'' by opening markets and
reducing its trade-distorting subsidies.
   Another item on Frederick's 1990 wish list would be that ``all
U.S. farm organizations and commodity groups stop speaking in
tongues that sound like a Babel of voices'' when it comes to
agricultural policies.
   Frederick said he also wishes that Yeutter ``would place more
emphasis on keeping agriculture a part of rural development and not
let Congress solve rural problems'' by imposing urban solutions.
   Asked to elaborate, Frederick said the Grange for some time has
been critical of rural economic remedies that would involve
factories and electric generating facilities to create a
``small-town Detroit'' environment.
   By doing that, he said, a community's base would be shifted from
agricultural to industrial or business in character.
   Many communities got in trouble when they were all based on
agriculture, and Frederick said it could be as disastrous to shift
entirely away from agriculture to one particular kind of industry.
   ``Rural development has never been high on USDA's list during
any administration,'' Frederick said. ``There have been stabs at
it. ... Hopefully, we can get it organized.''
   Frederick said he fears that important aspects of agriculture
may get lost in the shuffle as farm and rural development
legislation now in Congress is implemented.
   ``There's very little mention, if any, of the maintenance of
agriculture as the nucleus for rural communities,'' he said. ``Not
every rural community has the resources or the infrastructures to
take on economic development. So, they're going to have to build on
what that have _ and that's agriculture.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday Dec. 31</NOTE>

</DOC>