<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0144 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 2143EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama 3rdLd-Writethru   12-27 1080</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama, 3rd Ld - Writethru,a0676,1107</SECOND>
<HEAD>Troops Blast Embassy with Rock, Rap and Bad News for Noriega</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS one graf after 3rd graf, ```We feel ...' to UPDATE with
later Bush comment. Picks up 3rd graf, `The diplomatic ...' with minor
editing to conform, trim and RESTORING dropped word ``million'' in 8th
graf, `The president ...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos PAN5,9</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOSEPH B. FRAZIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. soldiers on Wednesday blasted
rock music and the latest Panama news bulletins at the Vatican
embassy where Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega is shuttered, as the
stalemate over his fate continued.
   Both the United States and the new U.S-backed Panamanian
government renewed their pleas Wednesday to the Vatican to release
the ousted dictator.
   ``We feel that the nunciature, the papal nuncio should in the
very near future ask the ex-dictator to leave,'' said President
Guillermo Endara. ``We believe that Gen. Noriega's crimes are not
political. He is a common criminal of the worst kind.''
   In Texas, President Bush said Wednesday he is determined to
bring Noriega to justice ``for poisoning the children of the United
States'' with drugs, but Bush conceded the Vatican's refusal to
give him up does ``complicate things.''
   The diplomatic standoff went into its fourth day and Noriega's
fate remained undetermined. A Vatican spokesman said he did not see
how Noriega could be released to the United States. Among
alternatives being discussed were transfer to a third country and a
trial for Noriega in Panama.
   ``He has been accused, justly accused, of homicides and
narcotrafficking and very, very horrendous crimes,'' Endara said at
a news conference.
   Also on Wednesday, the Panama Canal was returning to normal
gradually, and a spokeswoman said waterway officials hoped to go to
24-hour operation to clear a 125-ship backup as more personnel
returned to work.
   In Panama City, battered by days of fighting and looting, people
were returning to work and lined up outside grocery stores that
were not looted.
   The president of the Panamanian Chamber of Commerce, Alfredo
Maduro, put losses caused by looting between $750 million and $1
billion.
   At some gasoline stations, motorists were lowering buckets into
below-ground storage tanks to fill up their cars. The pumps were
destroyed at many stations by looters.
   In Colon, 50 miles northwest of Panama City, U.S. soldiers
confiscated a warehouse belonging to Carlos Duque, Noriega's
candidate for president in the annulled May elections. A U.S.
soldier who helped in the search said the drug-sniffing dog ``was
running around in circles'' but the troops wouldn't say if drugs
were found.
   On Wednesday, some of the 100 U.S. troops surrounding the
Vatican Embassy hooked up powerful loudspeakers in a nearby parking
lot and played rock songs that included ``I Fought the Law,''
``Voodoo Child'' and ``You're No Good.'' The music could be heard
by reporters on the 12th floor of a nearby hotel.
   Throughout the afternoon, the olive-green loudspeakers were
hooked up to U.S. Southern Command radio. If Noriega was listening,
he could have heard about negotiations over his status and that the
United States froze millions of dollars he allegedly stashed in
overseas accounts.
   A technician who got out of a U.S. military communications van
opened a telephone line box outside the walls of the embassy, but
it couldn't be determined if the lines were being fixed or tapped.
   The Americans also shot out all street lights with pellet guns
and mowed tall grass outside the embassy compound. A Southern
Command spokesman refused to say whether the actions might be for
security or for harassment.
   Noriega fled to the embassy on Sunday, five days after a U.S.
invasion toppled his government and sent him into hiding. U.S.
troops, armored cars and helicopters ring the embassy around the
clock to ensure the toppled strongman doesn't escape or get
spirited away.
   The United States wants to capture Noriega and bring him to the
United States to face drug trafficking charges filed in 1988.
   In Rome, Vatican spokesman Joaquin Navarro reiterated Wednesday
there is no legal way the Holy See can hand Noriega over as there
is no extradition treaty with the United States.
   Navarro added the Vatican is studying the case in its
``juridical, diplomatic and humanitarian, and therefore, ethical
considerations.''
   Without an agreement, it would be nearly impossible for Noriega
to get past the U.S. troops surrounding the Vatican mission. At the
same time, U.S. troops cannot go after Noriega because embassies
are inviolable under international law.
   Faced with the possibility Noriega could be granted asylum in
another country, the U.S. Justice Department filed papers Wednesday
in four countries to freeze bank accounts in which Noriega is
believed to have stashed more than $10 million in ``illegal drug
money.''
   Cuba and the Dominican Republic, where one of Noriega's
daughters lives, have been mentioned as possible havens.
   However, Dominican Foreign Minister Joaquin Ricardo said
Wednesday his country has an extradition treaty with the United
States and Noriega could be extradited if he goes there.
   Bush appeared to leave open the possibility that Noriega could
be tried in Panama. He said there was a threat of Noriega regaining
power if he remained ``unless he were ... sentenced to the prison
sentence he deserves.''
   Endara said Panama's constitution forbids extradition of
Panamaniam nationals to another country but said a loophole might
be provided by the 1904 treaty that allowed the United States to
build the Panama Canal.
   Also Wednesday, Panama's election commission certified that
Endara won a May 7 election nullified by Noriega. The commission
said tallies collected by Endara's coalition were enough to show
his ticket winning with 62.5 percent of the vote. Endara was sworn
in on Dec. 20, shortly after the U.S. invasion began.
   The U.S. military said it arrested most members of Noriega's
Defense Forces, which numbered 15,000, and only a few hundred
remained unaccounted for.
   Among those reported arrested Wednesday was Vicky Amado,
Noriega's long-time mistress.
   Southern Command said Wednesday 23 Americans were killed and 322
wounded since the United States invaded. It said 297 Panamanians
were killed and 123 wounded. Doctors say more than 100 civilians
also died during the fighting.
   Meanwhile, Panama's ambassador to Mexico, Jorge Turner Morales,
resigned and asked for asylum in Mexico, a Panamanian Embassy
employee said on condition of anonymity. Mexico has not officially
recognized the Endara government.
   ``I cannot accept a government that was imposed under the
machine guns of George Bush,'' Turner Morales was quoted as saying
by Mexico's Excelsior news service.
</TEXT>

</DOC>