<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0190 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2249EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Judge-Explosion 4thLd-Writethru a0717 12-18 1190</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Judge-Explosion, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0717,1227</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Bomb Kills Lawyer, `Strong Similarities' With Atlanta, Alabama Bombs</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: New throughout to recast, raise career background on Vance;
DELETES outdated 20th graf pvs, `In Birmingham ...; DELETES final four
grafs to tighten; no pickup.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos AX5,11,14, SAV1,2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BYRD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A lawyer was killed by a bomb blast in his
Savannah office Monday and a mailed bomb was removed safely from
the 11th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals, two days after a postal
bomb killed an 11th Circuit judge at his Alabama home.
   In Birmingham, Ala., where authorities were investigating the
bombing which killed U.S. Circuit Judge Robert S. Vance on
Saturday, an FBI agent said there were ``strong similarities''
among the three devices.
   Savannah attorney Robert Robinson, a black civil rights activist
and city alderman, died of his injuries at 8:25 p.m. while
undergoing surgery in Memorial Medical Center following the blast
in his office around 5 p.m., officials said.
   ``He lost his right arm, his left hand and some upper body
tissue and (had) severe damage to his legs,'' said Floyd Adams, a
fellow alderman. Robinson was unable to communicate with his
doctors, a hospital spokesman said.
   In downtown Atlanta, shaken employees evacuated the five-story
11th Circuit courthouse shortly before 10 a.m. Monday after the
bomb, in a small brown package, was found ``during a random
sampling of the mail,'' said police Maj. W.W. Holley.
   ``The preliminary investigation (in Savannah) indicates strong
similarities to the other explosive devices in Birmingham and
Atlanta,'' said FBI Agent Tom Moore.
   Moore said FBI and postal service bomb experts who were in
Birmingham yesterday and in Atlanta today are being flown to
Savannah. He wouldn't say whether the bomb came in Robinson's mail,
and Savannah police referred inquiries to the FBI.
   Savannah police refused to release details of the bombing, but
Clerk of Council Dyanne Reese said police told the mayor's office
Robinson ``received a package, similar to what's been happening in
Atlanta and Birmingham.''
   ``I was talking with Robby on the phone just before the bomb
exploded,'' said Mayor John Rousakis. ``We were discussing a
community-wide meeting on drugs ... tonight to be held at his
church.''
   Ms. Reese said said police originally believed a gas leak caused
the explosion, but later concluded it was a bomb.
   Vance, 58, died Saturday and his wife was seriously injured when
they opened a package addressed to him at their home in Mountain
Brook, a suburb of Birmingham.
   The Atlanta bomb was removed from the headquarters of the
12-member 11th Circuit, which handles federal appeals from Alabama,
Georgia and Florida. Vance was based in Birmingham and kept his
office there. Much of the 11th Circuit's caseload is drug-related
appeals.
   Vance also fought for racial moderation and progressive stands
in Alabama during 11 years as state chairman of the Democratic
Party. He was nominated to the court in 1977 by then-President
Carter.
   Investigators said there is nothing so far to tie Vance's
assassination to drug traffickers or his civil rights stand.
   In the past year, six pipe bombs were left in mailboxes in the
nearby suburb of Hoover, The New York Times reported Monday, citing
unidentified FBI officials.
   Only one of the bombs exploded, injuring the person thought to
have planted it, but authorities said they could have been lethal,
the Times reported.
   One such recipient, Chriss Doss, was a former associate of Vance
in the Alabama Democratic Party, the Times said.
   State Rep. Jim Pannell of Savannah, who went to law school with
Robinson, said Robinson handled many criminal and personal injury
cases, but could not think of any which would have supplied a
motive for the bombing.
   Robinson represented the National Association for the
Advancement of Colored People in a long-running desegregation case
against the Savannah school system, Pannell said.
   In Washington, D.C., Justice Department spokesman David Runkel
said, ``I think it's premature to draw any conclusions. ... At this
time, there is no civil rights investigation.''
   Runkel noted that Robinson's clients had included accused
cocaine dealers, adding ``there may be different theories floating
around out there.''
   The Savannah bombing occurred just hours after the pipe bomb was
removed from the Atlanta courthouse.
   Bomb specialists examined X-ray pictures of the package before a
technician in head-to-toe protective gear removed through the
court's front door, under a large flag flying at half-staff in
memory of Vance.
   Flak-jacketed officers and federal agents had sealed off the
street in front of the block-long courthouse and the package _
about 10 inches by 10 inches and 4 inches deep _ was placed in a
bomb-proof canister and taken away.
   Police confirmed the package was a bomb that afternoon, said
Postal Inspector Al Adams. The package contained a detonating
device, he said.
   Holley said the brown paper-wrapped package had arrived by mail,
not by hand delivery, and was addressed to the court, not to an
individual, unlike the bomb that killed Vance, Adams said.
   The package had a return address, but Adams declined to disclose
it, saying such addresses are always phony. ``We don't want to get
innocent people involved,'' he said.
   Adams did say the return address was not that of a federal
judge. The package that killed Vance listed the sender as another
federal judge at an almost certainly phony address, The Atlanta
Constitution said, quoting unidentified sources.
   Adams said Atlanta police dismantled the bomb without detonating
it and destroying the package. ``That's a big help to our
investigation,'' he said.
   In Washington, White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said
President Bush had contacted Attorney General Dick Thornburgh about
the investigation.
   ``The attorney general advised him we have not reached any
conclusions,'' Fitzwater said. ``We just don't have any answers yet
as to who might have done it to him.''
   Even before Monday's bomb scare, workers at the 11th Circuit
were scared because of Vance's assassination. During the
evacuation, several who declined to give their names and said they
were ordered not to speak to reporters, said they are reluctant to
return to work.
   When the courthouse was closed, employees were told to call
before returning to work Tuesday _ not only because of the bomb,
but because of unusual December snow in Atlanta early Monday.
   Federal judges around the country had been advised after Vance's
death not to open packages received in the mail until they could be
inspected.
   The FBI said it was giving top priority to finding out who
mailed the bomb that killed Vance, who was believed to be the third
federal judge assassinated in this century _ all three
assassinations occurring in the last 10 years.
   The 11th Circuit Court had opened for business as usual Monday,
despite the snowfall which had many of the city's law offices
opening late.
   Lamar Pope, supervisor of court security for the Northern
District of Georgia, would not comment on increased security
measures at the appeals court. But officials acknowledged that
plans for tighter security were going into effect at Atlanta's
Richard B. Russell Building _ home of the U.S. District Court and
other federal offices. Those plans began two months ago.
</TEXT>

</DOC>