<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0229 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0127EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-BusinessHighlights     12-22 0827</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Business Highlights,0866</SECOND>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Consumer spending rebounded 0.7 percent in
November from its sharp fall a month earlier, the government
reported.
   The Commerce Department said Thursday that consumer spending
rose at a seasonally adjusted annual rate to $3.54 trillion, a 0.7
percent increase and the steepest gain since a 1 percent jump last
March. Spending declined 0.2 percent in October.
   The government also reported a 0.8 percent increase in personal
incomes in November.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The federal budget deficit increased $28.96
billion in November, raising the imbalance during the first two
months of the fiscal year to more than half the ceiling for the
entire year, the Treasury Department said.
   Combined with the October deficit of $26.09 billion, the
imbalance totaled $55.05 billion, the government said Thursday. The
Gramm-Rudman deficit reduction law sets a $100 billion ceiling for
the fiscal year that began Oct. 1.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The cold snap gripping much of the nation is
draining supplies of home heating oil, raising prices and causing
spot shortages of the fuel, industry officials say.
   Consumers are paying as much as $1 a gallon in parts of the
Northeast, and some oil companies are taking steps to ensure
there's enough oil to go around.
   Exxon USA, Mobil Corp. and Star Enterprise, a Texaco Inc.
affiliate, reported Thursday that some of their Northeastern
terminals suffered temporary oil outages and that customers have
been sent to other facilities or forced to wait for new supplies to
arrive.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sears, Roebuck and Co. has announced an $800
million employee stock ownership plan that will increase its
workers' stake in the company to 21 percent from 15 percent and
save Sears money.
   The employee stock ownership plan will provide the Chicago-based
retailing and financial-services company with a cheaper way to fund
its profit-sharing program since it can deduct from its taxes
dividends paid on the ESOP shares, Sears said Thursday.
   Separately, Sears was accused in a lawsuit filed by New York's
attorney general that the retailer's ``everyday low prices'' policy
is a fraud. Sears denied the charges.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The savings and loan industry lost $3.8
billion in the July-September quarter, down only slightly from the
record high set the previous quarter, the government said.
   The loss at the nation's 2,903 S&amp;Ls, including 256 under
government control, was $261 million less than a record $4.1
billion loss reported for the second quarter, the Office of Thrift
Supervision said Thursday.
   For the year so far, losses total $11.5 billion, well on track
to top the $13.4 billion loss for all of 1988, the post-Depression
high.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A New Jersey auto plant will cut production in
half in February as General Motors Corp. puts 1,600 workers on
indefinite layoffs, the automaker said.
   GM and Chrysler Corp. also announced that additional plants will
be closed for short periods in January as automakers grapple with
high new-vehicle inventories during a period of low demand. The
announcements Thursday, coupled with those earlier this month,
bring the number of affected workers to more than 127,000.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Federal Aviation Administration has
awarded a contract potentially worth $853 million to a unit of
American Telephone &amp; Telegraph Co. for up to 40,000 computer
workstations at Transportation Department offices around the
country, officials said.
   AT&amp;T Computer Systems announced Thursday it had won the
networked computing contract, which will provide computer hardware,
software, training and maintenance for FAA and other government
transportation offices.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   American businesses plan to boost capital
spending in 1990, but the rate of increase is only a little more
than half this year's and includes the first decline in
durable-goods investment since 1986, the government said.
   According to a Commerce Department survey completed in November,
spending on new plants and equipment will total $490.1 billion next
year, a 4.9 percent jump but less than the 8.5 percent increase in
1989 spending over that of 1988.
   The 4.9 percent rate of increase is the slowest since a 4.2
percent advance in 1987, the department said Thursday.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Securities and Exchange Commission has
proposed new rules that would make mutual funds simplify and expand
the information they are required to supply investors.
   Three rules were proposed Thursday, one to clarify descriptions
of funds to investors, a second to provide better measures of fund
performance and a third to disclose who is making fund investment
decisions.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The stock market struggled to a small gain Thursday, halting a
weeklong slide. The Dow Jones industrial average, down 73.16 points
in the five preceding sessions, gained 3.20 to 2,691.13.
   The dollar declined modestly against most major currencies.
   Bond prices edged lower in light activity.
   Frigid weather forecasts continued to boost orange juice and
heating oil futures prices; precious metals turned lower; livestock
and meat futures advanced; and grains and soybeans were mixed.
</TEXT>

</DOC>