<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0140 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1630EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Korea     12-22 0424</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Korea,0438</SECOND>
<HEAD>Radical Students Protest U.S. Invasion of Panama</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL SHIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Radical students and police fought
with firebombs and tear gas Friday when the students tried to march
against the U.S. invasion of Panama and the presence of American
troops in South Korea.
   Students in Seoul and four other cities also demanded the
release of a jailed leader authorities believe sympathizes with
Communist North Korea.
   Police estimated the total number of protesters Friday
throughout the country was 1,800. They reported some arrests, but
did not give figures.
   About 250 students shouting ``Yankee go home!'' and ``Drive out
the Yankees who invaded Panama!'' fought riot police who blocked
them from marching off the Dongkuk University campus after a rally
against the government and United States.
   The students denounced the U.S. invasion of Panama as ``an
imperialistic show of military force.''
   Police fired tear gas to keep the Dongkuk students from marching
into the streets. There were no reports of arrests or injuries in
the 90-minute confrontation.
   The Dongkuk students shouted slogans demanding immediate
withdrawal of U.S. troops from Panama and South Korea. About 43,000
American soldiers are stationed in South Korea under a 1954 mutual
defense treaty.
   Police raided the Dongkuk campus before dawn Friday and seized
30 radical students accused of pro-North Korean activities.
   Clashes also took place near a downtown market in Seoul when
hundreds of students from several colleges occupied a section of an
eight-lane street. Police firing tear gas dispersed the students,
who threw hundreds of firebombs.
   Riot police firing barrages of tear gas moved into several
campuses in the southern cities of Kwangju, Taegu, Pusan and Taejon
to crush violent protests demanding the release of radical leader
Im Chong-suk.
   Im, 23, leads a radical group called the National Council of
Student Representatives and police had sought him for six months in
connection with previous violent demonstrations.
   He also is accused of sending a woman radical student leader, Im
Su-kyong, to a world youth festival in North Korea in July without
government approval. The two Ims are unrelated.
   South Korean citizens are not allowed to visit the North without
official permission.
   Three leaders of the largest dissident group, the United
National Democratic Movement, delivered a letter denouncing the
U.S. military action in Panama to the U.S. Embassy on Friday. The
embassy said it would have no comment.
   Korean radicals are a vocal minority in the nation of 42
million, but have little public support because of their extreme
views and actions.
</TEXT>

</DOC>