<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0150 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1449EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--Alumni Adv07   12-26 1171</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Alumni, Adv 07,1202</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv07</HEAD>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Jan. 7</HEAD>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<HEAD>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 1 b&amp;w photo.
ColorFoto subscribers get 1 35mm slide.)</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   With public financing of higher education waning
and the pool of potential freshmen dwindling, college alumni
associations across the country are following the example set by
the University of Michigan, long known for its fund-raising
success.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By LISA PERLMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ANN ARBOR, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Twice a year, 84-year-old Bert Wertman
makes the six-hour drive from his home in Buffalo, N.Y., to his
alma mater, the venerable, 172-year-old campus of the University of
Michigan.
   Wertman, who graduated in 1928 from the School of Business
Administration, returns to meet with other former directors of the
Alumni Association to discuss the university's future _ much of
which depends on alumni support.
   ``It's a continuous selling job to keep students interested
after they graduate,'' Wertman says. ``And I still do my part,
spreading the gospel of Michigan, as I call it.''
   Since graduating 61 years ago, Wertman has kept track of his 26
classmates of the Class of '28, bringing the remaining few together
for reunions and keeping them active in university affairs.
   It's his contribution to a vast network that tries to keep track
of some 330,000 alumni _ more than any other college or university
in the country, according to the New York City-based Council for
Aid to Education.
   In the last decade, as public financing of higher education has
decreased and the pool of potential freshman has shrunk,
state-funded colleges and universities have taken a lesson from
Michigan's long-established alumni programs, considered one of the
most successful in the country, even among its private counterparts.
   ``Our job is to cultivate alumni and keep them informed about
what's going on here and the challenges we're facing,'' says Robert
Forman, executive director of the Michigan Alumni Association for
25 years.
   That might involve an Alumni Association-sponsored African
safari _ one of 35 trips abroad this year _ a week at one of the
university's two family summer camps or a few courses at the Alumni
University, a summer school for past grads.
   Of course, the highlight for the second consecutive year is an
alumni trip to the Rose Bowl to root for the Big Ten football
champion Wolverines.
   The bottom line is that the better alumni feel, the more likely
they are to reach for their checkbooks.
   ``You used to find such professional programs only at your Yales
and Harvards, but in the last 10 years or so public institutions
have gone after and cultivated their alumni with a similar degree
of sophistication and success,'' says Paul Miller, vice president
of the Council for Aid to Education. ``It's gotten so now you can
phone in your credit card number to contribute.''
   Today's efforts to keep alumni interested in alma maters go
beyond newsletters, reunions and football telecast parties at local
alumni clubs. Some associations have turned increasingly service
oriented, selling members insurance, planning vacations and
sponsoring continuing education courses.
   The strategy seems to be working. Private support of colleges
and universities has nearly tripled in the last 10 years, says
Miller, whose organization tracks higher education fund raising.
   In 1987-88, alumni contributed about $2 billion to their alma
maters, up from $1.2 billion in 1982-83 and totaling 25 percent of
all voluntary support. At Michigan, about $22 million was raised by
alumni, not counting the corporate gifts that result from having an
alumnus on the board of directors _ or in the chief executive
officer's seat.
   But at Michigan and many other colleges, the Alumni Association
rarely asks members for money. That's the job of the university's
development office and its 17 individual colleges, which mail out
two or three requests a year.
   The Alumni Association works closely with the fund-raisers but
is an independent, self-supporting organization with 80,000
dues-paying members _ about one-quarter of all Michigan alumni.
   While fund raising and recruiting students remain the goals of
most alumni associations, many also are enlisting members in a host
of other activities, from advice on curricula and graduation
requirements to screening prospective students and providing
externships, in which students shadow alumni for a week or so to
learn about prospective careers.
   ``Those schools who use alumni as a source for money only are
missing the boat,'' Forman says.
   Some alumni clubs are even turning their efforts toward social
service projects within their respective communities, tutoring at
inner-city schools and volunteering at homeless shelters and soup
kitchens, says Sarah Hardesty, vice president of communications for
the Council for Advancement and Support of Education of Washington,
D.C.
   A University of Notre Dame alumni club in Washington, D.C., is
renovating apartments in a public housing project and a Duke
University club in the same city has adopted an inner-city
elementary school. Even small, private institutions are getting
into the act.
   More than 100 members of the Boston alumni club of Williams
College _ enrollment about 2,100 _ regularly volunteer at a food
bank.
   ``We still have happy hours, football telecast parties and golf
outings, but this is something we can get together and do for the
community,'' says Notre Dame grad Sheila McDaniel. ``And it makes
us feel good about where we went to school.''
   Still, reunions remain the mainstay of alumni contact. Michigan
holds about 75 class reunions each year. There are Michigan alumni
clubs in about 200 cities across the United States, as well as a
few in other countries. In 1971, the all-Michigan crew of Apollo 15
established the first extraterrestrial club when they planted a
Michigan flag on the moon.
   The list of famous Michigan alumni ranges from President Gerald
Ford and General Motors Corp. Chairman Roger B. Smith to rock star
Madonna and the late Gilda Radner. It also includes John A.
DiBiaggio, president of Big Ten rival Michigan State University.
   Alumni associations aren't waiting until a student leaves the
campus to get him or her thinking like alumni. About 180 students
are involved in Michigan's Student Alumni Council. At Notre Dame,
the first thing a student sees when he comes to the South Bend,
Ind., campus is the mobile Alumni Association welcome wagon.
   ``From day one I felt at home at Michigan, and I've never lost
that feeling,'' says Virginia Nicklas, class of '49 and a former
director and vice president of the Alumni Association. She also
travels to Ann Arbor twice a year for the directors meeting from
her home in Pennsylvania, where she works in the development office
at the University of Pittsburgh.
   Though she received her graduate degree there, her commitment to
Michigan runs deep; she's always in the market for a new outfit in
the school's colors of maize and blue.
   ``It seems almost every place I've traveled in the world, I've
met U of M graduates, and right away, there's that common bond,''
says the former sorority sister, her blue `M' earrings dangling.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>

</DOC>