<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0105 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1554EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Cold-WaterLoss     12-27 0302</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cold-Water Loss,0314</SECOND>
<HEAD>Water Losses Caused by Cold Plague Residents</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Cold Rdp</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Like thousands of Houstonians, Linda Woods spent
the Christmas holidays bedeviled by problems caused by the record
cold.
   On Saturday morning, the pipes in her attic froze.
   ``No coffee, no shower, nothing,'' she said. The single mother
packed up her two children and went to her mother's home, which had
water.
   After an hour, the electricity went out as utilities were
overloaded by the demand for heat.
   Two hours later, the family went shopping to keep warm at a mall.
   ``We were there about an hour and all their lights went off,''
Ms. Woods said.
   When they returned to her mother's home, the water was off
because a pump station lost power.
   The family went to a hotel Sunday morning, with the kids amusing
themselves ``by feeding about $20 in quarters into the Magic
Fingers thing on the motel bed while Mom and I played cards.''
   When the family returned to Ms. Woods' mother's house on
Christmas Day, there was electricity but no water.
   On Tuesday, Ms. Woods and her children went home to find her
pipes thawed _ and her kitchen and living room flooded because the
ice had ruptured the pipes.
   ``The phone still worked, so I called my mom and said, `Mom,
come on over _ I've got water,'' she joked.
   Paul Harrison, a 24-year-old University of Houston student, had
been excited when his parents from the Texas Panhandle decided to
visit for the holidays for the first time.
   But then the electricity went off Saturday and the water
dwindled to a rusty trickle.
   ``The really bad part was, I've called them every week since
I've been here and gloated over the weather,'' Harrison said. ``I
really wish I hadn't done that.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>