<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0051EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BusCrashTrial     12-23 0477</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bus Crash Trial,0488</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jury Recommends 16 Years for Man Convicted in Church Bus Crash</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHARLES WOLFE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CARROLLTON, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The man who caused the deaths of 27
people on a church bus in the nation's worst drunken-driving
accident was taken to jail after a jury recommended a 16-year
prison sentence.
   But the relatives of some of his victims said the jury, which
rejected murder charges to find him guilty of manslaughter, was too
lenient. They noted Larry Mahoney still has a family to celebrate
Christmas with.
   ``We're going to spend it in a cemetery with a headstone,'' Bill
Nichols, said after a sentencing hearing Friday, clasping hands
with his wife, Madeline.
   The couple's only child, 17-year-old William Joseph Nichols Jr.,
was among the 24 youths and three adults killed by smoke inhalation
and flames in a fire that swept through a former school bus after
Mahoney's pickup struck it on Interstate 71, five miles south of
Carrollton. Mahoney was drunk and driving on the wrong side of the
highway when the crash occurred May 14, 1988.
   Mahoney, 36, who had been free on bond prior to his conviction,
was led in handcuffs out of the Carroll County Courthouse Friday
and taken to the local jail after Circuit Judge Charles Satterwhite
discontinued his bail.
   Mahoney was convicted on Thursday of 27 counts each of
second-degree manslaughter and first-degree wanton endangerment, 12
of first-degree assault, 14 of second-degree wanton endangerment
and one of drunken driving.
   The jury on Friday recommended sentences totaling 611 years, but
opted to have them run concurrently. That effectively gave Mahoney
16 years of a possible 20-year sentence for assault, the most
serious offense. He would be eligible for parole consideration in
eight years under Kentucky law.
   Satterwhite is to sentence Mahoney February 23. The judge can
give Mahoney a lighter sentence, but cannot exceed the jury's
recommendation.
   ``If you ask me if I'm disappointed, yeah, I'm disappointed,''
said Assistant Attorney General Paul Richwalsky, who prosecuted
Mahoney on 27 murder counts. ``I thought all of the carnage ... was
worth more than eight years in prison.''
   The jury's recommendation shocked Karen Morgan, president of
Students Against Drunk Driving at Radcliff's North Hardin High
School.
   ``It's going to be hard going back to my school and ... telling
them that this man only got a minimum of eight years,'' said Miss
Morgan, whose 13-year-old brother, Phillip, was among those killed.
``What kind of example do you set for them?''
   Defense attorneys William Summers and Russell Baldani said they
were pleased with the verdicts and sentencing recommendation, but
will appeal the convictions.
   ``What is (Mahoney's) life worth?'' Summers said. ``Will it
bring somebody back? Will it make them feel better?''
   At his sentencing hearing, Mahoney told the jury he intended to
lecture schoolchildren on the evils of drinking and driving.
</TEXT>

</DOC>