<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0106 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1921EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-SavannahRiver 1stLd-Writethru a0585 12-19 0569</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Savannah River, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0585,530</SECOND>
<HEAD>Plant Operator Cited For Allowing Workers to Sleep on the Job</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 3 grafs to ADD that award fees are incentive payments
to the contractor. Picks up 3rd graf pvs `Westinghouse took ...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Energy Department gave the new operator of
the Savannah River nuclear weapons plant $3.9 million in award fees
despite serious safety lapses such as workers found sleeping on
duty, the agency said Tuesday.
   The award for Westinghouse Savannah River Co.'s first six months
at the site near Aiken, S.C., amounted to 52.5 percent of the
maximum possible award under terms of its contract, the department
said in a letter to Westinghouse last Wednesday.
   The contract provides for incentive payments, or award fees, if
the contractor meets criteria set by the department.
   Westinghouse took over for E.I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Co. in
April amid concern that Du Pont had allowed safety standards to
fall dangerously low. Du Pont had run the plant since it was built
in the early 1950s.
   In the letter, P.W. Kaspar, manager of the department's Savannah
River operations office, told Westinghouse Savannah River President
James Moore that while the company had made some important
improvements, its overall approach to instilling greater discipline
in plant operations was too narrow and not yet effective.
   Kaspar said the department's Award Fee Board, which evaluated
Westinghouse's performance from April 1 through Sept. 30, had
assigned a rating of 82 points out of a possible 100. Kaspar
personally knocked one point off the rating, resulting in an award
total of $3.9 million out of a maximum possible $7.5 million.
   ``The reason for this reduction was my assessment that progress
made to date on improving conduct of operations is inadequate and
not sufficiently reflected in the (board's) evaluation,'' Kaspar
wrote.
   ``While training programs appear to be sound, there is
insufficient on-shift coaching, rigorous enforcement of details and
followup of anomalies throughout the site,'' he added.
   Among the anomalies cited by Kaspar was employees found sleeping
on the job.
   Kaspar's letter provided no details, but plant spokesman Dean
Hoffman said Tuesday that two employees, in separate incidents, had
been found asleep when they were supposed to have been monitoring
the testing of cooling pipes at the L reactor, one of three
reactors at Savannah River that make a gas needed for nuclear
warheads.
   All three reactors have been shut down for more than a year for
safety improvements.
   Hoffman said unspecified ``disciplinary action'' was taken
against the employees several months ago, although they were not
fired.
   Kaspar attributed the sleeping incidents to excessive overtime
required by Westinghouse.
   Another problem noted by Kaspar was the intentional disablement
of alarms by Westinghouse employees.
   Hoffman said two employees recently were fired for tampering
with alarms in two areas of the plant, including the P reactor. The
alarms were installed to detect excessive amounts of radiation.
   Hoffman called the sleeping and alarm tampering ``isolated
incidents'' and said the company had made important strides toward
reaching Energy Department standards for operating the plant. He
added that the company would not be satisfied with its overall
performance until it reached the department's highest standards.
   Hoffman noted that the department had given Westinghouse an
``excellent'' rating for establishing and operating an integrated
design, engineering and construction organization. Ratings in other
areas were either ``good'' or ``marginal.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>