<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1339EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Bush 3rdLd-Writethru a0547-548-549 12-28 0743</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bush, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0547-548-549,700</SECOND>
<HEAD>White House Says Noriega Fate Up To Vatican, Sees No Hostage Problem</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Combines pvs; CORRECTS spelling of `asylum' in 2nd graf, minor
editing thruout to tighten.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM RAUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CORPUS CHRISTI, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The White House said today the fate
of ousted Panamanian leader Manuel Antonio Noriega is now ``in the
hands of the Vatican,'' although President Bush's spokesman said
U.S. troops surrounding the Vatican embassy are prepared to move in
if hostages are taken.
   Presidential press secretary Marlin Fitzwater said that the U.S.
position on Noriega, who is holed up in the Panama City papal
nunciature with several supporters, remains the same:``We believe
that he is, as an indicted person, a criminal and not a poliical
refugee in the normal sense of someone who seeks political asylum.''
   However, the spokesman suggested negotiations on Noriega remain
delicate.
   ``We continue to make our views known, the Vatican continues to
consider this matter, and we leave it to them to work this out as
they see fit,'' he said.
   ``This matter is now in the hands of the Vatican,'' said
Fitzwater, briefing reporters in Corpus Christi as Bush enjoyed a
hunting vacation on an isolated ranch near the south Texas
community of Beeville.
   Asked about a reported letter from the papal representative in
Panama City saying U.S. troops could go into the embassy if a
hostage situation arose, Fitzwater said:
   ``We have no indication there is trouble within the nunciature.
There are no hostages that we're aware of.''
   But, he added, ``Certainly, would there be any danger there, we
would be prepared to offer assistance to help.
   Noriega has been in the Vatican embassy since Christmas Eve.
   Fitzwater said that, altough some Noriega loyalists that had
been in the embassy with Noriega have been released to U.S.
authorities, ``most of his cronies are still there.''
   Fitzwater said that, overall, ``the situation is good and
steadily improving'' in Panama, with the U.S.-backed government of
Guillermo Endara ``continuing to expand its control.''
   Although Bush has voiced continued determination to have Noriega
returned to the United States, administration officials said
privately that little headway has been apparent in prying Noriega
from the Vatican Embassy to face drug trafficking charges in the
United States, and they expressed some frustration at the pace of
negotiations.
   ``I want to see this man who is under indictment brought to
justice for poisoning the children of the United States of America
and people around the world,'' Bush said at a barbecue held in
Beeville Wednesday night in his honor.
   The president and fellow Texan, Secretary of State James A.
Baker III, are spending the next few days quail hunting on the
10,000-acre ranch of William Farish, a wealthy Houston oilman and
longtime Bush friend.
   Bush, who has been coming to Texas for a holiday season quail
hunt annually for more than two decades, thanked the crowd of more
than 700 people ``for this homecoming.''
   Fitzwater said Bush was receiving briefings in writing and by
phone on any developments in Panama, but otherwise intended to
spend the day hunting.
   ``Look, I don't make any cover. I'm going to be enjoying myself
and I think the American people understand that,'' Bush told
reporters on his arrival at the Corpus Christi Naval Air Station.
   The president spent several hours fishing on nearby San Jose
Island, where he said he and Baker caught about a half-dozen fish.
   Meanwhile, Justice Department officials are planning to ask
``one or two'' more European countries to freeze bank accounts
where Noriega is thought to have hidden illegal drug profits,
spokesman David Runkel said today.
   Similiar requests were made Wednesday to the governments of four
nations _ France, Luxembourg, Switzerland and the United Kingdom.
Runkel said those governments are cooperating.
   Authorities in France responded by freezing accounts in two
banks holding $3.3 million under the names of Noriega and members
of his families. Swiss officials placed a ``precautionary'' freeze
on two accounts in banks in Zurich and Geneva.
   Speaking to reporters in Corpus Christi, Bush congratulated
Romania's new president, Ion Iliescu, and said he was ``amazed and
respectful'' of the changes there.
   ``My concern is for tranquility and freedom in Romania,'' Bush
said.
   He declined to criticize harshly the quick executions of former
dictator Nicolae Ceausescu and his wife, adding, ``We did say that
we were concerned that the trial of Ceausescu should have been more
open, but that's their matter.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>