<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 2348EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-StarvationDeath     12-24 0702</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Starvation Death,0725</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cottams Seek Normal Life, Attorney Says</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY10</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID S. MARTIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   WILKES-BARRE, Pa. (AP) _ Larry and Leona Cottam are trying to
resume a normal life while they fight their murder convictions in
the starvation death of their teen-age son nearly a year ago, the
couple's attorney said.
   ``Under the circumstances, they're doing quite well,'' said Al
Flora Jr., Luzerne County first assistant public defender, of Larry
and Leona Cottam. ``I don't know that they'll ever come back to
normal given what they've been through.''
   Free on bail, the Cottams have found a permanent home since
their third-degree murder convictions Sept. 8, and Larry has taken
a job as a laborer, Flora said.
   The couple recently sold the modest home where their 14-year-old
son, Eric, died in an upstairs bedroom last January, his 5-foot,
10-inch frame wasted to only 69 pounds.
   Eric's death ended the reclusive family's six-week fast,
undertaken despite nearly $4,000 in savings kept as a religious
tithe to God and in hopes God would rescue them from their plight.
   Cottam, a former Seventh-day Adventist pastor, reported his
son's death to police Jan. 4.
   Larry and Leona Cottam were charged with third-degree murder a
day later, while they were still undergoing treatment for
malnutrition at Mercy Hospital in Wilkes-Barre.
   District Justice Ronald Swank read the charges to Mrs. Cottam as
she lay in her hospital bed and to her husband in a hospital
visiting room as he sat in a wheelchair with an intravenous tube in
his arm.
   Laura Cottam, the couple's other child, also received treatment
for malnutrition and later was placed in foster care.
   The Cottams' financial problems began in March 1988 when Cottam
lost his job as a truck driver in a dispute with his boss over the
safety of the vehicle's tires.
   Cottam then refused to sign up for government assistance, and
neighbors said the family declined offers for help and withdrew
into their home on a dead-end street in Nuangola, a community of
700 residents south of Wilkes-Barre.
   Already, the Cottams were teaching their children at home and
had stopped attending church.
   In a seven-week trial, Luzerne County prosecutors claimed Larry
and Leona Cottam should have taken steps other than prayer to
prevent Eric's death and Laura's malnourishment.
   A jury deliberated less than two hours before finding the
Cottams guilty Sept. 8 of third-degree murder and other charges.
Third-degree murder, defined as a killing that is not premeditated
but is done with malice, carries a maximum sentence of 20 years.
   Judge Gifford S. Cappellini allowed Larry Cottam, now 40, and
Leona Cottam, 38, remain free on $50,000 bail each, which was
posted by a bail bondsman. Under the conditions of the bail, one of
their attorneys must see the couple once a week to ensure their
health.
   ``They're keeping their spirits up under the circumstances,''
Flora said. ``Their religious beliefs are still very firm. Would
they ever get into a situation like that again? I don't think so.''
   Mrs. Cottam has had a harder time than her husband, Flora said,
because she does not have a job and stays at home most of the time.
   Laura Cottam, who turned 13 last month, has entered school with
the support of her parents, who even sold Christmas cookies to
raise money for the school, Flora said.
   Flora and co-counsel Joseph Cosgrove claim the Cottams were
denied a fair trial in part because the couple were not allowed to
raise their children's right to freedom of religion.
   At the trial, Laura Cottam testified that her parents didn't
force her to take part in the fast. She said she had used her own
tithe money on food if she wanted.
   Flora and Cosgrove have filed post-trial motions seeking either
a new trial or dismissal of the charges.
   Flora said these motions will be supplemented when the 3,000- to
4,000-page court transcript is completed by the end of January or
early February. A decision by Cappellini on the post-trial motions
isn't expected until summer, he said.
   If the motions are denied, the Cottams have 30 days to file an
appeal the case to state Superior Court.
   ``It's a long process,'' Flora said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>