<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0124 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1813EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-MaineGov     12-28 0486</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Maine Gov,0500</SECOND>
<HEAD>Deadline Looming for Brennan to Decide on Gubernatorial Race</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER JACKSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AUGUSTA, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Joseph E. Brennan, who traded the
governorship for John R. McKernan's seat in Congress three years
ago, faces a self-imposed deadline this week to decide whether to
challenge McKernan's re-election bid for governor in 1990.
   Brennan, a Democrat, was constitutionally barred from seeking a
third consecutive term in 1986, when he was first elected to
Congress and Republican McKernan was elected governor, but no
longer faces that obstacle.
   For months, Brennan, 55, has courted speculation he would take
on McKernan, 41, and he has been under increasing pressure from
Democratic activists to do so.
   Brennan's closest advisers insisted Thursday that even they did
not know whether he would seek the governorship or a third term in
Congress.
   ``He still hasn't made up his mind completely,'' David Redmond,
Brennan's congressional chief of staff, said after having lunch
with his boss Thursday.
   No announcement was expected before Friday, and ``it's liable to
be Sunday'' at midnight, Redmond said, referring only half-jokingly
to Brennan's promise that he would disclose his plans before the
year's end.
   Brennan's supporters' hopes were buoyed by a recent independent
poll showing that a Brennan-McKernan race would be a virtual dead
heat, and Brennan fueled speculation earlier this month by
appearing before 300 Democratic faithful who had gathered on his
behalf in Augusta.
   ``In a sense,'' he told the crowd on Dec. 9, ``a governor is a
little bit more like a quarterback and, in some respects, in the
United States Congress, you're a little more like an offensive
lineman.''
   McKernan, who has not yet announced his candidacy for
re-election but has begun soliciting campaign contributions, has
said he is convinced Brennan will enter the race.
   Brennan has held open the prospect for too long to do otherwise,
McKernan said last week. ``I just think that when it gets right
down to it ... it's going to be very hard for him to go to his
friends and say, `I'm not doing it.'''
   Brennan's deliberations also are being monitored by Maine's
other member of the U.S. House of Representatives, Republican Rep.
Olympia J. Snowe, whom McKernan married this year.
   Democratic leaders were hedging their bets on Brennan's future
Thursday.
   ``Right now I would not call it, but I'm not a betting person,''
said Democratic State Chairwoman Keron Kerr.
   ``What do you hear?'' state Sen. Barry J. Hobbins, a former
state party chairman and one-time congressional candidate, asked a
reporter who had called to ask him the same question.
   Hobbins said he was surprised that speculation about Brennan's
future has spread so far outside of political circles. He said the
subject came up Thursday morning when he stopped at a rural grocery
store in western Maine.
   ``It's unbelievable,'' said Hobbins. ``Everyone's asking the
question, whether it's in Denmark, Maine, or the State House.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>