<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0107 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1911EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-PanamaRanch-Pool     12-23 0315</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Panama Ranch-Pool,310</SECOND>
<HEAD>Noriega Deputy Asks Marines for Return of Ranch</HEAD>
<UNK>EDITOR'S NOTE: The following is a pool report filed by Steven Komarow
of The Associated Press and Kathy Lewis of the Houston Post.</UNK>
<DATELINE>ARRAIJAN, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A top deputy to Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noriega telephoned U.S. marines who were occupying his ranch and
asked for it back, soldiers said Saturday.
   Rigoberto Paredes, Noriega's political chief in the area west of
Panama City and the reputed head of the local Noriega secret
police, was told he could reclaim the ranch and a nearby mansion if
he surrendered.
   He did not, and when the marines left the property on another
mission, angry local residents sacked it.
   They ``looted the house and set it afire,'' said Cpl. Jeff
Newsome of Norfolk, Va.
   Newsome said he took part in the initial attack when U.S. forces
fired upon and destroyed a local headquarters for Noriega's police.
   The burned-out, two-story station was empty but adorned Saturday
with a large makeshift banner declaring ``Endara Presidente.''
Guillermo Endara was sworn in as president of Panama when the U.S.
operation commenced on Wednesday. The United States considers him
the winner of the May election in Panama which Noriega declared
void.
   Arraijan, along the Pan American Highway, was still largely
isolated Saturday as the U.S. military continued its operations.
   The local citizens drank beer and watched as the soldiers took
into custody Noriega loyalists who were surrendering. Shops, some
of them which had been looted, were closed and citizens said they
had no food or water.
   ``We have wanted change for 20 years,'' said Bernalldo
Altamirri. ``We want everything finished. We want to pass a good
Christmas and a good New Year's.''
   ``If they do not catch Noriega, it is not finished,'' he said of
the U.S. operation.
   Felipe Barrera said, ``President Bush said he is sending food. I
don't see it.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>