<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0116 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1254EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthAfrica     12-20 0376</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa,0384</SECOND>
<HEAD>Factional Fighting Creates Crisis at Hospital</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID CRARY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thee more people were killed
in factional fighting in Natal Province, police said Wednesday, and
a Parliament member said Natal's biggest hospital for blacks should
be declared a disaster area.
   Carole Charlewood, who represents a Natal district for the
anti-apartheid Democratic Party, said in a letter to the Health
Ministry that the escalation of violence around the port city of
Durban has aggravated already critical problems at King Edward VIII
Hospital.
   She said the hospital staff is treating 20 to 30 gunshot victims
a day, and patients were exposed to ``squalor, overcrowding and
humiliation.''
   ``The pressures on (operating) theaters and staff means that
other patients requiring surgery must be bypassed, which has
resulted in many unnecessary deaths,'' Mrs. Charlewood wrote.
``Patients also are dying because the intensive care unit
facilities are hopelessly inadequate.''
   The Health Ministry said Health Minister Rina Venter was aware
of the problems at King Edward and giving them appropriate
attention.
   Scores of blacks have been killed in and around the Durban-area
township of Inanda this month, one of the worst surges of violence
during a three-year power struggle in Natal between members of the
relatively conservative Zulu organization Inkatha and supporters of
militant anti-apartheid groups. About 2,500 people have been killed
in the feud.
   The police unrest report Wednesday gave few details about the
latest killings, saying one man was shot to death in the
Durban-area township of Molweni and two killed in their home by
attackers near the town of Richmond.
   On Tuesday, Law and Order Minister Adriaan Vlok toured
battle-scarred sections of Inanda. He was accompanied by Mangosuthu
Buthelezi, leader of Inkatha and chief minister of the
semi-autonomous black homeland of KwaZulu.
   Vlok told reporters that poverty, high unemployment and
``appalling'' living conditions were a major factor behind the
Inanda violence. But he said peace was unlikely unless ``there is a
change of heart, away from hating one another.''
   Buthelezi says he is as firmly opposed to apartheid as more
militant groups aligned to the outlawed African National Congress.
But he opposes the ANC's use of violence and its advocacy of
confrontational tactics such as strikes, sanctions and
demonstrations.
</TEXT>

</DOC>