<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1458EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-RomanianChannel     12-23 0611</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romanian Channel,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romania Long a `Back Door' Channel for U.S. Initiatives</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GENE KRAMER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mobs also massed in the streets of Bucharest
20 years ago. But unlike the determined throngs now dismantling
Romanian President Nicolae Ceausescu's dictatorship, the crowds of
1969 were dancing in praise of Ceausescu _ and his American
visitor, President Richard Nixon.
   ``At one point, Ceausescu and I were literally swept up by the
dancing in the streets,'' Nixon recalled in his memoirs.
   Soon after his first inauguration, Nixon undertook a politically
daring visit to Bucharest. He became the first U.S. president to
visit a Soviet satellite capital, hoping ``to needle the Soviets,''
former Secretary of State Henry A. Kissinger recalled in his
autobiographical ``White House Years.''
   Early in his quarter-century reign, Ceausescu attracted the
attention of U.S. strategists with his effort to pursue a foreign
policy independent from Moscow.
   He kept Romania in the Warsaw Pact and ran a typically tough
domestic regime. But unlike other Warsaw Pact members, he did not
break relations with Israel after the 1967 Mideast War, he pursued
a strong relationship with China and he criticized the Pact's 1968
invasion of Czechoslovakia.
   Both Nixon and Kissinger said later that Ceausescu helped
provide a channel for diplomatic communications to Chinese leaders
before the United States had official relations with the mainland.
   Ceausescu kindled Nixon's interest when the future president
visited Bucharest as a private tourist in 1967 expecting a routine
reception. Nixon recalled in his memoirs that Ceausescu surprised
him with a grand welcome and ``Everywhere we were greeted with
outbursts of friendship from the people.''
   Nixon wrote that he told Ceausescu of his desire to normalize
U.S. relations with mainland China, planting the seeds of what
Nixon later called the ``Romanian channel'' in approaches to
Beijing and North Vietnam.
   After his 1969 inauguration, Nixon included Romania on his
round-the-world trip and recalled in his memoirs, ``When we landed
in Bucharest Aug. 2, I became the first American president to make
a state visit to a communist satellite country.
   ``President Nicolae Ceausescu is a strong, independent leader
who had cultivated good relations with the Chinese in spite of the
fact that he had to walk a very fine line lest the Soviets decide
to intervene in Romania as they had in Hungary in 1956 and in
Czechoslovakia in 1968. So far he had walked that line with
consummate skill.''
   Nixon said Ceausescu also agreed to do everything possible to
help U.S. negotiations with Hanoi to bring peace to Indochina.
   Nixon brought Ceausescu to Washington for a state visit in
October 1970, and said in his memoirs that the visit marked the
start of the ``Romanian channel'' to Beijing.
   Nixon recalled that the Romanian channel was used in 1971 when
Ceausescu's Washington ambassador conveyed a message from Premier
Chou En-lai saying ``in view of the fact I had visited Bucharest in
1969 and Belgrade in 1970, I would be welcome in Peking.'' Nixon
made his historic first visit to China in 1972, after two
exploratory missions by Kissinger.
   Kissinger wrote that Nixon visited Bucharest in 1969 to repay
Ceausescu's courtesies of 1967, ``but his principal reason was to
needle the Soviets.''
   Nixon used Ceausescu's 1970 Washington visit ``for a public step
forward'' in the feelers to China, Kissinger said. In a White House
toast to Ceausescu, ``Nixon toasted the many common interests of
the United States and Romania, listing prominently that of good
relations, such as Romania had, with the United States, the Soviet
Union and the `Peoples Republic of China.' It was the first use of
China's official name by an American president,'' Kissinger said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>