<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0196 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1502EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f BC-CreditMarkets Adv01   12-29 0760</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Credit Markets, Adv 01,0790</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv01</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Monday, Jan. 1</HEAD>
<HEAD>Number of Defaulted Corporate Bonds Hit Decade-High in 1989</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BART ZIEGLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The corporate bond market enjoyed a banner year
in terms of volume of new issues, but the quality of outstanding
bonds deteriorated and the number of defaulted issues hit its worst
level of the decade in 1989.
   Meanwhile, the municipal bond market saw moderate growth during
the year, reviving a trend that was distorted by the 1986 federal
tax changes.
   In the corporate market, the volume of new bonds in 1989 hit a
three-year high of $133.7 billion, according to a preliminary
figure compiled by Securities Data Co. The figure excludes
so-called ``hybrid'' debt issues such as mortgage-backed securities.
   But of the more than $900 billion in publicly traded corporate
debt outstanding, an estimated $6 billion defaulted during the
year, according to Moody's Investors Service Inc.
   Moody's said an estimated 45 corporations stopped making
payments on their bonds during 1989. That far exceeds the 33
issuers that defaulted in 1986, the previous record high for the
1980s, Moody's said.
   Moody's projects a continued rise in corporate bond defaults in
1990.
   ``You're going to find that some of these near misses of 1989
will default outright in 1990,'' said John Lonski, Moody's chief
economist.
   Standard &amp; Poor's Corp., the other major credit-rating company,
does not predict a major increase in defaults this year.
   ``We have not seen a wholesale across-the-board decline in
credit quality over the last six months, nor do we see one in
1990,'' said Gail Hessol, an S&amp;P managing director.
   But, she said, that projection does not include the troubled
junk bond market.
   ``We think the world has not yet seen the worst as far as junk
bond defaults,'' Ms. Hessol said.
   All of the corporate bond defaults in 1989 involved junk bonds,
which are high-yield, high-risk bonds issued by companies with low
or no credit rating. They often are used to raise the funds needed
for leveraged buyouts, in which the assets of the target company
are pledged as collaterial to raise the cash.
   The junk bond market was shaken in 1989 by a number of
well-publicized defaults, including those of Resorts International
Inc. and Integrated Resources Inc.
   If the economy weakens further, as many predict, the number of
defaults this year could be even greater, Lonski said.
   ``A weak economy is going to make it more difficult to disguise
the problems of troubled companies,'' he said.
   Lonski predicts a significant tapering off in new junk bond
issues this year, due mainly to the slowdown in takeovers. About
$25.3 billion worth of junk issues were sold in 1989, down 8.8
percent from 1988, according to Securities Data Co.
   As for investment-grade corporate bonds, Lonski foresees an
increase in new issues this year if interest rates continue to
drop. These new issues primarily will be sold to refund older,
higher-interest bonds.
   In the municipal market, a total of about $120 billion in
long-term new bonds were sold in 1989, according to preliminary
figures by the Public Securities Association.
   That figure is about 3.5 percent above the 1988 total of $116.9
billion, said the PSA, a trade group for the muni bond industry.
   ``The favorable interest rate environment and pent-up demand for
capital has fueled the increase in issuance,'' said PSA President
Heather L. Ruth.
   But both years' figures pale in comparison to the $222.2 billion
of state and local bonds issued in 1985, the year before the 1986
tax law revision. That law made it less desirable for banks to own
municipal bonds, drying up a prime customer for the securities, and
placed certain limits on the amounts of the tax-free bonds
municipal governments may issue.
   Many municipal and state governments rushed to sell bonds before
the tax law took effect. The volume of new bonds more than doubled
from 1984 to 1985.
   But in the past few years, the level of new muni bond sales were
``back to the same trend before there was a rush to market due to
the tax act,'' said PSA Vice President Caroline M. Benn.
   The PSA projects a continued strong supply of muni bonds in 1990
due to a number of infrastructure projects scheduled to start this
year, including a new airport in Denver and a major sewage plant
project in Boston.
   In addition, the PSA predicts that if interest rates continue to
drop, a number of municipalities and states will refund old,
higher-interest bonds.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Monday, Jan. 1</NOTE>

</DOC>