<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 2037EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-France-Romania 1stLd-Writethru a0765 12-24 0461</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-France-Romania, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0765,0471</SECOND>
<HEAD>France Offers To Back Intervention by Soviets or Volunteers</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs to UPDATE with Dumas saying France to coordinate
with Soviets on aid, French army to send help; pickup graf 6 pvs ``If other
...''</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The foreign minister Sunday offered to help put
together a ``brigade of volunteers'' to help Romanians fight forces
loyal to ousted Communist dictator Nicolae Ceausescu.
   If the Soviet Union thought it necessary to intervene in Romania
on the side of the anti-Ceausescu forces, France ``not only would
not object to it, but would support this action,'' Foreign Minister
Roland Dumas told Soviet officials.
   There was no indication, however, of imminent military
intervention by Soviet or other forces. Soviet Premier Nikolai I.
Ryzhkov said Saturday that sending the Red Army to Romania would be
``impermissible'' and a repetition of past mistakes.
   In a later interview Sunday on French TV, Dumas said the Soviets
``have just now let us know today that they are in agreement to
begin with us to coordinate all our aid.''
   He did not elaborate, but it was clear he meant humanitarian,
rather than military aid.
   The French army said it will provide 10 trucks and 30 soldiers
to help deliver medical aid to Romania.
   In a short statement Sunday, the Foreign Ministry said France
recognizes the National Salvation Committee as the legal authority
in Romania.
   So far, France has only been asked for humanitarian aid, but it
stands ready to respond if asked to go beyond humanitarian
measures, Dumas said on French radio.
   ``If other requests are made _ I don't know how the events will
unfold _ if another demand is made, we will appraise it. I can tell
you we are ready to respond to any new situation,'' he said.
   The foreign minister then added, ``Myself, I could very well see
the constitution of a brigade of volunteers. France could help in
it.''
   Interviewed by Agence France-Presse, Dumas recalled the
volunteers who participated in the Spanish Civil War and in the
liberation of France from Nazi occupation in 1944.
   ``Many people talk, but don't take enough action,'' he said.
   In an interview on French TV, however, Dumas said Western
participation in military intervention in Romania ``would pose
problems, because the region is a zone of the Warsaw Pact.''
   Romanian-born playwright Eugene Ionesco, who lives in France,
urged the West ``to provide military aid in arms and ammunition to
the regular Romanian army so it can defend the people against the
agents of the security police.''
   France has sent two planeloads of medical supplies and emergency
medical teams to Romania in a mission led by Bernard Kouchner,
minister for humanitarian action in the Socialist government.
</TEXT>

</DOC>