<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0126 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1326EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Panama-LatinAmerica 2ndLd-Writethru   12-20 0740</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Latin America, 2nd Ld-Writethru,a0636,0759</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nicaragua, Peru Condemn U.S. Invasion</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 10 grafs to UPDATE with Peru withdrawing its U.S.
ambassador, calling for postponement of drug summit. Pickup 8th, `Venezuela...'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nicaragua condemned the U.S. attack on
Panama today and placed its army on alert, while Peru ordered its
ambassador in Washington to return to Lima until all American
troops are withdrawn.
   Other Latin American nations expressed concern over the U.S.
intervention, and seven of them, including Peru, agreed to hold an
emergency meeting in Bogota to discuss the crisis.
   Nicaragua called for a meeting of the U.N. Security Council to
discuss the attack, and the world body was considering that request
today.
   Foreign ministers of Argentina, Brazil, Mexico, Uruguay, Peru,
Venezuela and Colombia planned to meet in Bogota tonight to discuss
the developments in Panama and issue a declaration, the Colombian
Foreign Ministry announced.
   Panama was part of the so-called Latin American Group of Eight
but was excluded after Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega ousted
Panamanian president Eric Delvalle in February 1988. The group
usually represents Latin America's stands on economic and political
matters.
   Presidents of the seven countries were in telephone consultation
over the situation in Panama and decided to hold the meeting in
Bogota, a Colombian spokesman said.
   The group has condemned Noriega's regime, but it has also
consistently rejected any direct U.S. intervention in Panama.
   President Alan Garcia of Peru condemned the U.S. military action
and said he was ordering Peru's ambassador in Washington to return
home pending a withdrawal of all American troops from Panamanian
territory.
   Garcia, reading a prepared statement at the Government Palace in
Lima, also said the drug summit Feb. 15 with President Bush and the
presidents of Colombia, Bolivia and Peru should be postponed as a
result of events in Panama.
   Venezuela, which has long opposed Noriega, condemned the U.S.
attack but recognized that the action was necessary.
   In a communique issued in Caracas, Venezuela blamed a ``lack of
an effective and firm response by our countries to the violation of
human rights and constitutional norms on the part of the de facto
government of Panama'' for the U.S. intervention.
   But Venezuela also called for U.S. troops to retire before it
would recognize the new government of Guillermo Endara, who was
elected president of Panama in May in a vote that was not
recognized by Noriega forces.
   Venezuela spearheaded attempts in the Organization of American
States to issue strong condemnations of the Noriega regime in an
effort to pressure him into leaving power.
   But Latin American nations showed strong revulsion to what they
saw as intervention in the internal affairs of a member country.
   While condemning the Noriega dictatorship's abuses, Venezuela
added that it lamented that ``traditional principles of
non-intervention ... have given way to this intervention that today
must be condemned and rejected.''
   Venezuela called for the immediate meeting of an OAS consulting
committee to ``analyze and take decisions that will contribute to
the re-establishment of Panamanian sovereignty.''
   In Buenos Aires, Argentine Foreign Minister Domingo Cavallo
expressed concern today and said the Group of Eight countries will
seek a way of ``acting together'' to end the conflict.
   Cavallo told reporters that President Bush spoke by telephone
with President Carlos Menem early today ``to explain the North
American position.'' ``There is a situation of heavy confrontation
between North American and Panamanian troops as well as armed
civilians who are acting in coordination with the Panama Defense
Forces,'' Cavallo said.
   Latin America, he said, ``is going to have to play a fundamental
role to prevent a deepening of the crisis and a greater spilling of
blood.''
   In Managua, Nicaraguan President Daniel Orgega declared a
``state of national alert'' and sent messages to the Security
Council, Non-Aligned Movement and Pope John Paul II saying he was
``deeply concerned by the invasion of Panama.''
   ``In addition to constituting a flagrant trampling of the
sovereignty and territorial integrity of Panama, it is a threat to
the peace and security of all Latin America, Central America and
especially constitutes a serious threat to Nicaragua,'' Ortega said
in a communique read on Voice of Nicaragua radio.
   The army was put on a ``state of combative general alert.'' The
communique said that implied immediate deployment of land, sea and
air combat units. Reserves and civilian militia also were called up.
   The United States supports the rebels seeking to oust the
leftist Sandinista government.
</TEXT>

</DOC>