<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0203 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 2236EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-GreatNorthern     12-27 0336</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Great Northern,0350</SECOND>
<HEAD>Great Northern Claims Takeover Would Prevent Needed Expenditures</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRIDGEPORT, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Great Northern Nekoosa Corp. said
Wednesday in federal court that needed capital investments at its
Maine operations could not be made and that anti-competitive
practices would result if Georgia-Pacific Corp. is successful in
its $3.8 billion takeover attempt.
   The testimony came in the opening day of a hearing on Great
Northern's request for an injunction to block the unfriendly
takeover. Great Northern claims antitrust laws would be violated if
the two forest products companies merged.
   U.S. District Judge Warren W. Eginton set aside 14 days for the
hearing.
   The chairman of Great Northern, William R. Laidig, testified
about the Norwalk-based company's plans for $2.5 billion in capital
investments and acquisitions in Maine over the next five years.
   Laidig, during questioning by the company's attorney, said
Georgia-Pacific would be so laden with debt if it were successful
in the takeover that it could not possibly carry out the capital
plans.
   The takeover would result in anti-competitive practices in
southern pulpwood markets and in the national market for paper used
in personal bank checks, Great Northern also asserted.
   Georgia-Pacific's chief executive officer, T. Marshall Hahn,
said outside the courtroom that the projected cash flow after a
merger of the two companies would be adequate ``even in a financial
crisis'' to finance needed capital expenditures.
   ``It's an old-fashioned combination of two strong industrial
companies,'' Hahn said, calling Great Northern's claims
``transparent nonsense.''
   ``There is no junk debt involved,'' he said.
   Great Northern has calculated the resulting debt would total
$4.5 billion.
   Attorneys for Atlanta-based Georgia-Pacific said a merger would
increase efficiency.
   As of Friday, 73.4 percent of Great Northern stockholders
tendered their shares under Georgia-Pacific's $63-a-share offer,
Stapleton said.
   The takeover battle is also being waged in Maine, where Great
Northern is incorporated. Georgia-Pacific is challenging
anti-takeover provisions in Great Northern's bylaws, as well as
Maine's corporate takeover law, which forces hostile suitors to
wait five years before merging with a targeted company.
</TEXT>

</DOC>