<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0005EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Koreas-Romania Bjt   12-28 0754</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Koreas-Romania, Bjt,0773</SECOND>
<HEAD>South Koreans Watch Romanian Collapse ... And Think Of The North</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KELLY TUNNEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   South Koreans watched Romania's
revolution stirred by the hope that communist North Korea will see
itself in the mirror and decide to change its rigid, totalitarian
ways.
   Romania's executed president, Nicolae Ceausescu, was the last
hard-line communist leader in the Warsaw Pact. His repressive rule
in isolated Romania often was compared to that of North Korea's Kim
Il Sung.
   Newspapers and TV stations here exhaustively covered the
collapse and a flood of editorials cautioned that North Korea risks
similar bloodshed if it fails to change.
   ``The North Korean leadership may well realize that its days are
numbered,'' said a Korea Times editorial. Romania, it added, ``will
hopefully serve as a grave warning to the Pyongyang leadership.''
   North Korea recognized the new Bucharest government on
Wednesday, saying it regards recent events as an internal Romanian
matter and expects to keep its ties with the Romanian people.
   Longtime observers saw the north's move as predictable and a
stall for time while it prepared a scenario to explain the new view
of the world to a citizenry used to accepting as dangerous any but
hard-line communist ideology.
   One Western diplomat, speaking on the condition of anonymity,
said: ``Hope for change is premature. North Korea feels change in
East Europe is the result of a bungled bureaucracy and since it has
no bureaucracy, it feels it needs no reform and has no problem.''
   In addition, North Korea is an Asian nation, not a European one
_ a nation bordered on the north and west by the Soviet Union and
China and on the east by the Sea of Japan. Capitalist South Korea,
inaccessible to North Koreans, is portrayed as a beggar country, a
stooge of American imperialists.
   North Koreans are isolated. They have no access to Western TV,
publications or merchandise, symbols diplomats call ``singing
commercials for capitalism.'' Citizens cannot leave the country
without permission.
   U.S. and South Korean observers see little possibility of a
popular uprising in the north. Any hint of dissent is crushed there
and the only news is that dictated by the government over
government-controlled radio stations.
   President Roh Tae-woo of South Korea said in a Christmas address
that North Korea is a tyranny which ``continues to hold sway,
seemingly uninfluenced by the winds of change blowing across so
many other communist states.''
   Still, Romania is bad news for the communist regime in the
north, which has portrayed Romania as a brother state, said Kim
Chang-soon, president of the Seoul government-funded North Korean
Affairs Research Institute.
   ``A news blockade may be the only choice they can make,'' ge
saud,
   Many South Koreans hope the north will see Romania's collapse as
a signal to be more receptive to capitalism and eventual
reunification of the two Koreas.
   The Korean peninsula was split into communist north and
capitalist south in 1945, a 155-mile Demilitarized Zone dividing
them. The DMZ is site of one of the world's greatest military
concentrations with 1.5 million heavily armed troops patrolling the
border.
   To help ease tensions, Seoul has worked to establish ties with
communist and East bloc nations. A spate of north-south talks has
been held this year, with little progress. The two countries remain
enemies.
   North Korea kept ties with communist and East bloc allies
undergoing change, but it shared a special kinship with Romania.
   Only last month, North Korea sent a congratulatory message to
the 14th Romanian Communist Party Congress in which it stressed a
joint struggle against capitalism. North Korea's foreign minister,
Kim Yong Nam, reportedly visited Bucharest just weeks ago to
reaffirm relations between the two countries.
   North Korea remains a totalitarian, inflexible regime under
77-year-old Kim Il Sung, who has dominated it with a personality
cult since the late 1940s. Kim designated his son as his political
heir in what would be the world's first communist dynasty.
   Most South Korean and U.S. observers reckon as almost nil the
prospect of change in North Korea while Kim Il Sung remains in
control. They say his son Kim Jong Il appears bent on continuing
the system.
   ``There are many similarities in the way Romania and communist
North Korea have held onto clannish despotism,'' said a Korea
Herald editorial. ``Few expected ... (Ceausescu) could be toppled
so quickly and easily. The Pyongyang regime must realize that
change will be the only option it will have in the very near
future.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>