<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0929EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-OaklandProbe     12-22 0259</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Oakland Probe,0268</SECOND>
<HEAD>Court Document Says Oakland Housing Police Stole from Undercover
Officers</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OAKLAND, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Undercover investigators who went into
public housing projects posing as drug dealers were beaten and
robbed by housing authority police, according to a court document.
   The 396-page affidavit filed in a probe of the Oakland Housing
Authority's 19-member force gives graphic accounts of nine alleged
run-ins between investigators and housing police, including
allegations that officers brutally beat unarmed investigators and
pocketed more than $900 in cash. The document was unsealed Thursday.
   The probe of the Oakland Housing Authority and its chief,
William H. Smith, was begun three months ago by the Oakland Police
Department, Alameda County District Attorney's Office and the state
Department of Justice.
   Smith previously denied any wrongdoing and any knowledge of
alleged wrongdoing by his officers.
   His agency operates 3,300 units that house 11,000 people.
   Authorities began the undercover operation to investigate
allegations of misconduct by the housing police, including
beatings, sexual assault, theft, falsification of arrest reports
and extortion.
   The affidavit was filed in Alameda County Municipal Court when
authorities sought a search warrant. After the warrant was issued,
investigators raided housing authority offices Dec. 11.
   Housing police, some videotaped by undercover teams, also
planted drugs to bolster arrests, said the affidavit signed by
Oakland Police Officer Marc Burrell.
   The male and female undercover officers posing as drug dealers
carried large amounts of cash into the city housing projects but
carried no drugs, the document said.
   Authorities would not comment further on the status of the
investigation.
</TEXT>

</DOC>