<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0819EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-NoriegaAttorneys     12-29 0292</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Noriega Attorneys,0303</SECOND>
<HEAD>Member of Noriega Defense Team Seeks To Extract Himself from Case</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   One of four Florida lawyers representing ousted
Panamanian leader Manuel Antonio Noriega has asked to be allowed to
quit in part because of public statements by the other attorneys in
the case.
   ``It was a question of drawing the line between function as a
lawyer and a general spokesperson,'' attorney Neal Sonnett said
Thursday. He said he'd rather not discuss his other reasons for
withdrawing.
   ``I have consistently refused to comment on Panamanian affairs _
they are outside my responsibility,'' he told The Associated Press.
``It's important for me to practice law.''
   ``I didn't really want to create a firestorm,'' he added.
``There have been other conflicts between me and co-counsel but
nothing I feel is appropriate to discuss.''
   Sonnett filed a motion Wednesday with the U.S. District Court
asking that he be allowed to quit representing Noriega on federal
drug charges filed in Miami in February 1988. The court usually
grants such requests.
   Although Sonnett in recent months has indicated that he was
pulling back from the case, both Frank Rubino and Raymond Takiff,
also Noreiga attorneys, said they were surprised by Sonnett's
motion.
   ``We've had no problems whatsoever,'' said Takiff. ``Just
general differences of opinion.''
   Takiff said he found Sonnett's move puzzling, especially since
Sonnett recently appeared on CNN's ``Crossfire'' and spoke of
Noriega.
   Sonnett countered that he appeared on the news show as president
of the National Association of Criminal Defense Lawyers to discuss
forfeiture of attorney's fees. He said he didn't talk about the
general.
   A fourth Noriega attorney, Steve Kollin, said he had no comment.
   Noriega was seeking asylum at the Vatican Embassy in Panama City.
</TEXT>

</DOC>