<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0165 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1539EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-Forecasters1990s Adv31   12-27 1174</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Forecasters 1990s, Adv 31,1214</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 31, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>World Notables: '90s Will Be Decade of Democracy and Environment</HEAD>
<HEAD>With BC-Preview 1990s</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Prominent personalities in political life, science, the arts and
other fields were asked by The Associated Press to sum up their
views of new directions in the world in the 1990s. Here are their
responses:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>VALERY GISCARD D'ESTAING, French statesman and former president:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The Soviet Union's exit from communism appears to be the most
difficult process to manage in the next 10 years. No doubt it will
involve periods of ... high inflation, and also political
convulsions. As the states of Eastern Europe move rather quickly
toward the European model, the Soviet Union will seek a separate
way, whose definition it probably will not be able to find soon.
This will lead it to remain in a state of uncertainty and strong
internal tension.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>LESTER R. BROWN, president of the Washington-based Worldwatch Institute:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The '90s promise to be the environmental decade, a time when
environmental trends increasingly will shape economic trends.
Rising world grain prices will likely be the first economic
indicator to signal trouble in the relationship between ourselves,
now numbering 5.2 billion, and the natural systems and resources on
which we depend. ... As the decade unfolds, the degradation of the
planet will begin showing up at harvest time.
   Reversing the deterioration of the planet will require
governments everywhere to redefine security, recognizing that the
principal threats to our future come less from military aggression
and more from environmental degradation.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>J. MICHAEL BISHOP, U.S. cancer researcher, co-winner of 1989 Nobel
Prize in medicine:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The prospect that seems most important to me is the potential
that our position as a pre-eminent nation in scientific research
may be eroded. I attribute it to the decline in real funding for
fundamental research. And to a decline in public education. ... I
think our nation is in danger of not taking intellect seriously
enough. ...
   Not even the parents of affluent children take the education of
their children as seriously as they should. They look to it as an
avenue to material success; they do not look to it for enrichment
of adult life. ... The public no longer cares about the creative
side of life.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DESMOND TUTU, South African Anglican archbishop:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   We are discovering a fundamental law of our human existence _
that we are made for interdependence with one another and with the
rest of creation. Consequently there will be increasing revulsion
with the arms race, with an increase in people's participation in
the peace movement. The big powers will persuade their surrogates
and clients to make peace in their respective areas. There will be
an upsurge of concern for human rights and interest in
participatory styles of government. ... AIDS and poverty will draw
us closer together.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>BAI HUA, leading Chinese poet and playwright:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Developments in the 1990s will be closer to the hopes of the
common people. Changes in the Soviet Union, Eastern Europe and Asia
all illustrate this point. Also people are becoming more and more
concerned with man's living environment, not only in the
relationship between people. I think there is hope.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>GRO HARLEM BRUNDTLAND, former Norwegian prime minister:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   I hope that we will see an increased democratization in Eastern
Europe but also in other parts of the world and that human rights
everywhere will be raised to a higher standard. People are more
aware of the world economy and the world's ecology than was the
case when we go back even one decade.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MARGARET THATCHER, British prime minister:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Global environment _ protecting the ozone layer, working towards
combatting the greenhouse effect _ are problems we must tackle
together. On the political front, while maintaining a strong NATO,
we should continue to work for further nuclear disarmament. We must
also continue to encourage the democratization process in Eastern
Europe and the Soviet Union, where we have seen such encouraging
developments recently. The prospects for progress in South Africa
are also very much at the front of our minds. Closer to home, we
shall need to ensure that Britain and its European Community
partners develop into a truly common market.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>JUAN ANTONIO SAMARANCH, International Olympic Committee president:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   We have to face some dangers. One of the dangers is doping, but
I think with the help of the governments and the international
federations, we will win this fight. ... Commercialization is very
necessary but we have to avoid its controlling sports. ... Speaking
about the situation in the Communist countries, I will say that the
political changes in these countries are also helping sports
relations. The Olympic Games in Seoul were perhaps the best ever
because there was a very good political ambience in the world.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>GEOFFREY PALMER, New Zealand prime minister:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   There is a danger that rapid economic growth in some parts of
the developing world could be mistakenly interpreted as the end of
the problems of economic imbalance between developed and developing
countries. In the 1990s, the international community must sustain
its commitment to development assistance efforts for deprived
countries and the poorest people within those countries.
``Sustainable development'' _ development of resources without
degradation of the environment _ will be the catchword of the next
decade.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NAGUIB MAHFOUZ, Egyptian winner of 1988 Nobel Prize in literature:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   At present in the Third World, readership has diminished because
people are preoccupied with their problems, their economic
problems. Art and literature are not flourishing. But hopefully
inflation will decrease, and at least a small base of literature
will be formed.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DEREK BOK, President, Harvard University:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Government agencies, foundations, corporations, and other
institutions tug insistently at professors for advice on a wide
variety of topics, while the public expresses irritation that
faculty members fly about so much and neglect their teaching and
students. Everyone is angry over rising college costs ... These
conflicts reflect a mounting confusion in the country over what we
really want of our colleges and universities and how we would like
their most creative, knowledgeable professors to allocate their
time. ... In the 1990s, universities, the government, and the
public at large will need to work harder to reconcile their
differences or we will surely damage institutions of great
potential value that are pre-eminent in the world and essential to
our society.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>BARRY COMMONER, leading U.S. environmentalist:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   We enter the next decade with the troubling knowledge that the
20-year effort to clean up the environment has failed. ...
   Environmental pollution is an incurable disease; it can only be
prevented.
   Pollution prevention means building new smog-less car engines;
eliminating the use of agricultural chemicals by shifting to
organic farming; replacing fossil fuels with solar energy.
   The transition to such ecologically sound production
technologies will challenge the taboo against questioning the
dominance of private interests over the public interest in
environmental quality. In the 1990s, we will need a perestroika of
our own.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Sunday, Dec. 31</NOTE>

</DOC>