<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0124 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1658EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-BushText 4thAdd   12-21 0720</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Bush Text, 4th Add,590</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHN: possible. Yeah?</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Q: Yes, Mr. President, what can you tell us about civilian
casualties, specifically Panamanian civilian casualties down there,
and was there any estimate given in the preplanning of this
invasion of civilian casualties?
   A: Our numbers are almost nonexistent, and I heard some reports
from a hospital, and we've not been able to confirm those numbers,
that some civilians were killed. And I just asked that of our
defense chief, who had the latest information when he came over
here. And so I just can't help you on the total numbers.
   Q: Well, then _ my _ the other question was, the second part,
was there an estimate in the preplanning of this invasion?
   A:I don't think an estimate of numbers, but a great concern
about that, and one of the reasons we went in with the force we
did, to take down the PDF and do it as quickly, was to minimize
civilian casualties. And the way we went after some of these
targets was to minimize civilian casualties. We _ a lot of kids
risked their lives going in at night. Parachuting in someplace at
night is not a piece of cake. And we _ some of that was to _ stay
away from the fact that civilians would be out and about in the
morning.
   Q: Mr. President, how do you rate the chances now that _
(laughter in response to off-mike comment) _ Noriega might be able
to manage some kind of a hit-and-run guerrilla operation from
hiding? What are the chances of that?
   A: I don't think so. The military doesn't seem to think that he
has the communications or a PDF-continued loyalty that would make
him go into the woods. I like the way Colin Powell put it: He
hasn't been in a jungle in a long time. And it's tough living, and
he's been living high off the hog, off the Panamanian people. And
so we don't expect kind of a Sierra Madre approach to this.
   Sarah, you've been very good and kind all year. This is my last
press conference here _
   Q: _ got a final question _
   A: _ and this is the second-to-last question. I hope it's a
gentle one.
   Q: What do you mean, your last press conference here, sir?
   A: Is that your question? Well, here is _ (laughter) _ here's
the thing. We've _ how many have we had this year?
   Q: No, but sir _
   STAFF: Thirty.
   A: We've had 30 press conferences this year, Helen, and some in
your midst here have come to me and said _ please Sarah, lighten
up, do not _ don't do this quite so much.
   Thank you very much.
   Q: This is a very mild question. Are you sending a letter today
to the Senate to coordinate with the War Powers Act? They have the _
   A: I don't know whether it goes today, but we will do what _
well, we're _ we will _ I think there's certain technical language
on this that _ but notification of the Congress will be done in
accordance with our policy.
   This is the last one.
   Q: Have the Soviets _ the Soviets have criticized very sharply
this distinction of yours to the point of saying they're going
forward and the United States is going backwards. What is your
reaction to this?
   A: My reaction is I need to get on a wire there _ in a telegram
or something _ explain this to Mr. Gorbachev. It's not altogether
surprising that he doesn't understand some of the special
arrangements that the United States has in Panama. It's not
surprising that he doesn't fully understand that this freely
elected man had been deprived of the democracy, and I also need to
let him know, OK, if American Marine is killed _ if they kill an
American Marine, that's real bad. And if they threaten and
brutalize the wife of an American citizen, sexually threatening the
lieutenant's wife while kicking him in the groin over and over
again, then, Mr. Gorbachev, please understand, this President is
going to do something about it.
   So we'll have to explain it very _ the last one, Maureen, and
then I really do have to go.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>