<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0938EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-EastGermany     12-27 0474</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-East Germany,0488</SECOND>
<HEAD>Political Negotiations Resume in Controversy</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NESHA STARCEVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The head of a new East German opposition
party today withdrew from talks between East Germany's coalition
government and other opposition groups after he was accused of
corruption.
   The announcement came as the talks, which concern the future
course of the country, resumed today after a Christmas break.
   Wolfgang Schnur, chairman of the Democratic Awakening Party, was
accused in the newspaper Junge Welt of using his position to obtain
a large apartment that originally had been allocated to a family
with several children.
   The 45-year-old lawyer denied the allegations but said he was
withdrawing from the talks until the matter had been clarified. He
said he was the target of a ``massive campaign'' aimed at
discrediting him and his party politically, and he claimed his
mother, who is Jewish, has received threats from neo-Nazis.
   Schnur, elected chairman of Democratic Awakening earlier this
month when the opposition group met to constitute itself as a
political party, said he would seek a vote of confidence from the
party board.
   Since the fall of hard-line Communist leader Erich Honecker on
Oct. 18, East Germans have been intent on rooting out corruption.
Most such allegations have centered on the top levels of the
now-ousted Communist Party leadership.
   East German leaders have instituted dizzying changes following
protests by hundreds of thousands of people for democratic reform.
It opened the Berlin Wall as part of loosened travel restrictions
in November, promised free elections and called for the talks
between Communist and opposition leaders.
   Honecker's successor, Egon Krenz, also resigned as president and
a non-Communist replaced him in a new coalition government, which
includes the Communists and four traditionally allied parties.
Communist Premier Hans Modrow is handling day-to-day affairs until
the free elections.
   The talks involve 37 representatives from five established
political parties, including the Communists, and representatives of
16 opposition groups.
   The discussion group is acting as a watchdog group on Modrow's
government until the elections May 6.
   Junge Welt, a youth-oriented newspaper once closely allied with
the Communists, made the allegations against Schnur.
   Schnur's party has maintained close contacts with West German
officials but is split on the question of reunification. It has
also called for a free market system in East Germany, although
there is a dispute on this topic as well.
   His movement has existed as a party for only two weeks, and its
national influence is still hard to assess.
   Schnur said he would sue the newspaper, which has become
increasingly independent and aggressive in its reporting. Schnur
also said his mother received anonymous letters containing threats
from neo-Nazis.
   East German leaders have said they are on guard against a
possible rise in nationalist and neo-Nazi groups, as a result of
the turmoil gripping the Communist country.
</TEXT>

</DOC>