<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1349EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MysteryDonor 1stLd-Writethru a0547 12-25 0700</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mystery Donor, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0547,0716</SECOND>
<HEAD>Retransmitting to restore writethru designation.</HEAD>
<HEAD>`Mystery Man' Showers College Professors With Trips, Other Gifts</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 12th graf, `Chemistry professor...', to CORRECT spelling
of Bocksch.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SPOKANE, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An anonymous benefactor is enriching the
lives of veteran Whitworth College faculty members, providing free
vacations anywhere in the world, exotic food and other gifts.
   ``This person has been a Santa Claus many times over,'' said Ed
Olson, a geology professor who has been given two weeks in New
Zealand with the use of a motor home next month.
   For the past year and a half, 17 faculty members who have been
at the small, private liberal arts college at least 20 years have
benefited from the largesse of a man they know only as ``M.M.'' for
mystery man.
   Professors typically are contacted by Laurel Livingston of the
Bremerton AAA Travel Agency, who offers them and their spouses
two-week vacations, including travel, lodging and sometimes $1,000
to cover miscellaneous expenses.
   After the trips, they get presents like Thanksgiving hams,
imported coffee, exotic foods from distant cities, cameras,
binoculars, calendars and art, many accompanied by notes signed
only ``M.M.''
   One professor got a coffee grinder and, a few months later, a
second coffee grinder with a note explaining the first model was
unreliable.
   The travel agent won't say who the donor is, but faculty members
believe he graduated from Whitworth sometime in the 1960s, went
into business in the Puget Sound area and lives in Seattle.
   ``We honestly can't identify who it is,'' said Howard Gage, a
math professor who took a gift trip to England with his wife last
summer. ``That's part of the fun.''
   ``This is too good to be real,'' said art professor Spike
Grosvenor, who got a trip to England last summer. ``It's the sort
of thing that only happens on Christmas TV specials or in the
Reader's Digest.''
   Recipients since the program began in June 1988 are 14 men and
three women 50 to 87 years old. Six are retired. Two other retired
faculty members were were unable to accept trips for health reasons.
   ``I've never heard of any other faculty group getting this sort
of reward,'' said psychology professor Patricia MacDonald, who has
taught at Whitworth for 35 years and received a trip to Hawaii last
summer. ``It makes us feel special.''
   Chemistry professor Bob Bocksch, the first recipient of a gift
vacation, initially refused a second trip.
   ``I think he felt our first trip didn't cost enough, being just
two weeks in Hawaii, so he suggested we take a second one,'' he
said.
   Bocksch wrote a note through the travel agent suggesting a
donation to a chemistry equipment fund instead.
   The donor sent a $5,000 check to the school, then insisted that
Bocksch take a second vacation. He relented and took a 10-day
Alaskan cruise.
   The first three trips were given to faculty members who were
told that the gifts were in gratitude to teachers who helped the
mystery man when he was a student.
   Later gifts went to ``people he wanted to honor for their
contributions to Whitworth,'' Livingston said.
   Livingston described the donor as a ``very generous, very caring
person'' who travels frequently and likes people. She said he would
not give his reasons for the gifts or say how much he had spent.
   Grosvenor is one of three recipients who have talked with him by
phone.
   ``Certain clues make me think he was a classmate of Howard
(Gage)'s and mine,'' Grosvenor said. ``He knew that I spent one
summer working as a groundskeeper at the college.
   ``Whoever he is, he does his homework. He knew all about my
field of study and that I had never been to Europe. It's amazing
how much he knew.''
   Grosvenor said the donor suggested a trip this fall to England
to study stained glass, the professor's special interest. He said
the resulting trip was ``the most wonderful, perfect vacation I
could have had.''
   Music professor Thomas Tavener was just offered a trip but has
yet to choose a destination. ``It is exciting,'' he said. ``I guess
there are benefits for staying in one place for 31 years.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>