<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1204EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Christmas-OtherReligions Bjt   12-24 0654</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Christmas-Other Religions, Bjt,0675</SECOND>
<HEAD>Have a Glorious Bodhi Day _ Non-Christians Are Celebrating, Too</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID BRIGGS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Moslem leaders from around the nation are
meeting in an annual conference on the prophet Mohammed, some
American Buddhists are giving new stature to Bodhi Day, and
lighting Hanukkah candles has become the second most widely
practiced observance among American Jews.
   It must be Christmastime.
   While Christian leaders bemoan the commercialization of
Christmas, other religious groups are reporting revived interest in
their own traditions in reaction to the relentless secular presence
of the holiday.
   ``What that reflects, frankly, is the attempt ... to compensate
for the overwhelming presence of Christmas in American society,''
said Rabbi A. James Rudin, national interreligious affairs director
of the American Jewish Committee.
   Rudin said there has been a ``mismatch'' because the Jewish and
Christian holidays fall near each other but are not equal in
importance.
   ``One is a minor Jewish holiday. One is a major Christian
holiday,'' Rudin said. ``The truth is Christmas is not the
Christian Hanukkah and Hanukkah is not the Jewish Christmas.''
   But that has not stopped Hanukkah, the eight-day Jewish Feast of
Lights that began Friday evening, from becoming an important
tradition in the United States. Surveys showed more than two-thirds
of all Jewish people in the United States light Hanukkah candles, a
ritual surpassed only by attendance at a Passover Seder.
   Among many Buddhists, special emphasis has been placed on the
Dec. 8 celebration of Bodhi Day, the day they believe the Buddha
became enlightened.
   The Rev. Carol Himaka, education director of the Buddhist
Churches of America in San Francisco, said Bodhi Day is being more
widely observed ``because of the need to have our own young people
recognize our own tradition.''
   Still, she said, many Buddhists celebrate Christmas the way a
lot of non-devout Christians mark the holiday _ with trees and
presents and little regard for the religious significance of the
birth of the person Christians believe is the son of God.
   ``It's more difficult to explain to young children, especially,
why they should not celebrate Christmas,'' she said.
   The Bahais, who say Jesus was a prophet sent by God, do not
believe there is a spiritual conflict in observing Christmas,
according to Katharine Bigelow, deputy director of the Bahai
National Office of External Affairs in Washington.
   ``I don't observe Christmas with my Bahai friends, but with my
family who is all Christian, I look forward to celebrating with
them,'' she said.
   Some Moslem leaders attending the Seerah Conference sponsored by
the Council of Masajid of United States over Christmas weekend said
that while Jesus also is a respected figure in their faith, all
trappings of Christmas should be avoided.
   ``We want our children to know about our religion and an Islamic
perspective,'' said Habib Malik, a teacher with the Muslim World
League in Philadelphia.
   ``We are concerned when we see some Moslem families bringing
Christmas trees home.''
   Imam Shamsher Ali, director of the Islamic Religious Center of
Long Island, said Moslem religious leaders emphasize at Friday
prayer sessions before Christmas that their faith teaches Jesus was
a prophet of God, but not the son of God.
   Competition with Christmas is not always a positive thing, other
religious leaders said.
   Rudin remembers being told as a child to be thankful he was
Jewish and receiving gifts for eight days during Hanukkah, while
``those quote `poor Christians' were only going to get gifts for
one day.''
   His advice: ``Let Hanukkah be Hanukkah.''
   Some celebrations this time of year are not tied to any religion.
   Kwanzaa, a holiday modeled on traditional African harvest
celebrations, is observed by some black Americans. It begins
Tuesday and runs through Jan. 1.
   And the Southern California wing of Atheists United exchanged
gifts Thursday afternoon to mark the winter solstice.
   ``Basically, it's a time to party,'' said Atheists United
President Alexander Prairie.
</TEXT>

</DOC>