<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0264 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1811EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-CommodityRdp     12-21 0687</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Commodity Rdp,0711</SECOND>
<HEAD>Frigid Weather Again Boosts Orange Juice, Heating Oil Futures</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID DISHNEAU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Frigid weather forecasts continued to boost orange juice and
heating oil futures prices Thursday as a record-shattering Canadian
cold front moved southward and eastward.
   On other commodity markets, precious metals turned lower;
livestock and meat futures advanced; and grains and soybeans were
mixed.
   Prices of most contracts for future deliveries of frozen
concentrated orange juice soared the permitted daily limit of 5
cents a pound on the New York Cotton Exchange. The limitless
contract for January delivery rose 7.25 cents to $1.417 a pound.
   Weather Services Corp., a private forecasting firm in Bedford,
Mass., rated the probability of a weekend freeze in the Florida
citrus belt at 80 percent Thursday, up from 75 percent on Wednesday
and 50 percent the day before.
   Peter Leavitt, executive vice president of Weather Services,
said the coldest temperatures _ projected at 18 to 28 degrees _
would likely occur Sunday morning in the citrus country.
   The expected freeze would rival one that occurred on Christmas
Day in 1983, severely damaging the Florida orange crop, and could
well be colder, Leavitt said.
   ``You cannot really underestimate the magnitude of this cold air
mass for this time of year,'' Leavitt said. ``This will go into the
books, I'm sure, as an historic event.''
   The enter of the cold front plowed out of the Northern Plains
and into the Midwest on Thursday, dropping temperatures as low as
22 below zero in Sioux City, Iowa, and pushing mercury below the
freezing mark nearly as far south as the Gulf of Mexico.
   In the populous Northeast, the area most closely watched by
heating oil traders at this time of year, the encroaching cold
front promised no relief from the sub-normal temperatures that are
likely to make this December the coldest on record.
   ``Temperatures in the Northeast have averaged below normal every
single day this month,'' Leavitt said. ``This is the 23rd straight
day of below-normal temperatures.''
   The cold has forced fuel oil dealers to delve into their
reserves to meet the extraordinary demand and, on Thursday, drove
heating oil futures prices up sharply on the New York Mercantile
Exchange for the fifth straight day and the 16th time in the last
17 trading sessions.
   The buying spilled over into the crude oil and gasoline pits,
powering futures prices for those commodities up as well.
   West Texas Intermediate crude oil settled 31 cents to 36 cents
higher with February at $21.52 a barrel; heating oil was .90 cent
to 4.05 cents higher with January at 79.81 cents a gallon; unleaded
gasoline was 1.55 cent to 2.41 cents higher with January at 55.63
cents a gallon.
   Precious-metals futures prices sagged in quiet trading on New
York's Commodity Exchange as players squared their books ahead of
the long holiday weekend.
   Gold futures finished $1.70 to $2.30 lower with December at
$411.90 a troy ounce; silver was 0.5 cent to 1 cent lower with
December at $5.543 a troy ounce.
   Livestock and meat futures settled higher on the Chicago
Mercantile Exchange after a late rally linked to technical factors
and to the cold weather in the Midwest, which has cut deeply into
hog marketings.
   Live cattle futures finished .35 cent to .50 cent higher with
February at 76.80 cents a pound; feeder cattle were .05 cent to .40
cent higher with January at 84.80 cents a pound; live hogs were .05
cent to .33 cent higher with February at 49.47 cents a pound;
frozen pork bellies were unchanged to .38 cent higher with February
at 49.60 cents a pound.
   Soybean futures prices settled slightly higher in a quiet
session on the Chicago Board of Trade while grain futures finished
narrowly mixed.
   Wheat futures settled \ cent lower to \ cent higher with March
at $4.12} a bushel; corn futures were } cent lower to 1 cent higher
with March at $2.38} a bushel; oats were 1\ cents to 2\ cents
higher with March at $1.54{ a bushel; soybeans were } cent to 2{
cents higher with January at $5.74{ a bushel.
</TEXT>

</DOC>