<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0203 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 2049EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f BC-WeeklyCommodities Adv30-31   12-29 0720</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Weekly Commodities, Adv 30-31,0740</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv30</HEAD>
<HEAD>$adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Weekend Editions Dec. 30-31</HEAD>
<HEAD>Another Wild Week For Heating Oil, OJ Futures</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID DISHNEAU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A shot of OJ with a heating oil chaser was the New Year's drink
of choice in the commodity pits.
   Orange juice futures rallied this past week after a damaging
freeze in the Florida citrus belt, and heating oil for January
delivery finished with a record high.
   On other markets, precious metals futures nosedived, most grain
and soybean futures fell, and livestock and meat futures were
little changed.
   Frozen concentrated orange juice for delivery in January soared
21 percent during the holiday-shortened, four-day trading week,
settling Friday at $1.6565 a pound on the New York Cotton Exchange
compared with $1.37 a week earlier.
   The contract jumped 16 cents on Tuesday alone as traders
returned from the long Christmas weekend to reports of widespread
damage to the Florida orange crop.
   Buying pressure eased on Wednesday, when profit-taking took the
January contract down nearly 3 cents. But the rally resumed
Thursday from news that Brazil, a major supplier of orange juice to
the United States, was suspending juice exports until next week,
when an official estimate of the Florida damage is expected.
   Analysts said Brazilian imports could increase by 20 percent
because of the Florida freeze. They said Brazilian officials are
probably trying to decide whether to raise the prices of their
orange juice.
   Futures prices jumped again Friday amid forecasts for a return
to normal temperatures in Florida this weekend. A warmup would
hasten the falling and rotting of freeze-damaged fruit and make it
more vulnerable to spoilage.
   ``Quite frankly, for some growers in Florida, this has been a
disaster,'' said Bert Ruiz, a vice president of Balfour Maclaine
Futures Inc.
   On the other hand, he said, speculators who bought the market
prior to the Christmastime freeze ``were paid handsomely.''
   The contract for January delivery of home heating oil expired
Friday at a record high of $1.06 a gallon the New York Mercantile
Exchange compared with 81.74 a week earlier, a 30 percent gain.
   Just one month ago, January heating oil was trading at about 62
cents a gallon.
   Jay Klopfenstein, head of Norwood Securities Inc. in Chicago,
called the market's gains ``a once-in-a-decade type of movement.''
Analyst Peter Beutel of Elders Futures Inc. described the December
rally as ``one of the most spectacular bull moves in heating oil of
all time.''
   The rally was largely linked to the unusually cold weather in
recent weeks, which caused shortages of home heating oil on the
cash market. The problem has been most severe in the heavily
populated Northeast, where this December has been among the coldest
ever.
   January heating oil rose sharply on Tuesday and Wednesday, then
retreated Thursday after hitting $1.02 a gallon early in the day.
   The market seemed to have peaked. But buyers roared back on
Friday and bid the price up to $1.06 by the close, reflecting
uncertainty over next week's weather.
   The late rally raised speculation that the market will continue
to surge when trading resumes next week.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Precious Metals</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Gold and silver futures prices fell sharply on New York's
Commodity Exchange, reflecting the withdrawal from the market of
investors who had bought heavily during late October and November
amid the startling political changes in Eastern Europe.
   The execution last week of Romanian dictator Nicolae Ceausescu
and the surrender to the Vatican of ousted Panamanian strongman
Manuel Noreiga seemed to ease investor fears about heightened
international tensions, analysts said.
   Traders also were disappointed that the Soviet Union has not
announced plans to back its currency with gold, as some experts had
expected, said Peter Cardillo, commodity trading adviser with
Josephthal &amp; Co.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Grains and soybeans</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The soybean market again led most grain futures lower as growing
conditions for the Brazilian soybean crop continued to improve.
Warmer temperatures in the Great Plains and forecasts for
above-average precipitation in that region next week weighed on the
wheat market, where traders are keeping a close watch on conditions
for the winter wheat crop.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Livestock and meat</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Cattle and hog futures were little changed in a week of light,
uneventful trading. Pork belly futures rallied after four weeks of
losses in reaction to a monthly Agriculture Department report
showing smaller-than-expected frozen belly stocks.
</TEXT>

</DOC>