<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0150EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-NuclearRisks     12-19 0626</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Nuclear Risks,620</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Knew of Health Risks to Nuclear Plant Workers, Report
Says</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government had clear evidence shortly
after the first nuclear bombs were built in the 1940s that weapons
workers were being exposed to potentially dangerous amounts of
radiation, according to a congressional report.
   Despite this information, including some not previously made
public, officials overseeing the bomb factories recommended not
informing workers of the possible health risks they faced at the
secretly operated facilities, the report said.
   ``The U.S. nuclear weapons program was exposing large numbers of
workers to potentially dangerous health risks but did nothing to
warn them,'' said Sen. John Glenn, D-Ohio, in releasing the report
on Monday.
   The report was prepared by the majority staff of the Senate
Governmental Affairs Committee, which Glenn chairs. The panel is
investigating the health research programs of the Energy
Department, which owns the 17 major facilities that design and make
nuclear arms.
   More than 600,000 people have worked at the weapons plants over
the past 45 years.
   The report focused mainly on the period 1947-54 when the Atomic
Energy Commission, the predecessor to the Energy Department, was
rapidly expanding nuclear arms production amid deep suspicions
about Soviet and other foreign development of the bomb.
   Records of an October 1948 meeting of an AEC advisory committee
indicated that enough was known then about releases of radiation at
the Hanford plutonium plant near Richland, Wash., to raise concern
about workers' health. Yet it was decided at the meeting not to
recommend closing Hanford temporarily while action was taken to
stop the release of plutonium particles into the air.
   Despite the concerns about health dangers, ``a counter-balancing
concern was the perceived need, fueled by Cold War fears, to
continue plutonium production because of the relatively small size
of the U.S. nuclear arsenal in 1948,'' the report said.
   The report quoted a committee report from the October 1948
meeting as saying, ``there is no scientific evidence that it is an
unwarranted hazard to continue the present process for six weeks,
during which steps will be taken vigorously to control the
hazard.'' The control measures apparently were not fully successful.
   In December 1948, the manager of the federal Oak Ridge weapons
plant in Tennessee recommended to the AEC's advisory committee that
workers who quit the weapons program be told if they had exceeded
radiation exposure limits, the report said. The manager also
recommended providing medical aid if a former worker developed a
radiation-related illness.
   The advisory panel rejected the recommendations, the report
said. Instead it recommended to the AEC that ``a terminating
employee should be advised at the exit interview as to the care
that the AEC utilizes in protecting each employee.''
   The documents uncovered by the Glenn committee indicated that a
major concern at the Hanford facility was the release of huge
numbers of plutonium particles. The problem, dating at least to
1947, was traced to corroded fan-duct work in the stacks of two
plutonium chemical separations plants.
   A March 1948 report by Dr. Herbert M. Parker, director of the
Hanford health instruments department of General Electric Co.,
which ran the facility for the government, said an average of about
7.4 billion particles were being released from the two plants each
month.
   Parker wrote that ``the critical hazard is to the inhalation and
lung retention of particles,'' which he said ``can produce
radiation damage.'' At the time it was estimated that a worker
could be inhaling about 16 radioactive particles per month.
   This suggests that over a one-year period a worker could have
inhaled an amount of plutonium that is more than twice the current
official lifetime lung burden allowed for Energy Department
workers, the Glenn report said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>