<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1053EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Somalia Bjt   12-30 0883</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Somalia, Bjt,0912</SECOND>
<HEAD>An Isolated Somalia Appears Near Collapse</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY18</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR's NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The writer, AP's East Africa bureau chief based
in Nairobi, Kenya, recently became the first American journalist
officially permitted to visit Somalia in nearly two years.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By REID G. MILLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOGADISHU, Somalia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The lights are going out in President
Mohammed Siad Barre's dingy, crumbling capital.
   After 20 years of often ruthless rule, the aging Siad Barre, who
is believed to be in his 80s, is isolated internationally and beset
by strife in his country.
   His power, most foreign observers agree, now extends no more
than 140 miles outside this seaside city, built three centuries ago
by an Arab ruler.
   ``Beyond that, it's a no man's land of war and banditry,'' says
one Western diplomat.
   But one foreign diplomat notes that those who oppose Siad Barre
may well have trouble agreeing on anything beyond their opposition
to him. The diplomat said there is no obvious person with the clout
or charisma to replace Siad Barre and lead the nation to a more
stable future.
   Strategically located at the tip of the Horn of Africa on the
eastern approach to the Red Sea, Somalia used to be wooed by both
the Soviet Union and the United States.
   But the Soviet Union abandoned Somalia in favor of rival
Ethiopia in their 1977 war over the Ogaden, long a disputed
territory on their central border.
   Now the United States, which happily picked up Siad Barre as a
client when Moscow dropped him, has tired of his human rights
abuses and stricken him from its list of friends.
   Washington has withheld or canceled more than $50 million in aid
dating back to 1987. Britain, France and other Western donors also
have slashed funds.
   Their growing unhappiness reached a peak in July when Siad
Barre's personal bodyguards, marked by their red-fringed berets,
crushed protests in the capital. According to diplomats, the guards
then rounded up 47 civilians, took them to a nearby beach, killed
them and buried the bodies in the sand.
   That came little more than a week after the United States
dedicated a new, $35 million embassy, the largest in sub-Sahara
Africa with a compound that boasts three swimming pools and a
nine-hole golf course.
   By the end of 1990, plans call for slashing the embassy staff of
about 430 in half, reflecting the sharp reductions in aid and the
number of people needed to administer it.
   Tribal rebellions in the north and south of the nation and clan
warfare in the center have sapped Somalia's treasury and helped
produce a sharp drop in export earnings. Never large to begin with,
they have fallen from about $100 million in 1986 to an estimated
$60 million in 1989.
   All of this has left Siad Barre with a bankrupt economy, an
annual inflation rate of 120 percent, an unpayable foreign debt of
$2 billion and a growing chorus of discontent that reaches even
into many government offices.
   Many of those offices barely function, the bureaucrats who man
them forced to find other sources of money on the outside or to
sell government services and favors to supplement their meager
incomes.
   Siad Barre has tried to defuse the growing opposition to his
regime by appointing a commission to rewrite the constitution to
permit multiparty elections late in 1990, a step his critics say is
too little too late.
   He also has offered to enter into unconditional peace talks with
his armed opponents, especially the Somali National Movement which
has routed government forces in much of the north of the country.
He had no takers.
   ``The opposition sees the government as crumbling. That's why
they're probably in no hurry to talk,'' said another diplomat, who,
like the first, spoke on condition he not be identified.
   Siad Barre faces another, smaller insurgency in southern Somalia
that surfaced only early this year. It has been largely stalled in
recent months by a rainy season that ends in January, when renewed
fighting is widely expected.
   The southern group, known as the Somali Patriotic Movement, has
spoken of a possible alliance with the northern insurgents, who
have been fighting off and on since 1981, but there is no evidence
of unity between them.
   In Mogadishu, where robberies and burlaries are soaring as the
desperately poor take to crime to meet their needs, public services
are virtually non-existent and many neighborhoods are almost always
without electricity because, it is said, the diesel fuel needed to
run the city's only power generator is siphoned off and sold by
government employees.
   Siad Barre, whose exact age is unknown but is thought to be in
the 80s, bemoans the loss of Western aid and denies the
well-documented human rights abuses that led to its reduction.
   ``It's no good to abandon your friends in a time of need,'' he
said in an interview in a luxuriously furnished conference room in
one of the many buildings that dot the large, walled compound in
which he lives and works.
   On the question of human rights abuses, he replied: ``It is
baseless. What's the use of arguing about it? It is being used as a
means to reach a certain goal. We do not believe it is fair.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>