<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0602EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ColdRdp     12-29 0725</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Cold Rdp,0749</SECOND>
<HEAD>South Assesses Damage From Cold Snap</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Stands for PM-Freeze-Disaster on the PM-News Advisory.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL MOKRZYCKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Florida and Texas officials are taking stock of crop damage from
the hard Christmas freeze and taking steps to help growers who lost
millions and farm workers who lost their jobs.
   Florida Gov. Bob Martinez declared his entire state a disaster
area Thursday and sought federal help, while Texas officials worked
to open relief centers for farm workers displaced by the worst
freeze to hit the lower Rio Grande Valley in six years.
   Elsewhere in the Deep South, crews worked to restore water
service after the past week's freezing weather burst pipes and
mains.
   Somewhat more moderate temperatures were returning to the South,
though at 5 a.m. EST today it was only 36 degrees in Jacksonville,
Fla., 33 degrees in Macon, Ga., and 26 degrees in Knoxville, Tenn.
Cities in the North were being spared the arctic blasts of recent
weeks, though snow fell from Salt Lake City to the Dakotas this
morning.
   The hard freeze Saturday and Sunday nights damaged oranges and
grapefruit in Florida's 700,000-acre citrus belt as well as winter
vegetable crops. The dollar value of the loss had yet to be
determined.
   The state's tropical fish industry, sugar cane crops and plant
nurseries also were hurt badly.
   After visiting several freeze-damaged farms, Martinez signed an
executive order declaring the disaster in all 67 Florida counties.
The move opens the way for a possible federal disaster declaration
by President Bush.
   ``From what I have seen, there is no question that Florida has
suffered devastating losses and that our state is a disaster
area,'' Martinez said. ``We must now do everything we can to help
those whose lives and livelihoods have been ravaged by the
unmerciful weather.''
   In a letter, Martinez asked Agriculture Secretary Clayton
Yuetter to approve Farmers Home Administration loans for growers.
Unemployment assistance, direct grants and other help also could
become available if Bush declares a disaster.
   State agriculture officials will assess each county to compile
loss estimated, which would be needed before a federal declaration
is made. That could take two or three weeks.
   A freeze in 1985 freeze cost the Florida citrus industry alone
about $255 million.
   Higher vegetable prices have already been reported, but the
impact on citrus prices could be minimal because of a large juice
reserve and the quick processing of frostbitten fruit into juice
concentrate.
   Florida's 33 citrus processing plants were pushed to the limit
Thursday in an effort to salvage frozen fruit and squeeze it into
juice before it spoils.
   ``We'll be open 24 hours per day, seven days a week during the
salvage process,'' said Steve Caruso, assistant general manager at
Citrus World, a processing plant in Lake Wales that produces about
400,000 gallons of fresh juice daily.
   In Texas, officials estimated that 60 percent of the lower Rio
Grande Valley's $80 million citrus crop and 80 percent of its
vegetable crop was lost when temperatures dropped into the teens
and 20s last weekend.
   There are 15,000 farmworker families in the Rio Grande Valley,
and Hidalgo County Judge Edgar Ruiz expects many to seek help
because without crops, they won't have work. The American Red
Cross, the Texas Department of Human Services and Hidalgo County
plan to open four relief centers.
   In Jackson, Miss., where an estimated 60,000 people were without
water or had greatly reduced pressure earlier this week, city crews
finished repairing 28 remaining breaks in the city's 900 miles of
pipes and mains.
   City officials asked some businesses to conserve water, but told
residents Thursday night they could safely use tap water for the
first time in nearly a week.
   Jackson officials also reported two cold-related fatalities,
including a 62-year-old man who died of heart problems when he fell
in a lake while trying to collect water to flush his toilet.
   At least 104 deaths nationwide since Dec. 15 have been
attributed to the cold. Several of the victims were children in
Southern states who fell through ice on ponds or lakes.
   The cold killed fish in Louisiana bayous and is threatening sea
turtles around Florida. The cold-blooded reptiles are sensitive to
temperatures and the cold makes them lethargic. Also in Florida,
the cold chased endangered manatees into pockets of warm water near
power plants.
</TEXT>

</DOC>