<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 0034EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Blue 1stLd-Writethru a0641 12-17 0350</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Blue, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0641,0358</SECOND>
<HEAD>Robert Blue, Two-Term Governor and Champion of the Elderly, Dead
at 91</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf to ADD that Blue was a Republican. Cathlene is
cq in penultimate graf.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FORT DODGE, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Robert D. Blue, a champion of the
elderly who served two terms as Iowa's governor in the 1940s, has
died of complications from a stroke. He was 91.
   Blue died Thursday at Trinity Regional Hospital in this city
about 70 miles northwest of Des Moines.
   The son of a locomotive engineer and a teacher, Blue worked his
way up from county attorney to city attorney, state representative,
speaker of the House and lieutenant governor. The Republican served
as governor from 1944-48 before losing a primary in his bid for a
third two-year term.
   Blue made enemies in organized labor during his second term when
he supported and signed what became known as Iowa's Right to Work
law, which prohibited companies from barring non-union employees.
   Other than the four years he served as governor in Des Moines,
Blue spent his entire life in his hometown of Eagle Grove 100 miles
north of Des Moines, where he practiced law.
   Blue was a charter member of the Iowa Commission on the Aging in
1965, and served until 1976.
   He also served on advisory committees on problems of the aging
for five governors, on the National Planning Board of the White
House Conference on Aging and on the National Advisory Council of
the Office of Economic Opportunity.
   As governor he pushed through a retirement pension for public
employees, and the inspection and licensing of nursing and
retirement homes.
   Speaking on the loneliness felt by the elderly, Blue once said,
``It isn't the salt and pepper that gives taste to food, it's the
company.''
   ``He made a difference for Iowa, and we are proud to have had
the benefit of his service,'' Gov. Terry Branstad said Friday.
   Blue is survived by his wife, Cathlene; a daughter; five
grandchildren and two great-grandchildren.
   Services were scheduled for Monday afternoon at the United
Methodist Church in Eagle Grove.
</TEXT>

</DOC>