<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0258EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Catastrophic-Refunds     12-20 0497</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Catastrophic-Refunds,500</SECOND>
<HEAD>Social Security Pushing for Faster Catastrophic Refunds</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NANCY BENAC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Social Security Commissioner Gwendolyn King is
supporting a plan under which the government early next year would
mail monthly refunds to millions of elderly people overcharged for
Medicare premiums.
   If the plan goes through, Social Security beneficiaries who
unavoidably will be overcharged by about $5.30 a month for their
Medicare coverage early in 1990 will be simultaneously issued
monthly refund checks.
   The overcharges are the result of Congress' late action in
repealing Medicare's catastrophic health-care program. Social
Security contends its computers can't be adjusted by January to
halt withholding of the extra Medicare premium for catastrophic
coverage.
   As a result, nearly 27 million Social Security beneficiaries who
have Medicare premiums deducted directly from their benefit checks
are expected to be overcharged from January through May.
   Social Security Commissioner Gwendolyn King said Tuesday a panel
of experts convened by the agency to study the problem suggested
issuing monthly or bimonthly refund checks to offset the
overcharges, or sending out lump-sum refunds late in the spring.
   Mrs. King said the Treasury Department, which actually issues
Social Security checks, reported that lump-sum refunds were the
most feasible option and that monthly refund checks would be ``much
worse than the other two scenarios.''
   However, Mrs. King said Treasury did not expressly rule out the
possibility of mailing monthly refunds, so she will ``send back a
signal that that would be our preferred option.'' She said she
would ask Treasury to advise her on whether it can provide monthly
checks.
   ``That option ... appears to be the best way to get money back
as quickly as possible,'' Mrs. King said in an interview. ``My
purpose has been to try to make the beneficiaries whole. They
should not have to pay for this problem. The question is how can we
get them this money.''
   Andy Montgomery, a spokesman for Treasury's Bureau of Financial
Management Services, said the agency has been meeting with Social
Security ``to identify the most expeditious way to achieve the
refunds. At this particular point, nothing has been decided.''
   Social Security initially had said it probably would issue the
refunds in lump sums late in the spring. Mrs. King's statement that
she would push for monthly refunds came on the same day that two
congressmen sent President Bush a letter asking him to support that
option.
   Reps. David Bonior, D-Mich., and Robert Wise, D-W.Va., said
retirees should not have to pay _ even temporarily _ for a program
that won't exist next year.
   ``For seniors, this isn't just a matter of principle _ it's a
matter of meeting rent payments, buying food and paying
utilities,'' Bonior said.
   Bonior said the General Accounting Office estimated the cost of
issuing monthly refunds at $25 million to $30 million, and said the
first refund checks could be in the mail by February.
   Mrs. King said each extra monthly mailing would cost about $10
million.
</TEXT>

</DOC>