<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0103 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1520EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-People     12-21 0940</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0979</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LAKELAND, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A sometimes sobbing Tammy Faye Bakker told
a church congregation of her life without Jim Bakker and how she's
hired an appeals lawyer to get her husband out of prison.
   ``Our lawyer felt we have a 77 percent chance, praise the
Lord,'' Mrs. Bakker said to thunderous applause at the Carpenter's
Home Church on Wednesday.
   Bakker is in a Rochester, Minn., federal prison serving a
45-year sentence for defrauding investors of the PTL Ministry,
which he founded.
   Mrs. Bakker defended her husband, saying he is incapable of
defrauding anybody.
   ``Jim walks in his own steps,'' she said. ``He doesn't walk in
the judge's steps. He doesn't walk in the government's steps. Who
are we to say his steps were not supposed to walk through prison?''
   The Rev. Karl Strader said he invited Mrs. Bakker to speak after
she came to the church Sunday to see a play. He said the invitation
was his way of showing friendship to the Bakkers during the
holidays and help her financially.
   The church did not compensate Mrs. Bakker, but a collection was
taken after her talk to pay for airfare for her and her son to
travel to the Minnesota prison during Christmas.
   The Bakkers' New Covenant church set up following the PTL
scandals has been moving from storefront to storefront in Orlando
because of financial problems.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor Arnold Schwarzenegger accepted substantial
undisclosed libel damages Thursday for an untrue story in a tabloid
that claimed he held ``fervent Nazi and anti-Semitic views.''
   Schwarzenegger's lawyer, James Price, told the High Court it was
now accepted by News Group Newspapers Ltd., publishers of the News
of the World, and journalist Sharon Ring, that there was no truth
in any of the allegations.
   The Feb. 21, 1988, editions of the Sunday paper also alleged
that Schwarzenegger, a native of Austria, was a ``secret admirer of
Adolf Hitler.''
   Robert Clinton, the paper's lawyer, said his clients deeply
regretted the damage and distress caused.
   ``My clients accept that Mr. Schwarzenegger has never espoused
Nazi and anti-Semitic views and has never been an admirer of Adolf
Hitler and what he and his evil regime represent,'' he said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>HOLLYWOOD, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tiny Tim appeared before the city
commission and tiptoed his way through an endorsement of a
sculptor's effort to live in a storefront studio.
   Local artists figured the 1960s celebrity could help sculptor
Darien Bogart persuade city commissioners Wednesday to let Bogart
live in a downtown studio.
   Tiny Tim, who is in town for club performances, was glad to
oblige. He even stopped to serenade passers-by plucking his ukulele
on the steps of City Hall.
   But as Tiny Tim stood before the City Commission, dressed in a
multicolored coat and a red, white and blue striped tie, his
support of Bogart wavered.
   ``I'm supportive with a lot of ifs,'' Tiny Tim said.
   It might be all right if Bogart kept the place clean and didn't
bother neighboring businesses, he said.
   But later: ``I can't see him living in a store that is on a main
thoroughfare. The danger there also is that others may follow suit.
To make it a thing to spread, right now it appears to be out of
taste.''
   Commissioners decided to research the issue and reconsider it in
February.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Singer Glen Campbell has come to the aid of a
5{-month-old boy whose doctors say will die unless he gets a liver
transplant.
   Charles and Jule Tenuta of Phoenix are trying to get their son,
Tommie, on a waiting list at the University of Chicago Medical
Center. But they don't have the required $100,000 down payment.
About $32,000 has been raised.
   Campbell, a Phoenix resident, announced Wednesday that he will
hold a benefit concert Jan. 9 at a nightclub and that the proceeds
would go toward paying for Tommie's transplant.
   ``You can raise money for a lot of things, and this little baby
comes up and he does need a liver transplant,'' Campbell said
Wednesday.
   Tommie's doctor, Dennis Shermeta, said the University of Chicago
Medical Center offers alternatives not available in Arizona. The
Chicago hospital recently performed the nation's first two living
donor liver transplant operations.
   Mrs. Tenuta said she would be willing to donate part of her
liver, but that the first order of business is to move to Chicago
with her son.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CUMMING, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Six of the seven O'Kelley brothers _ who
fought to remain together after their mother died, their father
abandoned them and their home burned down _ held a reunion on the
set where their story is being filmed.
   During an interview Wednesday with the television show,
``Entertainment Tonight,'' the brothers were asked how the movie
will affect them.
   ``We'll get some publicity, but in a couple of months it will be
back to normal,'' said Michael, 15.
   After news of their family disaster put the rural Gainesville
brothers in the spotlight in 1986 and 1987, they received more than
$200,000 in cash and gifts and a contract for the
made-for-television movie, ``Fire in the Heart.''
   A contractor also built them a four-bedroom house on the
7.5-acre farm where they had lived in a trailer.
   The attention also led to their separation, they said.
   Last year, Terry O'Kelley, now 22, relinquished custody of his
four younger brothers, saying tensions between the siblings made it
impossible for him to continue as a single parent.
   The film stars actor Rick Schroder as Terry, who was at his
mother's deathbed when she asked him to keep the boys together.
</TEXT>

</DOC>