<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0237 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1815EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Campeau-Lenders     12-19 0475</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Campeau-Lenders,0489</SECOND>
<HEAD>Campeau Trying to Reassure Lenders</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CINCINNATI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Campeau Corp., struggling under a
multibillion-dollar debt, says it hopes to reassure lenders who
finance shipments to its department stores that the company's
long-term fiscal health is sound.
   ``We respect the obligations of those with whom we do business
to make financial decisions that they deem to be in their own best
interests. We remain hopeful that we will be able to resolve this
situation favorably, well in advance of spring merchandise
deliveries,'' Carol Sanger, Campeau's vice president of corporate
communications in Cincinnati.
   Federated Department Stores Inc. and Allied Stores Corp., owned
by the Toronto-based Campeau, revealed last week that they are
trying to restructure $7 billion in debt and may need to seek U.S.
Bankruptcy Court protection from creditors while reorganizing their
finances. Campeau Corp. assumed more than $8 billion in debt when
it bought Cincinnati-based Federated in May 1988.
   Officials of CIT Group-Factoring, the New York retail lending
company and subsidiary of Manufacturers Hanover Corp., expressed
concern about the retailers' statements that they could run out of
cash by the end of January, endangering payments due suppliers in
February and beyond.
   ``Until the people who sit in the ivory tower in Toronto make
some decisions and let people know what's going on, we are
reserving a decision about future shipments,'' Francis X. Basile,
president and chief executive, said Monday. ``Hopefully, they will
do something positive to allow us to continue to support their
companies.''
   Last week, Heller Financial, a major lender in Chicago, cut off
credit on shipments to Campeau stores after the retailers'
disclosure last Wednesday.
   The moves could halt early delivery of spring merchandise to
Federated and Allied store divisions, including the
Cincinnati-based Lazarus, Burdine's of Miami and Bloomingdale's of
New York. It is not known how many clients represented by Heller
and CIT still plan to ship spring merchandise to the stores.
   CIT and Heller are ``factoring'' companies _ those that extend
credit to retailers and collect suppliers' bills from retailers _
and have significant influence in the apparel industry. Factoring
companies buy manufacturers' products and assume the risks that
those bills will be paid by retailers.
   Without credit from a factoring company, suppliers assume full
risk for payment on their shipments.
   Federated and Allied told the Securities and Exchange Commission
that store revenues and loans will give them enough cash until
mid-March. But money could run out by late January if suppliers
demand quicker payment on bills and lenders cut off money,
officials said.
   ``January 10 is the magical date,'' Basile said. Payments for
merchandise shipments are made on the 10th day of a month.
   Basile said Campeau's disclosure leads him to conclude the
company can meet payments due Jan. 10, but that payments due Feb.
10 could be in danger if the company runs out of cash.
</TEXT>

</DOC>