<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0191 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1003EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APArts:ChristmasShow Adv22   12-21 0821</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP Arts: Christmas Show, Adv 22,0834</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv 22</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Fri PMs, Dec 22 and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Dressing Toys and Christmas Trees That Sing and Dance</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By THEASA TUOHY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Zip. From Santas in tights to eight
maids-a-milking. Zip. From Ebenezer Scrooge's London to Christmas
in New York.
   And in they step, the high-kicking Rockettes and other
performers, from one costume to the next in a backstage
choreography with the precision timing of their on-stage routines
as Radio City Music Hall puts on its annual Christmas shwo.
   Dressers carrying plastic laundry baskets run with the clothes
dropped by one of the 79 cast members as he switches from the
London of Tiny Tim to the dancing rooftops of New York. Lined up
for each dancer in the production number are his tuxedo pants,
suspenders, fancy dressfront, bow tie and tailcoat in the order in
which they'll be donned. There also are black socks and patent tap
slippers, and a shoehorn beside each pair.
   ``The backstage choreography _ timing and rhythm _ is as
important as the choreography on stage,'' said Bree Daniels, who
has been a dresser for seven years, three at the Music Hall.
   Behind all this kinetic energy is the tiny, trim blonde whose
costumes are constructed, built, sewn, stamped and stretched with
this kind of activity in mind. And she's been doing it for 40 years.
   Leanne Mitchell, director of the Music Hall's mammoth costume
shop, constructs wings for Sugar Plum fairies, dresses Santa's
elves, sews buttons for wooden soldiers, stamps on sequins for
Rockettes, fashions swaddling clothes and drapes the brightly
colored silks of the Three Wise Men.
   Mitchell left her home in Iowa to come to New York and, in 1949,
at the age of 19, she was hired by the Music Hall as a seamstress.
The rest, as they say, is show biz.
   She still remembers her first glimpse, soon after she arrived in
New York, of the enchanted stage where today live camels bow to the
stable-born child, where the precision-dancing Rockettes bring
wooden soldiers to heel, where Christmas trees spring to life. She
even remembers the movie that played: ``A Date With Judy,''
starring Elizabeth Taylor and Jane Powell.
   She still seems slightly titillated by the glamour of it all and
admits she was awed by the girls of the chorus line when she first
joined the staff.
   ``I was their age when I came here,'' she says. Her mother told
her later that at the age of 8 she had written an essay saying that
someday she was going to come to New York and make clothes for the
Rockettes.
   ``They don't want something that doesn't fit them right. We have
to live with those costumes, we have to make them so they'll
last,'' she said drawing a comparison between one-shot shows on
television and the live spectacular on the Music Hall's vast stage
with its 43-foot turntable, 3-ton motorized curtain and 38-piece
orchestra that rises from its pit and moves across the stage. Not
to mention three live camels, and several sheep and donkeys that
bed down in the basement waiting for their stage cues for the
Nativity scene.
   The hard-working Rockettes will do their Christmas show 188
times in the eight weeks of its run through Jan. 3. More than 1
million people are expected to see the show in the cavernous Art
Deco theater that seats 5,874.
   What's changed? Not a lot, except stretch fabrics and punch-in
rhinestones and iron-on sequins. The unforgettable collapse in slow
motion of the line of 36 wooden soldier-Rockettes is pretty much
what audiences of the first Christmas show saw in December 1933.
Variety reported in 1934 that the slow motion had gotten slower.
   Fabrics with added give have made life a lot easier, says
Mitchell, whose work force varies from 6 to 30, depending on the
season. They made the 350 costumes used in the Christmas show, but
her $265,00 budget for this season was only for refurbishing and
making totally new costumes for two numbers out of 12. The
seamstresses are included in the 123 support staff for the 117
actors and musicians.
   Her job is to make clothes that fit the body, move with the body
and reveal as much of it as possible in the case of the
high-stepping Rockettes.
   During the scene preceding ``The 12 Days of Christmas,'' the
women's dressers drop long, puffy-skirted costumes at designated
spots so each Rockette coming off stage in an abbreviated Santa
outfit can strip to her bodysuit and step into a ``12 Days'' dress
almost in a stride. A dresser moves in and zips.
   Actors who switch in a wink from Nutcracker bears who cavort to
Tchaikovsky's ``Waltz of the Flowers'' to dancing Christmas trees
with twinkling lights and green felt arms need fast changes and
freedom to move.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv PM G</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Fri Dec. 22
</TEXT>

</DOC>