<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0112 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1516EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania Bjt   12-18 0851</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania, Bjt,0879</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Reported Killed in Biggest Romanian Protests in Years</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIOREL URMA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The biggest protests in two years were
reported in Romania, where Nicolae Ceausescu runs the Soviet bloc's
last hard-line regime, and a traveler said Monday at least two
people were killed, including a child.
   An unconfirmed report in the West German media said hundreds
were killed.
   Romania virtually sealed its borders, blocking or restricting
travel from neighboring Hungary, Yugoslavia and Bulgaria, and from
other countries, in an apparent effort to curtail reports of the
unrest at Timisoara, western Romania.
   Arriving flights were turned back around at the Bucharest
airport. Bulgarian TV said travelers were held in trains for hours
before being sent back by Romanian border guards.
   In a late evening report, the Yugoslav news agency Tanjug said
Romanian security forces took full control Monday of Timisoara,
just 30 miles from the Yugoslav border. Ceausescu flew to Iran
earlier in the day for a three-day official visit.
   Premier Miklos Nemeth of Hungary said there were unconfirmed
reports of protests in other Romanian cities and of soldiers being
placed on alert.
   A Yugoslav returning from Romania told The Associated Press
police fired on the protesters and at least two people were killed.
   He said other Yugoslav travelers reported seeing more bodies in
Timisoara after security forces dispersed the largest
anti-government protests since a protest by 10,000 workers at
Brasov in 1987.
   In West Germany, William Toetoek, an ethnic German writer who
immigrated from Romania, was interviewed on Bremen radio and quoted
witnesses in Timisoara as saying 300-400 protesters were killed and
hundreds injured.
   None of the reports of high death tolls could be confirmed.
   Bishop Endre Gyulay of the Roman Catholic diocese of Szeged in
Hungary, which includes Timisoara, told the church news agency
Kathpress, based in Vienna, that 30 or 40 people fled across the
border Monday and reported two deaths, of an old woman and a
29-year-old man
   ``Police and troops moved in quickly,'' the Yugoslav traveler
said, but only police were seen firing on were seen shooting at the
demonstrators.
   ``I saw two dead, including a child, on the streets,'' he said.
Other Yugoslav travelers said soldiers were seen three-deep at main
intersections in Timisoara on Sunday. The official Hungarian news
agency MTI quoted a Czechoslovak, not identified, as saying tanks
were in the streets.
   Resentment has grown against Ceausescu, who has resisted the
liberalization and reform sweeping through Eastern Europe. He has
been Communist Party chief since 1965, and with downfall of other
old guard Communists, has become the longest-serving leader in the
Soviet bloc.
   Ceausescu's crash industrialization program and the domestic
austerity he imposed to repay Romania's $11 billion foreign debt
have caused widespread shortages and food rationing. The pervasive
and feared secret police are the main agency used to keep the
people under control.
   Mihnea Berindei, vice chairman of the Paris-based Romanian
League for Human Rights, said he had reports of police firing on
the demonstrators in Timisoara.
   ``Shots were heard and there were injuries. Ambulances were seen
rushing to and fro,'' he said, quoting witnesses.
   ``There are reports of deaths, but we don't have any figures so
far because the entire area has been virtually isolated ... by the
security forces,'' Berindei said.
   Anti-government protests apparently began after hundreds of
ethnic Hungarians formed a human chain Friday night to prevent the
eviction Friday of the Rev. Laszlo Toekes, a Reformed Church
clergyman who has championed their rights, Berindei said.
   Toekes had been harassed for months by Romanian authorities. He
and his wife, who is pregnant, had remained inside his church since
masked assailants tried to attack him in his neighboring apartment
Nov. 2, Berindei said, again quoting witnesses.
   He said he did not know where Toekes was Monday night.
   Several thousand people, most of them ethnic Romanian students
and workers, protested in downtown Timisoara on Saturday and
briefly occupied the Communist Party headquarters, breaking windows
and smashing furniture, Berindei said.
   They also broke windows of bookstores, and burned the works of
Ceausescu, whose books are prominently displayed, he said.
   Protest continued Sunday, then police and army units intervened
and shots were fired, Berindei said.
   Other unrest preceded the weekend protests, Berindei said,
including a strike Dec. 8 at a truck plant in Brasov, north of
Bucharest, and a student protest before that at hostels in
Bucharest.
   In apparent response to the student action, Ceausescu ordered
Dec. 5 that their monthly stipends be increased by 10 percent, or
about $5 a month.
   Official media did not mention the weekend unrest, devoting
themselves instead to Ceausescu's visit to Iran.
   Emigres said Bucharest radio warned citizens on Sunday to remain
orderly or face serious consequences, which in Romania can include
long jail sentences or forced labor.
   Western diplomats reached by telephone Monday in Bucharest said
the capital appeared calm but the international airport was heavily
guarded.
   Thousands of Yugoslavs normally cross each day to Timisoara to
sell goods to Romanians, but a Yugoslav customs official said the
borders were sealed to all but official traffic.
</TEXT>

</DOC>