<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0165 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2259EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Panama 2ndLd-Writethru a0703 12-19 0754</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Panama, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0703,730</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Soldier Shot Panamanian With Unauthorized Weapon, Pentagon Says</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS grafs 4-5: ``In Panama,'' with report of planes arriving
in Panama</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSANNE M. SCHAFER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Military Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A U.S. soldier used an unauthorized weapon
when he shot a Panamanian police officer Monday, the Pentagon's
spokesman said Tuesday, calling the incident ``very regrettable''
but saying it had to be considered in the context of a
deteriorating situation.
   ``What you have is a very difficult atmosphere in Panama right
now. It's very tense,'' spokesman Pete Williams told reporters.
   He said people there are afraid for their lives amid the tension
that has followed two shooting incidents in recent days.
   In Panama, according to NBC News, C-141 transports landed at
Howard Air Base at 10-minute intervals throughout the afternoon.
These planes are the kind used to carry paratroopers in what the
Army said was a readiness exercise for elements of the 82 Airborne
Division at Fort Bragg, N.C., though it could not be determined
whether the planes in fact came from Fort Bragg.
   A reporter driving through the base Tuesday evening saw at least
10 large transport planes of an undetermined type, an unusually
large number, and six to eight helicopters instead of the usual
three or four.
   At the Pentagon, Williams said that although the Army lieutenant
was in an authorized area at the time of the shooting, he was in
civilian clothes and was carrying a sidearm.
   Asked if the officer had been authorized to do so, Williams
answered: ``I don't believe he was authorized to have a weapon.''
   The spokesman said the officer was still being questioned about
the incident, and he added, ``You have to go back to the climate in
which it happened.''
   The lieutenant ``says the Panamanian reached for a weapon,'' the
spokesman said.
   At the time, U.S. forces were on alert following the fatal
Saturday shooting of Marine 1st Lt. Robert Paz, 25, of Dallas, and
the reported beating of a Navy couple who U.S. officials say
witnessed the shooting.
   President Bush has refused to rule out military action against
the government of Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega in response to the
Saturday shooting.
   Williams, who said the Army lieutenant was still in Panama,
blamed the incident in part on Noriega's Friday declaration of a
``state of war'' with the United States.
   ``People fear for their lives in Panama right now,'' Williams
said.
   At the State Department, spokeswoman Margaret Tutwiler said
Noriega's irresponsible declaration of a state of war last week was
followed only hours later by ``indiscriminate and unprovoked
violence against Americans clearly increases tensions in Panama.
   ``We find the unwarranted use of violence against Americans by
the Noriega regime unacceptable,'' she said.
   Williams said that U.S. forces in Panama ``are ever-vigilant.
They are acutely aware of the events that are taking place around
them.''
   He said U.S. officials are ``proceeding with caution'' as the go
about their duties, but he added: ``We remain concerned about the
situation in Panama, it appears to be deteriorating.''
   When asked about reports of preparations among the 18th Airborne
Corps, the spokesman said the unit ``periodically conducts
emergency readiness deployment exercises to evaluate the readiness
of its units. ... Currently, elements of the 18th Airborne Corps
are conducting emergency deployment readiness exercises.''
   On Capitol Hill, Sen. Richard Lugar, R-Ind., called on Bush to
issue an ultimatum to Noriega, telling him that continued
anti-American agitation will not be tolerated.
   ``Noriega appears to be testing the parameters of American
tolerance,'' said Lugar, a senior Republican member of the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee. ``We need to avoid the appearance of
acquiescence that might embolden Noriega and lead to future
American and Panamanian casualties.''
   ``There are measured options, military and otherwise, that would
inconvenience Noriega and they ought to be considered promptly in
the wake of unacceptable activities of the Panamanian defense
forces,'' Lugar said.
   Sen. Christopher Dodd, D-Conn, the chairman of the Senate
Foreign Relations subcommittee on Western Hemisphere affairs, said
on NBC-TV that Bush was correct in avoiding talking about a
possible military response to Noriega.
   ``I think the president's handling that question appropriately.
... To not say exactly what you're going to do is probably the
right thing to do,'' Dodd said.
   The senator said that if the lives of U.S. citizens in Panama
are jeopardized, or if the canal were threatened, those two
situations ``would be two at least broad areas that would ...
warrant at least further consideration of direct military
intervention.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>