<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0261 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1144EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-BoardofTrade Open   12-18 0301</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Board of Trade, Open,0314</SECOND>
<HEAD>Grain Futures Slip In Early Trading</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The soybean market led grain futures prices lower
in early trading today on the Chicago Board of Trade following
reports of weekend rain in southern Brazil, a leading soybean
producer.
   The weather has been dry in the early Brazilian growing season,
raising fear of drought.
   Some of this morning's selling also reflected profit-taking
after last week's modest gains in the soybean and wheat markets.
   Weaker outside markets _ particularly a sharp early drop in gold
prices _ set a bearish tone across the grain-trading floor.
   Sub-zero temperatures in the nation's midsection helped support
the wheat and soybean markets last week. Temperatures have warmed
up slightly but are expected to plunge again before the weekend.
   Trading activity is likely to drop through the week, though, as
traders begin their holiday weekends.
   In early trading, wheat futures were unchanged to { cent lower
with the contract for delivery in December at $4.12} a bushel; corn
futures were \ cent to } cent lower with December at $2.35 a
bushel; oat futures were unchanged to \ cent lower with March at
$1.55\ a bushel; soybeans were 3\ cents lower to { cent higher with
January at $5.80 a bushel.
   Livestock and meat futures were mostly higher in early trading
on the Chicago Mercantile Exchange.
   Live cattle were .03 cent lower to .20 cent higher with December
at 78.12 cents a pound; feeder cattle were .18 cent to .43 cent
higher with January at 84.50 cents a pound; live hogs were .20 cent
lower to .40 cent higher with December at 53.30 cents a pound;
frozen pork bellies were .38 cent to .70 cent higher with February
at 51.90 cents a pound.
   Livestock and meat futures settled higher on Friday.
</TEXT>

</DOC>