<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1413EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Immigration Bjt   12-23 1055</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Immigration, Bjt,980</SECOND>
<HEAD>Immigration Reforms Said Falling Short, Causing Underclass</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JENNIFER DIXON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   WASHINGTON _ Immigration reform has freed more than 3 million
American residents from the label ``illegal alien,'' but Hispanic
activists say reform also has helped create a huge underclass ripe
for discrimination and exploitation by unscrupulous employers.
   The Immigration Reform and Control Act of late 1986 was supposed
to allow illegal aliens to enter the mainstream of American life
while also stemming the rising tide of illegal immigration across
the nation's southern border.
   Critics say the landmark legislation has only partially
succeeded in slowing the influx of aliens and has done little to
improve the lives of many alreading living here.
   Congress and the administration, these critics say, also have
turned their backs on a host of new problems.
   ``The '80s was a period of great promise that was never met; a
great promise that failed,'' said Dan Stein, executive director of
the Federation for American Immigration Reform. ``Americans looked
down the barrel of huge increases in immigration and failed to take
the steps needed to fix the system.''
   Hispanic rights organizations said the legislation, which bars
employers from hiring undocumented aliens, has created an
underclass of people desperate for jobs but vulnerable to employers
who pay subminimum wages and require workers to perform hazardous
tasks.
   At the same time, significant numbers of employers wary about
sanctions for breaking the new law are discriminating against
foreign-born or foreign-sounding job applicants, the activists
claim.
   And Congress and the administration have yet to make good on
their promise to increase the ranks of the Border Patrol by 50
percent. Before the bill's enactment there were 3,700 Border Patrol
agents; today there are 3,800 on duty, according to the Immigration
and Naturalization Service.
   The Border Patrol also has been thrown into the war on drugs and
other missions that divert its attention from patrolling the
border, said Rep. Bruce Morrison, D-Conn., chairman of the House
Judiciary subcommittee on immigration, refugees and international
law.
   ``It was, overall, an enforcement failure,'' Stein said. ``The
INS and the Border Patrol have known what needs to be done yet the
administration has never put pressure on Congress to give us a
respectable level of border funding.''
   The reforms, however, appear to have succeeded _ at least
initially _ in slowing the number of aliens crossing the Southwest
border illegally.
   Apprehensions of these illegal aliens _ considered the best
indicator of illegal immigration _ fell from 1.6 million in the
year before the bill's passage to 854,939 in fiscal 1989.
Apprehensions, however, have begun creeping up again, officials say.
   The bill also has succeeded in touching the lives of 3.1 million
people who were in the country illegally prior to its passage, but
who are now eligible to become citizens through its amnesty
provisions.
   ``One in every 100 residents (of the country) has been
touched,'' said Michael Fix, a senior research associate at the
Urban Institute, a Washington think tank. ``The scale is stunning
and the kind of money spent and the impact on society over the long
run is just stunning. This is a one-time program of the size of the
war on poverty _ a big social deal and I don't think the dimensions
are really appreciated.''
   But activists say the amnesty provisions split families, with
one spouse allowed to remain here legally and another unqualified
to apply for residency. Immigration reformers complain that
Congress failed to prepare for the clamor of relatives who surely
will follow.
   ``The failure to reform legal immigration (which favors
legalization of family members of new residents) will mean
unprecedented political pressure to admit millions more immigrants
when there's not general public support for it,'' Stein said.
   But Mario Moreno, director of the Washington office of the
Mexican American Legal Defense and Educational Fund, said Congress
could have helped far more people achieve residency through more
liberal amnesty standards.
   At the same time, those who don't qualify are ``outside the loop
of any sort of safety net,'' he said. ``There have been reports of
people being taken advantage of, of being exploited.''
   Some have taken such hazardous jobs as improperly managed
asbestos removal or working with toxic wastes, Moreno said.
   Jose Garcia De Lara, national president of the League of United
Latin American Citizens, said he has heard of illegal aliens doing
hazardous construction or agricultural work, or being forced into
crime.
   ``They're certainly an unprotected people,'' he said, and as
long as there is political and economic turmoil to the south of the
Rio Grande, Mexicans, Central and South Americans will continue to
try to enter the country illegally.
   ``Congress passed the bill and turned its back,'' De Lara said.
``Congress should roll up its sleeves and do a major overhaul of
IRCA and include an initiative to help the countries south of our
border.''
   Added Moreno: ``The unabated flow of aliens is not going to be
stopped by employer sanctions.''
   Activists complain those sanctions, however, are responsible for
employer discrimination against foreign-looking and
foreign-sounding job seekers.
   ``It's a very real, powerful problem,'' said Fix. ``While it may
be IRCA related, it's not just an IRCA problem. A lot of
discrimination predated IRCA.''
   De Lara said the Office of Special Counsel within the Justice
Department has done ``almost nil'' to enforce the law's
anti-discrimination provisions.
   Rep. John Bryant, D-Texas, a member of the immigration
subcommittee, agreed the administration has ``refused to take
seriously the obligation to enforce the anti-discrimination
provisions in the bill. They don't have the people to enforce it.''
   But Rep. Lamar Smith of Texas, the ranking Republican on the
immigration panel, said he's seen little evidence of discrimination.
   ``There have only been a dozen or so proven cases of
discrimination because of employer sanctions and this despite the
fact that a number of organizations have spent a lot of time trying
to come up with examples of discrimination,'' said Smith.
   INS spokesman Verne Jervis also said discrimination does not
appear to be severe.
   Enforcement of employer sanctions, however, has fallen short in
Smith's view.
   ``Until we vigorously enforce employer sanctions, we are not
going to significantly stem the flood of illegal aliens entering
the United States. I'm hoping we will see more enforcement, and the
imposition of more penalties, in the future,'' Smith said.
   C
</TEXT>

</DOC>