<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1119EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DrunkenDriving Bjt   12-30 0845</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Drunken Driving, Bjt,0867</SECOND>
<HEAD>Health Officials Hope For More Responsible Drivers</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Sharri is cq in 23rd graf.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JONATHAN YENKIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   From Harvard to the Hard Rock Cafe to Hollywood,
people concerned about highway carnage on New Year's are promoting
the designated driver. Researchers say the idea is catching on, but
habits do not change easily.
   ``We are helping reduce the number of highly intoxicated drivers
on the road,'' said Micky Sadoff, national president of Mothers
Against Drunk Driving. ``But we're not going out of business,
sadly.''
   Using 1988 figures, federal officials at the Centers for Disease
Control in Atlanta estimate that by the end of the holiday period
stretching from Dec. 21 to Jan. 2, 885 people will have died in
alcohol-related crashes.
   On New Year's Day, the researchers calculated, 58 percent of
traffic deaths involved drinking, compared with 39 percent
year-round.
   One death described by police as alcohol-related did get wide
attention last week: that of New York Yankees' famed player and
five-time manager Billy Martin, who died at 61 in a Christmas Day
crash near his home in upstate New York while riding in a pickup
truck driven by a friend. But in most cases, the public takes
little note of such deaths, experts say.
   ``We've become accustomed to a large background level of
carnage,'' said Terence Chorba, an epidemiologist who wrote the CDC
report.
   Chorba noted that the number of alcohol-related traffic deaths
in the holiday season are the equivalent of several airliners
crashing.
   But in traffic fatalities, ``one person dies here, one there,''
he said. ``It isn't perceived by the public to have the same type
of epidemic proportions.''
   The National Highway Traffic Safety Administration reports that
traffic fatalities related to alcohol have declined the past
several years, both in actual numbers and as a percentage of total
highway deaths.
   Last year, an estimated 18,502 people were killed in
alcohol-related crashes, or just under 40 percent of all traffic
deaths. In 1982, 20,360 people died in alcohol-related crashes, or
46 percent of all highway deaths.
   To further the shift in drivers' habits, the Harvard School of
Public Health has focused its efforts the past couple of years to
promote designated driver programs around the country.
   For example, Harvard has persuaded television networks and
Hollywood studios to use dialogue in which characters who have been
drinking let someone else do the driving.
   ``Cheers'' and ``Family Ties'' were among the popular television
shows depicting designated drivers last season, including Alex
Keaton, the brash young ``Family Ties'' character played by Michael
J. Fox. ``Growing Pains'' scriptwriters had a character seriously
injured in an alcohol-related accident.
   At the beginning of last year's television season in September
1988, a Gallup poll conducted for Harvard found that 62 percent of
respondents said they regularly appoint a designated driver when
drinking with friends. A follow-up poll at the end of the season in
June showed the figure climbing to 72 percent.
   ``I don't take those numbers literally,'' said Jay Winsten,
assistant dean at the Harvard School of Public Health. ``I think
it's strongly biased by respondents who want to give the socially
acceptable answer. But there's been a shift in public perception of
what a socially acceptable answer is.''
   Winsten says tough talk is still needed to combat drunken
driving.
   ``It needs to be viewed by the public as a major source of
violent crime,'' he said. ``Until it is viewed by the public that
way, we're not going to solve the problem.''
   A Roper poll published in July found 89 percent of respondents
saying the designated driver is a good or excellent way to cope
with drunken driving. That was the highest level of support among
several options, such as running public service advertisements,
using random police roadblocks and holding servers legally
responsible.
   Some businesses have encouraged use of designated drivers during
the holiday season.
   Crum &amp; Forster Insurance Group in Basking Ridge, N.J., sent
``designated driver'' cards before Thanksgiving to its 2,200
employees, entitling them to a free non-alcoholic drink at a
participating restaurant.
   In California, where a new law in 1990 lowers the threshold at
which a person is legally drunk, some 100 Marin County restaurants
and bars have agreed to serve free coffee and soft drinks to
designated drivers. Even video shops are offering free tape rentals
to sober drivers.
    In Boston, the Hard Rock Cafe is sponsoring a contest from New
Year's Eve until St. Patrick's Day, in which patrons will be
encouraged to designate a driver. The driver will receive free
non-alcholic drinks, and when the contest ends one of them will be
chosen at random to receive two free tickets to London.
   ``We're not discouraging drinking,'' said Sharri Miller,
secretary at the restaurant. ``We're offering a safe alternative
home.''
   Winsten said some groups, such as young men who go out drinking
together, are the toughest to influence even though they represent
one of the highest risk groups.
   ``You're not going to change them without a cop with a billy
club,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>