<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 1200EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Revolution Bjt   12-31 0894</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Revolution, Bjt,0916</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romania's Revolution Makeshift, Born of Terror</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALISON SMALE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Despair created the swiftest
revolution in the remarkable year that rid six East European
countries of Stalinism. What took years in Poland, months in
Hungary, and weeks in East Germany, Bulgaria, and Czechoslovakia
was accomplished in a few days in Romania.
   But the country's new provisional leaders face the most complex
task of any Eastern Europeans, improvising a democratic government
from the ground up after inheriting the remnants of a totalitarian
system.
   The revolt first stirred Dec. 15 in the western city of
Timisoara, when hundreds overcame the fear of Nicolae Ceausescu's
regime to defend an ethnic Hungarian pastor who had battled for
religious and human rights.
   Inspired young workers and students took to the streets of
Timisoara to cry for bread and freedom. Their massacre, reported to
Romanians by Radio Free Europe, their lifeline to each other and to
the outside world, stirred the rest of the country and sparked
unrest in several cities.
   The revolution reached the vital center of the country,
Bucharest, after Ceausescu returned Dec. 20 from a three-day visit
to Iran. He branded the Timisoara demonstrators ``hooligans'' and
organized a rally to support his views.
   ``It was when he called Romanians terrorists and hooligans that
it was enough,'' said Bogdan Lazaroae, a 21-year-old Bucharest
student. ``We work hard for him to build his golden palaces, and he
calls us terrorists.''
   Students turned the pro-Ceausescu rally into an anti-Ceausescu
protest, then held out for hours against security forces who shot
at them. By the morning of Dec. 22, workers had joined the
students, and crowds swarmed over the tanks sent to mow them down.
The army _ long held down by Ceausescu and used for farming and
construction rather than fighting _ switched sides.
   Ceausescu and his wife, Elena, fled their capital Dec. 22 as the
first waves of spontaneous joy and exultation crackled through
radio and television, by then in the hands of revolutionaries.
   Ion Iliescu _ who is now president _ and other revolutionary
leaders were summoned to the radio and television stations by the
demonstrators.
   Once on the air, Iliescu summoned all Romanians who wanted to
restore the country to attend a 5 p.m. meeting at Communist Party
headquarters.
   There, men and women who had objected to Ceausescu's rule but
were kept apart for months or years by watchful security agents met
other. New voices, like Petre Roman, emerged. Roman is now the
premier.
   Members of the makeshift government were forced to move around
in armored cars and shift headquarters by day. The population that
rejoiced at Ceausescu's downfall _ and with it the end of Communism
_ became fearful the old system could return and afraid that
Ceausescu's inheritors, many of them ex-Communists, would not
embrace real democracy.
   Free elections are promised for April, a schedule that seems
impossibly hasty in a country where there have been no politics for
more than 20 years.
   Conservative parties banned after the Communist takeover in 1947
are beginning to emerge, but, in a country where communications are
poor and radio and television are the only media reaching
nationwide, it is uncertain how much national impact they can have
by April.
   The governing National Salvation Committee said it is not a
party and therefore not a contender in the elections.
   While adopting some of the language of democracy _ separating
its powers, for instance, from those of the government _ the
committee and Iliescu have taken enormous power into their hands.
   Acting as an ad hoc legislature, they have repealed Ceausescu's
most hated laws, opened the borders for Romanians to travel,
appointed ministers and taken over the state-run media. Iliescu and
his defense minister, Gen. Nicolae Militaru, command the 180,000
army troops, and have already _ without explaining why _ sacked a
general who helped them during the revolt.
   The declaratory nature of their decrees rings old-style
Communist, even if the content is liberal, revealing how hard it
will be to overcome the stylistic remnants of Ceausescu's rule.
   Dealing with the economy will pose more enormous problems for
the new government.
   Pursuing a vision of a Greater Romania, Ceausescu burdened his
traditionally agricultural nation with industries it did not need
and could not run.
   He polluted the land, air and water with his grandiose projects
and destroyed the national heritage in cities and towns forced to
don the mask of his dreams for the proletariat _ towering apartment
blocks that looked modern but hid communal bathrooms and crumbling
walls.
   Nothing can reconstruct the thousands of old homes and 22
churches that disappeared so Ceausescu could build the Palace of
the Republic and Boulevard of the Victory of Socialism in central
Bucharest.
   His self-aggrandizing visions did give Bucharest a useful, and
efficient subway system. He also apparently managed to pay off the
foreign debt he ran up for his own glory _ by exporting the food
his people needed.
   Western diplomats in Bucharest see the lack of debt as one
potential asset as Romania's new leaders try to rebuild the nation.
   Other assets are Romania's oilfields and its scenic tourist
attractions. Romanians also have a flair for business and have
managed to salvage their peasant traditions on the land that should
be able to feed them in abundance.
</TEXT>

</DOC>