<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1110EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u e PM-APonTV-Zorro 1stLd-Writethru Adv29 12-29 0737</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP on TV-Zorro, 1st Ld-Writethru, Adv 29, b0182,0752</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv29</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Friday PMs, Dec. 29, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Zorro Rides Again</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS `Elsewhere in Television' item, to CORRECT air time of
`Stalin's Ghost,' to 10 a.m., sted p.m.; story moved Dec. 27 in advance</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAY SHARBUTT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Television Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When the New Year arrives, so will a gallant
masked figure from the past of old Spanish California. With sword
flashing, black cape billowing, white teeth gleaming, here comes
... Zorro?
   Yes, by neddies. Zorro. With a Z. It's the latest in a long line
of Zorros that includes the ABC series of 1957-59 that set millions
of tykes to running about in Zorro costumes, trying to puncture
each other in the name of justice.
   That one starred Guy Williams. This one, starring Duncan Regehr,
36, is the first new ``Zorro'' series ever on cable, specifically
the Family Channel, where the half-hour series will debut on Jan. 5.
   The show's star, a Canadian with Shakespearean stage credits, is
a very big Zorro. He stands 6 feet 5 inches tall and weighs 215
pounds. Were this a ``Zorro'' of fistics, not fencing, he'd be
right at home.
   This is because Regehr, a soft-spoken man with a dry sense of
humor, regularly used to put his dukes for sport. He once thought
of seeking a spot on Canada's Olympic boxing team. He fought 65
amateur bouts, he says, and had only three losses, none of them by
knockouts.
   It did enter his mind that a flattened nose might be bad for
someone seeking work as the handsome leading man in a work by
Shakespeare. ``That's why it was kind of dumb idea, don't you
think?'' he wryly asks.
   But that was when he was in his late teens, when the notion that
he could get his face rearranged had not quite sunk in: ``No, at
that age I think I was so stupid and cocky that I figured it
wouldn't happen to me.
   ``And fortunately I got out before it did. I hope.''
   Regehr's dossier includes such varied work as ``Hamlet'' at
Ontario's Stratford Shakespeare Festival and the role of the late
Erroll Flynn in CBS' ``My Wicked, Wicked Ways.''
   He shot 25 ``Zorro'' episodes in Spain this fall.
   The new series takes place, as have most `Zorro'' films, in
California in 1820. Regehr has, as have others before him, a
two-role part _ the dandy Don Diego Vega who really is the masked
Senor Zorro who zips about righting wrongs and leaving his
trademark ``Z'' carved in various places.
   George Hamilton played things for laughs _ and with a gay
look-alike brother _ in 1981's ``Zorro, The Gay Blade.'' So did CBS
in 1983 with a contemporary ``Zorro and Son,'' which was the sort
of show in which a Franciscan monk was arrested for ``selling wine
before its time.''
   But in this edition, done in the old romantic tradition, Don
Diego, usually played as a popinjay or even a fop, doesn't get that
treatment from Regehr:
   ``I've played hm more like a Renaissance man, interested in art,
science and music, more bookish rather than being, er, a little
light on the feet.''
   The actor, the son of an artist and a painter himself, has lived
for the past ten years in Los Angeles. But he and his wife,
Catherine, have a New Year's project _ to move to Vancouver Island
in British Columbia.
   He would keep a place in Los Angeles and commute there for film
and TV work, he says. But he no longer wants to call it home. ``I
did sort of like it 10 years ago, when it wasn't as crowded or
smog-filled,'' he says.
   Not now. And he has found that there is such a thing as too much
mellow, of which there is said to be a lot in Hollywood.
   In the old days, Regehr says, ``I could deal with the people
there, the `laid-backness.' Now, I don't know. It just seems too
relaxed to me.''
   __
   Elsewhere in television:
   `STALIN'S GHOST' ON NBC _ On Dec. 31, NBC is airing a one-hour
news special, ``Stalin's Ghost,'' at 10 a.m. EST. It's about the
legacy of death and repression by the late Soviet leader, and the
Stalinists who seek to turn back the reforms and liberalization of
the Gorbachev era.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Fri PMs, Dec. 29</NOTE>

</DOC>