<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0239 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2225EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Panama-Soldiers 1stLd-Writethru a0831 12-20 0770</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Soldiers, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0831,0790</SECOND>
<HEAD>Panama Forces' Loved Ones Wait and Worry Back Home</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 13 grafs to UPDATE with comments from grieving family
angered by invasion, further details, increases number of dead servicemen
to 15, tightens; picks up 13th graf: `At Fort ...</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JONATHAN W. OATIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A Marine killed in Wednesday's U.S. invasion of Panama had been
eager ``to get on with the job they were there to do,'' and
relatives of a slain soldier who remained in the Army despite their
pleas say they are angry.
   ``My own opinion, I think it was stupid,'' said Andriana Perez,
sister of Cpl. Ivan D. Perez, who died during the U.S. strike in
Panama. ``My father is very, very angry. We don't know how we feel
right now.''
   Perez, 22, of Pawtucket, R.I., had been in the Army for four
years, and his sister Adriana said he couldn't have been happier.
   He loved it so much, she said, that when he lost his sight in
one eye last year, the Army offered him an honorable discharge.
   ``He wanted to keep going,'' she said. ``We told him to get out,
he had a chance. He just really enjoyed being there. Ever since he
was a little kid, he wanted to be a soldier.''
   Paratroopers' wives, meanwhile, were told their husbands
wouldn't be home by Christmas.
   ``There was no way to tell when they'd be back,'' said Suzanne
Thornton, one of the military wives who attended a briefing at Fort
Bragg, N.C., home of the Army's 82nd Airborne paratroops.
   A serviceman airlifted out of that Central American country
worried about the family he left behind, and military retirees
cheered the invasion.
   ``If they want help, I'll join them,'' retired Marine William
Little said in Jacksonville, N.C., home of the Marines' Camp
Lejeune.
   Marine Cpl. Garreth C. Isaak, one of 15 servicemen killed in the
operation, had left on a three-month tour of duty in Panama in late
October, his father, Al Isaak, said in a telephone interview from
Greenville, S.C.
   Isaak, a Greenville native based at Camp Lejeune, had been
scheduled to return home in January, and would have turned 23 on
Dec. 28.
   Al Isaak said he spoke to his son about a week ago by telephone.
Two days ago, the family received a letter dated Dec. 10.
   ``He said he was anxious to get on with the job they were there
to do,'' said Bob Jones IV, a friend who read the letter. Jones
said Isaak was referring to U.S. military intervention in Panama.
   At Fort Bragg, military police ordered reporters out of the
area, and the base was closed to the news media until further
notice.
   Barbara Rogers said officials confirmed her husband, Sgt. Buck
Rogers, was involved in the operation, which was no surprise to
her. She said officials gave the wives something of a pep talk.
   ``They told us it's like they were training for a big football
game and this is the football game,'' she said. ``I know that
sounds crazy, but it's true.''
   Mrs. Thornton said it was comforting to hear any news. ``We were
worried, wanting to know something,'' she said. ``This put me at
ease as much as they could.''
   At the USO servicemen's lounge at Charleston International
Airport in South Carolina, an Air Force representative announced
that military charter flights scheduled for early Wednesday,
Thursday and Friday had been canceled, said lounge director Peter
Wells.
   ``We've got a huge amount of people (in the lounge) trying to
get out,'' many waiting for a flight to Panama, Wells said.
   Among those at the lounge was Army Spec. 4 Harry Gilliam of
Alexandria, La. Gilliam said he was worried because he hadn't heard
from his wife, Mirna, who's been in Panama since Saturday.
   He said he, his wife and two stepsons had been in Panama on
leave when he went to an Army post to look for a place to stay. The
Army ordered him to return to the United States, and hustled him
onto a plane before he could tell his family.
   His Panamanian wife and children were staying with his wife's
relatives in Panama City, but he hasn't heard from them since being
flown out.
   ``She needs to check in at a military base, where she needs to
check with the Red Cross,'' Gilliam said, almost in tears. ``I've
checked with the Red Cross here myself, and they said it might
difficult to get in touch with her.''
   He said he planned to stay in Charleston until he hears
something about his family.
</TEXT>

</DOC>