<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0201 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 2047EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama 3rdLd-Writethru a0807 12-22 0847</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0807, a0811,0870</SECOND>
<HEAD>Noriega Loyalists Launch Bold Attack, Assassination Attempt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs to UPDATE with 10,000 weapons found, 2,000
more troops to be sent, color from city, details. Pick up 5th, `The fighting...'
Minor editing thereafter to conform. UPDATES U.S. toll in 16th graf.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PAN1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fighters loyal to Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noriega launched a bold daylight attack Friday on the headquarters
of U.S. military forces and tried to assassinate the vice president
installed by the United States.
   On the third day of the U.S. occupation, Panama City was near
anarchy. Refugees pleaded for food and medicine as waves of looters
ransacked stores.
   U.S. troops searched residential areas of the capital and other
parts of this West Virginia-sized nation for Noriega, but found no
trace of the ousted dictator they were sent in to capture.
   Panamanians seemed to greet the U.S. troops with some
enthusiasm, but many residents of this city, wracked by savage
looting and littered with debris, were too frightened to go out on
the streets.
   Some said they had set up their own defense patrols to protect
themselves and their neighbors amid the chaos, which reigned in
both lower- and middle-class neighborhoods.
   In Washington, Pentagon officials said U.S. troops had seized
10,000 weapons, mostly made in the East bloc, in three separate
caches in the city. Lt. Gen. Tom Kelly, director of operations for
the Joint Chiefs of Staff, called the discoveries ``little short of
astonishing'' and said they led to questions about what Noriega's
plans may have been.
   A Pentagon source said 2,000 more soldiers would be airlifted to
Panama, bolstering the force of 24,000 already there, and President
Bush said the troops would stay ``to do what is necessary.''
   The U.S.-installed first vice president, Ricardo Arias Calderon
was leaving the National Assembly when members of pro-Noriega
``Dignity Battalions'' shot at his car. Arias was uninjured, but
two of his aides were wounded, said Arias aide Teni de Obaldia.
   The fighting around the U.S. Southern Command in Quarry Heights,
on the western edge of Panama City, started about 11:25 a.m. and
lasted an hour, with mortar blasts shaking the U.S. headquarters as
dozens of Noriega supporters attacked buildings nearby.
   Military officials at Rodman Naval Station, just across the
Panama Canal, said they had no information on casualties.
   The Supreme Court, about a mile to the southeast, was in flames,
and sporadic fighting swirled through parts of the chaotic city,
once a major international financial center but now a shell of
itself.
   Only several blocks away from southern command stands the Panama
Canal Commission headquarters. The headquarters itself was not hit,
but surrounding buildings including a warehouse were.
   Plumes of brown and black smoke could be seen from Rodman at
mid-afternoon, and U.S. Army helicopters flew over the area,
apparently searching for the attackers.
   Later Friday, U.S. troops fired shells and threw tear gas at a
residence adjacent to the Spanish news agency EFE where a friend of
Noriega reportedly lived in a wealthy neighborhood.
   Seven EFE journalists darted to the floor during the 20-minute
attack, which shook the office with three loud explosions and could
be seen from The Associated Press office 150 yards away.
   After the assault, neighbors with sledgehammers broke into the
residence and looted the house, which was apparently empty.
   Late Friday, the Pentagon updated its count of soldiers killed
in the assault so far to 21 along with two female dependents. It
said 221 were wounded and two were missing since the invasion
began. An American civilian, CBS News producer Jon Meyersohn, also
was missing after being abducted Wednesday from the Marriott Hotel.
   U.S. officials said 122 Panamanian soldiers were killed and 45
wounded.
   But Dr. Elmer Miranda, deputy director of Santo Tomas Hospital
in Panama City, said there were 200 dead bodies in the basement and
that he heard from a colleague of 60 more in Gorgas Hospital, run
by the U.S. Southern Command.
   Miranda appealed to Latin American nations and Europe to send
medical equipment because ``the United States is only giving us
bullets.''
   Thousands of refugees fleeing the fighting took cover in soccer
stadiums, churches and schools.
   ``They had water, but we're very short of food,'' said a Red
Cross worker who like others refused to give his name for fear of
reprisals.
   He said U.S. Army units were handing out rations but that it was
not enough.
   Noriega supporters in one district said they were running out of
ammunition and hope. Several pro-Noriega bands surrendered in
western Panama on Friday.
   But the dramatic attack on the very center of the U.S. military
area and the effort to kill Arias showed that U.S. efforts to
achieve control were falling short.
   About 200 reporters who arrived at Howard Air Force Base
overnight were not allowed into the city because military officials
said they could not guarantee their security, an indication U.S.
military forces are not in as much control of Panama City as they
have been claiming.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>