<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0273 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1312EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-CenTrust-Paul 1stLd-Writethru   12-20 0456</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-CenTrust-Paul, 1st Ld-Writethru,0471</SECOND>
<HEAD>Florida Comptroller Takes Action To Remove Paul As CenTrust Chairman</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf with 2 grafs of CenTrust comment.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CURT ANDERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TALLAHASSEE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   State Comptroller Gerald Lewis today
began legal action to remove David L. Paul as chairman of CenTrust
Bank of Miami, claiming Paul has used Florida's largest savings and
loan to support his ``opulent lifestyle.''
   Lewis filed an administrative complaint that seeks removal of
Paul as chairman of the thrift. Paul has 21 days to either contest
the complaint through a state hearing or comply with it.
   CenTrust said it would oppose efforts to oust Paul and called
Lewis' action was self-serving.
   ``This campaign is clearly aimed at generating favorable
publicity for the comptroller and supporting his own re-election
campaign whatever the cost to CenTrust, its shareholders and its
customers,'' the company said in a statement.
   The complaint charged that Paul used CenTrust employees to
perform personal services, charged the savings and loan for
thousands of dollars in personal bills and engaged in other
questionable financial transactions.
   ``Paul maintained an opulent lifestyle largely at the expense of
the association, and generally treated a federally insured
financial institution and public company as it if were his own
public piggy bank,'' Lewis said in the complaint.
   Paul's actions were unsound and unsafe business practices that
violated his duty as an officer of a financial institution, the
complaint charged.
   The complaint was filed 11 days after federal regulators, also
citing CenTrust's lavish spending practices, ordered the
institution to stop squandering its assets on fine art, sailboats,
excessive executive salaries and other personal expenses.
   Terence McElroy, spokesman for the comptroller's office, said
the action today was highly unusual.
   ``But it's a fairly unusual institution,'' McElroy said.
   The complaint questioned Paul's $4.8 million in salary between
January 1988 and September of this year during a time when the
thrift suffered operating losses of $76 million before taxes.
   CenTrust also bought some $30 million in art in 1988 without
Lewis' approval, spent thousands of dollars on executives' hotels
bills and used high-prices limousines to ferry the thrift's
officers around Miami, the complaint charged.
   The complaint also noted that $150,000 in CenTrust assets,
including security equipment, video cameras, office supplies,
telephones and air conditioners, were kept at Paul's home on La
Gorce Island in Miami.
   When federal regulators made their charges earlier this month,
Paul issued a statement saying he had turned around a previously
insolvent thrift and reduced its losses.
   ``We have achieved that without one penny of federal assistance
while investing millions of dollars in developing a first-rate
institution with the financial strength in place to meet the need
of our customers,'' Paul said at the time.
</TEXT>

</DOC>