<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0347EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-RetirementHomeFire Bjt   12-26 0566</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Retirement Home Fire, Bjt,0583</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sprinklers Had Been Planned for Retirement Home Where 16 Died</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DUNCAN MANSFIELD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHNSON CITY, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Owners of a high-rise retirement home
where a Christmas Eve fire killed 16 people had planned to install
a sprinkler system in the spring, the manager says.
   ``We didn't feel uncomfortable with the safety of the building.
We just had seen fires, basically on TV and other places. The
comment was made that the sprinkler system would have been a
benefit,'' Grant Trivett of M&amp;M Properties, which manages the John
Sevier Retirement Center, said Monday night.
   Trivett says the John Sevier Partnership, which owns the
11-story building, was going to have sprinklers put in at a cost of
$100,000.
   The 5-decade-old building did have water hoses on each floor and
met the fire code in effect in 1977, when it was converted from a
hotel into apartments for retirees, according to Lt. George
Leonard, fire marshal for this eastern Tennessee city of 40,000.
   He said the current fire code requires sprinklers for buildings
undergoing renovations.
   ``We inherit these buildings,'' Leonard said. ``They're no more
dangerous, it just means they don't meet the present codes ...
Legally they don't have to.''
   The fire broke out Sunday evening on the first or second floor
of the building, where about 145 people lived, and sent thick smoke
billowing through the upper floors. Officials said the deaths
occurred on the upper floors, probably because of smoke inhalation.
About 50 people were injured, including about 15 firefighters.
   The cause of the fire was under investigation, but Leonard said
it appeared accidental.
   In October, a resident of the home died when a kerosene heater,
apparently mistakenly filled with gasoline, ignited his apartment.
   After that fire, Assistant Fire Chief Paul Souder said, he
stepped up pressure on the owners to install sprinklers.
   ``I feel like if a building is sprinkled and if the sprinkler is
working properly then we wouldn't have had life loss,'' said
Leonard.
   Sunday's disaster might have been worse had so many residents
not been away for Christmas, said Mayor P.C. Snapp.
   ``I can't think of a worse time, on Christmas Eve,'' Snapp said.
``On the other hand, it could have been a good time because a
number of people had gone to visit relatives.''
   Fourteen victims lived in the building and the two others were
visiting residents.
   Residents of upper floors waved flashlights and screamed for
help from the windows of their smoke-filled apartments.
   ``We could hear some people over there screaming, `We can't hold
out much longer!' then all at once we didn't hear them anymore,''
said Alex Hambric, whose 77-year-old mother was rescued from her
ninth-floor apartment.
   Up to 250 firefighters fought the blaze, which took about nearly
seven hours to control. Some of them suffered frostbite.
   Most of the injured were treated for smoke inhalation and
released. At least one person was seriously burned, said Dan
Blevins, spokesman for Northside Hospital.
   Ten of 11 residents who had been listed as missing Monday have
been accounted for. The 11th person is believed to have been away
at the time.
   The fire marshal said he didn't know if owners plan to renovate
the building or tear it down. He said it appeared to be
structurally sound.
   Trivett, the building manager, said, ``If it's renovated, it
will be renovated to today's codes.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>