<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0100 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1537EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Nielsens     12-27 0485</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nielsens,0495</SECOND>
<HEAD>1950s `I Love Lucy' Christmas Special in Top 10</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JERRY BUCK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Television Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 33-year-old Christmas episode of ``I Love
Lucy'' made the Top 10 in the Nielsen ratings and was CBS'
highest-rated show for the week ended Dec. 24.
   The show, starring Lucille Ball and Desi Arnaz, was sixth in the
ratings. It was the first telecast of the black and white episode
since Dec. 24, 1956.
   NBC's ``Cheers'' was the top show, ABC's ``Roseanne'' was
second, and to the surprise of no one, NBC was the top-ranked
network overall. CBS pulled its own surprise by finishing second
for the second week in a row. ABC was third.
   Fox Broadcasting's ``Married ... With Children'' plunged to a
tie for 72nd place after the series' Christmas special the week
before was 13th. That was the highest rank achieved so far by a Fox
show.
   It was not a great week for Christmas specials, other than the
demonstration that Lucy can still pull in an audience. CBS'
``Frosty the Snowman'' was 20th, CBS' ``A Very Brady Christmas''
was 21st. CBS' ``Charlie Brown Christmas'' tied for 30th, CBS'
``Claymation Christmas'' tied for 41st, NBC's ``Christmas in
Washington'' tied for 56th, and CBS' ``A Christmas Carol'' tied for
62nd. The latter tied with a rerun of ``Murder, She Wrote,''
usually one of CBS' highest-rated series.
   The ABC movie ``Santa Claus: The Movie'' was 64th and the CBS
telecast of ``The Christmas Gift,'' the pilot movie for ``The
Waltons,'' tied for 65th. ABC's ``Julie Andrews: The Sound of
Christmas,'' tied for 70th, NBC's ``Magical World of Disney: A
Muppet Family Christmas'' was 74th and Fox's ``Simpsons Christmas''
was 75th.
   NBC was first in the A.C. Nielsen Co. survey with an average of
12.8, CBS was second with 11.7 and ABC third with 11.3. The ratings
represent the percentage of the nation's 92.1 million households
tuned to a show.
   For the season to date, NBC leads with 14.8, ABC is second with
13.1 and CBS third with 12.2.
   Here is the Top 10: NBC's ``Cheers,'' ABC's ``Roseanne,'' NBC's
``Dear John,'' NBC's ``The Cosby Show,'' NBC's ``A Different
World,'' CBS' ``I Love Lucy'' Christmas special, ABC's NFL Monday
Night Football _ Philadelphia vs. New Orleans, NBC's ``L.A. Law,''
NBC's ``Heat of the Night'' and CBS' ``Murphy Brown'' tied.
   The American invasion of Panama and the revolution in Romania
made for a big week in news. ABC's ``World News Tonight,'' first
for the 12th week, got its highest rating since the week ended Feb.
3. ABC led with 11.8, CBS was second with 11.0 and NBC was third
with 10.8.
   The lowest-rated show of the week was ABC's ``Life Goes On.''
Here are the five bottom network shows: NBC's ``Alf,'' NBC's
``Magical World of Disney: A Muppet Family Christmas,'' NBC's
``Bill Cosby Salutes Alvin Ailey,'' ABC's ``Free Spirit'' and ABC's
``Life Goes On.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>