<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0824EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-PitBullTrial     12-23 0410</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Pit Bull Trial,0420</SECOND>
<HEAD>Owner Convicted of Manslaughter in Pit Bull Attack</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN JOSE, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A jury found a man guilty of involuntary
manslaughter in his pit bull's killing of a 2-year-old boy in what
the prosecutor said was the first such case.
   The Santa Clara County Superior Court jury on Friday acquitted
Michael Berry, 39, of second-degree murder after a day and a half
of deliberations. Berry had been the first pet owner in the country
charged with murder because of an animal's actions, according to
Deputy District Attorney Dale Sanderson and the Humane Society of
the United States.
   Berry, who could have faced 15 years in prison if convicted of
the murder charge, was also found guilty of owning a mischievous
animal, cultivating marijuana, and keeping a fighting dog.
   Judge James Flaherty set a January sentencing date. Berry could
be sentenced to up to 4 years and 8 months in jail.
   Sanderson told reporters he was satisfied with the verdicts and
that ``I'm glad we ran with the murder charge.''
   Berry was charged in connection with the June 13, 1987, death of
James Soto, his neighbor, who wandered into the Berry yard and was
mauled to death by Berry's 4-year-old pit bull, Willy.
   The dog, which was kept in a locked cell during the trial, was
not as lucky as his master. Willy, according to the county Humane
Society, was to be killed, and was kept alive during the trial only
because he was ``evidence.''
   Berry claimed during the trial that the dead boy's parents
shared blame for the fact that the boy was allowed to get near the
pit bull, which was tethered to a stake in the yard.
   ``What we have is a guy who raises a dog that is bred for
aggressiveness and to be a combatant,'' Sanderson said during
Berry's arraignment. ``And, knowing the dog's propensity, he places
him in an area accessible to all, including children.''
   Sanderson acknowledged that there was no evidence of any actual
malice by Berry or intent by him to kill the Soto boy, but said the
prosecution was based on a theory of implied malice. That, he said,
allowed a murder conviction against someone whose actions showed
wanton disregard for human life.
   The state Court of Appeal agreed that Berry could be tried for
murder.
   During a search of Berry's home, authorities said they found
several publications on illegal dog fighting, and a dog-sized
treadmill.
</TEXT>

</DOC>