<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1555EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-People     12-24 0965</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,1002</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Did it seem like a script for a movie? Former
President Reagan showed up on the Southern Cal practice field for a
pep talk and a short but snappy pass with the Rose Bowl-bound
Trojan squad.
   ``Win one for the Gipper,'' Reagan said, repeating Pat O'Brien's
line from the 1940 film ``Knute Rockne-All American'' in which
Reagan starred as the doomed George Gipp.
   Reagan, wearing blue jeans, a checked shirt open at the collar
and track shoes, spent about 20 minutes Saturday chatting at the
50-yard line with the players.
   Reagan, who was a right guard in college for the Eureka Golden
Tornadoes, has shed his presidential neutrality since leaving
office and is a big Trojans fan, Coach Larry Smith said.
   ``He's in Southern California now, so he's a fan of the Southern
California football team,'' said Smith, whose squad will meet the
Michigan Wolverines in Pasadena for the Jan. 1 Rose Bowl game.
   Reagan was asked to throw a football to USC's top receiver, John
Jackson, who ran about 10 yards and cut to his right.
   ``I think at my age, you better keep it a very short pattern,''
said Reagan, 78, as he cocked and fired a bullet right into
Jackson's grip.
   ``I'll take him,'' Jackson, 22, later said. ``He's got a nice,
tight spiral.''
   Reagan was presented with a large-sized, cardinal and
gold-colored sweatsuit and he slapped ``high-fives'' with the
players and crouched on one knee for a team photo.
   Then he strolled off.
   ``Everybody's familiar with the president, but few get to catch
a pass from him,'' Jackson said. ``I'm going to go call my mom
right now.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>SALT LAKE CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Country-western star Reba McEntire spread
a little Christmas cheer by donating $500 to five local families.
   The gift certificates were delivered Saturday to the five
families by an aide to Gov. Norm Bangerter.
   ``It was a little unusual,'' said Doug Bischoff, deputy chief of
staff. ``But we're glad they called us.''
   McEntire wanted to make sure the money went directly to
individuals, not to institutions, Bischoff said. He said the money
had come to the Nashville, Tenn., singer from Utah fans.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>OAKLAND, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dave Stewart is pitching in to help put
his hometown back on its feet following the October earthquake that
devasted the Bay area and delayed the World Series in which the
Oakland A's pitcher won two games.
   Stewart, the series' most valuable player, has been making
appearances at local business functions to help raise money for
community rebuilding. He also will spend a week next month talking
about the drug problem at area schools, is on the board of
directors of the Oakland Boys Club and frequently speaks for the
Just Say No drug campaign.
   ``I'm born here; I'm raised here,'' he said last week. ``That's
the difference. I wouldn't expect a player born in Mobile, Ala.,
and playing in Oakland to care as much as I do. Part of my
character comes from this city. It's my roots.''
   During the series in which the A's shut out the San Francisco
Giants in four games, Stewart spent his days at the ballpark and
his nights driving to the Oakland freeway that collapsed during the
quake to watch rescuers pull bodies from the wreckage.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Eds: A longer version moved on sports wires.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Some 7,000 fans showed up at a party to say
goodbye to Steve Largent after he played his last game for the
Seattle Seahawks.
   ``I wish I was as neat as you all think I am but I'm not,''
Largent told the capacity crowd at the Washington State Convention
Center.
   Seattle's homeless will benefit from the $70,000 the party
produced, including $5,500 given by Largent's teammates.
   Largent, the Seahawks' record-setting wide receiver, went out in
a losing game Saturday, a 29-0 beating from the Washington Redskins.
   But judging from the tribute, Largent, 35, was anything but a
loser.
   ``You are one of those people who really have made a
difference,'' President Bush told Largent by videotape. ``I offer
my heartfelt thanks not only from the community of Seattle but from
this president.''
   ``Several times when I've watched you, I wanted to shout, `Win
one for the Gipper,''' former President Reagan said in another
videotaped message. ``You are truly a role model for the rest of
us.''
   ``For a guy too slow and too short, you sure fooled a lot of
people,'' Los Angeles Raiders defensive back Mike Haynes said in a
telegram.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sting says the idea that rock 'n' roll music is
rebellious is ``totally dead.''
   ``It has the semblance of rebellion but all these bands with
their long hair, wearing their sister's clothes and playing heavy
metal music, they strike me as being very close to Las Vegas
bands,'' he told Street News, a newspaper sold by the homeless, for
its January edition.
   ``They're not rebellious at all; they're conforming to very
obvious norms and I'm not particularly impressed by that. I just
don't think rock and roll is dangerous at all. It's everywhere, on
all the airwaves day and night. There's nothing new or unusual
about it,'' he said.
   The 38-year-old musician left his band, The Police, after it
became one of the most popular groups.
   Sting says it doesn't always make sense even to him that he is
starring in ``3 Penny Opera,'' a Broadway musical closing at the
end of the year.
   ``From a commercial point of view there's no benefit whatsoever
for anybody. It's just a way of saying, `I want to try something
else,''' he said. ``What I try to do in my life is kind of throw
curves all the time.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>