<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1134EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-JudgeIndicted     12-29 0305</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Judge Indicted,0314</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge Indicted on Charges He Stole About $1.8 Million from Clients</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWPORT, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A former state judge has been indicted on
charges that he stole about $1.8 million from clients of his law
practice, the attorney general's office announced today.
   John Fairbanks was named in four counts in an indictment
returned Thursday, and Sullivan County Superior Court issued a
warrant for Fairbanks' arrest.
   Assistant Attorney General John Davis said Fairbanks'
whereabouts were unknown, but his lawyer was trying to get him to
surrender.
   Fairbanks resigned in June as a judge in Newport District Court
after more than 30 years on the bench, and he also tried to resign
from the state bar. However, the state Supreme Court would not
accept his resignation in order to retain disciplinary
jurisdiction, and instead suspended him from practicing law.
   The indictment alleges that Fairbanks, 66, stole the money
between December 1983 and last April from his private law clients,
from beneficiaries of trusts for which he was trustee and from
heirs of estates for which he was executor, Davis said.
   Each offense is punishment by 7{-to-15 years in prison.
   Fairbanks has refused to reveal his assets or comment on the
case.
   The Attorney General's office has investigated allegations
against Fairbanks for almost a year.
   Four of his former clients filed an involuntary bankruptcy
petition against Fairbanks on Sept. 27, accusing him of ``fraud,
theft, embezzlement or larceny'' of more than $500,000 entrusted to
him in his law practice.
   Four other ex-clients have lawsuits pending, alleging he misused
about $628,000 they entrusted to him.
   Three of his sisters also have accused him of mismanaging the
Bess Fairbanks Trust, named after their mother. They were
beneficiaries of the trust, while Fairbanks served as trustee and
controlled its stock and cash, valued at $500,000 in 1985.
</TEXT>

</DOC>