<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0159 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2235EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Nielsens 1stLd-Writethru a0668 12-19 0454</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nielsens, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0668,0463</SECOND>
<HEAD>ABC's `Roseanne' Beats Out NBC's `Cosby' In Ratings</HEAD>
<BYLINE>Eds: SUBS 11th graf, `Here's the ..., to restore dropped `Golden
Girls.' ^By JERRY BUCK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Television Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two sitcom housewives, ABC's ``Roseanne'' and
Fox's Peg Bundy of ``Married ... With Children,'' stirred up things
in the Nielsen ratings for the week ended Dec. 17.
   ``Roseanne'' pushed NBC's ``The Cosby Show'' out of the top spot
for the first time since Thanksgiving. ``The Cosby Show,'' first
for the last three weeks, was third behind ``Roseanne'' and NBC's
``Cheers.''
   ABC continued its domination of the evening news. Its ``World
News Tonight'' had a rating of 11.0. CBS was second with 10.4 and
NBC was third with 10.2.
   In the season to date, ``Roseanne,'' starring Roseanne Barr, is
slightly ahead of Cosby. Each show has won six times and ``Cheers''
was ahead once.
   ``Married ... With Children'' scored its highest rating ever for
Fox Broadcasting Co. and came within striking distance of the Top
10. Its one-hour Christmas special, with guest star Sam Kinison
joining regulars Katey Sagal and Ed O'Neill, got a rating of 18.4
and ranked 13th.
   The Fox show edged out Bob Hope's Christmas show on NBC and such
favorites as ABC's ``Who's the Boss?'' and ``Coach'' and NBC's ``In
the Heat of the Night'' and ``Matlock.''
   A Fox Christmas special, ``The Simpsons,'' was 30th.
   NBC retained its wide lead for the week and for the season in
the A.C. Nielsen Co. survey. CBS took over second place from ABC,
its first time out of the cellar since the week ending Oct. 22.
Ironically, CBS claimed second place during a week it was without
an entertainment president; Jeff Sagansky's appointment was not
confirmed until Monday.
   NBC won with an average of 14.7 for the week. CBS was second
with 12.6 and ABC was third with 12.3. A ratings point represents
the percentage of the nation's 92.1 million households tuned to a
show.
   For the season to date, NBC leads with 14.9, ABC is second with
13.2 and CBS third at 12.3.
   Here is the Top 10: ABC's ``Roseanne''; NBC's ``Cheers''; NBC's
``The Cosby Show''; NBC's ``Golden Girls''; NBC'a ``A Different
World''; NBC's ``Empty Nest,'' CBS' ``60 Minutes,'' and ABC's
``Wonder Years,'' a three-way tie; NBC's ``Dear John;'' and NBC's
``L.A. Law.''
   CBS' ``Murder, She Wrote,'' which usually is in the Top 10, was
11th for the week.
   The two-hour movie marking the return of CBS' ``Beauty and the
Beast'' was 37th and its first regular episode was 54th.
   The five bottom network shows were ABC's ``Living Dolls,'' CBS'
``Saturday Night with Connie Chung,'' ABC's ``Trans-Antarctica
Expedition,'' ABC's ``Free Spirit,'' and, in last place, ABC's
``Homeroom.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>