<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0135 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1712EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Romania     12-18 0491</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Romania,500</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Protests Romania Crackdown</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM DRINKARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United States is formally protesting
Romania's weekend crackdown on protesters as ``a terribly mistaken
course'' by a government that sees its popular support slipping
away, the State Department said Monday.
   Romanian police opened fire on protesters during weekend
anti-government riots and at least two people, including a child,
were killed, a person traveling in the region said. An unconfirmed
report in the West German media said hundreds were killed.
   State Department spokeswoman Margaret Tutwiler said the violent
clashes were the result of suppression of legitimate dissent by
citizens frustrated with repression and hardships under the regime
of President Nicolae Ceausescu, among the last of the East Bloc's
hard-line communist rulers.
   Ceausescu has forcefully rejected reforms that are sweeping the
rest of Eastern Europe.
   ``Since the government doesn't have the support of the people,
it is following a terribly mistaken course of using security forces
to repress a serious manifestation of popular discontent with the
policies of the Ceausescu regime,'' Ms. Tutwiler told reporters at
the department's daily briefing.
   She said the U.S. ambassador in Bucharest, Alan Green, was
``determining what form our protest will take.''
   Ms. Tutwiler noted that the United States has ``consistently
criticized that regime's repression of dissent and denial of
fundamental human rights to its people.''
   She said the United States was ``especially critical'' of
authorities' use of force against the Rev. Laszlo Toekes, a
Reformed Church minister in Timisoara, in western Romania. The
unrest began Saturday after his congregation sought to protect him
from a court-ordered move to another town, Ms. Tutwiler said.
   ``The demonstration apparently grew in size and took on an
anti-government tone,'' she said. On Sunday, she said, government
security units ``brutally put down the demonstration with the use
of truncheons, tear gas and water cannons.''
   She said she could not confirm reports of casualties or of
gunfire.
   Toekes, an ethnic Hungarian, has championed the rights of other
ethnic Hungarians in the face of what they see as harassment by
Romanian authorities. When the protest began Saturday, he was
seeking to exercise legitimate religious rights, Ms. Tutwiler said.
   The U.S. Embassy has been repeatedly rebuffed in its efforts to
visit and talk with Toekes because of security personnel deployed
around his church and home, she said.
   ``We call upon the Romanian government to cease its pressure
against Rev. Toekes and his congregation and allow him to exercise
his fundamental freedom to communicate,'' Ms. Tutwiler said.
   As to reports that Hungary has sealed its borders in an effort
to prevent news of the unrest from reaching the outside, she said:
   ``Of course it would concern us, and of course as in all the
other countries we are for self-determination of those people. This
is no different in Romania than it has been in any of the other
countries'' where change has occurred in Eastern Europe.
</TEXT>

</DOC>