<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0279 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1954EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-BlinderRobinson     12-18 0284</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Blinder Robinson,0296</SECOND>
<HEAD>SEC Withdraws Appeal in 1983 Case</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DENVER (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Securities and Exchange Commission has
withdrawn an appeal to a federal judge's dismissal of its
6{-year-old civil case against Blinder, Robinson &amp; Co. Inc.,
officials said Monday.
   Tom Carter, SEC regional counsel, said the withdrawal was filed
Dec. 11 in the 10th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals.
   He declined to comment on the reason, but said it had nothing to
do with a separate disciplinary inquiry the SEC has undertaken into
the activities of Blinder, Robinson, a leading penny stock
brokerage.
   Penny stocks are inexpensive shares of startup companies ranging
from biotechnology research labs to energy and mining concerns. The
stocks usually are traded over-the-counter and have been targeted
by federal authorities as a frequent breeding ground for fraud.
   The SEC filed the civil case in April 1983, contending Blinder,
Robinson had failed to keep correct books and records and violated
customer protection regulations.
   In April, U.S. District Judge Lewis T. Babcock dismissed the
case after determining the SEC failed to comply with a court order
and had not acted in good faith.
   The judge also said the SEC could not use documents or testimony
obtained in the 1983 case in court against Blinder, Robinson.
Babcock said his ruling was justified by ``the SEC's egregious
conduct in this case.''
   On Dec. 12, Babcock ordered the SEC to pay Blinder, Robinson
$58,575 in attorney's fees, Carter said.
   In a news release issued Monday, Blinder, Robinson executives
said they are pleased ``that justice has been served by the award
of attorney fees and costs to defendants.''
   Carter said the SEC is considering a possible appeal to the
specific amount of the fees.
</TEXT>

</DOC>