<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1247EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Panama 4thLd-Writethru a0522 12-27 0962</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0522,0991</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Troops Keep Watch As Their Commander Negotiates Noriega's Fate</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 21 grafs to ADD Bush comments, soldiers playing loud
music outside Vatican Embassy. Deletes outdated material. Pickup 23rd,
`The U.S...</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PAN1,2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DOUGLAS GRANT MINE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. soldiers played loud rock music,
mowed the lawn and shot out street lights around the Vatican
Embassy today after hours of curbside diplomacy failed to break a
stalemate over the status of Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   Vatican spokesman Joaquin Navarro said in Italy today there was
no legal way the Holy See could hand over Noriega to U.S.
authorities.
   President Bush said he would not give up efforts to gain custody
of the ousted dictator, who is wanted in the United States on drug
charges.
   The Justice Department, meanwhile, asked authorities in
Switzerland, France, Luxembourg and Britain to freeze bank accounts
in which Noriega is believed to have stashed millions of dollars in
illegal drug profits.
   Before dawn, a company of American soldiers paraded past the
Vatican Embassy, where Noriega sought refuge Christmas Eve, five
days after American troops invaded Panama in an effort to capture
him.
   American troops mowed down a field of tall grass alongside the
embassy overnight and shot out all working street lights with a
pellet gun.
   Later in the morning, some soldiers hooked up small olive-green
speakers in the parking lot of the nearby Holiday Inn and played
David Bowie's ``Modern Love'' album and other rock music at high
volume. The sound easily reached reporters in a 12th-floor room
overlooking the Vatican Embassy.
   Army Lt. Col. Jerry Murguia, a spokesman for the U.S. Southern
Command, said he could not comment on why the troops might have
mowed the lawn and shot out street lights.
   The music appeared to relieve the tedium for some of the
soldiers, who have had to stand in the hot sun for hours wearing
heavy flak jackets.
   On Tuesday, U.S. soldiers searched the Vatican representative,
Monsignor Sebastian Laboa, and his car as he left the embassy,
apparently to prevent Noriega from being spirited out.
   After a week of fighting, order returned to Panama City. Crews
cleared mounds of garbage left from wild looting sprees that
emptied shelves, and many people returned to work.
   The U.S. military reported only scattered clashes with Noriega
loyalists Tuesday. A few members of his Defense Forces were
arrested and many surrendered.
   On the third day of negotiations over Noriega's fate, Gen.
Maxwell Thurman, who commands U.S. forces in Central and South
America, posted himself outside the Vatican Embassy for nearly six
hours Tuesday afternoon.
   He met three times with Laboa in the street and spent the rest
of the time waiting in a car, one of a caravan of sedans, jeeps and
armored personnel carriers that escorted him to the mission.
   Neither Thurman nor other U.S. officials would comment on the
negotiations.
   At the Vatican, Navarro told reporters the Holy See could not
legally give Noriega to U.S. officials because the embassy is
empowered to deal only with the Panamanian government. He said
Panama's U.S.-backed civilian government had not made any request
for Noriega.
   Navarro also said the Vatican had not spoken with other
countries about arranging exile for Noriega.
   The United States and the Vatican have no extradition treaty and
the Vatican criticized the bloody U.S. invasion that toppled the
general and installed the government of President Guillermo Endara,
who was elected in May in balloting Noriega nullified.
   Without an agreement, Noriega will not get past the U.S. troops
surrounding the Vatican mission. Under international law, embassies
are considered inviolable and U.S. troops cannot legally enter the
mission to get him.
   U.S. troops also surrounded the Cuban, Nicaraguan and Libyan
embassies, where it was thought Noriega might try to seek refuge.
In retaliation, Nicaragua announced today it will not permit a U.S.
plane carrying supplies to the U.S. Embassy in Managua to land next
month until the embassy standoff ends.
   Bush, speaking to reporters today in Texas, said he was
personally involved in trying to win custody of Noriega and had set
no time limit on negotiations.
   The U.S. Southern Command said Noriega probably went to the
Vatican mission on his own after his closest collaborators either
deserted him or were arrested.
   Lt. Col. Luis del Cid, considered one of Noriega's right-hand
men, pleaded innocent Tuesday in U.S. District Court in Miami to
drug smuggling charges.
   ``I surrendered myself _ I wanted to be brought here,'' he told
the court.
   He is charged with racketeering, drug smuggling and money
laundering in the same February 1988 indictment that names Noriega.
   U.S. Attorney Dexter Lehtinen said Del Cid was ``a liaison,
courier and emissary for Manuel Noriega, dealing wit drug
trafficking.''
   U.S. drug agents in Panama were scrutinizing thousands of
documents seized in raids on Noriega's houses and government
offices, including the headquarters of the Anti-Narcotics Special
Force.
   The information included files on foreigners entering and
leaving the country. A U.S. Drug Enforcment Administration agent,
who spoke on condition of anonymity, said some of the files were on
Colombian drug lords.
   In Panama City, U.S. troops continued to block some major
streets, adding to the usual traffic jams, and 15 tons of emergency
medical supplies arrived to help hospitals in need of blood,
surgical equipment and other basics.
   Since the invasion began, 23 Americans and 293 Panamanian
military have been killed and 330 Americans and 123 Panamanians
wounded, according to the Southern Command. Another 4,446
Panamanians have been detained.
   Panamanian doctors say more than 100 civilians were killed and
hundreds of others injured. No complete figure was available
because many civilians were buried quickly in common graves and
there were no authorities to keep records.
</TEXT>

</DOC>