<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0534EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Latvia     12-29 0507</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Latvia,0526</SECOND>
<HEAD>Republic's Parliament Votes To Drop Communists' Guarantee of Power</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANN IMSE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A second Baltic republic in less than a month has
voted to scrap constitutional guarantees of the Communist Party's
grip on power, said local activists and journalists in Latvia.
   The republic's parliament voted 220-50 on Thursday to drop the
constitutional provision that makes the party the ``leading and
guiding force of Soviet society,'' said Viysturs Koziols of the
Latvian People's Front newspaper Atmoda.
   Eriks Kehriks, chief of the official news agency Latinform,
confirmed the action.
   Neighboring Lithuania voted Dec. 7 to strip the Communist Party
of its leading role in society, and most of Eastern Europe shed
such provisions this year.
   Koziols said the Latvian parliament voted after a stormy debate
that lasted more than three hours.
   Sarmite Elerte, spokeswoman for the grass-roots Popular Front
movement, said the decision must be made final at parliament's next
session Jan. 10-11. Specific language is to be adopted then on
constitutional amendments legalizing alternative political parties.
   The change is expected to reduce the party's grip on all spheres
of life in the republic. Like its neighbors Lithuania and Estonia,
Latvia has a broad-based movement seeking independence from the
Soviet Union, which forcibly annexed all three nations in 1940.
   Lithuania also legalized alternative political parties.
   Its action to drop constiutional provisions giving power to the
Communists was the first threat to the party's guaranteed supremacy
in the Soviet Union.
   Since then, the issue has arisen in the national Congress of
People's Deputies and the parliaments of Estonia and Armenia, all
of which have similar provisions in their constitutions.
   None has taken a formal vote on the issue, but Estonia is
expected to in January.
   Lithuania's legalization of a multiparty system also helped push
the republic's Communist Party into breaking with the national
party last week.
   The Lithuanian Communists formed a separate party, which favors
independence. That move infuriated many Kremlin Communists, and the
national party's Central Committee decided to send its leader,
President Mikhail S. Gorbchev, to Lithuania next week to discuss
the dispute.
   On Thursday, tens of thousands of Lithuanians rallied to support
the republic's Communists against the Kremlin.
   The national television news show ``Vremya'' said thousands of
people gathered in Vilnius, Kaunas and Klaipede to hear ``bold,
uncompromising speeches'' supporting the party separatists.
   Scenes of the demonstration in Vilnius showed a huge crowd on
the central Gediminas Square numbering more than 50,000.
   The Latvian parliament also considered reinstating the flag and
national anthem of the independent republic that existed between
the two world wars, said Latinform's Kehriks. The vote was
postponed until January.
   In Estonia, the parliament approved hefty taxes on alcohol and
tobacco to finance pay raises for teachers, doctors, journalists
and others in social and cultural work, said Estonian Radio
commentator Peep Kala. Student stipends also will rise, he said.
   The retail price of beer will double, while the average price of
tobacco products will rise 50 percent and alcoholic beverages by 20
percent, Kala said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>