<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0165 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1200EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--Chlorofluorocarbons Adv01   12-28 0621</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Chlorofluorocarbons, Adv 01,0637</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv01</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Monday, Jan. 1, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>CFCs Mysteriously Being Absorbed into Earth, Oceans</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM McCALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ozone-depleting chlorofluorocarbons are
being absorbed by the soil and oceans, according to scientists who
say they still don't know where exactly the chemicals are going or
what the process means.
   Researchers Aslam Khalil and Reinhold Rasmussen were studying
Australian termite mounds to see how they dumped the gas methane
into the atmosphere when their measurements indicated that the soil
was absorbing CFCs.
   ``And it's not confined to Australian termite mounds. We looked
at areas of Brazil and found it. We also found it in Chinese rice
fields,'' said Khalil, a physicist at the Oregon Graduate Institute
of Science and Technology.
   The process may have only a minor effect on the atmosphere, but
to Khalil it suggests that CFCs' interaction with the environment
is more complex than has been thought. ``I don't think, on a global
scale, this will be significant, but compare the greenhouse gases.
They have only a minute effect by themselves. What's important is
their additive effect.''
   Two other atmospheric scientists, F. Sherwood Roland of the
University of California, Irvine, and Mario Molina of Massachusetts
Institute of Technology, agree the mechanism of chlorofluorocarbon
absorption by the soil may be worth studying, but that the effect
on the atmosphere is minimal.
   ``It's not a process that's materially shortening the
chlorofluorocarbon lifetime in the atmosphere,'' Roland said.
``It's not a major sink.''
   The ocean appears to be merely storing the CFCs, the scientists
said. ``CFCs are permanently lost in atmospheric processes but in
the ocean that's not so, it's just dissolving,'' said Khalil.
   The oceans' capacity is huge, so it's possible ``they will build
up over a very long time scale, on the order of thousands of
years,'' Roland said. ``But only about 1 percent of all CFCs are in
the ocean now, which again doesn't change the overall calculation
very much.''
   A much more serious concern is the amount of chlorofluorocarbons
stored in polyurethane insulation, vehicle air conditioning units
and home refrigerators, the scientists say.
   ``The ban on CFCs in aerosol sprays merely put them into
polyurethane insulating foam, just being stored for future
release,'' Khalil said. ``That's more alarming than soil uptake,
which at best is good, at worst is nothing.''
   Chlorofluorocarbons were widely used in aerosol propellants
until evidence mounted they were contributing to the depletion of
the Earth's protective ozone layer, which shields the planet from
harmful ultraviolet radiation.
   In May, representatives of 81 nations met in Helsinki and called
for the elimination of CFC use by the year 2000. Their declaration
seeks to toughen the provisions of a 1987 ozone-protection treaty
called the Montreal Protocol.
   ``About 85 percent of the CFCs manufactured already have been
released into the atmosphere,'' Roland said. ``For aerosol
propellants it's about a six-month lag time. For automobile air
conditioners, it's about two to three years. For home refrigerators
it may be 20 years.
   ``What that means is that we'll reach the maximum concentration
of CFCs in the atmosphere about five to 10 years after
manufacturing stops.''
   Khalil said, ``In a way, it's not bad that CFCs are tied up
somewhere, so their release is slow and won't bother anybody. It's
better than going into the air in large quantities.''
   Greenhouse gases that could contribute to global warming, such
as methane, are a far more serious threat, he, Roland and Molina
said.
   ``You can ban CFC production in the narrow, highly
industrialized band of cities in the Northern Hemisphere,'' Khalil
said, ``but you can't ban methane or carbon dioxide. You can't tell
bacteria to stop making it.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Jan. 1</NOTE>

</DOC>