<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0118EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-DrugPlanes     12-19 0625</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Drug Planes,610</SECOND>
<HEAD>Repairs on High-Tech Drug Planes Delayed</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LARRY MARGASAK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Heeding the warnings of two senators, the U.S.
Customs Service says it won't buy a third high-tech radar plane
until the two existing problem-plagued aircraft can locate and
track airborne drug smugglers.
   In a letter released Monday the Customs Service acknowledged,
however, that the computerized radar systems in the P3 Airborne
Early Warning aircraft won't be fixed until June _ half a year
after the most recent estimate.
   The planes are the government's frontline response to
intercepting drug flights, which carried an estimated 51 percent of
the cocaine seized during 1988 to the United States.
   The Associated Press reported in November that the radar systems
experienced problems since the moment the first plane arrived in
June 1988 at the Customs Service Surveillance Support Center in
Corpus Christi, Texas.
   Dennis DeConcini, D-Ariz., and Pete Domenici, R-N.M., wrote to
the agency Nov. 12, saying a third plane should not be ordered
``until the two ... aircraft currently being operated ... meet the
overall aircraft performance standards originally intended...''
   DeConcini is chairman and Domenici the ranking minority member
of the Senate Appropriations subcommittee that controls the Customs
Service budget. The planes are made by Lockheed Aeronautical
Systems Co., which predicted in November the problems should be
corrected around the end of this year.
   The first-of-their-kind planes were designed to find and track
smuggler aircraft and guide government interceptors chasing the
drug pilots _ but internal agency documents revealed that computer
failures severely hampered this mission. However, the planes have
continued flying while the Customs Service attempted to fix the
problems.
   In response to the senators, William Rosenblatt, the Customs
Service assistant commissioner for enforcement, wrote, ``We will
not enter into a contractual agreement for the third aircraft until
such time as ... we are entirely satisfied that the originally
intended performance standards are met'' and until the senators
give their approval.
   Rosenblatt's letter was written last week and released to the AP
Monday by DeConcini. The senator, a strong advocate of the
airplanes, said in a statement that he's satisfied the Customs
Service ``has responded in a responsible manner'' and has
``established a schedule to rectify the deficiencies.''
   ``I am satisfied,'' he said, that the agency is insuring ``the
viability of the air interdiction program while insisting that the
contractor live up to the terms of the contract.''
   The first P3 AEW cost $27 million and the second was bought for
$30.6 million. If the third plane is ordered, it would be expected
in 1992.
   ``Everyone was being a little optimistic'' in estimates that the
problems would be fixed by the end of this year, agency spokesman
Dick Weart said Monday. ``Extensive testing'' by Lockheed will take
longer than anticipated, he said.
   Rosenblatt said the agency is withholding $1.5 million from
Lockheed until the detection system is fixed and until the company
also replaces the cockpit windshields _ a separate problem that has
hampered pilot visibility.
   Rosenblatt said Lockheed is attempting to fix:
   _The ``tracker'' which automatically provides computer displays
on a target's course, speed and altitude. Radar operators have
complained the readings are so inaccurate that they can't
effectively guide Customs Service interceptors to a smuggler
aircraft. Some crewmen said they worried they could direct their
interceptors into a collision with a smuggler aircraft.
   _The system used by the P3 AEW planes to ``interrogate'' the
transponder signals of other aircraft to determine their
identification and location. The P3 interrogation signal is so
powerful that planes that may be 300 miles away appear on computer
screens as nearby targets.
   _The special windshields, built to prevent magnetic interference
from the radar. The windshields originally installed have
interfered with pilot visibility.
</TEXT>

</DOC>