<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0107 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1631EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Sinking-CoastGuard     12-19 0476</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sinking-Coast Guard,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lack of Coast Guard Regulations Cited As Contributing to Accident</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID BRISCOE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Coast Guard's failure to require life
rafts and signal beacons on small, commercial passenger boats
contributed to the loss of life in the sinking of a vessel off the
Oregon coast, the National Transportation Safety Board concluded
Tuesday.
   It was the first time the board has cited what it considers a
laxity in Coast Guard regulations as a contributory cause to an
accident it investigated.
   The board, on a 3-0 vote with one member absent, placed primary
blame for the accident on the vessel's captain, who was not
identified.
   The board also blamed the Coast Guard for failing in its
inspections to confirm whether hatchcovers on the 46-foot Cougar
were watertight before the Sept. 15, 1988, sinking, which led to
the deaths of the boat's captain, a deckhand and two passengers.
   One died 15 minutes before a helicopter rescued a ship's mate
and the boat's four remaining passengers, who had floated in the
cold water 35 miles west of Depoe Bay for 18 hours, investigators
said.
   The board said the Cougar's captain had failed to ensure that
hatchcovers were watertight, that the bilge pump was operating
properly and that rubber flaps designed to let water flow off the
deck were correctly installed.
   The flaps were on the wrong side, preventing water from flowing
off the deck, investigators said. The ship sank in moderately heavy
seas while returning from a fishing trip, after its crew and
passengers tried for 90 minutes to bail out the ship with buckets.
   The board estimates that more than 4,700 commercial vessels
capable of carrying 300,000 passengers fall under the same
regulations as the Cougar.
   The board for years has recommended that the Coast Guard require
all commercial boats to carry lifeboats that will keep all
passengers and crew out of the water if the ship sinks and that
emergency positon-indicating radio beacons, or EPRIBs, be carried
on all vessels so they can be quickly located by searchers.
   In the last five years, the board has investigated five
passenger vessel accidents, including two collisions, one fire, one
capsizing and one grounding. In each case, Coast Guard survival
craft requirements were found inadequate, but there has been no
change.
   The board recommended that the Coast Guard require that within
five years all floation devices and buoyant apparatus be replaced
by lifeboats, life rafts or inflatable devices that can keep people
out of the water.
   The problem is that floatation devices require that passengers
remain in the water, where they can suffer from a rapid loss of
body heat, or hypothermia.
   The board also advised the Coast Guard to improve its testing
rules and procedures and to require all passenger vessel operators
to file sailing plans before they set out.
</TEXT>

</DOC>