<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0163 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1900EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Czechoslovakia 1stLd-Writethru a0601 12-18 0660</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Czechoslovakia, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0601,0677</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prague to Discuss Soviet Troop Withdrawal With Kremlin</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: ADDS 2 grafs with presidential race developments.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GIRARD C. STEICHEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Government leaders will begin
talks with the Kremlin this week on withdrawing Soviet troops
stationed in Czechoslovakia since the 1968 invasion that crushed
reforms, officials said Monday.
   Also on Monday, the Communist Party's daily newspaper apologized
on its front page for its past practice of vilifying many of the
people who have emerged as leaders of the reform drive.
   The party leader, Karel Urbanek, was quoted as saying the
Communists probably will try to form a coalition with other parties
before free elections planned next year.
   Premier Marian Calfa and Foreign Minister Jiri Dienstbier _ a
non-Communist and former dissident _ are scheduled to visit Moscow
on Wednesday at the invitation of Soviet Premier Nikolai Ryzhkov.
   The state news agency CTK said Dienstbier would begin
negotiations for the pullout of the estimated 80,000 Soviet troops
stationed in Czechoslovakia. Dienstbier said Thursday their
withdrawal was expected soon but gave no details.
   All the hard-line leaders installed after the 1968 Soviet-led
invasion have been ousted, and the five Warsaw Pact nations that
participated in the invasion have since condemned it.
   The foreign minister has said the agreement allowing the
presence of Soviet troops in Czechoslovakia was invalid because it
was signed under pressure by Alexander Dubcek, leader of the
ill-fated ``Prague Spring'' reforms.
   Dubcek signed the initial document permitting the Soviet
presence after tense negotiations in the Kremlin, where he was
flown after the invasion. A second agreement was signed by Prague
and Moscow in October 1968.
   For two decades afterward, the official Communist daily Rude
Pravo tried to discredit Dubcek and former dissident Vaclav Havel,
now a leading presidential candidate.
   ``Stories like `Stool Pigeon,' `Who is Vaclav Havel,' `Dubcek's
Journey From Tragedy to Farce' and others did not express ... the
(true) attitudes of most of the paper's editors,'' according to the
newspaper's apology Monday.
   In a separate article, Rude Pravo quoted Urbanek as saying a
party congress this week must drawn on the ideas of Dubcek's
reforms and renew itself to survive.
   ``It is more than probable already now that the Communist Party
should go into the (free) elections in a coalition with other
leftist parties which already exist, as well as those to be
established in the future,'' he said.
   The party that dominated Czechoslovakia for 41 years has been
forced into the idea of a coalition by a peaceful revolt that began
Nov. 17, ended the party's guaranteed monopoly on power, and led to
the naming of a federal government dominated by non-Communists.
   Officials have said free elections, which would be the first in
Czechoslovakia in 43 years, could be held in June or July.
   The battle over the vacant presidency is the latest battle
between the communists and the opposition group Civic Forum, which
is pushing for the election of Havel, its leader.
   Hard-line President Gustav Husak resigned Dec. 10 after swearing
in the new government. Under current law, Parliament must elect a
new president within 14 days, but an amendment under consideration
would extend that period to up to 40 days.
   Both sides admitted last week that the deadline might have to be
extended.
   The official CTK news agency said about 10,000 people
demonstrated Monday in Ceske Budejovice in south Bohemia in support
of Havel.
   Havel, a playwright whose works were once banned, said Saturday
he would accept the presidency only temporarily until someone can
be elected for the five-year term by a new freely elected Federal
Assembly.
   Dubcek has also been mentioned as a presidential candidate.
   The Socialist Party, once closely allied with the Communists but
increasingly independent, on Monday announced it backed Havel's
candidacy.
   Cestmir Cisar, who was proposed for the presidency by the
official Socialist Youth Union, said on national TV Monday he was
not interested in being a candidate.
</TEXT>

</DOC>