<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1047EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-QuayleInterview Bjt   12-30 0782</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Quayle Interview, Bjt,760</SECOND>
<HEAD>Quayle: `I'm Not a Potted Plant'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RITA BEAMISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vice President Dan Quayle says he's not just a
``potted plant'' in the Bush administration and that he now knows
``what it takes'' to be president.
   Quayle also says he thinks he had a ``fairly easy'' first year
as vice president because of low expectations that followed the
media hazing he got when George Bush picked him as a running mate
last year.
   In an interview with The Associated Press, Quayle said he
expects the coming year to be more challenging. He likened himself
to a high jumper and said that this year ``the bar will be
elevated.''
   The vice president described his principal achievements so far
as ``establishing myself in this office, establishing the loyal
relationship I have with the president, being a team player that
makes a contribution to the president.''
   Despite sniping from some administration officials who privately
dismiss him as irrelevant, Quayle insists he is a contributor to
policy deliberations.
   ``I spend a great deal of time with the president,'' Quayle
said. ``We have a very close, personal, loyal relationship. I'm
not, as they say, a potted plant in these meetings.''
   His self-assessment is not shared by everyone in the White
House. One top administration official called Quayle's
contributions to policy making ``marginal.'' The official, speaking
on condition of anonymity, said Quayle ``rarely says anything''
during group meetings with Bush advisers. When he does, he can be
counted on to espouse the conservative line, officials say.
   Conversely, many others in the administration say the vice
president has acquitted himself well. Despite occasional
malapropisms, he has not fulfilled critics' predictions that he
would stumble and embarrass the administration with major gaffes.
   He meets with Bush daily, sits in on intelligence briefings and
frequently attends meetings Bush has with world leaders or domestic
groups. He is chairman of the president's Space Council and the
Competitiveness Council focusing on ways to spur business growth.
   He takes his cue from Bush, who as vice president never revealed
his advice to then-President Reagan, declining to disclose his
conversations with the president.
   He generally hews word-for-word to the administration line. But
on occasion, Quayle's conservatism has surfaced with a more
hard-line tone than Bush's statements, particularly regarding the
Soviets.
   Most recently, Quayle took a tough view of Soviet President
Mikhail Gorbachev, saying the United States should not let
Gorbachev's ``magnetic personality'' obscure true Soviet intentions.
   Quayle's remarks came just after Bush's Dec. 2 summit meeting
with the Soviet leader where U.S. officials stressed themes of
trust and cooperation.
   Quayle discounted the notion he has been instructed to placate
conservatives leery of Bush, or that he differs with Bush policy.
   ``It's the age-old game that is played in trying to find some
distinction between the president and vice president,'' he said.
   Asked why he has been more outspoken than Bush was as vice
president, Quayle said that while he patterns his vice presidency
after ``the George Bush model ... there is emerging the Dan Quayle
model.''
   Quayle said that today, he would probably give about the same
answer as he did in a major campaign debate last year if asked what
he would do if he were propelled into the Oval Office by the death
of the president.
   At that time, he said he would pray for himself and the country
and then call a meeting of Cabinet members and top presidential
advisers.
   ``I've been on this job approaching a year now. I know what to
do now if that tragic event should occur. Looking back, I'm not
sure the answer would be much different. ... I know what the
president does on a day-to-day basis, how he goes about the job.
I'm there. I'm present. He's always told me ... one of the
important roles of the vice president, any vice president, is to be
prepared.''
   ``Believe me I know what to do.''
   Quayle had a chance to perform under fire during the recent coup
attempt in the Philippines that occurred when Bush and his top
advisers were on their way to the Mediterranean superpower summit.
   He conducted an all-night meeting of National Security Council
principals, monitored events and kept a flow of information going
while Bush dispatched U.S. fighter planes to back up embattled
Philippine President Corazon Aquino.
   Quayle didn't get much publicity for his role, but he said,
``there was a job and I did it. ... It's just not something that
you talk about.''
   Still, Quayle continues to languish in public opinion surveys
and suffers a steady stream of comedians' jokes maligning his
intelligence.
   ``I don't worry about it,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>