<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1456EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     12-26 0614</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0635</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FORT WAYNE, Ind. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Indianapolis Colts rookie wide receiver
Andre Rison was driving 128 mph on his way home to Michigan for
Christmas, according to police who pulled him over in a 55 mph zone
in his 1989 Mercedes.
   ``He told the officer he thought he was driving between 95 and
100 mph because he said that's what it feels like when you're
driving 55 mph in a regular car,'' said Sgt. Dallard Tackett of the
State Police post at Fort Wayne.
   Rison was taken to jail, but released within an hour Christmas
morning after he posted $500 bond.
   Rison was the Colts' top draft pick out of Michigan State. The
Colts' season ended Sunday after a 41-6 loss to New Orleans.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PALM BEACH, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Indiana Gov. Evan Bayh, the nation's
youngest governor, spent a quiet 34th birthday here Tuesday,
reading and relaxing away from his home state.
   ``I think the older you get, birthdays have less significance,''
Bayh said of his lack of party plans. ``And some people say, given
my age, a few more birthdays could be helpful.'' His big treat for
the day was reading.
   ``I don't have time to do much leisure reading,'' Bayh told the
Indianapolis Star. ``I read three or four newspapers a day. My
favorite subject is history. I have a backlog of 10 to 15 histories
and biographies that I haven't delved into yet.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CLIO, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actress Zsa Zsa Gabor raked in 11 votes in a
nationwide poll to pick the year's top whiner.
   That made her the winner over ``Today'' show host Bryant Gumbel,
former First Lady Nancy Reagan and Tammy Faye Bakker, wife of
former PTL ministry leader Jim Bakker.
   Gabor apparently pulled ahead of the crowd to be honored for
National Whiners' Day on Tuesday because of her conviction this
year for slapping a police officer.
   The results of the poll _ 45 votes were cast from around the
country _ were announced by Kevin C. Zaborney, who says he invented
Whiner's Day four years ago because of his experiences working in a
fast-food restaurant.
   ``There was a girl who would whine about everything and
anything,'' he said. ``There are people who are whiners and she was
a whiner. Jokingly, I said, `There should be a National Whiner's
Day.'''
   Zaborney picked the day after Christmas, already a traditional
day for whining about the misfit presents under the Christmas tree.
   Family Circle magazine asked readers to send in their
nominations for this year's top whiner, that's how Zaborney
compiled the 45 votes.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Musician Neil Young is taking the bitter with
the sweet. His recent album ``Freedom'' has been critically
acclaimed but isn't getting much radio play time to display its
creative wares.
   ``Freedom'' recently hit a modest No. 35 on the Billboard
charts, even though music critics have praised it lavishly. Young
says he fails to get radio play time because he has dared to be
experimental with his work during the past decade, and because he
often gets boxed in as a ``classic rock'' artist on tightly
formatted radio stations.
   ``If something doesn't fit a station's image or sound, then it
doesn't get played,'' Young said in a recent interview. ``And there
are certain stations that won't play me regardless of what the
record is like. They don't want to play music that their parents
listened to because it doesn't fit their image.''
   Pop music critics have hailed ``Freedom'' as the most accessible
and interesting work Young has done since such hit records as
1970's ``After the Gold Rush'' and 1972's ``Harvest.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>