<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0201 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 2046EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f AM-BusinessMirror Adv03   12-29 0551</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Business Mirror, Adv 03,0568</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv03</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release AMs Wednesday, Jan. 3</HEAD>
<HEAD>Could Price Increases Mean Less Inflation?</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: RETRANSMITTING to fix cycle designator.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN CUNNIFF</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Analyst</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Consumer inflation is likely to pick up over the
next month or so, generating complaints from shoppers but barely
producing a reaction of any sort from economists.
   This is the reverse of how it was last year, when tense
economists trained telescopes on the horizon, stepping back from
time to time to issue warnings about the ogre's approach.
Consumers, meanwhile, hardly worried.
   All in all the consumers were right. Inflation did make a thrust
early in the year, accompanied by shrill warnings from the
economists, but it has been diminishing since then. Somehow,
consumers knew all along.
   This time, however, the increase in prices will be hitting in
especially sensitive areas of the market place, particularly at the
fruit and vegetable counters, and in the monthly bill from the
heating fuel supplier.
   Some of the price jumps, such as 35 percent from some heating
oil dealers, might remind people of the late and unlamented 1970s,
when prices changed so fast that people bought in advance of need,
figuring they'd save that way.
   But none of this is likely to excite forecasters, the very ones
who raised the alarm in 1989. It isn't systemic this time, they
explain, meaning that the cause lies in isolated, temporary factors
rather than a faulty economy.
   Still, that economic assumption might not be as sound as it
seems, relying as it does on still another forecast, this one of
meteorological conditions.
   Weather over the years has demonstrated that it presents
forecasting problems equal or worse than those encountered in
economics. Nevertheless, the relative calmness of economists is
based on a quick return to normal weather.
   Winter came early, savagely and relentlessly to much of the
northern tier of the United States, and thrust cold waves deep into
the South.
   In the North, and in much of the South too, it meant higher fuel
usage, the threat of shortgages and higher prices. Making matters
worse, it forced some refineries to close. Farther south it
destroyed vegetable and fruit crops.
   Economists now assume the severe weather factor will abate,
although like so many of their assumptions _ about politics, for
example _ they have very little expertise in the area. Regardless,
they say, winter ends in three months.
   Meanwhile, there could be an economic effect of an opposite sort.
   Because of added costs in the food and fuel areas, millions of
consumers might have less to spend on other goods and services.
That could lead to lower prices for some items, enough even to
offset the food and fuel inflation.
   Moreover, if the cold weather continues _ in this city it
averaged more than 10 degrees a day below normal for December _ it
could further reduce demand by making it too uncomfortable to look
for cars and houses.
   Thus, those higher food and fuel prices that will have people
grumbling over the next few weeks aren't likely to bother the
professional inflation watchers.
   As they see it, those higher prices are isolated and temporary.
Why, they say, it is even possible they could help lower inflation.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End advance AMs Wednesday, Jan. 3.</NOTE>

</DOC>