<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0211EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Nicaragua-US 3rdLd-Writethru a0423 12-22 0688</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nicaragua-US, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0423,0705</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tit-for-Tat: Armored Cars Surround U.S. Embassy, Later Withdraw</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs to UPDATE with tanks withdrawn. Picks up
11th pvs, `Each vehicle...' EDITS thereafter to conform.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FILADELFO ALEMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANAGUA, Nicaragua (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government moved tanks and armored
cars into positions outside the U.S. Embassy Thursday after U.S.
soldiers surrounded the Nicaraguan Embassy in Panama, but later
withdrew them without explanation.
   President Daniel Ortega said earlier Thursday that ``if the U.S.
government withdraws the armored cars and troops that surround the
Nicaraguan Embassy, then we will respond in the same way here.''
   A curfew was in effect in Panama City and it was not immediately
known if the U.S. troops left the Nicaraguan and Cuban missions.
   Associated Press photographers in Managua saw at least seven
Soviet-made T-55 tanks, three armored personnel carriers and three
trucks of anti-aircraft weapons leave the embassy between 9:30 and
10:30 p.m. (10:30 and 11:30 EST).
   Embassy spokesman Lou Falino said people at the embassy heard
the noise of several engines ``but they could not determine if the
tanks were withdrawn because it was dark.'' He was contacted at his
home.
   American armored cars, part of a U.S. invading force, surrounded
the Nicaraguan and Cuban embassies in Panama City Thursday after
rumors spread that Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega was hiding in one of
the two missions.
   ``We have ordered exactly that the same thing be done here,
around the U.S. Embassy, as was done in Panama City,'' Foreign
Minister Miguel D'Escoto told a news conference. He indicated he
was holding the United States responsible for the safety of
Nicaraguan diplomats in Panama.
   Reporters in Managua saw the Soviet-made T-55 tanks and armored
carriers brought in Thursday afternoon and parked, partially
hidden, behind the U.S. Embassy.
   Each vehicle was manned by a crew of six and armed with a
machine gun and a light cannon. Col. Julio Ramos of the army
general staff personally supervised the deployment shortly after
midday.
   An AP photographer at the scene said at first the armored
carriers were pointing their machine guns and cannon away from the
embassy compound. But an officer ordered the crews to keep the
weapons aimed at the mission.
   Asked for comment, Ramos said he was acting ``on higher orders,
for reasons already explained by Foreign Minister D'Escoto.'' But
an unidentified officer, interviewed live by state radio, said
``this is in response for what they are doing to us now in Panama.''
   ``They have just surrounded our embassy in Panama, and they
think we are going to remain here with our arms crossed?'' the
officer added.
   D'Escoto told reporters Nicaragua has demanded ``the immediate
withdrawal of the invading, imperialist U.S. military presence
around our diplomatic mission in the independent and sovereign
Republic of Panama.''
   ``As soon as they dismantle their deployment there, we are going
to do the same here _ so, we are going to wait until they become
reasonable,'' D'Escoto added, calling the American encirclment of
the embassies in Panama City ``an act of intimidation.''
   He said there were women and children, as well as diplomats,
inside the Nicaraguan Embassy in Panama.
   Soviet-made T-55 tanks, guns, mortars and antiaircraft cannon
were in place all over Managua and in other strategic locations
around the country early Wednesday, hours after American troops
invaded Panama to oust and try to capture Noriega.
   The deposed strongman is wanted in the United States on
drug-trafficking and money-laundering charges.
   Nicaraguan officials said the measures were taken in case the
United States instigates military action against this country.
   For many years, Sandinista spokesmen have been saying the United
States intends to invade Nicaragua. U.S. officials have persistenly
denied this.
   Charge d'affaires John Leonard has been the senior diplomat here
since Ambassador Richard Melton was expelled July 11, 1988, after
the ruling leftist Sandinistas accused him of interfering in
Nicaragua's internal affairs.
   Relations between the Sandinista government and the United
States have been steadily deteriorating since 1980, about a year
after the Sandinistas came to power, when they established military
ties with Cuba and the Soviet Union.
</TEXT>

</DOC>