<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0155 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1539EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-Symposium-WesternEurope Adv31   12-26 0815</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Symposium-Western Europe, Adv 31,0841</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 31, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WORLD SYMPOSIUM '90s: Europe _ Merging of East and West? ^With
LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MORT ROSENBLUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   West Europeans are looking anxiously eastward as
they plunge ahead with elaborate plans for the 1990s in a climate
changing so quickly that answers are coming faster than questions.
   Their grand design is a ``single Europe'' of 12 Economic
Community members starting at the end of 1992, a melting away of
internal barriers and a blending of policies under the umbrella of
the North Atlantic Treaty Organization.
   But after the Berlin Wall crumbled, and as a 44-year-old Iron
Curtain buckles, everything from the pace of integration to the
overall strategy has been thrown into doubt.
   Some Europeans suspect that against Soviet President Mikhail S.
Gorbachev's image of a ``common European home,'' the smaller
``single Europe'' structure is a shaky house of cards.
   NATO is under mounting pressure to stand down in the face of
former enemies who are now acting like friends.
   The official view, stressed at a European Community summit at
Strasbourg in December, is that a united Western Europe is crucial
to helping Eastern Europe.
   EC leaders moved closer to a central bank, a common currency and
uniform social benefits. They also agreed to set up a Bank of
Europe to help newly democratic eastern neighbors.
   The EC called for a flexibility yet to be defined, and most of
its leaders applauded Washington's plans to support a stronger EC
and to broaden NATO into a political forum for solving problems.
   U.S. Secretary of State James A. Baker III, speaking on a visit
to Berlin in December, suggested a greater dialogue with the East,
not only on European problems but also to ease tensions elsewhere
in the world.
   ``As Europe changes, the instruments for Western cooperation
must adapt,'' he said. ``Working together, we must design and
gradually put into place a new architecture for a new era.''
   Whatever shape a new Europe takes, its leaders agree, the
cornerstone will be Germany. In many ways, the divided nation has
already united. Much hangs on how this union is formalized.
   Germany would grow from a reasonably sized EC partner to a
colossus of 80 million inhabitants with a gross national product of
$1.4 trillion, approaching the Soviet Union's.
   Without a separate East Germany, the Soviet Union's Warsaw Pact
military alliance is reduced to a few satellites that are fast
slipping away.
   Foreign Minister Hans Dietrich Genscher of West Germany insists
that a re-united Germany would demilitarize Europe and draw the
Soviet Union and other Eastern European countries closer to the EC.
   But President Francois Mitterrand of France maintains it is too
early to predict the direction Europe now will take.
   France clearly prefers separate Germanys while publicly
supporting the Germans' right to settle the issue themselves.
French leaders expect Moscow to block any formal reunification.
   Other EC partners, while encouraging the lightning-fast changes,
take a similar stance for varying reasons.
   Spain, Portugal and Greece fear investment and development funds
they counted on will be diverted to the East. Italy argues that
postwar borders should remain intact.
   Britain, which has resisted EC monetary and social integration,
may find an ally in a West Germany anxious to preserve some
independence within a single Europe.
   But Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher, after an emergency summit
in November, made it plain that Britain was not anxious for a rapid
blurring of East-West lines in Germany.
   ``All military matters must continue to be conducted through
NATO and the Warsaw Pact,'' she said. ``At a time of great change,
it's necessary to keep the background of stability and security.''
   In West Germany, reunification is already a dominant issue in
general elections, still a year off.
   Chancellor Helmut Kohl has thrown open the door and encouraged
investment to speed unification. In Bonn, West German officials
already refer to ``the eastern part of the country.''
   If Kohl's center-right coalition stays in power, it will have a
mandate to push reunification. In such circumstances, Kohl is
likely to have reluctant support from Mitterrand, among others.
   In broad terms, Western Europe's mood is buoyant. The
Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development estimates put
growth at 2.7 percent for 1991, higher than in the United States.
   The Soviet Union would like a share of that prosperity. Some
officials say the Soviets now prefer trade to domination in Europe.
   On Dec. 18, the Soviet Union and the EC signed a 10-year trade
pact, opening the way for a larger Western role in a changing
Soviet economy.
   Foreign Minister Eduard Shevardnadze remarked: ``This is a
result of a gigantic effort made by the peoples of Europe to
overcome political and military confrontation, to overcome the
economic division of our continent.''
   In short, he said, ``the Cold War is over.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Sunday, Dec. 31</NOTE>

</DOC>