<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0852EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-India     12-20 0468</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-India,0482</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Indian Government to Combat Separatist, Religious Violence</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RAJU GOPALAKRISHNAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Ramaswamy Venkataraman,
outlining the policies of India's new government, said today there
would be no compromises in tackling seccessionist campaigns by Sikh
and Moslem militants.
   In a speech prepared by Prime Minister V.P. Singh's government,
Venkataraman told a joint session of Parliament that new efforts
must be made to halt religious strife and corruption.
   The president, whose post is largely ceremonial, also said India
would retain friendly ties with the Soviet Union and United States,
seek to solve a border dispute with China and strengthen economic
ties with Japan.
   Singh, whose centrist National Front alliance took office after
forging a coalition with Hindu right-wingers and secular
communists, listened attentively in the front row of the Central
Hall of Parliament.
   Rajiv Gandhi, whose five-year tenure as prime minister ended in
the November election debacle for his Congress Party, took notes.
   Venkataraman, noting that voters had given ``a clear verdict in
favor of change,'' said the new government would strive to meet the
challenges ahead.
   ``The Punjab problem has defied solution so far,'' he said,
referring to the Sikh separatist movement that has claimed more
than 7,000 lives in the past six years and triggered the 1984
assassination of Gandhi's mother, Prime Minister Indira Gandhi.
   ``There will be no compromise with separatism and no yielding to
extremists, but there is admittedly a compelling need for a
national endeavor to resolve the problem,'' the white-haired
president said.
   He said Singh's government would broaden the discussions it has
already initiated on finding a political solution for Punjab,
India's most prosperous farming state.
   The nationally televised, 15-minute speech set out a course of
action for government but gave few specifics. It was delivered in
the same Parliament hall where India's independence was proclaimed
at midnight on Aug. 14, 1947.
   Turning to Kashmir, where pro-Pakistan Moslems seek to secede
from India, Venkataraman vowed: ``There will be no compromise on
the country's unity, sovereignty and integrity.''
   The 2-week-old government of Singh has already had its first
serious challenge from Kashmiri militants. On Dec. 8, militants
kidnapped the daughter of Home Minister Mufti Mohammad Sayeed, also
a Kashmiri Moslem.
   The young woman, a hospital intern, was released unharmed after
six days when the government freed five Moslem extremists.
   In a reference to Hindu-Moslem riots that claimed more than 300
lives this fall in other states, the president said: ``Violence has
no place in the land of Mahatma Gandhi, the apostle of
non-violence.''
   He was referring to Indian independence leader Mohandas K.
Gandhi.
   Venkataraman said that under Singh, whose chief campaign pledge
was to eradicate government corruption, legislation would be
introduced to appoint an ombudsman, or watchdog, whose jurisdiction
would include the prime minister.
</TEXT>

</DOC>