<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1356EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-FirstStirrings-Iowa     12-24 0456</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-First Stirrings-Iowa,440</SECOND>
<HEAD>Faint 1992 Rumblings Heard in Iowa</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-First Stirrings Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE GLOVER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When the phone rang the other day in Joe
Shanahan's office, he wasn't surprised to find an aide to Sen.
Lloyd Bentsen on the line, looking to trade gossip about a
political consultant.
   ``I have a lot of newfound friends in Bentsen's office,'' said
Shanahan, spokesman for the Iowa Democratic Party.
   Bentsen, the Texas senator who was the Democrats' vice
presidential nominee in 1988, isn't the only prominent Democrat
keeping tabs on Iowa, the state with the first caucuses in the
presidential sweepstakes.
   Those mulling a run for the White House in 1992 _ or consultants
looking to align themselves with a presidential campaign _ are
keeping an eye on 1990 elections in Iowa, which has tough contests
for governor and Senate.
   ``Anybody who is looking down the road to 1992 has a good reason
to visit the state,'' said Phil Roeder, political director for
Democratic Sen. Tom Harkin, who is being challenged next year by
Republican Rep. Tom Tauke.
   Indeed, many potential 1992 Democratic candidates have been
stopping in Iowa of late.
   New Jersey Sen. Bill Bradley came to raise money for Harkin, and
activists on hand said there was some informal talk about the
possibility of a Bradley presidential bid.
   Bentsen was the featured speaker at the state Democratic Party's
annual fund-raiser this past fall, denying any interest in running
for president in 1992 but nonetheless taking time to talk to
reporters about his ideas for national election strategy.
   House Majority Leader Richard Gephardt, winner of the 1988 Iowa
caucuses, visited recently, and Jesse Jackson was on hand the day
after the last election and since to speak at a funeral.
   ``Those people have been out here under the auspices of helping
the Democratic Party,'' said Shanahan. ``You can read whatever you
want into that, but we're glad they're here.''
   And, although President Bush is expected to be unopposed for the
Republican nomination should he seek re-election, Democrats haven't
had the state to themselves.
   Texas Sen. Phil Gramm and television evangelist Pat Robertson,
an unsuccessful 1988 GOP presidential candidate who finished second
in Iowa last year behind Sen. Bob Dole, have dropped in for quick
visits, fueling speculation they might be looking down the road to
1996.
   Iowa political operatives aren't surprised at the early
attention; presidential candidates who have done well here often
began their caucus campaigns a year or more before the vote.
   Said Roeder:
   ``If we get by with 12 to 15 hours of down time between the 1990
elections and the beginning of the 1992 caucuses, that will be a
pretty liberal amount of time.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>