<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1620EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Bush-Text     12-24 0614</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Text,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>President Bush's Christmas Broadcast to U.S. Armed Forces</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is the text of President Bush's radio
address Sunday to U.S. armed forces.
   Hello to all our men and women in uniform and to your families,
and a special salute to those right now engaged in restoring
democracy and freedom in Panama.
   This has been an historic and extraordinary year for our nation
and, indeed, the world. Just sit back and think for a moment, about
the dramatic events of 1989, so many of them events about freedom,
democray, man's quest to determine his own destiny.
   You know, Chancellor Kohl of Germany called me just after the
Berlin Wall came down. And he told me that this incredible event
could not have occurred without America's resolve demonstrated in
Europe and around the world over the last 40 years. You, the men
and women of our armed forces, you are the embodiment of America's
resolve.
   I have talked with you before tonight during this past year at
Elmendorf, or Rhein Main, and Pease, and on the landing decks of
the America and the Forrestal, or the bridge of the Belknap, and
seen first hand, the job you do for our country. And I've seen you
at the times when America remembers her fallen sons and daughters,
at the cemetery in Nettuno, Italy, last May; at the Iwo Jima
memorial in June or at the Texas Vietnam memorial, just last month.
   And finally, I've been with you when we must share our grief for
those more recently lost in defense of freedom. In April, with the
men behind the guns of the proud battleship Iowa.
   Now, brave Americans have died again in combat, just last week.
In Panama, as in every other such test in our history, Americans
put their lives on the line for the basic values of liberty and
decency on which our nation is founded.
   Our hearts and those of every American go out to the families of
those who fell. To all those who mourn a husband, a son, a brother,
a father or a friend, I can only offer the thanks of a grateful
nation. Your loved ones served a noble and just cause with honor
and distinction.
   Not long ago, I shook the hand of a woman who had lost two sons
in war. She'd said that it would be an honor to shake the hand of
the President of the United States. But in truth, I was the one
honored to shake her hand, for it is she and millions of other
mothers and fathers, daughters and sons, whose decency, service,
and courage embody the spirit of America.
   Wherever you are, whatever your rank or branch of service, I
want you to remember something about America. We are a people with
the endurance to work day and night for peaceful solutions when we
can. But we are also a people with the strength to confront tyranny
when we must. General Noriega is the latest one to learn that
lesson.
   It is Christmas Eve. Forty-five years ago to this very day, I
arrived home from the Pacific. History has long since passed
judgment on those years of conflict. But that war did not end all
wars, and today we still live in times of great challenge, and
there are still times when America must sacrifice in the cause of
peace.
   Years from now, let it be said that America used her strength
for good, and let it be known that she honored her defenders of
freedom.
   Merry Christmas to all of you, and thank you. God bless you, and
God bless the cause of freedom.
</TEXT>

</DOC>