<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0510EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Japan-Markets     12-29 0673</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Japan-Markets,0695</SECOND>
<HEAD>Market Ends Year At Another Record High, Up 29 Percent Since January</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TETSUO JIMBO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Tokyo Stock Exchange closed its 1989 trading
today with a half-day session in a festival mood, and the fourth
consecutive day of record-setting left the market's key index 29
percent higher than at the year's beginning.
   The dollar rose sharply, closing 1989 at a level 13.9 percent
above its 1988 close.
   The 225-issue Nikkei Stock Average, the stock exchange's main
barometer, finished at 38,915.87 points on its fourth consecutive
day of setting a record-high closing. In just a half-day session,
it gained 38.93 points, or 0.1 percent.
   The stock market opened 1989 on Jan. 4 with the Nikkei at
30,243.66, and the index followed its familiar upward direction
throughout the year, reaching the 35,000-point mark Aug. 16 and the
38,000-point mark Dec. 13.
   Its 1989 gain of 29.0 percent, however, was below 1988's 39.9
percent.
   The dollar closed today at 143.40, up 1.25 yen from Thursday's
close of 142.15. It opened at 143.45 and stayed in a narrow range
between 143.15 yen and 143.60 yen. It had gained 0.05 yen on
Thursday after a five-day decline totaling 2.13 yen.
   The U.S. currency had ended 1988 trading at 125.90 yen. This
year, despite pressure from the world's monetary authorities to
reduce its strength, it traded as high as 151.30 in June.
   After a New Year holiday, the Tokyo markets will reopen Thursday.
   The stock market was particularly strong in the last two months
of this year, when domestic politics finally settled down after a
long period of instability and investors looked for business
opportunities from the reform movements in Eastern Europe.
   Tokyo share prices recovered quickly from the crash in October,
when Wall Street's confidence was shaken by the failure of a United
Airlines buyout effort.
   Following an abrupt drop of 7.1 percent in the Dow Jones
industrial average on the New York Stock Exchange Oct. 13, the main
index in London fell 3.2 percent and the Frankfurt market lost 13.2
percent.
   Tokyo shares, however, declined only 1.8 percent, or 647.33
points, on the first trading day after the Wall Street crash, and
quickly regained 527.39 points the next day. In the next two
months, the index rose about 10 percent.
   ``I think the Tokyo market's strength was reconfirmed this year
when the crashes in the New York and London markets were blocked by
Tokyo's strength,'' said Josen Takahashi, a chief analyst at
Mitsubishi Research Institute, a major private think tank.
   The Tokyo market also had recovered quickly from the crash of
October 1987 and emerged as a powerhouse of world stock markets.
   Today the Tokyo market's capitalization is estimated at $3.5
trillion, more than 25 percent larger than the New York Stock
Exchange, and Tokyo is outperforming other major stock markets
around the world.
   Analysts said the Tokyo market overcame a number of obstacles
this year, including the death of Emperor Hirohito in January, the
resignations of two prime ministers in two months, currency
fluctuations and fear of creeping inflation.
   ``There were some negative factors this year, but overall, the
market situation was bullish throughout the year,'' said Ichitaro
Watanabe, a dealer with Nikko Securities Co.
   In the currency market, dealers attributed the dollar's upward
trend throughout 1989 to the gap in key interest rates between
Japan and the United States.
   Lower interest rates, like Japan's, tend to make a nation's
currency less attractive to investors.
   On Monday, the Bank of Japan, in an effort to stem inflationary
pressure, raised the discount rate _ the rate the central bank
charges on its loans to commercial banks _ to 4.25 percent from
3.75 percent.
   The dollar, however, showed a moderate decline of only 0.95 yen
against the Japanese currency after the announcement and began
climbing again on Thursday.
   But dealers say the dollar is expected to head downward early
next year in anticipation of a further downswing in U.S. interest
rates, the subject of speculation in recent weeks.
</TEXT>

</DOC>