<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0448EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CanalCelebration     12-19 0523</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Canal Celebration,0538</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Canal Lock Gates Cause For Celebration In Lockport</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALAN FLIPPEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOCKPORT, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The city that draws its name and history
from the westernmost locks of the Erie Canal plans a party tonight
for a public works project _ the replacement of the lock gates that
were installed 72 years ago.
   Lockport residents plan to celebrate with light and song even
though the days have long since passed when Lockport's locks were
the city's lifeblood.
   ``It's probably the most significant thing to happen to the
community, certainly the most significant investment in the
canal,'' said Mary Brennan-Taylor, chairwoman of the Canal
Spotlight Committee.
   The locks, she said, bring tourists and ``give the community a
sense of identity.''
   Lockport's two locks carry the canal up over the Niagara
Escarpment on the final leg of its route from Albany to Buffalo.
The town was founded four years after the canal opened in 1825, and
grew to become a city in 1865.
   ``There were hotels, stores, bars, businesses along the canal.
There were grocery stores right down the lock,'' said assistant
city historian Howard Colbey. ``Mills used the spillway of the
locks for power.''
   John Bloom, a 73-year-old resident who worked on canal boats in
the 1930s and 1940s, said his barges used to stop for groceries in
Lockport, make deliveries to businesses along the canal and haul in
building stone from nearby quarries.
   ``There was one (barge) right after another, 24 hours a day,''
he said.
   The present gates were installed in 1917, when the entire canal
was rebuilt and widened. But the canal's usefulness as a shipping
route ended when the St. Lawrence Seaway opened in the 1950s, and
many of the flour, paper and textile mills along the canal went out
of business. Lockport's major employer today is the Harrison
Radiator Division of General Motors.
   The canal is now used mainly by pleasure boats, but interest in
the locks has been rising in the past few years. On summer days,
lock workers say, the walls and bridges overlooking the lock are
frequently jammed with sightseers.
   The attention paid to the $2.3 million lock replacement has
nevertheless surprised many of those working on the project.
   ``The local paper comes out every day and takes pictures,'' said
Earl Kostuk, job superintendent for SCC Contracting of Niagara
Falls, which is performing the work under state supervision.
   The plans for tonight's celebration call for 300 residents
holding red glowsticks to line the walls of the lock, singing
Christmas carols and the traditional Erie Canal folk song, ``Low
Bridge, Everybody Down,'' as all of Lockport's churches peal their
bells in unison, Mrs. Brennan-Taylor said.
   Downtown stores will stay open late, like they did when the
canal was an important shipping artery.
   Further festivities are planned for May, when the project is
finished and the canal opens again for navigation.
   Bloom, who tells fourth-graders about life on the barges as part
of the local history curriculum, said he was pleased by the plans.
   ``I think it's wonderful. They need it,'' he said. ``They should
never close the canal down.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>