<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0190 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1651EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Dollar-Gold     12-27 0479</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dollar-Gold,0498</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar, Gold Lower</HEAD>
<HEAD>Precede LONDON BC</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dollar drifted mostly lower in very thin
pre-holiday trading Wednesday, dipping to what traders said was its
lowest level against the West German mark since the spring of 1988.
   Gold prices, meanwhile, declined sharply in the United States
and overseas. On the Commodity Exchange in New York, gold bullion
for current delivery settled at $400.80 a troy ounce, down $6 from
Tuesday. Republic National Bank in New York, quoted a late bid for
gold at $400.55 an ounce, off $6.45.
   Currency dealers said the dollar remained pressured by the
continued strength of the West German mark and from expectations
that U.S. interest rates will decline further because of weakness
in the American economy.
   The mark has been on the rise for several weeks amid rapid
political and economic reforms in Eastern Europe. Many economists
predict West Germany's economy will be bolstered as more Eastern
European countries, including neighboring East Germany, open their
doors to the West.
   In late New York trading, the dollar closed at 1.6895 West
German marks, down from 1.7090 Tuesday.
   Gabriele Schmitt, a currency trader with the Bank of New York,
said that was the weakest close this year and the lowest level
since April 1988.
   Although sentiment toward the dollar remains bullish, dealers
said they expect trading to remain very light in the two days
before the long New Year's holiday weekend.
   In Tokyo, where trading ends before Europe's business day
begins, the dollar fell to 142.10 Japanese yen from 142.37 yen
Tuesday. It traded at 142.05 yen in London, and at 142.00 yen in
New York, up from 141.845 yen Tuesday.
   The dollar was weaker against the British pound. In London,
sterling rose to $1.6255 from $1.6205 late Friday. Later, in New
York, it fetched $1.6275, up from $1.6265 Tuesday.
   Most European financial markets were closed on Monday and
Tuesday for the Christmas holiday.
   Other late dollar rates in New York, compared with Tuesday's
quotes, included: 1.5295 Swiss francs, down from 1.54525; 5.7600
French francs, down from 5.8020; 1.15735 Canadian dollars, down
from 1.6005; and 1,263.75 Italian lire, down from 1,272.75.
   Late dollar rates in Europe compared with Friday: 1.6895 West
German marks, down from 1.7090; 1.5355 Swiss francs, down from
1.5475; 5.7760 French francs, down from 5.8385; 1.9080 Dutch
guilders, down from 1.9330; 1,266.00 Italian lire, down from
1,277.75; 1.1587 Canadian dollars, up from 1.1585.
   Gold closed in London at a late bid price of $406.25 an ounce,
down from $412.25 Friday. It fell in Zurich to $406 an ounce from
$413.
   In Hong Kong, gold closed at $408.49 an ounce, down $5.45 from
Tuesday.
   Silver prices also slipped. On New York's Comex, silver bullion
for current delivery settled at $5.240 a troy ounce, down from
$5.512. Silver fell in London to $5.41 an ounce from $5.58 bid
Friday.
</TEXT>

</DOC>