<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0105EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-Noriega-Surroundings Bjt   12-23 0520</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Noriega-Surroundings, Bjt,520</SECOND>
<HEAD>Photos of Mother Teresa and Hitler Found in Noriega's Quarters</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDITOR'S NOTE: The following is based on pool dispatches.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEVEN KOMAROW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   American troops who stormed Gen.
Manuel Antonio Noriega's quarters found photographs of Adolf Hitler
and Mother Teresa, a voodoo witches' brewery and a packet of
cocaine wrapped in a banana leaf, U.S. officers say.
   The ousted dictator's homes and offices also contained items
ranging from Christmas trees to high-powered arms as well as a
collection of pornography, Gen. Maxwell Thurman, commander of the
U.S. Southern Command, and other officers told reporters Friday.
   A bucket in an upstairs bathroom of one house was filled with a
rusty-red looking substance identified as blood. An officer said he
did not know what kind of creature the blood came from or what it
was used for.
   Officers said soldiers who burst into the house on the first day
of the U.S. intervention here Tuesday narrowly missed capturing
four voodoo witches from Brazil.
   The so-called ``witch house,'' a fortified structure specially
built for Noriega, contained such voodoo artifacts as dead fish
adorned with yellow ribbons, two bowls of popcorn cluttered with
dead flowers, and broken statues.
   ``This was the brewery for the witches, if you will,'' said Col.
Mike Snell, the officer in charge of the area.
   Thurman said the ``voodoo practitioners ... practiced rituals
for Noriega's protection.''
   The banana leaf with the cocaine inside it was found in a
freezer. Snell said it was part of 50 pounds of the drug found in
Noriega's quarters.
   The general's office in Panama's military barracks at Fort
Amador had two display cases containing plastic frogs, electronic
toys such as a video wristwatch and framed pictures of Hitler,
Mother Teresa and Libyan leader Moammar Ghadafi. His downtown
office was adorned with Christmas trees, more electronics and more
frogs.
   Pornography was found at both offices, Snell said.
   Sgt. 1st Class Joseph Torregrossa said the Fort Amador office
also contained expensive prints and ``a lot of expensive weapons,
mostly automatic. He had German Lugers, Israeli Uzis, all sorts of
real sophisticated stuff.''
   Thurman told reporters, ``He was clearly dedicated to outfitting
a substantial force, outfitting dignity battalions, which in the
long run would have given the U.S. a tremendous challenge in this
area.''
   U.S. intelligence officials scoured the offices in the hope of
finding records that would help trace Noriega's assets. In
Washington, Justice Department spokesman David Runkel said
financial documents seized by the troops in Noriega's offices might
help authorities trace assets and bank holdings stashed in foreign
countries.
   Snell said Noriega had been spotted at the house during the last
several months.
   He said the house was searched for booby traps after pipe bombs
were found in it.
   Lt. Curtis Vinyard said the house had apparently been occupied
until shortly before it was stormed by U.S. troops.
   ``There was still a candle burning,'' he said.
   The house, on the seacoast near here and close to several U.S.
military bases, was stormed by U.S. soldiers on Tuesday, about six
hours after the U.S. invasion began.
</TEXT>

</DOC>