<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1023EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Poland     12-30 0485</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Poland,0502</SECOND>
<HEAD>Parliament Changes Poland's Name, Drops Communists' Leading Role</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH G. SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Parliament today restored Poland's
historic name that had been changed by the Communists 45 years ago,
and amended the constitution to drop the leading role of the
Communist Party in state affairs.
   Senators rose and sang ``God Who Watches Over Poland'' and the
national anthem after voting 79-0 with two abstentions to make the
constitutional changes.
   Parliament's lower house, the Sejm, had approved the changes
Friday by a vote of 374-1 with 11 abstentions. Senate approval is
needed for measures to become law.
   The Senate vote confirmed restoration of the Republic of Poland
as the country's official name from the People's Republic of Poland
imposed when the Communist Party took power in 1944.
   On Friday, the Senate approved 11 economic laws passed on two
previous days by the Sejm which were backed by the Solidarity-led
government and aim to create a market-economy and reduce inflation.
   The amendments restore democratic language and traditions,
changing a phrase that called Poland a ``socialist society'' to a
``citizens' society.''
   The Senate also favored the Sejm decision to restore the crown
that symbolizes Polish sovereignty and unity that graced the head
of the eagle on the national emblem until the Communist takeover.
   After the Senate vote, an eagle with a crown brought two weeks
earlier by an unknown farmer was hung in the Senate hall.
   The farmer, who name was not noted when he made the gift to the
Senate's Human Rights Commission, said the eagle was the only
souvenir he had of his father.
   The amendments give citizens the right to create political
parties. Until now, the Communist Party, the Democratic Party and
the Peasant Party were the only legally recognized parties.
   The ammended constitution now guarantees protection of private
property.
   The amendments eliminate or modify articles which are
inconsistent with democratic reform until a new constitution can be
written.
   The critical pieces of legislation include two key laws on
unemployment designed to protect workers. The government estimates
that as many as 400,000 people could become unemployed as a result
of the radical economic program.
   The other new laws regulate activities of the National Bank,
credit policy, joint ventures, foreign capital, hard currency,
customs, and taxation.
   The hard currency law aims to create internal convertibility of
the zloty which means Poles eventually will be able to use zlotys
in hard currency stores that now exist throughout Poland.
   Another goal of the law is to make the zloty a convertible
currency on the world market, but first the official rate of the
zloty must converge with an unofficial legal rate. Finance ministry
officials say this must happen gradually.
   On Wednesday, Parliament passed a law regulating financing of
state enterprises and one limiting the growth of wages, a measure
designed to hold down inflation now running at 900 percent.
</TEXT>

</DOC>