<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0329EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Japan-Markets     12-18 0373</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Japan-Markets,0384</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar Dips, Stocks At Another Record High</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dollar fell slightly against the Japanese yen
today, while the key index on the Tokyo Stock Exchange closed at a
record high for the fourth consecutive trading day.
   The dollar finished trading at 144.22 yen, down 0.08 yen from
Friday's close of 144.30 yen. After opening at 144.30 yen, its high
for the day, the U.S. currency ranged as low as 144.10 yen in quiet
trading.
   Dealers said trading was mixed, reflecting the market's usual
slowdown at the end of the year.
   They said market attention was focused on the dollar and the
mark today because of the dollar's early volatility against the
West German currency.
   A dealer at a major Japanese bank said there was some
dollar-selling by trust banks, but with most participants already
having fixed their positions in advance of the New Year's holidays,
he said the U.S currency was likely to stay in a very narrow range.
   Participants said prospects for an interest rate reduction by
the U.S. Federal Reserve Board this week were good, after Friday's
reports showed U.S. producer prices falling 0.1 percent in November
after rising 0.4 percent in October, but said the market had
already largely discounted the expected move.
   On the stock market, the Nikkei Stock Average of 225 selected
issues, which gained 90.34 points for a record-high closing on
Friday, added another 315.14 points, or 0.82 percent, to close at
38,586.18.
   It was the sixth consecutive advance for the Nikkei index, which
has set new highs for four straight days since Wednesday.
   Securities dealers said the index continued to soar as the
market's enthusiasm outpaced some profit-taking by cautious
investors.
   While shares rose almost across the board, the rises in
construction and petroleum shares were particularly notable,
dealers said.
   Dealers attributed the Nikkei's continuing rise to favorable
economic and political conditions worldwide, and the strong showing
of the futures market.
   ``I would not be surprised if this bullish trend lasts until the
end of the year,'' said a dealer at a major securites company,
speaking on condition of anonymity.
   Volume traded on the first section of the exchange, where major
shares are listed, was estimated at 850 million shares.
</TEXT>

</DOC>