<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0146 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1835EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CounterfeitShoes     12-29 0551</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Counterfeit Shoes,0568</SECOND>
<HEAD>International Counterfeit Shoe Ring Cracked</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PN4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM F. RAWSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The indictment of 18 people by a federal grand
jury has broken up a ``worldwide conspiracy'' that made and
marketed millions of counterfeit name-brand athletic shoes, a
federal prosecutor said Friday.
   Federal agents executed arrest and seizure warrants ``throughout
the country'' on Thursday and Friday, winding up a 4{-month
investigation directed by agents from the U.S. Customs Service
office in Nogales, Ariz., said U.S. Attorney Stephen McNamee.
   The 18 defendants are charged with violating U.S. trademark laws
and money-laundering, McNamee said.
   McNamee said federal agents have seized $4.5 million in cash and
other assets from defendants in the case.
   He said authorities in Chile and Mexico also made arrests in the
case.
   McNamee was uncertain whether any or all of the defendants
arrested in other countries would be extradited to the United
States, but said both Mexico and Chile had been cooperating in the
investigation and that cooperation was being sought from other
governments as well.
   The indictment, returned Wednesday in Tucson and unsealed
Friday, alleges that South Korean businessman Dae Yun Hwang is the
head of the operation. Three other South Koreans also were
indicted, McNamee said.
   At least seven of the defendants had been arrested by mid-day
Friday, McNamee said. He did not say which seven were in custody
and did not know if any of the Koreans had been arrested.
   McNamee said the counterfit shoes were made in Hwang's South
Korean factories and smuggled into the United States and other
countries, where they were marketed with such brand-name labels as
Reeboks, Vans, Converse, Avia, Tiger, Puma, Adidas, L.A. Gear,
Nike, Pony and Jordache.
   The shoes were sold through major retail organizations, he said.
   He said the investigation began Aug. 4 when Mexican customs
refused to allow 40 cartons of shoes to cross the border from
Nogales.
   U.S. Customs agents examined the shipment and found that it
contained counterfeit shoes bearing a number of brand-name lables.
The shipment was seized and a nationwide investigation was launched.
   Harley Lewin, a New York lawyer representing Converse, Reebok
and Van Doren Rubber Co., maker of Vans, said his clients have
filed two civil actions in federal court in San Diego seeking a
total of $12 million in damages.
   ``We think that over a period of two years, in excess of two
million pairs of shoes were counterfeited,'' he said.
   All of those named in the two lawsuits were among those listed
in the federal indictment, Lewin said.
   U.S. Attorney General Dick Thornburgh called the indictment and
arrests ``a notable victory against international consumer fraud,
money laundering and smuggling.''
   ``Criminal activity is increasingly international in scope, and
we are responding in kind with law-enforcement activities on a
world-wide basis,'' Thornburgh said in a statement.
   In addition to Hwang, McNamee identified those named in the
indictment as B.S. Kim, M.K. Kim and H.S. Tae, all of South Korea;
San Diego residents Byron McLaughlin, Debbie Watson, Celeste Cota,
Nathan Betech, Marcos Betech, Abraham Betech, Isaac Paz and
Herminia Ascensio; Glenn McLaughlin of Iquique, Chile; Roman Trenka
of San Juan, Puerto Rico; Dudley W. Miller III of Boston; Sol
Weisenberg of Cincinnati; Natalie Ann Quaratino of Mexico City; and
Jorge Fitch Lazaro of Guaymas, Mexico.
</TEXT>

</DOC>