<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 0439EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Philippines-Kidnapping 1stLd-Writethru   12-31 0377</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Philippines-Kidnapping, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0629,0387</SECOND>
<HEAD>Precede: MANILA</HEAD>
<HEAD>French Missionary, Niece Kidnapped in Southern Philippines</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: UPDATES with new details, CORRECTS place of kidnapping and identity
of previous kidnappers</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MARAWI CITY, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gunmen believed to be Moslem
bandits kidnapped a French missionary and his niece in the southern
Philippines, and police killed one of the abductors in a firefight,
police and church officials said Sunday.
   The Rev. Michel de Gigord and his 29-year-old niece, Benedict,
were abducted Saturday after leaving Saint Mary's Convent in
Marawi, 510 miles southeast of Manila. said the Rev. Leo Laviste,
Vicar General of Archdiocese of Iligan and Marawi cities.
   Laviste said they have not yet heard from the kidnappers.
   Laviste said de Gigord, was driving his niece toward Iligan
City, 20 miles to the north, when six armed men stopped their car
near the convent's gate.
   One of the gunmen shoved de Gigord from the driver's seat and,
followed by a jeep boarded by the other kidnappers, drove the
priest's car to the shores of nearby Lanao Lake and sent the two
victims by boat to an island in the lake, Laviste said.
   Neighbors who saw the abduction immediately informed authorities
in the convent who notified the local police.
   Pursuing policemen engaged in a gunbattle with some of the
gunmen who had been left behind on the lakeshore, killing one of
them, Marawi police station commander Capt. Jalandoni Cota. He said
the others escaped.
   Police also recovered de Gigord's vehicle, abandoned by the
kidnappers. There was no report on what happened to the kidnapper's
jeep.
   Sources at the Lanao del Sur provincial military and police
headquarters said the victims have been moved by the kidnappers to
the town of Madamba, 23 miles west of Marawi, late Sunday morning.
   Provincial commander Lt. Col. Omar Manabilang has sought the
assistance of the mayors of Madamba and two adjacent towns and
local Moslem religious leaders to help rescue the priest and his
niece, the sources said.
   De Gigord, a member of the Paris Foreign Mission, has been
chaplain at the Mindanao State University in Marawi for the past 10
years. He was kidnapped by Moslem bandits in February 1985 and held
captive for about a month in their mountain hideout but was
released unharmed.
</TEXT>

</DOC>