<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1415EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Turkey-GreekChurch     12-17 0331</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Turkey-Greek Church,0343</SECOND>
<HEAD>Greek Orthodox Building Reopens in Turkey After 48-Year Dispute</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VEDAT ERDAMAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ISTANBUL, Turkey (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Greek Orthodox Church celebrated
Mass on Sunday in a 16th-century building that it finally restored
after settling a long dispute with the Turkish government with the
help of Jimmy Carter.
   Patriarch Dimitrios II, who led the service, said the reopening
of the refurbished building, which was severely damaged by fire 48
years ago, could help improve relations between Greece and Turkey.
   More than 1,500 people, including representatives from 13
Eastern Orthodox churches around the world, attended the Mass at
the Patriarchal Church of St. George. The celebrants included 400
people from Greece, including four government ministers and two
former premiers.
   The ceremony was broadcast by the state-run ERT television of
Greece.
   Turkey's tourism minister, Ilhan Akuzum, also attended.
   In his address, Dimitrios said he hoped the inauguration of the
building would contribute to the development of peace between
Greece and Turkey, which have been bitter enemies since Turkey
occupied the northern part of Cyprus since 1974.
   Greece's state minister, Nikos Temelis, said after the ceremony
that his country would work toward furthering cooperation between
the two nations.
   A message of congratulations was sent by former President
Carter, who helped obtain the Turkish government's permission to
rebuild the four-story wooden structure, which houses offices and a
small church.
   The building was gutted by fire in 1941. An adjacent building
has been used as the church's offices since then.
   The Turkish government for years denied repeated requests for
permits to rebuild, saying the Greek government had refused similar
project requests by the Turkish-Moslem minority in Western Thrace.
But the Greek Orthodox church was finally granted permission in
1987 after the intercession of Carter and Archbishop Iakovas of
Americas during 1986 visits.
   Turkey, a predominantly Moslem country, is a secular state.
   There are 5,000 ethnic Greeks living in Istanbul, down from
100,000 when the republic was set up in 1923.
</TEXT>

</DOC>