<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0189 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1751EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s f BC-Canada-Trade Adv31   12-27 0937</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Canada-Trade, Adv 31,0968</SECOND>
<HEAD>One Year Later, Some Canadians Grump Over Free Trade Agreement</HEAD>
<HEAD>Graphic in AP Access under CANTRADE</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SOLL SUSSMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TORONTO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The furor that marked approval of the free trade
agreement with the United States has subsided, but critics in
Canada blame the year-old pact for bad economic news ranging from
unemployment to a big rise in imports.
   The agreement's supporters, just as adamantly, credit it with
operating smoothly and preparing the way for growth.
   The pact that took effect on Jan. 1, 1989, phases out over a
10-year period virtually all remaining tariffs in the world's
largest trading partnership. Most analysts agree that no method has
been devised to measure its early effects accurately.
   ``I think the concrete ways to measure it are difficult at this
point,'' said Jim deWilde, a professor at the University of Western
Ontario's business school. ``It's an adjustment in the way Canada
and the United States conduct a very large trading relationship.''
   ``It's going to be very difficult to calculate the precise
impact,'' economist Alan Rugman of the University of Toronto said.
   The value of two-way trade in goods grew dramatically during the
past decade, more than doubling from $76.85 billion in 1980 to
$153.02 billion in 1988, U.S. Commerce Department figures show.
   In all of those years, the United States bought more goods from
Canada than the Canadians bought in return, netting Canada a trade
surplus that helped restrain inflation and keep people working.
   Canada's Parliament approved the pact only after a heated
election campaign dominated by the trade debate returned Prime
Minister Brian Mulroney's Progressive Conservative Party for a
second consecutive majority government.
   Mulroney argued that the agreement he had signed with
then-President Reagan would ensure Canada's access to the vastly
larger U.S. market at a time when protectionism was increasing
around the world.
   His opponents insisted the pact was unnecessary because 80
percent of U.S.-Canadian trade already was tariff-free. By lowering
the remaining barriers, the opponents argued, Canada would be
swamped culturally and economically by its more populous, powerful
southern neighbor.
   The argument lingers on.
   ``The fact is, when choices have to be made between saving
Canadian and American jobs, multinational firms sacrifice Canadian
jobs every time,'' John Turner, leader of the opposition Liberal
Party, told Parliament in early December following a flurry of
announcements about plant closings and layoffs.
   Finance Minister Michael Wilson replied that any job losses are
unfortunate, ``but we have to realize we have a dynamic economy.
There are jobs that are being created every day, there are jobs
being lost every day.''
   The Canadian Labor Congress, a key opponent of the trade
agreement, has a list of 70,000 jobs lost in plant closings and
layoffs this year, by such companies as Gerber, General Electric
and Burlington Industries.
   Maude Barlow, head of the nationalistic Council of Canadians
that opposes the agreement, said the trends sending jobs to U.S.
over Canadian operations are clear even if not every layoff can be
traced directly to free trade.
   A survey taken for the national news weekly Maclean's at yearend
found that 52 percent of Canadians think the free trade agreement
is a bad idea, up from 32 percent a year ago. But, while 42 percent
of Canadians a year ago believed that free trade was the most
important issue facing the country, only 7 percent believe that now.
   The persistent criticism of the trade agreement parallels
evidence of an economic slowdown in Canada, with some warnings of
an imminent recession.
   Canada's healthy trade balance, historically considered a sign
of economic strength, showed a monthly deficit in October, the
first time that has happened in more than 13 years.
   Federal officials attributed the $362 million shortfall partly
to the high value of the Canadian dollar, which makes imports
cheaper and Canadian goods more expensive. Government critics
blamed the trade agreement.
   ``Is this what the prime minister meant when he said that his
trade deal would make our trade more and more secure?'' Turner
asked.
   Mulroney replied that the deficit reflected increased imports of
capital goods and machinery, which he said will help Canada
restructure its industries and exploit the free trade pact more
effectively.
   The agreement not only phases out tariffs but also creates new
ways to settle trade disputes and eases investment and the movement
of employees between the two countries.
   Canada and the United States agreed recently that the pact was
working well enough to merit acceleration of tariff cuts on an
additional $6 billion worth of trade starting April 1.
   ``Overall, we're extremely satisfied,'' Trade Minister John
Crosbie said Nov. 30 after the second meeting of the Free Trade
Commission created by the pact.
   ``It's remarkable how well it is working and what few disputes
we have,'' U.S. trade representative Carla Hills told reporters at
the meeting in Ottawa.
   Although the impact of the trade agreement may be difficult to
measure, companies now refer to it regularly in their planning.
   ``It's accelerated the need for Canadian corporate strategists
to think about the performance of their companies in a larger
context,'' said deWilde, of the Western Ontario business school in
London, Ontario.
   Arthur Church, president of Champion Road Machinery Ltd., said
his company has started to examine Japanese management techniques
and take other steps to increase productivity as his larger U.S.
competitors discover the Canadian market.
   ``I truly believe that before free trade many of our American
competitors did not know where Canada was,'' he said at a forum for
exporters. ``We can complain, or we can do something about it.''
  
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End adv for Sunday Dec. 31.</NOTE>

</DOC>