<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0119 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2012EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Namibia     12-21 0356</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Namibia,0367</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cabinet Will Have Whites, Businessmen, Opposition Parties</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WINDHOEK, Namibia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sam Nujoma, expected to be Namibia's
first president, on Thursday named a white, a businessman and
opposition party members to a Cabinet that will take power when the
territory becomes independent next year.
   The announcement was seen as the latest move by Nujoma and his
South-West Africa People's Organization to bring about
reconciliation in the territory wracked by 23 years of war against
South African rule.
   Leftist SWAPO captured last month's U.N.-supervised elections.
The seven parties represented in the constituent assembly reached
tentative agreement Wednesday on a constitution, and independence
is likely to be declared in March, according to most observers.
   Nujoma named 14 of the 16 Cabinet posts, but did not fill the
agriculture or wildlife ministries. Nujoma, a virtual certainty to
become president, also left the prime minister's post open for the
time being.
   The most prominent jobs all went to leading SWAPO members.
   But Nujoma also named Reinhold Rukoro of the Namibia National
Front as deputy minister of justice and Reggie Diergaardt of the
United Democratic Front as deputy minister for trade and industry.
   Also, a white accountant with no party affiliation, Gert
Hanekom, was named auditor general. Zed Ngavirue, chairman of a
private mining company, will head the National Planning Commission.
   Leftist SWAPO holds 41 of the 72 seats in the assembly. The
Democratic Turnhalle Alliance, a multiracial coalition that favors
a capitalist economy, has 21 seats. The remaining 10 seats are
divided among five other parties.
   The draft constitution has a declaration of fundamental rights,
including freedom of movement, speech and a free press. It also
envisions a multiparty democracy, regular elections for two houses
of Parliament, an executive president and an independent judiciary.
   SWAPO waged a bush war against South African rule of the
territory from 1966 until April of this year.
   South Africa, which captured Namibia from Germany in 1915, will
continue to administer the territory until independence. However,
it has withdrawn all its troops.
   The more than 6,000 U.N. military and civilian personnel in
Namibia are scheduled to remain until the end of March.
</TEXT>

</DOC>