<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1042EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-Noriega-Secrecy     12-22 0702</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Noriega-Secrecy,1st Ld-Writethru, a0431,650</SECOND>
<HEAD>Noriega Would Raise CIA Connection At Drug Trial</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: SUBS 4th graf pvs bgng: ``At the same'' to clarify that officials
don't expect any of the charges to be scuttled by secrecy issues</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES ROWLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Manuel Antonio Noriega's longstanding
relationship with the CIA could pose problems for federal
prosecutors if the deposed Panamanian strongman is caught and
brought to trial on U.S. drug trafficking charges, government
sources say.
   Federal prosecutors expect Noriega would try to force the
government to drop charges against him by seeking court disclosure
of classified information that he was an informant for the spy
agency, these officials added.
   Such an approach would mirror the legal defense strategy used by
Oliver North and others with some success in the Iran-Contra
affair, in which independent counsel Lawrence E. Walsh was forced
to drop some key charges when the government refused to allow
disclosure of secrets in open court.
   At the same time, Justice Department officials said Thursday
they do not expect the secrecy problems in Noriega's case to
scuttle any of the charges that the Panamanian helped Colombian
drug lords smuggle cocaine and marijuana through Panama to this
country.
   Noriega was indicted in 1988 by grand juries in Miami and Tampa,
Fla.
   Prosecutors are anticipating that Noriega will claim that his
alleged drug activities were sanctioned by the U.S. government
because he was a CIA informant.
   But the government is prepared to offer evidence that none of
the drug-trafficking activity was approved by the U.S. government,
said one source, speaking on condition of anonymity. Prosecutors
will argue that just because Noriega may have been an informant for
the CIA or the Drug Enforcement Administration he is not immune
from criminal prosecution, the source said.
   The secrecy issues involving Noriega's case were among the items
discussed at a meeting about the case Dec. 15 attended by
prosecutors, top officials of the Justice Department's criminal
division and other law enforcement agents, said spokesman David
Runkel.
   Officials decided at that meeting to try Noriega first on
charges filed in Miami that he took a $4.6 million bribe from
Colombia's Medellin cartel to protect cocaine-smuggling and
money-laundering operations in Panama.
   Runkel said last week's meeting had been scheduled for several
weeks and was not convened in anticipation of the U.S. invasion of
Panama.
   The secrecy problems in Noriega's case were termed
``manageable'' by one official, who spoke on condition of
anonymity. But the official quickly conceded that Iran-Contra
prosecutors probably thought the same thing about their case
against former White House aide North.
   Walsh was forced to drop major charges that North conspired to
divert U.S.-Iran arms sale proceeds to the Nicaraguan rebels,
because the government wouldn't release information deemed relevant
to the defense. The Classified Information Procedures Act empowers
judges to dismiss criminal charges if the government refuses to
allow the disclosure of secrets needed for a trial.
   North was convicted of charges that he tried to cover up his
involvement in the Iran-Contra affair. But all Iran-Contra charges
against a former CIA agent, Joseph Fernandez, were dismissed
recently when the Bush administration blocked disclosure of
classified information.
   In Noriega's case, ``there is certainly going to be a CIPA
problem,'' said Victoria Toensing, a former senior Justice
Department official who now practices law in Washington.
   ``When people are saying he was on the CIA payroll, then you are
going to have the more complicated level that some of these things
regarding sources and methods are classified,'' she said.
   Before Noriega was indicted in 1988, prosecutors consulted with
the CIA and other intelligence agencies, said a government source,
who spoke on condition of anonymity. The agencies posed no
objections to proceeding with the case, the source said.
   Between the Miami and Tampa cases, Noriega is charged with
pocketing some $10 million in bribes and commissions for protecting
money-laundering and smuggling operations in Panama.
   Runkel said the Justice Department decided that Noriega would be
tried first on the charges in Miami because prosecutors there have
a stronger case.
   If convicted of all the charges against him, Noriega faces a
possible sentence of 145 years in prison and more than $1.1 million
in fines.
</TEXT>

</DOC>