<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0211 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2130EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Romania     12-20 0299</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Romania,0308</SECOND>
<HEAD>Moldavians Ask Congress to Appeal for Reason</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Moldavian delegates, worried about their ethnic
brethren in Romania, asked the Soviet Congress on Wednesday to
appeal for ``reason and order'' there.
   Ion Drutse, a well-known Moldavian poet, said the Stalinist
regime of President Nicolae Ceausescu might embark on a new wave of
repression against Romanians seeking greater democracy.
   ``It would cost him nothing to build his palace of the skulls of
his subjects,'' Drutse told a reporter in the lobby of the
Kremlin's Palace of Congresses.
   Anti-government protests began last weekend in Timisoara, a city
of 350,000 people in Transylvania, western Romania. Estimates of
the number of people killed by Ceausescu's security forces reach
the thousands.
   Soviet Moldavia, a small repubic of about 4 million people, is
on Romania's eastern border. Moldavians are essentially ethnic
Romanians whose territory has gone back and forth, last falling
into the Soviet sphere during World War II. The declaration
proposed by the Moldavian legislators expresses hope that ``all
problems will be solved in the framework of reason and order'' and
through dialogue between the Romanian government and population,
Drutse said.
   Moldavians said they asked the Congress leadership to put the
declaration up for a vote, but it had not been done by Wednesday
evening.
   Drutse said he believed passing the declaration could help ease
tension in Romania because every ``tyrant is afraid of something.''
   The Soviet Union has made no move toward intervening in its
ally's affairs.
   Foreign Ministry spokesman Vadim Perfiliev said Wednesday a
``massive flow of information'' made it hard to judge what was
happening in Romania, but if reports of loss of life were
confirmed, ``this is a reason for profound regret.''
   Official media have taken a critical tone toward Ceausescu's
Stalinist regime.
</TEXT>

</DOC>