<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0165 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 2128EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-RatArt     12-29 0443</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rat Art,0460</SECOND>
<HEAD>Artist To Mash Rat on Canvas? Rat for Rat's Sake, Says Humane Society</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Note contents may be offensive to some readers.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VANCOUVER, British Columbia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The humane society says it
will oppose an artist's plan to snuff his pet rat Sniffy by
flattening it with a 55-pound concrete block.
   Actually, two canvases would be created in smashing the rat: One
under the hapless rodent and one on the block Rick Gibson plans to
drop onto his pet next week.
   ``I'm giving a public demonstration, a free art lesson, to show
people how they could do this themselves,'' Rick Gibson said
Friday. ``People will be able to crush other creatures in the
comfort of their own homes sort of thing to see what sort of
patterns they get.''
   Ah, but is it art?
   Gibson insists the killing will be humane and legal, and Sniffy
will be well-cared for right up to the end. ``I have no desire to
mistreat him at all. I'm going to be treating him humanely at all
times,'' he said.
   Ingrid Pollack of the Vancouver Humane Society said the killing
would be ridiculous and sick. She said the society will try to halt
Gibson's plans.
   Gibson has created a guillotine-like apparatus to execute his
plan. There is a cage for the rat on the bottom. The weight slides
down a pole. He tested it on a squash.
   ``I've had this idea mulling around in my mind for some time,''
Gibson said.
   He plans to roll the apparatus in front of the Vancouver Library
on Jan. 6 for a Saturday afternoon performance for a few of his
friends.
   Killing a rat for art is no worse than trapping or poisoning it
as a pest, Gibson said.
   He bought Sniffy from a pet shop and says it otherwise probably
would have ended up as a meal for a snake or a lizard.
   ``For the life of me I can't tell the difference between what
I'm doing and what they do when they have rats in the house,''
Gibson said. ``So I don't know what the fuss is about, if there is
any.''
   Gibson, 38, recently returned to Canada after six years in
England. He plans to return in February to appeal a conviction for
outraging public decency by making earrings out of freeze-dried
human fetal tissue.
   In Vancouver last July, Gibson said, police stopped him from
consuming a slice of human testicle he acquired from a medical
supply store. He said he was able to complete the art performance
in September.
   ``I just wanted to be the first cannibal in Vancouver to go
public,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>