<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0166 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 2030EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WKD--RecordReviews Adv00   12-26 0590</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--Record Reviews, Adv 00,0613</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv 00</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Anytime</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WEEKEND ENTERTAINMENT AND ARTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>In the Groove: Record Review</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   ``Louder Than Love'' (A&amp;M) _ Soundgarden
   
   The future of heavy metal is here and its name is Soundgarden.
   On ``Louder Than Love,'' its debut album for a major label, the
Seattle-based quartet has stripped the genre down to its
bare-knuckled essentials _ loud guitar, shrieking vocals and
crashing drums. It's loud, but it is by no means just noise.
   The Parents Music Resource Center obviously broke out in a cold
sweat over the repetition of ``gonna kill your mother'' in the
cynical ``Hands All Over,'' hence the album's warning sticker. But
the PMRC didn't bother to read a little deeper into the lyrics,
which are really a commentary on the destruction of the
environment: The ``mother'' becomes Mother Earth.
   Soundgarden responds, though, when lead singer Chris Cornell
sings: ``Hands all over words I utter _ Change them into what you
want to _ Like balls of clay.''
   And yes, obscenities are chanted about a zillion times in ``Big
Dumb Sex,'' but that's the point _ the song is a wicked, Spinal
Tap-ish blast at all the big dumb sex songs floating around the
radio. It seems as if Soundgarden figured that everyone else beats
around the bush about sex in their songs, so we might as well say
exactly what our intentions are.
   On tracks such as ``Gun'' and ``Power Trip,'' the band points
out the problems that arise when power surfaces in violence and
exploitation.
   The biting ``I Awake'' looks at an abusive relationship from the
viewpoint of the abuser. Cornell sings: ``You have a good day _
It's not your fault _ I know it hurts.'' The real kicker comes in
the repeated line, ``Remember I love you.''
   Soundgarden follows the path blazed by Metallica and Jane's
Addiction in reminding listeners that we don't live in a pretty
world. It's a shame that their music, like that of Metallica and
Jane's Addiction, will probably make the radio waves.
   _ By Kira L. Billik, Associated Press Writer.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   
   ``In the Land of Salvation and Sin'' (Elektra) _ The Georgia
Satellites
   
   Give the Georgia Satellites credit for candor _ they make no
attempt to camouflage their many influences.
   The liner notes for ``In the Land of Salvation and Sin'' salute,
among others, Hank Williams Jr., the Replacements and Tom Petty and
the Heartbreakers. The songs recall, among others, Steve Earle
(``Bottle O' Tears''), Lynyrd Skynyrd (``All Over But the Cryin''')
and the Rolling Stones (``Stellazine Blues'').
   There's nothing wrong with a few borrowed riffs when they're
well used, and ``Salvation and Sin'' is a solid set. It sounds like
a tight bar band on a good night.
   Lead songwriter Dan Baird, while not terribly original,
nonetheless has talent. His two ballads, ``Another Chance'' and
``Sweet Blue Midnight,'' are particularly appealing. The former is
about growing older (``Don't want to die asking for another
chance''); the latter, with Nicolette Larson providing lovely
harmony vocals, concerns the search for comfort amid life's
uncertainties.
   Most of Baird's uptempo tunes work, too, with drummer Mauro
Magellan and bassist Rick Price usually able to find a groove.
   The Georgia Satellites' potential likely is limited because of
Baird's singing and Rick Richards' slide guitar _ both are
nondescript performers. But Baird's songwriting and the band's
ability to distill their diverse influences make ``Salvation and
Sin'' worth a listen.
   _ By Steven Wine, Associated Press Writer.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Release Anytime</NOTE>

</DOC>