<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0146 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1454EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-UN     12-20 0575</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-UN,0593</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Says it Acted in Self-Defense in Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER JAMES SPIELMANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>UNITED NATIONS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. Ambassador Thomas R. Pickering said
Wednesday the United States acted in self-defense when it sent its
military forces to Panama to oust military leader Gen. Manuel
Antonio Noriega from power.
   Alejandro Serrano Caldera, the ambassador of Nicaragua, which
called for an emergency Security Council meeting, retorted that
``the United States has no legal or ethical right to intervene in
other countries' affairs.''
   Speaking outside the council chambers, Serrano Caldera said the
Panamanian people ``have the right to self-determination; this
action by the United States violated the sovereignty of the
Panamanian people.''
   ``We want the council to call for an immediate withdrawal of the
U.S. troops,'' Serrano Caldera said, speaking in Spanish.
   Nicaragua's U.N. mission announced the Sandinista government had
declared a national alert and mobilized troops against what
President Daniel Ortega said was Washington's ``serious threat
against Nicaragua.''
   Security Council ambassadors met individually in the morning and
scheduled private consultations for the rest of the day; it was
unclear whether a formal, public meeting would be held.
   Pickering said the United States had the right to intervene
under Article 51 of the U.N. Charter, ``which provides for the use
of armed force to defend a country, to defend our interests and our
people, it's the so-called `self-defense article.'''
   Panamanian soldiers shot and killed a U.S. Marine officer at a
roadblock on Saturday night.
   Panama's declaration last week that a ``state of war'' existed
with the United States and ``the attacks on our citizens over the
weekend are several of the things which the president has cited
which required us to move in self-defense,'' Pickering said.
   Article 51 of the Charter permits the use of ``individual or
collective self-defense if an armed attack occurs against a member
of the United Nations, until the Security Council has taken
measures necessary to maintain international peace and security.''
   Pickering said he was talking with council members and favored
more consultations before any public meeting is held.
   White House press secretary Marlin Fitzwater said President Bush
ordered U.S. troops to seize Noriega and bring him to the United
States for trial on drug trafficking charges.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III informed Secretary-General
Javier Perez de Cuellar of the military moves at 2 a.m. Wednesday,
said the U.N. chief's spokesman, Francois Giuliani.
   Perez de Cuellar is ``extremely concerned'' about the crisis,
Giuliani said.
   Panama repeatedly has come before the Security Council to
complain of allegedly provocative U.S. military maneuvers it said
were intended to lay the groundwork for an invasion to topple the
government.
   In August, Panamanian Foreign Minister Jorge Ritter asked the
council to send military observers to his country to prevent the
U.S. Army from goading confrontations as a pretext for armed
intervention.
   U.N. military observers, said Ritter, ``will insure that the
reality of the situation cannot be hidden and it will be recorded
in the annals of history as a crime.''
   However, Panama did not have any nation on the council introduce
a resolution to send observers, a necessary step toward sending a
mission.
   Panama said in April and August that the United States is trying
to provoke confrontations in order to keep control of the Panama
Canal. Under a 1977 treaty, the United States is to turn over
control of the canal to Panama at the end of 1999.
</TEXT>

</DOC>