<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0813EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-Glance     12-20 0419</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Glance,0434</SECOND>
<HEAD>Troubled Land at the Midsection of the Hemisphere</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are some facts and figures on Panama:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   THE LAND _ Panama is an S-shaped tropical isthmus that links
Central America and South America. It is bordered on the west by
Costa Rica and on the east by Colombia. It is slightly larger in
area than the state of West Virginia.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   THE PEOPLE _ The country has 2.2 million people, 70 percent of
them a mixture of Spanish and Indian descendants. Fourteen percent
are West Indian, 10 percent are Caucasian and 6 percent Indian.
Spanish is the official language but English is widely spoken. The
main religion is Roman Catholicism.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   THE GOVERNMENT _ The government had been nominally headed by
provisional President Francisco Rodriguez, who took office Sept. 1.
But the real leader was Defense Forces chief Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noriega who last week assumed the title of head of state. He
inherited command of the military from Gen. Omar Torrijos, who
seized power in 1968 and died in a plane crash in 1981.
   Noriega engineered the ouster of President Eric Arturo Delvalle
in February 1988. Delvalle had tried to fire Noriega, who was
indicted in Florida on federal drug trafficking and money
laundering charges. Noriega has denied the charges.
   The United States, which has continued to recognize Delvalle,
imposed economic sanctions on Panama in an effort to force Noriega
from power.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   THE CANAL _ The 51-mile Panama Canal, connecting the Atlantic
and Pacific oceans, was built by the United States from 1904 to
1914 on territory leased from Panama. Treaties signed by
then-President Carter and Torrijos in 1977 transfer control of the
canal and its defense to Panama on Dec. 31, 1999.
   The 10-mile-wide canal zone was turned over to Panama after the
treaties went into effect in 1979.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   THE ECONOMY _ Panama was a leading international financial
center with about 120 banks holding an estimated $30 billion in
assets. But a flight of capital caused by the political struggle
over Noriega's rule has sharply reduced assets to about $8 billion,
according to government figures.
   U.S. officials have complained that secret bank accounts the
country offered as business enticements helped make Panama a haven
for illegally laundered drug money.
   Opposition leaders say unemployment last year more than doubled
to 23 percent. The country's main crops are bananas, pineapples,
cocoa, corn, coconuts and sugar. The official currency is the
dollar, but it is called the balboa.
</TEXT>

</DOC>