<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0349EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-HowardBeach     12-27 0447</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Howard Beach,0460</SECOND>
<HEAD>Riot Charges Overturned in Second Howard Beach Trial</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RONALD POWERS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A state appeals court has overturned the
misdemeanor riot convictions of three young men in the Howard Beach
racial killing and dismissed the indictments against them, saying
the trial judge committed two errors.
   Prosecutors either can appeal, resubmit evidence to a grand jury
for new indictments or dismiss the case against the three white
defendants.
   ``We are studying the opinion and we are considering a further
appeal, and that's as far as we are going to comment at this
particular point,'' Matthew Greenberg, a special assistant attorney
general, said Tuesday.
   The 19-year-old defendants _ William Bollander, Thomas Farino
and James Povinelli _ were charged with taking part in the attack
on three black men three years ago in the mainly white Howard Beach
section of Queens.
   One of the victims, Michael Griffith, was killed when the mob
chased him onto a highway where he was struck by a car.
   The three young men whose convictions were overturned were found
guilty in the second trial related to the case.
   In the first trial, three other white youths were convicted of
manslaughter and assault in the fatal attack. Their case is
apparently unaffected by the appellate ruling handed down Dec. 11.
   In overturning the misdemeanor convictions from the second
trial, a five-judge panel said the trial judge made two important
errors in charging the jury.
   The panel said the judge, Thomas A. Demakos, ``over strenuous
defense objections,'' furnished the jury with verdict sheets that
improperly described some of the alleged crimes.
   It said the judge also erred by refusing a defense request to
instruct the jury on disorderly conduct as a lesser offense of
second-degree riot.
   Defense lawyer Spiros A. Tsimbinos said he and his clients
learned of the ruling Saturday.
   The Rev. Al Sharpton, a community activist who advised the
attack victims not to cooperate with investigators until a special
prosecutor was appointed, said the ruling was ``an outrageous act.
It's a smack in the face of all people, especially black people.''
   Farino, Bollander and Povinelli were convicted in 1988 of
second-degree riot, but acquitted of a more serious felony riot
charge for their roles in the Dec. 20, 1986, attack.
   Demakos sentenced the three on Sept. 19, 1988, to 34 days in
jail to be served on weekends over a four-month period. But they
were granted a stay pending appeal and spent no time in jail after
their conviction.
   In July, the appellate panel unanimously upheld the conviction
and sentences of the three defendants convicted of manslaughter and
assault in the first Howard Beach trial.
</TEXT>

</DOC>