<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0118 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 2136EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CrackLungs     12-23 0306</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Crack Lungs,0314</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Possible Link Between Crack and Pneumonia Symptoms</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Doctors say heavy crack-smoking is making
addicts critically ill with symptoms similar to pneumonia,
according to a published report.
   The condition, which has been dubbed crack-lung, is not readily
detected unless patients tell doctors of their crack addiction, The
New York Times reported in Sunday editions. If not treated
properly, it can lead to death.
   The condition has been identified in four inner-city hospitals
in Detroit and the problem also has been recognized in New York and
Baltimore, the newspaper said.
   While giving outward signs of suffering from pneumonia, the
patients do not respond to antibiotics or other anti-pneumonia
treatments.
   Scientists remain unsure what causes the condition, but some
believe it is caused by a variation of any number of ailments that
occur when poisonous compounds are introduced into the lungs, the
Times said. The condition also may be caused by other drugs used in
combination with crack or used to produce the cocaine-derivative.
   Dr. Dana G. Kissner, a Detroit pulmonary specialist, said
crack-lung patients suffer severe chest pains and breathing
problems, and often have high temperatures and cough up blood.
   Kissner, who with four other colleagues reported the condition
in the journal Radiology, said the young people he saw with the
condition were smoking between 15 and 25 pipes of crack a day.
   One thing that makes the condition unique is the absence of an
infectious organism _ a virus or bacterium _ and the
ineffectiveness of antibiotics in fighting it, Kissner said.
   But the condition can be successfully treated with
corticosteriods, which are anti-inflammatory drugs, Kissner said.
   Dr. James T. Kennedy, an associate professor at the New York
University School of Medicine, said he has seen about 24 young
people with the condition in the last two years.
</TEXT>

</DOC>