<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0442EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Cuddlers Bjt   12-20 0673</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Cuddlers, Bjt,0691</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hospitals Turn to Volunteers for Love Treatment</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BA1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATTY REINERT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BALTIMORE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nancy Gephart dons a blue hospital gown once a
week and does for strangers' children what she used to do for her
son. She feeds them, talks to them, sings to them and holds them.
   She is one of a growing number of hospital ``cuddlers,'' who try
to provide emotional support and a healing touch to sick children
whose parents either cannot or will not do so.
   Nearly three decades ago, Gephart spent as much time as she
could at her son's bedside at Mount Washington Pediatric Hospital
as he lay suffering from rheumatic fever.
   ``In those days, visiting hours were very restricted, but now
parents are allowed to visit day or night _ but some of them
don't,'' Gephart said. ``Some of the parents just can't face the
severity of a child's (medical) problems.''
   Susan Kolodner, the hospital's director of volunteers,
characterized the children as ``medically fragile,'' adding:
   ``This is their home for several months or even years, and their
parents can't be here all the time. That's where the cuddlers come
in _ to provide an extra pair of hands for the nurses and to
provide the children with extra attention and love.''
   When Mount Washington began its cuddler program in 1986,
hospital officials were looking for ``the grandmother type,''
Kolodner said.
   The first cuddlers came from a retirement home up the street.
   ``At first, I said, `I can't do that. I don't have time,''' said
Edith Dobbs, a retired nurse who lives at that home. ``But I was so
impressed with their orientation program and with the nurses. ...
When I left, I was signed up for Tuesday mornings and I've been
here every Tuesday morning for the last three years.''
   The program has since expanded to include volunteers of all
ages. The 60 current cuddlers range from early 20s to 84, Kolodner
said.
   Once Mount Washington's cuddler program was established, other
area hospitals were swamped with calls asking about similar
volunteer programs, said Debbie Bangledorf, volunteer programs
coordinator for Johns Hopkins Hospital and Hopkins Children's
Center.
   ``We kept getting requests from people saying, `Do you have a
cuddler program?' so we sat down and said, `Hey, let's do it,'''
Bangledorf said. ``It's been an overwhelming success.''
   Other hospitals have started similar programs, in part to deal
with the growing number of children born to drug-dependent mothers.
Addicted at birth, the children require extra attention and
nurturing to calm them.
   ``Sometimes it will take two hours just to get a baby to drink a
few ounces of formula,'' said Gephart. ``The nurses each have to
take care of up to four patients. They just don't have the time to
sit for two hours with one baby.''
   Michele Jacobs, a nurse at Mount Washington, said the babies
quickly learn to associate their nurses with the sometimes painful
treatments they administer.
   ``But they get to know the cuddlers and you can see their faces
light up when a cuddler comes in,'' Jacobs said. ``They don't
associate the cuddlers with pain. They associate them with loving
and playing and cuddling. The cuddlers are a major, major help to
the babies.''
   ``They know when they see us that we're not anybody who's going
to act on them,'' said cuddler Rochelle Savetman. ``We never hold
them while they're getting shots or medicine. ... We're just
company for them.''
   Jacobs said parents also are grateful for the cuddlers' services.
   ``They feel better knowing that if they can't be here, there is
someone who will watch over their children and give them comfort,''
she said.
   ``People say this is one of the most giving things you can do,''
Gephart said. ``But it's definitely a two-way street. I get so much
out of it _ just to see a child who has been unresponsive smile, or
to get a child to eat something or to sleep. I get as much out of
it as they do.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>