<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0119 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1342EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MountainClimbing     12-20 0331</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mountain Climbing,0340</SECOND>
<HEAD>Climbing Mount Everest May Cause Brain Damage</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: For Release at 6 p.m. EST</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   People who climb Mount Everest and other lofty
peaks may suffer oxygen deprivation that damages their brains and
results in temporary memory trouble, according to a study.
   The research on 35 mountaineers found mild impairments of
long-term memory as well as difficulty spelling and following
simple commands. While the problems showed up on psychological
tests, most were too modest to hinder the climbers' daily lives.
   While the research suggests the impairment eventually eases, the
researchers were unsure whether it always goes away.
   ``When you go to extremely high altititudes, you are getting
close to the threshhold of oxygen lack that can cause an impairment
of brain function,'' said Dr. Thomas F. Hornbein. ``It looks like
most of it is transient in most people, but some are more
susceptible than others.''
   Hornbein, an anesthesiologist at the University of Washington,
outlined the results in Thursday's New England Journal of Medicine.
   The study was based on tests administered to 34 men and one
woman before and after trips to Mount Everest or Tirich Mir from
1981 to 1984.
   Reports of memory loss and other apparent brain damage among
mountaineers first surfaced following British journeys to Mount
Everest in the 1920s and 1930s.
   ``There is a lot of individual variability,'' said Hornbein.
``One would expect that repeated exposure will produce greater and
longer-lasting impairment. But there are probably people who can go
high and not have any problem whatsoever.''
   He noted that the brain has tremendous capacity to recover from
injury and is probably able to compensate for most of the death of
brain cells that apparently results from temporary oxygen
deprivation.
   Hornbein, who climbed Mount Everest in 1963, said the
possibility of temporary brain damage should be kept in
perspective, considering all the hazards of mountaineering.
   ``Most climbers would consider this a pretty trivial risk in
comparison with all the others,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>