<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0122 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1319EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Romania 4thLd-Writethru   12-20 0824</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania, 4th Ld-Writethru,a0650,0850</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ceausescu Confirms Crackdown in Romania</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE with Ceausescu confirming army crackdown
on dissent. TRIMS to tighten. No pickup.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BEL3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALISON SMALE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Romanian President Nicolae Ceausescu
today blamed ``fascist, reactionary groups'' for anti-government
protests in his country and confirmed that the army had to
intervene to restore order.
   In a 25-minute address on national radio and television hours
after he returned from a three-day visit to Iran, Ceausescu made no
mention of casualties in the west Romanian city of Timisoara.
   Witnesses coming out of Romania have suggested that hundreds of
people were killed when security forces opened fire on
anti-government protesters on Sunday. Reports today suggested the
unrest had spread to other cities.
   Ceausescu said the army had to restore order in Timisoara after
unrest was provoked by ``fascist, reactionary groups who wanted to
destroy the independence and to stop the construction of socialism
in Romania.''
   The address, monitored by The Associated Press in Vienna, did
not say what steps would be taken to prevent continuing unrest.
   Troops and police were reported patrolling Bucharest and other
Romanian cities today in an apparent attempt by the hard-line
Communist authorities to stamp out any further protest.
   About 50,000 demonstrators took to the streets today in
Timisoara, 30 miles from the Yugoslav and Hungarian borders, the
Yugoslav news agency Tanjug said in a report from Bucharest quoting
the Yugoslav Consul in Timisoara.
   Demonstrators reportedly passed the Yugoslav Consulate, chanting
slogans against Ceausescu. The group passed Romanian army tanks,
but soldiers watched without intervening, the Tanjug report said.
   Ceausescu did not mention that reported protest, or unrest said
by Romanian emigres and other sources to have spread to other
cities in the Balkan nation.
   The 71-year-old Ceausescu, who has been in power 24 years and is
the longest-serving Soviet-bloc leader, refuses to adopt democratic
reforms sweeping the East bloc.
   He has forced hardships and rationing on his 23 million
citizens, who have become increasingly dissatisfied with his harsh
rule as the once-rigid nations around them adopt reforms.
   Tanjug quoted unofficial sources in Bucharest as saying that ``a
state of full alert has been introduced across Romania as protests
and unrest continue in Timisoara and other towns.''
   Witnesses have reported hundreds died during the recent unrest,
but an Austrian traveler, Helmut Wolf, who returned from Timisoara
today said the death toll in anti-government demonstrations was
``more than 1,000.''
   ``Sunday was brutal'' as security personnel fired into crowds of
civilians in the city, Wolf said. Downtown Timisoara, a city of
350,000, is in ruins, he told Austrian radio.
   Late Tuesday, Tanjug quoted unidentified witnesses as saying up
to 2,000 people may have been killed when security forces shot into
the crowd protesting the rigid policies of Ceausescu's Communist
government.
   Mihai Munteanu, a member of the Soviet Parliament from the
Soviet republic of Moldavia, said he spoke with acquaintances in
Romania today and was told pro-democracy demonstrations were going
on in many cities.
   In Iasi, people were burning books by Ceausescu, Munteanu said.
Iasi is an industrial and university center 250 miles northeast of
Bucharest, the capital. It is near the border with Moldavia.
   There also have been unconfirmed reports of clashes in the
cities of Arad, Brasov, Ploiesti, and Bucharest.
   Timisoara was inaccessible to foreign travelers and telephone
callers today, according to Hungarians who tried to telephone and
Yugoslav border guards.
   Tanjug said from Bucharest that foreign reporters who tried to
reach the town were turned back.
   Wolf, who returned to Vienna today after overseeing relief
shipments from Timisoara, told Austrian radio that houses in the
city center were on fire.
   ``Tanks were everywhere,'' Wolf said in the interview.
   A Yugoslav trucker who speaks Romanian said he saw graffiti on
walls while driving in a Timisoara suburb that called for ``an
uprising by Romanians against the Ceausescu regime on Dec. 24.''
   The trucker, who demanded anonymity, said he heard gunfire and
saw the sky being lit from the direction of Timisoara as he drove
near the city today.
   A Hungarian radio reporter meeting people arriving from
Bucharest today said the Romanian army has been mobilized and that
on Tuesday night reservists were called in.
   In Bucharest, a spokesperson for the U.S. Embassy told The
Associated Press that ``there is an increasing police and military
presence in the streets of Bucharest. The streets are calm and
quiet.''
   A Hungarian who called Bucharest and four other major Romanian
cities from Budapest today said he was told of a heavy military and
police presence in the streets.
   Guards at factories and offices have been doubled, according to
his informants and a brief report from Bucharest by the Soviet news
agency Tass.
   The Hungarian reported that in Brasov, Romania's second-largest
city, helicopters were patrolling overhead in addition to the
increased security in the streets. Brasov was the scene of
Romania's last major anti-government demonstration, in November
19to
discuss the operation and give his legal advice, Runkel said.
   Runkel cited the ``inherent right of self-defense'' in Article
51 of the United Nations Charter and the right of the U.S.
government to protect its citizens, military installations and
institutions under Article 21 of the Organization of American
States treaty.
   The Panama Canal Treaty also empowers the United States ``to
protect and defend the canal and its availability to all nations,''
Runkel said.
   The spokesman said that ``the democratically elected government
of Panama was consulted prior to and welcomed the action taken by
the United States.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>