<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0180 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2114EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Yugoslavia     12-18 0626</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Yugoslavia,0644</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Currency Proposed as Yugoslavia Weighs Economic Overhaul</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DUSAN STOJANOVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BELGRADE, Yugoslavia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Premier Ante Markovic proposed
introduction of a new convertible currency unit in Yugoslavia on
Monday at a key parliamentary session that is to consider sweeping
economic and political reforms.
   Markovic also announced tight monetary and budgetary controls;
free formation of interest rates, which in the past were set by the
National Bank; and government control of prices on electricity,
gasoline, rail transport, rents, postal services and medicines.
   He asked for an overhaul of the criminal code, including
dropping so-called ``verbal offenses'' under which thousands of
people were prosecuted for privately or publicly criticizing the
Communist regime.
   The new program is designed to lead the nation out of its worst
economic and political crisis and to curb rampant inflation.
Parliament must approve it during a three-day session or the
government says it will resign.
   Markovic said a solution to Yugoslavia's crisis ``is not
possible without a completely new economic and political system
that would ensure economic efficiency and political democracy with
full freedoms and human rights.''
   He said Yugoslavia should ``adopt all norms of a democratic and
pluralistic society,'' adding that Yugoslavia must not be satisfied
only by market-oriented reforms but should introduce radical
political changes as well.
   Winding up his 90-minute address, he pleaded for undivided
support from the deputies for the reforms ``crucial for the fate of
this country.''
   Markovic said Yugoslavia successfully ended negotiations with
the International Monetary Fund on obtaining new loans. Yugoslavia
is seeking loans from the IMF and the World Bank to implement its
new reform package.
   Under his proposal for a new currency unit, one new
``convertible dinar'' would be worth 10,000 old dinars. He said
Yugoslavs would be able to freely purchase foreign currencies with
dinars in local banks.
   The exchange rate would be fixed at seven dinars for one West
German mark and stay fixed until June 30. Before, the dinar rate
was adjusted daily against foreign currencies and lost value
rapidly as inflation hit 2,000 percent.
   One U.S. dollar would be worth 12 new dinars, instead of the
120,000 dinars now, Markovic said.
   He said the dinar was pegged to the mark because of the mark's
``greatest stability'' on world money markets, and will vary in
comparison to other Western currencies according to fluctuations in
the value of the mark.
   He said the changeover will take place Jan. 1, 1990, if
Parliament approves the package. Yugoslavia's last re-evaluation of
the dinar occurred in 1965.
   The central bank would for the first time become fully
autonomous in conducting monetary policies in accordance with
market mechanisms and will no longer be allowed to print money to
cover state deficits, Markovic said.
   Markovic's government took over last March. It has moved quickly
to introduce market mechanisms as a way out of a crisis that
includes a $17 billion foreign debt and a 17 percent unemployment
rate.
   His reform program has been bitterly attacked by conservatives
in the communist leadership, particularly in the republics of
Serbia and Montenegro, where local leaders oppose his efforts to
restructure the economy and promote greater political pluralism.
   Authorities in the two republics fear the popular discontent
that could be ignited by Markovic's reforms, which include firing
hundreds of thousands of employees in loss-making firms. They
prefer short-term measures such as price freezes.
   On Monday, the state-run trade union of the underdeveloped
republic of Montenegro organized a half-hour general ``warning''
strike by 160,000 workers to pressure the government to adopt
urgent measures to contain hyperinflation.
   Similar short general strikes are expected in the economically
poorest region of Macedonia on Thursday and in Serbia on Wednesday,
the day deputies are expected to vote on Markovic's program.
</TEXT>

</DOC>