<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0086 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1540EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-ThirdWorldDebt     12-17 0349</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Third World Debt,0358</SECOND>
<HEAD>World Bank Sees More Aid to East Europe</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: For release at 6:30 p.m. EST; Time set by source.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CARL HARTMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The World Bank, the biggest source of aid to
the Third World, is planning new help to Eastern Europe but will
not reduce aid to developing countries, according to bank Vice
President Stanley Fischer.
   ``As far as the World Bank is concerned, we don't see how
lending to Eastern Europe is going to detract from our lending to
Africa and Latin America,'' Fischer, the bank's top economist, said
at a news conference Friday.
   Bank President Barber W. Conable said the bank had $350 million
worth of loans prepared for projects in Poland and might lend as
much as $1 billion more in the coming year. So far Poland has not
had any loans from the bank.
   ``As Poland stabilizes, if it does, it's very likely that our
lending program will increase,'' Fischer said.
   In the year that ended June 30, Hungary got $345 million in
loans, Yugoslavia $198 million and China $1.3 billion. There would
have been more for China, but Conable cut off new loans when
Beijing violently crushed the movement for more democracy last June.
   The bank's annual report on Third World debt, released Friday,
predicted that the money owed by developing countries would rise
next year to $1.319 trillion from this year's $1.29 trillion. It
estimated that this year Third World countries will be paying out
$51.6 billion in principal and interest beyond what they will be
getting in new loans.
   Third World governments complain that this outflow leaves them
little to put into schools, roads, farms and other public
improvements.
   The bank's loans for the year totalled $21.3 billion, most of
which it borrowed on world markets.
   The United States is the biggest shareholder in the bank, which
has its headquarters in Washington. China, Hungary, Poland and
Yugoslavia are already among the 152 countries that own it.
Czechoslovakia is trying to join, and the Soviet Union has said it
would like to.
</TEXT>

</DOC>