<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0129 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1649EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Colombia     12-18 0462</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia,0476</SECOND>
<HEAD>Colombians Search for Medellin Drug Boss Escobar</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HAROLD OLMOS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soldiers searched northern Colombia on
Monday for drug lord Pablo Escobar Gaviria, boss of the deadly
Medellin cartel.
   After a four-month war against drug traffickers in which the
cocaine gangs have killed at least 200 people, Colombian
authorities were heartened Friday by the death of Gonzalo Rodriguez
Gacha in a police shootout near Covenas, on the Caribbean coast.
   On Sunday, President Virgilio Barco said: ``We will continue our
commitment to eradicate narco-trafficking from Colombia. Looking at
what happened to Rodriguez Gacha, those involved in this illegal
activity will realize what their end will be.''
   Rodriguez Gacha, 42, his son Fredy and five bodyguards were
killed Friday in the first major government victory of the drug
war, which Barco declared after the assassination Aug. 18 of Sen.
Luis Carlos Galan, the leading presidential candidate.
   ``We keep up our search for Escobar Gaviria and other drug
traffickers,'' Defense Minister Gen. Oscar Botero told reporters
Monday.
   Officials said a long fight remains. As Barco put it Sunday:
``This war has had a development favorable to the government, but
it is not over yet.''
   Drug gangs have killed at least 200 people the past four months
in bomb attacks in Bogota, Medellin, Cali and other cities.
Sixty-three died when a vehicle loaded with explosives exploded
this month outside the headquarters of the Colombian Intelligence
Police.
   Security sources said elite military units concentrated their
search for Escobar Gaviria on Monday near Cartagena and Sincelejo
in northern Colombia, where intelligence reports said he had
planned to meet with Rodriguez Gacha.
   Bogota newspapers said the two had intended to plan sabotage
actions to discourage President Bush from attending an anti-drug
summit Feb. 15 with the presidents of Colombia, Peru and Bolivia.
   When asked about the reports, a U.S. Embassy official said: ``We
know nothing of it.''
   The government has offered a reward equivalent to $580,000 for
information leading to the arrest or death of Escobar Gaviria, who
is said to have hundreds of men in his own private army.
   A similar amount was offered for Rodriguez Gacha, who had an
army of about 2,000.
   A diplomat said of Rodriguez Gacha's troops: ``They are
mercenaries. Now that their boss is dead, they are probably ...
fleeing.''
   Escobar Gaviria escaped into the jungle Nov. 22 when police
surrounded Cocorna, a town 110 miles from Bogota, where he was
hiding.
   If captured alive, Escobar Gaviria would be extradited to the
United States for trial on federal drug smuggling charges. So far
10 Colombians have been extradited to the United States to face
drug charges.
   Colombian drug gangs are believed responsible for 80 percent of
the illegal cocaine that enters the United States.
</TEXT>

</DOC>