<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0120 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2013EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China-US     12-21 0673</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-US,0694</SECOND>
<HEAD>China Welcomes U.S. Decision on Satellites</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM ABRAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   China on Thursday praised President Bush for
easing economic sanctions, saying the measures would help restore
normal relations.
   Bush's actions were ``positive steps helpful to the
normalization of relations between China and the United States,''
said Foreign Ministry spokesman Jin Guihua. ``We welcome this.''
   Bush this week exempted from economic sanctions the export of
three communications satellites to be launched by China and
sanctioned Export-Import Bank credit to companies doing business in
China.
   The relaxation of sanctions followed a Dec. 9-10 visit to
Beijing by National Security Adviser Brent Scowcroft that ended a
U.S. ban on high-level exchanges between the two sides.
   The Bush administration, which imposed the sanctions after the
bloody military attack on student-led pro-democracy demonstrators
this June, has been criticized for being too friendly to Beijing's
hard-line leaders.
   White House officials said the decision to allow China to launch
satellites for Australian and Hong Kong firms, and the waiving of
restrictions on low-interest Ex-Im Bank loans to Americans
investing in China, were in the ``national interest.''
   White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said the sale of the
satellites will bring $300 million worth of business to U.S. firms.
   Jin declined comment on whether Bush's actions would help settle
other outstanding issues, particularly that of Fang Lizhi, the
outspoken dissident who has been hiding in the U.S. Embassy in
Beijing since June.
   Jin repeated the Chinese position that Fang's future is a
``sensitive question'' that must be solved through joint efforts of
the two sides.
   Jin also reread a Foreign Ministry statement issued earlier
condemning U.S. military action in Panama, saying it was
interference in the internal affairs of another country and a
violation of international law.
   On Saturday, a senior Soviet Communist Party official arrives
for a visit to include talks between the two largest Marxist
nations on the crisis in world communism.
   The crumbling of one-party Communist rule in Eastern Europe is
certain to be on the agenda during the weeklong visit of Valentin
Falin, head of the decision-making Central Committee's
International Department, a Soviet Embassy official said.
   The official, speaking on condition of anonymity, said the
Chinese are unhappy with events in Eastern Europe and are eager to
sound out the Soviets on their approach to the popular groundswell
of opposition to Communist rule.
   The official said the Chinese have also expressed concern about
growing turmoil in Romania, East Europe's most stubborn holdout
against political reform and a staunch ally of China since its
military crackdown.
   On bilateral matters, Falin will discuss how to improve
party-to-party relations following the May visit of President
Mikhail S. Gorbachev, which ended a 30-year freeze in Sino-Soviet
party contacts.
   Falin has asked to meet party General Secretary Jiang Zemin, and
a favorable response from the Chinese would indicate their
willingness to move party relations to a higher plane, the official
said.
   The two sides may touch on a planned visit by Premier Li Peng to
Moscow, tentatively set for next April.
   The official said overall Sino-Soviet relations have generally
progressed well since the Gorbachev visit in spite of the June
turmoil in China and divergences in views on political reform.
   He said there were so many Soviet delegations visiting China
that the embassy could no longer handle them all. Trade along the
once-tense border is booming, and total bilateral trade is expected
to increase substantially from last year's $3.25 billion.
   The official China Daily said Thursday that the two countries
are now discussing cooperation in a $46 million project to build
China's first coal slurry pipeline.
   Soviet officials acknowledge, however, that China's top priority
is still obtaining Western technology, and China's strained
relations with the West will not result in a sharp increase in
Sino-Soviet economic exchanges.
   The Soviet Union, the official said, hopes better relations with
China will facilitate multinational development of Siberia's rich
natural resources, with Chinese laborers being brought in for
projects backed by Japanese, U.S. and South Korean technology and
financing.
</TEXT>

</DOC>