<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1317EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Bennett-Drugs     12-17 0311</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bennett-Drugs,320</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bennett Calls Legalized Drug Supporters Indifferent to Minorities</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The argument that drugs should be legalized is
fed by indifference to the fact that a large number of drug users
are minorities, federal anti-drug coordinator William Bennett said
Sunday.
   ``I have to tell you I've heard in some circles, `Well, let them
kill each other,''' Bennett said on the ABC-TV program, ``This Week
With David Brinkley.''
   ``That is not worthy of the American people,'' said Bennett, who
did not say who harbored that attitude.
   Bennett, who is director of the Office of National Drug Control
Policy, has been a vocal opponent of calls to make illicit drugs
legal. Among the advocates of legalization are Baltimore mayor Kurt
L. Schmoke, who is black, economist Milton Friedman, and U.S.
District Judge Robert Sweet, who last week became the first federal
judge to publicly voice such an opinion.
   Friedman and Sweet also appeared on the show, but did not
address Bennett's comments.
   Bennett made his remarks in response to a question by
conservative columnist George Will.
   ``Do you think if the people disproportionately killing
themselves off were white suburban high school students there would
be a different kind of argument going on?'' Will asked. ``I'm
asking is there a certain racial indifference in this argument?''
   ``I'm afraid there is,'' Bennett responded.
   The drug coordinator said that neither Sweet nor Friedman had
that attitude.
   But he said: ``I'm afraid that's in the air. But these are our
children we have to protect, black or white, whatever, and we're
not going to protect them very well if we let this genie out of the
bottle.''
   Sweet and Friedman said that law enforcement efforts, rather
than halting the multi-billion dollar drug industry, are resulting
in wasted money.
   ``What we have now is not working,'' Sweet said.
   Bennett called such arguments ``irresponsible nonsense.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>