<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0214 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0205EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-BusinessHighlights     12-21 0850</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Business Highlights,0890</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Investors took the Panama crisis in stride with only a few brief
blips registering on financial markets around the world.
   The dollar, oil and many stocks moved higher Wednesday on the
news of the surprise U.S. military action, but prices later receded
amid the usual concerns about interest rates and the economy.
   President Bush ordered troops into Panama on Tuesday night
following several days of tension.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Citibank closed its branches in Panama City, soap-making at the
Colgate-Palmolive factory halted and Borden shut an ice cream plant
following the U.S. military action in Panama.
   The Panama Canal was also closed Wednesday, but shippers
remained calm, although a prolonged shutdown could delay exports of
South American fruit, raise some prices in the United States and
force importers to find alternate routes.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.S. economy grew at a faster rate in the
third quarter than previously estimated, the government said, but
analysts say it is fast running out of steam and some suggest it is
flirting with a recession.
   The Commerce Department said Wednesday the gross national
product grew at an annual rate of 3 percent in the July-September
period, up from a 2.5 percent rate reported in October and the
subsequent revision to 2.7 percent last month.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   European food concern TLC Beatrice International
Inc.'s decision to scrap a public stock offering to raise up to
$194 million reflects a general weakness in the market for new
issues, analysts said.
   The move also postponed what would have been two firsts: the
first former Beatrice Cos. spinoff to go public since a $6 billion
takeover of the conglomerate in 1986 and the first black-owned
company to be listed on the New York Stock Exchange.
   TLC Beatrice on Tuesday canceled the offering of 18.5 million
shares of stock priced from $9 to $10.50 a share.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Billionaire Donald Trump reportedly is among
bidders weighing a possible purchase of Bloomingdale's but the
department store chain's troubled owner, Campeau Corp., declined to
confirm Trump's interest.
   Campeau spokeswoman Carol Sanger said Wednesday the company
intends to maintain silence for the duration of the sale process.
The identity of the bidders will not be disclosed and all
negotiations are confidential.
   Meanwhile Wednesday, two clothing makers joined merchandise
credit firms in suspending business with Campeau's Federated and
Allied department stores as a result of Campeau's financial
situation.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A proposal by the European Economic Community
to overhaul agricultural trade will clear the way for final
negotiations with the EEC in 1990, the Bush administration said.
   ``This is the last of the major proposals to be submitted and
now will permit the final negotiations on agriculture to get under
way early next year,'' U.S. Trade Representative Carla Hills and
Agriculture Secretary Clayton Yeutter said Wednesday.
   However, they said, the United States cannot accept an EEC
proposal to ``rebalance'' import protection, Mrs. Hills and Yeutter
said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   American Airlines Chairman Robert L. Crandall said
his deal to buy foreign routes and other assets of Eastern Airlines
should be approved by government regulators ``in the national
interest.''
   Failure to allow the deal would invite greater control of
international air travel by foreign carriers, Crandall said
Wednesday of the $471 million purchase announced Tuesday.
   The complex deal with Eastern parent Texas Air Corp. gives
American control of Eastern's prized Latin American routes and
would greatly enhance American's presence in foreign markets.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>TALLAHASSEE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   State officials took action to oust the
head of Florida's largest savings and loan, claiming he used $45
million in depositors' money to bankroll an art collection and
extravagant lifestyle.
   David L. Paul, chairman and chief executive officer of CenTrust
Bank of Miami, has 21 days to resign or contest a complaint filed
Wednesday by Comptroller Gerald Lewis. A statement released by
CenTrust said Paul would ``vigorously oppose'' removal.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Troubled Wang Laboratories Inc., which has been
criticized for having too limited a product line, said it would
expand its line of computer equipment that uses popular
industrywide standards.
   Analysts said Wednesday's move marks an important departure for
Wang, which has suffered recent losses and has slashed its work
force. The move follows a recent trend in which computer companies
have been making equipment that is compatible with that of other
manufacturers.

</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The stock market drifted through a trendless session Wednesday,
registering no strong reaction to the U.S. military action in
Panama. The Dow Jones average of 30 industrials dropped 7.68 to
2,687.93.
   The dollar finished mostly lower in the United States after
ending mixed overseas in what dealers called a muted response to
the events in Panama.
   Treasury bill yields tumbled and bond prices were narrowly mixed
after the Federal Reserve appeared to signal an easing of monetary
policy.
   Orange juice futures prices rose; sugar futures fell; coffee
futures gained; precious metals advanced; energy futures were
mixed; grains and soybeans fell; and livestock and meat futures
retreated.
</TEXT>

</DOC>