<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0114 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1332EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SalvationArmy     12-22 0312</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Salvation Army,0321</SECOND>
<HEAD>Salvation Army Office Reopens in Time for Christmas</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW BEDFORD, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A flood of overnight donations saved
the Salvation Army here, which had been swamped by needy families
and closed four days before Christmas.
   ``The outpouring of the public has been marvelous,'' Maj. Robert
Pfeiffer, who runs the office, said Friday. Pfeiffer said several
thousand dollars had been donated by corporations and individuals
after word of the closing spread.
   On Thursday, Pfeiffer closed his doors because he ran out of
money for food and gifts for those in need. Pfeiffer's $80,000
budget, which proved adequate in past years to take the local
office from Nov. 1 through Dec. 24, fell short this year because
more families than usual needed assistance.
   The money that came in Thursday night and Friday morning will
keep the office afloat, Pfeiffer said.
   ``We are not turning anyone away,'' Pfeiffer said. ``The
Salvation Army is alive and well in New Bedford.''
   Pfeiffer blamed recent layoffs of 1,000 workers at various
businesses for the increase in needy families. Friday, 400 more
were laid off as the Carol Electronic Cables closed, he said.
   ``The families I was seeing were basically recently unemployed
people _ people who didn't have great life savings,'' Pfeiffer
said. ``I had people who said `Last year we gave to you, and this
year we have to come and take.'''
   His office usually helps about 1,300 families during the
Christmas season. This year, 300 additional families came.
   On Thursday, Pfeiffer shut down after more than 100 people came
to the office seeking help. He offered assistance to those
families, but said he could not take anybody else.
   ``We've gone into using the canned food we had put aside for
January and February,'' Pfeiffer said.
   About half a dozen bell ringers were scattered through New
Bedford seeking more money Thursday, Pfeiffer said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>