<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0555EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Romania-Iliescu     12-26 0576</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Iliescu,0596</SECOND>
<HEAD>New President Was A Purged Communist Party Official</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIOREL URMA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ion Iliescu, Romania's new president, is
a former senior Communist official who was demoted for standing up
to Nicolae Ceausescu and is said to be a close friend of Soviet
leader Mikhail S. Gorbachev.
   Ceausescu had stripped Iliescu of the prestigious post of party
secretary and had him assigned to direct a publishing house.
   Iliescu, 59, announced on television Friday the formation of the
National Salvation Committee, which he described as the ``new organ
of state power'' in Romania. On Saturday, he announced Ceausescu's
arrest.
   Today, Iliescu was appointed president by the provisional
government.
   He holds a university degree in business administration and also
studied hydrology at Moscow University, where knowledgeable
Romanians say he got to know Gorbachev.
   While originally one of Ceausescu's close aides in the late
1960s as the man responsible for youth problems and propaganda, he
was demoted from the Central Committee in 1971 and later from the
Cabinet.
   He became regional party secretary in Timisoara, western
Roamania, and in Iasi, near the Soviet border, in the early 1970s
and was summoned to Bucharest and named chairman of a council for
water administration.
   Fired from that job after a sharp exchange with Ceausescu and
the dictator's wife, Elena, at a party meeting in the mid-1980s,
Iliescu was named director of the Editura Tehnica publishing house.
   His reported friendly ties with Gorbachev saved him from a more
dramatic fall, informed sources said.
   ``Iliescu, as a local party chief, was very informal. He never
used the word `comrade' when addressing people and was ready to
talk to them as soon as they knocked at his door,'' said Cornelia
Dimitriu, a university professor in Iasi, where Iliescu was sent in
1974 to serve as regional party secretary.
   ``He couldn't stand Ceausescu's personality cult and he did not
refrain like others from expressing it,'' she said in an interview.
``He often did not obey the orders he received from Bucharest.''
   ``Iliescu fell out of favor with Ceausescu because he was
outspoken and frequently aired his grievances. He is a technocrat
and not an ideologist,'' Ms. Dimitriu said.
   Born in 1930 into a worker's family in eastern Romania, Iliescu,
who is married but has no children, held a number of Central
Committee jobs throughout the 1960s, enabling him to work his way
up through the Communist Party.
   At one point he headed the Central Committee's Department of
Propaganda, and from 1967 to 1971 he was Minister of Youth Problems.
   Iliescu, long rumored to be a possible successor to Ceausescu,
did not sign a March 1989 letter to the former Romanian leader that
protested the dictator's human rights violations and his despotic
rule.
   Informed Romanians said it might have jeopardized Iliescu had he
openly joined them, preferring to appear unblemished in the eyes of
Ceausescu, whose secret police reportedly kept close tabs on his
private life.
   ``He obviously managed to outfox them,'' Mircea Stoica, a former
professor at Bucharest University said.
   Iliescu stated Friday that the new government would establish
``a new structure of political power.''
   ``The old structure of party and government was liquidated,''
Iliescu said, possibly indicating the demise of Ceausescu's
Communist Party in Romania.
   ``We will establish a provisional structure which will prepare
free elections (in April) in which the people will be the decisive
factor for pur public life, Iliescu said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>