<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0058EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-PropaneBlast 2ndLd-Writethru a0710 12-28 0618</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Propane Blast, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0710,0630</SECOND>
<HEAD>Propane Blast Forces Evacuation of Thousands</HEAD>
<BYLINE>Eds: ADDS byline. Subs 2nd graf with 4 grafs to UPDATE with larger
evacuation area, quote about population density, reports and quote about
looting. Picks up 3rd graf pvs, `Two hours ...' ^By RON FOURNIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BATESVILLE, Ark. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A factory propane tank exploded
Wednesday, shooting a huge plume of smoke and fire into the sky and
forcing fire and emergency crews to retreat from the blaze after
evacuating about 3,500 people.
   No injuries were reported at White-Rodgers Co. when the tank
exploded shortly before 4 p.m. Workers were evacuated and people
who live within a 1{ miles were ordered from their homes, said Dale
Rust of the Independence County Office of Emergency Services.
   ``It is the most thickly populated area of the city,'' said Rust.
   Independence County Sheriff David Hunter said there had been
some reports of burglaries in the evacuated area. Rust said 10
state troopers were being sent to the city to help control looting.
   ``We're having people ripping us off out here,'' Hunter said.
   Two hours after the blast, firefighters were pumping water on
the burning tank and about a half-dozen others that are mostly
surrounded by a fire wall in an area separate from the main plant
building, Rust said.
   The evacuation area was expanded to a radius of 1{ miles from
the fire after 7 p.m. Police placed road blocks around the area,
said Faye England, a dispatcher at the Batesville Police Department.
   ``It should burn itself out ... if it doesn't rupture and
explode before then,'' Rust said. ``We're trying to keep the tanks
cool to keep them from rupturing.''
   At 9 p.m., officials withdrew emergency workers and eight
firefighters from the fire scene after gas was detected in the air
around the fire. The firefighters left untended nozzles playing
streams of water onto the fire.
   There was no immediate word on when the emergency workers would
be allowed back into the fire scene.
   The plant, a division of Emerson Electric, manufactures water
heater and gas controls and employs about 1,000 people.
   County Judge David Wyatt said about 3,500 people were removed
from the area around the plant.
   About 12,000 gallons of propane is contained in 14
interconnected tanks at the plant, which could cause damage within
a mile if it all exploded, Rust said.
   Rust estimated that the fire was burning up about 500 gallons of
propane an hour.
   In addition, the tank is burning from both a safety valve at its
top and a leak at its base, adding to the risk of an explosion,
Rust said. The lower fire could boost temperatures and pressure in
the tank, he said.
   Ambulances were used to evacuate residents of the 121-bed
Wood-Lawn Nursing Home, and emergency officials drove through some
neighborhoods using loudspeakers to urge residents to leave their
homes.
   The nursing home patients were evacuated to a Methodist church,
and other churches opened to accommodate people forced from their
homes, Rust said.
   Ross Jones, who was at a nearby store when the blast occurred at
mid-afternoon, said he witnessed ``both vibrations and something we
heard,'' then saw smoke rising into the air.
   Jones said he heard a second blast about 10 minutes later and
saw a second plume of smoke. He said he drove by the plant and saw
the blaze and heard ``a roar like jet engines,'' apparently the
noise of pressurized propane gas escaping from the tank.
   Rust said officials had no idea what caused the tank to rupture
and explosion. An investigation would begin when the fire was
brought under control, ``but we're not worrying about that right
now.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>