<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1239EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-US-Panama 2ndLd-Writethru a0530 12-23 1110</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-Panama, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0530,990</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Sends 2,000 More Troops to Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 4th graf pvs, bgng: Pentagon officials, with 2 grafs to
UPDATE with military dissidents taking over island prison and provide new
casualty figures. SUBS grafs 18-19 pvs, Bush went, to UPDATE with Bush
to attend Pentagon briefing Sunday, make radio address. Picks up 20th graf
pvs, Panama's new</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HARRY F. ROSENTHAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Pentagon dispatched 2,000 more combat
troops into Panama today in the face of continued, unexpectedly
stiff resistance from loyalists of fugitive Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noriega.
   The fresh troops, from the Army's 7th Light Infantry Division,
were being airlifted throughout the day from Fort Ord, Calif., as
U.S. commanders in Panama reported burgeoning concern over the
harassing attacks _ and weapons supplies _ of Noriega's so-called
dignity battalions.
   The new arrivals joined 24,000 U.S. troops already in Panama,
many of them bone-weary, as the nation's largest military force to
see combat since Vietnam faced a changed mission _ from
conventional warfare to counterterrorism.
   U.S. military officials also reported that prisoners at an
island penitentiary apparently had overcome their pro-Noriega
guards and had radioed for help from American forces. The prison
group was said to include some of the former Panamanian officers
who led a failed coup attempt on Oct. 3.
   Pentagon officials put the U.S. casualty count at 24 soldiers
killed, 238 wounded and two missing. In addition, they said, two
civilian dependents have been reported killed.
   In Panama City, Lt. Col. Jerry Marguila, spokesman for the U.S.
Southern Command, said 139 of Noriega's fighters had been killed.
Though the Panamanian Defense Forces were neutralized quickly by
the U.S. assault which began early Wednesday, Noriega's hit-and-run
dignity battalions are ``increasing their activities of harassing
attacks with small arms and mortar fire, threatening the civilian
population, and hostage-taking,'' he said.
   When pressed for specific numbers, Marguila replied ``I don't
have in my mind an increase in numbers between today and yesterday
of dignity-battalion efforts. It's just that they are becoming more
of a concern, because they are taking more of our time as opposed
to the PDF.''
   At the Pentagon, one military official, speaking on condition of
anonymity, conceded the ferocity of the dignity battalions had
caught U.S. commanders off guard. And he said that despite the U.S.
seizure of several large weapons caches, it appeared that the
Noriega die-hards still had access to fresh arms.
   Defense Secretary Dick Cheney was at the Pentagon on Saturday to
keep tabs on developments in Panama as well as the bloody
revolution which ousted Romanian dictator Nicolae Ceausescu.
President Bush was at Camp David, Md., where he worked on a
Christmas Eve address to the American military men and women around
the globe.
   Noriega, meanwhile, continued to defy capture despite a rash of
rumors as to his whereabouts.
   ``It's simply a difficult operation. ... There are a lot of
places to hide,'' Lt. Gen. Tom Kelly, director of operations for
the Joint Chiefs of Staff, said late Friday.
   The administration also offered what it said was new evidence of
drug dealings by Noriega _ including a 110-pound stash of cocaine
found near Noriega's private office at a military barracks.
   ``He is clearly not only a narco-trafficker, but apparently he
condones and uses the stuff himself,'' said Gen. Maxwell Thurman,
the head of the U.S. Southern Command in Panama.
   The Noriega headquarters was described as ``opulent,''
containing a movie theater, jade, art and jewels. U.S. troops also
found a picture of Adolf Hitler in a closet and an assortment of
occult and witchcraft paraphernalia, according to U.S. officials.
   The fighting with Noriega's outmanned supporters continued
despite the presence of 11,000 troops brought in Wednesday to join
the 13,000 normally stationed there.
   Members of Noriega's ``Dignity Battalions'' were waiting when
first vice president Ricardo Arias Calderon was leaving the
National Assembly on Friday and fired shots at his car. Arias was
not injured, but two aides were wounded.
   Kelly said the U.S. military is ``looking at re-establishing the
police force. He said his commanders estimated that ``clearing the
city'' would take five to 10 days.
   Thurman, in Panama City, said more ``civil affairs units'' were
being brought to help re-establish civil systems in areas of
economics, public facilities and such special functions as
displaced persons, refugees and evacuees.
   Bush went to Camp David, Md., for the Christmas holiday, but
White House officials said he would attend a briefing Sunday at the
Pentagon.
   Bush was briefed by telephone Saturday morning at Camp David by
national security adviser Brent Scowcroft on both the Panama
situation and developments in Romania, White House spokesman Sean
Walsh said. Walsh provided no details of the briefing.
   Bush was scheduled to make a 5-minute radio address over the
Armed Forces Network on Sunday and Walsh said part of the message
would be directed at servicemen in Panama.
   Bush plans to visit soldiers wounded in Panama in a Houston
hospital on Dec. 31.
   Panama's new ambassador to Washington, Carlos Rodriguez, moved
into the embassy on Friday after meeting with Bush. The keys to the
mission were turned over to him by a State Department official in
late afternoon.
   Congressional leaders received briefings about the situation in
Panama by the Pentagon, State Department and CIA.
   Sen. Sam Nunn, chairman of the Senate Armed Services Committee,
said the briefing had underscored his support for the operation and
said the administration ``made a very strong case for
justification.''
   Nunn said that beyond the initial reasons for the military
actions cited by President Bush, there was evidence that ``General
Noriega himself ... has been acting irrationally beyond his normal
conduct.''
   Offers were made to Noriega through diplomatic channels that he
could leave for a third country _ one that has no extradition
treaty with the United States, Nunn said. ``He was given an
opportunity, another course not to have to confront the United
States,'' the senator added.
   Nunn said it was clear the invasion was launched without a good
fix on Noriega's whereabouts, but called it a rare flaw in an
otherwise well-run operation.
   Both Kelly, in the Pentagon, and Gen. Maxwell Thurman in Panama,
said an astounding cache of weapons was seized by American troops
in Noriega's headquarters.
   ``One wonders what the intentions of Noriega were,'' the general
said, referring to the 10,000 mostly Eastern bloc weapons that were
found. He acknowledged that Noriega's defense forces had put up a
tougher battle than expected.
   The remnants of Noriega's armed civilian battalions, he said,
``are looting, sniping, they are lawless.'' But, he said, ``I'm
satisfied it's under control. We're not getting anything we can't
handle.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>