<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0247 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0509EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-SPE--Bride&amp;Groom:Travel     12-18 0359</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-SPE--Bride &amp; Groom: Travel,0367</SECOND>
<HEAD>SPECIAL EDITION</HEAD>
<HEAD>Bride &amp; Groom: Travel</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Affluent couples who want a ``royal'' honeymoon can be
accomodated at Cliveden, one of England's better known stately
homes, with a travel package by Fischer Travel Enterprises of New
York.
   Honeymooners can enjoy Cliveden's setting in 375 acres set along
the Thames, along with various outdoor and water sports, according
to Bill Fischer, president of the agency. The 300-year-old house
was once home to Frederick, Prince of Wales, the Dukes of
Buckingham, and the Astors.
   He also suggests a Hayman resort holiday off the Great Barrier
Reef in Australia, or a private pavillion suite at Amanpuri, on
Puket Island on the southern coast of Thailand.
   ``Many couples seek out excitement during their wedding trip, to
make it truly special, says Fischer. _
   For those who want the wedding in an exotic locale, with most
arrangements taken care of, there is the Damion Waring Estate on
the island of Oahu, Hawaii.
   The estate's gardens were originally designed as an outdoor
photography setting for the late R.G. Damien Waring, a noted
wedding photographer in Hawaii. Couples who came for their bridal
pictures began asking to have their weddings there. The requests
spawned the estate's business as a wedding center.
   The estate managers, who include Waring's widow, Lurlene, say
that weddings often can be done less expensively at the estate than
at home. The enterprise provides a wedding coordinator who in
consultation with the couple will organize choice of priest or
minister, music, witnesses, transportation, hair and makeup for the
bride, tuxedo rental for the groom, along with photographic and
video coverage of the ceremony. The estate even will assist the
couple in obtaining the marriage licence.
   The estate can be contacted at 5253 Kalanianaole Highway,
Honolulu, Hawaii 96821, or 800-648-5040. _
   European packages with honeymooners in mind are being offered in
l990 by Air France.
   Couples can take in the Spirit of Carnival in Venice, Italy,
from Feb. 23 to March 1, the Grand Prix in Monte Carlo from May 23
to 28 or the Beaujolais Nouveau Celebration in France from Nov. 11
to 15.
</TEXT>

</DOC>