<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0217 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1916EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Braniff     12-28 0511</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Braniff,0531</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dallas Man Wants To Buy Braniff, Turn It Into Business Fliers' Carrier</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto DN5</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN A. BOLT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Braniff Inc. would be returned to Texas and
revived as a business fliers' airline _ with some entire flights
reserved for corporations _ under a Dallas businessman's plan to
buy the company now in bankruptcy reorganization.
   Kay Cohlmia, a former Braniff employee and aviation company
owner, said Thursday he has lined up some investors, but hasn't
arrived at a price for the airline. Braniff, based in Orlando,
Fla., filed for Chapter 11 protection from creditors in late
September and has ceased operations.
   ``We don't know how much money it's going to take to buy it,''
he said.
   Cohlmia said he talked to attorneys for Braniff's unsecured
creditors' committee, to Merrill Lynch Capital Partners and to
Teamsters union officials.
   ``We're going to take a look and see what his idea is,'' said
Richard Levy, an attorney in New York for Braniff's unsecured
creditors.
   But Levy cautioned, ``It's nothing like there's something that's
moving with any pace here. We'll consider all appropriate ideas, as
I hope (Braniff) will.''
   Cohlmia said he would go to Orlando to discuss his plans with
various people involved in Braniff's bankruptcy proceeding on Jan.
6, the same day a series of court hearings are scheduled.
   He said he hasn't talked to Braniff officials because ``they
won't appoint anybody there'' to run the airline.
   Braniff moved its headquarters from Dallas to Orlando earlier
this year, but Cohlmia said he would return the carrier to its
traditional home.
   Cohlmia _ who once proposed a ``smokers' airline'' _ provided
only bare outlines of his plan, which he said includes a contract
with Dallas company JOH Inc. to lease jets for the first outbound
and last inbound flights daily out of Dallas-Fort Worth
International Airport.
   He described JOH as a diversified holding company owned by Jo
Ann Harris. Ms. Harris had not returned phone calls late Thursday.
   ``Depending on how many planes we're allowed to get,'' he said a
Cohlmia-run Braniff would be a long-haul, one-price carrier,
ferrying businessmen from New York to Dallas and other cities. He
envisions a round-trip fare at $399 between Dallas and New York.
The current full-price, round-trip fare is about $900 on most
carriers.
   ``We have a great plan, an incredible plan,'' he said.
   Cohlmia worked for Braniff in the 1960s as a baggage handler
before founding Cohlmia Aviation Inc., which ferried checks for the
Federal Reserve System.
   Then in 1984 and 1985, he said, ``I put the first mail hub
together, operating the western part of the United States, using
Las Vegas as our hub.''
   ``I thought he was a good operator,'' Las Vegas postmaster
Joseph A. Ryan said, adding Cohlmia lost the contract to a lower
bidder after 18 months.
   Braniff had 4,800 employees, including about 450 in Dallas, when
it filed for bankruptcy protection on Sept. 28.
   BIA Acquisitions, an investor group formed by PaineWebber Group
Inc., bought Braniff in 1988 for about $100 million.
</TEXT>

</DOC>