<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1339EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Poland-LedtheWay Bjt   12-17 0757</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland-Led the Way, Bjt,0778</SECOND>
<HEAD>Poles Who Led the Way Now Sit Back and Enjoy</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DANISZEWSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The democratic revolution sweeping Eastern
Europe in recent weeks has been greeted happily by Poles, who have
had the satisfaction of seeing their hard-line neighbors finally
following in their footsteps.
   In a few tumultuous weeks, East Germany, Czechoslovakia and
Bulgaria have all seen the birth of mass civic opposition movements
demanding pluralism, abandonment of the leading role of the
Communist Party and free elections.
   For Poland, all those things were old hat. They were won in the
independent Solidarity movement's decade-long struggle, first in
the 1980 shipyard strikes, through the long winter of the
martial-law period and then in the triumphant years of 1988-89 when
the movement was reborn, handily won parliamentary elections and
took control of the government.
   ``Cribbing from Poland,'' one newspaper headline crowed last
week about events in East Germany and Czechoslovakia.
   ``We have gone the farthest and without the fireworks,''
Solidarity leader Lech Walesa said.
   While much of the world may credit Mikhail S. Gorbachev with
sparking the reform movement in the Soviet Union's former
satellites, Poles generally ask: Would there have been Gorbachev
without Walesa first?
   Even Poland's Communist Party, a minor partner in a
Solidarity-led coalition government after it couldn't form a
parliamentary majority of its own, is patting itself on the back.
   ``We decided a year ago that all the processes would be managed
in an evolutionary way,'' party spokesman Jan Bisztyga said. ``In
the other countries, there was no such logical decision by the
establishments.''
   Amid the joy, there has been the occasional discordant voice,
worrying that Poland might be overtaken by its neighbors in the
race for reforms or elbowed to the sidelines as others seek aid
from the West.
   For instance, the Polish Parliament still has not removed the
clause in the constitution granting the ``leading role'' to the
Communist Party, with parliamentary leaders saying that clause is
obviously moot at the moment but economic issues are more pressing.
   Zdzislaw Najder, a sociologist close to Solidarity, noted in the
government newspaper that other countries are overtaking Poland in
this aspect of constitutional reform.
   ``Faced with this new situation, shouldn't we perhaps reconsider
another acceleration of institutional reforms in this country? This
is not just a matter of winning the race for priority claims _ this
is a question of installing a sound political system and of our
international prestige,'' he said.
   For Poles, the current situation is fraught with irony.
   Normally known as the most restive country in Eastern Europe,
Poland has been an island of tranquility this autumn while its
previously staid neighbors in East Germany and Czechoslovakia were
packing public squares by the hundreds of thousands.
   ``We Poles _ constant rebels, as we were thought of the world
over _ are the prop of stability in Eastern and Central Europe
today,'' government spokeswoman Malgorzata Niezabitowska declared
at a news conference.
   And the Polish transition to democracy this year was achieved
more through hard, dull negotiating and grassroots political work
than through mass rallies, dramatic gestures or ultimatums.
   Instead of a huge wave of euphoria sweeping Poland after the
installation of a Solidarity government in September, activists
barely stopped to celebrate before getting down to the serious work
of reforming the moribund economy and rebuilding democratic
institutions after 45 years of one-party rule.
   But with the possible exception of the rise of populism in East
Germany, which has been accompanied by reports of anti-Polish
discrimination and has awakened fears of German reunification and
expansionism, Poles express paternal pride in the developments
elsewhere in the region.
   Adam Michnik, editor of the pro-Solidarity newspaper Gazeta
Wyborcza, recalled the appeal issued at the Solidarity trade union
congress in 1981 urging the other peoples of Eastern Europe to rise
up.
   At the time it was said, even by union sympathizers, that
Solidarity had gone too far and was inviting Soviet intervention.
   But in his recent travels around Eastern Europe, Michnik told a
gathering of Solidarity activists, he is surprised at how widely
that appeal is still remembered.
   ``Sometimes actions which seem pragmatically unwise in the short
term bear fruit in the long term, in great moral and political
capital,'' he said.
   Michnik said the model created by Solidarity of demanding
independence while eschewing violence or retribution has been
widely emulated.
   ``In this sense, Solidarity's path has become the path of the
most enlightened and best democratic forces in Central and Eastern
Europe,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>