<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1429EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     12-28 0432</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0452</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fans of the pop group New Kids on the Block put on
a hysterical show of appreciation that forced the cancellation of a
concert.
   About 4,000 concert-goers _ primarily teen-age girls and their
parents _ attended Wednesday's show, a benefit for Boston Against
Drugs. But the show ended before the first number when hundreds of
fans surged toward the stage.
   The musical group of five Boston teen-agers made a brief
appearance on stage before scampering to safety.
   Backstage the group presented Boston Against Drugs with a check
for $25,000.
   No injuries were reported. Police said one person was arrested
for drunken and disorderly conduct.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Richard Lewis says next week's episode of
``Anything But Love'' will be the first in which he and Jamie Lee
Curtis get a love scene.
   ``We were so intimidated,'' the star of the ABC comedy told the
Daily News. ``Jamie Lee's husband was in the audience and so was my
girlfriend. So we were embarrassed by the whole thing.''
   ``Believe me,'' he said, ``you can't have loved ones watching
you act.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>FORT LAUDERDALE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A lawyer who represented Rodney
Dangerfield in a lawsuit against a car dealership that used a
Dangerfield sound-alike in a commercial is now suing the comic,
claiming he owes more than $24,000 in legal fees.
   Robert Shupack's lawsuit, filed Wednesday, also names
Dangerfield's nephew Leonard Garfinkel, who is identified as his
uncle's agent or trustee.
   Shupack, of Hollywood, Fla., says nearly $18,000 of the money is
for the lawsuit he filed against Hollywood Honda. That suit was
settled out of court.
   Garfinkel said he had no comment.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rock Hudson's former secretary says his own
life is ``being made into a lie'' in an upcoming TV movie about the
actor.
   ``They've established my character as Mr. Big, (which) is not
true at all,'' Mark Miller, 63, said by telephone Wednesday from
his home in Hawaii.
   Susan Schafer, an attorney for the producer of the movie, the
Konigsberg-Sanitsky Co., insisted the script will be accurate.
``Rock Hudson'' is scheduled for broadcast Jan. 8 on ABC.
   Miller said he believes the script is being used to support an
account of Hudson's final years by Marc Christian, the star's
lover. Hudson died of AIDS in 1985.
   Christian sued the Hudson estate, saying the actor should have
revealed to Christian that he was infected with the AIDS virus. He
was awarded $21.7 million, which was cut to $5.5 million. The case
is under appeal.
</TEXT>

</DOC>