<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0109EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-Troops     12-25 0524</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Troops,0547</SECOND>
<HEAD>Combat Christmas in Panama: Glad to Be Alive</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CANDICE HUGHES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Though the Christmas trees and bright
faces of loved ones may have been missing, the 26,000 U.S. soldiers
occupying Panama on Christmas Day had a lot to be thankful for:
they were alive.
   A few even managed to gloat. ``I was freezing to death on Pope
Air Force Base (in North Carolina) five days ago,'' one said at the
former home of the ousted Panamanian strongman, Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noriega. ``Now I'm eating off Noriega's china.''
   However, 21-year-old Sgt. Ernie Nieto, said, ``I'm just glad to
see Christmas. The other night (in combat) I just wanted to see
sunup.''
   He spoke at the fire-blackened ruins of Panamanian Defense
Forces headquarters, destroyed in the early hours of the invasion.
   Nieto's tour of duty in Panama was up the day before the United
States invaded Dec. 20, and he had planned on a Christmas at home
in Albuquerque, N.M.
   Instead, he was in a gutted building.
   At the home of Noriega, two squads from the 82nd Airborne
Division munched the modern version of K-rations a few yards from
the deposed dictator's lavish Christmas tree.
   For the men on guard at the gate, there were soft drinks and
cheers from Noriega's neighbors.
   ``Do you need anything? Do you want some ice?'' Ana Julia Real
asked as she handed four quart bottles of Coca-Cola over the high
stone wall.
   ``Merry Christmas!'' a man called as he passed.
   E4 Greg Frye of Daltona, Fla., passed the sodas around to the
rest of his squad, sweating in the tropical heat.
   ``I try not to think about Christmas because that just makes it
harder,'' he said. ``But the moral support of the people has really
helped.''
   Sgt. John Stowe was one of the few who had planned to spend
Christmas in Panama City. But he thought it would be his hometown,
Panama City, Fla.
   Instead of unwrapping Christmas gifts, he was cracking open
boxes of G3 assault rifles at an arms cache.
   He didn't seem to mind. The cache was one of the biggest found
so far.
   At the international airport, which U.S. troops seized the first
night of the invasion, a group of soldiers sat around with their
M-16s singing Christmas carols.
   For some, it was still a family Christmas, even though they were
far from home.
   Sgt. 1st Class William Lucas and his son, Pvt. William Lucas
Jr., both parachuted in with the 82nd Airborne Division from Fort
Bragg, N.C. So did Lt. William Knowlton and his brother, 2nd Lt.
Mark Knowlton, of Fayetteville, N.C.
   Marine Corp. Chris Moeller, 20, managed to get someone to call
his wife, Jamie, and his 2-year-old son, Matthew, with this
message: ``Tell her I love her very much and to have a very merry
Christmas.''
   Mrs. Moeller, in Martin, Tenn., wept when she got the call.
   ``One guy he knows was killed and another was wounded,'' she
said. ``I have been so worried.''
   The corporal's presents are wrapped and waiting for him when he
gets home, she said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>