<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0095 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1058EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-Nicaragua     12-20 0326</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Nicaragua,0334</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sandinistas Mobilize Troops, Call U.S. Invasion Serious Threat</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FILADELFO ALEMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANAGUA, Nicaragua (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The leftist Sandinista government put
its armed forces on maximum alert today, mobilized troops and tanks
and called the U.S. invasion of Panama ``a serious threat to
Nicaragua.''
   Large howitzers were set up in the center of downtown Managua
and Red Beret special forces in camouflage uniforms were posted at
the international airport.
   President Daniel Orgega declared a ``state of national alert''
and asked for an urgent meeting of the U.N. Security Council. In
New York, the Security Council agreed to meet in emergency session
today.
   Ortega also sent messages to the Non-Aligned Movement and Pope
John Paul II saying he was ``deeply concerned by the invasion of
Panama.''
   ``In addition to constituting a flagrant trampling of the
sovereignty and territorial integrity of Panama, it is a threat to
the peace and security of all Latin America, Central America and
especially constitutes a serious threat to Nicaragua,'' Ortega said
in a communique read on Voice of Nicaragua radio.
   The army was put on a ``state of combative general alert.'' The
communique said that implied immediate deployment of land, sea and
air combat units. Reserves and civilian militia also were called up.
   Reporters saw Soviet-made T-55 tanks moving through the capital.
At least 20 howitzers were set up in the old shell of the city
center, flattened in the 1972 earthquake and fires, and never
rebuilt.
   ``When the world is demanding dialogue, peaceful solution of
conflicts and renunciation of the threat and use of force ...
actions like those that are causing destruction and death in our
sister state of Panama threaten the security and precarious
stability of the Central American region,'' said the communique.
   In declaring the state of alert, the government mentioned U.S.
invasions of Nicaragua earlier this century and continuing
confrontation over U.S.-supported Contra rebels in the past 10
years.
</TEXT>

</DOC>