<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0925EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Afghanistan     12-27 0393</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Afghanistan,0406</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rallies Mark 10th Anniversary of Soviet Invasion of Afghanistan</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRYAN WILDER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ISLAMABAD, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Afghan refugees today rallied in
several Pakistani camps to mark the 10th anniversary of the Soviet
intervention in Afghanistan.
   Also today, Western diplomats in Islamabad said the latest
reports indicate the Communist government, which the Red Army left
behind in Afghanistan in February, has arrested more than 200
people in a recent coup plot.
   Tens of thousands of Afghan guerrillas and their supporters
burned effigies and listened to impassioned speeches at refugee
camps around the Pakistani frontier city of Peshawar, where several
U.S.-backed rebel groups are based.
   They vowed to keep fighting for the downfall of President Najib
and pledged to replace his Marxist administration with a
guerrilla-run, Moslem government.
   About 100,000 Soviet troops intervened in Afghanistan in
December 1979 to replace one pro-Moscow government with another.
They stayed on to help fight the insurgency that began when the
Afghan Communists seized power in 1978.
   Soviet forces fought the guerrillas for nine years before
completing a phased withdrawal Feb. 15. The Kremlin continues
massive military supplies to the Kabul government. The Moslem
rebels are supported by the United States.
   The Communists still hold Afghanistan's major cities, but the
guerrillas control most of the countryside.
   Gulbaddin Hekmatyar, leader of the hard-line Hezb-i-Islami
guerrilla group, told a crowd of supporters at the Hyatabad refugee
camp near Peshawar today that his party would never enter a
coalition with the Communists.
   ``We believe that only the cessation of delivery of arms to the
crumbling Kabul regime will seal the fall of this disgusting
regime,'' Hekmatyar said.
   He also has accused the United States of interfering with his
aims.
   Western diplomats in Islamabad, speaking on condition of
anonymity, said the ruling People's Democratic Party of Afghanistan
has arrested more than 200 people in the latest outbreak of
factional infighting in Kabul.
   Officials in Kabul reported only the arrest of about 100
clandestine Hekmatyar supporters earlier this month. However,
Western diplomats allege that it was a coup plot among members of
the Afghan army.
   In recent years, the governing ``Parcham'' wing of Najib's party
has survived several conspiracies by the ``Khlaq'' faction, which
is dominated by the military.
   An estimated 2 million Afghans have fled the civil war to
neighboring Pakistan and 1 million went to Iran.
</TEXT>

</DOC>