<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0157 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1956EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     12-29 0307</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0320</SECOND>
<HEAD>Winter Storms in the West, the Midwest and the South</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Storms dumped snow, freezing rain or rain on sections of the
West, the Midwest and the South on Friday as winds gusted to more
than 60 mph in Northern California.
   Snow fell in Arizona, New Mexico, Colorado, Nebraska, Wyoming,
the Dakotas, Montana, Minnesota, Wisconsin, Michigan, New York, New
Jersey and Pennsylvania. Michigan and Nebraska also received
freezing rain.
   In six hours ending at 1 p.m. EST, 9 inches of snow fell in
Flagstaff, Ariz.; 2 inches in Houghton Lake, Mount Clemens and
Saginaw, Mich.; and 1 inch in Marquette and Oscoda, Mich.
   New Mexico's Sacramento Mountains received 8 inches of snow.
Ruidoso and Cloudcroft each received about 4 inches.
   Winter storm warnings, winter storm watches or snow advisories
were up in parts of Arizona, California, New Mexico, Ohio, New York
and Pennsylvania.
   Rain fell on Indiana, Illinois, Missouri, Kansas, Kentucky,
Tennessee and Mississippi.
   Heavier rainfall in the six hours ending at 1 p.m. EST included
1.36 inch in Lafayette, La; .89 inch in Paducah, Ky. and .68 inch
in Baton Rouge, La.
   Winds gusted over 60 mph in higher elevations near San Francisco
Bay and at some of the higher summits of the Sierra Nevada in the
morning. High-wind warnings were issued for the Yosemite National
Park area.
   Friday was the 22nd day in a row the temperature in Portland,
Maine, had not exceeded 32 degrees. It was the longest stretch of
freezing temperatures in the city's 50 years of record-keeping.
   The low temperature for the Lower 48 states Friday morning was
recorded in Grand Forks, N.D., where it was 17 degrees below zero.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EST ranged from 5
degrees below zero in Caribou and Limestone, Maine, to 81 degrees
in Kingsville, Texas.
</TEXT>

</DOC>