<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1017EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-RockwellAllegations     12-27 0348</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Rockwell Allegations,0358</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lawsuit Claims Rockwell Sought Information on Whistleblowers</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rockwell International Corp. obtained
confidential files about industry whistleblowers during a fraud
investigation, documents filed by an aerospace worker in U.S.
District Court allege.
   The documents claim that Rockwell officials sought information
on aerospace workers who complained of alleged fraud and safety
problems in the space shuttle program, The Houston Post reported
Tuesday.
   Rockwell has denied the allegations in filings in the lawsuit.
The company has no further comment because the litigation is
pending, spokeswoman Janet Dean said at the corporation's
headquarters in El Segundo, Calif.
   The lawsuit claims Rockwell used information it collected _ and
some of the law enforcement agencies that provided it _ in a
campaign of intimidation against whistleblowers that began after
the 1986 Challenger explosion.
   ``It is just beyond my wildest beliefs,'' said Ria Solomon, who
contends in her lawsuit that Rockwell stepped up a pattern of
harassment after she filed a civil rights lawsuit against the
company. ``Something like this should not happen in America,'' she
told the Post.
   Rockwell obtained information ranging from court documents and
police reports open to the public to personal data and criminal
histories kept on a computer network reserved for law enforcement
agencies, the court documents allege.
   Ms. Solomon said she and her mother received threatening
telephone calls and that phone lines and an electrical fuse box at
her home were destroyed after she reported illegalities in the
shuttle program.
   The court documents filed included depositions from other
whistleblowing employees.
   Ms. Solomon claims she lost her job at Unisys Corp. in 1987
because she objected to fraud and safety violations that could
endanger a space shuttle crew.
   Unisys, a subcontractor for Rockwell Space Operations Co., a
Houston-based subsidiary of Rockwell International, is responsible
for developing and distributing computer software for the shuttle
program. Rockwell is the primary contractor for the shuttle
construction.
   Ms. Solomon reached an undisclosed, out-of-court settlement with
Unisys and four Unisys employees. The suit remains against
Rockwell, RSOC and two RSOC security officials, James Roberts and
Danny T. Myers.
</TEXT>

</DOC>