<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0115 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 2124EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-RobinsonFuneral 1stLd-Writethru a0613 12-23 0589</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Robinson Funeral, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0613,0602</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hundreds Brave Savannah Snow For Funeral of Slain Alderman</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 13 grafs to UPDATE with quotes from service, detail
on weather; picks up 7th graf, `Hours before ...'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAVANNAH, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 450 mourners braved snow and freezing
temperatures Saturday to attend the funeral of Alderman Robert
Robinson, the civil rights attorney killed by a mail bomb and
eulogized as someone who loved politics and people.
   ``He would never let you down,'' Savannah NAACP President Curtis
Cooper told mourners at St. Paul's CME Church. ``He was the type of
man who could walk with kings, but never lost the common touch.''
   Robinson, 42, died Monday night shortly after a bomb mailed to
his Savannah law office exploded as he opened it. He was the second
victim of mail bombs federal officals believe might have been sent
by racists with grudge against the 11th U.S. Circuit Court of
Appeals.
   Robinson's death came two days after a similar bomb killed 11th
Circuit Judge Robert S. Vance and seriously injured his wife at
their home in a Birmingham, Ala., suburb.
   Despite the cold and more than 2 inches of snow in the Savannah
area, mourners packed the church for Saturday's service.
   The Rev. Henry Delaney, pastor of St. Paul's, said Saturday that
Robinson's death might seem senseless, but is part of a higher
political agenda for black Americans.
   Delaney said the death should be used to propel black politics
in Georgia forward, without fear of racist retaliation. He pointed
out that New York City elected its first black mayor shortly after
a black teen-ager was shot to death in a predominantly white
neighborhood.
   ``Don't you give up, Mrs. Robinson. Don't you give up, mother
Robinson. Don't you give up, children,'' Delaney shouted,
addressing Robinson's widow, mother and two children.
   ``Robbie was killed because he was a lawyer and because he
sought to rectify wrongs,'' said Alderman Floyd Adams, his voice
often cracking with emotion. ``If he were here, he would say `Don't
look at this as a setback. Don't be discouraged.'''
   W.W. Law, a former president of the National Association for the
Advancement of Colored People, said Robinson's life should serve as
a role model for young people, to inspire them to help those
shackled by social or economic injustice.
   ``There is so much instruction to be learned from this life,''
he said. ``He was the model of self-improvement and worked toward
the improvement of his community.''
   State Rep. Jim Pannell said Robinson's loss should strengthen
people in their resolve to help each other.
   ``The bombs of hatred will not drive us back,'' he said.
   Hours before Robinson died, a parcel bomb was found at the 11th
Circuit building in Atlanta. The next day, another one was
discovered at the Jacksonville, Fla., office of the National
Association for the Advancement of Colored People.
   On Friday, a county circuit judge in Hagerstown, Md., was
injured when a bomb exploded in his apartment 20 minutes after a
package was delivered. FBI officials said preliminary reports
indicated the incident was unrelated to the other bombings.
   FBI investigators have concentrated on possible racial
motivations in the slayings.
   Robinson represented the NAACP in a desegregation case involving
Savannah schools.
   Agents determined that Vance wrote an opinion in an unrelated
Jacksonville school desegregation case in September that was a
victory for the NAACP. A three-judge panel of the appeals court
unanimously reversed a lower court's ruling that Jacksonville could
stop busing students because the school system was integrated.
</TEXT>

</DOC>