<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0104 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 2126EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-Panama-DelCid 3rdLd-Writethru a0625 12-25 0368</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Panama-Del Cid, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0625,320</SECOND>
<HEAD>Indicted Panamanian Officer Brought to Miami to Face Charges</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 6th graf pvs bgng, `A federal,' with 1 graf to UPDATE with
del Cid at Metro Correctional Institute at Miami, more detail on arraignment</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RUTH SINAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Panamanian officer indicted along with
deposed dictator Manuel Antonio Noriega on drug-related charges was
escorted to Miami on Monday by U.S. drug enforcement agents, the
Justice Department announced.
   Lt. Col. Luis del Cid, a Noriega loyalist who commanded a Panama
Defense Forces unit in the province of Chiriqui, gave himself up to
U.S. forces in Panama, said spokeswoman Deborah Burstion-Wade.
   Del Cid was one of 15 Noriega associates indicted in February
1988 by a federal grand jury in Miami. He is wanted on four counts
related to cocaine possession and laundering drug profits, the
spokeswoman said.
   After turning himself in, del Cid was arrested by agents of the
Drug Enforcement Administration in Panama, she said.
   DEA agents escorted him to Miami. ``Normally he would have been
flown in by U.S. marshals, but this was not an ordinary case,'' she
said.
   Ms. Burstion-Wade said Monday night that del Cid had been taken
to the Metro Correctional Institute, a federal facility in Miami.
His initial court appearance was scheduled for Tuesday afternoon,
and U.S. Attorney Dexter Lehtenin is to handle the matter for the
government, she said.
   Del Cid surrendered on Saturday and declared loyalty to the new
government of Guillermo Endara, installed as president last week
after U.S. troops invaded Panama to remove Noriega from power.
   The Miami indictment unsealed Feb. 5, 1988 against Noriega, del
Cid and others alleges that the ousted strongman accepted a $4.6
million bribe from Colombia's Medellin cartel to protect shipments
of cocaine, launder money, supply drug laboratories and shield drug
traffickers from the law.
   A separate federal grand jury in Tampa, Fla., indicted Noriega
several days later on charges of taking another $5.4 million bribe
from the Colombia drug cartel.
   The Justice Department has said that if Noriega is brought to
the United States, he would be tried first in Miami because the
prosecutors' case there was stronger than in Tampa.
</TEXT>

</DOC>