<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0840EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Philippines     12-26 0279</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Philippines,0289</SECOND>
<HEAD>Communist Leader Escapes From Military Prison</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A jailed leader of the outlawed
Communist Party escaped from a maximum-security stockade by bribing
her guards, a military official said today.
   Wilma Tiamzon, wife of party chairman Benito Tiamzon, escaped
Monday during Christmas celebrations inside Camp Crame, the
Philippine Constabulary headquarters, in suburban Quezon City, the
official said.
   The escape was discovered this morning, said Col. Alfredo
Filler, chief of staff of the Constabulary.
   A press statement said Mrs. Tiamzon, who was arrested Oct. 2,
``apparently mixed with visitors who were allowed inside the ...
jail and slipped without being noticed.''
   Mrs. Tiamzon allegedly was the head of the party's Finance
Commission, secretary of its National Peasant Commission and a
member of the executive committee of the party Central Committee
and of the Politburo. A $46,000 reward had been offered for her
capture.
   Her husband remained at large.
   ``It seems that they bribed the guards,'' Filler said, adding
that a Constabulary officer and three enlisted men were being
questioned. ``With regard to the physical security at the camp, I
think we have taken every measure to ensure that there will be no
other escape.''
   Romulo Kintanar, chief of the Communist New People's Army,
escaped from the same stockade in November 1988.
   Kintanar and his wife, Gloria Jopson, escaped while attending
the birthday party of camp's jail warden, who has since been
replaced.
   Constabulary chief Maj. Gen. Ramon Montano today ordered the
arrest of the officer in charge of the stockade, Capt. Victor
Diego, and three enlisted men for ``laxity.''
   Montano also ordered the constabulary's inspector general, Brig.
Gen. Carlos Malana, to investigate the latest escape.
</TEXT>

</DOC>