<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0307EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-NYCPolice     12-19 0493</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-NYC Police,0509</SECOND>
<HEAD>Surprise, Skepticism Greet Brown Appointment</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIRGINIA BYRNE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police union leaders expressed skepticism and a
wait-and-see stand over the appointment of Houston Police Chief Lee
Brown as the city's new police commissioner.
   ``Midtown South is bigger than the whole town of Houston. Our
problems are 20 times bigger. Let's see what he can do,'' said Lt.
James Gebhardt, head of the Lieutenants Benevolent Association, a
union that represents 1,100 lieutenants.
   Brown, 52, has headed a 4,000-officer department in Houston
since 1982, and Gebhardt questioned whether he is prepared to run
the 26,000-officer force, the nation's largest.
   ``The challenges are there. It's whether he can handle a
department this big,'' Gebhardt said.
   Mayor-elect David Dinkins selected Brown on Monday over four
other finalists, including the current commissioner, Richard Condon.
   ``We need the best police commissioner we could find,'' Dinkins
told reporters. ``Of all of the finalists, he seemed to be the
absolute best in the country.''
   Brown will take over Jan. 22 in a city wracked with drug-related
crime. The murder rate is at a record level, with crack the prime
cause.
   ``The thing that will hit him immediately is the drug-crime
problem,'' said Thomas Reppetto, head of the independent watchdog
Citizens Crime Commission and a member of the search committee that
interviewed Brown.
   Brown, who called his appointment a ``once-in-a-lifetime
opportunity,'' has served as public safety chief in Houston,
Atlanta and Portland, Ore.
   Small potatoes, some said.
   ``Atlanta and Houston are different from New York City. I think
he's going to find that out very quickly. I think he's got a tough
row to hoe,'' said Michael Vecchione, a former department attorney
who now sits on the Civilian Complaint Review Board.
   ``He's an out-of-towner so he'll have to learn the city
system,'' said Sgt. Joe Toal, head of the Sergeants Benevolent
Association of 3,000 sergeants. ``I guess we're in for a lot of
changes.''
   Brown is the first commissioner from out of town since Howard
Leary of Philadelphia served from 1966-1970. Vecchione said his
outsider status wasn't an asset.
   ``Police officers do not take well to outsiders. It's not going
to be easy for him,'' Vecchione said.
   ``Why did they have to go outside? Does this mean that there is
nobody in the NYPD who is qualified?'' asked the Rev. Lawrence
Lucas, a black activist who is pastor of the Roman Catholic Church
of The Resurrection in Harlem.
   Condon predicted that Brown's biggest challenge ``is definitely
the budget and the fact that we have a tremendous problem with
narcotics.''
   ``The preliminary estimate is that we are not going to be adding
to the police department. If anything, we're going to be losing
police officers. I think that's a terrible problem,'' Condon said.
   Vecchione also said Brown will have a difficult time figuring
out New York's police department. ``It will take time until he
knows where all the bodies are buried,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>