<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0155EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-YuleBang Bjt   12-20 0558</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Yule Bang, Bjt,530</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chemist's Christmas Show Seeks to Lure Kids Into Science</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WX7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT M. ANDREWS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bassam Z. Shakhashiri is ushering in the
Christmas season with a bang.
   Several hundred children squealed with delight Tuesday night
when a loud boom and burst of flames from an exploding hydrogen
balloon signaled the start of the Lebanese-born professor's 20th
annual Christmas science show.
   It's called ``Once Upon a Christmas Cheery in the Lab of
Shakhashiri,'' and he's taking his popular chemistry lecture this
season to Madison, Wis., Washington and Boston.
   Standing on the stage of the National Academy of Sciences
auditorium, Shakhashiri doffed his tuxedo jacket, black bow tie and
ruffled shirt and set to work wearing a ``Science is Fun'' T-shirt.
   For the next hour, he captivated his audience of more than 600
kids and their parents with a demonstration of ``the beauty, the
magic and the adventure'' of science, often using ordinary
household chemicals found in vinegar, laundry detergent and
disposable diapers.
   As Shakhashiri performed his scientific sleight of hand, bottles
popped their corks, a metal can collapsed, a phony dollar bill
vanished in a puff, a dishpan overflowed with fog, clear liquids
turned into Yuletide greens and reds or glowed in the dark, and a
gooey yellow stuff kept oozing out of its glass jar like a yogurt
machine gone haywire.
   While a visiting Santa Claus applauded from the front row,
Shakhashiri delivered his show-stopping finale, shaking a flask
containing silver nitrate, ammonia, sugar and other ingredients to
produce a giant, shiny Christmas tree ornament. Then he made his
pitch to the wide-eyed youngsters.
   Have fun and work hard in school, he said, and think about a
career in science or mathematics ``because our country needs you.''
   Shakhashiri, whose first name rhymes with ``Shazam'' and means
``Smiley'' in his native Beirut, emigrated to the United States
with his parents in 1957. He is a chemistry professor at the
University of Wisconsin at Madison on leave as assistant director
of the National Science Foundation, an independent federal agency
that awards grants to colleges and public schools for scientific
education and research.
   It was at the Wisconsin campus that Shakhashiri delivered his
first Christmas lecture ``for kids of all ages'' in 1970. He
borrowed the idea from Michael Faraday, the great English chemist
and physicist whose Christmas science lectures for children were
popular in the 1840s.
   ``I'm trying to share the excitement and joy of doing hands-on
science,'' Shakhashiri said in an interview. ``I don't try to snow
anybody with technical details. My idea is to capture their
interest and not allow them to extinguish their flame of
curiosity.''
   Shakhashiri is disturbed by a foundation estimate that the
United States faces a cumulative shortfall of 450,000 native-born
college graduates with bachelor's degrees in science, math and
engineering by the year 2000, and a projected shortage of 8,000
scientists with doctorates by 2004.
   ``It's very, very alarming,'' he says. The nation desperately
needs highly trained scientists to tackle such challenges as the
superconducting super collider, space stations, human genetic
mapping and the AIDS epidemic, he says.
   ``What's at stake is the pre-eminence of the United States in
science and technology and the global economy, and the quality of
life not only in the United States but on earth,'' Shakhashiri said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>