<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0289 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1914EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Campeau     12-22 0491</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Campeau,0507</SECOND>
<HEAD>Federated, Allied Receive Delinquency Notice</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CINCINNATI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Federated Department Stores Inc. and Allied
Stores Corp. said Friday they have received notices that the
companies failed to comply with reporting requirements under their
bank credit agreements.
   The notices, which were dated Thursday, said reports must be
made within 10 days or the loans would be considered to be in
default, the two Campeau Corp. divisions said.
   Federated and Allied said they reported in quarterly filings on
Oct. 28 that they were unable to determine whether they were
solvent, although they also could not determine if they were
insolvent.
   In separate but identical statements, Federated and Allied said:
``The company believes it is in full compliance with its reporting
obligations under its credit agreement, and it has advised the
lender that it believes the lender's assertion of a default on such
basis is wholly without merit.''
   Trading in Campeau stock was halted Friday at the Toronto Stock
Exchange. Campeau has been publicly foundering in financial
difficulties since September, when it announced that its cash flow
might not be adequate to meet its cash needs in the coming months.
   At that time it received $250 million in new financing from
Olympia &amp; York Developments Ltd. Bloomingdale's, Campeau's prize
retail chain, was put up for sale and Robert Campeau was forced to
give up control of the company he founded.
   About a half dozen bidders reportedly are considering buying the
17-store Bloomingdale's chain. Among those who have expressed
interest are JMB Realty Corp., a shopping mall developer; Japan's
Tokyu Department Store Co.; real estate developer Donald Trump; a
group led by Joseph Brooks, chairman of the Ann Taylor store chain;
and a group led by Bloomingdale's Chairman Marvin Traub.
   A sixth bidder, possibly Japanese, also is expected to take part
in the second round of bidding.
   Campeau has said it hopes to complete the sale by February.
   Negotiations have been under way for the past week between
Campeau's restructuring committee, chaired by Olympia &amp; York
representative Lionel Dodd, and the company's creditors to
restructure much of its $10 billion debt.
   After Campeau's third-quarter results were released last week,
the company said its U.S. retail operations might be forced to file
for protection from creditors under U.S. bankruptcy law because
cash flow doesn't appear adequate to cover debt payments.
   Retail analyst Karen Sach at Standard &amp; Poor's Corp. in New York
said there was speculation that Campeau would soon announce that it
wants to sell other retailers besides Bloomingdale's or that it had
decided not to sell Bloomingdale's.
   Campeau's stores around the United States include Abraham &amp;
Straus, Burdines, Lazarus, Rich's, The Bon Marche, Jordan Marsh,
Maas Brothers and Stern's.
   Although sales and operating profits are up from last year,
financing costs have increased so much that Campeau lost $390
million in the first nine months of the year, compared with a loss
of $24 million for the same period last year.
</TEXT>

</DOC>