<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0325EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-DEA-Marijuana Bjt   12-30 0451</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-DEA-Marijuana, Bjt,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>DEA Rejects Relaxation of Marijuana Restrictions</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By W. DALE NELSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Drug Enforcement Administration, rejecting
a recommendation of its own chief judge, has refused to relax
restrictions on marijuana.
   The order by Administrator John C. Lawn, published Friday in the
Federal Register, means that marijuana will continue to be listed
under Schedule I of the Controlled Substances Act, for substances
with a high potential for abuse and no accepted medical
application, where it has been classified since the act was passed
in 1970.
   NORML, the National Organization for Marijuana Law Reform,
petitioned three years ago to have the substance reclassified to
Schedule II, meaning it would remain unavailable to the general
public but could be prescribed by doctors for limited purposes.
   The DEA's chief administrative law judge, Francis L. Young,
recommended Sept. 6, 1988, that marijuana be placed on the less
restrictive schedule, calling it ``one of the safest
therapeutically active substances known to man.''
   Young cited a number of medical experts and patients as saying
marijuana helped suppress nausea and vomiting experienced by cancer
patients receiving chemotherapy, and was effective in controlling
muscle spasms of patients with multiple sclerosis.
   ``The evidence in this record clearly shows that marijuana has
been accepted as capable of relieving the distress of great numbers
of very ill people, and doing so with safety under medical
supervision,'' Young wrote. ``It would be unreasonable, arbitrary
and capricious for DEA to continue to stand between those sufferers
and the benefits of this substance in light of the evidence in this
record.''
   Lawn, in his order, said that Young ``failed to act as an
impartial judge in this matter.''
   ``He appears to have ignored the scientific evidence, ignored
the testimony of highly credible and recognized medical experts
and, instead, relied on the testimony of psychiatrists and
individuals who used marijuana,'' the administrator said.
   He also said that Young, in his findings of fact, ``ignored any
evidence presented by the government.''
   ``Mr. Lawn found that there was a lack of credible evidence to
support a conclusion that safety, efficacy and acceptance had been
demonstrated for the medical use of marijuana,'' the DEA said in a
news release.
   Young could not be reached for comment.
   Donald Fiedler, national director of NORML, said, ``The ruling
is arbitrary and capricious because it means doctors now don't have
that tool available to use marijuana as a medicine. Denying access
to medicine to those who need it is hypocrisy in the worst sense.''
   The DEA said physicians and scientists will be able to continue
to file proposals with it and with the Food and Drug Administration
for further research on medical aspects of marijuana.
</TEXT>

</DOC>