<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0210 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1758EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-AutoLayoffs Bjt   12-28 0453</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Auto Layoffs, Bjt,0469</SECOND>
<HEAD>GM Plans to Cut 3,200 Jobs at Kansas, Georgia, Oklahoma Plants</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM S. BERGSTROM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   General Motors Corp. will cut about 3,200
production jobs at three plants in February and March because of
slow auto sales, the nation's biggest automaker said Thursday in
another indication of the industry's severe slump.
   The cuts are in addition to temporary shutdowns announced last
week by GM, Ford Motor Co. and Chrysler Corp. and mark the second
major production cuts announced by GM in as many weeks.
   ``The market is forecast to be continually weak into the first
part of 1990,'' said William Steele of Montgomery Securities Inc.
in San Francisco.
   The Big Three auto companies said last week they planned
temporary January shutdowns at 42 of their 53 U.S. assembly plants,
affecting more than 127,000 workers.
   Ford and Chrysler spokesmen said Thursday their companies hadn't
made plans for further cuts.
   At GM, production will be cut in February and March at three
midsize car assembly plants, spokeswoman Nettie H. Seabrooks said.
   On Feb. 26, the company will lay off the 1,900-employee
afternoon shift at the Doraville, Ga., plant where the Oldsmobile
Cutlass Supreme is made, Seabrooks said.
   On the same date, about 700 of the 4,200 workers at GM's
Fairfax, Kan., plant will be laid off, cutting production of the
Pontiac Grand Prix, she said.
   On March 26, about 600 of the 6,000 employees at GM's Oklahoma
City plant will be taken off assembly line work as Buick Century,
Pontiac 6000 and Oldsmobile Cutlass Ciera production is slowed.
   The Oklahoma City employees won't be laid off, but will be
transferred to a ``jobs bank'' that provides them with other work
while production jobs are suspended, Seabrooks said.
   She said the cutbacks are for an indefinite period.
   General Motors on Dec. 22 announced it planned to eliminate a
production shift at its Linden, N.J. on Feb. 26, resulting in
indefinite layoffs for about 1,600 workers. The automaker also cut
or indefinitely idle a total of about 1,040 jobs at three Canadian
plants.
   GM is cutting production because of slow auto sales that have
bloated inventories at a time that slow economic growth is not
expected to help reverse the trend.
   ``With so much talk of recession, it causes people to hold off
on their big ticket purchases,'' Steele said.
   However, he predicted, sales are likely to revive with easing
interest rates late in the first half of 1990.
   Steele said that after a slow start, car and light truck sales
would total 14.4 million for 1990 _ falling short of an expected
14.9 million total for 1989 _ and then rally to 15.5 million in
1991.
</TEXT>

</DOC>