<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0331EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-FarmPrices     12-30 0615</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Farm Prices,610</SECOND>
<HEAD>Farmers Receive Record-High Prices in 1989</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Agriculture Department says farmers saw
prices rise again in December and are winding up 1989 as a year of
record-high prices, eclipsing the old 12-month record set five
years ago.
   Prices farmers got for raw products rose 0.7 percent from
November to December, leaving the monthly average 2.1 percent above
the level of December 1988.
   Higher prices for hogs, cattle, milk and eggs were mostly
responsible for the increase from the November average, the
department's Agricultural Statistics Board said Friday in its final
report of the year. Lower prices were reported for lettuce,
oranges, cotton and broilers.
   Most of the price information was collected at mid-month before
the latest freeze that swept into Florida and Texas, destroying
citrus and vegetable crops. The preliminary figures will be revised
next month.
   The report said the December milk price was the highest on
record and that the average for hogs was the highest since October
1987.
   John Buche of the department's National Agricultural Statistics
Service said the preliminary 12-month price average for all farm
commodities _ about 147 percent of a 1977 base used for comparison
_ is the highest on record.
   The previous high index reading was 142 percent in 1984, he
said. The 1988 average was 138 percent.
   No new figures were provided on prices farmers pay to meet
expenses. Due to budget restrictions, those are computed every
three months. In October, the ``prices paid'' index averaged 2.9
percent more than a year earlier.
   On Dec. 20, the department's Economic Research Service issued
income estimates showing that net cash income of farmers in 1989
may be in the range of $52 billion to $57 billion, compared with a
revised estimate of $57.2 billion in 1988.
   Department economists say the decline is due mostly to larger
expenses as they put more land back into crops, and to reduced
federal payments.
   Net cash income is the money nationally that farmers have left
from gross cash income during a calendar year after deducting cash
expenses. It includes government payments and proceeds from crops
grown previously but sold during the year.
   Department projections for 1990 show net cash income ``likely
will exceed'' $50 billion for the fourth consecutive year.
   Consumer food prices are estimated by USDA economists to have
risen about 5.7 percent this year, the sharpest rise since 1981.
They project food prices may rise 3 percent to 5 percent in 1990.
   Based on the preliminary figures, the December price index for
livestock and poultry rose 2.4 percent from November and averaged
9.7 percent more than a year ago.
   The meat animal portion of the index was up 2.9 percent from
November and 8.4 percent from December 1988. Dairy prices rose 2.5
percent from November and 18 percent from a year ago.
   Department economists predict milk output will increase in 1990
and that the record price levels will recede.
   Earlier Friday, the department announced a 50-cent reduction in
the federal price support of milk beginning Jan. 1 to $10.10 per
100 pounds. The cut was ordered to help stem an expected rise in
surplus production in 1990.
   Under the dairy price support program, USDA buys surplus butter,
cheese and non-fat dry milk to bolster the price of milk at the
farm. With a lower support for 1990, officials say less surplus
production will be bought.
   Crop prices, overall, declined 1.6 percent from November and 8.1
percent from December 1988, including lower prices for fruit,
commercial vegetables and cotton. Food grains _ wheat and rice _
were up 2.7 percent from November but averaged 1.9 percent below a
year ago.
</TEXT>

</DOC>