<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0230 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0215EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-BusinessHighlights     12-29 0836</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Business Highlights,0880</SECOND>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. industry should enjoy its eighth
consecutive year of rising sales in 1990 but growth will be
sluggish, with automaking and construction particularly hard hit,
the government said.
   In its annual industrial outlook, the Commerce Department
predicted Thursday that 150 of 193 manufacturing industries it
surveyed would enjoy rising sales in the coming year.
   But the other one-fourth of manufacturing industries will
experience either no sales increase or a decline in sales, the
department predicted.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United States enters the 1990s facing
tough decisions needed to erase policy mistakes in the last decade
that threaten its global economic leadership, a congressional study
concluded.
   The study, prepared by the staff of the Joint Economic Committee
and released Thursday, said the No. 1 economic problem facing the
country was the federal budget deficit.
   ``We will not solve our most pressing economic problems unless
we reduce the deficit,'' the study said.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The recent weather-related jump in energy and wholesale food
prices should have a minimal impact on interest rates barring
severe crop or oil shortages, but frigid temperatures in coming
months could chill investors' inflation outlook, economists said.
   A record-setting cold snap in the past week has heavily damaged
fruit and vegetable crops in such major growing areas as Florida
and Texas and sent heating oil prices soaring in many parts of the
country.
   Oil futures prices, which had risen sharply in recent days,
dropped Thursday amid profit-taking and higher deposit requirements
imposed by the New York Mercantile Exchange.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eastern Airlines said it will cut 600 jobs and
temporarily trim salaries for about 10,000 workers as the
retrenching carrier prepares to sell its Latin American routes and
shrink its home base.
   The downsizing, announced Thursday, is part of Eastern's plan
for reorganization in the wake of the strike that idled the carrier
for several months early this year.
   The move reflects Eastern's intention to return to its original
reorganization plan of cutting its pre-strike operations by a
third. In August, Eastern said it decided to pare operations by
only 10 percent.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   General Motors Corp. will cut about 3,200
production jobs at three plants in February and March because of
slow auto sales, the nation's biggest automaker said in another
indication of the industry's severe slump.
   The cuts, announced Thursday, are in addition to temporary
shutdowns announced last week by GM, Ford Motor Co. and Chrysler
Corp. and mark the second major production cuts announced by GM in
as many weeks.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CAMDEN, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three heirs to the Campbell Soup Co. fortune
put their 17 percent stake up for sale and urged that the entire
food-products company be sold, intensifying a rift between members
of the founding family.
   The group, comprised of three nieces of Campbell's late Chairman
John T. Dorrance Jr. and their husbands, said in a Securities and
Exchange Commission filing that it would seek ``a price per share
significantly in excess of current market value.''
   The group also said Thursday it would encourage Campbell's board
of directors to do the same and consider ousting members who
opposed a sale.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Florida orange growers and northern heating-oil
users may curse the cold, but the weather has been a blessing to
commodity speculators who have profited from skyrocketing futures
prices of the two products.
   Speculative trader George Booth estimated Thursday his customers
will make $700,000 to $1 million from the Florida freeze.
   The Norwood Hyacinth Fund, a public futures fund managed by Dunn
Capital Management Inc. in Stuart, Fla., tallied profits of
$383,000 in the heating-oil futures market from Nov. 22 through
Wednesday.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United States has asked Japan to help
rebuild Panama's shattered economy and dispatched a team of experts
to assess the costs of repairing the devastation from last week's
military invasion, officials said.
   In addition, representatives from the Treasury, State and
Commerce departments have begun deliberations on long-term plans to
repair the damage wrought by two years of U.S. economic warfare
against former Panamanian ruler Manuel Antonio Noriega.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   With air travel expected to slow during the winter months, big
airlines are aiming to stimulate traffic by cutting fares as much
as 30 percent in selected markets.
   The fare reductions, in effect through early March, only apply
to around 10 percent of the airlines' route networks _ but they
involve densely traveled routes.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Stock prices inched up Thursday, continuing their tentative
yearend rally. The Dow Jones average of 30 industrials rose 7.90
points to 2,732.30.
   The dollar finished sharply higher in domestic trading after
putting in a mixed performance overseas. Gold prices fell.
   Bond prices advanced moderately.
   Orange juice futures prices added to their freeze-driven gains;
near-month heating oil futures closed lower for the first time in
nine days; precious metals retreated; grains and soybeans advanced;
and livestock and meat futures were mixed.
</TEXT>

</DOC>