<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0517EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-Shopping     12-28 0425</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Shopping,0438</SECOND>
<HEAD>Food Carts Overflow as Panamanians Stock up Just In Case</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOSEPH B. FRAZIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Felicidad Pena de Navarro's
supermarket cart overflowed with canned goods, rice, sugar and
other non-perishables as she shopped for the first time following
the U.S. invasion.
   But the housewife was not only concerned with serving her family
dinner Wednesday night. She was shopping ahead in case of more
turmoil, which in recent years has engulfed Panama often and with
little warning.
   ``We're going to put this away and not touch it, put it away for
the next time,'' Mrs. Pena de Navarro said.
   She and others lined up outside the Gago supermarket, one of the
few that reopened because it hadn't been looted following the U.S.
invasion that toppled Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   ``This time it hit us at night,'' Mrs. Pena de Navarro said of
the Dec. 19-20 military assault.
   ``I was going to go shopping the next day and my husband said I
was an idiot, why didn't I think ahead. Well look, now I'm thinking
ahead,'' said Mrs. Pena.
   A battalion of stock clerks raced to pile foods on shelves
faster than shoppers could pull them off. Trucks rolled up with
fresh vegetables and milk, unseen here in recent days.
   A group of U.S. soldiers in combat gear mingled with the
shoppers to buy cartons of juice or soft drinks and to pose with
shoppers who wanted their pictures taken.
   Store employees gleefully waved them to the head of the long
checkout lines, where they deposited hefty tips on the bewildered
bagboy who sacked up their orders.
   Hundreds of stores hit by looters were left bare of items from
food to furniture, and even cars were stolen from dealerships.
   Looters tended to favor jewelry shops, camera stores and
electronics such as stereos and television sets. Bookstores were
not bothered.
   While most Panamanians live fairly well by regional standards,
it still is a country where aspirin tablets and cigarettes often
are sold one at a time.
   The small open-air markets that sell everything from soup to
soap are concentrated in the poorer areas of the capital where the
fighting was heaviest, and are just beginning to reopen with scant
merchandise.
   Produce is starting to arrive from the countryside but shipments
are being slowed by a gasoline shortage.
   Earlier this week, large piles of produce reportedly were
rotting in rural areas because there was no way to get the food to
market or to refrigerated storage.
</TEXT>

</DOC>