<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0149 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 2244EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Deaths 1stLd-Writethru a0690 12-27 0698</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Deaths, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0690,0739</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eds: ADDS Phelan and Craft. AMs separates moved on Randall as a0511;
on Garde as a0489; and on Franklin as a0675.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Walter Randall</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ORLANDO, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Walter Doane ``Bo'' Randall, renowned as
one of the world's best knife makers, died Monday at age 80.
   The cause of death was not available.
   Randall, who began hand-crafting hunting knives half a century
ago as a hobby, had an eight-member factory in Orlando that turned
out knives favored by the Army's Special Forces and military men
and civilians in many countries.
   Randall knives are displayed in the Smithsonian Institution and
the Museum of Special Warfare at Fort Bragg, N.C.
   The knife-collector's bible, American Knives, called Randall the
world's greatest blade maker.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Betty Garde</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Betty Garde, who appeared in hundreds of
radio plays and portrayed Aunt Eller in the original Broadway
production of ``Oklahoma,'' died Monday at age 84.
   The cause of death was not available.
   Garde began her stage career in the early 1920s. She played
character roles in Broadway productions such as ``The Social
Register'' and ``The Primrose Path.''
   In the 1930s she moved into radio, appearing in three dozen
shows over the years, including ``The Eddie Cantor Show,'' ``Perry
Mason'' and ``The Fat Man.''
   She probably was best known as the wife of ``Lorenzo Jones'' and
as ``Mrs. Wiggs of the Cabbage Patch.''
   Garde worked on several Orson Welles radio specials and appeared
regularly in the dramatic anthology ``Theater Guild on the Air.''
   She had a few motion picture and television roles, notably as
Wanda Skutnik in the James Stewart film ``Call Northside 777.''
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Cecil Franklin</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Cecil Franklin, singer Aretha Franklin's brother
and personal manager, died Tuesday of a heart attack. He was 49.
   Franklin was assistant pastor of New Bethel Baptist Church in
Detroit.
   He became an aide to his father about 20 years ago at the church
the Rev. C.L. Franklin Sr. founded in 1946.
   The elder Franklin, a civil rights activist, died in 1984.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Mickey Hooten</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mickey L. Hooten, a broadcasting executive for
The Hearst Corp., died Sunday of a heart attack at age 54.
   Hooten joined Hearst in 1974 as program manager of WTAE-TV in
Pittsburgh.
   In 1976, he became vice president and general manager of
Hearst's WISN-TV in Milwaukee.
   He was named general manager of television for Hearst
Broadcasting in 1984 and became a corporate vice president in 1986.
   Hooten also worked at KTBS-TV in Shreveport, La., WTOL-TV in
Toledo, Ohio, WIS-TV in Columbia, S.C., and WGHP-TV in High Point,
N.C.
   He was a past chairman of the ABC Television Network Affiliates
Board of Governors.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Carol Phelan</NOTE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Carol Phelan, whose husband led the ethics probe
that prompted the resignation of former U.S. House Speaker Jim
Wright, died Tuesday of a heart attack in Hawaii at age 52.
   She was the wife of Chicago lawyer Richard J. Phelan, who is
seeking the Democratic nomination for Cook County board president
in the March 1990 primary.
   A partner in the Chicago law firm of Phelan, Pope &amp; John, Phelan
drew national attention when he led the investigation of Wright for
the House ethics committee. The Texas Democrat resigned earlier
this year.
   Mrs. Phelan founded Riverside Architects Ltd. in Chicago in
1985. She was also founder and president of the Hope Through
Housing Foundation, which arranges low-cost housing for the
handicapped, elderly and single-parent families.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Roy Craft</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>STEVENSON, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Roy D. Craft, former publisher of the
Skamania County Pioneer and a former publicist for Marilyn Monroe,
died Monday from emphysema and pulmonary edema at age 81.
   Craft was editor and publisher of the newspaper from 1958 to
1974. After selling the paper, he continued to write his column,
``Talking it Over,'' until his death.
   Craft served in the Army during World War II. After the war, he
moved to Hollywood, where he worked as a correspondent for Life
magazine, then as a publicist for Howard Hughes' film studio.
   He then became a publicist for Miss Monroe.
   Craft also promoted Elvis Presley's first film ``Love Me
Tender.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>