<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0240 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0503EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-SPE--Bride&amp;Groom:TheAlcoholQuestion     12-18 0403</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-SPE--Bride &amp; Groom: The Alcohol Question,0405</SECOND>
<HEAD>SPECIAL EDITION</HEAD>
<HEAD>Bride &amp; Groom: The Alcohol Question</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   When planning their wedding party, Donald and Susan Waite
confronted the issue of whether and how to serve alcohol at their
wedding.
   The Waites decided to serve both liquor and non-alcoholic
drinks, set up at separate bars. The Waites took another step that
is becoming more common, according to their caterer: They specified
that no alcohol be used in food preparation.
   Serving food laced with spirits creates a problem for people
with ulcers and other physical disabilities and for recovering
alcoholics, so it's better not to do so, according to caterer Molly
Siple. The Waites' sensitivity is not unique. ``My mail is filled
with questions on how to handle alcohol,'' says Cele Lalli, editor
of Modern Bride. It can be particularly touchy if one family has
religious scruples against alcohol and the other family does not.
   ``I always tell readers that they don't have to serve alcohol if
doing so would make them uncomfortable. Often a good compromise is
to have two separate bars _ one with alcohol and the other
without,'' adds Lalli.
   According to Millie Martini Bratten, an editor at Bride's
magazine, ``We see more people beefing up the nonalcoholic side of
the wedding by serving designer waters and natural sodas. There's
more of a choice for people who don't drink.''
   Boyce Brawley, of New York Parties, says concern about guests'
drinking is much more evident among hosts than it used to be. ``Our
bartenders can cut someone off by not serving them.'' At some
weddings, only champagne and sparkling water are served. If there
is a full bar, bartenders are urged to exercise discretion, perhaps
making succeeding drinks weaker for a guest if they notice he has
been consuming a great deal of alcohol.
   There was a period when everything, including the cake, was
soaked in liqueur. That's no longer fashionable, according to
Brawley. ``The idea of being a social drinker is being looked at
with more scrutiny.''
   Wedding consultant Marcy Blum says hosts worry about too long a
cocktail hour. ``They don't want guests drinking for two hours,
whereas in the past they didn't care. At two recent weddings we set
up a separate non-alcoholic bar and featured non-alcoholic
prominently. Smoking grass outside _ something that used to happen
at weddings _ is no longer considered acceptable,'' she adds.
</TEXT>

</DOC>