<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0178 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1252EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-YE--Chronology'89 Adv00-1stAdd   12-19 1039</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-YE--Chronology '89, Adv 00 - 1st Add,1090</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv00</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release in Year-End Editions</HEAD>
<HEAD>UNDATED: 184 survivors.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   JULY 27 _ Carl Pettersson convicted in slaying of Swedish
Premier Olof Palme, but conviction later overturned. Korean Air
DC-10 crashes in Libya; 80 die.
   JULY 28 _ Israelis kidnap Sheik Abdul-Karim Obeid of Hezbollah
from southern Lebanon.
   JULY 31 _ Lebanese kidnappers claim they hanged U.S. hostage
William Higgins, a Marine lieutentant colonel.
   AUG. 3 _ Hashemi Rafsanjani sworn in as Iran's new president.
   AUG. 5 _ Congress passes landmark $159 billion bill to bail out
savings and loan industry; President Bush signs it into law four
days later.
   AUG. 7 _ Communications workers strike three regional phone
companies. U.S. Congressman Mickey Leland killed in plane crash in
Ethiopia.
   AUG. 9 _ Toshiki Kaifu named new prime minister in Japan.
Mexican train crash kills 112.
   AUG. 14 _ P.W. Botha resigns as president of South Africa. F.W.
de Klerk formally succeeds him a month later.
   AUG. 18 _ Assassination of Colombian presidential candidate
touches off drug war in Colombia.
   AUG. 18-19 _ Polish leader Gen. Wojciech Jaruzelski approves
first non-Communist government in Poland since World War II,
nominating Solidarity activist Tadeusz Mazowiecki as prime minister.
   AUG. 20 _ Barge rams pleasure boat in London's Thames River, 57
die.
   AUG. 24 _ Pete Rose banned from baseball for life. Unmanned
exploratory spacecraft Voyager 2 passes within 3,000 miles of
planet Neptune.
   AUG. 30 _ Hotel queen Leona Helmsley convicted on tax evasion
charges, later sentenced to four years in prison and fined $8.8
million.
   AUG. 31 _ England's Princess Anne and husband Mark Phillips
officially separate.
   SEPT. 3 _ Cuban plane crash in Havana suburb kills 170.
   SEPT. 6 _ South African elections; some 25 die in rioting.
   SEPT. 10 _ Hungary drops requirement for East Germans to have
exit permission from East Berlin government. Exodus of East Germans
that began in summer increases.
   SEPT. 14 _ Gunman shoots workers at printing plant in
Louisville, Ky., killing eight and wounding 12 before taking his
own life.
   SEPT. 17-21 _ Hurricane Hugo sweeps through Caribbean and into
Charleston, S.C., with 135 mph winds, killing 62.
   SEPT. 19 _ Bomb explodes on French UTA DC-10 airliner over Chad,
killing all 171 aboard.
   SEPT. 20 _ De Klerk inaugurated as South African president.
   SEPT. 21 _ School bus crashes into Texas water pit, killing 20.
Soviet Union reports 292 people killed in ethnic violence in
various republics since January 1988.
   SEPT. 22 _ Irish Republican Army bomb blast at military barracks
in Deal, England, kills 11.
   SEPT. 26 _ Vietnam declares troop withdrawal from Cambodia
completed.
   SEPT. 29 _ Zsa Zsa Gabor convicted and later sentenced to three
days in jail for slapping policeman.
   OCT. 3 _ Military coup against Noriega in Panama fails.
   OCT. 5 _ PTL preacher Jim Bakker convicted on fraud charges and
later sentenced to 45 years. Dalai Lama wins Nobel Peace Prize.
   OCT. 7 _ Hungarian Communist Party formally disbands,
reconstituting itself as Hungarian Socialist Party. Parliament
later rewrites constitution and adopts laws allowing several
parties to contest free elections next year.
   OCT. 13 _ Stock market plunges 190.58 points, its second biggest
drop ever, four days after hitting record closing high of 2,791.41.
   OCT. 17 _ Earthquake measuring 7.1 on Richter scale rocks San
Francisco Bay area, killing 67 and causing $7 billion damage.
   OCT. 18 _ Amid large demonstrations, East German Communist Party
chief Erich Honecker ousted and replaced by Egon Krenz. Space
shuttle Atlantis launched on mission to send Galileo probe on
six-year journey to Jupiter.
   OCT. 23 _ Explosion at Phillips plastics plant in Pasadena,
Texas kills 23, injures 120.
   OCT. 28 _ Oakland Athletics sweep San Francisco Giants to win
quake-delayed World Series. Aloha commuter plane crashes in Hawaii,
killing 20.
   OCT. 29 _ Jet fighter plane crashes on deck of aircraft carrier
USS Lexington, killing five, in worst of string of Navy accidents
that kill 13 people within six weeks.
   NOV. 4 _ Thailand's worst typhoon in 35 years ravages Gulf of
Thailand and Unocal oil rig Seacrest capsizes. At least 200 die in
storm, 447 more missing.
   NOV. 9 _ East Germany lifts travel restrictions and opens
gateways through Berlin Wall.
   NOV. 10 _ Bulgarian Communist Party chief Todor Zhivkov ousted
and replaced by moderate.
   NOV. 11 _ Rebels in El Salvador launch major new offensive.
   NOV. 14 _ Czechoslovakia announces it will open borders.
   NOV. 15-16 _ Tornadoes and severe storms in eastern U.S. kill
31, including nine children when wall of school cafeteria collapses
in Newburgh, N.Y.
   NOV. 16 _ South African government announces it will repeal law
allowing segregated public facilities. Six Jesuit priests and two
others tortured and murdered in El Salvador.
   NOV. 17 _ Hundreds of demonstrators clubbed and tear-gassed as
riot police crush peaceful demonstration in Prague.
   NOV. 22 _ Lebanon's newly elected president, Rene Mouawad,
assassinated by bomb. Elias Hrawi elected two days later to replace
him.
   NOV. 27 _ Bomb probably planted by Colombian drug traffickers
aboard Avianca jetliner explodes shortly after takeoff from Bogota,
killing all 107 aboard.
   NOV. 29 _ Czechoslovak Parliament deletes leading role of
Communist Party from constitution after massive protests force
resignations of Communist hard-liners.
   NOV. 30 _ Alfred Herrhausen, chairman of West Germany's largest
bank, killed by bomb blast. Red Army Faction terrorist group claims
responsibility.
   DEC. 1-9 _ Dissident elements in Philippine military attempt
coup against Corazon Aquino's government. At least 113 people
killed.
   DEC. 2 _ V.P. Singh becomes prime minister of India, succeeding
Rajiv Gandhi, who resigned after election loss.
   DEC. 3 _ East German Communist leader Krenz and ruling party
Politburo resign two days after Parliament votes to eliminate
party's constitutional guarantee of power.
   DEC. 6 _ Gunman kills 14 women at University of Montreal.
   DEC. 10 _ Hard-line Czechoslovak Communist President Gustav
Husak resigns after swearing in Cabinet dominated by non-Communists.
   DEC. 14 _ Opposition candidate Patricio Aylwin elected president
of Chile in first democratic elections since 1973.
   DEC. 16 _ Anti-government protests break out in western Romania
and are put down by hard-line Communist authorities. Dozens and
possibly hundreds of people are reported killed.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Release in Year-End Editions</NOTE>

</DOC>