<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0092 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1046EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Panama-Miami 1stLd-Writethru a0553 12-20 0537</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Miami, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0553,0548</SECOND>
<HEAD>Noriega's Lawyer: Noriega Will Die Rather Than Be Captured</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS one graf after 7th graf, `Takiff questioned ...' with
trial judge comments. ADDS two grafs with comments from Panamanian exile.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TRACY FIELDS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A lawyer for Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega said today
the Panamanian leader would die rather than surrender to U.S.
forces sent to bring him to this country to face drug charges.
   Panamanian exiles here celebrated the U.S. attack.
   Noriega was indicted on federal drug charges in Miami and in
Tampa in 1988. Attorney Raymond Takiff said he talked with the
general Monday evening.
   ``We discussed various things, including this very real
possibility (of U.S. military action),'' the Miami lawyer said in a
telephone interview.
   The attorney said he had planned to fly to Panama City this
evening to meet with Noriega. This morning, he spoke with members
of the general's staff who didn't know his whereabouts.
   ``He's a fighter,'' Takiff said. ``I feel unhappily secure in my
belief that he will be killed, he will not be captured. Should that
occur, the truth will never come out.''
   Takiff questioned news accounts that Noriega had declared war on
the United States, which he described as ``just some more
propaganda that's come across again out of context.''
   U.S. District Judge William M. Hoeveler, assigned as the trial
judge in the Miami indictment, said today: ``If General Noriega is
apprehended and brought here for trial, he would be given the same
treatment as any other person accused of a crime _ no more, no
less. All his rights will be protected.''
   Also closely following events were members of Miami's Panamanian
exile community, including Luis Endara, cousin of Guillermo Endara,
who won the country's May election but was blocked by Noriega from
taking power. Guillermo Endara declared himself president shortly
after the U.S. military action began.
   ``I can assure you 99.99 percent of all Panamanians are up. I
know of at least five parties going on (in Miami),'' Luis Endara
said in an early-morning telephone interview.
   He added that he had been in telephone contact with Panama.
   ``Many of the opposition's key people have taken refuge in safe
places since we had reports way back from before the elections of
May that the dignity brigades (armed citizens who support Noriega)
had lists of key opposition people to attack should something like
this happen,'' he said.
   Convinced the military action would be a success, Luis Endara
predicted many Panamanians living in this country would return to
their homeland afterward.
   ``Exiles will probably return to Panama once everything is back
to normality,'' he said. ``We will probably see for the first time
an emigration back to a country that has been liberated.''
   Another Panamanian in Miami said that if Noriega is captured, he
will have to ``face all the things that he has done to the
Panamanian people.''
   ``I think he owes to the Panamanians many things and this is the
first thing we have to face,'' said Aurelio Barria, founder of the
National Civic Crusade in Panama. ``We would like to find the truth
of all the cases pending and try him in Panama.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>