<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0728EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-Latin     12-22 0563</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Latin,0580</SECOND>
<HEAD>Protests In Three Capitals, Garcia Says He Won't Meet With Bush</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LIMA, Peru (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of protesters angered by the invasion
of Panama marched outside the U.S. Embassy in Lima and at American
missions in two other Latin American capitals.
   President Alan Garcia, a strong critic of the U.S. action in
Panama, on Thursday repeated his proposal to postpone the Feb. 15
drug summit with President Bush and the presidents of three Andean
nations.
   ``I cannot meet with the leader of an invading nation,'' he said.
   In Washington, the Organization of American States suspended its
session Thursday five minutes after it opened because delegations
were divided on the wording of a resolution condemning the U.S.
action.
   OAS Chairman Angus Albert Khan of Trinidad and Tobago said he
was approached by several delegations asking for more time before
debate begins on a resolution submitted Wednesday by Nicaragua. He
did not say when the session would resume.
   Thousands of American troops were sent to the Central American
nation Wednesday to topple the government of Gen. Manuel Noriega,
who is wanted in the United States on drug trafficking charges and
who voided free elections in May.
   Hundreds of protesters chanting anti-American slogans marched in
downtown Lima Thursday night and burned an American flag near the
U.S. Embassy to protest U.S. military actions in Panama.
   In Mexico City about 2,000 people, shouting ``Yankee killers!''
and ``American terrorism!'' gathered outside the U.S. Embassy for
the second such demonstration there in as many days.
   Protesters threw rocks and eggs filled with red and blue paint _
the colors of Panama's flag _ leaving the embassy's white marble
facade speckled with at least a dozen stains. More than 100 police
officers kept the crowd from rushing a barricade and no injuries or
other incidents were reported.
   In the Dominican Republic, about 200 protesters picketed in
front of the U.S. Embassy in Santo Domingo. President Joaquin
Balaguer condemned the U.S. invasion, calling it a violation of
Panamanians' right to self-determination.
   Bush is to meet with Garcia and Presidents Virgilio Barco of
Colombia and Jaime Paz Zamora of Bolivia on Feb. 15 in Cartagena,
Colombia, to discuss how to fight drug trafficking in the four
countries.
   But in a communique released Thursday by the Peruvian government
news agency Andina, Garcia said, ``Holding a dialogue with a pistol
on the table cannot be tolerated.''
   The communique did not give a time or set conditions under which
the summit should be held.
   Referring to the U.S. intervention in Panama, Garcia said in the
communique that the United States ``could seek to do the same in
Peru if it should think the (Peruvian) government isn't doing
enough to fight drug trafficking.''
   In Bogota, Foreign Minister Julio Londonno said the United
States must pull its invading forces out before Latin American
nations will work for a solution to the Panama crisis.
   ``No country can assume the right of intervene, directly or
indirectly, in other state's affairs, whatever reasons or purposes
it may have, much less militarily,'' he told a news conference.
   Some Latin American leaders, including Venezuelan president
Carlos Andres Perez, have proposed a recognition of Guillermo
Endara as Panama's president in exchange for an immediate
withdrawal of U.S. troops.
   Endara, winner of the May 7 presidential elections annulled by
the Noriega government, proclaimed himself president on Wednesday
as the invasion began.
</TEXT>

</DOC>