<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0146 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1754EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-AviationSecurity     12-18 0535</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Aviation Security,510</SECOND>
<HEAD>FAA Knew About Moscow Embassy Warning Before Flight 103</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID BRISCOE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Federal Aviation Administration was
advised eight days before the bombing of Pan Am Flight 103 that the
U.S. Embassy in Moscow was warning employees of a terrorist threat
against Pan Am flights on the same route, a presidential panel
disclosed Monday.
   FAA officials acknowledged that they had received a telex from
the embassy on Dec. 13, 1988, but said they did nothing about it
even though they said it is against government policy to warn
employees but not the general public of such threats.
   The issue of a dual standard in warnings of potential terrorism
is one of several being taken up by the seven-member Presidental
Commission on Aviation Security and Terrorism, which held its
second hearing into the Dec. 21, 1988, bombing over Lockerbie,
Scotland, of Flight 103, in which 270 people died.
   The panel also received the results of a congressional report
that said stepped-up security measures since the disaster may be
ineffective at high-risk foreign airports due to a lack of training
standards.
   The report by the General Accounting Office faults the FAA for
not establishing minimum training requirements for people who
screen baggage and conduct other security operations at foreign
airports.
   Kenneth Mead, GAO director for transportation issues, told the
commission that the congressional watchdog agency has found several
``fundamental deficiencies'' in FAA security programs.
   Earlier reports, he noted, had found problems with passenger
screening, airport security controls and security inspections.
   Mead said the FAA has concurred with most of the agency's
findings and made some changes but does not keep close enough tabs
on security on a daily basis.
   Sen. Alfonse D'Amato, R-N.Y., a commission member, said the
congressional studies indicate that ``the FAA and the present
system have flunked when it comes to providing basic security
systems that anyone can have confidence in.''
   D'Amato said problems with the FAA suggest there may be a
conflict between its role of promoting aviation and that of
ensuring passenger safety.
   Producing a copy of the telex from the Moscow embassy to the
FAA, D'Amato said it proves the FAA was aware that U.S. officials
were warning State Department employees, but not the general
public, about the threat.
   ``Since a number of people from this post will be flying out of
Frankfurt in the next two weeks, post plans to issue an internal
administrative notice warning employees of the threat,'' said the
telex to the FAA. ``No recommendation will be made as to course of
action to be followed by travelers.''
   Relatives of Flight 103 victims say they believe several
government employees changed reservations to get off the flight
after the warning, while the general public was not informed of the
threat, which specified a Pan Am flight within two weeks after Dec.
5 en route from Frankfurt to New York.
   Flight 103 originated in Frankfurt and was en route to New York
from London when it blew up.
   Officials later said the specific threat that had prompted the
warning was not credible, and they believe it was only a
coincidence that it came just two weeks before the bombing.
</TEXT>

</DOC>