<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1113EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NorthwestPilots     12-17 0533</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Northwest Pilots,0547</SECOND>
<HEAD>Northwest Pilot Shortage Forces Cancellations</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. PAUL, Minn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A chronic pilot shortage has forced
Northwest Airlines to cancel hundreds of flights in recent months
and prompted the airline to temporarily cut back its pilot training.
   But the carrier says its flight cancellations are back at
``normal'' levels and contends its record for the 12 months before
October was consistent with that of other major airlines.
   Some of the carrier's pilots say postponing training could only
aggravate the problem, according to a story in Sunday editions of
the St. Paul Pioneer Press Dispatch.
   ``That's the best that can be said about it,'' said Gerald
Wallin, Northwest's senior director of flight administration until
mid-August. ``It's like eating your seed corn.''
   In October, Northwest canceled 707 flights for non-mechanical
reasons _ 1.8 percent of all flights. That's the worst rate among
the 13 major carriers, according to an internal U.S. Transportation
Department report obtained by the newspaper.
   Wallin and others called the number of halted flights
extraordinary and said they believe cancellations at Northwest
stemming from pilot shortages have at least doubled since early
this year. The Transportation Department, which counts canceled
flights, would not release historic data for comparison.
   Other major carriers facing fast industry growth have had
similar problems with flight cancellations. According to the
Transportation Department figures, USAir cancelled 1.3 percent of
its flights for non-mechanical reasons in October, followed by
United, which cancelled 1.1 percent of its flights.
   A statement from the suburban Eagan-based airline acknowledged
that cancellations were higher than normal in late October and
early November. However, it said its record for the 12 months ended
Sept. 30 was ``consistent with the performance of all other major
airlines.''
   ``It is unfair to judge Northwest's flight schedule
dependability based on only one month.''
   The statement also said, ``Northwest has not at any time
canceled required FAA training for its pilots.''
   A Northwest spokesman would not elaborate on the statement.
   But Northwest employees past and present said the situation is
troubling because the airline has scrapped many high-revenue
international flights on large jetliners.
   Moreover, the carrier's new owners hope to build the airline by
wooing new passengers with good service. Northwest chairman Alfred
Checchi intends to double the size of the airline in the next five
years to help reduce $3.1 billion in debt from his group's August
takeover of the company.
   A group led by Checchi bought the nation's fourth largest
carrier for $5.65 billion. In September, Checchi became Northwest's
chairman when former chairman Steven Rothmeier and Rothmeier's top
four executives resigned.
   Northwest's problem with cancelled flights has been building
over several years, according to pilots and former managers, and
was exacerbated by top-level decisions during the years Rothmeier
ran the carrier.
   ``Rothmeier's group continually had a pilot shortage and they
never hired enough pilots to meet demand,'' said Duane Woerth, a
member of the Master Executive Council of the Northwest chapter of
the Air Line Pilots Association union, which represents the
carrier's 5,400 pilots.
   Woerth and others said Northwest is taking steps to remedy the
problem. In mid-November, it halted all pilot-advancement training;
the company said it is continuing to train newly hired pilots.
</TEXT>

</DOC>