<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0169 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2018EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Ferry     12-18 0303</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Ferry,0309</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hearing Begins on Manslaughter Charges in Ferry Disaster</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A hearing began Monday on whether there is enough
evidence to try P and O European Ferries and seven company
executives and seamen for manslaughter in the Zeebrugge ferry
disaster, which killed 193 people.
   P and O is charged with corporate manslaughter, the first such
prosecution in England, because of the accident in 1987. The ferry
Herald of Free Enterprise was swamped when its rear doors were left
open, and capsized outside the harbor of Zeebrugge, Belgium.
   The hearing is expected to last about three weeks. The decision
to presecute capped more than two years of court and police
proceedings, a public inquiry that blamed the ship owners and an
inquest that returned a verdict of unlawful killing.
   If tried and found guilty, the company could be liable to an
unlimited fine and the individuals could face maximum sentences of
life in prison. No pleas were taken Monday.
   Appearing in court were John Alcindor, deputy chief
superintendent of P and O European Ferries; Wallace Ayres, director
and head of its technical department; Jeffrey Develin, director and
chief (marine) superintendent; Capt. David Lewry, captain of the
ferry; and senior master John Kirby.
   Two other men, first officer Leslie Sabel and assistant bosun
Mark Stanley, decided not to participate in the first phase of the
preliminary hearing, but were to appear when the evidence has been
completed in the cases of the other men.
   Summonses against the company and individual defendants accuse
them of the manslaughter of four victims: passengers Alison
Gaillard and Martin Spooner, and crew members Richard Barnard and
Maria Richards.
   The father of Mrs. Gaillard, who died with her husband Francis,
is Maurice de Rohan, chairman of the Herald Families Association.
Spooner's father, Peter, is the association secretary.

</TEXT>

</DOC>