<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0094 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1213EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Panama-Refuge     12-22 0464</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Panama-Refuge,0474</SECOND>
<HEAD>With Panama Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>If Noriega Takes Embassy Refuge, He Could Face a Long Stay</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   If Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega manages to make his way to a
foreign embassy in Panama City, he could be there a long time.
   U.S. troops have put the Nicaraguan and Cuban embassies in the
Panamanian capital under tight surveillance in case the ousted
leader attempts to seek sanctuary there. So far, U.S. officials
say, there is no sign Noriega is inside either embassy.
   Under international law, embassies are sacrosanct ground. An
embassy's territory belongs to the country it represents, not to
the country where it is situated. Forces from the outside cannot
legally enter embassy territory to seize a person the embassy wants
to shelter.
   But an embassy's right to grant sanctuary to someone does not
mean that person has a right to free passage out of the country. A
refugee may have to wait inside the embassy for years until
political conditions permit his departure.
   In June, Chinese dissident Fang Lizhi took refuge inside the
U.S. Embassy in Beijing. Although talks since then between U.S. and
Chinese officials have reportedly touched on Fang's case, he
remains holed up in the embassy, liable to arrest if he comes out.
   Perhaps the longest instance of political refuge in an embassy
involved Hungarian Cardinal Josef Mindszenty, who hid out for 15
years at the U.S. Embassy in Budapest. He was arrested by Hungary's
Communist rulers in 1948 as an enemy of communism and sentenced to
life in prison.
   Hungarian revolutionaries freed him during the 1956 uprising,
but Mindszenty took refuge in the U.S. mission in Budapest after
Warsaw Pact forces crushed the revolt. He lived there until the
Vatican arranged for his release to the West in 1971.
   Elsewhere in the East Bloc, seven Pentecostalists claiming
religious persecution lived for five years in a cramped room at the
U.S. Embassy in Moscow, leaving in 1983.
   The largest number of people to seek refuge at a foreign embassy
at once may have been in Cuba in April 1980, when 10,000 Cubans
entered the grounds of the Peruvian Embassy seeking to emigrate.
Cuban authorities finally persuaded the crowd to go home, and
eventually almost all of them received exit visas.
   In 1973, after Salvador Allende was overthrown as president of
Chile and died in a battle in the presidential palace, his widow
and her children received refuge in the Mexican Embassy in
Santiago. The Mexican government then flew them out of the country.
   In South Africa, some 20 prisoners and anti-apartheid activists
have taken refuge in the U.S., British, West German and Dutch
diplomatic missions in recent years. Most were eventually allowed
to go free, with South African government assurances that they
would not be punished.
</TEXT>

</DOC>