<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0147 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1555EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-King     12-22 0454</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-King,0469</SECOND>
<HEAD>King Michael Says He's Ready to Head Constitutional Monarchy</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HANNS NEUERBOURG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GENEVA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Exiled King Michael of Romania said Friday he's
ready to return to his country as head of a constitutional monarchy
``if the people want me to come back.''
   ``I have been waiting for this for 40 years,'' he told a news
conference convened hastily after the reported overthrow of
President Nicolae Ceausescu. ``If people want me to come back, of
course, I will come back.''
   ``Romania has had a constitutional monarchy before the war and
it proved itself,'' he said. ``If things turn the right way I don't
see why this could not happen again.''
   Michael, 68, left his country in the first days of 1948 after
signing an act of abdication but he repeated Friday that he did so
under duress.
   ``Therefore, I consider that I have remained king of Romania and
the head of state for the past 40 years,'' he said. ``It has never
stopped.''
   He said he was flooded with telephone calls and messages telling
him of the rapid developments in Romania but that he has had no
direct contact with his native country up to now.
   When asked about his feelings, he replied: ``Overwhelmed.''
   ``You cannot find the right words to express it,'' he said. ``It
has been a great relief and sadness at the same time because of
this terrible bloodshed.''
   Before the question-and-answer session, which was mostly in
English, he read a statement in French in which he paid ``homage to
my courageous compatriots, men and women.''
   He urged legalization of all democratic organizations and
parties, free elections in six months, release of all political
prisoiners and ``absolute respect for the transitional government.''
   Michael renewed an appeal for an end to violence and urged
Romanians to adopt a spirit of reconciliation, ``despite the
humiliations and the cruel living conditions imposed on you.''
   ``We have too much to do to rebuild our country than to lose our
time for personal revenge,'' he said later.
   Asked what he would suggest should be done with Ceausescu, he
said: ``Maybe I have some ideas,'' drawing laughter from the
journalists.
   Then he continued that ``it is up to the people at home to
decide,'' adding that he thought it only right that those ``who
have been leading the country for the past 20 or more years should
get the just answer, that they should be tried.''
   He was flanked by his wife, Queen Anne, a Princess of
Bourbon-Parma, and his oldest daughter, Princess Margarita, who
would be the first in line to succeed him.
   Michael, who holds a British passport, moved to Switzerland more
than 30 years ago.
</TEXT>

</DOC>