<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0134 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1709EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-PoliceTaping     12-18 0572</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Police Taping,590</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hearings Open Into Police Eavesdropping Practices</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DIAMOND</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police departments across the country
routinely tape conversations between jailed suspects and their
lawyers, a congressional hearing was told Monday.
   The hearing by the courts subcommittee of the House Judiciary
Committee grew out of a Connecticut auto case that came to light
earlier this year.
   But state or local police or corrections officers in at least 12
other states routinely record lawyer-client conversations, said the
subcommittee chairman, Rep. Robert W. Kastenmeier, D-Wis.
   ``A clear pattern is emerging across the country,'' said
Kastenmeier. ``It is unfortunate but likely that as we explore what
happened in these states, information about other states will come
to light.''
   Kastenmeier said information gathered by the subcommttee
indicates that some form of bugging or wiretapping of conversations
between jailed suspects and their attorneys has gone on in Rhode
Island, West Virginia, Georgia, New Mexico, Oregon, Alaska,
Wyoming, Vermont, Indiana, Utah, Nebraska and New Jersey.
   Antonio Califa, legislative counsel to the American Civil
Liberties Union, detailed several instances of police taping:
   _In Rhode Island, state police since 1988 have taped incoming
and outgoing calls on a system that connects the state's five
barracks. According to Califa, the U.S. attorney has begun a
preliminary investigation.
   _In West Virginia, state police have been taping telephone
conversations from suspects to their families and lawyers for 20
years, Califa said. Callers are not warned that the calls are being
recorded.
   _The Utah Civil Liberties Union is planning a lawsuit alleging
that the state Department of Corrections routinely taped
conversations between convicted prison inmates and their attorneys.
   Federal law forbids telephone taping except when investigatrs
obtain a court order based on probable cause in a criminal
investigation or when both parties to the conversation agree to the
taping. Many state laws mirror the 1968 federal statute but some
permit taping if only one party to the conversation consents.
   Monday's hearing included a videotape of a telephone
conversation on August 5, 1988, between a suspect in a Connecticut
vehicular homicide case and his attorney.
   During trial a Connecticut State Police officer testified that
the call was recorded as part of routine department policy.
   An investigation by The Hartford Courant revealed that the
secret tape-recording by state police was widespread, prompting
Gov. William A. O'Neill to order an immediate halt to the taping of
attorney-client calls. The revelations cost Public Safety
Commissioner and State Police Commander Lester J. Forst his job.
   A later state investigation concluded that the tapes were not
used to illegally gather evidence against suspects.
   The Connecticut State Police have insisted from the start that
the tapes were not listened to.
   Attorneys Elliot B. Spector and Marcia J. Gleeson, representing
Connecticut and 19 defendants including two top former state police
officials, wrote to Kastenmeier on Saturday that the witness list
for Monday's hearing would only expose one side of the story.
   ``The news media, some public figures and criminal defense
attorneys hysterically characterized these events as criminal acts
amounting to a national crisis,'' Gleeson and Spector wrote. ``I
would hope that the committee will take a more cautious approach to
this issue.''
   Gleeson said committee staff members rejected offers to provide
an opposing point of view in the hearing.
   Members of Kastenmeier's staff said the committee sought to
question Connecticut State Police Lt. Col. John Mulligan about the
taping practices but that Mulligan refused.
</TEXT>

</DOC>