<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0107 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1554EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CDC-Measles     12-21 0339</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-CDC-Measles,0349</SECOND>
<HEAD>Measles Deaths Most Since 1971</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release 6 p.m. EST</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BYRD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The measles explosion of 1989, involving
unvaccinated preschoolers and schoolchildren whose shots didn't
work, has been accompanied by the most measles deaths in 18 years,
federal health officials said Thursday.
   Forty-two deaths from measles have been reported this year, said
national Centers for Disease Control measles specialist Dr. William
L. Atkinson. That's the largest death count since 90 in 1971, he
noted.
   Nationwide, 14,714 measles cases were counted with two weeks
left in the year, the CDC said in its weekly report. That's more
than five times the 2,876 cases reported at this point a year ago.
   An analysis of measles cases in the first six months of this
year shows 30 percent occurred in children under 5, who are too
young to fall under school-vaccination laws. Fifty-one percent
occurred among young people 5-19.
   In the wake of the new measles explosion, CDC researchers have
recommended this year that children get vaccinated twice _ the
initial dose at 15 months in most areas, then again at school
entry, ages 4-6.
   In the first half of this year, 51 percent of measles cases
occurred among people who were believed ``appropriately
vaccinated,'' the Atlanta-based CDC said.
   The unvaccinated preschoolers present a separate problem,
Atkinson noted.
   ``We've got to find some sort of clever ways to motivate parents
to get their kids vaccinated,'' he said. ``A 15-month-old doesn't
walk in on his own.''
   Large measles outbreaks are continuing in Los Angeles, Chicago
and Houston, primarily among young blacks and Hispanics, the CDC
noted. Vaccination rates in some inner cities are as low as 49
percent in 2-year-olds, the agency said.
   Federal health officials believed measles eradication was within
reach early in this decade; just 1,497 cases were reported in 1983.
But the disease has bounced back, although still nowhere near the
pre-vaccine levels of half a million cases a year.
   During 1971, when 90 patients died, 75,290 cases were reported.
</TEXT>

</DOC>