<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1931EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-Detained     12-24 0756</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Detained,0778</SECOND>
<HEAD>Little by Little, Noriega's Forces Have Been Giving Up</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOSEPH B. FRAZIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RODMAN NAVAL STATION, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In groups or alone, with or
without their weapons, members of the Panamanian Defense Forces are
surrendering.
   Even before ousted dictator Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega went to
the Vatican embassy Sunday to ask for political asylum, hundreds of
his troops were giving up the fight.
   The baseball field at Rodman Naval Station, on the west bank of
the Panama Canal, is one of several detention centers the U.S.
military has set up to process those who turn themselves in or are
captured.
   About 1,400 surrendered or were caught in the first 24 hours of
the U.S. invasion early Wednesday. They continue to trickle in, and
more than 100 have passed through Rodman by Sunday.
   They sit in brightly colored tents on the baseball field,
waiting to be questioned and sent elsewhere for processing. The
barbed wire and police dogs are reminders that it's a war, not a
picnic.
   ``They tell us what they have to say and we make a
determination,'' said Eugene Richley, the master-at-arms in charge
of the center. He said some of those who appear at the gate are
refugees and some are allowed to stay on the base if they are
perceived to be in danger.
   ``But most just walk up to a checkpoint. They appear friendly,''
he said.
   Richley said most are former members of the Defense Forces who
expressed interest in joining a new security force being formed
under President Guillermo Endara. He said these men are being
screened further.
   Col. Roberto Armijo, who switched allegiance from Noriega to
Endara and was put in charge of the new police corps, appealed
Saturday to the former Defense Forces members to join the new
government and re-establish harmony ``as soon as possible.''
   ``I ask all members of the Defense Forces to come to the nearest
garrison,'' he said.
   Vice President and Interior Minister Ricardo Arias Calderon, the
man in charge of domestic security, said he holds ``no rancor or
desire for revenge'' against the military under Noriega.
   ``I offer you the absolute respect of the civilian authority but
we have the right to demand that you be loyal to your oath,'' Arias
added. He asked for reconciliation.
   Naval and Marine officers said those suspected of being
criminals or looters are kept in jail.
   A Marine Corps spokesman, Chief Warrant Officer Charles Rowe,
said Panamanians are held if they are caught in combat with U.S.
forces, if they give themselves up, or if they are turned in by
people believed to be reliable.
   ``Most of them just walked up to a checkpoint and say they want
to avoid more problems,'' Richley said. He said the ``detainees'' _
the U.S. military here is not using the term ``prisoner of war'' _
are treated in accord with the Geneva Convention.
   Those who surrender their arms along with themselves receive a
bonus, depending on the weapons. The United States is paying $150
for an automatic rifle, a princely sum to many Panamanians.
   Government TV runs a message on the screen almost constantly
notifying watchers of ``Passports to Freedom'' _ U.S.-issued
documents given to people who turn themselves in. The announcement
said the ``passports'' assure the bearer of safety, food, medical
attention and, eventually, another job.
   ``Remember: You don't have to suffer any more,'' the message
concludes.
   At the U.S. military's westernmost checkpoint on the Pan
American Highway, about 15 miles west of the capital, Marine Lt.
Dan Krauss of Portland, Ore., said several members of the Defense
Forces had presented themselves, including one lieutenant with his
Soviet-made AK-47 assault rifle, a pistol and all of his uniforms.
   ``He said his people _ there were about 25 men _ wanted to give
up. He told us that they had waited a long time for this, that they
were just laying low in their barracks,'' Kraus said.
   ``He had a full seabag issue of uniforms. It was clear that he
didn't want to resist,'' he added.
   Krauss said three soldiers surrendered before the U.S. takeover
began.
   ``We understand there was already some shooting, and they didn't
think that was a very good idea,'' he said, adding that the three
eventually were freed.
   Krauss said dozens of residents have given information as to
where to find Rigoberto Paredes, a Noriega crony and former member
of Panama's National Assembly who owned much of the property in the
area and wielded power ruthlessly.
</TEXT>

</DOC>