<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0101 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1229EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Ethiopia-Famine     12-22 0324</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ethiopia-Famine,0332</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ethiopia Considering Sending Relief Food to Rebel Areas</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ADDIS ABABA, Ethiopia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ethiopia has asked local aid
agencies to determine how to supply food to hundreds of thousands
of drought victims facing starvation in rebel-held northern zones,
a government official said Friday.
   If it comes about, it would be the first time President Mengistu
Haile Mariam's 15-year-old Marxist government has taken part in the
distribution of relief supplies to rebel areas.
   Foreign Minister Tesfaye Dinka, in describing his government's
plans to ambassadors and relief officials, said the drought was
affecting the northern provinces of Eritrea, Tigre, Wello and
Gondar, as well as parts of Harrar in the east and Omo in the south.
   Only Tigre, which is controlled by the rebel Tigre People's
Liberation Front, posed a problem, he said.
   The front, which has been fighting since 1975 for increased
autonomy and Mengistu's ouster, took control of Tigre in an
offensive this year. The province has an estimated population of 3
million.
   Because of the security situation, Tesfaye said the government
had asked its relief organization, the Relief and Rehabilitation
Commission to study how emergency food can be supplied to the area.
The commission is expected to have an anser within a month, he said.
   Other agencies to be involved are the Ethiopia Red Cross, the
Ethiopian Orthodox Church, the Mekane Yesus Evangelical Church, and
the Catholic Church, he said.
   The United Nations has estimated crop failures in northern
Ethiopia could threaten as many as 4 million people with starvation
and has appealed for 600,000 tons of emergency food. The
government's preliminary estimate of the number under the threat of
starvation was 1.8 million.
   Tesfaye did not mention the possibility of establishing safety
corridors through which food and supplies could move unhindered
into the embattled areas. President Daniel arap Moi of Kenya said
10 days ago that Mengistu had agreed to such a plan. Ethiopia has
not acknowledged Moi's announcement.
</TEXT>

</DOC>