<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0213 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1235EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-UTC-Thailand     12-19 0546</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-UTC-Thailand,0567</SECOND>
<HEAD>United Technologies Gives to Thai Charity As It Seeks Engine Order</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARTFORD, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   United Technologies Corp., vying for more
than $100 million in jet-engine orders from Thailand's national
airline, has donated $500,000 to a charity run by the Thai royal
family, a newspaper reported today.
   UTC officials called the donation to typhoon victims
humanitarian and said they often give money to victims of natural
disasters, but some industry experts said the contribution appeared
to be an attempt to curry favor with a potentially big customer,
The Hartford Courant reported in a copyright story.
   ``They didn't give that out of the goodness of their heart,''
said retired Navy Rear Adm. Gene R. LaRocque, director of the
Center for Defense Information, a Washington watchdog group.
   Thai officials in Washington said UTC's contribution to the
typhoon relief fund was the largest they were aware of.
   The contribution was given to Thailand's ambassador to the
United States during a private ceremony Dec. 5 at his Washington
residence, U.S. and Thai government officials and an aide to UTC
consultant Alexander M. Haig Jr. confirmed Monday.
   Haig, former U.S. secretary of state and a former UTC president,
approved UTC's contribution to victims of Typhoon Gay in his role
as head of the corporations Pacific advisory committee.
   The typhoon ravaged southern Thailand in November, killing
nearly 500 people and leaving thousands homeless.
   Sales to Thailand of UTC products, ranging from Pratt &amp; Whitney
engines and Sikorsky helicopters to Otis elevators, have grown
seven-fold in the past five years, to $69.1 million in 1988.
   Last summer, Thai Airways International canceled a $65 million
engine supplier, Fairfield-based General Electric Co., and switched
the order to Pratt &amp; Whitney. The order was for engines on three
Airbus A300 wide-bodied jets.
   Pratt and GE are now competing for as much as $120 million in
Thai Airways engine orders, expected to be announced early next
year. Those engines would power at least six A300s and one Boeing
747 being added to the airline's fleet.
   UTC spokesman Dan Harrison said Monday there were no conditions
attached to his company's donation.
   ``Thailand is an important country to us,'' Harrison said. ``But
the contribution was made for humanitarian reasons.''
   Harrision said UTC officials felt the amount of money was
``appropriate given the magnitude of the typhoon.'' He said the
giant aerospace and industrial concern also contributed to relief
efforts for victims of Hurricane Hugo and the earthquakes in San
Francisco and Armenia, but he said he didn't know how much it gave.
   The U.S. goverment donated $75,000 to the typhoon victims, the
Thai embassy said. GE did not contribute, spokesman Dwight Weber
said.
   UTC wanted to keep its donation quiet and ``didn't want any
publicity,'' said Promjit Boon-Lang, an information officer at the
Thai embassy.
   Franklin J. Parisi, UTC vice president for communications, said
the corporation makes donations ``all the time that we don't
announce.''
   LaRocque said the contribution, while legal, has an
``unpleasant, malodorus smell to it.''
   Industry analysts said UTC's contribution reflects its
recognition of the way business is done in many foreign countries.
   ``Business is done any way you can do it in Asia, any way you
can get it done,'' said Mark A. Bobbi, an analyst with Forecast
International in Newtown, Conn.
</TEXT>

</DOC>