<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0099 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1651EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     12-30 0679</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0704</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   All but one of the half-dozen paintings on the
walls of the mayor's office were taken down as Edward I. Koch moved
out of City Hall after serving as New York's 105th mayor for 12
years.
   ``It's like Saigon, I imagine, was,'' Koch said to reporters
Friday, comparing his last day at work to the fall of the
Vietnamese capital to communists in 1975. ``The only thing that was
missing was the sound of helicopters to take you out.''
   Koch pointed out that the stage set up on City Hall plaza for
Monday's inauguration of Mayor-elect David Dinkins was about three
times the size of the one he used in 1978.
   ``He deserves it!'' Koch remarked.
   Koch lost to Dinkins in the Democratic primary.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Director Costa-Gavras, known for such political
films as ``Z'' and ``Missing,'' has watched his plans for a movie
involving Eastern European characters crumble like the Berlin Wall.
   Costa-Gavras said the ongoing upheaval that has toppled
communist governments has forced big changes in a script about two
Poles living in Paris.
   ``Characters, when they speak about the country, have different
speeches now,'' he said last week. ``They don't have difficulties
going there that they used to. Everything is upside down.''
   While he waits for rewrites, Costa-Gavras said he'll be in Paris
spending the holidays with his family.
   His latest feature, ``Music Box,'' recently opened, with Jessica
Lange starring as a Chicago lawyer defending her Hungarian-born
father against charges of Nazi war crimes.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Eds: The following item moved on sports wires.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>WICHITA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Los Angeles Clippers basketball star Danny
Manning is being sued for more than $10,000 by a woman who claims
he insulted and punched her during a bachelorette party in June.
   Karen Hopkins alleges that Manning, who led the Kansas Jayhawks
to a national college basketball championship in 1988, punched her
in the eye and knocked her over when she told him he was rude at a
Wichita nightclub.
   Clippers spokesman Bill Kreifeldt said Manning had no comment.
   Ms. Hopkins, 31, claims her trouble began when she went to the
defense of her sister, who, the lawsuit alleges, was verbally
abused by Manning and had a beer poured on her.
   Police records indicate they were called to the club for the
June 3 party, but not because Ms. Hopkins had been injured. Police
spokesman Lt. Mike McKenna could not say Friday why police were
called, but he said Ms. Hopkins' name was in the police report.
McKenna could not elaborate on the report.
   Ms. Hopkins' attorney, Ron Beal, said she decided to sue for
compensation for her injuries rather than sign a criminal complaint.
   John Karagianis, who owns the nightclub, said his employees told
him that a scuffle broke out at the club after a crowd pestered
Manning for his autograph. Manning and a group of friends left the
club before police arrived, Karagianis said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Phil Peschi Sr. has been in Mummers Parades
for 62 years, and he wasn't about to let a leg amputation stop him
from being an active participant in this year's parade.
   Peschi had to get special permission to allow his wheelchair in
the New Year's Day parade as part of the Trilby String Band. The
chair is considered a float under parade rules because it has
wheels, and floats aren't allowed in the parade as part of string
bands.
   On Monday, Peschi will be in full Mummer regalia for Trilby's
presentation of ``Jungle Jive.'' He will be dressed as a tribal
chief and his wheelchair will be a throne.
   ``The chair will be `Mummerized' to look like a throne, so I can
wear a suit,'' said Peschi, who is Trilby's co-captain along with
his son, Phil Jr.
   Peschi lost his right leg to gangrene in August 1986 after being
in a coma for 14 weeks.
   He participated in the last three parades in Trilby's ``banner
car,'' which rides in front of the strutting band unit.
</TEXT>

</DOC>