<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0129 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2039EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-BoatPeople     12-19 0479</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Boat People,0497</SECOND>
<HEAD>Legislators Endorse Forced Repatriation Of Vietnamese</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MAUREEN JOHNSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Legislators on Tuesday endorsed Prime Minister
Margaret Thatcher's controversial policy of forcibly repatriating
Vietnamese from Hong Kong, and the government indicated it will
resume the deportations, which had been suspended.
   The 309-219 vote in the House of Commons followed an acrimonious
three-hour debate.
   Paddy Ashdown, leader of the centrist Social and Liberal
Democratic Party, said repatriating the boat people against their
will ``shames our government, shames the prime minister and
ultimately shames our nation.''
   The first deportations of 51 Vietnamese on Dec. 12 provoked an
international outcry. The U.S. Administration called it
``unacceptable.''
   The Conservative government suspended the repatriations to allow
for the parliamentary debate.
   ``It was a decision that gave pleasure to none and, I
acknowledge, has caused anxiety to many,'' Foreign Office Minister
Francis Maude told the Commons Tuesday night.
   But he said the burden of 57,000 boat people now lingering in
Hong Kong detention camps and the prospect of thousands more
arriving when the sailing season begins in the spring had become
``intolerable.''
   All but 13,000 of the boat people have been classified as
economic migrants, not political refugees fleeing persecution.
   ``For those of us who do have those responsibilities, they
cannot be dodged, they cannot be shirked and we won't shirk them,''
Maude declared, indicating the repatriations will resume. He gave
no date.
   ``Of course, the United States has been critical. There are
historical reasons for this. But ... they have had no realistic
alternative to propound,'' Maude added.
   The government, meanwhile, could face another storm of criticism
after an announcement due Wednesday on the number of Hong Kong
Chinese who will be given residence rights in Britain after China
takes over the colony in 1997.
   Leaks from government officials put the total at about 225,000
of the 3.25 million Hong Kong Chinese who now hold British
passports without residence rights.
   The British move is intended to cover about 50,000 key
government employees, entrepreneurs, and their families needed to
maintain the British administration and the territory's capitalist
system.
   Dozens of British legislators have threatened to vote down new
legislation to alter current Hong Kong passports.
   The rebellion is led by right-wingers opposed to immigration
from Britain's largely African, Asian and Caribbean former colonies.
   The government argues that with the insurance policy of British
residence, such people will stay for now and not join the estimated
1,000 skilled residents leaving Hong Kong each week for Australia,
Canada or the United States.
   ``We most certainly have a duty to those Crown servants in Hong
Kong who have enabled us and will enable us to carry out British
administration right up to 1997,'' Mrs. Thatcher told a questioner
in the Commons.
   China has pledged to allow capitalism and a great degree of
autonomy in Hong Kong for 50 years.
</TEXT>

</DOC>