<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0202 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1646EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Dollar-Gold     12-26 0325</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dollar-Gold,0343</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar, Gold Lower</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dollar declined Tuesday against most key
foreign currencies in extremely thin post-holiday trading.
   Gold prices fell here after rising in Asia.
   The financial markets were closed on Monday in the United States
and in Europe in observance of Christmas.
   But dealings remained sparse Tuesday as many U.S. traders
decided to extend their holiday and most European markets remained
closed for Boxing Day.
   Traders said the market had little reaction to the Bank of
Japan's decision Monday to raise its discount rate _ the interest
charged for loans to commercial banks _ to 4.25 percent from 3.75
percent. The move, which boosts the value of the yen against the
dollar, had been widely anticipated by the market, they said.
   Nonetheless, the overall sentiment toward the dollar remains
bearish as prospects for lower U.S. interest rates rise with more
evidence of economic weakness, said Earl I. Johnson, a trader with
Harris Trust &amp; Co. in Chicago.
   In Tokyo, the dollar closed at 142.37 yen, down 0.35 yen from
Monday. In New York, the dollar traded at 141.845 yen, lower than
142.35 yen Friday.
   The dollar lost value against the British pound, with sterling
costing $1.6265, higher than $1.62425 Friday.
   Other late dollar rates in New York, compared with late quotes
Friday, included: 1.6987 West German marks, down from 1.7070;
1.54825 Swiss francs, down from 1.5490; 1.16005 Canadian dollars,
up from 1.15925; 5.8020 French francs, down from 5.8345; and
1,272.75 Italian lire, down from 1,277.75.
   On the Commodity Exchange in New York, gold bullion for current
delivery fell $6.40 to $406.80 a troy ounce. Republic National Bank
in New York quoted a late bid for gold at $407 a troy ounce, off
$6.75 from Friday.
   Earlier, in Hong Kong, gold rose 40 cents to close at $413.85 an
ounce.
   Silver bullion settled at $5.512 a troy ounce on New York's
Comex, down 4.8 cents from late Friday.
</TEXT>

</DOC>