<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0214 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1938EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Panama-WarPowers 1stLd-Writethru   12-20 0585</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-War Powers, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0836,570</SECOND>
<HEAD>Invasion Legal Under U.S., International Law, Administration Says</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: ADDS 3 grafs to include comment from Yale law professor.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES ROWLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bush adminstration argued Wednesday that
the U.S. invasion of Panama was legal under both domestic and
international law but some lawyers who have tried war-powers cases
disagreed.
   Secretary of State James Baker cited Article 51 of the United
Nations Charter that gives nations the right to act in self-defense
and a similar provision of the Organization of American States
treaty as the legal basis for the invasion.
   Article 21 of the OAS treaty gives the United States the right
to protect its citizens, installations and institutions, the
secretary said.
   Baker also cited the terms of the Panama Canal Treaty that give
the United States the right to exercise force to protect the canal
to keep it operating.
   Attorney General Dick Thornburgh advised President Bush about
the legality of the operation before it was launched, said Justice
Department spokesman David Runkel.
   Thornburgh ``believes there is a legal basis for this action
being taken under U.S. law,'' Runkel said. ``It is my understanding
there is clearly legal authority under both U.S. law and
international law.''
   But two attorneys for the Center for Constitutional Rights, a
liberal New York-based civil liberties group, disagree.
   `I'd say it's clearly illegal under the UN Charter and the OAS
charter,'' said attorney Jules Lobel, who is also a law professor
at the University of Pittsburgh.
   ``The United States doesn't have the right to unilaterally
decide to overthrow another governent by the use of force,'' Lobel
said. ``Nothing that the president said today or the secretary of
state said would give the the United States such a right.''
   Lobel said the United States must show it is acting in
self-defense for the invasion to be legal under the UN Charter and
the OAS treaty.
   ``I don't think that can be based on some speculated threat that
American citizens might be endangered,'' Lobel said. Baker had
cited an intelligence report that Panamanian Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noreiga was poised to attack Americans.
   ``If American citizens might be endangered, the obvious thing to
do is to protect them and evacuate them not overthrow the
government,'' Lobel said.
   Both Lobel and David Cole, another attorney for the center, said
the invasion also violated the war-powers provision of the
Constitution, which requires congressional approval of the
deployment of troops in this fashion.
   ``I think the intent of the framers of the Constitution is
clear, if the United States is going to offensively use military
force abroad it must be approved by Congress and not by four
leaders in Congress,'' Lobel said.
   ``As a purely technical constitutional matter, the president
does not have the authority to do what he did,'' Cole said. ``As a
matter of legal and political reality, if Congress doesn't try to
stop him, I think it's unlikely the courts would.''
   Yale University law professor Harold Koh voiced caution about
the invasion, saying ``the rationale of protecting the securityof
the canal must be limited to making sure there is no damage to the
canal or some impairment of the security of the canal.''
   ``It can't be an all-purpose justification of wide-ranging
actions to restructure the government,'' Koh said.
   Koh also expressed skepticism about justifying the invasion as
an effort to arrest Noriega. ``As a matter of international law,
there is a danger in converting political action into so-called
crime fighting action.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>