<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0093 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1809EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Bush'sOptions 2ndLd-Writethru a0579 12-25 0887</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush's Options, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0579,870</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush's Options Shift From Military to Diplomatic, Legal Fronts</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 6th graf bgng, `The White House' with 1 graf to UPDATE
with Monday's negotiations</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RUTH SINAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Manuel Antonio Noriega's decision to seek
asylum at the Vatican's embassy in Panama City forces President
Bush into the thicket of diplomacy and international law in pursuit
of his goal of bringing the deposed dictator to trial on drug
trafficking charges.
   ``Now it's up to the lawyers and the diplomats,'' summed up
Pentagon chief Dick Cheney, whose troops tried but failed to
capture the elusive dictator in more than four days of searching.
   When Noriega drove up to the Vatican embassy in Panama City on
Christmas Eve, Bush accomplished a central goal of the invasion he
ordered last week: removing the indicted drug trafficker from all
power in Panama.
   But how Bush, Panama's U.S.-backed government, the Vatican and
other nations handle the next step could determine not only
Noriega's fate, but the future of the strategically placed isthmus
for years to come.
   U.S. interests appear to be best served by Noriega's speedy
removal from the Papal Nunciature, where he is protected by
diplomatic immunity and by the spotlight of international
attention. As long as he stays, attention could be diverted from
U.S. efforts to restore order to the devastated country.
   In talks with Vatican officials in Rome on Monday, the Bush
administration delivered a forceful message demanding Noriega be
turned over to U.S. custody. The message was delivered ``in
extraordinarily tough terms,'' said one official, who spoke on
condition of anonymity.
   But the Vatican, which has offered haven to Noriega's foes in
recent months, would have to reverse centuries of practice and
diplomatic principle to hand the general to the United States
against his will.
   Asked if a simple turnover were foreseeable, Vatican spokesman
Joaquin Navarro said, ``Well, I don't think so. There isn't an
extradition treaty or anything.''
   Bush, who has held several diplomatic jobs in his career,
presumably understands the complexities well. The United States has
been sheltering Chinese dissident Fang Lizhi in the U.S. Embassy in
Beijing for many months despite Chinese demands to hand him over.
   Bush could ask the government of U.S.-backed President Guillermo
Endara to demand Noriega be handed over by the Vatican. But Endara
has already said his country is forbidden by its constitution to
extradite any Panamanian citizen to the United States.
   Another solution could lie in removing Noriega from Panama to a
third country. The United States set a precedent for such a
scenario when it negotiated with Noriega in 1988 after he was
indicted in Florida, and again as recently as October.
   State Department officials were apparently prepared to drop
their demand for bringing Noriega to the United States if he agreed
to resign his posts. Later, the U.S. upped its ante and demanded
that Noriega leave Panama.
   Spain, Cuba and the Dominican Republic _ where Noriega has a
daughter and some real estate _ have been mentioned as possible
exiles. Until now, Noriega has refused to go.
   But in any deal Noriega works out, he would likely demand a
promise that he not be extradited to the United States.
   That could create a problem with Spain which has a 1970
extradition treaty with the United States.
   Foreign Minister Francisco Fernandez Ordonez said Monday that
Spain would not be a convenient place for Noriega to seek asylum
because he would have to be turned over to U.S. authorities on
drug-related charges.
   An exile closer to home could prove troublesome, if it left
Noriega close enough to foment resistance to the new Panamanian
government among former loyalists of his regime.
   ``Part of the deal would have to be that he promise not to
interfere in Panamanian politics,'' said James Goodby, a professor
of diplomacy at Georgetown University. ``The farther away he goes,
the better.''
   Even if Noriega were brought to this country, other
complications could stand in the way of a trial.
   Raymond Takiff, Noriega's attorney in Miami, said prosecution
would result in sensitive information being divulged about
Noriega's long association with the CIA. Federal prosecutors
familiar with the case say they believe a trial could go forward.
   The nature of the sensitive information could include material
relating to Bush himself.
   According to Kevin Buckley, who is writing a book for Simon and
Schuster about Noriega, the deposed Panamanian leader and Bush
first met in 1976. Bush headed the CIA at the time, and Buckley
said Noriega commanded his country's intelligence services.
   In 1983, Bush visited Noriega in Panama and reportedly hinted
that if the general helped the U.S.-backed Nicaraguan Contra
rebels, the United States would turn a blind eye to his drug profit
laundering, Buckley said. Bush has denied making any such promise.
   Noriega also met in 1985 aboard a yacht with former White House
aide Oliver North to discuss help for the Contras, according to
Buckley.
   ``He (Noriega) knows where a lot of skeletons are buried in
Central America and some of them may be very close to Bush's
office,'' said William Schneider, a senior fellow at the American
Enterprise Institute.
  
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Ruth Sinai has been covering foreign affairs for
The Associated Press in Washington since 1987.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
</TEXT>

</DOC>