<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0257EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Nicaragua-US 2ndLd-Writethru   12-30 0458</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nicaragua-US, 2nd Ld-Writethru,a0431,0471</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nicaragua Expels 20 U.S. Diplomats In Retaliation For Panama Incident</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 3 grafs to CORRECT Nicaragua expelling 20 diplomats
and ordering the mission to cut its support staff to 100 people. Pickup
2nd graf pvs, `The announcement...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FILADELFO ALEMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANAGUA, Nicaragua (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Daniel Ortega said Friday
that 20 American diplomats will be expelled in retaliation for an
incident at the Nicaraguan Embassy in Panama.
   Ortega also ordered the embassy to cut its service and
administrative staff from 320 people to 100 people. It was not
immediately known how many are American.
   The 20 diplomats will be given 72 hours to leave Nicaragua after
their names are made public, Ortega said in the announcement
broadcast nationwide by a government radio network.
   The announcement came just hours after Nicaragua's amabassador
to Panaman, Antenor Ferrey, said U.S. troops surrounded his
residence in Panama City, ordered all personnel inside to evacuate
and searched the building for weapons.
   Ortega called the diplomatic incident ``unheard of.''
   The troops seized five rifles inside the residence that Ferrey
said were there for self-defense. A U.S. Army colonel in charge of
the operation later apologized and returned the rifles, Ferrey said.
   ``They acted arrogantly, like Rambos!'' Ortega said of the
incident. ``We were at grave risk a political-military clash with
the United States, which has maintained an aggressive attitude
against Latin American countries.''
   Ortega claimed the U.S. soldiers ``stole more than $2,000 and
took away some clothes from the residence.''
   U.S. Embassy and military officials said they had no information
on the incident.
   Ortega's announcement also said the U.S. Embassy will be forced
to ``compact its 220 of its personnel of 320, leaving only 100 in
service.'' This was taken to mean that another 220 embassy
employees, mostly Nicaraguan administrative and service personnel,
will also be forced to leave their jobs.
   It was not immediately clear if the embassy had that many
support personnel. The phones of the embassy and the homes of
several senior officers were either not answered or rang busy.
   U.S. diplomatic representation in Nicaragua was lowered when
Ortega's leftist Sandinista regime expelled Ambassador Richard
Melton and eight other American diplomats in July 1988, accusing
them of meddling in Nicaragua's affairs.
   The government accused the diplomats of inciting street
demonstrations against the Sandinista regime. The U.S. denied the
accusation.
   Since then, the embassy has been headed by charge d'affairs John
Leonard, and relations have not been too cordial.
   Diplomatic tension between the countries has been increasing
since U.S. troops invaded Panama on Dec. 20 and deposed strongman
Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   American troops have been surrounding the Nicaraguan Embassy
offices in Panama City along with those of the Cuban and Libyan
embassies.
</TEXT>

</DOC>