<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0911EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-EastGermany 1stLd-Writethru a0478 12-18 0704</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-East Germany, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0478,0720</SECOND>
<HEAD>Renamed and Redirected, Communists Resume Talks With Opposition</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: LEADS with 13 grafs to UPDATE with talks disrupted, new decisions
made. Pickup 11th pvs, `In his...</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   ;SUBS grfs 13-19 pvs,
``The new...its principles...' with 4 to trim, delete redundancies.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY6</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAROL J. WILLIAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   East German Communists and opposition
factions today resumed talks on the nation's future over the din of
hundreds of protesters who banged on windows and demanded a part in
the negotiations.
   The forum brought together various political parties, social
organizations and fledgling pro-democracy movements into a council
of more than 40 that is to advise the interim government until free
elections in May.
   After two hours of debate, participants decided to allow five
more groups, including the official trade union federation, to take
part in the talks and granted observer status to four more.
   The negotiators agreed to meet each Monday to propose
legislation and proposed that future discussions be carried live on
television and radio.
   Hundreds of angry demonstrators disrupted the first hour of the
session, using bullhorns to shout their demands to be included and
banging on windows of the ground-floor conference room of the
Lutheran Church building where the talks were held.
   ``Anyone who tries to force his participation in this way is not
acting in the interests of democracy,'' President Manfred Gerlach
said as the noise overwhelmed speakers.
   The participants proposed a message of solidarity to Premier
Hans Modrow and West German Chancellor Helmut Kohl, who meet
Tuesday in Dresden.
   They said the German-German summit expresses the will of both
nations to improve relations, but they warned against any moves
that would damage the sovereignty of either state _ a call to leave
the reunification issue off the agenda.
   The meeting comes a day after the Communist Party concluded an
emergency congress in which it embraced a multiparty system and
changed its name to the Socialist Unity Party of Germany-Party of
Democratic Socialism.
   The long title reflects both a new orientation to democratic
principles and an eagerness to divorce itself from the corruption
and power abuses that tainted former Communist leaders ousted in a
pro-democracy movement that began in September.
   New Communist Party leader Gregor Gysi and Wolfgang Berghofer,
his chief deputy, opened the talks Dec. 7.
   At that session, May 6 was set as the date for the first-ever
competitive elections to seat a new Parliament, kicking off a
volatile campaign season likely to result in a minority role for
the Communists.
   The talks have spurred the discredited Communists to consult
with their broadening opposition on how to run the country until
elections are held.
   In his address Sunday to the congress' final session, Gysi set
out a new course for the party that breaks with four decades of
Stalinism.
   Nearly 2,700 delegates unanimously approved the draft of a new
statute, to serve as the party rulebook until its next regular
congress, as well as the outlines of a new program.
   The Communists were stripped of their constitutional mandate to
rule during a parliamentary session Dec. 1. It reduced their status
to that of any other political force, though the premier and much
of his Cabinet are Communist.
   When a new Parliament is seated after elections, it in turn will
name a new government.
   The Communists polled only 12 percent support in a public
opinion survey conducted by major West German pollsters in early
December, and Modrow himself has predicted his party could win no
more than 20 percent of the vote if elections were held now.
   Two other political conventions were held over the weekend, by
the small Christian Democratic Union of East Germany that is aiming
to win votes from the religious population, and by the opposition
group Democratic Awakening.
   Despite the Communists' opposition to reunification, the theme
has taken hold among some political groups.
   Delegates at the founding party congress of Democratic Awakening
in Leipzig voted 350-35 with 21 abstentions that the right of
German unity should be inscribed in the East German constitution.
   The Christian Democratic Union's leader, Lothar de Maiziere,
told delegates he could envisage a single German state within a
united Europe.
</TEXT>

</DOC>