<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0118 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1704EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-LakesShipping     12-28 0427</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lakes Shipping,0440</SECOND>
<HEAD>Great Lakes Shipping Ends Down</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAULT STE. MARIE, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The main shipping link between
the Great Lakes closed two weeks early Thursday because of ice, a
gloomy finale to a slump caused by coal strikes, November gales and
a sluggish steel industry.
   ``We'll probably not even reach the tons we carried in 1988.
We'll probably be even or down as much as 2 million tons,'' George
Ryan, president of the Lake Carriers' Association, said from
Cleveland.
   Shippers in 1988 posted their best year since the crash of the
steel industry six years before. This year's slump reverses a trend
of increases since the recession.
   Ryan blamed the weather. November gales prompted ships to drop
anchor, and ore, coal and stone shipments that month dropped 10
percent or 12.8 million tons. Coal alone was down 17 percent.
   Early December ice closed the major link between the lakes, Soo
Locks on Lake Superior, two weeks early.
   An estimated 2 million tons of cargo, most of it iron ore, was
stranded in port until spring when the last freighter, the American
Republic, locked through Sault Ste. Marie at 2:44 p.m. Wednesday.
   On Thursday, 22 ships remained on the four lower lakes, fighting
the ice to finish their deliveries before heading home for winter.
Ryan said cargo should continue to move down Lake Michigan to
Indiana ports through the middle of January.
   He was unsure what 1990 will bring, but some carrier customers
expect more of the same.
   ``We'll have some slowdown, not drastic,'' said M. Thomas Moore,
chairman of Cleveland-Cliffs Inc., the nation's largest iron ore
producer.
   The biggest Great Lakes cargo traffic is in moving ore from
mines in Minnesota and Michigan's Upper Peninsula to steel mills on
the lower lakes. Deliveries began the year at a pace to break
1988's post-recession record, but stalled over the summer.
   Reduced demand for the raw ore that goes into steelmaking is the
problem, Moore said. Steel sales are down and more mills are
recycling steel rather than producing it, he said.
   Coal shipments have been depressed since May by a strike at
Pittston Co. mines in West Virginia, Virginia and Kentucky. As of
December, Lake Erie ports had moved 2.4 million tons less coal than
they had by December 1988.
   Shipping lanes this week remained open in the lower lakes,
though they are restricted in some areas.
   Conditions on western Lake Erie and the Detroit River have
improved since late last week, when eight vessels were stopped or
slowed by ice, the Coast Guard said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>