<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0153 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1517EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-MailBombs 3rdLd-Writethru a0733 12-20 0884</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mail Bombs, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0733,0905</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge's Funeral Held Under Tight Security</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 3 grafs after 9th graf pvs, `Family friends ...' with
comment from NAACP's Hooks.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HOYT HARWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOUNTAIN BROOK, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bomb-sniffing dogs and dozens of
police provided security today at the funeral of a federal judge
killed by a parcel bomb in a wave of attacks that may have been
carried out by white racists.
   More than 700 mourners, including Attorney General Dick
Thornburgh and FBI Director William S. Sessions, filled a suburban
church for the service in memory of U.S. Circuit Judge Robert Vance.
   Vance was a man ``who stood up for the underdog and the
oppressed,'' his friend U.S. Bankruptcy Judge Clifford Fulford of
Birmingham told mourners. ``No wonder his assassins could not stand
such a man in their presence.''
   The 58-year-old Vance was killed by a package bomb Saturday. FBI
agents say the bomb and three others, including the one that killed
Savannah, Ga., lawyer Robert Robinson, 42, on Monday, all bore
Georgia return addresses or postmarks.
   Links to NAACP school desegregation efforts have been
established in all four cases, leading investigators to speculate
that a white racist group may be responsible. After police defused
a bomb at an NAACP office in Jacksonville, Fla., Tuesday, the
organization placed all its offices on alert.
   Four anonymous letters mailed in August to declare war on
various federal appeals courts are being examined for clues to the
bombings, FBI spokesman Greg Jones said today in Washington.
   St. Luke's Episcopal Church, in a quiet area of this wooded,
exclusive suburb of Birmingham, was surrounded by police barriers
as part of security precautions that included bomb searches and
guards.
   Among those attending was Supreme Court Justice Anthony Kennedy,
who oversees Vance's appellate circuit. Vance's wife, Helen,
remained hospitalized from wounds received in the bombing.
   Family friends said Vance's body had been cremated and his ashes
will be placed in the church.
   In Baltimore today, NAACP executive director Benjamin Hooks said
the attacks will not prevent the NAACP from ``moving forward full
speed ahead on the job of trying to make America a place of equal
justice for all.''
   ``I think it's the work of white supremacists without any
question. I think it reveals the derangement, demented, criminally
stupid minds,'' Hooks said.
   Hooks said he had been assured by Sessions and Thornburgh that
the bombings were being given the highest priority.
   William Hinshaw, agent in charge of the Atlanta FBI office, told
The Birmingham News in an interview published today that the deadly
package addressed to Vance was mailed Thursday from Newnan, a town
of about 11,500 people 30 miles southwest of Atlanta.
   The bomb that killed Robinson on Monday is believed to have been
mailed Friday from Macon, 82 miles southeast of Atlanta, Hinshaw
said, but the postmark was destroyed in the blast.
   The Atlanta Constitution quoted unidentified sources as saying
it bore a return address in Warner Robins, a town near Macon.
   The bomb found Tuesday in Jacksonville also was mailed Friday
from Macon, Hinshaw said. A Jacksonville NAACP official, Lloyd N.
Pearson, told the Macon Telegraph and News the package bore the
return address of a Warner Robins lawyer.
   Another device was mailed Saturday from the Atlanta area to the
11th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals clerk's office in Atlanta,
Hinshaw said, and the Constitution reported it bore the return
address of an Atlanta lawyer. The court, on which Vance served,
handled appeals of federal cases from Georgia, Alabama and Florida.
   That bomb was removed safely. All four bombs reportedly were
designed to hurl nails or shrapnel.
   Sessions told reporters that some organized group could be
responsible for the bombs. He said a pattern of racist attacks
``has to be one of the factors in the back of all our minds.''
   ``Common sense would tell you _ the number of incidents ... in
three different states, all part of the 11th Circuit. It's quite
possible there is more than one (person responsible),'' Sessions
said.
   Benjamin Hooks, executive director of the National Association
for the Advancement of Colored People, said he believed an
organized group was behind the attacks. He instructed the civil
rights group's 1,800 offices to take precautions in handling mail.
   Hooks also said he fears the bombings were the beginning of a
wave of attacks: ``The thing has come to the place where everyone
may be in jeopardy, from the president on down.''
   One possible link between the cases was the NAACP's efforts to
desegregate Southern schools, authorities said. Evidence included:
   _Vance wrote the 11th Circuit's unanimous opinion three months
ago that ruled in favor of the NAACP in a desegregation suit
against the Jacksonville, Fla., schools.
   _Robinson, a black city alderman, represented the NAACP in
another desegregation case involving Savannah area schools. On
Sept. 29, an 11th Circuit panel that didn't include Vance upheld a
desegregation plan opposed by the NAACP.
   _The Jacksonsville NAACP chapter talked with Robinson about its
desegregation case, but Robinson did not represent them. ``He gave
us some advice,'' said the Rev. Fred Newbill, pastor of the First
Timothy Baptist Church.
   Vance and Robinson shared a moderate-to-progressive political
stance and an interest in civil rights, but friends of the two
believed they had never met.
</TEXT>

</DOC>