<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0126 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1427EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Lithuania     12-22 0497</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lithuania,0510</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lithuanian Lawmaker Calls on Kremlin to Start Talks on Independence</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Lithuanian lawmaker Friday challenged the
Kremlin in front of the entire Soviet parliament to begin talks
leading to full independence for his Baltic republic.
   Lithuania ``was forcibly included in the Soviet Union,'' said
deputy Kazimeras Motieka. If the Kremlin is serious about reform,
he said, it should move to eliminate the results of the crimes of
dictator Josef Stalin, who annexed the Baltic region.
   ``As a person empowered by the voters of Lithuania, I call upon
the government of the U.S.S.R. to begin official negotiations in
the near future with fully empowered representatives of Lithuania
on the liquidation of Stalinist crimes and on the restoration of
the independence of the Lithuanian state,'' Motieka told the
Congress of People's Deputies, or parliament.
   Drawing a parallel with Romania, where President Nicolae
Ceausescu was overthrown Friday, Motieka said: ``We also have a
dictator: Moscow. If the Soviet Union is building a government of
laws, well, legality and occupation don't go together.''
   The challenge by Motieka, a lawyer, came two days after the
Lithuanian Communist Party voted to declare itself independent from
its mother party in Moscow.
   It was the first time a delegate from one of the restive Baltic
republics used the national parliament to advance demands for full
independence, and it marked the latest step in the Baltic
progression from calls for sovereignty to outright secession.
   After Motieka's speech, Lithuanian deputy Vytautas Landsbergis
said the Lithuanian parliament had already created a commission
that is working on the steps necessary for the Baltic state to
achieve independence. Motieka's appeal stemmed from that
commission's work, said Landsbergis, head of the Lithuanian
people's front, known as Sajudis.
   President Mikhail S. Gorbachev responded sharply to the
Lithuanian Communist Party's decision Wednesday to separate from
the Soviet Communist Party.
   Gorbachev sent a message to Lithuanian Communists on Thursday
saying their decision could only be assessed ``as a step aimed at
the split of the Lithuanian Communist Party from the Soviet
Communist Party.''
   His message said the ruling Politburo would convene an emergency
meeting soon to address the move.
   Landsbergis said he thought the Lithuanian Communist Party's
decision to secede was a normal ``step in perestroika.''
   Delegates from the Baltic republics have been struggling for the
last two days over Congress' plans to create a committee to rule on
conflicts between local laws passed in the republics and national
Soviet law.
   Baltic deputies object that because they were unlawfully
incorporated into the Soviet Union, they should not be forced to
comply with Moscow's laws. Baltic deputies say it makes no sense to
establish a committee to oversee a constitution that is being
rewritten as the country reforms.
   A committee that developed the legislation offered a compromise
that would limit the Constitutional Oversight Commission's right to
review certain ethnic issues, but Baltic republics said the wording
of the compromise was too vague. It was sent back to the committee.
</TEXT>

</DOC>