<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1725EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Czechoslovakia 1stLd-Writethru a0718 12-17 0836</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Czechoslovakia, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0718,0861</SECOND>
<HEAD>Citizens Remember March That Began Revolt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: RECASTS lead graf; SUBS 9 grafs for 10-11 bgng `After the...'
to UPDATE with details of march, ADD development in Romania. Picks up 12th
graf `Havel was...' with minor editing to trim</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto XPRA1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SYDNEY RUBIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tens of thousands of students
marched on Sunday and hundreds attended a special Mass to
commemorate a rally a month ago that turned violent, shocked the
country and triggered a peaceful revolution.
   Roman Catholic priest Vaclav Maly, who was stripped of his state
license to preach for signing a human rights charter, addressed
about 1,000 people under the baroque, vaulted ceiling of St.
Margaret's Basilica.
   Hundreds of Roman Catholic faithful who could not get inside
stood in the rain to hear Maly's first public Mass in 11 years.
   The Mass was dedicated to a peaceful student rally Nov. 17
organized to honor a student killed by the Nazis 50 years ago. The
rally ended when club-swinging police attacked the students, and
143 people were injured.
   Czechoslovakia exploded in the weeks that followed, with
hundreds of thousands of people pouring into the streets demanding
democratic reform. The embattled Communists surrendered their
41-year monopoly on power, swore in a new government dominated by
non-Communists and promised free elections.
   Elsewhere in Eastern Europe on Sunday:
   _The East German Communist Party called for a ``human,
democratic socialism'' and stressed its opposition to German
reunification as an emergency congress ended. The party adopted a
new platform designed to guide it until a regular congress in
February.
   _Poland's Solidarity-led government introduced radical economic
legislation in an effort to break monopolies, cut subsidies,
privatize industry and curb 900 percent inflation.
   _Some 800 mostly elderly delegates of Hungary's Communist Party
held a congress in Budapest in an effort to reorganize the party,
which was disbanded Oct. 8 and transformed into the Hungarian
Socialist Party.
   _Romanian police clashed with thousands of anti-government
demonstrators over the weekend after authorities tried to deport a
dissident clergyman, the Hungarian state news agency and other
sources said Sunday.
   After the Mass in Prague, students retraced the three-mile path
of the Nov. 17 march, walking to Vysehrad Cemetery and cathedral
and winding through Prague's historic streets for a rally at
Wenceslas Square.
   About 100,000 people marched, many carrying candles and banners
saying ``Havel for President'' and chanting ``Long live Havel!''
   Dissident playwright Vaclav Havel is the opposition Civic
Forum's candidate for president, a largely ceremonial but symbolic
post. Hard-line President Gustav Husak resigned one week ago.
   The students paused for a moment of silence and to light candles
at the site of the police charges.
   Bystanders cheered and applauded as the marchers headed slowly
to Wenceslas Square through clogged streets.
   ``We are just so grateful to the students for what they did to
bring about this change,'' said an elderly woman, speaking on
condition of anonymity.
   ``It's such a terrible shame that our generation was not able to
do the same thing.''
   Havel was reported Saturday to have reached an agreement with
the other main presidential contender, Alexander Dubcek, in which
Dubcek would accept another top post and Havel would become
president. But Dubcek, who engineered the ``Prague Spring'' reforms
crushed by the Soviet-led invasion in 1968, was quoted as telling
an Italian newspaper on Saturday that he remains interested in
becoming president.
   Havel, in a televised speech Saturday night, said, ``We are all
grateful to the students for having given the revolution its
beautiful, dignified, peaceful, and I daresay, affectionate face
that is now admired by the whole world.
   ``It was a revolt of the truth against the lie, of purity
against filth, of the human heart against violence.''
   At the start of Sunday's Mass, Maly was bathed in television
spotlights as he received a one-minute ovation.
   Switching from Czech to English halfway through his sermon, Maly
said:
   ``You can experience here an alive church that ... doesn't wish
to master, to rule society, but a searching church, searching for
God's truth.''
   The service ended with voices raised in the haunting hymn of St.
Wenceslas, patron saint of Bohemia, and Czechoslovakia's national
anthem. One by one, the crowd slowly raised their hands in the
now-familiar sign of victory.
   Under Communist rule, the Roman Catholic Church struggled to
serve the nation's estimated 9.3 million Catholics, who comprise 60
percent of the population.
   Maly, like many of his fellow priests, could not preach or hold
services without a government license. Communist authorities
refused to approve many of the men proposed by the Vatican to fill
bishoprics.
   Bishoprics fell vacant and remained so. Cardinal Frantisek
Tomasek, 90, remained spiritual leader despite his age out of fear
he might not be replaced.
   Maly was stripped of his license to preach after signing the
Charter 77 human rights document. He held services illegally in his
cramped apartment for laymen who faced discrimination for their
Christian beliefs.
   Now, Maly's name is being mentioned as a replacement for Tomasek.
</TEXT>

</DOC>