<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0102 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1353EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     12-29 0916</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0943</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: RETRANSMITTING to restore AMs cycle designator</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WEST HOLLYWOOD, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor Christian Michael Slater was
jailed Friday after he allegedly led authorities on a chase,
crashed his sports car into a pole and scuffled with sheriff's
deputies.
   Slater, 20, whose film credits include ``Heathers'' and
``Tucker,'' was booked for investigation of drunken driving, hit
and run, driving with a suspended license, evading arrest, and
assault on a peace officer, sheriff's Sgt. Cecil Rhambo said. Bail
was set at $3,000. The actor remained in custody Friday.
   The chase began about 1 a.m. when a deputy saw a late-model Saab
Turbo 900 traveling at more than 50 mph in a 35 mph zone, the
sergeant said. When the deputy tried to stop the motorist, he sped
off, made two right turns and drove into an alley, where his car
slammed into a telephone pole, he said.
   Three passengers remained in the car while Slater got out and
scaled a chain link fence, said Rhambo. When three deputies tried
to arrest him, a ``small struggle'' ensued, he said.
   Slater also has appeared in the films ``The Name of the Rose''
and ``The Legend of Billie Jean.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Eds: Sinbad, one name, is cq.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>KANSAS CITY, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Comedian-actor Sinbad told 100
underprivileged youths they can succeed through hard work,
confidence and a good education despite the negative influences of
drugs and crime that surround them.
   ``A lot of you may not know how much you have to offer, how
important you are,'' the actor, who plays Walter on the TV series
``A Different World,'' said Thursday during a visit to the YMCA
Youth Extension Center. ``I'm here to tell you you can do anything
you want to. But not if you're dead or in jail.''
   Sinbad, who was in town for a performance at the Midland
Theater, said that speaking in black communities was a way for him
to give back some of what he's learned to youngsters in need of
role models.
   ``There's something happening in the community that is very
tragic,'' he said. ``We have brothers killing brothers, right in
our own neighborhood, and over what? Dope, drugs.''
   He told the youths: ``I don't drink and I don't hide the fact
that I don't.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   New York will get its first first lady in 12
years when Joyce Dinkins' husband David gets sworn in as mayor Jan.
1.
   Mrs. Dinkins, who shunned the limelight during her husband's
11-month campaign to become the first black mayor of New York, told
New York Newsday in an interview published Friday, ``I haven't been
newsworthy up until now.''
   Mrs. Dinkins said she doesn't plan to change but predicted, ``I
probably will be less private.''
   She left her job as coordinator of the city office of the state
Department of Taxation on Dec. 14 after 11 years at the agency.
   ``I thought being first lady would be a full-time job and I
thought that the demands of my new career would really not allow me
to work full time,'' she said.
   As the city's official hostess, Mrs. Dinkins, 60, will take on
jobs done by Diane Coffey, chief of staff for outgoing Mayor Edward
I. Koch, a bachelor.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>TULSA, Okla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Record-breaking football receiver Steve
Largent was named by the Jaycees Friday as one of the 10
Outstanding Young Americans for 1990.
   The award goes to 10 Americans ages 21 through 39 who exemplify
the best attributes of the nation's adults. The recepients will be
honored Jan. 20 at the 52nd awards congress in Tulsa, headquarters
of the U.S. Junior Chamber of Commerce.
   Largent, 35, was an overlooked receiver in the National Football
League when he joined the Seattle Seahawks in 1976. He went on to
set nearly every NFL record for receiving, including most touchdown
receptions, before retiring at the end of this season. He is
dedicated to community and national charities, including the Spina
Bifida Foundation.
   The other recipients are William Webster, Missouri attorney
general; Vin Weber, R-Minn.; David Cradick, a radio personality
from Dallas; John Croyle of Gadsden, Ala., founder of a boy's
ranch; Capt. Mario Garcia Jr. of Mayaguez, Puerto Rico, who
counsels ghetto drug abusers; Cynthia Gettinger of Bradenton, Fla.,
who won four gold medals in the 1988 Para-Olympics; Jeff Keith of
Fairfield, Conn., the first amputee to run across America; Lt. Col.
Bentley Rayburn of Holloman, N.M., the youngest tactical fighter
squadron commander in the U.S. Air Force; and Janni Smith of Los
Angeles, founder of a health care center for paralysis patients.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Comedian Bob Hope and actress-singer Pia
Zadora have joined the group of celebrities participating in this
year's Rose Bowl festivities.
   Hope, Ms. Zadora and a host of Hollywood stars were invited to
salute the University of Michigan Wolverines in the 43rd annual Big
10 dinner. Michigan, the Big 10 champion, will meet the University
of Southern California, the Pac 10 leader, in the Rose Bowl
football game on New Year's Day.
   The dinner, held Friday night, is hosted each year by the Big 10
Club of Southern California. Other celebrities set to participate
in the fete include Claude Akins, Zsa Zsa Gabor, Jermaine Jackson,
Tommy Lasorda, Gavin MacLeod and McLean Stevenson.
   Entertainment is to be provided by comedian Norm Crosby,
impersonator George Kirby, Hope and Ms. Zadora. Rose Queen Yasmine
Delawari and her court are scheduled to be in attendance.
</TEXT>

</DOC>