<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0182 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2235EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel 1stLd-Writethru a0693 12-21 0519</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0693,0534</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israeli Troops Kill 2 Palestinians</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE wounded. Pick up 4th pvs, `Also
Thursday...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EILEEN ALT POWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israeli troops shot and killed two Palestinians
on Thursday after soldiers were stoned as they tried to arrest
uprising activists in a West Bank village, the army said.
   Five other Palestinians, two of them women, suffered gunshot
wounds in the incident, Arab reports said.
   In the occupied Gaza Strip, 21 Palestinians were shot and
wounded in scattered stone-throwing clashes with Israeli troops,
Arab reports said.
   The military confirmed seven wounded in Gaza and five in the
West Bank.
   Also Thursday, more than 150 Palestinian university
administrators and professors launched a campaign to demand Israel
to reopen colleges and universities closed by the army almost since
the start of the Palestinian uprising.
   At an organizational meeting, the group said that the closures
in the West Bank and Gaza since January 1988 were depriving 42,000
Palestinians of an education and seriously damaging the finances of
the institutions.
   ``We are being banned from a basic right, access to schools and
universities,'' Adib Khatib, a vice president at An-Najah
University in Nablus, told the meeting in Jerusalem. ``This
collective punishment must be brought to an end.''
   The deaths occurred in Beit Furik, a village of about 5,000
people near Nablus.
   The army said soldiers raiding the village were attacked with
stones and concrete blocks and that one officer was lightly wounded
in the face.
   ``The soldiers shot a number of plastic bullets at the stone and
block throwers,'' the army said. ``Later it was reported that two
were killed.''
   The victims, Ayesh Wajeeh Khatatbeh, 17, and Zahi Tawfik
Hannani, 21, both were hit in the head, Arab reports said.
   The deaths raised to 633 the number of Palestinians killed by
Israelis since the start of the Palestinian revolt in December 1987.
   Forty-three Israelis also have been slain, and 161 other
Palestinians have been killed by fellow Arabs, most on suspicion of
collaborating with Israel.
   In the West Bank town of Bethlehem, soldiers putting up strings
of colored lights for Christmas Eve choir services were stoned by
Palestinian youths wearing green head bands of the Islamic Jihad
fundamentalist movement, witnesses said.
   The soldiers were decorating because Palestinian municipal
officials have canceled Christmas festivities in solidarity with
the uprising. The troops chased the stone throwers, but no arrests
were reported.
   The army announced Thursday that it has adopted rules to punish
the parents of child stone throwers in the Gaza Strip by
confiscating property or sealing off rooms in houses.
   The spokesman said the steps were being taken because minors,
those under age 12, cannot be jailed under Israeli law.
   ``All this is because we can't put the boy in jail,'' said the
spokesman, who cannot be identified under military regulations.
   The new rules require parents to post bail if a child is caught
throwing stones repeatedly. The spokesman said that if a family
refused to pay, the army could confiscate property or seal a room
of the family's house.
</TEXT>

</DOC>