<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0201 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0712EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e AM-APArts:Mock'90s Adv29   12-21 1162</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-AP Arts: Mock '90s, Adv 29,1196</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv29</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Friday AMs, Dec. 29, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Editors of Mock '90s History Wish the World a Nice Millenium</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID GERMAIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A quick reality check on the 1990s.
   It was the decade Ted Kennedy announced his clan's goal for the
21st century: a million Kennedys by the year 2050.
   It was the decade Raisa Gorbachev kicked her husband out of
office and capitalized the Soviet Union with the slogan: ``Let's go
shopping.''
   It was the decade that Bennie, the retarded gofer on ``L.A.
Law,'' became chief justice of the U.S. Supreme Court.
   Wasn't it?
   Tony Hendra and Peter Elbling hope so. The two
satirists-turned-prophets have just published ``The '90s: A Look
Back,'' a retrospective on the decade whose catch-phrase was _ will
be _ uh, might be? _ ``Have a nice millennium.''
   In putting together the book, ``one thing that emerged was a
certain kind of attack on creeping niceness, the feeling that
everything is coming out all right,'' Hendra said in a telephone
interview.
   ``Dan Quayle will be running in 1996 and it's the perfect slogan
for him, `Let's all have a nice millennium together,''' said
Hendra, a former editor of National Lampoon who played the band
manager in Rob Reiner's rockumentary spoof, ``This Is Spinal Tap.''
   Hendra and Elbling gathered more than 75 writers and artists to
produce their pseudo-history, including author George Plimpton,
comics Bill Murray and George Carlin and playwright David Mamet.
   In their world, things to come include social unrest by the
second-homeless, middle-income Americans who can't afford summer
homes; monster Alka-Seltzer tablets dropped into mountain lakes to
solve the acid rain problem; and a National Weather Service
announcement that trailer parks cause tornadoes.
   Geraldo Rivera is elected president, and declares that his
inauguration was ``my first public appearance in 10 years where no
one took a swing at me.''
   ``The line between politics and show business became so blurred
in the '80s,'' Elbling said in a telephone interview. ``If Reagan,
why not Geraldo? If a B-movie actor, why not a B-grade talk show
host?''
   Marilyn Quayle nearly derailed her husband's 1992 presidential
campaign by posing nude. The book includes a picture.
   ``But I wish she had gone to the gym and worked out before she
posed,'' Elbling said.
   Tasteless? Maybe, the editors admit.
   ``But no more tasteless than what's going on in the world,''
said Elbling, who has worked with Chicago's Second City comedy club
and appeared on NBC's ``Cheers'' and ``The Golden Girls.''
   With satire, you're almost bound to offend someone, Hendra said.
``If you don't you're probably not doing a very good job. It's a
sign you're doing the job right when the nitwits and hypocrites get
exercised about something you've written.''
   ``The '90s'' is a sequel to their 1979 book, ``The '80s: A Look
Back,'' edited by Hendra, Elbling and Christopher Cerf _ son of
humorist Bennett Cerf. Elbling said Cerf's schedule didn't allow
him to work on the new book, but he is listed in the credits as
``editor in absentia.''
   In 1979, the editors found they always had to explain what the
title meant.
   ``People asked if we meant the 80s age group, or the 1880s,''
said Hendra. Americans weren't conscious of the ``1980s as an
entity,'' he said.
   With the '90s book, they haven't had to explain the title at all.
   ```Decade-think' has become part of the national
consciousness,'' he said. ``Even the lowest form of intelligence,
airline magazines, are doing stories about the '90s.''
   Published by Avon Books, the book uses issues of the late '80s
to extrapolate the future. In response to President Bush's call for
a ``kinder, gentler nation,'' America introduced the low-voltage
electric chair. In 1994, the issue of dumping medical waste at sea
came to a climax when an entire operating room _ complete with
comatose patient _ washed ashore in New Jersey. The disease of the
'90s was CHIPS _ Computer Human Infectious Parasitic Syndrome _ the
transfer of computer viruses to the human nervous system.
   And the economic war with Asia took a twist when the CIA
recommended that Japan vaporize two American cities with small
atomic bombs in August 1995 to stimulate new U.S. economic growth.
The Japanese refused, saying they had no nuclear bombs.
   ``If you can say that some frightful thing has already happened,
you do it with the hope that people will laugh and then not let it
happen,'' Hendra said.
   Hendra and Elbling talk as if they're really living in the year
history's odometer clicked around to three zeros. They consider the
'90s a done deal, with their book standing as the decade's
definitive history.
   ``We feel as if we've lived through the '90s and we feel an
obligation to share our insights,'' Elbling said.
   Hendra and Elbling kill off a good share of today's public
figures _ Queen Elizabeth is beheaded by Margaret Thatcher; Lauren
Bacall, Rex Reed and other Dakota apartment dwellers are murdered
by Yoko Ono so she can buy their co-ops; and Dan Quayle
mysteriously ascends into heaven during a ski trip.
   ``Disposable people make good jokes,'' says the book's
introduction.
   In fairness, the book also brings back some of history's dead:
``We know Nostradamus' predictions that the dead would rise from
their graves as the Millennium approached were true; and we have
Nostradamus himself to prove it.''
   The decade ends with a public suicide by Donald Trump _ who has
become a trillionaire recluse with shoulder-length hair and gnarled
finger nails _ a shot literally heard 'round the world.
   ``I think Don's much too busy ransacking parts of the globe to
take much offense at anything we might write about him,'' Elbling
said.
   Some predictions in the book already are coming true, in
principle if not in fact.
   ``The '90s'' predicts the Berlin Wall will be torn down. In the
book, though, the wall is moved to Central Park to separate blacks
from whites in another divided city, New York.
   And Eastern Europe's shift away from communism is
well-represented. After seizing power, Raisa Gorbachev proclaims
``a softer, fluffier'' Soviet nation as a brigade of washer-dryer
combinations rolls by in the first Maytag Day parade.
   The three zeroes in the year 2000 could be the key to
understanding the decade, Elbling said. The noughts could signify
the start of the third millennium, or they could be read as,
``oh-oh-oh,'' exclamations signaling the end of the world.
   ``Nobody knows if we'll even be here in 10 years,'' he said.
``Everything could come to a crashing halt or a crashing bang. That
`oh-oh-oh' kind of sums it up.''
   Hendra said those ``ohs'' are a problem for the book he wants to
do 10 years from now.
   ``What do you call a book for the year 2000? The `Oh-Ohs: A Look
Back'?'' he said. ``I'll cross that millennium when I come to it.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Friday AMs, Dec. 29</NOTE>

</DOC>