<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1230EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania-Rural     12-29 0644</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Rural,0665</SECOND>
<HEAD>Revolution Unleashes Peasants' Hopes for Democracy</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE JAHN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CORNESTI, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   No flags flutter from the hovels of
Cornesti, and not one house has been scarred by bullets. But the
revolt has unleashed hopes in this peasant village that are as
fervent as any in Bucharest.
   ``We want to live just like anybody else in a free capitalist
society,'' Laszlo Kiss said.
   Kiss's daughter, Tuende, said she already is making plans to run
her own shop, an unheard of activity under executed dictator
Nicolae Ceausescu, who allowed no private entrepreneurship during
his 24 years of communist rule.
   ``Then,'' she said with a dreamy smile, ``I want to see the
world.''
   For Ion Ardilian, Kiss's neighbor, the revolt that brought
promises of democracy has opened the door ``to the possiblity of
working as hard as I want and owning as much property as I can
afford.''
   The village of 600 people is less than five miles from
Timisoara, the nation's fourth-largest city, where a small crowd
protecting a defiant Protestant pastor Dec. 15 sparked nationwide
unrest that ended the Ceausescu era.
   To the outsider, it seems another world, reachable only by a
dirt road pitted with deep potholes.
   The village of small houses showed no sign on a recent afternoon
of the historic events of the past two weeks. The main dirt road
was nearly deserted.
   But villagers said the revolution has inspired in them the same
pride and joy as those of their urban countrymen. And, while
acknowledging that Cornesti appears the same in many ways as before
the revolution, Kiss and others said change was coming.
   ``The same people are sitting in the village council chairs as
before, but they're just keeping the seats warm until new people
are chosen,'' Kiss, 47 said. ``We're not interfering, we're happy
to let things take their course.''
   ``The village leadership became Communist Party members just to
be able to oppress us,'' added Ardilian, 32. ``Whenever someone did
something they didn't like, they bought in the militia to get their
own way. But we're not seeking revenge, we're content to wait.''
   The status of approximately 30 informers, until recently in the
pay of Ceausescu's infamous Securitate secret police, also remains
the same.
   ``Nobody had anything to do with them before, nobody has
anything to do with them now,'' said Kiss. Relatives gathered in
the family's cold and modest sitting room, where a bed-couch piled
high with thick quilts competed for space with a kitchen table and
chairs.
   Kiss, a farm laborer with a small plot of land and some sheep of
his own, painted a dismal picture of life in Cornesti under
Ceausescu.
   ``As a villager, you never went to any functionary, whether in
the city or here, without eggs, meat or other `gifts,''' he said.
``If you didn't bribe them, you accomplished nothing.''
   ``I once had a herd of 100 sheep but was forced to sell most of
them to the state,'' he said. ``When I refused, I was labeled an
anti-socialist element and threatened by the Securitate.''
   The family's life was further complicated by their religious
beliefs. As Seventh Day Adventists, outside the mainstream Orthodox
Catholic Church controlled by the state, they faced hurdles at
school and the workplace.
   ``My two sons and daughter weren't allowed to complete high
school, and the boys were forced to find work as manual laborers,''
he said.
   There were no battles in Cornesti of the kind in the major
cities that pitted the army and civilan revolutionaries against
die-hard Securitate agents.
   They offered their services anyway.
   ``We were told that civilians were not needed, and the army
could mop up the terrorists alone,'' said Kiss. ``But decades of
oppression have made us alert.
   ``We're ready to fight and to die, if necessary, to prevent a
return to dictatorship.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>