<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0094 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1716EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Koch     12-26 0370</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Koch,0381</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mayor Regrets That Blacks Didn't See Him as Friend</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN SHANAHAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mayor Edward I. Koch said Tuesday that his
biggest regret in 12 years at City Hall is that he did not get
credit for helping blacks.
   ``Many people in the black community do not perceive that I was
their friend,'' he said in his annual year-end meeting with
reporters, the last scheduled major press conference of his
mayoralty.
   Koch, who lost his re-election bid to David Dinkins, who is
black, claimed credit for appointing the city's first black police
commissioner, Benjamin Ward, and the first black deputy mayor for
economic development, Stanley Grayson.
   He said that under his administration, the percentage of civil
service jobs held by members of minority groups grew from 31
percent to 62 percent.
   He said he created Operation Giant Step, a program to put
4-year-olds in kindergarten, that he said was helpful largely to
black children.
   ``I believe this administration has been more helpful to the
black minority than all administrations before us,'' he said. ``I
don't think we got credit for it.''
   He discussed a remark that contributed to his political demise,
his statement during the 1988 presidential campaign that Jews
``would be crazy'' to vote for Jesse Jackson.
   That caused a black backlash that carried into this year's
mayoral primary, when Dinkins took 97 percent of the black vote.
   Koch maintained, however, that the black outpouring for Dinkins
was a matter of ethnic pride rather than an attack on him.
   He said the second half of his remark about Jackson went
unheeded. It was, ``... in the same way that blacks and supporters
of black causes would be crazy to vote for George Bush.''
   Asked how history would judge him in the light of dealing with
new problems such as the drug abuse, AIDS and homelessness, he
said, ``They know that within the confines of what a mayor can do,
that I did a lot.''
   After 25 years in city and federal government, Koch, 65, a
former congressman and City Councilman, will be embarking on a new
career as a newspaper columnist, radio and TV commentator, and
university and guest lecturer.
</TEXT>

</DOC>