<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1323EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Christmas-Czech     12-25 0692</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Christmas-Czech,0711</SECOND>
<HEAD>Freedom Celebrated Under the Christmas Tree</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-World Christmas, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SYDNEY RUBIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Many families reunited for the
first time in decades, carolers sang on Prague's old Charles
Bridge, and church bells rang across the nation Monday on
Czechoslovakia's first free Christmas in 41 years.
   ``I feel like this is a miracle,'' said Ivan Martin Jirous, who
was in prison last Christmas serving time for offering unauthorized
lectures on art and publishing an unofficial arts magazine.
   Jirous, 45, was released Nov. 25, about a week after the start
of the peaceful revolution that ousted the hard-line Communist
president, put the government in the hands of reformers and set the
nation on the road to electing a former dissident, Vaclav Havel, as
president before the new year.
   Imprisonment and exile have torn apart families for years.
   Jirous, who spent more than eight years in jail for his
``subversive'' activities, accompanied his two young daughters and
his wife to church Monday to give thanks for his release which he
called ``a present from the mercy of God.''
   On Christmas Eve 1978, Jirous was in Ostrov Nad Ohri prison,
notorious for its brutal guards as well as for the cruelty between
prisoners.
   ``But on Christmas something happened,'' Jirous recalled. ``We
placed a table in the middle of our cells and everybody broght
food, Chrismas sweets, fruit, everything good that they had.''
   ``Together we sat at the long table and there were no
differences, no accounting done on how much we brought or took. We
sang songs, not real Christmas carols because people who are in
Czechoslovak prisons do not know about Christmas, maternal warmth,
the closeness of families, morals or religion. But together we
sang.''
   Jirous said he considered saying a few words about the meaning
of Christmas, the birth of Christ and Christian charity.
   ``But I didn't. The way these people at the bottom of society
were unselfishly and joyously together was the real fulfillment of
Christmas _ without a theological facade. It was my most beautiful
Christmas,'' he said.
   On the 15th century Charles Bridge, groups of young carolers
sang haunting, traditional Christmas melodies in the days leading
up to Christmas. In previous years, police chased carolers from the
broad, cobbled King's Road.
   ``Rejoice, the Christ is born, rejoice!'' the carolers
exuberantly sang Sunday night while joy illuminated the faces of
many listeners.
   ``Everybody is so happy, so cheerful. It is euphoric with
everybody chatting about the future,'' said Dagmar Vogel, 22, home
for Christmas for the first time since she was 15 months old.
   Family conversations are filled with new possiblities: the
chance to study abroad, to write freely, to work without fear, to
be reunited with relatives overseas, she said.
   Miss Vogel's parents emigrated from Czechoslovakia to
Switzerland after the 1968 Soviet invasion crushed the reforms of
the ``Prague Spring.''
   For 21 years they kept in touch by letter, but Miss Vogel said
she did not know many of the family members she has met since
coming home this week.
   ``There are so many aunts, cousins I haven't met. But from the
first moment, I've felt like I belong. It's great to have a family.
It's wonderful to know somebody is there,'' she said, standing
beside the giant fir tree on Old Town Square with a sign reading,
``Freedom Under the Christmas Tree.''
   On Christmas Eve, Miss Vogel, her family and millions of other
Czechoslovaks watched Christmas Mass on an unprecedented live TV
broadcast. The Mass from Prague's 13th century Strahov Monastery
was said by Vaclav Maly, a former dissident priest who was banned
for 11 years for his human rights activities.
   Millions of other believers jammed into churches and Cathedrals
throughout the nation for midnight Mass. On Christmas Day,
90-year-old Cardinal Frantisek Tomasek said Mass at the gothic St.
Vitus Cathedral overlooking the city, delivering a sermon on the
responsiblity that freedom brings.
   In central Prague, on the site where pro-democracy rallies
turned the tide of Czechoslovak history last month, crowds of
students gathered to sing and share the holiday at the statue of
Bohemia's patron saint: good King Wenceslas.
</TEXT>

</DOC>