<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0170 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1026EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APonTV-Jeff Adv20   12-19 0757</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP on TV-Jeff, Adv 20,0779</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv20</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Wednesday Pms, Dec. 20 and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>New CBS Programs Chief Says Escaping Nielsen Cellar Is Possible</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAY SHARBUTT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Television Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jeff Sagansky, a senior program executive at NBC
when it was rising from third to first in prime time ratings,
doesn't consider a similar rise impossible for CBS, third for the
last two seasons.
   ``I think that ... CBS has got the same challenge that NBC faced
in the early '80s,'' says Sagansky, named as CBS Entertainment
president this week and now facing the considerable task of helping
it escape the Nielsen cellar.
   ``I know, having done that, that it is doable,'' he says. ``A
lot of people say, `Oh, it's impossible.' But I know that's not the
case.''
   At 37, picked from his well-paid post as president of Tri-Star
Pictures, Sagansky was NBC's vice president for series in 1983-85,
and helped develop ``Cheers,'' the top-rated ``The Cosby Show'' and
``Miami Vice.''
   In succeeding Kim LeMasters, who resigned as CBS' chief
programmer Nov. 30 after two years, he now faces ratings combat
with his former NBC boss, Brandon Tartikoff, who still is NBC
Entertainment president; with ABC; with the upstart Fox network and
with the ever-growing cable monster.
   With independent stations and videocassette players also
battling for viewers' attention, Sagansky has his work cut out. As
he notes, ``There's a lot more competition now than when NBC'' made
a comeback.
   His philosophy for dealing with it all:
   ``I think it's a case of really targeting your development for
specific time slots and having a sense of showmanship, of putting
shows on that intrigue viewers, that make a splash, that capture
their attention.
   ``The hardest thing to do now is to sort of cut through all the
media clutter with a new show.''
   Sagansky's first task will be to consider a midseason schedule,
see which new series might replace fading ones, and generally ready
CBS for the February ratings ``sweeps.''
   That's one of four key periods of intense audience measurements
each year in all TV markets. Local stations use the results to set
advertising rates.
   After sweeps preparations, Sagansky starts inspecting series
pilots and other programs, preparing for his first fall campaign.
He also has the weak-rated ``The Pat Sajak Show'' in late night to
worry about.
   Despite the task facing Sagansky, his boss, CBS Broadcast Group
President Howard Stringer, is optimistic. ``We're feeling fairly
strong now,'' he said, but he won't forecast whether Sagansky can
help CBS avoid a third season as third in prime time ratings.
   ``I don't want to put labels on it,'' he said. ``I don't want to
put pressure on Jeff. The fact is that we preach patience more than
we practice it.''
   The TV division of Columbia Pictures _ Columbia owns Tri-Star _
makes network programming, including CBS' ``Designing Women'' and
``The Famous Teddy Z.'' But Stringer said no concessions or deals
for future series were made for Sagansky to be let out of his
Tri-Star contract, which had a year to run.
   In the course of negotiations with Columbia, he said, ``all
those ... who were new to Columbia began to find out how much
business we're doing, and the more they found that out the less
difficult it became.''
   Stringer called the talks ``an amicable series of discussions.
We were in a hurry, but they didn't have to be.''
   Sagansky cheerfully admits that many of his Hollywood friends
thought he had taken leave of his senses when he agreed to become
the third CBS Entertainment president in as many years.
   ``But it was certainly the biggest challenge that I'd ever been
offered, and I didn't want to run away from it,'' he said by phone
from his CBS office in Los Angeles. ``All my friends in the movie
business said, `Don't leave,' and all my friends in the television
business said, `This is exactly the job you should be doing.' So it
was sort of split.
   ``But yes, a lot of people thought I was nuts to do it.''
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Elsewhere in television...
   ANOTHER REASON TO ABSTAIN ON DEC. 31: Alf, the furry star of the
NBC sitcom bearing his name, will be among those joining Bryant
Gumbel on New Year's Day when ``Today'' reviews the '80s. Other
looking-back analysts include book critic Christopher Lehman-Haupt
and USA Today TV reporter Brian Donlon, who will discuss whatever
it is TV has been doing for the past 10 years.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Wed PMs, Dec. 20</NOTE>

</DOC>