<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1227EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Europe-Storm 2ndLd-Writethru a0496 12-18 0335</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Europe-Storm, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0496,0338</SECOND>
<HEAD>Toll From Atlantic Storm Climbs to 18 In France and Britain</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: New grafs 1-3 UPDATE death toll and weather situation. INSERT
graf after 7th, `Near the...' to add details. Pickup final graf, `In Britain...</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A wave swept a teen-age angler out to sea and
gusting high winds blew two cars into a head-on collision, killing
two people, to bring the weekend death toll from a savage tropical
storm to at least 18.
   Seven people were killed and 11 reported missing in France and
Britain over the weekend after the storm moved in with heavy rains,
lightning and wind blowing from the southwest Atlantic at speeds of
75 mph.
   Residents along French coastal areas areas had more rain and 62
mph gusts this morning, but the wind dropped later in the day and
forecasters predicted much milder winds Tuesday.
   Widespread damage was reported in western parts of the country,
with roofs torn off homes, trees and telephone lines toppled, and
structures knocked over by the gale-force winds.
   Two people died Sunday night on a highway near the northern
industrial city of Lille when a gust of wind pushed a car driven by
Laurent Dufour, 28, into the path of another vehicle carrying a
family of five.
   Dufour and Odile Denneulin, 15, died instantly. Denneulin's
parents and two siblings were injured.
   Near the Mediterranean Sea port of Toulon, an unidentified
teen-ager drowned Sunday when a huge wave swept him out to sea as
he fished from the shore. Three people near Paris died Sunday
afternoon when the storm pushed briefly into the capital.
   In Mauleon, 230 miles southwest of Paris, a 43-year-old man died
Saturday when a gust of wind knocked him off the roof of a shed he
was repairing.
   In Britain, the 35-foot fishing boat Destiny sank Saturday in
Scotland's Firth of Clyde, 750 feet from safe harbor, and all six
fishermen were believed lost in heavy seas and driving snow,
authorities said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>