<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0122 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1644EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-BushText 3rdAdd   12-21 0809</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Bush Text, 3rd Add,760</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHN: elected president.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   A: I would encourage as much as their constitution calls for.
But the election of Endara was, as you point out, so overwhelming,
the vote count so high, that I don't think anybody can suggest
somebody else might well have won that election.
   Q: But Mr. President, what I pointed out was that it was never
final and it was never verified. It was _
   A: Well, because it was aborted by this dictator Noriega,
``maximum leader'' _ so decreed three days ago, but he was acting
like maximum leader before that, thwarting, frustrating the will of
the Panamanian people. So, I think the international community that
oversaw those elections, including a former president of the United
States, felt that it went pretty well.
   Yeah, on the aisle.
   Q: Mr. President, if I can go back _
   A: Then Ellen.
   Q: _ to the question _
   A: Excuse me. You go ahead and then I got to go to Ellen.
   Q: If I can go back to the question of hostages, they say that
you anticipated Noriega might escape the initial assault, and so
there were plans to go after him. Where are your priorities, sir;
in getting Manuel Noriega or in dealing with the Americans who
might be held? Because if you get Noriega, the Americans may still
be held.
   A: And if we get Noriega, in quite a _ pretty much likelihood
they'll be released unless somebody wants to use a held American as
a ticket to get out of town. So we're doing both. We are
concentrating every way we possibly can to find Noriega, and that
is not drawing down _ here is my answer, it is not drawing down on
the assets that we have available to safeguard the lives of
Americans. They are not mutually exclusive.
   Ellen?
   Q: Sir, why is it that tens of thousands of American fighting
men, and with all of our intelligence, we are still _
   A: Ellen.
   Q: _ unable to catch one bad guy from Panama?
   A: Because intelligence is imperfect, Ellen.
   Q: And sir, did we _ did we make an effort _
   A: It's good, sometimes it's certain _ counting numbers, very
sure. Intention of a person to be someplace or move, very
difficult, but it's still sophisticated. I am convinced we've got
the best, but that's why, it is imperfect.
   Q: A follow-up, sir? Had you made an effort prior to the
invasion to go down and capture General Noreiga?
   A: Have I? No, I've been right here on the job (Scattered
laughter).
   Yeah?
   Q: Had the administration, sir? Had our people, had Americans
made an effort to do so?
   A: Have _ was there some operation, you mean? Not that I know of.
   Yeah, in the middle?
   Q: What was the _
   A: I was thinking of the lady next to you, but go ahead and then
we'll go again.
   Q: What led you to approve _
   A: You're next, you're next.
   Q: What led you to approve of the decision to have a bounty on
Noriega, and is this the type of thing that we will be doing in the
future?
   A: His picture will be in every post office in town, that's the
way it works, he is a fugitive drug dealer and we want to see him
brought to justice. And if that helps, if there is some incentive
for some Panamanian to turn him in, that's a very _ a million bucks
that I would be very happy to sign the check for.
   Yes?
   Q: Yeah, I was going to ask you about Panama and the Panamanians
who have suffered mightily as a result of all of this, not only
because of the sanctions that we have imposed for a long time, but
the military action, the homes destroyed, the lives lost, and so
forth. Are you willing to make now a major commitment in terms of
aid to Panama to help rebuild what has been destroyed down there?
   A: Yes, I am willing to help the Panamanian people. We have
already ordered the lifting of sanctions, we are _ I am convinced
that as we open up economic channels they'll do a much better, the
standard of living will increase for all as we go forward with
investment. We have permitted now the reflagging, or the _ stop,
put it this way _ don't have to unflag their Panamanian vessels,
and there are other things that we can do. We've released escrowed
funds. We are trying to help Mr. Endara already with, you know,
operating funds to pay the workers and the people. And beyond that,
though, I think your question goes _ I think we will feel obligated
to try to help in every way possible.
   Yeah?
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>