<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0121 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 2222EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Czechoslovakia 2ndLd-Writethru   12-30 0625</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Czechoslovakia, 2nd Ld-Writethru,a0588,0643</SECOND>
<HEAD>Havel Pays Tribute to Political Prisoners</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf, `The playwright...' with 1 graf to restore dropped
words. Pick up 3rd pvs, `He also...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SYDNEY RUBIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vaclav Havel toured his vast
presidential home on Saturday and placed flowers at the statue of
St. Wenceslas to honor political prisoners who fought for change.
   The playwright who spent five years in prison for dissident
activities used his first full day as the country's first
non-Communist president in 48 years to pay tribute to the
casualties of the movement he helped lead.
   He also met with President Mario Soares of Portugal, also a
former political prisoner and the first head of state to visit the
new president.
   Havel and Premier Marian Calfa appointed a non-Communist
interior minister. Government television said the appointee,
Richard Sacher, is a member of the People's Party, which was once
allied with the Communist Party but has become increasingly
independent in the wake of the country's peaceful revolution.
   The new president toured the medieval Hradcany Castle, where the
presidential office and residence overlooks the city.
   ``Havel took stock of the premises with which he is not very
well acquainted,'' said Michael Zantovsky, a spokesman for the
group Civic Forum, which led the revolution.
   Havel met for the first time with some members of the staff, who
just a few weeks ago were employed by Gustav Husak, the hard-line
Communist president. Husak served 21 years and was ousted Dec. 10
by the pro-democracy revolution.
   Havel has said he will serve as Czechoslovakia's ninth president
only until April, when the first free elections in four decades are
to be held.
   Havel was accompanied to the statue of Bohemia's patron saint by
Soares, who was jailed for battling a right-wing government.
   Soares, recognized by the United Nations for his human rights
work, returned to Lisbon after the 1974 revolution overturned
Portugal's 48-year-old regime.
   ``Havel and Soares wanted to remember the last five weeks in
Czecholovakia and to express their solidarity with students and
others who have been beaten or harassed and who were working for a
day such as this,'' said student leader Simon Panek, who attended
the brief ceremony under gray winter skies.
   Soares arrived in Czechoslovakia on Wednesday on an informal
visit to last several days.
   Later, Havel held a brief informal meeting with his new reform
government at the Vikarka Pub inside the walls of the castle,
according to a friend of the president's who asked not to be
identified.
   Havel was unanimously elected Friday by the Communist-dominated
Parliament. By early evening, Prague's beautiful streets were
filled with people celebrating their victory over the Communist
regime. The party lasted until early Saturday. Thousands danced in
the cobbled streets to the strains of Bohemian violins or electric
guitars.
   Men in feathered Moravian hats toasted Havel's health with mugs
of Pilsner beer under a giant Christmas tree in the center of the
square.
   At a nearby bar, several men identifying themselves as former
Husak bodyguards gave away bullets.
   ``We don't have guns anymore, but we have a few bullets left,''
said one burly man.
   Pope John Paul II on Saturday offered congratulations to
Czechoslovakia's new leaders.
   In a telegram to Czechoslovakia's Roman Catholic primate,
Cardinal Frantisek Tomasek, the pope hailed the ``great and
significant moments in the life of your noble republic.''
   He expressed hope the election of Havel as president and
Alexander Dubcek as chairman of the legislature marks ``a decisive
step toward peace and prosperity in freedom and in the path of (the
country's) ancient Christian traditions.''
   Dubcek was the Communist Party chief who was ousted after he
instituted liberal reforms that were crushed by a military invasion
in 1968.
</TEXT>

</DOC>