<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0185 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2207EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BusCrashTrial     12-18 0552</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bus Crash Trial,0571</SECOND>
<HEAD>Witness Says Driver Ordered Drink Before Church Bus Crash</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHARLES WOLFE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CARROLLTON, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A witness, testifying Monday in the
murder trial of a driver whose collision with a church bus killed
27 people, said the man asked for a drink and ``drank it straight
down'' shortly before the crash.
   Kelly Osborne's testimony for the prosecution ``blew away'' the
argument by defendant Larry Mahoney's attorneys that Mahoney was
tricked into getting drunk, said Special Prosecutor Paul Richwalsky.
   Osborne was one of several rebuttal witnesses presented by the
prosecution after the defense rested its case Monday.
   Mahoney, 36, is accused of causing the nation's worst
drunken-driving accident the night of May 14, 1988, as he drove his
pickup truck on the wrong side of Interstate 71, five miles south
of Carrollton.
   The defense contends that Mahoney, thinking he had been handed a
glass of water, was duped into swigging from a tumbler of Osborne's
vodka the night of the crash.
   But Osborne was adamant Monday that he prepared a vodka and
Sprite at Mahoney's request, using a plastic cup.
   ``He just picked up the cup ... and he just drank it straight
down,'' Osborne said. ``He coughed a couple of times. I figured it
was just because he had drank it so quick.''
   Osborne, a retiree from Cincinnati, said he met Mahoney by
chance at the home of Jay Gibson, Osborne's neighbor at a
campground outside Carrollton.
   Mahoney arrived in his pickup with Gibson and another friend.
All were drinking beer.
   Mahoney ``asked me if I had any beer. ... They was out,''
Osborne said.
   Osborne said he didn't have any beer, but offered to give
Mahoney a mixed drink from the dregs of a half-gallon vodka bottle
kept stashed in his truck.
   Mahoney's attorneys pointed out that Osborne mentioned beer but
said nothing about vodka in at least three statements to
investigators, the first on June 10, 1988.
   ``Here's a guy who, less than four weeks after the accident,
couldn't remember anything,'' said one of the attorneys, Jack
Hildebrand.
   Richwalsky countered that defense attorneys, after talking about
Osborne's alleged role at length during the trial, did not put him
on the stand because they knew his testimony would be damaging.
   Testimony by two other prosecution witnesses aimed at rebutting
defense claims the disaster was caused in part by an inherently
dangerous bus.
   William Boehly, director of statistics and analysis for the
National Highway Traffic Safety Administration, said buses are four
times safer than cars, based on accidents per miles traveled.
Boehly said there had never been a comparable disaster involving a
school bus.
   Hugh T. Spencer, a University of Louisville chemical engineering
professor, disputed defense testimony that smoke from the fire was
laced with cyanide caused by burning seat covers and cushions.
   Cyanide is flammable and was burned before having a chance to
poison any of the victims, Spencer said.
   The bus, a former school bus bought by the Radcliff First
Assembly of God church, was returning from a Cincinnati amusement
park at the time of the crash. Twenty-four children and three
adults died in the fire that followed the crash.
   Mahoney is charged with 27 counts of murder, 12 of assault, 42
of wanton endangerment and one count of drunken driving.
</TEXT>

</DOC>