<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0189 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1854EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SAC-Soviets     12-22 0524</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SAC-Soviets,0539</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Students View U.S. Nuclear Command Center</HEAD>
<HEAD>With Laserphoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM NOLAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>OFFUTT AIR FORCE BASE, Neb. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A small group of Soviet
teen-agers occupied the U.S. Air Force's nuclear command center on
Friday as the invited guests of the Strategic Air Command.
   The tour marked the first time Soviets have been allowed in
SAC's new $88 million underground command post. Air Force officials
could recall only one other time in SAC history that Soviets have
been allowed in its inner sanctum.
   ``It was all very interesting,'' said Andrei Berezin. ``I can't
see this in my country.''
   Lt. Gen Donald Aldridge, SAC vice commander in chief, welcomed
the Soviet students in Russian as the teens sat in the hardened
underground bunker that is used to direct U.S. nuclear forces.
   The recent thaw in east-west relations was evident as Brig. Gen.
Kenneth Keller briefed the students on the command post's
capabilities. There was no reference to nuclear weapons or their
potential targets in the Soviet Union.
   The briefing instead focused on the design of the command
center, Air Force weather forecasting and SAC's communications
system.
   The students spoke by radio with the Looking Glass aircraft, an
alternate command post that is kept airborne round-the-clock. They
also got a weather briefing in English and Russian from Eielson Air
Force Base, Alaska, the closest SAC installation to the Soviet
Union.
   ``These systems are in place to ensure that we preserve peace in
the world and we work very hard at that job,'' Keller told the
students.
   Peace was on the mind of Marina Ovechkina, who wore a peace sign
button on the tour. Miss Ovechkina said she always wears the button
and did not consider that it could attract attention at SAC
headquarters.
   Air Force officials cited time constraints and the spirit of
good will in deviating from their standard tour program, which
includes briefings on U.S. and Soviet military capability.
   ``This is a tour where the youths understand and we understand
that this is something that is in the best interest of all of us to
work these peace issues through,'' said Col. Larry Greer, a SAC
spokesman.
   The Strategic Air Command is the Air Force's long-range strike
force of manned bombers and intercontinental ballistic missiles.
Since 1961 it has maintained the airborne Looking Glass, which
would take control of U.S. nuclear forces if the president and
other leaders were killed.
   The students, aged 15-17, said they were impressed by the tour,
which also included a look at EC-135 Looking Glass aircraft, Offutt
dormitories and the base gymnasium.
   ``This is very interesting and when I come back home I will tell
my friends and parents about this,'' said Natalya Gudkova.
   But Tatjana Zabortseva said she was more impressed by the
manners of Nebraskans. ``In Omaha, people say `excuse me' and
`thank you.' That I like,'' Miss Zabortseva said.
   The students have been in the United States since Nov. 27 in an
exchange program with Omaha's Westside High School. They are
scheduled to leave Wednesday, and a group of Westside students is
to visit the Soviet Union in late March.
</TEXT>

</DOC>