<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0232 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1837EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f BC-BusinessHighlights     12-29 0829</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Business Highlights,0869</SECOND>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government said its chief barometer of
future economic activity edged up 0.1 percent in November, a tiny
increase seen by many analysts as evidence that growth in 1990 will
be modest at best.
   The Commerce Department said Friday the small rise in its Index
of Leading Economic Indicators followed a revised 0.3 percent
decline in October.
   For most of the year, the leading index has been flashing
signals that the U.S. economy was headed for a rather dramatic
slowdown in growth and analysts said the weak November showing did
not change that picture.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Workers feel increasingly insecure at their jobs
and are worried about layoffs in 1990, an informal call-in survey
sponsored by a job-counseling company found.
   About 600 of the 1,100 people who participated in the national
call-in were employed, and nearly half of that number, 44 percent,
felt 1990 would bring significant changes for them in the
workplace, the firm, Challenger, Gray &amp; Christmas, said Friday.
   The survey is not scientific because it was not a random
sampling of the population.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   United Airlines, Trans World Airlines and
Eastern Airlines said they were considering new surcharges on
tickets to help cover the skyrocketing cost of jet fuel.
   Other airlines also may be weighing the measure, which if
imposed would be the first special fuel surcharge by the airlines
since the 1970s oil crisis.
   A fuel surcharge likely would be figured into fares rather than
charged separately, analysts suggested Friday. They speculated the
airlines might charge around $3 per ticket.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Energy futures prices surged as a late rally
boosted heating oil to a six-year high on the New York Mercantile
Exchange.
   Heating oil for delivery in January, which had declined Thursday
after a two-week rise, jumped 5.47 cents Friday to finish at
$1.0187, helped by a wave of frenzied buying in the final 30
minutes of trading.
   The advances followed a string of sharp gains in recent weeks
due to severe cold and declining inventories.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prices received by farmers for raw products
averaged a record high in 1989, eclipsing the old 12-month mark set
five years ago, according to preliminary figures from the
Agriculture Department.
   Prices farmers got for raw products rose 0.7 percent from
November to December, leaving the monthly average 2.1 percent above
the level of December 1988, the department's Agricultural
Statistics Board said Friday.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The once-raucous takeover business ended the
1980s subdued and humbled as the value of corporate acquisitions
plunged more than 60 percent in the fourth quarter from the
stratospheric levels of a year earlier.
   There were 935 acquisitions valued at $72.2 billion announced
during the last quarter of 1989, Securities Data Corp., a financial
research firm, said Friday.
   A year earlier, when the merger business reached its zenith with
the record $24.53 billion buyout of RJR Nabisco Inc., there were
two fewer deals, 933, but the acquisitions totaled a record $183.1
billion.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Heck's Inc., unable to turn a profit
despite emerging from federal bankruptcy court protection, said it
would sell its retail operations, including 55 discount stores in
six states, to New York-based Jordache Enterprises Inc.
   Faced with mounting debts that totaled $9 million since
February, Heck's essentially decided to give away its retailers to
a subsidiary of Jordache which in return will assume the chain's
debts and longterm obligations, Heck's said Friday.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PERTH, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Australian brewing interests of Bond
Corp. Holdings Ltd. were placed in receivership by a state Supreme
Court after National Australia Bank Ltd., a major lender, requested
the action.
   The move cast further doubt on the future of the G. Heileman
Brewing Co., based in La Crosse, Wis. Alan Bond, who controls Bond
Corp. Holdings, purchased Heileman in 1987 for about $1.3 billion.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CAMDEN, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Campbell Soup Co. said it has completed its
search for a new chief executive officer but will not disclose its
choice until after New Year's.
   Campbell Chairman Robert J. Vlasic said Friday the board of
directors' first choice has accepted an offer to succeed R. Gordon
McGovern, who retired in November as president and chief executive
officer of the food-products company.
   Three members of the Campbell family, which controls about 59
percent of the company's 129.6 million outstanding common shares,
said Thursday they would sell their 17 percent stake and urge a
sale of the entire company.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The stock market closed out a decade of dramatic gains with a
broad advance Friday. The Dow Jones industrial average rose 20.90
to 2,753.20, extending its gain for the week to 41.81 points.
   The dollar closed higher in light dealings.
   Bond prices fell in light trading.
   Energy futures surged, orange juice futures rose dramatically,
precious metals advanced, grains and soybeans were mixed, and
livestock and meat futures were mixed.
</TEXT>

</DOC>