<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0120 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 2006EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Iran     12-26 0727</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Iran,0749</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iran Tries to Undo Its Warm Welcome of Ceausescu</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NEIL MacFARQUHAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iran recognized Romania's new government
Tuesday and lawmakers demanded to know why Nicolae Ceausescu was
warmly welcomed to the Tehran just days before he was deposed and
executed, Iranian media reported.
   Tehran Radio, monitored in Nicosia, said the Foreign Ministry
announced recognition of the provisional government in Bucharest.
   ``Iran's Foreign Ministry is certain that the two nations' ties
will continue, and that after the establishment of the popular
government in Romania, these relations will expand,'' the statement
said.
   The ministry also informed the Romanian ambassador in Tehran
that Iran's Red Crescent Society, the Moslem equivalent of the Red
Cross, is ready to send medical aid to Bucharest to help people
wounded in the fighting that toppled Ceausescu, the radio reported.
   The Islamic Republic News Agency, monitored in Nicosia, said the
Majlis, or parliament, summoned Foreign Minister Ali Akbar Velayati
to explain Ceausescu's official visit to Tehran from Dec. 18-20.
   Ceausescu was deposed by a popular uprising on Friday. He and
his wife, Elena, were executed Monday after they were found guilty
during a secret military trial of genocide and other ``grave
crimes'' during his 24-year rule.
   Ceausescu left for Iran in the midst of huge protests against
his rule. His security forces fired on demonstrators, reportedly
killing thousands. On Friday, the army turned against him, and
Ceausescu was forced to flee his palace.
   The Islamic Republic News Agency said the issue of Ceausescu's
visit was ``snowballing as the biggest goof of the Iranian Foreign
Ministry.''
   The government appears increasingly embarrassed by its embrace
of Ceausescu, who also had close ties with China. China on Tuesday,
seeking to avoid any comparisons to its own crackdown on protesters
in June, succeeded in blocking debate on Romania by the U.N.
Security Council in New York.
   The Iranian news agency said 45 deputies in the 270-seat Majlis
demanded that Velayati appear.
   The Majlis Foreign Relations Committee, which met with Velayati
a day earlier, said Tuesday that his answers to their questions
``were not satisfactory enough.''
   No details of the exchange were provided, but the Majlis and
Velayati sit in opposing political camps in Iran. The Majlis is
dominated by hard-liners of the Islamic revolution opposed to
opening Iran to foreign investment and other pragmatic measures
that Velayati supports.
   IRNA said in an earlier report that Velayati ordered Iran's
ambassador to Bucharest, Mohammad Jamshid Gowhari, be fired.
   IRNA said the dismissal ``was due to Gowhari's failure to
furnish the foreign ministry with a comprehensive report on the
internal situation in Romania'' before Ceausescu's visit.
   Gowhari was dismissed only three months before he was due to
return to Tehran, IRNA reported.
   Ceausescu was given a red carpet welcome in Tehran. Romania was
Iran's second-biggest trading partner in Eastern Europe and during
Ceausescu's visit he signed an agreement to buy 1 million barrels
of oil and 1 billion cubic meters of gas a year.
   He met President Hashemi Rafsanjani, who termed Ceausescu's
visit ``successful'' and noted that the grounds for economic
cooperation were ``completely fertile.''
   After Ceausescu left and reports from Romania illustrated the
brutality of his regime, Iranian newspapers demanded an official
explanation why the Romanian leader had been allowed to visit
Tehran.
   Velayati responded Sunday by saying the visit had been arranged
after frequent requests from Bucharest. But he stressed that
Iranian leaders repeatedly advised Ceausescu to ``bow to his
people's demands'' while he was in Tehran.
   Iran also has denied European reports that Iranians were
fighting alongside Ceausescu's security police against rebel forces
and that Ceausescu had stashed a fortune in gold in Tehran banks.
   During Ceausescu's visit, IRNA praised Romania as ``the sole
East European country rigidly adhering to its past government,'' a
reference to the reform movements that have changed Poland,
Hungary, Czechoslovakia, Bulgaria and East Germany.
   Iran's state-run television network lauded Ceausescu while he
was in Tehran. This week, it broadcast commentaries criticizing his
rule.
   IRNA claimed Tuesday that Ceausescu ``received a cold welcome''
and said that Iran's spiritual leader, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei,
``called off a scheduled meeting with him.''
   The agency also said that while Ceausescu was in Tehran,
``protests were made'' in the Iranian parliament about the visit.
None of the reported protests were mentioned by Iran's
state-controlled media while Ceausescu was in Tehran.
</TEXT>

</DOC>