<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1152EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Romania 6thLd-Writethru a0503 12-26 1151</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania, 6th Ld - Writethru, a0503,1179</SECOND>
<HEAD>Videotape Shows Bodies Of Ceausescu And Wife After Execution</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 14 grafs to UPDATE with TV showing torture chamber,
report 60,000 killed during Ceausescu's rule; picks up 11th graf pvs, `This
morning ...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY5,TOK4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DUSAN STOJANOVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Government TV today showed the bodies
of former President Nicolae Ceausescu and his wife after they were
executed by a firing squad, and Romanians rejoiced at evidence of
the Communist dictator's death.
   Television also showed a former torture chamber run by his
dreaded secret police in the western city of Timisoara. It said
more then 12,000 protesters were killed by the police after the
unrest that sparked a popular revolt.
   The new provisional government today appointed its leader, Ion
Iliescu, as chairman of the 37-member governing council. The
government also named a prime minister.
   The videotape showed the Ceausescus' bullet-riddled bodies lying
against a wall after an earlier sequence of the couple in
captivity. A close-up showed Ceausescu lying with blood on the
right side of his head.
   The actual shooting by firing squad was not shown, nor was its
location disclosed.
   Ceausescu, 71, and his wife, Elena, 72, were tried by a secret
military tribunal and executed Christmas Day for ``genocide'' and
other crimes. They were captured Saturday, a day after a popular
uprising forced them from power.
   ``We are people carried away by a very spontaneous process,''
Iliescu told French television. ``So there was a general demand
which pushed us to follow this process, first of all under the
pressure of the terrorist groups who wanted to free him.''
   The new prime minister, Petre Roman, told the network the
tribunal sentenced Ceausescu to death because officials had
information ``concerning possible attacks on the place where he
was.''
   By trying the couple, putting them to death swiftly and showing
the bodies, the revolutionary government apparently was trying to
persuade Ceausescu's ruthless security troops to surrender to the
army, which joined the people in revolt. Thousands have been killed
since the revolt began 11 days ago.
   The new government blamed Ceausescu for the deaths of 60,000
people. The death toll was for the whole of Ceausescu's 24-year
rule, said Romanian sources abroad and a correspondent for the
Yugoslv state Tanjug news agency.
   Reports have said as many as 80,000 died in the popular
uprising. Hundreds were reported tortured and buried in mass
graves, and thousands were killed in some of the fiercest street
battles since World War II.
   The military tribunal said the Ceausescus also were convicted of
undermining the nation and its economy and attempting to flee with
more than $1 billion plundered from the people and stashed in
foreign banks.
   The broadcast of the torture chamber showed ``calcinated bodies,
pieces of hairy scalps, blood and tortured bodies lying on the
floor. The victims were brought here naked,'' an unidentifed
commentator said.
   ``How small were Hitler's lackeys. They were genuine angels
(compared with the secret police),'' he said.
   This morning, an uneasy calm prevailed in Bucharest with no
shooting to be heard for the first time in days and, according to
the radio and Romanian sources, Ceausescu loyalist forces were
surrendering en masse.
   Power stations, factories, dairies and bakeries have resumed
production, the official news agency Agerpress said this morning.
   There was a brief celebration in downtown Bucharest, with cars
honking their horns, as government radio announced the appointment
of the new leaders, who included Dumitru Maziliu as vice chairman
of the governing council.
   It said the National Salvation Committee also issued a decree
appointing Roman prime minister until elections promised for early
next year. Romanian observers in the West said they did not know
who Roman was.
   Another decree, also signed by Iliescu, appointed Maj. Gen.
Nicolae Militaru minister of national defense. Iliescu, said to be
a close friend of Mikhail S. Gorbachev from school days in Moscow,
is a former senior Communist official whom Ceausescu demoted for
speaking out against the dictator.
   Sporadic fighting in central Bucharest had continued late into
Monday night, driving many people from the streets by the time the
executions were announced.
   TV footage showed Ceausescu being helped out of an armored
vehicle by a soldier, then submitting to a blood pressure test.
   Unshaven, gaunt and visibly tired, Ceausescu smiled a few times
for the cameras and once patted the hand of his wife and
second-in-command, who sat forlornly, a beige fur-lined coat pulled
tight around her and her head swathed in a scarf.
   Romanians at the Intercontinental Hotel clustered eagerly around
a TV set as the footage appeared around 1:45 a.m., cheering and
even spitting at the television screen at their hated ex-rulers.
   ``Oh, what wonderful news. The anti-Christ died,'' an
unidentified Bucharest radio announcer exulted minutes after the
announcement was made.
   ``Today, we removed the most hideous tyrant who soiled with
blood the history of Romania,'' added another unidentified man on
radio hours later.
   Word of the execution came three days after the Ceausescus fled
Bucharest by helicopter, toppled by a popular revolt that began
Dec. 15 in the western city of Timisoara with unrest that led to a
massacre of anti-government protesters by security forces.
   Word of the execution, the first of a Communist leader in
Eastern Europe since Imre Nagy was hanged in 1958 for his part in
the 1956 uprising in Hungary, came without warning.
   Today, China and Iran _ which had maintained friendly ties with
Ceausescu's Romania _ joined other countries including the Soviet
Union, West Germany, Japan and the United States in recognizing the
new government. Romanian ambassadors in at least 27 countries also
declared their support.
   Food and medical supplies poured in from countries including
Czechoslovakia, Hungary and France, among the first nations to
recognize the new government.
   The National Salvation Committee has drawn together
ex-Communists, dissident intellectuals and the priest whose
threatened arrest sparked the revolt. It has pledged an end to
one-party rule and free elections by April.
   In Timisoara, local army commander Corneliu Vajda said 600
bodies of people slain by security forces had so far been found in
mass graves and estimated the total number of dead at 4,670, the
Austrian Press Agency reported, quoting Finnish journalist Marita
Vihervuori as its source.
   Unconfirmed reports of casualties have run as high as tens of
thousands. But Victor Ciobanu, health minister under Ceausescu and
now in opposition to him, said 500 people had died in Bucharest
alone over the past four days, with 2,000 wounded.
   A skittish calm that settled over much of Bucharest earlier
Monday was shattered Christmas night by a flurry of automatic
weapons and artillery fire.
   Heavy explosions boomed near the Intercontinental Hotel in
downtown Bucharest. Volleys of sniper fire were answered
immediately with staccato bursts of automatic weapons that drowned
out the Christmas carols playing for the first time in 42 years on
Romanian radio.
</TEXT>

</DOC>