<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1201EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Pope-Text     12-25 1148</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Pope-Text,1189</SECOND>
<HEAD>Text of Pope's Christmas Message</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-World Christmas, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VATICAN CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Vatican's official English translation
of the annual Christmas Day message ``Urbi et Orbi'' _ ``to the
city and to the world'' _ from Pope John Paul II:
   ``He gave power to become children of God'' (John 1:12). Today
is the Solemnity of Christmas. The eyes of our soul see the Child,
laid in the manger.
   The gaze of our faith rests upon the words of the Prologue of
John: ``To all who received him, he gave the power to become
children of God.''
   We bless you, Son of Man, who are the Eternal Word.
   Glory to the Father who has given You, his Only-Begotten, to us.
Glory to the Spirit, who proceeds from the Father and from You, O
Son of God.
   Glory to the ageless mystery, which embraces all things.
   In this night, that mystery has drawn close to mankind: it has
entered mankind's life and history. It has passed the threshold of
our human existence.
   The child wrapped in swaddling clothes and laid in a manger. The
helpless human child _ and at the same time, the power which
transcends all that man is, all that he can accomplish. For man
cannot become like God through his own efforts _ as history has
made clear, from the beginning.
   And yet, man can become like God through God's own power. This
power is in the Son, the eternal word, who ``became flesh and dwelt
among us'' (John 1:14).
   Today is the first day of his sojourn in our midst.
   ``He was in the world, and the world was made through him, yet
the world knew him not. He came to his own home, but his own people
received him not.
   ``But to all who received him, he gave power to beome children
of God; who were born ... of God'' (John 1:10-13).
   History continues on its way, countless men and women, nations,
peoples, languages, races, cultures, millions upon millions...yet
he is unique: laid now as a child in the manger (``there was no
room ... in the inn'') and later upon the cross. He, and none other.
   And then, risen _ He, and none other.
   How many have received him not? How many still receive him not?
How many know of him? How many do not?
   We would like to measure with human statistics, how far this
power reaches, the power which is in Him. Born, crucified, risen.
   We would like to know, humanly speaking, how many have become,
in him and through him, children of God _ children in the Son.
   But human measurements cannot fathom the mystery of God.
   They cannot fathom the gift of God's birth, present in the
history of mankind, present in the history of the world, at work in
human souls through the power of the spirit, the giver of life.
   ``All the ends of the earth have seen the victory of our God''
(Psalms 98:3).
   Yes. The shepherds of Bethlehem came, and they saw.
   Yes. The Wise Men from the East came, and they saw.
   And the aged Simeon and the prophetess Anna saw, in the Temple
at Jerusalem.
   Just how do the ends of the earth see You, O Word Incarnate?
   Because you are for everyone. The salvation of our God is for
everyone, and it comes through You.
   God ``desires all men to be saved and to come to the knowledge
of the truth'' (1 Tm 2:4).
   Truth is through you. And grace as well. You are the truth. You
are the Way and the life (cf. John 14:6). And even though your own
people received you not ... even though there was not room for you
at the inn ... in you God has received ... God has received each
one of us.
   In you, God has received us as well, the men and women of the
second millenium, now hastening to its end.
   He has not regarded our contradictions, our infidelities, our
inconsistencies.
   Indeed, he has sent You, his Word, to heal us of them. To tell
us that, by taking the road we are taking, we are racing towards
self-destruction.
   The world longs for peace: yet every day our brothers and
sisters are dying in the present conflicts, in Lebanon, in the Holy
Land, in Central America; they are dying in fratricidal struggles
for supremacy: racial, ideological, economic; they are dying
because of senseless and reckless courses of action.
   The world longs for reconciliation: yet every day thousands of
refugees are abandoned and rejected; ethnic and religious
minorities go neglected in their basic needs; whole groups are kept
on the margins of society in ever-growing isolation.
   The world longs for balance, both within and without: yet every
day the environment becomes more polluted for reasons of
self-interest or from lack of concern.
   The message of truth and grace which comes to us at Christmas
through You must touch each of us. That message is for us, because
You have come for us, You have become one of us. Make us receive
You, O eternal Word of the Father!
   May the world receive You. Awaken in hearts the rejection of all
barriers be they of race, ideology, or intolerance. Guide the
negotiations now under way for arms reduction and control.
   Strengthen all who strive for an end to the hostilities that
have continued for all too long in Africa and in Asia, so that the
peoples involved may regain their freedom and their rights through
frank and trusting dialogue.
   And may this old Europe of ours also receive You, O Word
Incarnate! Deep within her she carries the imprint of your Gospel,
from which she has derived her culture, her art, her concept of the
inviolable dignity of man.
   May this Europe open her doors and her heart to understand and
receive the anxieties, the fears and the problems of the Nations
which seek her help.
   May she respond with the strength and the generosity of her
Christan roots to this very special moment of history _ a true
Kairos of God's Providence _ which the world is now experiencing,
as if awakened from a nightmare and opened up to a better hope.
   In particular, bless at this hour, O Lord, the noble land of
Romania, which is celebrating this Christmas in fear and trembling,
with sorrow for the many human lives tragically lost and in the joy
of having taken once more the path of freedom.
   Brothers and Sisters present here. Brothers and Sisters,
listening to me by radio and television, on every continent.
   Come to the crib of the helpless child, who is the Power of God.
He is born for us. Come ... and you will see ... and you will be
received, for today there have been revealed God's goodness and His
love for mankind.
</TEXT>

</DOC>