<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0294 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1752EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-American-Eastern 1stLd-Writethru   12-20 0801</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-American-Eastern, 1st Ld-Writethru,0824</SECOND>
<HEAD>Crandall: American Airlines Deal In National Interest</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS new graf after 9th graf pvs ``American is ...'' to ADD
stock price. SUBS pvs grafs 15-16 ``Crandall said American's ...'' to explain
employee total. Edits final two grafs to conform.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAN SEWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   American Airlines chairman Robert L. Crandall said
Wednesday his deal to buy foreign routes and other assets of
Eastern Airlines should be approved by government regulators ``in
the national interest.''
   Failure to allow the deal would invite greater control of
international air travel by foreign carriers, Crandall said a press
conference called to discuss details of the $471 million purchase
announced Tuesday.
   The complex deal with Eastern parent Texas Air Corp. gives
American control of Eastern's prized Latin American routes and
would greatly enhance American's presence in foreign markets.
   The purchase is subject to review by the Justice and
Transportation departments and the U.S. Bankruptcy Court overseeing
Eastern's Chapter 11 reorganization.
   ``We think it benefits consumers, the citizens of Miami,
American's shareholders and employees ... (and) benefits every U.S.
citizen,'' Crandall said.
   Some U.S. officials, including Transportation Secretary Samuel
Skinner, have expressed qualms about whether international route
authorities, granted by governments, should be sold.
   Crandall said the deal gives Eastern needed cash as it
reorganizes into a carrier that is focusing on Atlanta and would
give the international routes to a carrier that can ``use them more
effectively.''
   Since foreign governments restrict the number of U.S. carriers
allowed to fly to their countries, Eastern's financial difficulties
presented American with ``a major opportunity'' to realize its
ambitions to become a major international carrier. American wants
to expand in the Pacific, he added, but Japan remains very
restrictive.
   ``American is a fast-growing company and we plan to continue
that expansion through the 1990s,'' Crandall said.
   The price of shares in American's parent AMR Corp. lost $1.25 to
$58.75 on the New York Stock Exchange Wednesday.
   The leader of Eastern's Machinists union, which began the
crippling March 4 strike that led to Eastern's filing for Chapter
11 bankruptcy five days later, said the proposed deal should be
rejected.
   ``Quite honestly, I don't look for this thing to get any quick
approval,'' Charles E. Bryan said. ``If there's any credibility
with Skinner and the Department of Justice people, I would highly
doubt that thing would be approved.''
   But, Bryan said, ``It seems that (Texas Air chairman) Frank
Lorenzo gets what he wants in Washington. He seems to have
Washington completely wired.''
   If government review results in approval of the deal, American
officials said, American's daily departures out of Miami will rise
from the current 41 to about 80 in the second half of 1990. The
increase would include 25 more daily domestic departures.
   Eastern, which says it is ``de-hubbing'' its home city, is
Miami's No. 1 carrier with 76 daily departures.
   Crandall said American's expansion in Miami will add about 2,000
jobs there. American plans to absorb some 2,600 to 2,700 employees
in the Latin American countries American will begin serving,
American officials said.
   American spokesman Ed Martelle said the total includes all
Eastern employees in those countries, employees of four South
American ground handling companies in which Eastern had interest,
and employees of the Texas Air computer reservations system, System
One.
   Peter Dolara, an American senior vice president, said American
would consider hiring some of the more than 2,000 Eastern pilots
who were told the carrier had no jobs for them when they ended
their strike last month. Dolara said, though, there was no
commitment to hiring any Eastern employees other than the ground
personnel already working for Eastern in the Latin countries.
   The deal increases American's Central and South American
destinations from one city in Venezuela to 20 in 15 countries. The
package also includes a London route and Eastern's unused authority
to fly from Miami to Madrid, Spain.
   Besides being the No. 1 domestic airline, American serves seven
Mexican destinations and about 20 in the Caribbean. It also has a
growing presence in Europe, where it has 5 percent of the market,
and the Pacific.
   The purchase includes gates at several U.S. airports currently
held by Eastern and sister carrier Continental Airlines, plus
Eastern facilities at U.S., Puerto Rican and South American
airports.
   As part of the agreement, Continental will drop a $1 billion
antitrust lawsuit against SABRE, the computer reservation system
owned by AMR. Crandall said American paid full value for the Texas
Air and Eastern assets, not extra money to settle the litigation.
   Texas Air said the deal would pump $349 million into Eastern.
Continental, which is selling the Miami-London route, will realize
$102.5 million. System One will net $19.5 million through the sale
of telecommunication and data-processing systems needed to service
the Latin American routes.
</TEXT>

</DOC>