<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0094 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1446EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     12-27 0590</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0614</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sylvester Stallone has sued an art broker for
$5 million, claiming she led him to pay millions of dollars more
than he should have for several artworks.
   The fraud and breach-of-contract suit, filed Tuesday, charges
that Barbara Guggenheim persuaded Stallone to pay $1.8 million for
a painting she told him was an excellent investment.
   After buying it sight unseen, the star of the ``Rocky'' and
``Rambo'' movies said he discovered that 25 percent to 30 percent
of it had been restored or retouched and that its previous owner
had tried for some time to sell it.
   Based on that painting, the suit charges, Stallone believes he
also paid too much for several other works bought through Ms.
Guggenheim.
   Ms. Guggenheim could not immediately be reached for comment.
There is no Los Angeles-area phone listing for her.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>HALLANDALE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Romanian gymnastics star Nadia
Comaneci and her companion, Constantin Panait, have been avoiding
family, fellow Romanians and even some people who want to help them.
   One of those who haven't heard from Nadia and Panait is Maria
Panait. When Constantin ran off with Nadia, he left his wife with
four young children and no money.
   ``I thought at least he would call for Christmas,'' she said
Tuesday, ``but no.''
   Sightings of the couple have been reported from all over.
   ``I heard West Palm Beach from one member of my congregation,''
said Father Traian Pedrescu, pastor of The Holy Trinity Romanian
Orthodox Church in neighboring Mirmar, a gathering place for many
of the estimated 5,000 Romanians in South Florida.
   ``But honestly, with what is happening now in our country, most
of them would say, `Who cares?'''
   Mike Jacki, executive director of the U.S. Gymnastics
Federation, expected to hear from Nadia. After her escape from
Romania last month, the federation received more than a dozen
offers for movies, books and appearances.
   ``And I'm almost willing to bet that to this day, she doesn't
know a thing about them,'' Jacki said. ``We could never reach her
to tell her, so we put it out through the media.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gov. Rose Mofford was released from the hospital
Wednesday, nine days after emergency surgery to remove her
gallbladder.
   Mrs. Mofford, 67, who checked into St. Joseph's Hospital and
Medical Center on Dec. 17, said as she left the hospital that she
was feeling good and ``anxious to get well.''
   Press secretary Vada Manager said Mrs. Mofford has been walking
around several times a day and doing some work from her hospital
bed.
   Mrs. Mofford's doctors want her to spend two to three weeks
recuperating at home before she returns to a full schedule at the
Capitol, Manager said.
   But he said she still plans to deliver her State of the State
message when the Legislature convenes Jan. 8.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LINCOLN, Neb. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Friends of Gov. Kay Orr are planning a
birthday party for her Jan. 5, but the celebration will be a little
more cozy than last year's.
   Some 3,000 people attended last year's party, held in a building
on the state fairgrounds. This year's will be at an indoor sports
complex at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln.
   ``It was 20 below and it got a little cold, that's why we moved
it this year,'' said Bill Orr, the governor's husband.
   The governor will be 51 on Jan. 2. Friends in all 93 counties
will bake birthday cakes. Admission is $10 per couple or $25 per
family.
</TEXT>

</DOC>