<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0220 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1335EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--BroadwayConductor Adv31-2Takes   12-18 0738</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Broadway Conductor, Adv 31-2 Takes,0759</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 31</HEAD>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<HEAD>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 5 b&amp;w photos.)</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Come take a ride on a New York subway with a
conductor who likes to entertain his passengers with funny
announcements at each station stop. Harry Nugent, the son of a
circus barker, says he wants o reassure the riders that they
haven't left civilization behind when they walk down the subway
stairs.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By RICK HAMPSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The No. 1 Broadway local is packed, but the
subway can't leave the station. It can't leave the station because
the train's doors can't close. The doors can't close because some
idiot is holding them open for a late arrival on the platform.
   This is bad enough, but the passengers must now brace for an
accompanying sonic assault _ the obligatory conductor's admonition
over the public address system, always delivered in harsh, loud New
Yawkese:
   ``STANCLEARADACLOSINDOORS.''
   But instead, this morning they are surprised to hear:
   ``Your heart's in the right place, but your foot isn't. If you
don't want to ride, just step onto the platform. You'll find it's
quite stationary.''
   This message is delivered not as a rebuke, but as a gentle
reminder, and the speaker's voice is smooth and soothing, like that
of a professional broadcaster from the old school.
   The impression _ and the hope _ that this will not be the usual
subway trip is confirmed at the next stop.
   ``This is Rector Street, well-positioned in the financial
district. Rub shoulders with the Stock Exchangers, but stand clear
of the closing doors. This is the No. 1 to Van Cortlandt Park.''
   The conductor is Harry Nugent, who has raised station-stop
announcements to an art and introduced a measure of civility into a
subterranean realm that could use it.
   Nugent, 60, is a pleasant man with a neat moustache and receding
hairline who manages to look natty in the standard blue Transit
Authority uniform and cap.
   Imaginative announcements break the tedium, he explains. But he
also wants passengers to feel they haven't left civilization merely
by walking down a flight of stairs.
   ``This is Franklin Street, TriBeCa in location, litigious in
concept and convenient to an eclectic collection of courthouses.
Franklin will be followed by Canal as we make our way to Van
Cortlandt Park.''
   How did a guy who talks like this get into subway conducting?
   Nugent says he spent 15 years at Look magazine ``basically as a
gofer with a nice office on the 16th floor.'' When the magazine
folded he became a conductor because, he says with a smile, ``I
didn't want to get out of communications.'' Then he adds: ``It was
a port in a storm.'' That was 17 years ago.
   ``Now we're entering 14th Street Station. If you think you'd
like to change into something else, you can slip into a 2 or a 3
train. Speaking of numbers, we're the 1 to Van Cortlandt Park.''
   Before leaving the train, a middle-aged man carrying a briefcase
walks up to Nugent and tells him, ``If the rest of the Transit
Authority was as competent as you, they'd have no problems.''
   A well-dressed woman asks Nugent for his name, which she writes
down in a notebook. She seems reluctant to get off at her stop.
   ``We're approaching 23rd Street, which puts its best foot
forward with the illustrious Chelsea Hotel. Its other foot isn't
bad either _ the Flatiron Building. The next stop we encounter will
be 28th Street.''
   Nugent says he began to embellish his announcements about eight
years ago, when the Transit Authority was trying to get conductors
to give passengers more information _ a process that was abetted by
the arrival of new trains with audible public address systems.
   Nugent had spent a lot of time between stops thinking about what
to say. ``At first I just wanted to break the hostility with a few
elegant announcements. But the point I'm at now is probably absurd.
Maybe I've been breathing too much steel dust down here.''
   ``Our stop is 28th Street, noted for its flora and fauna. It's
the site of the flower district and the fur district. Twenty-eighth
will be followed by 33rd. That's the way it is on the No. 1 local.''
   Perhaps the steel dust is taking effect.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>