<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0048EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Romania-Force Bjt   12-20 0557</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Force, Bjt,0574</SECOND>
<HEAD>Only Violence Can Bring Down Ceausescu</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIOREL URMA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In contrast to the largely peaceful
changes in other Eastern European countries, President Nicolae
Ceausescu of Romania appears determined to use force to defend his
hard-line regime.
   Ceausescu, 71, the most senior Soviet bloc leader after 24 years
in power, has said reform-minded Communists elsewhere have betrayed
their people by refusing to defend Marxist orthodoxy.
   Ceausescu's refusal to embrace change has isolated him from all
his Warsaw Pact allies. Some analysts say he is seeking stronger
ties with rigid Communist systems similarly opposed to political
reform, particularly North Korea, Cuba and China.
   His leadership is based on a family dynasty with some 40
relatives reportedly placed in key state and party jobs. His wife
Elena, virtual second-in-command in Romania, is a Politburo member
and first vice premier.
   One of Ceausescu's brothers, Ilie, is an army general and deputy
defense minister. Another brother, Nicolae Andruta, is a police
general and deputy interior minister and another brother, Ion, is
in charge of economic planning.
   His youngest son, Nicu, 39, is a Politburo candidate member and
party chief of Sibiu region in southern Transylvania.
   ``Romania is a showcase for any repressive totalitarian state.
The harsher the repression, the more violent the public upheaval it
brings about and the greater the desire to take revenge on
leaders,'' Ion Ratiu, chairman of the London-based World Union of
Free Romanians, said Monday.
   Since he became party leader in 1965, Ceausescu has exercised
absolute power and carried out a foreign policy independent of the
Soviet Union.
   While that maverick stance won him praise and credits from the
West, Ceausescu kept Romanians under iron-fisted control. Now, with
reform ascendent in the rest of the Warsaw Pact, the harsh Romanian
stand draws condemnation from abroad.
   About 30,000 coal miners went on strike in the Jiu Valley in
1977 and 10,000 workers demonstrated in the city of Brasov in 1987
demanding freedom, better living conditions and Ceausescu's ouster.
Police arrested hundreds of demonstrators and their leaders
disappeared.
   An extensive secret police force keeps strict control on
religious and political expression, and dissent is quickly crushed,
making chances for peaceful change in Romania seem remote.
   But poverty and despair engendered by economic problems and
political repressions could cause people to risk direct
confrontations with armed forces, as in Timisoara now.
   Unlike recent protests in Prague and East Germany, witnessed and
reported by the Western media, demonstrations in Romania have taken
place well outside the public eye.
   The Western reporters permitted into the country in recent years
have been kept under close watch, and police have detained
journalists and even diplomats attempting to visit the country's
few dissidents.
   Romania has closed its borders and barred most foreigners from
entering the country in an apparent attempt to prevent the spread
of news about the Timisoara protest, the largest demonstration
against Ceausescu's policies since the Brasov riots.
   Romania has little tradition of democratic rule. After five
centuries under the Ottoman Turks, Romania won independence in
1877, becoming first a monarchy, then, during the Second World War,
an ally of the Nazis.
   The last monarch, King Michael, was forced to abdicate in
December 1947 under threat of civil war and pressure from the
Kremlin and its Romanian Communist allies.
</TEXT>

</DOC>