<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0237EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Gramm'sCandidates     12-20 0566</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Gramm's Candidates,560</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gramm's Involvement in Races Angering Democrats</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JENNIFER DIXON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Democrats are attacking Sen. Phil Gramm for
handpicking candidates to challenge Texas' Democratic congressmen
next year, but they say the senator's record of choosing Republican
losers gives them little to worry about.
   Calling those who complain ``wacko,'' Gramm says the Democrats
are running scared because ``1990 doesn't look like a good year for
them.''
   Gramm, a first-term Republican, is running for re-election next
year and is not believed to be currently facing a serious
challenge. His only announced opponent is Democratic state Sen.
Hugh Parmer, a former mayor of Fort Worth. The filing deadline is
Jan. 2.
   While Gramm's people say the senator is concentrating on his own
race, Howard Schloss, spokesman for the Democratic Congressional
Campaign Committee, claims Gramm has handpicked challengers to
Reps. Jim Chapman of Sulphur Springs, Greg Laughlin of West
Columbia and Bill Sarpalius of Amarillo.
   ``He's going into the district, handpicking the candidate,
forcing him down the throat of the local Republican Party, then the
candidate loses and everybody has hard feelings,'' Schloss says.
``He's being a real Lone Ranger, causing problems in his own
party.''
   Gramm intervened this summer in a special election to fill the
Fort Worth seat vacated by former House Speaker Jim Wright when he
released a name recognition poll conducted by Dr. Bob Lanier,
signaling to local Republicans they should rally behind the
physician.
   Lanier lost a close race to Democrat Pete Geren.
   In 1985, Gramm helped create a congressional opening by
recommending Democratic Rep. Sam B. Hall Jr. for a federal
judgeship. Gramm backed Republican candidate Edd Hargett, who lost
the election despite outspending Chapman 3-1.
   Gramm, however, says he's not handpicking candidates, merely
talking to people who are interested in running for office. State
GOP Chairman Fred Meyer and Gary Koops, a spokesman for the
National Republican Congressional Committee, agree and say the
senator is a tireless worker for the party.
   ``I've talked to 200 people about running for governor,
lieutenant governor, attorney general, Congress, state Senate,
state representative, county commission, county sheriff. People who
are interested in running for office talk to me,'' Gramm said.
   But several Texas Democrats say Gramm's intervention damages the
congressional delegation's bipartisan unity.
   ``It creates schisms and divisions that we don't need, as well
as bitterness _ there's no way better way to alienate a person than
to go out and solicit someone to run against him. It's one of the
most personally offensive things anybody could possible do,''
Wright says. ``I wish he would reconsider and consider the effect
on the delegation.''
   Countered Gramm: ``Wright was elected running against a
long-time entrenched incumbent. Did that tear up the delegation? I
think what's happening is that the Democrats are getting scared.''
   With the delegation's clout at low ebb from Wright's resignation
and other setbacks, Democratic Rep. John Bryant says Gramm's
interference is particularly unwelcome as Texans fight to preserve
federal funding for several state projects.
   ``It's very difficult to work with a guy who spends all of his
time trying to create political problems for you,'' Bryant says.
``He does it every two years _ the opponents he recruits always
lose, but it creates an enormous amount of ill-will in the
congressional delegation. He's hard to work with anyway, a
shameless headline seeker, and this just makes it worse.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>