<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 2358EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Koch'sFarewell     12-25 1068</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Koch's Farewell,1102</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hizzoner Leaves Center Stage, or Does He?</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Tuesday AMs report.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ If New Year's Day seems strangely muted next
week, it may be because an American original is leaving the stage.
David Dinkins becomes New York's first black mayor. But it is
departing Ed Koch who stretched another kind of color line to the
outer limit.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>

</TEXT>
<NOTE>By SAUL PETT</NOTE>
<NOTE>AP Special Correspondent</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   He goes as he came, possibly the most
effervescent politician of the dying decade.
   To effervesce, Mr. Webster says, is to ``bubble and hiss.'' If
anything, the unretiring retiring mayor of New York now leaves
office after 12 noisy years with more bubble than hiss.
   ``God has been very nice to me,'' Ed Koch concludes, without
suggesting that God ever got a single word in edgewise.
   American leaders cross the bridge from power to private life in
a variety of moods. Ulysses S. Grant worried about money. William
Howard Taft felt like a ``giant locomotive suddenly pulling a toy
train.'' Herbert Hoover and Jimmy Carter felt dejected and rejected.
   Ed Koch was also rejected by the voters but not _ never _ by Ed
Koch. He sounds like the happiest lame duck in the pond.
   He says he no longer feels like Sisyphus of Greek mythology,
trying every day to push a huge boulder up a mountain and every
day, near the top, watching it roll back down.
   ``But now, now I'm crossing over into the promised land!'' he
says, arms akimbo, grinning to his ears, little brown eyes dancing,
bald pate dazzling in the reflected light of a new dawn.
   ``No more decisions. I don't have to alienate anybody. Suddenly
I'm popular again. Maybe it's nostalgia, maybe revisionism is
setting in early. But even the columnists who reviled me unfairly
are saying nice things.
   ``The job of mayor could shorten your life. God extended mine. I
came through that stroke two years ago with no diminution of
faculties. Mother Teresa prayed for my full recovery, and she is a
powerful person.
   ``I am a lucky man. I can sing and dance. I can walk and talk.''
   Encountering no resistance to that last verb, Koch said he was
looking forward to the practice of law, lecturing around the
country, teaching at New York University, writing a column for the
New York Post and doing TV and radio commentary. All in all, he is
expected to avoid the poverty line by about $500,000 a year.
   In a farewell interview with The Associated Press, Koch spoke
warmly of the New York police. During his tenure, he went to 50
police funerals and wept, and as his days in City Hall dwindled
down, he tried to visit every one of the city's police precincts
during shape-up to thank them and say goodbye.
   He told them his plans and offered to help anybody who thought
Koch could be of help as a private citizen. He had pictures taken
with them. Now and then a policeman stepped forward, made a little
sentimental speech and gave the departing mayor a present, like a
sweat shirt.
   Koch leaves a lovely, muted office in a corner of City Hall,
gently decorated with graceful paintings, comfortable furniture and
a restrained number of pictures taken with foreign dignitaries. The
room suggested little connection with the raucous world outside.
Here, the mayor received visitors in shirt sleeves and, usually, in
full gallop.
   The job of mayor of New York is often called the second toughest
in the country. Had this mayor ever thought of going for the
toughest?
   ``No.''
   Not even one teensy passing thought about becoming the first
Jewish president of the United States?
   ``No, no, no. It's never been part of my life's goals. I swear,
it never entered my mind that it was doable. Running for governor
(and losing) was foolish enough.''
   City Hall, he insists, was pinnacle enough, and he leaves ``on a
high,'' proud he was one of only three men to serve three terms,
confident of his place in history, feeling in no way a loser or
ignored. He says Fiorello La Guardia was New York's greatest mayor
but didn't become that in people's minds until years after he
served.
   As for his own record, ``I'm proud of bringing fiscal stability
back to the city, of returning a spirit people had lost when we
felt like beggars under (predecessors) Abe Beame and John Lindsay.
I gave people back a sense of themselves and a sense of humor and a
sense of getting things done.''
   He closes out 25 years of public service as district leader,
city councilman, member of Congress and mayor. Still, he does not
fear decompression leaving power and the march of great events. He
is particularly confident he will not have to fight back tears
leaving reporters.
   He says he took much unfair abuse from the media in the kind of
coverage that keeps good people from running for public office. He
particularly will not miss six columnists he doesn't name who, he
says, wrote with one voice like ``clones of each other.'' He said
they actually took part in political campaigns to defeat him.
   ``Because I'm such a powerful personality, I gave life back to
City Hall, made it relevant again. I exercised the power of an
office that had gone into eclipse. And so I was blamed if a sparrow
fell anywhere in the city.''
   Six large sparrows were convicted of corruption during Koch's
tenure. ``Each was like a dagger in my heart, and I'll never get
over it. In this respect, I think my administration was equal to
the best but we got the worst attacks from the press. In Lindsay's
time, the entire police force was corrupt. One of his commissioners
even sold a reservoir to organized crime.''
   Oh, yes, Koch is doing another book, which reminds him of the
time a Brooklyn rabbi was showing him around. There, the rabbi
pointed, is the biggest library on Jews in the world.
   Koch: Do you have my books?
   Rabbi: Which ones?
   Koch: ``Mayor,'' ``Politics'' and ``His Eminence and Hizzoner''
(written with Cardinal John O'Connor in alternating chapters).
   Rabbi: We'll take the first two.
   Koch: Why not the third?
   Rabbi: You know we can't have his book in our library.
   Koch: You could tell your people to read every other chapter.
</TEXT>

</DOC>