<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1311EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Sweden-Marriage     12-28 0366</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sweden-Marriage,0378</SECOND>
<HEAD>Swedish Couples Rushing to Walk Down Aisle</HEAD>
<DATELINE>STOCKHOLM, Sweden (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Live-in couples who have put off
marriage are rushing to wed before Jan. 1 because of a change in
the death-benefit law.
   Couples are flocking to churches and town halls to marry before
the new rules come into effect in the new year. At stake are
widow's pensions of up to $160 a month.
   ``We've performed 100 civil marriage ceremonies daily since
November. We've had to hire extra staff,'' Stockholm City Hall
official Anna Barrett said Thursday.
   Stockholm City Hall registrars used to perform about 12
marriages a week, and only on Fridays. Now they carry out six
weddings every 30 minutes, seven days a week. Couples chose between
three-minute or 20-second ceremonies.
   A clerk at the Two Hearts goldsmiths said gold rings were in
such demand that some couples had to get married without them.
``Some borrow our test-rings for the occasion and get their own
later,'' she said.
   At the Lutheran parish of Storkyrkan _ ``The Big Church'' _ in
the medieval part of Stockholm, Anna Ekstrom said more than 50
marriage ceremonies were performed this year, compared with 35 in
1988.
   Many Swedish couples prefer to live together in common-law, or
``sambo'' relationships. Cohabitation is socially accepted and
children in such families have virtually the same legal status as
children of married parents.
   ``Sambo'' is short for ``sammanboende,'' which means, ``people
living together.''
   Until now, women who took part in such relationships qualified
nearly automatically for supplementary pension benefits after their
partners died.
   Under the new rules, women who are under 45 years old and who
have children will not receive the same benefits unless they have
been legally married to their partners.
   Childless women in common-law relationships will continue to be
eligible for supplementary death benefits. But officials say many
childless couples, not fully understanding the new regulations, are
also rushing to get married.
   Maud Gardelius of the National Social Insurance Office said the
new benefits rules have made couples see the financial side of
romance.
   ``They discovered that they were not protected in the old
relationship. This change has put a spotlight on the situation,''
she said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>