<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0111 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1426EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Bush 4thLd-Writethru a0593 12-29 0942</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bush, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0593,900</SECOND>
<HEAD>White House Says Vatican Doing `Fine Job'</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Inserts 2 grafs on State Department rejection of Vatican comment
after 5th graf, The spokesman's</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM RAUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CORPUS CHRISTI, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The White House today sought to
make peace with the Vatican, asserting the Roman Catholic Church
was ``doing a fine job'' in its deliberations over the fate of
deposed Panamanian leader Manuel Antnio Noriega.
   It also said talks with church officials ``continue in a
positive vein'' and that no deadline had been set for resolving a
deadlock over Noriega's refuge in the Vatican's embassy in Panama
City.
   Presidential press secretary Marlin Fitzwater brushed aside the
Vatican's assertion that it had ``no obligation to turn over this
man to an occupying force'' and instead lavished praise on papal
authorities.
   ``It's a very difficult situation, very tense circumstances.
They are managing a difficult situation,'' Fitzwater told reporters
as President Bush continued to enjoy a hunting vacation on a ranch
near the south Texas community of Beeville.
   The spokesman's remarks were in contrast to earlier, more
assertive White House statements suggesting the United States was
forcefully pressing for Noriega's return to stand trial on
drug-trafficking charges in this country.
   While Fitzwater was soft-pedaling U.S.-Vatican tensions, State
Department deputy spokesman Richard Boucher in Washington took
issue with a church spokesman's description of the United States as
an occupying power.
   ``We are down there with the consent of the government of
Panama, the legitimately elected leaders of Panama. That means
we're not an occupying power,'' Boucher said.
   On another subject, Fitzwater said he had no information to
impart on a report in today's editions of The Washington Times that
Noreiga had been tipped off 48 hours in advance of last Wednesday's
U.S. invasion. However, the spokesman said, ``He had an extensive
intelligence operation.''
   In any event, Fitzwater said, ``it's history now.''
   Apparently attempting to sooth increasingly harsh exchanges
between the United States and the Vatican over Noriega, Fitzwater
told reporters: ``I think the Vatican is doing a fine job. We
appreciate their efforts.''
   The Vatican had flatly said it would not turn over Noriega _
holed up in the Vatican embassy since Christmas Eve _ to the United
States.
   In a written statement today, the White House said: ``Our
discussions with Vatican officials continue in a positive vein. We
appreciate the papal nuncio's efforts to resolve the current
situation. We remain hopeful for a resolution of the problem and
there are no fixed deadlines to be met.''
   Fitzwater said he did not know if U.S. troops ringing the
Vatican embassy would now stop bombarding the building with
nerve-rattling rock music.
   But he said the administration clearly did not want to encourage
or aggravate any further confrontation with the Vatican.
   ``This matter has to play out,'' he said. ``We can't predict how
long it will take. We'll just go calmly along ....''
   Fitzwater had said Thursday it was up to Vatican officials to
break the stalemate over Noriega's fate, ``and we leave it to them
to work this out as they see fit.''
   Fitzwater today made it clear the White House was attempting to
seek to play down the entire matter. ``There's just not much that
we can say or want to say while this is going on,'' he said.
   In fact, even getting information from Bush and Secretary of
State James Baker III from the secluded ranch about 60 miles
northwest of here was proving to be a chore for Fitzwater.
   ``I called this morning for a report _ but they were out
hunting,'' he confessed.
   Bush planned to head later today for his adopted hometown of
Houston. He was to stay there through New Year's Day _ with a side
trip Sunday to two military hospitals in San Antonio to visit U.S.
servicemen wounded in Panama.
   In Washington, meanwhile, the Justice Department acknowledged it
failed to follow its own guidelines for considering national
security problems when it brought drug charges against Noriega.
   ``It now appears that there was some rush to draw up the Noriega
indictment'' and guidelines requiring a review of national security
implications ``may not have been completely followed,'' spokesman
David Runkel told reporters.
   He added, however, ``We believe there is a strong case against
General Noriega and that case can be successfully brought to
trial.''
   Concerns about disclosure of secrets in the Noriega case have
arisen from reports that he worked closely with the CIA and the
Pentagon while he served as the head of Panama's military
intelligence service and after he became commander-in-chief in 1983.
   Fitzwater, briefing reporters here Thursday, said it is still
too early to discuss a reduction in the 26,000 U.S. forces
stationed in Panama, even though the U.S.-installed government of
President Guillermo Endara appears to be ``continuing to expand its
control.''
   ``We'd like to have a drawdown as soon as possible, but we can't
tell you exactly when,'' with U.S. military forces still ringing
the Vatican embassy, he said.
   Fitzwater said the United States is no longer willing to allow
Noriega to travel to a third country where he would be shielded
from drug-trafficking charges that await him in Florida _ even
though Noriega had been offered such a deal privately by the
administration as recently as October.
   ``We had to go in militarily, we have paid a price for this, and
our objective is that we want him returned to the United States for
prosecution,'' he said.
   ``The difference is, before, the offer was if he would go in
peace, save lives and bloodshed and so forth, and he chose not to
do that,'' the spokesman said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>