<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0244 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0842EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Sears     12-22 0655</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Sears,0677</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sears Forms ESOP, Faces Lawsuit Over Ads</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID DISHNEAU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sears, Roebuck and Co. is giving its employees a
bigger stake in the company, and is fighting accusations that its
new ``everyday low pricing'' policy is a fraud.
   The Chicago-based retailing and financial-services conglomerate
announced an $800 million employee stock ownership plan Thursday
that will increase its workers' share of Sears common stock to 21
percent from 15 percent and save the company money.
   But even as Sears trumpeted the benefits of the ESOP, its
retailing division was forced to defend its claims of lower retail
prices against the New York State Attorney General's contention
that prices at Sears stores are the same or higher than under old
pricing policies.
   ``We have a valuable reputation for trust and integrity with
American consumers and we intend to prove these malicious charges
are false,'' said Michael Bozic, chairman and chief executive
officer of the Sears Merchandise Group.
   The employee stock ownership plan will provide Sears with a
cheaper way to fund its profit-sharing program since it can deduct
from its taxes dividends paid on the ESOP shares, said Sears
spokesman Douglas Fairweather.
   The ESOP will buy the shares, totaling about 22 million at the
current stock price, on the open market over the next several
months with money loaned by the company.
   The loan will be repaid from dividends on the ESOP shares and
future contributions to the profit-sharing plan, Fairweather said.
   Sears stock was up 25 cents at $36.87{ at midday in New York
Stock Exchange trading.
   In a prepared statement, Sears Chairman Edward Brennan said the
``increased ownership of Sears shares reinforces our employees'
commitment to Sears' success.''
   About 280,000 of Sears' 520,000 employees will participate in
the ESOP, Fairweather said.
   Sears was one of the first U.S. companies to establish a
profit-sharing plan for employees, in 1916. Under that plan, the
company buys stock and distributes it to employees.
   Fairweather said that with the ESOP, ``we're buying 15 years
worth (of stock) in one fell swoop and putting it in a trust. It
doesn't really affect the employees participating in the
profit-sharing plan; it's just a different way to fund it.''
   With the ESOP, Sears joins a growing list of companies that have
created such plans for a variety of reasons.
   Employers hope that employees who are also shareholders will
work harder to make the company grow and increase the value of
their investment.
   In addition, some companies have created ESOPs as a takeover
defense, believing that employees would be less likely than other
shareholders to sell their stock to an uninvited suitor.
   Fairweather said the Sears ESOP is not a takeover defense,
although there has been speculation the company could become a
takeover target because its value if broken up and sold is higher
than its stock price indicates, according to stock analysts.
   In addition to its retailing operation, Sears owns the Dean
Witter Reynolds brokerage house, Allstate Insurance and the
Coldwell Banker real-estate company.
   The lawsuit filed in New York State Supreme Court in Buffalo
attacks Sears' new retailing strategy, which the company
implemented with much fanfare last spring in a bid to win back the
market share Sears has been steadily losing to discounters such as
K mart and Wal-Mart.
   Sears began a $90 million advertising campaign in March touting
its new pricing policy, which said customers would receive
substantial savings over Sears' old prices, New York State Attorney
General Robert Abrams said.
   Sears contended in a statement that Abrams' charges were
distorted, untrue and based on a skimpy investigation that sampled
only a few of the more than 100,000 items sold by the chain.
   The state asked the court to fine Sears, stop it from engaging
in such practices in the future and order restitution for consumers
``who were induced to buy items because of the fraudulent
advertising and sales practices.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>