<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0152 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1922EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Congress-Panama 1stLd-Writethru   12-21 0778</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Congress-Panama, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0661,650</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lawmakers Say Bring Combat Troops Back Soon; Police Work Could Last</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: ADDS 3 grafs to UPDATE with Obey comment on need for new elections
in Panama.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-US-Panama Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAWRENCE L. KNUTSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   American combat soldiers should be withdrawn
from Panama as quickly as possible, members of Congress said
Thursday, but one said some troops should remain as policemen and
could still be there ``on Christmas eve a year from now.''
   Rep. Les. Aspin, D-Wis., chairman of the House Armed Services
Committee, said the presence of U.S. soldiers may be required for
an indefinite period if the Panamanian Defense Forces are unable to
perform normal police functions and defend the new democratic
government.
   ``I think the chances are that there is going to be a need for
them to be there,'' Aspin said, adding that police and public
safety operations in Panama appeared to have broken down.
   Manuel Antonio Noriega's Panamanian Defense Forces performed
many police functions as well as military ones. Their headquarters
was the main target of the first U.S. assault.
   Aspin said of some U.S. troops: ``I do see a need for them to
stay. I would not be surprised to see them there on Christmas eve a
year from now.''
   He said that American combat troops were withdrawn from Grenada
two months after the U.S. intervention there but that military
police units were not removed until 18 months later.
   Other members of Congress said there is a pressing need to move
far faster in Panama.
   Rep. Frank McCloskey, D-Ind., a member of the House Armed
Services Committee, said ``the most negative situation'' would
exist if in 24 hours Noriega _ now a fugitive with a $1 million
reward offered for his capture _ was holding hostages, or if
fighting lasted beyond 24 to 48 hours.
   ``I'd say if we have any kind of significant ongoing hostilities
or ongoing hostage situation where Noriega has some leverage, it's
going to be an extremely tense time for the Americans,'' he said.
   Aspin agreed that a combination of an uncaptured Noriega, a
faltering government, attacks on Americans and sporadic sniper fire
could change positive perceptions of the U.S. action.
   ``You could have this thing turn real sour for George Bush real
quick,'' Aspin said.
   McCloskey said, ``I backed President Bush and the necessity to
make a military move on Noriega, given the violence against our own
military personnel and dependents. As in any situation things go
wrong in the implementation.
   ``I just hope they are supersensitive to concerns for civilian
casualties, both Americans and Panamanians,'' McCloskey said.
   Rep. Nicholas Mavroules, D-Mass, another committee member, said
there are several positive aspects in the present situation in
Panama.
   ``Noriega is not administering the affairs of the government of
Panama, that is the key factor,'' he said. ``I think Noriega's
input into the affairs of Panama is at an end.''
   ``If we can firm up the new government, make that government
secure, then the special forces have to come out of there,''
Mavroules said.
   He said that if U.S. forces remain _ and their stay is seen as
long-term or indefinite _ the governments of Latin America would be
``extremely upset to see any American military outside of the U.S.
bases.''
   ``That's why it's important they get out, and that they get out
just as quickly, just as soon as possible,'' Mavroules said.
   ``But I can't place any time limit on that,'' the congressman
said.
   Much congressional comment has been supportive of Bush's action
in sending thousands of troops against Noriega and his forces.
However, there has been criticism, too.
   Rep. Pat Schroeder, D-Colo., said, ``As much as we support
Tuesday's U.S. military action in Panama, we should remember ...
that Noriega himself is the toxic waste of a polluted Reagan-Bush
foreign policy.''
   ``Noriega was A-OK as long as he did our bidding and supported
assistance to the Contras in Nicaragua,'' she said. ``It didn't
matter if he murdered Panamanians or peddled cocaine.''
   Meanwhile, the chairman of a subcommittee that controls foreign
aid said the new government should call elections to revalidate its
popular support in the face of criticism that it is a
U.S.-installed regime.
   ``The new Panamanian government ... will have difficulty
establishing credibility throughout Latin America unless it
immediately announces that it regards itself as a temporary
government and will guarantee a new election next year,'' Rep.
David Obey, D-Wis., said in a letter to Bush.
   Elections would mute criticism and ``could create a much more
stable situation in Panama than would otherwise be the case,'' said
Obey, chairman of the House Appropriations foreign operations
subcommittee.
</TEXT>

</DOC>