<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0319EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Young 1stLd-Writethru a0721 12-30 0290</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Young, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0721,0296</SECOND>
<HEAD>Daisy Young, Mother of Andrew Young, Dies at Age 87</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 5th graf, `In addition ..., with 5 grafs background, detail,
quotes from Andrew Young; no pickup.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Daisy Fuller Young, mother of Mayor Andrew Young,
died Friday night. She was 87.
   Mrs. Young died at Crawford Long Hospital, said hospital
spokeswoman Tisha Burland. A statement released by Young's office
said Mrs. Young died of natural causes. Funeral arrangements were
pending.
   A retired schoolteacher, Mrs. Young recently relocated to
Atlanta from New Orleans. She was active in an Atlanta senior
citizens organization and led a fund-raising drive for programs for
the elderly in the city.
   She was the wife of Dr. Andrew J. Young Sr., who died in 1980.
   Young, who leaves office Tuesday, said his mother had a mild
case of the flu and a fever Thursday and had complained of
indigestion Friday. A doctor checked on her twice Friday, Young
said, and said she seemed OK.
   Young said his mother ``just slowly, gradually stopped breathing
in a very peaceful and beautiful way.''
   ``In a Christian family such as ours, you give thanks for 87
good years with a wonderful mother,'' Young said in a voice choked
with emotion.
   Mrs. Young was a graduate of Straight College, which later
merged with New Orleans University to form Dillard University. She
was on the board of trustees at Dillard.
   Mrs. Young worked as a schoolteacher in New Orleans and later
became office manager of her husband's dental practice, which was
operated in the family home.
   In addition to Mayor Young, a former ambassador to the United
Nations, Mrs. Young is survived by another son, Dr. Walter Young,
eight grandchildren and two great-grandchildren.
</TEXT>

</DOC>