<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0123 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1809EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-US     12-28 0632</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-US,0654</SECOND>
<HEAD>Troop Pullout from Panama by February Unlikely, U.S. Says</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOSEPH B. FRAZIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United States would like the
extra troops it sent here out by February but that is unlikely
because Panama's security forces must be rebuilt from scratch, a
senior U.S. Embassy official said Thursday.
   The official told a press briefing the newly formed security
forces are made up largely of officers and troops from Gen. Manuel
Antonio Noriega's old Panama Defense Forces and that adjustments
are being made province by province.
   ``We cannot get to that fully in one month,'' he said, speaking
on condition of anonymity.
   He said one change already was made in the southern city of Las
Tablas in Los Santos province.
   While people there were celebrating, he said, the zone military
commander told them to whoop it up all they wanted but to bear in
mind that the Americans were leaving _ and he was staying.
   The man was arrested and replaced, but this is the type of thing
that needs to be sorted out, the official said.
   ``It is no secret that the new government does not have a lot of
confidence in some of these people,'' he said.
   He said former officers who were exiled, arrested or retired
because Noriega didn't like them were called back to duty, but they
make up a small minority of the officer corps.
   He said no indication emerged of a guerrilla movement taking to
the hills following last week's U.S. military invasion that drove
Noriega from power. Should that happen, he said, the United States
_ not Panama _ probably would deal with it.
   The United States had 12,000 troops stationed in Panama and
14,000 more were brought in as reinforcements. The official said
authorities had hoped to be able to withdraw all the extra troops
by February.
   ``That's probably not meetable,'' he said
   He said one problem is that the strength of Noriega's
paramilitary ``Dignity Battalions'' is not known. He said the
battalions are ``still there to be turned back on again.''
   U.S. troops are convinced of Cuban troop involvement but no
evidence has surfaced, he reported.
   He said about 3,300 ``shooters'' were in the 16,000-strong
Defense Forces and about three-fourths of those have been accounted
for. The rest were in support or police roles, he said
   The official said he believes the new government is looking at
forming a security force at a lower level than a conventional army
but stronger than a police force. Also, there may be a move to
decentralize and move some functions to other agencies. Noriega had
consolidated all police-related functions within the Defense Forces
to keep better control.
   The AP reported Tuesday that U.S. military officials want to
establish a professional army but officials of President Guillermo
Endara's government fear an army would become a threat to
democracy. The armed forces ruled Panama the last 21 years.
   The U.S. official said a list exists of people sought by
Panamanian and American forces. Most were caught, but some are
believed to be in the Vatican Embassy and the Cuban Embassy
residence.
   Noriega's wife, Felicidad, is in the residence. She is not on
the wanted list, but investigators want to see if she came by all
she has legally, he said.
   He said former Finance Minister Orville Goodin, who holds
Panamanian and American citizenship, had $3 million in cash with
him when arrested.
   ``I think they just gave it back to the bank he took it from,''
the official said.
   He said the United States does not want to be seen as running a
puppet government in Panama.
   ``What we want to do is fix it right,'' he said. ``We sure don't
want to do this again.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>