<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1508EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Clan     12-23 0400</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Clan,0413</SECOND>
<HEAD>Marxist Dictator Created `Socialism in One Family'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIOREL URMA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Deposed Communist leader Nicolae
Ceausescu ran Romania with a tightly run clan that included an
estimated 40 members of his family in positions of power.
   Soon after he assumed power March 22, 1965, Ceausescu did what
other hard-line Communist leaders did to establish and cement
authority: he brought his own followers into the party's top
echelons.
   But his unlimited ambitions and mistrust of his minions prompted
him to place family members in lead positions.
   Ceausescu's wife, Elena, a Politburo member and first deputy
premier, was the second most powerful figure in both the party and
state hierarchy.
   One of his brothers, Ilie, was an army general and deputy
defense minister. Another brother, Nicolae Andruta, was a police
general and deputy interior minister.
   Another brother, Ion, was responsible for state economic
planning. Among other brothers, Marin was a diplomat and Florea an
editor with the Communist Party newspaper Scinteia.
   Ceausescu's brother-in-law, Vasile Barbulescu, was a party
secretary in charge of agriculture, and Gheorghe Petrescu, Elena's
brother, was in charge of the trade unions.
   Ceausescu's youngest son, Nicu, 39, was reportedly a womanizer
and a heavy drinker, reputed for his passion for Western sports
cars and hunting parties. He was linked romantically at one time to
Romanian gymnastics star Nadia Comaneci, who defected to the United
States on Nov. 28.
   Nicu, nicknamed the ``Crown Prince,'' was party secretary in the
Sibiu county in southern Transylvania, home to a powerful military
and security garrison.
   He was also known to have killed at least two people in traffic
accidents, when he ran through red lights.
   Nicu was known as a gambler, who at one time lost $1 million in
one night alone playing roulette in a Las Vegas casino, Romanian
officials said.
   Nicu's wife, Poliana, was chairwoman of the Pioneers' National
Council, the Romanian equivalent of the Boy Scouts and Girl Scouts.
   One of Ceausescu's other sons, Valentin, was a leading nuclear
researcher and his daughter, Zoia Elena, led the Institute of
Mathematics in Romania's capital.
   Scores of other more distant members of the clan occupied
positions in security, trade and agriculture.
   ``He was worse than Stalin, who wished to institute socialism in
one country. Ceausescu's slogan was socialism in just one family,''
said Romanian writer Dan Petrescu, a dissident writer.
</TEXT>

</DOC>