<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0163 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1338EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-Symposium-Soviet-East Adv31 1stLd-Writethru 12-27 1100</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Symposium-Soviet-East, Adv 31, 1st Ld-Writethru, b0613,1126</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 31, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WORLD SYMPOSIUM '90s: The Soviet East _ An Uncharted Course</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 24th graf ``The last rock ... anti-government demonstrators''
to update with Ceausescu's execution and increase in death toll from hundreds
to thousands.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN-THOR DAHLBURG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Soviet Union and its old East bloc allies
roared out of the 1980s on an incredible wave of reform that
shattered the very foundations of communism. They move now into the
1990s on an uncharted course of high hopes and deep concerns.
   One grim possibility came from Soviet journalist Alexander
Kabakov, writing in the monthly magazine Art of Film: It is the
mid-1990s and Mikhail S. Gorbachev's reforms have failed. The
Soviet Union has splintered into warring cantons. Famine grips the
land, and roaming gangs of thugs rule Moscow.
   His nightmare is no idle fancy for a people who have known
revolution, civil war and famine in this century. Again there is
widespread worry, disillusionment and lack of faith as the Soviet
Union, 72 years old, staggers into a new decade.
   In Eastern Europe, the Kremlin's allies are still aglow over the
contagious political reforms that toppled the region's last
hardline leader, Romania's Nicolae Ceausescu, in the final days of
the 1980s. But they are also girding for tough years ahead.
   ``Someone will have to tell Czechoslovaks they have to work
harder and earn less,'' warns the Czechoslovak economist Dusan
Triska.
   In Bulgaria, ``We can hardly point to a sub-branch and even a
single production which is competitive on free international
markets,'' says Premier Georgi Atanasov.
   A liberator of Eastern Europe who has also freed his own people
from decades of repression, the 58-year-old Gorbachev has failed to
deliver more tangible goods at home. As the 1990s dawn, and with
them the sixth year of Gorbachev's reign, there still are lines for
soap, matches, even sausage so foul it's called ``doggy delight.''
Many items aren't available at all.
   Communists no longer talk about burying capitalists; they want
to mimic them.
   ``Now we need your ideas. Now we need your lessons in
managing,'' Vitaly Korotich, editor in chief of Ogonyok magazine,
told Americans recently. Marxism hasn't adequately fed Soviets;
soon Big Mac will have a chance. Moscow's first McDonald's opens in
January.
   The 1990s pose history's greatest challenge for what was once
labeled ``the Soviet bloc.'' Erstwhile truths now discredited, Old
Guard leaders tossed in the trash bin of history, Eastern Europe
and the Soviet Union want to become smoothly functioning components
in the modern world economic order.
   But can they?
   Even in Hungary, a pioneer in implementing free-market
practices, managers still have little concept of profit-oriented
thinking, competition and labor productivity ``where you pay those
who work and fire those who don't,'' says U.S. Ambassador Mark
Palmer.
   The specter of hard times looms everywhere:
   Hungary's government is proposing an austerity program
foreseeing a 15 percent increase in consumer prices and a slash in
state subsidies.
   Czechoslovakia, which had Europe's No. 6 economy before World
War II, must undo 40 years of Communist under-investment and shoddy
maintenance of industry.
   ``We will have to abolish many insufficient factories and
gradually open to the international market,'' says economist
Miroslav Slouf, deputy mayor of Prague. ``Any newly elected
government will be unpopular within months.''
   Inflation tops 600 percent in Poland, and Poles donate the
family silver and money hidden under mattresses to a fund to help
the nation. Economists in Warsaw, their desks piled high with dire
forecasts, struggle to draft a reform blueprint that will encourage
Western help.
   The coming austerity could have high political costs.
   Shorn of their legally guaranteed grip on power in Hungary, East
Germany and Czechoslovakia, Communists are now condemned to share
power and even lose it. Their Bulgarian comrades, possibly the
Romanians, and finally the Soviets, are fated to follow.
   Politicians more responsive to voter demands will bring even
more unraveling in the old Soviet bloc. Communism, borne into East
Europe on the bayonets of the Red Army in World War II, already
must compete with other creeds, like Solidarity-style trade
unionism and Roman Catholicism in Poland. The Kremlin is sending
signals it will brook virtually any style of reform, as long as its
allies stay in the Warsaw Pact military alliance.
   The late Soviet dissident Andrei Amalric wrote a book, ``Will
the Soviet Union Survive Until 1984?'' It has, but enters the 1990s
riven by ethnic disputes that constitute the most violent menace
both to unity and Moscow's authority. This continent-sized land of
more than 100 nationalities is being unraveled by demands of
Azerbaijanis, Armenians, Georgians, Estonians, Latvians and others.
   In the 1990s Gorbachev's Kremlin must placate those
nationalities or see the multi-ethnic empire the Bolsheviks seized
from the czars disintegrate. So far, the Kremlin's efforts have
largely failed. Using more traditional tactics _ repression _ would
cost the Soviets much of the good will they have accumulated abroad
in the Gorbachev era.
   More than anything else, the next Soviet decade depends on one
man, Mikhail Sergeyevich Gorbachev, the stocky son of a southern
Russian peasant who is unquestionably one of the most gifted
political operators of the century. He may not be able to realize
his vision of a more modern, open, better working Soviet Union at
peace with the world. But it is impossible to imagine anyone else
doing it.
   The last rock of Stalinist stability in the Soviet bloc was
swept away by the reform tide on the eve of the 1990s, though not
without bloody resistance. Nicolae Ceausescu, 71, was driven from
power by a mass uprising of Romanians enraged that his security
forces had slain thousands of anti-government demonstrators.
Ceausescu and his wife, Elena, were executed on Christmas Day.
   That revolt, which lasted less than a week, was the final act in
a remarkable year that saw hardline leaders in Poland,
Czechoslovakia, East Germany and Bulgaria ousted by popular
pressure, street demonstrations and civic bravery.
   Still untouched, by all accounts, was Albania, which long ago
sealed itself up in a Stalinist mold apart from the world and now
is more alone than ever in a churning sea of change.
   But a joke making the rounds in Warsaw reflected a view of Poles
that the liberalization process they began is inevitable for all.
   The joke goes:
   Q. How long does it take to overthrow communism?
   A. Ten years in Poland, 10 weeks in East Germany, 10 days in
Czechoslovakia ... and 10 seconds in Romania.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Sunday, Dec. 31</NOTE>

</DOC>