<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0910EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Vatican-Noriega 1stLd-Writethru a0506 12-29 0526</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Vatican-Noriega, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0506,0537</SECOND>
<HEAD>Holy See Urging Noriega To Leave Embassy Refuge</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 11 grafs with Vatican spokesman warning of ``steps''
if U.S. disturbances continue outside its embassy in Panama, corrects that
nuncio was not searched; picks up 12th pvs, `Navarro was...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY BETH SHERIDAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VATICAN CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Vatican is urging Panamanian strongman
Manuel Antonio Noriega to leave his refuge at its embassy in Panama
City, a Holy See spokesman said today.
   The spokesman, Joaquin Navarro, also criticized U.S. activities
outside the Vatican embassy and said ``steps'' would be taken if
the disturbances continue. He did not elaborate.
   U.S. forces have staked out the mission and blasted rock music
from a stereo system in the street to try to put pressure on
Noriega to surrender to be prosecuted on U.S. drug trafficking
charges.
   ``The nuncio is doing his best to convince Gen. Noriega to
abandon the nunciature on his own, by himself,'' spokesman Joaquin
Navarro said. ``At the same time he cannot force Noriega to leave
nor can he consign him to U.S forces.''
   It was the first time the Vatican said publicly it was trying to
persuade Noriega to leave. However, Navarro said the possibility
had been discussed with Noriega since he took refuge at the mission
on Sunday.
   In what has appeared to be a standoff, the Vatican has insisted
that the papal nunciature, or embassy, cannot legally turn the
general over to U.S. forces since, under accepted international
procedures, an embassy is only empowered to deal with the
government of the host country.
   Navarro today said the Vatican still has not received a formal
request from the new Panamanian government to turn over Noriega.
   Navarro denounced U.S. ``interference'' in the embassy's
autonomy.
   ``An occupying power cannot interfere with the works of a
diplomatic mission nor can it demand that a person seeking asylum
in that mission be handed over to it,'' Navarro said.
   He was asked to comment on U.S. tactics, such as the searching
of the nuncio or the shooting out of street lights to blacken the
area at night in hopes of thwarting a possible undetected exiting
of Noriega.
   ``If this is going to continue, further steps will be taken'' by
the Vatican, the spokesman said, without giving details. He added,
however, that the Vatican was not in a ``clash'' with the United
States.
   Navarro was asked about Panamanian officials' statements that
the government of President Guillermo Endara has sent a letter to
the Vatican asking that Noriega be expelled from the embassy.
   ``We haven't got that letter,'' Navarro said. Asked how come, he
replied, ``I don't know, ask the post office, the telex'' office,
he said.
   The Vatican's top spokesman said there had been progress in
negotiations between the United States and the Holy See over
Noriega's fate.
   Asked for details, he replied, ``The positions are clearer.''
   On Wednesday, he estimated that the standoff would be resolved
to both sides' satisfaction within a few days.
   He said today he still expected the matter to be resolved in
days but that ``it could be 20, 30 or 40 days.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>