<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0423EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-HBOSuit     12-29 0431</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-HBO Suit,0441</SECOND>
<HEAD>Music Syndicate Sues HBO; Could Disrupt Schedule</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GARY LANGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The music syndicate BMI is suing Home Box Office
to bar the cable company from broadcasting BMI-copyrighted songs,
which are used in a number of movies HBO has scheduled to run.
   In a suit filed in U.S. District Court in Manhattan Thursday,
BMI asked that HBO be barred from transmitting the songs after
Sunday, when the companies' licensing agreement ends.
   Judge Vincent Broderick declined to issue an immediate bar,
scheduling fuller arguments before another judge, Pierre Leval, on
Tuesday.
   BMI, or Broadcast Music Inc., represents more than 100,000
composers and publishers of more than 1.5 million songs, collecting
a contracted fee whenever one of its songs is played. It licenses
radio and television stations, hotel and restaurant chains, even
discotheques.
   The suit comes amid efforts by BMI to boost its cable television
levies. Beyond raising basic rates, BMI wants to collect from local
cable systems as well as from cable programmers. It now charges
programmers alone.
   The suit said negotiations between BMI and HBO on a new contract
had been fruitless. Ahrold declined to say what HBO currently pays
BMI or how much more BMI wants.
   The suit listed 11 films in HBO's January schedule that include
BMI songs, including the Beatles' ``Helter Skelter'' in the movie
``U2 Rattle and Hum,'' the song ``Strangers in the Night'' in
``Fright Night'' and George Thorogood's ``Bad to the Bone,'' heard
in ``Talk Radio.''
   BMI has sued several other cable television programmers alleging
copyright infringement this year, but Thursday's suit was its first
seeking to prevent transmissions in advance, said BMI spokesman
Robbin Ahrold.
   BMI President Frances W. Preston said its rates for cable
television have been discounted while the industry developed, but
``must now be brought into line with the full value of the use of
the BMI repertoire.''
   Moreover, under BMI's reading of copyright law, ``License fees
must be paid by both the programmer and the local system operator,
each of whom receives revenues for the use of BMI's repertoire,''
she said.
   Ahrold likened the concept to a hotel piping radio music into
its halls: Both the radio station and the hotel must pay BMI, he
said.
   HBO, owned by Time-Warner Inc., has more than 23 million
subscribers, making it the largest pay-television service in the
nation, according to BMI's suit. HBO spokesman Jim Noonan said he
had not seen the suit and could not comment on it, but he said HBO
still was negotiating with BMI on a new contract.
</TEXT>

</DOC>