<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1225EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Punjab     12-17 0495</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Punjab,0511</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Main Sikh Parties Stay Away From Political Meeting on Punjab</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIJAY JOSHI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government Sunday held a meeting of
political parties to discuss Sikh separatism in Punjab but the two
main Sikh parties stayed away, demanding an investigation into
alleged human rights abuses.
   Prime Minister V.P. Singh presided over the meeting, his first
political initiative to address Sikh militants' demands for an
independent homeland in the northern farming state. More than 7,000
people have died in an 8-year-old separatist movement in the region.
   About 40 leaders from 21 parties attended the meeting, and they
later issued a statement that was endorsed by all but one of the
parties.
   ``While serious efforts to find a political solution continue,
the people must be reassured that there would be no letup in the
fight against terrorism,'' the statement said.
   Former Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi's Congress Party dissociated
itself from the statement, saying it could not be considered a
consensus document since Congress had no part in drafting it.
   Punjab's two main Sikh parties, the Akali Dal-Mann and Akali
Dal-Badal, boycotted the meeting. Before discussions can be held,
they said, tensions must be eased in the state and police must be
investigated for alleged human rights violations.
   Akali Dal-Mann Party, known to be supported by Sikh extremist
groups, won nine of the state's 13 parliamentary seats in last
month's general elections.
   The conference condemned the daily killings in Punjab but made
only one specific recommendation _ repealing a law that gives the
government broad powers to detain suspected extremists.
   The law was passed by Gandhi's government and officials at the
meeting said the recommendation to repeal the statute probably was
the reason the Congress Party refused to endorse the joint
statement.
   Congress issued a separate statement that said the government
asked the participants to reach a consensus without stating its own
position.
   Gandhi was forced to resign as prime minister after the party
failed to maintain a majority in Parliament following the general
elections.
   Singh took office on Dec. 2. He visited Sikhism's holiest
shrine, the Golden Temple, five days later but described the visit
as personal.
   Nonetheless, he was the first prime minister to visit the temple
in five years and the trip was seen as an astute move to assuage
Sikhs angered by an army raid on the shrine in June, 1984.
   The attack was ordered by Indira Gandhi, the former prime
minister's mother and predecessor, to flush out Sikh extremists
entrenched inside.
   She was assassinated four months later by two Sikh bodyguards.
Anti-Sikh riots ensued nationwide and more than 3,000 Sikhs were
killed.
   Militants say India's Hindu-dominated government discriminates
against Sikhs socially and culturally and wants an independent
homeland in Punjab.
   Sikhs are in a slight majority in the state, which borders
Pakistan. Nationwide they make up 2 percent of the 880 million
people, while Hindus make up 80 percent of the population.
</TEXT>

</DOC>