<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0108 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1256EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Panama-Analysis Bjt 990 12-22 1055</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Analysis, Bjt, 990</SECOND>
<HEAD>White House, Kremlin in Role Reversal</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WALTER R. MEARS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   There's something of a role reversal and, it
seems, a rule reversal as well in the way the Kremlin and the White
House are dealing with each other on the American intervention in
Panama.
   Their words and contacts point to an effort on both sides to
keep the episode from intruding on the thaw in East-West relations.
   The Soviet Union denounced the U.S. military move, calling it an
invasion and an act of aggression _ but adding to that predictable
response the observation that it will not necessarily become a
problem issue between Moscow and Washington.
   President Bush sent a personal message to Soviet President
Mikhail S. Gorbachev on the military action he ordered early
Wednesday against the Panamanian regime of Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noriega.
   He told a news conference Thursday that he needs to explain the
operation to Gorbachev more fully.
   ``It's not altogether surprising that he doesn't understand some
of the special arrangements the United States has in Panama,'' the
president said.
   Bush said he had responded to provocations that included the
killing of an unarmed American Marine, the brutalizing of American
citizens, the denial of office to a freely elected leader.
   Given all that, he said, his message would be:
   ``Then, Mr. Gorbachev, please understand, this president is
going to do something about it.
   ``So we have to explain,'' he said.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III said the critical Soviet
statements were not unexpected, and that the initial comments may
have been issued before the first Bush message reached Gorbachev.
   Not that it would have made much difference. American
intervention, whatever the cause or justification, is guaranteed to
produce critical reaction from Moscow, just as the United States
has assailed Soviet moves in Afghanistan and elsewhere.
Furthermore, Noriega has close ties with Cuba, the Soviets' Western
ally, and with the Marxist government of Nicaragua.
   ``The United States must immediately stop its armed intervention
in Panama,'' said Vadim P. Perfiliev, spokesman for the foreign
ministry in Moscow. A Tass commentary said the U.S. action
encroaches on the progress attained elsewhere in world affairs.
   But those comments were tempered by Perfiliev's observation that
superpower relations have moved beyond the point at which any such
episode, anywhere in the world, was deemed a matter of East-West
confrontation.
   The U.S. intervention comes as the Soviet Union watches barriers
fall and governments turn from Communist dominance toward democracy
and free market economic systems. Moscow once proclaimed a doctrine
of limited sovereignty for the satellite states, insisting on its
right to intervene against threats to their Communist regimes.
   Intervention to keep the satellites in line was a Moscow habit
during the height of the Cold War. It happened then in East
Germany, in Hungary, in Czechoslovakia, in Poland.
   Gorbachev turned away from that posture. Indeed, while the
Romanian government was trying to put down protests with force, the
Soviet president said Wednesday that changes in Eastern Europe
should come ``peacefully, without violating public order and the
rights of citizens.''
   Moscow has not resisted the freedom movements that have changed
the face of Eastern Europe, most dramatically with the dismantling
of the Berlin Wall, and on Friday with the overthrow of the
hard-line Communist government in Romania.
   Sen. Sam Nunn, D-Ga., chairman of the Senate Armed Services
Committee, noted the possible connection, saying it was unfortunate
that the United States ``was required to take these steps in Panama
at a time when we are urging restraint on the part of the Soviet
Union toward other nations and on the part of China toward the
democratic aspirations of its own people.''
   Baker said the Soviet Union is supporting democracy through its
forbearance, and argued the United States is doing so by doing the
opposite in Panama, by intervening.
   ``Let me say that I think both the United States and the Soviet
Union today are supporting democracy,'' Baker said at a first-day
briefing on U.S. intervention in Panama.
   ``The difference is that the Soviet Union supports democracy by
staying out of countries and thus permitting democracy to proceed.
In this one and very unique instance, the United States did it by
going in to assist a democratically elected government against a
dictator.''
   The Panama operation drew protests from most Latin American
capitals, even from governments hostile to Noriega. He may be
detested, but so is Yankee intervention.
   Mexico, for example, said Panamanian problems must be resolved
by the Panamanian people.
   But they tried, and Noriega wouldn't let it happen, which is the
Baker argument.
   Noriega reneged on this year's elections because he was losing,
and installed his proxies to govern. The Organization of American
States tried to talk him into yielding power to an elected
government; five times its emissaries went to Panama City on that
futile mission.
   Latin American states voted at the OAS on Friday for a
resolution assailing ``the military intervention in Panama,'' a
measure that gained something in the translation.
   The English language version expressed regret, the Spanish
translation deplored the operation.
   The OAS urged an immediate end to the fighting and said American
troops should be withdrawn. The vote was 20 to 1; only the U.S.
delegate voted no.
   The Latin protests were inevitable. And despite the easing of
East-West tensions, Soviet officials and commentators weren't about
to let Washington off the hook easily.
   Georgi Arbatov, a Soviet expert on U.S. affairs, called the
operation a return to gunboat diplomacy and said it could
strengthen hardliners opposed to arms reductions.
   He also said in an ABC-TV interview that Noriega is a problem
the United States created for itself, by training him and once
having him on the CIA payroll.
   For all of that, there remains the possibility that the Panama
precedent could be argued in connection with future Soviet
intervention, if it comes to that, in a place like Lithuania. That
Baltic state has been part of the Soviet Union since 1940; an
independence movement there is strong and gaining despite Kremlin
warnings that it will come to grief and great trouble.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Walter R. Mears, vice president and columnist
for The Associated Press, has reported on Washington and national
politics for more than 25 years.
</TEXT>

</DOC>