<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1112EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ChildSupport     12-17 0381</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Child Support,0393</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge's Ad Finds Delinquent Parents</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fifty-five people responded to a judge's
newspaper ad that they'd be jailed for not paying child support
unless they appeared in court.
   Judge Stephen E. Levin had placed an ad in the Philadelphia
Daily News a week ago, listing 142 people accused of delinquency in
child support payments. The judge's message: Appear in court Friday
or ``YOU WILL BE JAILED!''
   ``This is an experiment, and I think it's worked out very
well,'' Levin during a break between cases.
   The ad, which cost the court $5,525, listed 136 men and six
women and offered ``ONE LAST opportunity to appear and work things
out.''
   In addition to the 40 people in court Friday, 15 others had
surrendered earlier in the week and resumed support payments.
   Several men waiting their turn said they had been alerted to the
ad by friends.
   ``When I went to cash my check, the guy told me,'' said an
electrician who declined to give his name. ``I couldn't believe
they put it in the paper. I felt like I had murdered somebody or
something.''
   The man said he fell behind in his support payments for his
9-year-old after losing his job about two years ago and then ``got
scared and took off'' when a bench warrant was issued for his
arrest.
   Many of those waiting to be heard Friday were angry and said the
ad had embarrassed them and their families.
   ``They printed my father's name on the list and he is very
embarrassed. My name is Joseph Ciambella Jr., and they left off the
`junior,''' the younger Ciambella said.
   ``I'm the one who hasn't paid my child support, and it's because
I haven't seen my son, who's 5, in two years. My mother and father
have only been able to see him five times since he was born.''
   Levin said if the ad proves to be cost effective, he will run
others.
   ``These people are really afraid. What will happen is that a lot
of people who would have totally ignored us will pay what they owe
in child support,'' he said.
   ``It is clear that there will be some people on the list who are
not deadbeats, but they will be rare exceptions,'' he added.
</TEXT>

</DOC>