<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1236EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Top10Stories 2Takes   12-28 0901</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Top 10 Stories, 2 Takes,0921</SECOND>
<HEAD>Editors Vote: Fall of Communist Regimes Tops 1989's Stories</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN BARBOUR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Newsfeatures Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The overwhelming story of 1989 was the disintegration of
communism in Eastern Europe and Mikhail S. Gorbachev's efforts to
lead the Soviet Union into a freer society, according to a poll of
Associated Press newspaper editors and broadcast news directors.
   The communist turnaround received 3,256 points, almost the sum
of the two stories that finished second and third, the crushing of
China's Tiananmen Square pro-democracy movement, and the Alaskan
oil spill.
   The China story narrowly outpolled the oil spill in editor
interest, 1,690 points to 1,687.
   In the poll, 315 editors and news directors ranked the stories.
A first-place vote earned a story 10 points and a 10th-place
listing one point.
   Late-developing stories were not on the ballots, which were due
by Dec. 15, five days before the United States invaded Panama and
seven before the bloody ouster of dictator Nicolae Ceausescu in
Romania.
   The decline of communism was voted No. 1 by almost the same
margin as in an earlier AP poll of the top stories for the decade,
a poll in which the AIDS epidemic was voted No. 2 for the 1980s.
   The No. 4 story for 1989 was the San Francisco earthquake, with
1,616 points, followed by: the continuing abortion controversy,
1,225; the international drug war, 1,061; Hurricane Hugo, 935;
government ethics, including scandals involving the Department of
Housing and Urban Development and the Pentagon, 751; the federal
bailout of savings and loans, 515; the conviction of Oliver North
and the lingering investigation of the Iran-Contra affair, 511.
   Notable stories of 1989 that did not make the top 10 included
the Malta summit; the crash of United Flight 232 and the skill of
its crew in saving 184 lives; the conviction and 45-year sentence
of TV evangelist Jim Bakker; the lifetime ban of Pete Rose from
baseball; the unprecedented meeting of Gorbachev and the pope; the
USS Iowa gun turret explosion; the death of Iran's Ayatollah
Ruhollah Khomeini; the Soviet withdrawal from Afghanistan; the
plight of the hostages in Lebanon, and the election of New York
City's first black mayor and Virginia's first black governor.
   The top 10 stories:
   1. When Mikhail Gorbachev rose to power in 1985 and gave the
world two new words, glasnost and perestroika, no one could have
guessed the incredible changes that would burst forth, like a genie
from a bottle, four years later.
   But there it was in 1989: thousands standing in the streets of
Hungary, Czechoslovakia, Bulgaria and East Germany, demanding a
voice in government, a more open society, and eviction of the old
Communist guard. In Poland, Solidarity won an election and began to
build economic ties with the West to try to pull the country out of
poverty.
   In the Soviet Union, Gorbachev had to slow the rate of change
while he struggled to improve the economy with links to the West.
But even there, ethnic republics pressed for more independence.
East-West relations also underwent change, leading even the most
resistant American doubters wondering whatever had happened to
``the evil empire.''
   2. Beijing was hosting the first Chinese-Soviet summit in 30
years, but the historic event was upstaged by the drama unfolding
in Tiananmen Square.
   For seven weeks, the hundred-acre square had been occupied by
thousands of demonstrators, demanding greater democracy and
humiliating the government. For seven weeks, the government had
responded with tolerance and restraint.
   Then, at 2 a.m. Sunday, June 4, barely two weeks after Gorbachev
left Beijing, a convoy of trucks accompanied by 10,000 foot
soldiers of the People's Liberation Army swept through the streets
and opened fire on the crowds.
   By 5 a.m., the square was empty, except for the charred hulks of
vehicles and debris left by the protesters. Hundreds _ perhaps
thousands _ were dead.
   The United States condemned China's military crackdown on the
pro-democracy demonstrators. At year's end, controversial
fence-mending visits by National Security Adviser Brent Scowcroft
were followed by signs of a warming between the two countries.
   3. Early on March 24, the tanker Exxon Valdez strayed off course
and struck a reef in Alaska, spilling 11 million gallons of crude
oil into the pristine waters of Prince William Sound.
   The spilled oil contaminated 1,000 miles of coastline and killed
tens of thousands of shore birds, including 138 bald eagles.
   Volunteers from the lower 48 states, responding to news photos
of oil-soaked otters and crippled birds, joined Alaska fishermen
hosing down beaches, rescuing wildlife and wiping off rocks, one at
a time. Ultimately, more than 2.6 million gallons of oil was
recovered.
   The worst oil disaster in U.S. history sullied Exxon's
reputation as well as Alaska's coast. It also resulted in criminal
charges against Exxon Valdez Capt. Joseph Hazelwood, 42, who was
fired amid allegations he'd been drunk at the time of the accident.
is trial is scheduled to begin Jan. 22.
   4. As 58,000 fans packed San Francisco's Candlestick Park with
21 minutes to go before the start of the World Series' third game
between the Oakland A's and the Giants, television screens across
America suddenly went black.
   The nation's next look at San Francisco was of a city in
darkness except for a fire fed by open gas lines in the Marina
District and the headlights of thousands of vehicles inching along
in countless traffic jams.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>