<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0251 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0732EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-BusinessHighlights     12-18 0826</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Business Highlights,0868</SECOND>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Policymakers at the Federal Reserve will move
to push interest rates lower, possibly as early as this week,
private economists say.
   The expected round of credit easing in response to evidence of a
weakening economy and moderating inflation would cause a variety of
business and consumer rates to fall, the economic forecasters say.
Among the rates that could drop would be the prime rate and home
mortgage rates.
   The Federal Open Market Committee is meeting today and Tuesday
for its final strategy sessions of the year.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. corporations are skimming billions of
dollars from their employees' pension programs to finance buyouts,
ward off takeovers or simply pocket the profits.
   These ``reversions,'' legal under a 1974 law, face growing
criticism amid warnings that parts of the nation's $2 trillion
private pension system are on shaky ground and could eventually
force a massive taxpayer bailout.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.S. merchandise trade deficit surged to
$10.2 billion in October, the worst imbalance in 10 months, as a
record level of imports swamped a small rise in exports, the
Commerce Department said.
   The October deficit was a sharp 19.8 percent higher than the
September imbalance of $8.51 billion, reflecting a higher foreign
oil bill and big increases in imports of food and industrial
supplies, the government said Friday.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A sharp drop in gasoline costs helped push
wholesale prices down in November for the third time in five
months, the government reported.
   The annual rate of inflation, as measured by the Labor
Department's Producer Price Index released Friday, was 4.6 percent
for the first 11 months of the year, up from 4 percent for all of
1988 but much lower than was feared earlier this year.
   The index dipped 0.1 percent last month following a 0.4 percent
gain in October and a 0.9 percent spurt in September. It declined
0.5 percent in July and 0.4 percent in August.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Industrial production was little changed in
November despite rebounding from a major strike and a devastating
earthquake, the government said.
   The Fed attributed the 0.1 percent gain Friday to a rebound from
the Boeing Co. strike and from lingering effects in the computer
and related industries from the San Francisco Bay-area earthquake
in October, when output slumped 0.6 percent.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>ROCHESTER, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eastman Kodak Co. said costs related to a
restructuring announced this year would reduce fourth quarter
earnings by $273 million, significantly more than the company had
predicted.
   The $273 million charge Friday brings Kodak's total 1989
restructuring costs to $500 million, or $850 million before taxes,
spokesman Henry Kaska said. The photography giant had charged $227
million against its second quarter earnings.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The average U.S. income rose slightly in 1988,
but was far outpaced by Japan, the World Bank reported.
   The average per capita income in the United States last year was
$19,780, compared with $18,580 in 1987. In Japan, the average
income rose from $15,840 to $21,040, the World Bank said Friday.
   The Swiss continued to rank first in per capita income with a
1988 average of $27,260, up from $21,310 in 1987.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A regional real estate slump prompted Bank of New
England Corp. to announce it will sharply boost reserves against
bad loans and that it expects a substantial loss for the year.
   The bank also announced Friday it had reassigned a senior
executive overseeing its real estate group, that it was considering
the sale and merger of some operations and that it may rescind its
common stock dividend declared Nov. 27.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gillette Co., trying to rebuild profits hurt by
recent takeover battles, has announced it will realign its
operations and sell some of its European business, affecting about
750 workers in the process.
   Gillette said Friday it was creating a North Atlantic Shaving
and Personal Care Group that would encompass its shaving products
and toiletries segments.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ivan F. Boesky, Wall Street's most notorious
felon, has been permanently released from a federal prison camp and
will serve the rest of his sentence at a Brooklyn halfway house,
authorities said.
   Boesky, 52, was granted the transfer to the halfway house about
10 days ago from the minimum-security Lompoc Federal Prison Camp in
California, where he was imprisoned since March 1988, prison
spokesman Gavin O'Connor said Friday.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A midsession selloff drove stock prices lower Friday amid
worries about real-estate finance and the outlook for the economy
in early 1990. The Dow Jones industrial average dropped 14.08 to
2,739.55, reducing its gain for the week to 8.11 points.
   The dollar finished mostly lower in thin dealings.
   Bond prices were predominantly lower.
   Gold and energy prices rose dramatically after Panama's latest
declaration of hostility against the United States; livestock and
meat futures advanced; grains and soybeans were mixed.
</TEXT>

</DOC>