<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0212 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1433EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i AM-AsianFishWars Adv20-1stLd-Writethru b0418 12-18 1011</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Asian Fish Wars, Adv 20-1st Ld-Writethru, b0418,1034</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv20</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Wednesday AMs, Dec. 20, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Search for Fish Snags Ties Among Asian and Pacific Nations</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: CORRECTS 27th graf, The U.S. Senate ... on driftnetting., to
make bill pending in House.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID THURBER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   With stocks diminishing in their own waters, Asia's
fishing nations are casting for new fishing grounds in a search
that is bringing conflicts with allies and new links with
traditional enemies.
   The issue also has reached the U.S. Congress where senators and
representatives act either for environmental reasons or to assure
plentiful supplies of tuna and salmon for American West Coast
fishermen.
   Much of the conflict, however, is in the South Pacific, where
environmentalists and governments charge that fish stocks are being
wiped out by a sudden wave of Japanese and Taiwanese fishing boats
using giant nets called driftnets.
   Japanese fishing officials say the criticism is another form of
``Japan-bashing'' motivated more by displeasure over Japan's rapid
economic growth than environmental concerns.
   ``We don't want another World War II to occur as a result of the
current situation, but there are people in Japan who now feel
isolated and unfairly treated by the outside world in the same way
that people did before the war,'' said Kiyoshi Katsuyama, a
Fisheries Agency official.
   In recent years, Japan, Taiwan and South Korea have sought
fishing rights in other nations' waters as fish resources have
declined along their own heavily harvested coasts.
   But countries like the United States that once welcomed Asian
fishermen to their relatively unexploited 200-mile economic zones
now have developed their own fishing industries and are limiting
foreign access to stocks that are seen increasingly as a limited
resource.
   ``It's a whole new situation that fisheries is entering,'' said
Ian Kennedy, fisheries officer at New Zealand's embassy in Tokyo.
``There's a definite trend from management not only within 200-mile
limits, but with the high value of migratory species, of fish
migrating outside the limits.''
   In 1981, Japan was allowed to catch about 1.2 million tons of
fish within the United States' 200-mile zone, but its quota was cut
to virtually zero by 1988.
   In their search for fish, some countries are entering deals with
nations they had little to do with before:
   _Companies in anti-communist South Korea have landed deals to
fish in Soviet, Chinese and Vietnamese waters.
   _Taiwanese fishing companies plan to visit the Soviet Union
early in 1990 to explore fishing cooperation, officials say.
   _China has established joint ventures with Nigeria,
Guinea-Bissau, Senegal and Morocco in Africa and plans to increase
its fishing fleet in foreign waters next year from 100 to 120
boats, according to official press reports.
   _Japan is interested in entering joint ventures in Soviet waters
but is waiting for more signs of political stability in Moscow
before deciding, U.S. officials say.
   But increasingly, Asian fishing powers are turning to
international waters for their fish.
   Last season, after Japanese fishing researchers discovered large
supplies of albacore tuna in the South Pacific high seas, Japanese
driftnet boats in the region increased from 20 to 60, and Taiwanese
boats surged to at least 60 and perhaps as many as 130.
   Driftnets, which sweep as much as 30 miles of ocean at once,
consist of a line of nets, each about two miles long, separated
from each other by about a quarter of a mile, Japanese fishing
officials say. The nets, attached to floats, are allowed to drift
until they are picked up later.
   Driftnetting countries say the nets are the only economically
feasible way to fish on the high seas, where fish are less
concentrated than in coastal areas.
   In October, however, Prime Minister Geoffrey Palmer of New
Zealand asked the United Nations to ban driftnetting, calling them
``walls of death'' that ``catch and kill, like a vacuum cleaner,
virtually every living creature _ including some endangered species
_ which come in contact with them.''
   In November, 20 South Pacific nations decided to ban driftnets
from their economic zones and urged Japan and Taiwan to agree to a
regional prohibition on the method.
   The two nations agreed to reduce their fleets but refused to
discuss a total ban; Japan called instead for an international
commission to oversee regional fishing stocks.
   ``There's no scientific evidence yet that driftnetting is
damaging fisheries resources, so it's premature to institute a
ban,'' said Kunio Kimura, senior managing director of the Japan
Fisheries Association.
   ``It's true that there is an incidental catch of marine animals
in driftnets,'' said Katsuyama, the Fisheries Agency official.
``But it's a mistake to ban a method because one or 10 are caught.
If the number is too large, then what we need to do is reduce it.''
   Controversy over driftnetting originally began in the North
Pacific, where U.S. salmon fishermen protested poaching by Asian
squid driftnetters.
   Taiwan has acknowledged that violations occurred and, along with
South Korea, has agreed to let U.S. officials inspect driftnet
vessels suspected of illegally catching U.S. fish.
   American officials in Tokyo say that because of the Japanese
government's tough monitoring, they do not believe Japanese
driftnetters now are poaching substantial amounts of U.S. salmon,
despite such charges by members of the U.S. Congress.
   A bill before the U.S. House of Representatives would prohibit
imports of all fish caught with driftnets, while a congressional
subcommittee has given its approval to a bill calling on the Bush
administration to seek an international ban on driftnetting.
   That could be embarrassing to the United States, said an
American official in Tokyo, ``because the U.S. has one of the
biggest driftnet fisheries in the world'' _ for salmon in American
waters near Alaska and elsewhere.
   ``Environmentalists have a bad taste in their mouth regarding
Japan because of its whaling,'' the U.S. official said, speaking on
condition of anonymity. ``There's a sense that if Japan does it, it
must be bad environmentally. But if Japan does change its policy
regarding driftnetting, it could start pointing its finger at us.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Wednesday AMs, Dec. 20</NOTE>

</DOC>