<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0113EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     12-25 0525</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0545</SECOND>
<HEAD>On the Light Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Teddy Bear made it home for Christmas, a
bit battered but still a happy sight to the dog's owners, who were
almost fleeced out of reward money offered for their pet's return.
   The 4-year-old Chinese Shih Tzu slipped its collar last Monday,
leading Dean and Susan Rider to post reward offers around town and
in the newspaper.
   They got a call from a man who said he and his wife had picked
up the dog and taken him to San Diego. In exchange for wiring of
the $300 reward money, the caller said he would ship Teddy Bear
home.
   But when Dean Rider checked the address the man gave, he learned
it was a residential hotel that doesn't allow pets. And there was
no one registered there under the name given to Rider.
   But after they were the focus of a newspaper story about the
incident, the Riders got another phone call, this one legitimate.
   An employee at the Mission District animal shelter recognized
the dog pictured in the newspaper story as one brought to the
center after being hit by a car. The good Samaritan immediately
called the Riders.
   ``He's got a big fat lip, and a bruised hip, a gash in his paw
and an eye infection, but he was wild with joy when he saw us,''
said Rider about his pet.
   He said the 12-pound dog, with its fluffy, long hair tied in a
knot on his head, will heal eventually.
   Teddy Bear is spending the holiday playing with his sister,
Bitsy, and the Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals is
$1,000 richer thanks to a donation by the Riders.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>ROCKWALL, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Texas congressman says he would like to
run against those who are whispering he should retire because of
his age _ in a footrace, not an election.
   Rep. Ralph Hall, 66, said the rumors he will retire after his
fifth term are simply not true. He said he is still in great shape.
   ``I run a mile and a half and do 100 sit-ups a day,'' he said.
``As long as I'm healthy and my wife's healthy, I intend to stay in
Congress.''
   And to those who started the rumors, Hall said: ``I challenge
them to a race, whoever they are.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two police officers trying to deliver a pregnant
woman to a Bronx hospital on Christmas Eve instead delivered a baby
girl in the back seat of their squad car.
   Clarice Ikoli, 25, of the borough of Manhattan was visiting
friends in the Bronx when she went into labor about 2:30 p.m.
Sunday, said Lt. Ray O'Donnell, a police spokesman.
   Officers Thomas Vinton and Kevin O'Keeffe responded to the 911
call, and helped Ms. Ikoli into the back seat of their radio car,
O'Donnell said.
   But they never got away from the curb. Ms. Ikoli promptly gave
birth to a baby girl, assisted by the two officers.
   Mother and daughter, who is to be named Christine, were taken to
Bronx-Lebanon Hospital, where they were doing fine, O'Donnell said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>