<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1635EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-Israel 1stLd-Writethru a0701 12-17 0491</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Israel, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0701,0501</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: East Germany Wants to Discuss Ties With Israel</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: ADDS 2 grafs at end with Gysi also favoring diplomatic ties.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-East Germany, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARIEH O'SULLIVAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   East Germany's premier says his nation is
willing to change its policy of denying responsibility for the Nazi
Holocaust as a way to establish diplomatic ties with Israel, a
newspaper reported Sunday.
   ``We have approached Israel officially with a request to discuss
establishing diplomatic relations,'' Premier Hans Modrow was quoted
as saying in an interview published in the daily Haaretz.
   Foreign Minister Moshe Arens told Israel radio Sunday that
officials had not received a formal East German request for
diplomatic relations. But he welcomed what he called growing signs
of ``repentance'' by Soviet bloc nations for unwavering support for
the Arab world.
   Many East bloc countries that broke ties with Israel after the
1967 Middle East war recently have expressed interest in renewing
relations.
   But Israel never has had diplomatic ties with East Germany,
which has maintained that it bore no responsibility for the
Holocaust because the nation did not exist at the time.
   The Nazis killed about 6 million Jews before Germany was
defeated in World War II and divided into two states.
   When Modrow was asked about payments to Holocaust survivors, he
told Haaretz: ``We are certainly prepared to discuss the issue with
official representatives of the Jewish organizations dealing with
it and of Israel.''
   East German Deputy Foreign Minister Heinz-Dieter Winter said
last week that his country would discuss ``humanitarian
assistance'' but not war reparations.
   Motti Amichai, a spokesman for the Israeli Foreign Ministry,
said that would not be enough.
   ``What we want is very clearly the acceptance of responsibility,
and if you accept the responsibility, then you need to pay
reparations,'' Amichai said.
   The Holocaust still is a deeply painful issue in Israeli
society, but many believe that establishing ties with East Germany
would not cause the riots that erupted when Israel began diplomatic
relations with West Germany in 1965.
   Shevach Weiss, a left-wing legislator and Holocaust survivor,
said in a telephone interview Sunday: ``Forty-five years after the
war the population of East Germany is made up of young people. Most
Israelis understand that you have to have relations with East
Germany, especially after having ties with West Germany.''
   Weiss said, however, that Israel should insist that East Germany
accept responsibility for the Holocaust and pay reparations.
   Since 1952, West Germany has paid more than $43 billion in
reparations to Holocaust survivors and their families.
   Newly elected East German Communist Party leader Gregor Gysi
also told Haaretz he expects his nation to establish diplomatic
ties with Israel.
   ``We are interested in ties with Israel in all fields, including
of course diplomatic relations,'' he said. ``This doesn't mean we
agree with Israel on every issue, but we have relations with many
countries that we disagree with.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>