<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0410EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-Streets     12-22 0655</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Streets,0680</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chaos in Streets, Looters Drive Off With BMWs</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALINA GUERRERO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Taking advantage of chaos in the
streets and the absence of police, Panamanians ignored a curfew to
strip store shelves bare and drive spanking new BMWs off new car
lots.
   While people in some poor districts hawked the spoils of their
sprees at cut-rate prices, others fled bombs and gunfire as U.S.
troops hunted soldiers and paramilitary bands loyal to Gen. Manuel
Antonio Noriega.
   To try to control the situation, U.S.-installed President
Guillermo Endara on Thursday ordered a curfew that was to last
until 6 a.m. today. But there was no one to enforce it.
   The police are part of the Panamanian Defense Forces, which
either scattered after the U.S. attack or are still fighting. U.S.
troops were busy chasing the resisters.
   At U.S. Southern Command, an officer said plans were being made
to start enforcment action.
   ``This city has been raped, both by the U.S. Army and by
looters,'' said one man along the Via Veneto, a row of fancy stores
near the hotel district.
   Planes dropped two bombs late Thursday in San Miguelito,
location of the Tinajitas garrison where Dignity Battalions and
other Noriega loyalists were holding out.
   Flares lit the dark sky and machine gun fire rattled in the
night. The firing had tailed off by early this morning.
   U.S. troops and armored personnel carriers surrounded the Cuban
and Nicaraguan embassies _ once they found them.
   ``Do you speak English? Do you know where the Cuban Embassy
is?'' asked one armored vehicle driver who had parked near the
Spanish Embassy. When told where to go, he roared off.
   Soldiers at U.S. checkpoints scrutinized identifications. At
some checkpoints soldiers checked IDs against lists of suspects.
Hundreds of Panamanians had been detained at the checkpoints but it
was unclear what was happening to them.
   Dignity Battalions temporarily took over a central hotel
district but appeared more interested in looting, vandalizing and
stealing cars than confronting U.S. troops.
   Thousands of people from children to grandparents poured through
peeled back iron doors on stores along Central Avenue, finding
products with flashlights and matches.
   Some looters hit the basics, like food, soap and toothpaste,
which could become scarce. Many were poor and said they had come to
look for clothes or Christmas presents.
   ``Somebody's going to take it anyway,'' said one embarrassed man
carrying a trash bag stuffed with loot. Like most Panamanians met
on the street, he refused to give his name.
   Others ran to more expensive tastes.
   On the road to the airport, where looting continued through the
afternoon, new BMWs were being driven off a car lot.
   At a large supermarket, one man got to the last case of
champagne, 12 bottles, picked it up and began walking out.
   ``Merry Christmas,'' he said.
   Teams of four or five men lugged furniture and large appliances.
A warehouse district near San Miguelito was sacked and some
buildings were burned.
   Some storeowners stayed put or hired armed guards.
   Stores that were open made customers stand outside barred gates
and give their orders to the owners, who took the money and passed
out merchandise through the bars.
   Much stolen merchandise ended up in impromptu markets in poor
districts. Designer brassieres, French champagne and Gucci watches
were going at bargain-basement prices.
   ``He doesn't have any running shoes for me, but I ordered a pair
for tomorrow,'' said a buyer, about 50 years old, at one of the
markets.
   ``Look,'' said a young man showing off a gold watch. ``I bought
it for $20. The salesman didn't even realize it is a Gucci.''
   Looking down on the scene from a nearby balcony, a middle-aged
woman shook her head in dismay.
   ``It makes me feel like sitting down and crying,'' she said as a
couple of handcarts were rolled down the street full of looted
merchandise.
</TEXT>

</DOC>