<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0186 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1830EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Media     12-22 0578</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Media,0596</SECOND>
<HEAD>Newly Freed Romanian Reporters Pledge Honest Reporting</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TEDDIE WEYR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Romanian journalists pledged Friday to
break the bonds of censorship that kept them tightly muzzled for
decades under the harsh regime of Nicolae Ceausescu.
   In the streets of Bucharest, jubilant Romanians lifted the car
of a Bulgarian reporter in gratitude for his honest reporting.
   Demonstrators marched to the state TV and radio where they took
over the michrophones and announced, ``We have won.''
   For hours, there were continuous, live TV broadcasts as people
took turns at the microphones in the jammed studios. It also showed
scenes of hundreds of thousands of people on the streets.
   Previously, state-run TV had broadcast only two hours a day;
most of that time was filled with footage of Ceausescu, who built a
personality cult in the media.
   Only hours after a popular uprising toppled Ceausescu, the state
news agency Agerpres issued a statement pledging to report honestly
on events at home and abroad.
   As the media in the rest of Eastern Europe became more open in
the wake of democratic reforms sweeping their countries, the
Romanian media remained staunchly loyal to Ceausescu's hard-line
regime, eulogizing him and keeping silent on the changes in the
rest of the Soviet bloc.
   ``The Romanian news agency Agerpres no longer needs the
censorship's special approval to issue fake positions ... that have
no basis,'' Agerpres said.
   In the streets of the capital, jubilant Romanians thanked
reporters from neighboring East bloc countries who had filed vivid,
extensive accounts of what was happening in Romania this past week
and were nearly the sole source of information from that country
after Ceausescu sealed the borders Sunday.
   Many Romanians are able to pick up radio and TV broadcasts from
neighboring Bulgaria, Yugoslavia and Romania or listen to Western
radio stations beaming programs into Romania which also relied
heavily on the East European news agency accounts for their
information.
   The correspondent for the Bulgarian news agency BTA, Peyto
Petkov, reported that grateful demonstrators lifted his car and
thanked him for informing the world of what had happened in their
country.
   The correspondent for the Yugoslav news agency Tanjug said
reporters pushing through the crowd were greeted with cries of
``Thank you, neighbors!''
   The news agency's correspondent, Petar Tomic, said a Romanian
security agent had visited him Friday after the fall of the
Ceausescu regime and apologized for monitoring his telephone calls.
   Tanjug reports out of Bucharest were more detailed than those
from other East bloc countries, even before the reforms that swept
Eastern Europe. Its previous correspondent, Dragan Markovic, was
expelled last year for his reporting after having reported from
there for more than four years.
   The Agerpres statement said:
   ``Along with the entire central and local press, the radio and
television, all the mass media, Agerpres will do its duty and
inform faithfully, honestly and in a civilized manner the home and
international public opinion about all the events in Romania and
the world,'' the statement said.
   ``We will give ... a full and honest image of all Romanian
events,'' it said.
   The statement was issued by ``the Romanian news agency
journalists who never lost their professional conscience, those who
until yesterday were compelled to ... systematically disinform''
the Romanian and foreign public.
   Only hours after the people took over the radio and television
stations, Agerpres also began giving detailed accounts of the
events in the streets.
</TEXT>

</DOC>