<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0263 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1451EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-TokyoBull Bjt   12-22 0775</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tokyo Bull, Bjt,0800</SECOND>
<HEAD>38,000 and Rising: Sun Doesn't Set on Tokyo Stock Exchange</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARI YAMAGUCHI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Tokyo Stock Exchange is heading for the 40,000
barrier that bullish Japanese analysts hope will make it a
bellwether for the world's financial markets.
   While American markets have been battered by recession fears and
volatile swings, Japanese stocks have risen ever higher, buoyed in
part by the nation's growing sense of itself as a global economic
leader.
   ``Until a couple of years ago, the first thing in the morning
brokers used to do was to check how the Dow Jones did overnight,''
said Kenji Maeda of Yamaichi Securities Co., referring to the
widely watched New York Stock Exchange barometer.
   Now, he said, ``it's not just Wall Street but something else _
political, economic news or disaster _ that affects us here and
elsewhere, too.''
   Tokyo is certainly not immume from the jitters that plague
investors in other markets. Just this past week, worries about
rising interest rates in Japan and the implications of the U.S.
attack in Panama knocked stock prices off their record-setting pace.
   But, over the course of the last several weeks, the Tokyo market
has set a string of new highs. Since Wall Street's Oct. 13th
debacle, when the Dow Jones industrial average lost more than 190
points, the 225-issue Nikkei Stock Average has gained more than
3,800 points, or about 10 percent.
   It took only six trading days for the Nikkei to jump from 36,000
to 37,000, and 10 more trading days to surpass the 38,000-point
mark recently.
   The index has risen more than 8,000 points, or nearly 30
percent, in the course of the past year, hitting its current record
of 38,586.18 last Monday. Analysts predict it will hit 40,000 early
next year.
   The Dow Jones average, by comparison, is up about 500 points
over the year, or a little less than 25 percent.
   The Nikkei closed out the week Friday at 38,040.37, dragged down
by the concerns over interest rates and Panama.
   Not everyone reads the year's numbers as good news. Many foreign
economists say the Tokyo market is overpriced and they play down
its worldwide importance. They say European markets still follow
New York, as they did during the October drop, though Tokyo is
admired for its resilience.
   Analysts credit affluent investors, a shortage of traded shares
due to Japan's interlocking companies, fairly stable foreign
exchange and interest rates, and widely used index-linked buying
for Tokyo's steady rise.
   Political events such as the opening of the Berlin Wall also
have fueled optimism in Japan, whose economic power could be
further enhanced by the growth of consumer economies in Eastern
Europe. In addition, the Tokyo market tends to rise at the end of
every year as dealers create momentum to get the New Year off on
the right foot.
   ``Participants are reacting in anticipation of future trends in
the world, instead of trading restlessly, watching economic
fundamentals and indicators on a day-to-day basis,'' said Masahiro
Umemori, an analyst with Normura Securities Co.
   Added Maeda: ``The recent quick rises in share prices made
investors impatient and feel obliged to buy so that they won't miss
the bus.''
   Kazuyuki Suzuki, a dealer with Daiwa Securities Co., said the
Nikkei picked up speed when the Berlin Wall was opened in early
November.
   ``The index has been rising overwhelmingly fast since then,
although nothing in the economy has changed, except for investors'
expectations for more business opportunities in eastern Europe,''
he said.
   Others said recent statements in Washington that the United
States may cut defense spending because of easing East-West
tensions has boosted the Nikkei.
   In Tokyo, only about 25 percent of the total number of stocks
are traded on the market, while the rest are held by business
alliances among companies and never offered for sale.
   Rinichi Kozaki, chairman of Toyo Trust Investment Management
Co., said the practice magnifies share-price rises because a lot of
money is chasing the small number of shares that actually change
hands.
   Dealers said index-linked buying _ which has been blamed for
causing turmoil in the U.S. stock market _ has enabled a few rich
institutional investors to push up the Japan market's direction.
   Individual investors accounted for 31.6 percent of trading in
November, while corporate investors had the rest, according to
Tokyo Stock Exchange statistics.
   Thanks in part to the increased value of the yen since 1985, the
Tokyo exchange has become the world's largest in terms of the value
of listed companies. The total value is about $4 trillion, compared
with about $3 trillion for New York Stock Exchange-listed companies.
</TEXT>

</DOC>