<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 2346EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-LiverTransplants     12-26 0303</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Liver Transplants,0312</SECOND>
<HEAD>Living Donor Recipient Has Follow-up Operation</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation's second recipient of a liver from a
living donor underwent another operation Tuesday to remove a pocket
of infection from her abdomen, officials at the University of
Chicago Hospitals said.
   Sarina Jones, a 16-month-old liver defect victim from
Millington, Tenn., received part of a liver Dec. 8 from her father,
Robert Jones, a dry-wall installer.
   Hospital spokeswoman Susan Phillips said Dr. Jean Emond, a
member of the original transplant team, decided the best way to
deal with the small abcess was to reopen the operation incision to
drain and clear the area of infection.
   ``She tolerated the procedure very well, and was out of the
operating room in about two hours,'' said Ms. Phillips, adding the
infection had not been life-threatening.
   The spokeswoman said Sarina was listed in critical but stable
condition after the two-hour operation, and was expected to be
transferred out of the intensive care ward within several days.
   Also Tuesday, Alyssa Smith, who preceded Sarina as the nation's
first living-donor liver transplant recipient, had her condition
upgraded to serious.
   ``She continues to progress well,'' Ms. Phillips said.
   Alyssa was given a ``day pass'' from the hospital to visit with
her parents on Christmas Day at a Ronald McDonald House for
relatives of ailing children.
   Teresa Smith, 29, an elementary school teacher who donated part
of her liver to her daughter for the Nov. 27 transplant, was
released from the hospital two weeks ago. The Smiths are from
Schertz, Texas.
   Alyssa is expected to leave the hospital sometime after the
first of the year if all continues to go well, according to Ms.
Phillips.
   Sarina and Alyssa suffer from biliary atresia, a usually fatal
congenital defect which is the leading cause of liver transplants
in children.
  
</TEXT>

</DOC>