<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0158 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1933EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Panama 2ndLd-Writethru a0755 12-21 0957</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Panama, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0755,950</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush: U.S. Troops to Stay `As Long as It Takes'</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 10th graf: ``The Pentagon,'' with latest casualty figures,
21 deaths, 208 wounded</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERENCE HUNT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP White House Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush vowed Thursday that American
troops would scour Panama ``as long as it takes'' to capture Manuel
Antonio Noriega. He said the loss of American lives in the military
action ``has been worth it'' and called the U.S. commitment
open-ended.
   Expressing sorrow over the deaths, Bush said ``military
casualties are a burden which a nation must endure and all
presidents have to face up to, but which we can never accept.''
   Several congressmen called for the troops to be brought home
quickly, though one _ Rep. Les Aspin, chairman of the House Armed
Services Committee _ said some might have to remain as policemen
until ``Christmas eve a year from now.''
   Bush said the operation was ``open-ended as far as going after
Noriega, open-ended as far as restoration of order in Panama.''
   A day after ordering 9,500 fighting men into Panama, to join
more than 13,000 already stationed there, Bush said the military
mission ``is not over, but pretty well wrapped up.''
   U.S. forces encountered sporadic firing in Panama City but were
reported in control of several key points in the city, including
the legislative building, said Pentagon spokesman Pete Williams.
   Officials said most units of Noriega's Panamanian Defense Forces
had fled into the jungles, and that U.S. troops may be ordered to
follow them.
   Bush said that with Noriega on the run and a new president,
Guillermo Endara, in place, ``the government is beginning to
function and the man (Noriega) controls no forces. And he's out.
But, yes, I won't be satisfied until we see him come to justice.''
   Bush made his remarks at a White House news conference at the
very hour a military aircraft arrived in Dover, Del., bearing the
bodies of some of the Americans killed in Panama.
   The Pentagon said 21 troops had been killed in action, 208 were
wounded and one was missing.
   In addition, an American civilian, Candy Helin, 43, was killed.
A schoolteacher of gifted children at a U.S. government school in
Panama, she was killed by stray fire from the Panamanian Defense
Forces, officials said.
   Military hospitals in San Antonio, Texas, reported they were
treating about 190 troops evacuated from Panama, a higher count
than reported at the Pentagon.
   Asked if the attempt to catch Noriega had been worth the loss of
life, Bush said, ``I have to answer: Yes, it has been worth it.''
   U.S. officials said 59 Panamanian soldiers had been killed and
66 wounded. Army Lt. Gen. Tom Kelly said U.S. troops had taken
1,500 prisoners, most of them regulars from the Panamanian Defense
Force.
   Bush said 11 people said to have been abducted by Panamanian
troops from a Smithsonian research facility had been freed.
   However, Williams, the Pentagon spokesman, said there were other
reports of an unknown number of Americans being held in three
separate incidents.
   The Pentagon said the U.S. offer of a $1 million bounty for
Noriega had prompted many calls but no results.
   ``We've had a lot of nibbles,'' said Rear Adm. Ted Sheafer, an
intelligence specialist for the Joint Chiefs of Staff.
   ``Suddenly the number of reports on his location has gone up
dramatically,'' he said. ``A lot of it turns out to be very bogus.''
   Bush said, ``That's $1 million bucks I'd be very happy to sign
the check for,'' and he joked that Noriega's wanted poster ``will
be in every post office in town.''
   Noriega is under indictment in the United States on drug charges.
   The general dropped from sight and eluded capture as American
troops landed in Panama.
   ``The good news _ he's out of power,'' Bush said. ``The bad news
_ he has not yet been brought to justice. ... There is a certain
level of frustration on that account.''
   Bush said, ``I won't be satisfied until we see him come to
justice.''
   Asked how long he would chase Noriega, Bush said, ``As long as
it takes.''
   Defense Secretary Dick Cheney had suggested that some elements
of the U.S. force might be withdrawn by Christmas, although the
White House later suggested that might be overly optimistic.
   White House press secretary Marlin Fitzwater said, ``We
certainly aren't willing to give a timetable to it. But everyone
recognizes this is not going to be a case of going in Wednesday and
coming out Thursday.
   ``The new government doesn't have an easy task,'' Fitzwater said
at his own news briefing. ``Don't look for results overnight.''
   Bush used the word ``invade'' to refer to the U.S. operation in
Panama but caught himself and changed it to ``send in those troops
down into Panama.''
   He acknowledged that he had changed course from October, when he
was criticized for not supporting or joining the effort by
Panamanian officers to overthrow Noriega.
   The president said, ``I think what changed my mind was ... the
death of the Marine, brutalizing, really obscene torture of the
Navy lieutenant and the threat of sexual abuse and the terror
inflicted on that Navy lieutenant's wife, the declaration of war by
Noriega.''
   Bush said he needs to spell out those incidents to Soviet
President Mikhail S. Gorbachev, whose government has criticized the
intervention.
   Bush said that with instances of harassment and death, ``Mr.
Gorbachev, please understand this president is going to do
something about it.''
   Meanwhile, Fitzwater said Bush still anticipates attending a
Feb. 15 drug summit with Latin American leaders in Cartagena,
Colombia, even though Peru's president, Alan Garcia, pulled his
ambassador from Washington in protest of the Panamanian
intervention and called for postponing the summit.
</TEXT>

</DOC>