<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0145 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1857EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Panama-HowLong 1stLd-Writethru a0665 12-21 0810</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-How Long, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0665,810</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pentagon Fears Long-Term Panama Fight</HEAD>
<HEAD>Desk: Updates with comments from Bush, Cheney, subbing 6 grafs for
8th graf pvs, At a</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSANNE M. SCHAFER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Military Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pentagon officials fear actions by Noriega
loyalists _ taking Americans hostage, perhaps, or attacking the
Panama Canal _ could force U.S. troops to transform their
``mop-up'' operation into a long-term guerrilla engagement.
   The nation's military leaders were looking at Thursday's Day 2
of ``Operation Just Cause'' as crucial in the battle for control of
the Central American nation, said one high-level military official.
   The fear is that unless Manuel Antonio Noriega's supporters are
captured and disarmed, they could continue to threaten Panamanian
citizens and the lives of the 35,000 Americans living in the
country, or at the very least offer a serious disruption to any
return to normalcy at the canal and elsewhere, officials said.
   ``This is a key day because it will determine whether the
Panamanian Defense Forces and the dignity battalions are
consolidating, or whether they remain as pockets of resistance that
can be cut out and neutralized,'' said the highly placed officer,
who spoke on condition he not be identified by name.
   Asked how long he believed the strike force of thousands of U.S.
troops will remain in the country, the official said, ``I don't
think anybody here knows.''
   Remarking that the forces were going house-to-house in their
efforts to clean out the remaining Noriega loyalists in Panama City
_ and could be forced to search the countryside in search of the
deposed general _ the official said, ``It's not just a mop-up
operation anymore.''
   Asked if U.S. military units might well be facing a protracted
guerrilla battle in urban and country areas in their search for
Noriega, the official answered, ``Yes. It very well may be.''
   President Bush, asked at a session with reporters whether he
believed the intervention would become a guerrilla operation, said,
``I don't think so,'' adding that Noriega has been stripped of his
communications capabilities and the support of military forces that
would allow him to mount an opposition in the countryside.
   ``He hasn't been in a jungle in a long time. And it's tough
living, and he's been living high off the hog, off the Panamanian
people. And so we don't expect'' a kind of mountain guerrilla
organization to arise reminiscent of that led by Cuba's Fidel
Castro in the 1950s, Bush said.
   Defense Secretary Dick Cheney, in a separate session with
reporters, said that while major resistance from the Panamanian
military had ended, he could not ``rule out any possibility'' of
such things as terrorist attacks.
   ``It's still a situation in which there is ongoing conflict and
firefights,'' said Cheney said, acknowledging the possibility of
individual terrorist strikes and the taking of U.S. hostages.
   ``Clearly, we haven't resolved all the potential situations
where there may be Americans being held,'' Cheney said. ``We are
aggressively working every one of those cases,'' he said in
comments to a group of news service and newspaper reporters.
   At a public briefing on Thursday, Pentagon spokesman Pete
Williams struck a positive note, saying that ``the organized
resistance ... has ceased at this point'' and that the ``objective
of the day'' was to support the establishment of a democratic
government under the newly sworn and U.S.-supported president,
Guillermo Endara.
   Williams did acknowledge, however, that there was ``some
conflict continuing'' with some members of the Noriega's ``dignity
battalions'' _ the his armed supporters in civil garb _ that remain
in Panama City.
   At the briefing, Army Gen. Tom Kelly, the joint staff's director
of operations, advised reporters that there was no time estimate
available for when the increased U.S. forces might withdraw.
   ``We don't have a time line,'' Kelly said. ``They will be there
until the job is done.''
   Rear Adm. Ted Sheafer, who also briefed reporters, said U.S.
military officials still think Noriega is inside Panamanian borders.
   ``We believe he is in the country,'' Sheafer said.
   On Capitol Hill, Sen. Robert Kasten, R-Wis., expressed concern
over a long-term engagement.
   ``If there is a beginning, middle and end to American military
involvement it is far better than having this thing dragging out
over weeks and months,'' Kasten said.
   Another senior Pentagon official, who also spoke privately, said
he was confident that the specialized U.S. military units on
Noriega's trail will ultimately be successful.
   ``It may take some time,'' he said, ``But they'll get him.''
   ``Noriega is noisy, blustery, and has such a big ego that it is
nearly impossible for him to travel incognito,'' the official said.
   The official said that the U.S. intervention force will be able
to sustain itself easily over the long term, if a lengthy presence
is necessary, because of the well-organized U.S. base of operations
that has been in place for decades in Panama.
</TEXT>

</DOC>