<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 2333EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania 10thLd-Writethru a0664 12-25 0863</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania, 10th Ld - Writethru, a0664, a0665, 2 Takes,0883</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ceausescu, Wife Executed, Romanian Media Announce</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 8th pvs, `Ceausescu, dressed...' to ADD
another detail from film. Pick up 9th pvs, `Romanian staff...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos BUC2,3, NY36</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MORT ROSENBLUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ousted President Nicolae Ceausescu and
his wife Elena were executed Monday after they were convicted of
genocide and ``grave crimes'' against Romania at a secret military
trial, the provisional government said.
   Ceausescu, 71, the last hard-line Communist leader in the Warsaw
Pact, was chased from power Friday after his dreaded security
forces massacred thousands protesting his repressive 24-year rule
and harsh economic policies.
   He and his wife, who served as a virtual second-in-command, were
executed by firing squad after a trial at an undisclosed location,
according to Bucharest Radio and Romanian television.
   The radio and television, which formerly were controlled by
Ceausescu, are under control of the National Salvation Comittee,
the new provisional government.
   Fighting in central Bucharest, which continued spporadically
late into the night, had driven many people from the streets by the
time the announcement of the executions was made around 8:30 p.m.
(1:30 p.m. EST.) However, cheers rang out from the few people on
the streets and from apartment balconies.
   The broadcasts on both radio and television did not specify
where the executions took place.
   Romanian television early Tuesday showed the Ceausescus before
their execution, being brought to an undisclosed location in an
armored car.
   Ceausecu, dressed in a dark suit and a heavy black overcoat,
looked gaunt and tired but smiled as a man in a white coat checked
his blood pressure. His wife looked forlorn as she sat against a
wall, dressed in a beige fur-lined coat with her head covered
peasant-style in a scarf.
   The footage also included a scene of the couple sitting at a
wooden table, apparently at their trial.
   Romanian staff at the Hotel Intercontinental clustered cheering
around a television set when the film appeared. Some even spat in
the direction of the television in a gesture of contempt.
   The film was the first of Ceausescu to be shown since the new
government announced his capture Saturday.
   Bucharest Radio blamed the Ceausescus for the deaths of more
than 60,000 Romanians and said they plundered the poor country of
more than $1 billion that they deposited in foreign banks. The
report did not make clear whether the deaths occurred during the
11-day uprising that toppled Ceausescu or during his entire tenure.
   ``Oh, what wonderful news!'' an unidentified announcer said.
   ``The anti-Christ died'' on Christmas Day, the announcer said.
   Ceausescu became the first Eastern European leader executed
since Imre Nagy, the leader of Hungary's revolt against Soviet rule
who has hanged in June 1958.
   The radio interrupted patriotic music to make the announcment
that the couple had been executed after being convicted by a
military tribunal of ``particularly grave crimes,'' including
subversion of the state, theft of public assets, destruction of the
national economy and an attempt to escape.
   ``Today, we removed the most hideous tyrant who soiled with
blood the history of Romania,'' an unidentified radio announcer
said. ``Let's be happy in the New Year.''
   The couple built a cult of personality unequaled in Eastern
Europe since the days of Josef Stalin. His party hailed him as
``the Conducator'' and the ``Genius of Carpathians.''
   Just one month ago, the Communist Party gave Ceausescu another
five-year term in a lavish show of support for his rejection of
reforms sweeping Eastern Europe.
   The National Salvation Committee had announced over the weekend
that it would put the Ceausescus on trial and impose severe
punishment. It was not immediately clear why the committee pledging
to restore democracy in Romania chose to put the Ceausescus on
trial in secret and execute them immediately.
   The decision could have stemmed from an attempt to stop the
fierce fighting in Bucharest and other cities between the
pro-Ceausescu security forces and the army, which is supporting the
popular revolt.
   ``We regret the trial did not take place in an open and public
fashion,'' White House spokesman Sean Walsh said in Washington.
``We urge an end to all violence and bloodshed in Romania.''
   Ceausescu came to power in 1965 and built an autocratic
Stalinist regime, but was once courted by the West for his refusal
to slavishly follow the Soviet line. In recent years his regime
became isolated and was criticized for the forced destruction of
ethnic villages and the draconian measures imposed to pay off the
nation's foreign debt.
   Ceausescu and his 72-year-old wife fled the presidential palace
by helicopter Friday.
   Their last public appearance was at a government-orchestrated
rally Thursday in Bucharest at which thousands of angry people
jeered them and demanded their ouster. Ceausescu appeared startled
and halted his speech. His troops later fired on the crowd.
   The Ceausescus' son Nicu and daughter, Zoia-Elena, were paraded
before TV viewers after their arrests on Friday and Sunday.
   On Monday, Ceausescu's die-hard security agents continued to
battle army patrols and snipers fired at civilians venturing onto
Bucharest streets. The fighting followed some of the fiercest
fighting in Europe since World War II.
   MORE
</TEXT>

</DOC>