<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0110 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 2024EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania 4thLd-Writethru a0627 12-23 1340</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania, 4th Ld - Writethru, a0627,1384</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ceausescu Reported Captured; Fighting Continues</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS grafs 13-15, `Romanian television...' with 5 grafs to ADD
quote on Ceausescu's capture and clarify withdrawal of earlier report.
Pick up 16th pvs, `Emil Bobu...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos FRA2, FRA4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MORT ROSENBLUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Revolutionary leaders said they had
captured deposed President Nicolae Ceausescu on Saturday and would
put the Soviet bloc's last Stalinist dictator on trial. Heavy
fighting broke out in the capital.
   The insurgents claimed control of the country after a night of
ferocious battles between army units siding with pro-reform
protesters and security forces loyal to Ceausescu, who fled his
palace Friday.
   But loyalist guards continued to battle army units in Bucharest
Saturday. Bursts of gunfire echoed among the grandiose canyons of
buildings and monuments the Communist leader built to himself
during 24 years of rule.
   Rocket-propelled grenades slammed into the 13-story television
building in an attempt to silence the opposition's broadcasts.
   At about 1 a.m. Sunday local time (7 p.m. EDT), most of the
shooting in Bucharest had stopped and the city was virtually
silent, Hungarian Defense Ministry spokesman Gyoergy Keleti said on
Hungarian television.
   Fighting raged Saturday at Bucharest's international airport
Otopeni, with pro-Ceausescu forces in helicopter gunships strafing
army units, the state news agency Agerpres said.
   The pilot of an Austrian plane that brought aid into Bucharest
Friday evening said when he returned to Vienna late Saturday that
he had seen at least 30 bodies of dead attackers at the airport.
   The pilot, who was not identified in an interview with Austrian
television, said battles raged for hours at the airport, with
grenades and mortars being used.
   Fighting also was reported in outlying cities, including
Timisoara, where the revolution broke out on Dec. 15. However, an
Associated Press reporter in the city said revolutionary soldiers
were in control.
   An Austrian television reporter said there was an ``unbelievable
attack'' Saturday afternoon by pro-Ceausescu forces who had
parachuted into Timisoara the day before. He quoted eyewitnesses as
seeing bodies on the street.
   Hundreds of people have been killed in two days of street
fighting and thousands more were reported killed in a week of
crackdowns on the burgeoning protest movement.
   Revolutionaries took swift revenge against pro-Ceausescu
fighters captured near the downtown post office, killing them on
the spot.
   Romanian television gave a jubilant boost to the revolt,
announcing that the army had captured Ceausescu and his wife,
Elena, one day after the dictator was ousted by a week-old popular
revolt.
   The ``dictatorial family, Nicolae and Elena Ceausescu, was
captured,'' declared Ion Iliescu, a member of the provisional
revolutionary governing coalition.
   Ceausescu did not appear on televison, however. Broadcasters
said he would not be shown to prevent rescue attempts by loyalists.
   The television had first reported Friday that Ceausescu and his
wife were captured, but withdrew that report.
   Iliescu called Ceausescu a ``poison hyena'' and said the new
government would prosecute the former president and his wife, who
had been the second most powerful person in the country.
   Emil Bobu, who in the past was put in control of the country
when the Ceausescus were traveling abroad, also was captured with
the Ceausescus, Iliescu said.
   On Friday, the revolutionaries announced they had captured
Ceausescu's eldest son, Niku, a powerful member of the ruling
familial cabal.
   In Bucharest, fighting continued around the television and radio
stations and the partly damaged Communist Party headquarters, where
security forces barricaded themselves late Friday. Revolutionary
force appealed to residents nearby to evacuate.
   Gorbachev asked other Warsaw Pact nations to cooperate in
devising ``coordinated efforts in providing support to the people
of Romania,'' the Tass news agency reported.
   Hungarian Foreign Minister Gyula Horn said said a Warsaw Pact
meeting planned Sunday was scrapped because ``the situation shows
signs of stabilization.''
   Soviet officials all but ruled out direct unilateral Soviet
military help, but Gorbachev said medical aid was being extended.
   ``The first planes with medicines and urgent supplies have
already arrived in Bucharest,'' Tass quoted Gorbachev as saying.
``But they still are being held up in the Bucharest airport, which
is blockaded.''
   Doctors at Bucharest Emergency Hospital said they had treated
hundreds of wounded at that hospital, one of 14 in the city.
   Dr. Marian Palaschivescu, haggard in a filthy blue terry cloth
hospital jacket, told reporters 51 bodies had arrived by early
afternoon at Bucharest Emergency Hospital. He then glanced at three
sets of legs protruding from the trunk of a car that screeched to a
stop. ``No, 54,'' he said.
   The army, which rose against Ceausescu on Friday, was joined by
amateur revolutionaries suddenly at war after decades of
repression. Their ragtag forces were nervous and often
trigger-happy in the face of desperate professionals fighting for
their lives against inevitable criminal prosecution under a
reformist government.
   The National Salvation Committee, the name of the coalition
provisional government, announced that Gen. Nicolae Militaru, an
army officer demoted under Ceausescu, had been appointed defense
minister.
   Maj. Gen. Stefan Gusa, former first deputy defense minister and
Gen. Victor Stanculescu were appointed his deputies, Romanian
television said.
   ``We are in control almost all over the country,'' Gusa
announced over Romanian radio. ``There still are isolated bands of
desperates who try to destroy what we have conquered. They have
failed and they will fail.''
   ``Let us restore the quiet in these historic but also difficult
moments,'' he urged. ``Everything must go back to normal as soon as
possible.''
   The National Salvation Committee warned against last-ditch acts
by the cornered presidential guards and the hated special police.
Guards screened all people entering the Intercontinental Hotel.
   The Italian news agency ANSA said the National Salvation
Committee also had advised embassies in Bucharest to barricade
themselves.
   Chinese embassy windows had bullet holes in them, and the Soviet
news agency Tass said it had been told a building housing Soviet
trade representatives was in the firing line.
   The diehard forces supporting Ceausescu adopted guerrilla
warfare tactics in the city, holing up in hotels, apartment
buildings and on roofs and firing at soldiers and civilians on the
streets.
   Despite the tension, many Romanians were clearly enjoying their
sudden freedom. People took wild rides around town waving huge red,
gold and blue flags from which they had ripped the center symbol of
Ceausescu's brand of communism.
   Romanians on the street expressed happiness in tempered terms,
but choked voices and misted eyes underscored the feeling.
   As gunfire smacked the television building, the youth program
editor, Marin Constantin, clowned for a dozen people pinned down
with him.
   ``This has finally woken us up from our sleep of death,'' he
said.
   The state of the war shows partly why it was necessary,
Romanians pointed out. About the only thing in apparent abundance
in this shortage-plagued nation was ammunition.
   Taxis were commandeered to carry wounded, and few private cars
had enough fuel. Many shops were closed, but they are usually
bereft of goods when open.
   Early Saturday, Petre Roman, one of about 20 members of the
National Salvation Committee, said the committee wanted free
elections by April and would assure ``a certain amount of political
and economic stability'' in the meantime.
   In Timisoara, the birthplace of the revolt that swept Ceausescu
from power after 24 years of increasingly autocratic rule, two
people were reported killed and six wounded in fighting Saturday.
   Fierce fighting also was reported at various times from the
cities of Brasov, Arad and Sibiu.
   Relatives continued a grisly search in forests outside Timisoara
through mass graves of corpses, most naked and many mutilated, of
victims of a massacre by security forces last weekend.
   The protests began when hundreds of people gathered Dec. 15 to
rally against the threatened arrest of an ethnic Hungarian pastor.
They evolved into huge demonstrations that drew hundreds of
thousands nationwide.
   Ceausescu ordered troops to fire on protesters, fueling more
demonstrations.
   Romanian television said the death toll approached 12,000, but
there was no confirmation.
   The revolt reached Bucharest on Thursday. Ceausescu and his wife
fled the city in a helicopter Friday.
</TEXT>

</DOC>