<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0102 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1912EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ScienceFair     12-19 0618</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Science Fair,0636</SECOND>
<HEAD>Westinghouse Does `the Right Thing'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICK HAMPSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   They spent months and years toiling in
laboratories and stuffy libraries but when it came time to get
their projects to the nation's top science fair, 90 high school
students were a day late.
   Under contest rules, the science papers absolutely, positively
had to be in Washington, D.C., by midnight Friday. But, because of
a Federal Express error, the papers from 90 students at New York's
Stuyvesant High School arrived Monday.
   The students were disqualified from the Westinghouse Science
Talent Search _ until Westinghouse executives in Pittsburgh
intervened.
   ``It just wasn't fair, so we're going to admit them,'' said
Charles Carroll, a Westinghouse spokesman. ``We asked ourselves,
`What's the right thing to do?' Disqualification seemed like an
unfair penalty.''
   ``We're elated!'' said Stuyvesant Assistant Principal Harold
Lehrman. ``After I got the call, the news spread through the school
like wildfire. Everyone was cheering.''
   That included Leland Gershell, who spent the last 18 months
designing and performing an experiment that linked the fluoride
content of dental patients' saliva with their susceptibility to
cavities.
   For a while, Gershell was afraid his work _ he pored over dozens
of scholarly journals and collected and analyzed dozens of vials of
patients' drool _ had been in vain.
   A Stuyvesant teacher sent two boxes to the Westinghouse
competition in Washington last Thursday. One box, containing about
70 papers, arrived the next day, just before the deadline. But the
second box, mailed at the same time and same place, arrived three
days later to be rejected and sent back to New York.
   Federal Express admitted it misrouted the box and sent
Westinghouse an affidavit to that effect. But Carol Luszcz, program
director, said that made no difference.
   Competition applications warn that ``a postmark of Dec. 15 will
not suffice, and packages sent via a guaranteed delivery service
will be refused if they arrive after the deadline.'' There also is
an underlined warning _ ``LATE ENTRIES WILL BE DISQUALIFIED WITHOUT
EXCEPTION'' _ and a recommendation that applicants allow for the
holiday mail crush.
   ``Ever year we get papers late, but we just can't take them,
whether it's the applicant's fault or the mail's fault or God's
fault,'' Ms. Luszcz said before she was overruled by the
Westinghouse Educational Foundation, which pays for the competition.
   One year, she said, about 30 applicants were rejected even
though their applications were delayed by a blizzard in the Midwest.
   Carroll, speaking by telephone from Pittsburgh, said that what
set Stuyvesant apart was what he termed ``the twin boxes ... They
were sent out together, so it was decided to treat them as one.''
   Ms. Luszcz said the deadline was important, because competition
judges begin reading the papers in Washington almost immediately
after the deadline, and that equity required that similar papers be
read by the same judges.
   Carroll said the judges would be reconvened to consider the 90
Stuyvesant papers.
   The Westinghouse competition is the ultimate high school science
fair. The ranks of winners include five Nobel laureates, eight
MacArthur fellows and two winners of the Field Medal, the top prize
in mathematics.
   Of the 1,900 scholarships awarded since 1942, New York City
students have won roughly a quarter. Stuyvesant students are
regularly among the semifinalists, including 26 last year.
   A group of 300 semifinalists will be announced Jan. 17 and 40
finalists on Jan. 26. About $140,000 in scholarships will be doled
out about a month later.
   On Tuesday afternoon Federal Express said it had located the big
cardboard box and was flying it back to Washington. ``It's kind of
a happy ending,'' said Federal Express spokesman Armand Schneider.

</TEXT>

</DOC>