<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0097 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1341EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Bush-Threat     12-18 0386</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Threat,360</SECOND>
<HEAD>President Scoffs at Reports Drug Lords Targeting Him</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Bush Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HARRY F. ROSENTHAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush scoffed Monday at a published
report that Colombian drug lords are putting up $30 million to have
him killed, saying it won't keep him from attending a drug summit
in Colombia in February.
   ``I wish they would bring the source in so we could take a look
at it,'' Bush told reporters during a year-end interview. ``There's
nothing to it.''
   Newsweek magazine, in its Dec. 25 issue, quotes an unidentified
State Department official as saying intelligence reports found the
drug cartels tried to recruit Mideast terrorists to kill the
president.
   ``I've got total confidence in our security people,'' Bush said.
``I'm not going to do anything reckless ... we've got outstanding
Secret Service people. And let me take this opportunity to reassure
the American people we will not unduly risk anyone's life here.''
   As the questioning continued, Bush retorted:
   ``Nobody has to go but me. I'm the only one that's invited. So
where do you get this `we' stuff?''
   A reporter asked if Bush will be responsible if anyone is hurt.
Many people, including reporters and photographers, travel with the
president.
   Bush suggested that perhaps stringers _ local reporters who work
part-time for out-of-town media outlets _ should substitute for the
White House press on the trip.
   ``People are also concerned about you and they think there's no
such thing as a guarantee in this life,'' the reporter persisted.
   ``But you can't walk out to the drug store with that approach,''
said Bush. ``I'm not going to live in a cocoon.''
   Reminded that there had been 250 bombings in Colombia in three
months, the president said:
   ``You're trying to send a message that we want to support the
president of Colombia,'' Virgilio Barco. ``He is a brave man. He is
fighting our fight for us as well as for his own people and I don't
want to sent a timorous signal to him. ...
   ``I have responsibilities not to do anything imprudent regarding
the presidency and I will fulfill those. But I also have
responsibilities to try to support a courageous person who has
risked a great deal to fight a fight in which we all have
tremendous interest.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>