<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0126 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1818EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-BurningDrums 1stLd-Writethru a0637 12-28 0518</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Burning Drums, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0637,0529</SECOND>
<HEAD>Yo! Put Out Those Fires, Philly Street Vendors Are Told</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf, `For generations ..., to CORRECT spelling of
doo-wop.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PX1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ERICH SMITH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Yo! Put out those fires!
   For generations, merchants at their stalls in the open-air
Italian Market _ a Philly tradition along with the Liberty Bell and
soft pretzels smeared with mustard _ have warmed their hands around
roaring trash fires in metal drums. And millions of moviegoers
watched doo-wop singers crooning around street fires in ``Rocky.''
   But in a state where clean-air laws have banned the burning of
leaves for years, the street fires of South Philadelphia must go,
says city Managing Director James White. He wants the fires doused
by Jan. 7.
   Produce vendors at the Italian Market paused between sales
Thursday to say they'll probably obey, but not cheerfully.
   ``I was born here in 1928 and there's always been fire cans on
this street to keep warm,'' said Anthony Messina. ``But times
change. What can I do? What can I say? I'll probably get a kerosene
heater, but I don't like it.''
   Next door, Lawrence Lacovara, 31, fed cardboard boxes and boards
into a steel-drum fire. What will he do in two weeks, when the ban
will be in force?
   ``Get a kerosene heater, probably, or a heater with a blower.
It's going to cost more, though,'' he said.
   Up the street Joseph Girado carved up empty produce boxes while
his wife and son waited on customers. The cardboard went, piece by
piece, into a drum 20 feet away, where the flames helped ward off
temperatures in the low 30s.
   ``I don't see any damage from that fire, do you?'' he asked.
``That's a tradition. It keeps me warm. It keeps my customers
warm.''
   ``We're trying to make an honest living here. We're working like
dogs _ like animals. If I had any sense I wouldn't be here. We
don't get any benefits, no paid vacation, no retirement _ and now
this.''
   City Councilman James Tayoun, who is going to bat for the
vendors, said the ruckus started because of complaints from the
Health Department.
   ``The merchants cannot physically operate without a decent
source of heat,'' Tayoun said. ``They've been there long before us.
I see no reason we can't allow them to burn clean wood. If they
burn other trash, they should be cited.''
   The federal Environmental Protection Agency isn't involved, but
an EPA spokesman said putting out the fires is probably a good idea.
   ``Research indicates that any kind of open burning is a serious
problem,'' said Lee Blackburn, an EPA expert on air quality. ``A
lot of particulate matter comes out. Inks, solvents and plastics
being burned can release a lot of toxic components.''
   Standing over a roaring trash fire on Ninth Street, Pervis Adams
was unconvinced.
   ``I think kerosene heaters give off as much pollution as this,''
he said. ``What about fireplaces? Are they going to make people
quit using them, too? Go look at junkyards, they're burning there
all the time.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>