<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0113EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-NoriegaPal     12-23 0456</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Noriega Pal,0471</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Attacks Office of Noriega Buddy, Looters Have Field Day</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CANDICE HUGHES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At the sledgehammer's final blow, a
cheer went up from the crowd outside a house belonging to one of
Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega's closest associates.
   People poured into the house at a dead run, exultant. They
poured out again with bottles of French champagne, silver coffee
pots and sequined sombreros.
   But this was no ordinary looting mission. It was a middle-class
crowd for the most part, and they were venting pent-up loathing for
the general and all he stood for.
   ``Democracy has arrived,'' one young man said. ``We don't want
these military guys running things. They are thieves.''
   Someone emptied a case of campaign-style buttons bearing the
slogan: ``Onward with Noriega!'' and began gleefully stomping on
them, grinding them flat with a little dance as onlookers applauded.
   The house belonged to Carlos A. Wittgreen, a businessman
believed to be a key player in the maze of front companies hiding
Noriega's money-laundering and cocaine-smuggling schemes.
   ``He's Noriega's right hand,'' one man said as people opened box
after box of handcuffs in amazement.
   The house was sacked after a U.S. armored vehicle bombarded the
place.
   Troops barricaded the street at mid-afternoon Friday and opened
fire. They pelted it with tear gas and demanded Wittgreen's
surrender over a bullhorn.
   When no one emerged, they left and the people began running
toward the house, cheering.
   Teresa Bay Guardia sat on the grass nearby, sorting through the
files and boxes of documents her teen-agers were hauling out as
fast as they could. Their eyes streamed from the biting sting of
the tear gas trapped inside, but they were grinning like they'd
just won the lottery.
   ``I'm gathering evidence,'' she said as sofas, office chairs,
potted plants and paintings went by at a dizzying clip. ``I have a
friend in the opposition I'm giving this to.''
   There was a pile of letterhead stationery. Five different
companies. Five different addresses. One telephone number.
   Someone else found a handwritten ledger in a spiral notebook.
Page after page of coded transactions, many with Noriega's general
staff.
   Guardia, a U.S. citizen raised in Panama, looked at the pile of
documents as though Christmas had come a few days early to Panama.
   ``I've walked many a mile, been in many a demonstration against
Noriega,'' she said. ``This is the first time I haven't been afraid
to give my name.''
   She said she couldn't understand the international criticism of
the U.S. invasion. ``Ask the Panamanians. We're the one's who have
been living the situation,'' she said.
   Even with the lawlessness and looting that has broken out, she
said, ``We're delighted.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>