<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0195 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0127EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-AMR-TWA Bjt   12-19 0724</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AMR-TWA, Bjt,0749</SECOND>
<HEAD>TWA To Sell Chicago Holdings To American, Icahn Says Other Sales
Possible</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By R.B. FALLSTROM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Trans World Airlines Inc. pilots are calling a
planned $195 million sale of assets to American Airlines the first
step in a liquidation.
   TWA Chairman Carl Icahn warned that other asset sales are
possible after Monday's announcement that the airline had agreed to
sell to American its Chicago-London route, a maintenance hangar and
four gates at O'Hare International Airport.
   Icahn, in a letter to TWA employees, said the deal was designed
to help restore TWA to profitability and give the company extra
cash in case of a protracted slump.
   Leaders of the TWA branch of the Air Line Pilots Association
blasted the deal, saying it would further alter the balance of
power in the industry. Kent Scott, chairman of the union's
executive council in St. Louis, TWA's hub city, said the pilots
would try to block the deal, which requires government approval.
   ``There is no possible way that TWA can get stronger if it gets
smaller,'' Scott said. ``We think that this is just a first step in
a controlled liquidation of TWA.
   ``In our view, this is not just an isolated sale of a route that
doesn't fit into the TWA route system, as Carl Icahn would like to
portray it,'' he said.
   Analyst Paul Turk, who follows the industry for Avmark Inc.,
agreed with the pilots.
   ``Any diminution of TWA's overseas operation is probably not a
good sign _ not for the long-term health of the airline,'' Turk
said.
   A spokeswoman for the Independent Federation of Flight
Attendants said her union also opposed the sale.
   ``We would be very disappointed to lose the routes,'' said Joan
Wages, a legislative representative in Washington, D.C. ``I'm sure
that the Department of Transportation will look very closely at
this.''
   Icahn, who has been rumored to be seeking buyers for the
airline, did not identify which assets may be sold. TWA spokesman
Don Morrison declined to elaborate.
   ``It is clear that TWA can no longer afford to make investment
decisions based on traditional thinking,'' Icahn said. ``There are
unprofitable assets at TWA which have been untouched purely because
of `tradition.' These assets, if sold, could put us on the road to
profitability.''
   Icahn, saying only three or four major airlines will exist by
the mid-1990s, said he would use TWA's cash to expand
internationally, including applying for permission to fly to Tokyo
from St. Louis.
   But he said TWA was not having financial difficulty.
   ``TWA currently has over $700 million in cash, and I hope within
the next several months to have well over $1 billion,'' Icahn
wrote, saying TWA's investments added $500 million to the airline's
books in realized and unrealized gains.
   ``This cash reserve will help protect TWA from the economic
downturn that I have been predicting and that is already occurring
in our industry,'' Icahn said.
   Icahn, a billionaire corporate investor, was TWA's ``white
knight'' in 1986, buying the airline in a $440 million deal to
thwart an attempted takeover by Frank Lorenzo's Texas Air Corp.
TWA, based in Mt. Kisco, N.Y., is the nation's eighth-largest
carrier.
   The sale gives American, the No. 1 carrier, a second London
route. The airline, a unit of AMR Corp., has flown to London from
Dallas-Fort Worth International Airport since 1982.
   The deal leaves TWA with three gates in Chicago, Morrison said.
The transaction is dependent upon TWA losing enough money this year
to negate clauses in its agreements with its pilots union.
   David Berkley, a spokesman for the pilots, said the intent of
the agreements were to give Icahn a chance to sell assets only as a
last-ditch effort to save the company.
   ``What we didn't foresee was the methodology Icahn used to take
the company private,'' Berkley said. ``Privatization is directly
responsible for the losses in the air. He put so much debt on TWA
and extracted so much cash that it negatively affected operations.''
   While American was buying the TWA holdings, an expected
announcement on a multimillion-dollar expansion into Latin America
did not materialize. Published reports said American would by
Eastern Airlines' Caribbean routes Monday, but no deal was
announced.
   During the past year, American has worked on expanding its
international business, adding European and Pacific Rim flights.
</TEXT>

</DOC>