<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1348EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-PensionRaids Bjt   12-17 0955</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pension Raids, Bjt,950</SECOND>
<HEAD>Legal Loophole Allows Firms to Tap Pensions for Cash</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRYNA BRENNAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. corporations are skimming billions of
dollars from their employees' pension programs to finance buyouts,
ward off takeovers or simply pocket the profits.
   These ``reversions,'' legal under a 1974 law, face growing
criticism amid warnings that parts of the nation's $2 trillion
private pension system are on shaky ground and could eventually
force a massive taxpayer bailout.
   Big business, backed by the Bush administration, argues that the
pension raids only involve surplus money, most of it supplied by
the employer in the first place. Some unions and workers, however,
say they are being robbed of money that is rightfully theirs.
   Corporate raiders, taking hundreds of millions of dollars in a
single reversion, have attracted most of the attention. But big
business isn't alone in taking advantage of the law.
   Some 2,000 companies have applications pending with the Internal
Revenue Service for pension reversions. Among them, according to
IRS documents obtained by The Associated Press: The Museum of
Modern Art in New York, which is seeking $17 million; the Detroit
Athletic Club, seeking $842,000; Niagara University, $500,000; the
St. Louis Country Club, $736,000.
   The 1974 Employment Retirement Income Security Act, known as
ERISA, allows employers to pull back the money by terminating the
pension programs and paying off the employees, usually with a lump
sum.
   Industry statistics show that 25 percent of the plans are not
replaced. In many other cases, the pensions are succeeded by
programs that provide fewer benefits. And even if a plan is
restored, it has been stripped of its cushion against potential
future losses from bad investments or stock crashes.
   The Labor Department estimates that about 80 percent of private
pension plans contain some sort of surplus, making them potential
targets.
   Michael S. Gordon, a Washington pension attorney, likens the
maneuver to ``breaking into a piggy bank.''
   ``In order to get its mitts on what is usually a surplus, the
employer will terminate the plan. Not for any sound business
reason, but to help finance a takeover or ward off one,'' Gordon
said.
   ``That money should stay in the retiree system,'' said James B.
Foley, a retired American Red Cross vice president whose former
employer took an almost $100 million reversion this year.
   The West German company, Tengelmann Group, recouped the money it
used to buy Great Atlantic &amp; Pacific Tea Co. by terminating the A&amp;P
pension plan and netting more than $200 million. On the other side,
Union Carbide helped thwart a takeover by GAF by pulling $500
million from its pension plans.
   Exxon Corp. drew a record $1.6 billion reversion in 1986.
   The government's official tally shows that since 1980, about
2,000 companies have terminated their employer-paid plans to nab
about $26 billion. And those figures do not include the far more
numerous reversions of less than $1 million.
   Ten reversions of more than $1 million were completed in May and
June of this year, the IRS documents show. At the same time, 298
smaller ones were completed.
   Jeffrey Mamorsky, a New York pension attorney and author, says
the money is a well-deserved reward for companies, large or small,
that have managed their pension programs well.
   ``We don't live in a communist country,'' he said. ``There's
nothing that's forcing employers to install the plan or keep the
plan.''
   Gordon, who helped write the ERISA law, disagrees. ``The
attitude of the (Bush) administration and business is totally at
war with the interests of the beneficiaries across the United
States,'' he said.
   Sen. Howard Metzenbaum says he's been fighting for six years to
make it tougher for companies to skim off the excess money.
   ``I don't think it should be legal,'' the Ohio Democrat said.
``I'm not saying any of these people are being evil; I just say
they're being unfair.''
   But Mark Ugoretz, executive director of the ERISA Industry
Committee, argues that restrictive laws will cause employers to
dump their plans.
   ``Ultimately you will see a complete reduction in plan
funding,'' Ugoretz said. ``It would weaken the retirement security
of people in the plans. It would substantially jeopardize the
status of the PBGC.''
   The Pension Benefit Guaranty Corporation, or PBGC, is the
federal insurer for employer-paid plans. Already holding a deficit
of $1.5 billion, the PBGC gets most of its revenues from premiums
paid by the companies.
   James B. Lockhart, executive director of the PBGC, said most of
the deficit stems from the beleaguered steel industry but noted
that pension funds of the major airlines are underfunded by about
$2 billion. Should they collapse, the burden would fall on the
federal agency.
   Papers obtained under the Freedom of Information Act showed that
Delta Air Lines and Pan American World Airways are among the
companies that have been fined by the PBGC for making late premium
payments. Both have underfunded plans.
   The PBGC also filed a contingency claim against Eastern Air
Lines to cover an estimated pension plan underfunding of $1.1
billion.
   The pension agency faces another threat from the Dallas-based
LTV Corp. The company declared bankruptcy in 1986 and saddled the
PBGC with claims of about $2.3 billion for more than 108,000
employees.
   LTV has since restructured and come out of bankruptcy, but
contends that the government should still have to pay its pension
obligations.
   The case is before the Supreme Court, where a ruling in favor of
LTV could open the door to similar maneuvers by other companies
seeking to dump their pension obligations on taxpayers.
   ``Like the federal savings and loan insurance program, the
pension termination insurance program is in dire financial
condition,'' the Justice Department says in a legal brief backing
the PBGC's suit.
</TEXT>

</DOC>