<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0142EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-CableTV-Sports Bjt   12-29 0579</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Cable TV-Sports, Bjt,570</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cable Industry Says There's More Sports on TV Than Ever Before</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAY ARNOLD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The cable television industry is firing back
at critics who claim sports on ``free television'' are becoming
extinct, saying there is more sports programming on TV than ever.
   Total broadcast network sports programming rose to a record
1,753 hours in 1988, an Olympics year, according to a study
released Thursday by the National Cable Television Association.
   At the same time, the study said:
   _Local broadcast stations increased their coverage of Major
League Baseball games to 1,647 games in the 1989 season, up from
1,536 in 1985.
   _ABC, CBS and NBC increased their college football coverage by
52 percent, from 27 regular season games in 1987 to 41 games in
1989.
   _National network broadcast coverage of both National Collegiate
Athletic Association regular and post-season games grew by 21
percent over the past four years, from 86 games in the 1986-87
season to 104 games in the current 1989-90 season.
   The cable group acknowledged the huge growth of cable TV sports
programming during the 1980s, but said it had been achieved
``without depleting broadcast television sports coverage.''
   The growth of cable ``has expanded viewers' sports programming
options by providing coverage of games and sports which have either
never been available to broadcasters or which have been ignored by
broadcast TV,'' NCTA said in the study, ``Fair Games: Broadcast and
Cable Coverage of Televised Sports.''
   The study comes at a time when critics in Congress and
broadcasting are saying cable is siphoning sports away from
so-called free television. At hearings in November, Sens. Howard
Metzenbaum, D-Ohio, and Arlen Specter, R-Pa., said sports such as
professional baseball and football could lose their antitrust
exemptions if they reduce the amount of free sports programming.
   Lawmakers have been particularly concerned about two recent
cable sports deals: a 12-year, $550 million agreement by the New
York Yankees giving all TV rights to the Madison Square Garden
cable network beginning in 1991; and Major League Baseball's
12-year, $400 million contract with the ESPN cable network to show
175 baseball games a year beginning next season.
   Madison Square Garden has been negotiating with a local
broadcaster in New York, WPIX, to provide 40 to 50 Yankees games a
season. WPIX previously has carried Yankees games.
   Under ESPN's contract, the national cable network will be able
to black out all other baseball coverage on Wednesday nights.
   National Football League executive Art Modell told the Senate
hearings there was ``a good chance'' the NFL will increase the
number of regular season games on cable next year to 16, up from
eight.
   Metzenbaum worried aloud that cable's ability to generate income
both through advertising and subscriptions gives it an advantage in
negotiating for sports programming.
   However, NBC recently agreed to a four-year contract that will
increase the number of nationally televised National Basketball
Association games.
   But the cable organization's study showed that regional cable
coverage of NBA games will surpass local broadcast station coverage
for the first time in the 1989-90 season: 790 games to 716 games.
Regional cable carried 638 games last season, compared with 679
games on local broadcast stations.
   ``The vast majority of cable's sports programming does not
consist of events or games which have `migrated' from over-the-air
television,'' the study said. ``Cable's increased presence in
sports programming has served to expand viewers' access to sporting
events without depleting broadcast television sports coverage.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>