<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0552EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     12-25 0621</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0638</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cold Front Settles Into Florida's Keys</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Arctic winds froze Florida early today, dropping temperatures
below the freezing mark from Jacksonville to Miami. Tampa was 28
degrees early Christmas morning, the same temperature as Anchorage,
Alaska.
   But in the Midwest, Christmas brought warmer weather.
Temperatures early today rose to 20s throughout the region _ even
Minneapolis, which had experienced nearly five straight days below
zero.
   On Sunday, the northern Florida town of Crestview reported a low
of 9 degrees. The warmest temperature in the state was 52 degrees
at Key West.
   During the past three days the latest surge of arctic air left a
trail of nearly 300 broken temperature marks from the Canadian
border to the Gulf of Mexico.
   The arctic blast combined with low pressure off the Carolina
coast to bring record snows and blizzard conditions to eastern
North Carolina. Snowfall totals ranged up to 15 inches in Pender
and New Hanover counties, and high winds whipped the snow into
drifts up to 8 feet.
   A snowfall of 15 inches at Wilmington, N.C., was their greatest
since records began in 1871. For parts of the Carolinas, today was
the first white Christmas on record.
   Record lows for the date on Sunday included: Albany, N.Y., minus
15; Allentown, Pa., minus 5; Apalacicola, Fla., 14; Baton Rouge,
La., 10; Brownsville, Texas, 18; Burlington, Vt., minus 18;
Charleston, W.Va., minus 9; Concord, N.H., minus 20; Daytona Beach,
Fla, 20; Fort Lauderdale, Fla, 30; Houston, 11; Key West, Fla., 44;
Lexington, Ky., minus 10.
   Also: Longview, Texas, 9; Meridian, Miss., 6; Miami, 31; Mobile,
Ala., 9; New Orleans, 15; Orlando, Fla., 22; Portland, Maine, minus
13; Syracuse, N.Y., minus 14; and Tallahassee, Fla., 13;
   In the Midwest, southerly winds brought much warmer weather.
Temperatures have been rising almost continuously since Saturday
morning, with Sunday afternoon higs in the 30s and 40s, with 50s
and 60s reported in the southern High Plains.
   A winter storm watch, however, was posted today for parts of
western and central upper Michigan near Lake Superior, where up to
a foot of snow is possible by Christmas evening.
   Southern California, meanwhile, recorded temperatures into the
80s on Sunday, with several cities reporting new record highs for
the date.
   The high for the nation Sunday was 89 degrees at Fallbrook,
Calif.
   Other reports at 3 a.m. EST today:
   _EAST: Albany, N.Y. 05, partly cloudy; Atlanta 25 snow; Boston
13 fair; Buffalo 16; Charleston, S.C., 15 fair; Chattanooga 24
snow; Cincinnati 16 cloudy; Cleveland 15 cloudy; Detroit 14 snow;
Hatteras 23 cloudy; Jacksonville 20 fair; Key West 49 cloudy;
Knoxville 22 cloudy; Macon 29 cloudy; Miami 31 fair; New York 15
fair; Philadelphia 11 fair; Pittsburgh 12 cloudy; Portland, Maine,
05 fair; Richmond 10 fair; Tampa 28.
   _CENTRAL: Birmingham 24 cloudy; Bismarck 34 fair; Chicago 14
cloudy; Denver 28 fair; Des Moines 32 foggy; Fort Worth 26;
Indianapolis 14 snow; Kansas City 29 fair; Little Rock 30 cloudy;
Louisville 18 snow; Memphis 26 cloudy; Nashville 20 snow; New
Orleans 27 fair; North Platte 31 fair; Oklahoma City 31 fair; Omaha
34 cloudy; Rapid City 40 windy; St. Louis 22 snow; Minneapolis-St.
Paul 29 foggy; Sault Ste. Marie 13 cloudy; San Antonio 25 fair.
   _WEST: Albuquerque 32 fair; Anchorage 28 cloudy; Boise 19 foggy;
Casper 29 fair; Fairbanks 02 cloudy; Great Falls 37; Las Vegas 46
fair; Los Angeles 64 fair; Medford 28 foggy; Pendleton 30 freezing
drizzle; Phoenix 54 fair; Portland, Ore., 34 fair; Reno 33 cloudy;
Salt Lake City 24 foggy; San Diego 52 foggy; San Francisco 45 fair;
Seattle 43 foggy; Spokane 34 drizzle.
   _INTERNATIONAL: Calgary 46 partly cloudy; Montreal 16 snow;
Ottawa 14 snow; Toronto 12 snow; Winnipeg 19 cloudy; Merida 57; San
Juan 74.
</TEXT>

</DOC>