<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0119 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 2159EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Romania     12-30 0359</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Romania,0371</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Israel Paid Ceausescu Cash for Jewish Immigrants</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israel paid thousands of dollars in cash to
Nicolae Ceausescu for every Romanian Jew he allowed to emigrate, an
Israeli newspaper reported.
   For years, Ceausescu received between $5,000 and $7,000 for
every visa issued to Jews, and some $50-$60 million ended up in the
dictator's own pocket, Yediot Aharonot said in its weekend edition.
   Ceausescu was executed on Christmas Day.
   Quoting reliable sources, the paper said official agencies
responsible for immigration in Israel, including the Foreign
Ministry and the quasi-governmental Jewish Agency, acknowledged
Ceausescu was paid but would not give specific figures.
   Israeli officials reportedly knew of the payoffs for years, but
they dared not expose or publicize it for fear it would halt
immigration from Romania, Yediot said.
   ``Our interest was the protection of the Jews in Romania and not
what kind of dictator Ceausescu was,'' the paper quoted an
unidentified official involved in the deals as saying.
   According to the paper, the money given Ceausescu was raised by
various Jewish organizations. It said reliable sources in the U.S.
Jewish community had confirmed that Ceausescu received the money
for the past 20 years.
   The English-language Jerusalem Post said the money was handed
over in suitcases filled with U.S. dollars.
   The head of the Immigration Committee in the Knesset, or
parliament, Michael Kliner, told Yediot that helping bring Romanian
Jews to Israel meant saving lives and therefore ``all necessary
steps were kosher.''
   A spokesman for the Foreign Ministry, Motti Amichai, said the
ministry knew of no such deals with Romania.
   Repeated telephone calls to the spokesman for the Jewish Agency
went unanswered.
   On Wednesday, Israel announced its support of the new Bucharest
regime but refrained from personally criticizing Ceausescu, who had
been highly regarded here for maintaining a longstanding alliance
with the Jewish state.
   Ceasescu was the only East bloc leader to maintain ties with
Israel after the 1967 Middle East war, when others broke links and
sided with the Arabs.
   About 400,000 Romanians have immigrated to Israel since its
founding in 1948 and some 1,500 have immigrated each year for the
past 10 years.
</TEXT>

</DOC>