<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0223 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1738EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-WallStreet 2ndLd-Writethru   12-29 0479</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Wall Street, 2nd Ld-Writethru,0498</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eds: Updates with revised NYSE index in 3rd from last graf.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHET CURRIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The stock market closed out a decade of dramatic
gains with a broad advance Friday as traders finished up their
yearend shuffle on Wall Street.
   The Dow Jones average of 30 industrials rose 20.90 to 2,753.20,
extending its gain for the week to 41.81 points.
   In 1989 the average climbed 584.63 points, or 26.96 percent,
capping off a rise for the decade of 1,914.46 points, or 228.25
percent.
   Advancing issues outnumbered declines by more than 2 to 1 in
nationwide trading of New York Stock Exchange-listed stocks, with
1,083 up, 484 down and 425 unchanged.
   Analysts said traders were buying cautiously in hopes that the
market could get off to a strong start on 1990 next week.
   Much anticipation has focused of late on the so-called ``January
effect,'' a historical tendency for the market in general and small
stocks in particular to do well in the early stages of a year.
   But brokers also cited persistent worries about the outlook for
the economy over the next several months.
   The Commerce Department reported this morning that the index of
leading economic indicators rose 0.1 percent in November after
posting a revised 0.3 percent decline the month before.
   Smith International dropped ~ to 12{ and Dresser Industries was
down ~ at 44~. Dresser said late Thursday it had called off its
planned acquisition of Smith International.
   Among actively traded blue chips, Philip Morris rose { to 41|;
International Business Machines held steadyu at 94[; American
Telephone &amp; Telegraph slipped [ to 45{, and American Express was up
1[ at 34~.
   Closed-end funds investing in single countries or regions of the
world remnained one of the market's hottest groups. Italy Fund
gained 2| to 17; Austria Fund 1 to 20{, and Templeton Emerging
Markets Fund { to 15\.
   One Price Clothing Stores, traded in the over-the-counter
market, fell 1} to 9. The company said it expected to report a
significant decline in its fourth-quarter earnings because of
sluggish sales.
   Volume on the floor of the Big Board came to 145.94 million
shares, up from 128.03 million in the previous session. Nationwide,
consolidated volume in NYSE-listed issues, including trades in
those stocks on regional exchanges and in the over-the-counter
market, totaled 185.52 million shares.
   As measured by Wilshire Associates' index of more than 5,000
actively traded stocks, the market increased $28.19 billion, or
0.83 percent, in value.
   The NYSE's composite index of all its listed common stocks
gained 1.45 to 195.04.
   Standard &amp; Poor's industrial index rose 2.99 to 403.49, and
S&amp;P's 500-stock composite index was up 2.73 at 353.40.
   The NASDAQ composite index for the over-the-counter market added
4.84 to 454.82. At the American Stock Exchange, the market value
index closed at 378.00, up 4.10.
</TEXT>

</DOC>