<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1936EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Hijacking-Passengers     12-17 0490</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hijacking-Passengers,0506</SECOND>
<HEAD>Air China Passengers Recall Hijack</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHLEEN MACLAY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Passengers on an Air China jet hijacked en
route from Beijing to New York said Sunday the flight was
frightening even though they didn't know the plane had been
commandeered until it landed in Japan.
   ``The rumors were spreading around the plane; we didn't know
what was happening,'' said Ann Ofstedal, who said she had been
studying for the past three years at a Beijing university.
   ``Even from talking to the crew, we could get very little
information,'' she told reporters at San Francisco International
Airport. ``They said they were also very worried.''
   Flight 981 was flying from Beijing to New York via Shanghai and
San Francisco on Saturday when Zhang Zhenai ordered the plane to
fly to Seoul, South Korea. Korean authorities refused permission to
land, and the plane was diverted to Fukuoka Airport on Japan's
southern island of Kyushu.
   There, a purser reportedly pushed Zhang out the plane's rear
door, shattering his legs and pelvis. He was being treated at a
Japanese hospital.
   Authorities reported that Zhang, a 35-year-old cotton factory
foreman, threatened crew members with a knife. He reportedly told
Japanese police he participated in pro-democracy demonstrations in
China last June and decided to flee after the crackdown.
   Ofstedal said the crew at one point asked passengers for rope.
Although no one was told why it was needed, she said there was
speculation an overwrought passenger needed to be subdued. Later,
she said she heard Zhang had been tied up with the rope with the
help of passengers.
   The plane returned to Beijing with 185 of its 200 passengers,
including Zhang's wife and 10-year-old son. Police and airline
officials said they did not know what happened to them, but foreign
reporters saw the wife led from the plane in handcuffs.
   The flight to New York then resumed on a new aircraft. China's
Civil Aviation Administration said most of the passengers were
Chinese. Japanese police said there were 19 non-Chinese, including
12 Americans.
   Ofstedal said she became suspicious when the flight from Beijing
to Shanghai, which normally takes 1 hour and 45 minutes, lasted
more than two hours and the plane spent more than an hour circling
a small island.
   ``People were acting very calm,'' she said, ``but it was
obviously very tense.''
   Wang Yuan of Beijing said she didn't realize a hijacking was
taking place, although she and others were worried because the
flight to Shanghai was taking so long.
   When the plane flew to Fukuoka, she said through a translator,
passengers knew something was wrong when they looked out the
windows and saw tall buildings and roadways full of cars, an
unusual sight in China.
   Asked if she was sympathetic to Zhang's comments that he was
motivated by fear of reprisals for speaking out against his
government, Ofstedal replied, ``I think he could have chosen a
better way.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>