<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1028EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Japan-Soviet     12-18 0519</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Japan-Soviet,0532</SECOND>
<HEAD>Japan-Soviet Peace Treaty Talks Stall Over Land Dispute</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ERIC TALMADGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Japanese and Soviet negotiators trying to draft a
treaty to formally end their World War II hostilities wound up
talks today with ``absolutely no new points of contact,'' a Foreign
Ministry official said.
   Although both governments have expressed a desire to improve
their chilly relations, the Japanese official said neither was
willing to compromise on a territorial dispute over several islands
in the southern Kurile chain held by the Soviets since the end of
the war in 1945.
   ``There were absolutely no new points of contact,'' said the
official, who briefed reporters on condition of anonymity. He said
the Soviet delegation called Soviet possession of the islands a
``postwar reality,'' and urged Japan to ``assume a stance that
recognizes the results of the war.''
   Japan, however, renewed its claim to what it calls the
``northern territories,'' a group of small islands off Hokkaido,
Japan's northernmost main island.
   The official said the Soviet delegation proposed the exchange of
draft treaties, but that Japan refused because of ``reservations
regarding the validity of such drafts'' while the territorial
dispute continues.
   Soviet Deputy Foreign Minister Igor Rogachev, head of the Soviet
delegation, was scheduled to continue talks with his Japanese
counterpart, Hisashi Owada, on a less formal level Tuesday, the
official said.
   Rogachev, completing a tour of five Asian nations, is scheduled
to fly back to Moscow Wednesday.
   The apparent failure of the talks comes less than two weeks
after Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu, prompted by rapid changes in
Eastern Europe and the recent mood of East-West detente, called for
a new era in bilateral relations.
   Exchanges between the two nations have recently increased, and
along with a scheduled visit of Foreign Minister Eduard
Shevardnadze next March, Soviet President Mikhail Gorbachev is
expected to visit Japan in 1991. If he does, he will be the first
Soviet president to do so.
   Foreign Ministry officials said their expectations for any new
developments were low going into the talks, but room for compromise
had been indicated earlier by Politburo member Alexander Yakovlev,
a close adviser to Gorbachev who during a visit to Tokyo last month
spoke of a possibility of a ``third route'' toward improved
relations.
   However, no progress toward opening up a new path was made in
today's talks, the official said, adding that both countries
continue to have a ``different approach.''
   ``What the Japanese call the territorial problem, we call the
definition of borders,'' he quoted a Soviet official as saying.
   He said most of the seven-hour talks dealt with the Soviet claim
to historical and legal jurisdiction over the islands, which they
say have belonged to Russia since the late 18th century and were
defined as Soviet territory by the Yalta Conference in 1945 and the
San Francisco Peace Treaty of 1951.
   Japan disputes those claims, countering that the islands have
been an integral part of its territory since ancient times. Tokyo
also claims a treaty signed in 1855 and a treaty ending the
Russo-Japanese War in 1905 give Japan rightful ownership.
</TEXT>

</DOC>