<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0232 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1548EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WKD--David Adv29-31   12-18 0690</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--David, Adv 29-31,0706</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv29</HEAD>
<HEAD>$adv30</HEAD>
<HEAD>$adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Weekend Editions, Dec. 29-31, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WEEKEND ENTERTAINMENT AND ARTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>The Artists: David Retropsective Ends Bicentennial</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARILYN AUGUST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   France ends a hectic year of bicentennial
celebrations with an immense retrospective of the works of
Jacques-Louis David, the painter who put his genius to the service
of politics _ and ultimately, his own ambition.
   On show through Feb. 12 in the Louvre are 245 paintings,
sketches and drawings by the man whose artwork and career reflect
the turbulent and bloody events of 200 years ago.
   ``The Oath of the Jeu de Paume'' and ``The Distribution of the
Eagles,'' monumental works too fragile to be moved, can be seen at
the Palace of Versailles.
   Few French artists were as problematic as David, who emerges
from history as hungry for power as the successive dictators he
served. He was chief propagandist of the revolution and later the
premier painter of Napoleon Bonaparte. After the emperor's fall,
David fled to Belgium where he lived until his death, too proud to
ask for a pardon from the restored Bourbon monarchy.
   His remains came home to France on Dec. 19 for a proper and
official burial in the Pere Lachaise cemetery in Paris.
   ``This is both a symbol of Franco-Belgian friendship as well as
a tribute to the man whose life and work were wedded to history,''
French culture minister Jack Lang said.
   A political propagandist, the artist immortalized such
revolutionary heroes as Jean-Paul Marat, whom he depicted dead in a
bathtub, and Joseph Bara, the young boy bayonetted for refusing to
salute the king and who cried ``Vive la Republique'' instead.
   More than any other artist, David's work recounted the events of
his day as they happened. ``The Coronation of the Emperor and the
Empress'' (1805-07) looks much like a modern-day news photo,
despite the fact that David painted himself into the spectator's
gallery and added Napoleon's mother when she was absent.
   In his private life, David was ruthless. Hated and loved, feared
and respected, he had few friends and confided in no one. Some say
he was plain cold-blooded. As a member of the Committee of General
Security, he signed many arrest warrants, sending some of his own
artist colleagues to the guillotine.
   Though he escaped death after Robespierre's fall, he did spend
some time in jail where he produced two of his most fascinating
works, a haunting self-portrait and the huge painting ``The Sabine
Women.''
   Inspired by a true-to-life historical event, David depicts the
ancient Sabine women thrusting themselves and their babies between
battling Romans and Sabine men.
   Often interpreted as an appeal for national reconciliation in
war-torn France, David wrote, ``That was my thought when I grabbed
the paintbrush.''
   Critics agree that modern art begins with David. An unparalled
draftsman and master of color, he abandonned the flowery,
decorative styles of his predecessors and embraced simple
structures and forms borrowed from classical painting and sculpture.
   His embrace of classical themes _ the result of a five-year stay
in Rome, in 1775-80 _ was interpreted in many different ways. For
Robespierre and his revolutionary followers, David was a precursor
of the values they invoked to justify the Reign of Terror.
   David's ``The Lictors Bringing Back to Brutus the Bodies of His
Sons'' (1789), characterized by Brutus' icy stoicism, was often
cited as a perfect example of the personal sacrifice necessary for
the overall good of the nation. The work, in fact, was a royal
commission and had nothing to do with the revolution.
   A gifted portraitist, David also immortalized the coquettish and
beautiful Juliette Recamier reclining on her day bed, and Napoleon
astride his rearing white horse crossing the St. Bernard Pass.
   He even flaunted the strict rules of the Academy to which he
belonged, depicting his subjects on huge canvasses normally
reserved for historical tableaux or religious themes.
   Visitors familiar with David's work will be surprised to see the
number of portraits David never finished, including the famed
Madame Recamier, because he often quarreled with his subjects.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Weekend Editions, Dec. 29-31</NOTE>

</DOC>