<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0650EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-SuspectedBomb     12-28 0318</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Suspected Bomb,0326</SECOND>
<HEAD>Suspicious Package Found, Federal Building Evacuated</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GREENVILLE, Miss. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A bomb squad discovered sex and drug
education pamphlets in a suspicious parcel addressed to schools
with the largest black student bodies, officials said.
   ``We classified it as a suspicious package. We have since then
been able to open it. ... It contained harmless sex and drug
education material,'' Maj. Marvin Minor, the deputy police chief,
said Wednesday evening.
   The parcel was addressed to ``the principal of the largest black
high school in Greenville and to the school that had the most black
children,'' said Assistant Superintendent Arthur Peyton.
Greenville's public school system is mostly black.
   After the parcel was discovered Wednesday morning, 105 workers
were evacuated for nearly two hours from the federal building,
which includes the post office. Other buildings in a two-block
radius also were evacuated.
   Police took the padded parcel to a remote area near the
Mississippi River, where they were joined by an explosives handling
team from Pine Bluff, Ark. Agents from the U.S. Bureau of Alcohol,
Tobacco and Firearms, FBI and U.S. Marshals Service also were on
the scene.
   ``It just so happened to look like a bomb,'' Minor said. ``It
was sent by some guy from Washington, D.C.''
   Minor identified the man only as ``Rev. Babb.''
   Also Wednesday, authorities in Charlotte, N.C., removed a
package from the porch of state District Judge Bill Constangy's
home and destroyed it, discovering it held only a doll, police said.
   Authorities were investigating whether the incidents were
related to a spate of mail or package bombs directed against
judges, courts, attorneys and civil rights organizations in
Alabama, Georgia, Florida and Maryland.
   Three of those bombs exploded, killing a federal judge in a
Birmingham, Ala., suburb Dec. 16 and a black civil rights attorney
in Savannah, Ga., on Dec. 18. A Hagerstown, Md., judge was wounded
in the third incident last week.
</TEXT>

</DOC>