<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0228 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 2100EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f BC-WeeklyWallStreet Adv30-31-1stLd-Writethru   12-29 0661</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Weekly Wall Street, Adv 30-31-1st Ld-Writethru,0685</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv 30</HEAD>
<HEAD>$adv 31</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Weekend Editions Dec. 30-31</HEAD>
<HEAD>Stock Market Played Favorites in '89</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 16th graf pvs ``Other readings ...'' to CORRECT New York
Stock Exchange composite index per late change by NYSE. Pickup 17th graf
``Volume on ...''</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHET CURRIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The stock market put a final flourish on the
``Money Decade'' by climbing to record highs in 1989.
   But the year's advance paid out its benefits very unevenly _ for
example, rewarding investors in energy while stinting on high
technology and industrial America.
   Many of the market's biggest winners and losers for the year
underwent drastic form reversals from earlier in the decade.
   Anyone who witnessed the depression of the mid-1980s in the
nation's ``oil patch'' might have been startled to see the list of
1989's best performing stock groups, as compiled by Dow Jones &amp; Co.
through Dec. 26.
   Oil drilling ranked No. 1, up 87.02 percent; oilfield equipment
and services No. 3, up 56.26 percent, and pipelines No. 6, up 52.93
percent.
   Their resurgence heralded a rebound in prices of energy
commodities, which was given extra impetus by a blast of frigid
winter weather across much of the nation in the last few weeks of
the decade.
   ``Energy will be an enduring theme throughout the '90s,''
asserted John Connolly, an analyst at Dean Witter Reynolds Inc.
   ``With U.S. oil production clearly in decline, the non-OPEC free
world has now flattened out. Meanwhile, demand is rising inexorably
as conservation and substitution wane.''
   At the other end of the spectrum stood the computer, its image
badly faded in the investment world from the moment just a few
years earlier when Time magazine accorded it the status of
``machine of the year.''
   Computer stocks, down 18.61 percent, had an uncontested hold on
last place in the Dow Jones group rankings for a year marked by a
steady stream of earnings disappointments in the industry.
   The most celebrated downer among the computer stocks was
International Business Machines, which fell to its lowest levels
since 1983 and finished the year below 100, far short of the peak
of 175~ it reached in 1987.
   But IBM, the long-time darling of investing institutions, was by
no means alone in the doghouse. Unisys, the product of a 1986
merger between Burroughs and Sperry, and Prime Computer both
sustained drops of more than 50 percent at their low points for the
year.
   The question many investors were asking as the 1990s began: Was
the earnings growth potential of the computer dissipating, turning
it into just another cyclical industrial commodity?
   Between extremes like that, the Dow Jones average of 30
industrials rose 41.81 points in the last week of the year to
2,753.20.
   That left the average up 584.63 points, or 26.96 percent, for
1989, and up 1,914.46 points, or 228.25 percent, for the decade.
   Other readings for the week showed the New York Stock Exchange
composite index up 3.09 at 195.04; the NASDAQ composite index for
the over-the-counter market up 10.25 at 454.82, and the American
Stock Exchange market value index up 7.16 at 378.00.
   Volume on the Big Board averaged 121.33 million shares a day,
against 168.70 million the week before.
   Some of the brightest stars among individual stocks for 1989
were closed-end investment companies formed in recent years to
invest in the stock markets of countries as diverse as Switzerland
and the Philippines.
   The Spain, Malaysia, Thai and Asia Pacific funds all ranked high
on the list of percentage gainers. They were joined as the year
drew to a close by the Germany and Austria funds, amid intense
demand for potential beneficiaries of the opening of Eastern Europe.
   That underscored one point on which most Wall Streeters readily
agreed: Wherever the markets go in the '90s, the script is likely
to be played out on a truly global stage.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Weekend Editions Dec. 30-31</NOTE>

</DOC>