<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0117 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1951EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-FamilySlaying     12-26 0449</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Family Slaying,0462</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police: Bodies of Murdered Family Set On Fire</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DRYDEN, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police on Tuesday were looking to question a
bicyclist seen riding near this small upstate New York town shortly
before a family of four was shot to death and set afire in their
suburban home.
   Warren Anthony Harris, 39, his wife, Delores, 41, their
daughter, Shelby, 15, and son, Marc, 11, were found dead Saturday
morning after neighbors in the affluent suburb of Ellis Hollow
heard their fire alarm and called authorities.
   All four had been shot once through the head between 6 p.m. and
10:30 p.m. Friday.
   Police have given no motive for the crime, although they said
some money may have been taken from the purse and wallet of the
Harris couple. Investigators said there was no evidence of a
break-in, but an inside telephone wire was pulled from the phone.
   A bicyclist riding in near zero-degree weather was seen at about
4:30 p.m. last Friday heading toward Dryden along a road where the
family lived, state police said.
   A witness saw the bicyclist but could not describe the sex, race
or age because the rider was wearing a parka, said Capt. Carl
Shaver of the state police's Bureau of Criminal Investigations.
   Three of the victims were tied up in one room before being shot
while the fourth was found on the floor of another room, said Capt.
Robert J. Farrand, acting commander of state police Troop C. The
bodies of all four then were doused with gasoline and set on fire,
Farrand said.
   Violence is relatively uncommon in the area. The deaths raised
the number of killings to only six this year around Ithaca, a city
of 26,000 that is home to Cornell University. The Harrises lived
between Ithaca and Dryden, about 10 miles to the east.
   The family's van was found Saturday about 5 miles east of their
home at an Ithaca shopping center. Police believe the killer or
killers used the van to flee.
   Shaver said he felt only one person was involved in the
killings, but he said that had not been firmly established.
   Autopsies were begun Sunday at the Onondaga County Medical
Examiner's office. Results were expected to be released Wednesday
or Thursday, police said.
   ``They are doing an extremely thorough, detailed job,'' Shaver
said. Medical examiners were looking not only for the cause of
death but also for any indication of what happened to the Harrises
before they were killed.
   Deanco Inc., an Ithaca-based electronics distributor where
Warren Harris was employed as East Coast sales director, is
offering a $5,000 reward for any information that leads to an
arrest of the killer, state police said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>