<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0093 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1450EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Communism     12-28 0611</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Communism,0635</SECOND>
<HEAD>Despite Revolt, Communists Still Hold Power</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERRY LEONARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Romanians still learning to openly
question their government said Thursday they are nervous about the
number of former Communists leading their revolution.
   Less than a week after Communist dictator Nicolae Ceausescu was
overthrown, captured and executed by a popular revolt, Romanians
are sure of only one thing: they won't turn back.
   ``We will continue the revolution until we get democracy,'' said
Valentin Hornicar, who was with the student protesters occupying
the Communist Party's Central Committee building.
   ``We want a real democracy with a government and an opposition.
There is no way back. We suffered too much,'' he said.
   Romania's interim government is a group of intellectuals,
dissidents and disaffected former Communist officials who call
themselves the National Salvation Committee.
   The committee has promised free elections by April and has
repealed some of Ceausescu's most repressive laws.
   ``I don't trust this government because it includes Communists.
They turned once, they could turn again,'' said Hornicar, 26.
   ``This is the symbol of power in this country,'' he said,
gesturing to the massive Central Committee building.
   ``We want the government to come here and say who elected
them,'' Hornicar said. ``They think that if they change some of
Ceausescu's hated laws that will be enough. It is not enough.''
   Others offered support to the interim government but tempered it
with concern about former Communists in its ranks.
   ``Not all the people have made up their minds on this thing,''
said Aurel Palea, a computer technician.
   ``I trust this government,'' he said. ``But there are Communist
members in this government. We only hope they want to help and to
make something for this country.''
   The National Salvation Committee decided at a meeting last night
to separate government from political functions, with the committee
itself acting as a makeshift legislature, Western diplomats said.
   The diplomats, who asked not to be further identified, said the
fluid membership of the committee originally consisting of 37
people, had been expanded to 101, including representatives from
all of Romania's 40 regions.
   The committee includes some prominent ex-Communists who had been
ousted or demoted for criticizing Ceausescu. They include newly
chosen President Ion Iliescu, former Foreign Minister Corneliu
Manescu and Silviu Brucan, former ambassador to the United States.
   Another leading member is Dumitru Mazilu, a diplomat under house
arrest for most of the last two years because he refused to doctor
a report for the U.N. Human Rights Commission in Geneva.
   Other prominent members are grass-roots dissidents, such as
University Professor Doina Cornea, clergyman Laszlo Toekes and poet
Mircea Dinescu.
   But even Dinescu was a member of the Communist Party until last
spring.
   Diplomats note that Communist Party membership was virtually
automatic for anybody in leading positions.
   ``The Communists are compromised. Communism made it to power
with terrorism, and now it must be destroyed everywhere. The people
will not be fooled again,'' said Gheorghe Tagarta, 40.
   But university librarian Ion Visoiu said in Romania everyone had
to be a Communist of a sort just to work.
   ``You can't compare us with the other Eastern European countries
that have changed. They did it more slowly. Their opposition was
better organized.
   ``Structurally, we are still peasants. We still think like
peasants. We will make a lot of political mistakes, but in time we
will have a good thing,'' he said.
   Visoiu said he has confidence in Iliescu and the new government,
and he said it is trying to recruit the best experts to run the
country.
   ``My worry is that the enthusiasm of the moment will pass too
soon,'' Visoiu said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>