<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0138 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1553EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SpringBreak     12-22 0342</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Spring Break,0351</SECOND>
<HEAD>Daytona Beach Wants to Tone Down Spring Break</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DAYTONA BEACH, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Daytona Beach has established a
spring break task force to prevent a repeat of destruction and
chaos caused last March by an estimated 400,000 revelers.
   ``Spring break in 1989 was totally out of control,'' Mayor Larry
Kelly told the Sun-Sentinel in Fort Lauderdale. ``Frankly, there
was an attitude by certain businesses and public officials to let
it all hang loose. And I think it was a serious mistake.''
   Daytona Beach's problem sounded familiar to officials down the
coast in Fort Lauderdale. They had told the spring break crowd
three years ago it was no longer welcome in Fort Lauderdale.
   Daytona Beach began a campaign to lure the young vacationers to
their city. But now, the task force will study how it might follow
Fort Lauderdale's lead to tone down the partying.
   Last March, Daytona Beach private and public property was
destroyed and visitors urinated in back yards, brawled in the
streets and more. The experience prompted the establishment of the
Spring Break Festival Task Force.
   ``The accent is on that third word because that's what we're
trying to make it _ a festival instead of a free-for-all,'' said
Suzanne Smith, director of special events for the Daytona Beach
Chamber of Commerce.
   Fort Lauderdale Mayor Bob Cox once told Kelly on network
television that he'd be only too glad to let Daytona Beach become
the new mecca for spring break.
   ``He turned to me and said, `You can have them,''' the Daytona
Beach mayor recalled. ``And I got them.''
   City officials and business leaders in Daytona Beach eager to
boost local revenues mounted expensive advertising campaigns
touting their sandy shores to vacation-hungry college students no
longer wanted in Fort Lauderdale.
   Cox said he would gladly share tips with Daytona Beach officials
on Fort Lauderdale's successful steps to shed its decades-old
party-time image.
   He said two important measures include cracking down on alcohol
on the beach and erecting walls along the Strip to separate
pedestrians from motorists.
</TEXT>

</DOC>