<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0288 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1649EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-CenTrust-Paul     12-20 0546</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-CenTrust-Paul,0567</SECOND>
<HEAD>State: Thrift Chairman Used Deposits as `His Own Public Piggy Bank'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CURT ANDERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TALLAHASSEE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   State officials took action Wednesday
to oust the head of Florida's largest savings and loan, claiming he
used $45 million in depositors' money to bankroll an art collection
and extravagant lifestyle.
   David L. Paul, chairman and chief executive officer of CenTrust
Bank of Miami, has 21 days to resign or contest a complaint filed
by Comptroller Gerald Lewis. A statement released by CenTrust said
Paul would ``vigorously oppose'' removal.
   ``Paul maintained an opulent lifestyle largely at the expense of
the association and generally treated a federally insured financial
institution and public company as it if were his own public piggy
bank,'' Lewis said in the complaint.
   The complaint claimed Paul violated his duty as officer of a
financial institution by using CenTrust employees to perform
personal services, charging the company for personal bills and
buying luxuries.
   It cited $30 million in art bought with CenTrust funds,
including $12 million paid for Peter Paul Rudens' ``Portrait of a
Man as Mars.'' Some of the paintings were kept at Paul's Miami
Beach home before state regulators ordered them sold.
   The complaint also questioned Paul's $4.8 million salary from
January 1988 to September 1989, when the thrift suffered pre-tax
operating losses of $76 million.
   CenTrust said in a statement the charges were not justified and
the thrift had improved net worth signficantly during Paul's six
years in charge, and accused the comptroller of a ``campaign of
harassment and disinformation.''
   CenTrust, with $9 billion in assets, is Florida's largest thrift
and the 22nd largest in the country. It has 70 branches, most in
south Florida.
   But the thrift has steadily lost money for more than a year,
including $9.1 million in the quarter ended Sept. 30.
   The comptroller's complaint was filed 12 days after federal
regulators, also citing CenTrust's lavish spending practices,
ordered the institution to stop squandering assets.
   The U.S. Office of Thrift Supervision barred CenTrust from
increasing executives' salaries, ordered it to sell a $233,000
sailboat and prohibited CenTrust from spending any more money on
Paul's yacht, the Grand Cru.
   Other expenses questioned by Lewis include:
   _A $6.1 million CenTrust loan to Paul to buy and improve his
house and property, as well as payment by CenTrust of telephone,
garbage and lawn bills in 1986-87.
   _A $5 million executive retirement system begun in 1986 with
deposits in an English bank. Lewis contends the system has
insufficient documentation.
   _$1.4 million a year to lease a corporate jet and hangar at
Miami International Airport as well as $26,000 a year for a
Mercedes-Benz limousine, $40,000 to purchase a Lincoln limousine
kept in New York and $33,000 in other car expenses.
   _$363,000 for security guard service at Paul's home the past two
years.
   _$150,000 in bank assets kept at Paul's home, including security
equipment, video cameras, office supplies, telephones and air
conditioners.
   _$47,000 spent by Paul in 1988 during a 35-night stay at a New
York hotel. The average daily expense was $1,186.
   CenTrust has sought federal approval to sell 63 branches and
their accounts to Great Western Financial of Beverly Hills, Calif.
CenTrust also is planning to convert from a state charter to a
federal charter.
</TEXT>

</DOC>