<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0108 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 2223EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RetirementHomeFire 1stLd-Writethru a0566 12-25 0649</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Retirement Home Fire, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0566,0661</SECOND>
<HEAD>Authorities Confirm 16 Dead In Retirement Home Fire; Cause Unknown</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 3 grafs after 9th graf, `The fire...' to UPDATE with comment
from building management on sprinklers.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto XJC1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DUNCAN MANSFIELD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHNSON CITY, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Christmas Eve fire that killed 16
and injured dozens at a high-rise retirement home might have been
worse if so many people hadn't been away for the holiday,
authorities said Monday.
   Officials accounted for 10 of 11 residents who had been listed
as missing after the blaze at the 11-story John Sevier Retirement
Center. The 11th person is also believed to have been away at the
time, they said.
   ``I can't think of a worse time, on Christmas Eve,'' said P.C.
Snapp, mayor of this town of 40,000. ``On the other hand, it could
have been a good time because a number of people had gone to visit
relatives.''
   The blaze surged through the lower floors of the brick building,
sending thick smoke to the floors above. Residents of upper floors
waved flashlights and screamed for help from the windows of their
smoke-filled apartments.
   About 50 people were injured, including about 15 firefighters,
some of whom also suffered frostbite. Most were treated for smoke
inhalation and released. At least one person was seriously burned,
said Dan Blevins, spokesman for Northside Hospital.
   The cause of the fire was under investigation.
   ``My personal feelings are, it was an accidental fire,'' said
Lt. George Leonard, city fire marshal.
   The building, a former hotel renovated in 1977 and turned into
an apartments for retirees, didn't have sprinklers but had water
hoses on each floor.
   The fire marshal said the building complied with fire codes at
the time of its renovation. If the building were renovated today it
would be required to have sprinklers. ``Basically, it was not an
unsafe building,'' Leonard said.
   The John Sevier Partnership, which owns the building, had
planned to have a $100,000 sprinkler system installed in the
spring, said Grant Trivett of M&amp;M Properties, which manages the
building.
   ``We didn't feel uncomfortable with the safety of the building.
We just had seen fires, basically on TV and other places. The
comment was made that the sprinkler system would have been a
benefit ...,'' Trivett said Monday night.
   ``If it's renovated, it will be renovated to today's codes. You
know, it would be a shame to not utilize the building in the
future,'' Trivett said.
   In October, a resident died in a fire in the building when a
kerosene heater, apparently mistakenly filled with gasoline,
ignited his apartment.
   Two of the victims Sunday were people who had been visiting
residents when the fire alarms sounded at 5:11 p.m. In all, nearly
150 people lived in the building.
   As many as 250 firefighters fought the fire, which was brought
under control by midnight.
   Fire Chief Doug Buckles said the fire was believed to have begun
on the first or second story, but the deaths occurred on the higher
floors, probably because of the smoke.
   ``We began hearing fire alarms go off, but they were not loud
enough that we realized what it was,'' said Ben Peterson, who was
visiting his grandmother on the fourth floor. ``By the time we
finally realized what it was and went into the hall, it was full of
smoke.''
   ``It was terrible last night. It was a terrible ordeal,'' said
Samuel E. Williams, 52.
   ``I'm like other people, I'd like to know what caused that fire
because it was so fast. It was just like that,'' Williams said,
snapping his fingers. He said he escaped from his third-floor
apartment through billowing smoke.
   ``What really got to me, after we were out on the street and
looking up,'' he said, ``we saw people laying out their windows,
saying, `Help me!' And we couldn't help them.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>