<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0155EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Cuba-Nuclear     12-29 0541</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Cuba-Nuclear,540</SECOND>
<HEAD>Defector Says Castro Had Plan for Attack on Florida Site</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In 1983, during a time of tension in the
Caribbean, a ``hysterical'' Cuban President Fidel Castro developed
a contingency plan to launch an air strike against a nuclear power
facility in south Florida, according to a Cuban defector.
   Gen. Rafael del Pino, who defected to the United States in 1986,
said Castro was worried about a possible U.S. blockade of Cuba at
the time of the U.S.-led invasion of Grenada in October 1983.
   Del Pino said Castro summoned the high military command and
ordered them, as a contingency, to have the computers aboard MiG-23
fighter planes programmed to fly to a nuclear energy plant in south
Florida.
   An air strike was to have been ordered if there were ``some type
of blockade of Cuba, some type of reaction on the part of the
United States, a product of the situation in Grenada,'' he said.
   The spokesman at the Cuban diplomatic mission in Washington was
unavailable for comment Thursday on del Pino's allegations.
   The invasion of Grenada generated anxiety in Cuba because the
two governments had established close political and military ties.
Cuban officials were concerned that Cuba might be the next target
of the Reagan administration but no action was taken.
   Del Pino said Castro has a ``holocaust temperament'' that
emerges during difficult periods. At the time of Grenada, he said,
Castro was ``hysterical.''
   Del Pino, the highest ranking Cuban ever to defect, commented in
an interview with Radio Marti, the Voice of America broadcast
operation to Cuba. A transcript was made available Thursday.
   The installation del Pino was referring to apparently was Turkey
Point, about 24 miles south of Miami where two nuclear generators
are located. The facility is operated by Florida Power &amp; Light Co.
and is adjacent to Homestead Air Force Base, which closely monitors
all incoming flights in the area.
   According to del Pino, the Cuban MiG's are equipped with
conventional as opposed to nuclear bombs.
   Nonetheless, he said, Castro ``doesn't realize that if this
plant is destroyed, it would not only annihilate all the Cubans in
Miami but would also be much worse than Chernobyl because the
radioactivity would fall on Cuba. In other words, 90 miles away,
the Cuban people would be affected because of the absurd reaction
of that man (Castro).''
   Chernobyl is the site in the Soviet Union where a major accident
occurred at a nuclear power facility in 1986.
   Unlike the Chernobyl plant, all active commercial U.S. nuclear
reactors are surrounded by steel-reinforced concrete shells to
prevent the release of radioactivity in an accident. But the shells
are not meant to shield the reactor against bombs, according to
Frank Ingraham, a Nuclear Regulatory Commission spokesman.
   Dale Thomas, a spokesman at Florida Power &amp; Light, declined
comment when asked if the firm has taken into account the
possibility of an attack by Cuban planes.
   He said the company's security precautions are not public
information for the most part. He added that the company does have
an emergency planning zone extending 10 miles from the Turkey Point
installations. Among other steps, the plan includes procedures for
evacuating all residents within the zone.
</TEXT>

</DOC>