<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0184 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2026EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-FarmIncome     12-20 0387</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Farm Income,400</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report Changes Farm Income Figures</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Agriculture Department report Wednesday
showed that farmers didn't make as much money the last few years as
agency economists had been reporting.
   The Economic Research Service, the professional USDA agency that
keeps the financial books on agriculture, issued revised estimates
reflecting higher expenses than had been used in the earlier
computations.
   One of the effects was to reduce the net cash income of farmers
_ the money left over after deducting cash expenses from gross cash
proceeds during the calendar year. It includes government payments
and proceeds from crops grown in earlier years.
   The revisions, based on 1987 figures from the federal census of
agriculture, showed that net cash income in 1987 was $54.5 billion
instead of the $57.7 billion reported as recently as a month ago.
   In 1988, according to te revisions, net cash income of farmers
rose to $57.2 billion _ not the $59.9 billion stated previously.
   This year, according to the agency's new report, the net cash
income of farmers may be in the range of $52 billion to $57
billion. That is unchanged from the earlier forecast.
   Economist Greg Gajewski, who oversees preparation of the monthly
report, said that the 1987 census benchmark now being used showed
that farm expenses turn out about 3 percent higher than had been
estimated earlier.
   ``It suggests farmers did a little less well than we thought
they were doing,'' Gajewski said in a telephone interview.
   But he noted that despite the downward revisions, the new income
numbers for those years are still records and that ``the rebound
from the financial crisis is still very real.''
   The revised figures also prompted changes in another method of
farm accounting used by the agency. That involves ``net farm
income,'' which measures the value of production, including federal
payments, in a specific year. Changes in the value of crop and
livestock inventories are part of the annual accounting.
   Under this method, net farm income in 1987 was $43.5 billion
instead of the $47.1 billion reported previously. In 1988, net farm
income was revised to $42.7 billion from $45.7 billion.
   This year's estimate was pegged at $48 billion instead of in a
range of $48 billion to $53 billion used a month ago.
</TEXT>

</DOC>