<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0171 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1750EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-PanamaPool-Witches     12-22 0359</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama Pool-Witches,350</SECOND>
<HEAD>The ``Witches'' House</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   EDITOR'S NOTE: The following is from a pool dispatch.
   FORT AMADOR, Panama (AP) _ U.S. military officers showed off a
house near Panamanian Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega's barracks where
they said he ``kept his Brazilian witches.''
   Inside they confiscated a packet of cocaine which had been
wrapped in a banana leaf and placed in a freezer.
   It was part of the 50 pounds of cocaine they said they found in
the Panamanian portion of Fort Amador, a shared U.S.-Panamanian
military facility.
   U.S. authorities said a bucket containing a rusty-red looking
substance in an upstairs bathroom was blood used in rituals.
   Spread out on a pallet in an upstairs office were two dead,
smelly fish that looked like they had been placed on a bed of rice
with slices of carrots. The fish were ceremoniously adorned with
colored ribbons. Something in the shape of a rotted papaya split in
half was stuck with dozens of toothpicks.
   On a nearby desk were bowls of popcorn _ popped and unpopped. It
was cluttered with dead flowers, broken statues and a newspaper
photo of Noriega.
   ``General Noriega kept his Brazilian witches here. You all know
he was a big believer in witchcraft,'' said Col. Mike Snell of the
Task Force Bayonnette Command.
   ``This was the brewery for the witches, if you will,'' Snell
said.
   He said the cocaine had not been analyzed but added ``we're sure
it's cocaine.''
   As he began his tour, Snell said ``We're going to see some
things that remind you of voodoo cults.''
   He said Noriega had been spotted at the house in the last
several months.
   The cocaine had been removed but a small residue of a powdery
looking substance remained in the freezer.
   Snell said pipe bombs had been found in the house which
subsequently has been searched repeatedly for booby traps.
   Because of the continuing concern about booby traps, lights in
the house could not be turned on. Even with a flashlight it was
impossible to verify that the bucket of blood was that.
   In a bedroom, gold spikes heels, pantyhose, face cream and other
women's garmets were left.
</TEXT>

</DOC>