<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0175 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0941EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APonTV-NearDeath Adv01   12-29 0801</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP on TV-Near Death, Adv 01,0822</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv01</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Monday PMs, Jan. 1, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>New Frederick Wiseman Film Focuses On Hard Questions Of Life, Death</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARLENE LEVINSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAMBRIDGE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In a new documentary about the end of
life in a hospital intensive care unit, patients are dying,
husbands and wives weep and doctors talk about God and ethics.
   Frederick Wiseman wept making ``Near Death,'' his 23rd
documentary. But he says he's cheered by the thought-provoking and
often surprising results.
   Intensive care takes on new meaning here, where the dying peer
into the abyss and discover a rare sense of belonging. Here
physicians and nurses display exquisite sensitivity as they guide
patients and their families to choose comfort over heroics.
   ``A lot of people want to live in a community where people are
tuned in to each other and care for each other and listen to each
other,'' Wiseman said in an interview at his film studio here.
``For most of us, that doesn't happen.''
   In daily life, said Wiseman, ``we also have to deal with
banality and cruelty and indifference. A lot of these things are
filtered out in the intensive care unit.''
   Shot in black and white at Beth Israel Hospital in Boston and
nearly six hours long, the film scheduled to be broadcast on PBS
stations this month uses Wiseman's trademark fly-on-the-wall
technique.
   No narrator or talking heads intrude to explain things. It's
just a camera and a microphone watching and listening in as
families and the fatally ill reckon with death.
   In a hospital, however, death is a complicated business.
Technology sticks a wedge in the door to life. Machines and
powerful medicines allow us to gamble on one more day, one more
kiss goodbye, one more week or month or more in the land of the
living.
   While the notion of choosing when and how to die is eerie, it is
part of the modern way of death. Slightly more than half the deaths
in 1986, the last year for which such figures are available,
occurred in hospitals, according to the National Center for Health
Statistics.
   Wiseman's intention in making the film was to stimulate
discussion of what many of us and our relations may someday
encounter _ ``to show in some detail the kind of decisions people
have to make.''
   ``Near Death'' keeps the viewer in emotional suspense. What is
most riveting is the candor. This is no place to tip-toe with the
truth.
   ``If he breathes, he breathes. If he doesn't, it's in God's
hands,'' a doctor tells a patient's son.
   A nurse explains to an 83-year-old man: ``You're not going to
get better. It's sad and it's frustrating and it's anger-provoking.
But you're not going to get better.''
   The man smiles sadly. He listens. She continues, ``I want to
help you ... (but) I don't want to keep you alive unless you like
living. We're telling you what we know about your body and asking
you to make a decision ...''
   The man tells her wants to see his children.
   A wife cries to a husband slipping from her with every breath:
``He's my life. He's my life.''
   This is not the place to go gently into that good night.
Ghastly, ghostly lights shine to keep the dark out. Translucent
tubes gurgle. Electronic monitors hum and shoot across their
screens jagged, fragile traces: lifelines.
   Patients lie shrouded in their beds and stay tethered to the
life-saving machines. Sometimes the only sign of the tenacity of
life is a wiggle of a toe, a squeeze of the hand, a blink.
   Wiseman trained his camera on four people, two elderly men with
heart disease, a 33-year-old man whose chemotherapy for testicular
cancer turned his lungs to the density of cork, and an elderly
woman with severe difficulty breathing on her own.
   These patients, their spouses and their children agreed to have
their most intimate and painful moments filmed to give to others
what they would have liked for themselves, Wiseman said: the chance
to preview the ambiguities and uncertainties of the life-and-death
questions.
   But the patients and their kin are not alone in their suffering.
   A doctor named Scott is reassuring to patients and kind to their
families. But to his colleagues he talks often about his doubts _
and theirs.
   ``I'm quite nihilistic about what happens,'' he tells one
doctor. ``A lot of this stuff is not really relevant to making
quality of life all that much better. It's really rolling the rock
up the hill and having it come back down again. That's what a lot
of this is.''
   But he says later, ``God decides. We don't decide. These things
have a life of their own.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Mon PMs, Jan. 1</NOTE>

</DOC>