<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0233 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1725EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Dollar-Gold     12-19 0573</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dollar-Gold,0592</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar Mostly Higher, Gold Mixed</HEAD>
<HEAD>Precede LONDON BC</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dollar finished slightly higher Tuesday
against most major currencies but slipped against the Japanese yen
in quiet global foreign exchange dealings.
   Gold prices were narrowly mixed. Republic National Bank of New
York quoted a bid for gold as of 4 p.m. EST of $411.75 a troy
ounce, down $1 from Monday's late bid. Earlier, gold gained on New
York's Commodity Exchange and in Europe.
   Currency analysts said the pace of trading has slowed in recent
days as the yearend holidays approach and traders try to protect
whatever gains they may have made for the year.
   ``We are in a holiday trading period, and a lot of bank traders
are not as active as they had been,'' said James Merrill, senior
international economist for the financial services company
McCarthy, Crisanti &amp; Maffei.
   He said the currency markets appeared to be largely unaffected
by new government reports of a decline in housing starts and a
slightly bigger-than-expected rise in consumer prices last month.
   The 4.7 percent decline in housing starts indicated some
sluggishness in the economy, weakness that many analysts feel the
Federal Reserve will eventually respond to by lowering interest
rates.
   But the 0.4 percent rise in consumer prices was slightly
stronger than analysts had expected, and could delay the Fed's
credit relaxation.
   Dollar traders were also wary about making big commitments until
they get some indication from the two-day meeting of Federal
Reserve policymakers on what course they have charted for monetary
policy over the next few weeks.
   If the Fed moves to lower interest rates, the dollar could be
hurt since falling interest rates cut the returns foreigners get on
dollar-denominated investments.
   The dollar's decline against the yen was attributed to
speculation that the Bank of Japan may soon raise its key lending
rate. Japanese authorities denied the rumors of an imminent rate
hike, but speculation persisted that an increase would eventually
be necessary to shore up the yen.
   In Tokyo, the dollar fell 0.42 Japanese yen to close at 143.80
yen. Later, in London, the dollar was quoted at 143.80 yen. The
dollar fell to 143.65 yen in New York from 143.725 yen late Monday.
   The dollar gained against the British pound. In London, the
pound fell to $1.6005 from $1.6020 late Monday. In New York, the
pound fell to $1.6010 from $1.60685.
   Selected late dollar rates in New York, compared with late rates
Monday, included: 1.7365 West German marks, up from 1.7210; 1.5565
Swiss francs, up from 1.5410; 5.9275 French francs, up from 5.8800;
1,289.25 Italian lire, up from 1,285.00; and 1.16085 Canadian
dollars, up from 1.16075.
   Late dollar rates in Europe, compared with late rates Monday,
included: 1.7365 West German marks, up from 1.7245; 1.5615 Swiss
francs, up from 1.5480; 5.9300 French francs, up from 5.8890;
1.9575 Dutch guilders, up from 1.9455; 1,291.25 Italian lire, up
from 1,289.25; and 1.1613 Canadian dollars, up from 1.1610.
   On New York's Commodity Exchange, gold for current delivery
edged up 10 cents a troy ounce to $411.90.
   Earlier, gold rose to $413.75 a troy ounce in London from
$409.25 late Monday; to $414.00 in Zurich from $408.50 and to
$412.80 in Hong Kong from $410.97.
   On New York's Comex, silver for current delivery fell 3.8 cents
an ounce to $5.527. Silver rose in London to a late bid of $5.57 a
troy ounce from $5.55 late Monday.
</TEXT>

</DOC>