<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0085 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1342EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mandela     12-21 0541</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mandela,0556</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mandela, White Activist Meet After 28 Years</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto CPN1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SAHM VENTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PAARL, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jailed black leader Nelson Mandela
held an emotional reunion Thursday with an ailing, 84-year-old
white women who was his co-defendant in a landmark anti-apartheid
trial 28 years ago.
   Helen Joseph, who in the 1960s was one of the first whites
banned by the government, spent four hours with Mandela in Victor
Verster Prison near Cape Town.
   ``He was in very good form, full of jokes, full of laughter,''
Ms. Joseph said outside the prison gate. ``He looks forward to
coming home, but he doesn't know when it will be.''
   She described the meeting as a ``wonderful, friendly, loving
visit.''
   Mandela, 71, heads the outlawed African National Congress
guerrilla movement and is the country's best known black leader. He
has been imprisoned for more than 27 years and is serving a life
sentence for plotting to overthrow the white-run government, but
his release is widely expected within weeks.
   Mandela and Ms. Joseph both emerged as leading voices of the
anti-apartheid movement in the 1950s. They were among more than 150
codefendants at a marathon treason trial from 1956-61.
   Ms. Joseph, now confined to a wheelchair most of the time,
recalled how she and Mandela often traveled together to the
courthouse in Pretoria. To take their minds off the trial, they
would take turns picking out homes where they would want to live,
she said.
   All the accused were acquitted, but the trial made clear the
government's intention to clamp down on opponents. Mandela went
underground shortly after the trial to form the ANC's armed wing.
He was arrested in 1962 and has been imprisoned since.
   Ms. Joseph resumed her anti-apartheid activities after the
trial, but was placed under police restrictions, including house
arrest, for most of the 1960s and 1970s. Police lifted the
restrictions in 1982, when she was 77. A year later she was
arrested for singing and giving a clenched-fist, black power salute
while attending a treason trial.
   Last year the ANC awarded her its highest award for her
``outstanding contribution to the struggle to end apartheid and
transform South Africa into a united, democratic and non-racial
country.''
   She still goes to anti-apartheid rallies in her wheelchair and
is greeted with rousing cheers by black audiences.
   She said both she and Mandela were excited to see one another
for the first time in 28 years. All her previous requests to visit
Mandela had been turned down.
   She said Mandela has agreed to meet government leaders,
including President F.W. de Klerk, because ``the time has come for
peaceful talks between the government and the ANC.''
   ``The ANC can't give up the armed struggle at this stage, but he
(Mandela) is very hopeful,'' said Ms. Joseph.
   She said Mandela believes ``de Klerk is a sincere person, but
his limitation will be what his National Party government will
allow him to do. He feels de Klerk is not a free man.''
   De Klerk says he wants to end discrimination and bring blacks
into the national government within five years. However, he opposes
a one-man, one-vote system and envisions a mechanism that will give
whites veto power on major policy decisions.
</TEXT>

</DOC>