<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0290 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1719EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-WallStreet 1stLd-Writethru   12-20 0513</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Wall Street, 1st Ld-Writethru,0534</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eds: Updates with closing prices throughout.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHET CURRIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The stock market drifted through a trendless
session Wednesday, registering no strong reaction to the U.S.
military action in Panama.
   The Dow Jones average of 30 industrials dropped 7.68 to
2,687.93, extending its loss over the last five trading days to
73.16 points.
   But advancing issues nosed out declines in nationwide trading of
New York Stock Exchange-listed stocks, with 759 up, 749 down and
492 unchanged.
   Volume on the floor of the Big Board came to 176.52 million
shares, down from 186.06 million in the previous session.
Nationwide, consolidated volume in NYSE-listed issues, including
trades in those stocks on regional exchanges and in the
over-the-counter market, totaled 216.34 million shares.
   Analysts said investors were cautiously watching the situation
in Panama, but apparently not viewing it as any cause to make big
changes in their strategies.
   They noted that the prospective economic effects of the
confrontation, if any, remained unclear.
   At the same time, brokers said, stock traders appeared to draw
only brief encouragement from an upward revision in the latest
government figures on economic growth.
   The Commerce Department said the gross national product grew at
a 3.0 percent annual rate, after adjustment for inflation, in the
third quarter of the year, up from a previous estimate of 2.7
percent.
   Economists' projections remained gloomy, however, for the
results to be posted in the fourth quarter and the early stages of
1990.
   Citytrust Bancorp, which became the latest northeastern regional
banking company to increase its reserves against bad loans because
of a weak real estate market, fell 3 to 11. Citytrust also said it
was eliminating its quarterly dividend.
   Walt Disney tumbled 11] to 112 in selling attributed to
recession worries and a warier appraisal by some analysts of the
company's earnings outlook.
   Stride Rite dropped 3} to 23{ on word from the company said its
earnings for this year and next were likely to come in on the low
side of estimates.
   Late in the day, however, an investor group said it proposed to
buy Stride Rite for $32 a share.
   Helene Curtis Industries fell 3| to 25}. The company reported
earnings of 28 cents a share for the fiscal quarter ended Nov. 30,
down from 40 cents in the like period a year earlier.
   Among actively traded blue chips, American Telephone &amp; Telegraph
dropped 1\ to 44\; Philip Morris \ to 40[; McDonald's | to 32~;
International Business Machines [ to 94|, and General Electric ] to
62].
   As measured by Wilshire Associates' index of more than 5,000
actively traded stocks, the market increased $3.55 billion, or 0.11
percent, in value.
   The NYSE's composite index of all its listed common stocks edged
up .14 to 189.54.
   Standard &amp; Poor's industrial index slipped .60 to 391.86, and
S&amp;P's 500-stock composite index was up .38 at 342.84.
   The NASDAQ composite index for the over-the-counter market
rallied 2.59 to 436.94. At the American Stock Exchange, the market
value index closed at 368.18, up .23.
</TEXT>

</DOC>