<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0757EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Romania-Journalists 1stLd-Writethru   12-25 0593</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Journalists, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0488,0608</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Foreign Journalists Dead, Four Others And A Diplomat Wounded</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with Turkish journalist wounded;
picks up 3rd pvs, `The four...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TIMISOARA, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two foreign journalists have been
killed and five wounded, including two Americans, during fighting
between revolutionaries and forces loyal to deposed President
Nicolae Ceausescu.
   Danny Huwe, 42, a Belgian reporter for the Belgian VTM
television, was shot and killed by snipers late Sunday when he
tried to enter the capital from Sofia, Bulgaria, by car, VTM said
today.
   On Saturday, Jean-Louis Calderon of France's La Cinq TV station
was crushed to death by a tank in Bucharest as he was reporting on
the fighting.
   Emre Aygen, 30, a reporter for the Turkish state television TRT
was seriously wounded early today on the outskirts of Bucharest,
said Hale Tuna, a TRT official in Ankara, Turkey. Tuna said Aygen
was wounded in the head by sniper fire as he traveled with a group
of journalists.
   The four other journalists were wounded in the western city of
Timisoara, and three ambulances sent into Romania from Yugoslavia
to evacuate the journalists today. All four were expected to
survive.
   Three of the journalists _ John Daniszewski of The Associated
Press, John Tagliabue of The New York Times, and an Italian
photographer _ were wounded in separate incidents while driving in
cars.
   A Yugoslav reporter was shot while dashing through the streets
of the western Romanian city, 20 miles east of the Yugoslav border.
   A Yugoslav diplomat was grazed by a bullet.
   A group of uniformed men on Saturday night ordered a car
carrying Daniszewski and a Yugoslav reporter, Ljuba Pajic, to stop,
then opened fire as soon as Daniszewski stepped on the brakes.
   One bullet struck his arm and two others grazed his head, the
Yugoslav Consulate said, quoting Pajic, who was not injured. The
assailants fled after robbing the reporters, the consulate said.
   Daniszewski arrived in Yugoslavia today, where he was
hospitalized in satisfactory condition.
   It was not immediately clear whose side the assailants were on.
   The fighting, in which security forces loyal to Ceausescu are
pitted against anti-Ceausescu civilians and their allies in the
army, has been fierce in Timisoara, the cradle of the insurgency
that toppled the hard-line Communist dictator in a week.
   Louis D. Boccardi, the president and general manager of the AP,
said: ``The AP is doing everything possible to help John
Daniszewski.
   ``The events in Romania graphically show the dangers that
correspondents, AP and others, experience in reporting world news
and the courage and bravery they display in doing their jobs.''
   Tagliabue was wounded in the back by a sniper who fired on a car
carrying him and other reporters, said Bernard Gwertzman, foreign
editor of The New York Times. The exact nature of Tagliabue's
injury was not clear, Gwertzman said in New York, but the reporter
was reported in satisfactory condition at a Timisoara hospital.
Tagliabue is the younger brother of Paul Tagliabue, commissioner of
National Football League and a Washington lawyer.
   The Warsaw-based Daniszewski, 36, left Poland last week to cover
the Timisoara fighting. He has been the AP's Warsaw correspondent
since June 1987, reporting on the political upheaval that climaxed
this year with the installation of a non-Communist leadership in
Poland.
   An Ohio native whose parents live in the Dayton suburb of
Centerville, Daniszewski is a graduate of the University of
Pennsylvania and worked for the AP in Philadelphia, Harrisburg and
New York before joining the news agency's foreign service.
</TEXT>

</DOC>