<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0121EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-ChileanFruit     12-18 0623</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Chilean Fruit,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chilean Fruit Exporters Seek Better Sales After Cyanide Scare</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH MESCE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Grapes and other fruit from Chile are
beginning to arrive in the United States and exporters are hoping
for a banner year after last season's disastrous cyanide-poisoning
scare.
   Chilean fruit exporters have seen a substantial increase from
previous years in early orders from U.S. grocery chains, said David
Holzworth, a Washington attorney who represents the Chilean
Exporters Association.
   ``The biggest silver lining (of the cyanide scare) for the
industry has been the recognition by retailers of how important
Chilean fruit was to their produce sales,'' Holzworth said.
   He said produce sales for some of the large grocery chains were
off as much as 25 percent last March and April as a result of the
poisoning scare that kept Chilean fruit off the shelves for several
weeks.
   ``The importance of the products to the retail industry has come
home,'' he said. ``So we're looking at a very good year so far as a
result of that recognition.''
   The new season is proceeding under a cooperative agreement
signed by Chilean and U.S. officials that formalizes emergency
procedures to ensure the safety of fresh fruit exported from Chile.
   The memorandum of understanding outlines steps the two countries
would take to handle an emergency like the cyanide scare, should
another occur.
   Several ships have arrived in U.S. ports recently, bringing
early shipments from Chile, but the FDA sees no need to institute
special procedures for monitoring the produce, officials said.
   ``As far as Chilean fruit is concerned, we are in routine
coverage of the fruit,'' said Richard Davis, FDA's regional
director in Philadelphia.
   ``We normally would collect samples of fruit to be analyzed for
pesticides and we would also check for the presence of sulfites,
which is used as a preservative for grapes and only a certain
amount of it is allowed.''
   He added that the FDA is applying ``the same rules to Chilean
fruit as to any other fruit.''
   The scare began March 12, when the FDA announced that it had
found traces of cyanide in two grapes from Chile. Earlier in the
month, an anonymous caller to the U.S. embassy in the Chilean
capital of Santiago had threatened to inject cyanide in export
fruit.
   The FDA ordered Chilean fruit held in ports where it was coming
into the United States, urged stores to remove the fruit from their
shelves and began a series of special inspections to determine
whether any more fruit was contaminated.
   No other fruit was found to be tainted, but millions of dollars
worth of fruit had to be dumped because it had gone bad while it
was withheld from the market during the inspections. At the time,
Chilean exporters and U.S. importers said they lost about $240
million because of the health scare.
   The impact on the Chilean fruit industry is still being felt.
Holzworth said many small companies have gone out of business or
have been bought out by larger companies.
   Grapes constitute about 70 percent of the fruit Chile exports,
and virtually all of the fresh grapes sold in the United States
during the winter months are from Chile.
   Chile exported nearly 44 million crates of fruit to the United
States and Canada last winter, and 6 million crates had to be
dumped.
   This year, if the harvest continues to be good, Chilean
exporters expect to send as much as 48 million crates of fruit to
the United States and Canada, Holzworth said, and ``what you'll see
is the best of the best.''
   Exporters will be sending to U.S. markets ``the premium quality
fruit ... to make sure the initial market acceptance will be
high,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>