<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0122 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 2211EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Tutu     12-23 0391</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Tutu,0401</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tutu in Holy Land; Supports Palestinian State</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARIEH O'SULLIVAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Archbishop Desmond Tutu of South Africa told a
group of Moslem clerics and Palestinian activists Saturday that he
supports the Palestinian struggle for an independent state.
   He made the comment during a five-day Christmas pilgrimage to
the Holy Land that has angered some Israelis. The nation's two
chief rabbis have refused to meet with Tutu, and some Israelis say
the visit could provoke Christmas rioting among Palestinians.
   Near the Al Aqsa mosque, one of Islam's holiest sites, Tutu
bowed his head in a moment of silent prayer at a stone platform in
memory of more than 600 Palestinians killed by Christian militiamen
in 1982 at refugee camps near Beirut, Lebanon.
   ``We support the struggle of the Palestinian people in their
longing for statehood and independence,'' Tutu told assembled
Moslem clerics and Palestinian activists.
   Among about 30 Palestinian dignitaries was Feisal Husseini, a
leading activist in the occupied territories who supports the
Palestine Liberation Organization.
   ``We pray that the day will come soon when a Palestinian state
will exist side-by-side with a Jewish state and Arab and Jew will
hold hands together,'' Tutu said.
   ``We come as those who know suffering from the inside, and we
hope that our presence in this country will bring hope and
encouragement to the people who are the victims of injustice and
oppression.'' he said. ``We are struggling for our own
self-determination in South Africa.''
   Tutu, who won the Nobel Peace Prize in 1984 for his efforts to
end racial discrimination in his homeland, spent the morning in
meetings with Palestinian religious leaders. He then visited
Judaism's holiest site, the Western Wall in Jerusalem, where one
Orthodox Jew shouted ``Don't desecrate the wall!'' as Tutu
approached.
   Tutu met with Rabbi Yehuda Getz, the rabbi in charge of the
Western Wall, and prayed at the site while ultra-orthodox Jews sang
and danced in the background in celebration of the second night of
the Jewish holiday of Hanukkah.
   Earlier Saturday, Tutu, leader of South Africa's Anglican
Church, met with the patriarchs of the Latin, Greek Orthodox and
Armenian churches.
   The civil rights crusader arrived Friday for his visit. He was
scheduled to visit Bethlehem in the Israeli-occupied West Bank on
Christmas Eve and preach in Jerusalem on Christmas Day.
</TEXT>

</DOC>