<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0338EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-ColdRdp Bjt   12-25 0657</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Cold Rdp, Bjt,0685</SECOND>
<HEAD>White Christmas in Georgia, Carolinas as Cold Snap Persists</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserColor NY12</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL MOKRZYCKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The Carolinas and parts of Georgia had their first white
Christmas in at least a century and Florida utility officials asked
people not to use electric ovens to cook holiday turkeys today as a
stubborn cold wave refused to ease.
   Temperatures in northern Florida were lower than in Anchorage,
Alaska, this morning _ 22 in Jacksonville at 2 a.m. EST, compared
with 31 in Anchorage.
   One visitor to Florida wasn't complaining.
   ``This is nice. It's not Christmas without some cold,'' said
Louis Dussault of Montreal, strolling in Miami Beach with his wife
and two children.
   Florida Gov. Bob Martinez extended a state of emergency to
today, easing weight restrictions on roads and bridges to help
growers move freeze-damaged citrus and strawberry crops quickly.
   ``There is no one smiling in Florida agriculture today,'' said
Roy Parke of Parkesdale Farms in Plant City, self-proclaimed winter
strawberry capital of the nation.
   And though warmer weather creeped slowly eastward, it was too
late to prevent citrus crop devastation in the lower Rio Grande
Valley of Texas, where temperatures plunged to 11 degrees during
the weekend. Temperatures hit the low 50s there Sunday but dipped
below freezing again this morning.
   ``It's going to take probably weeks and maybe months to
determine how much damage we've had,'' said Richard Hensz, director
of the Texas A&amp;I University Citrus Center in Weslaco. ``But it's
very extensive.''
   The arctic blast has left a trail of nearly 300 broken records
from the Canadian border to the Gulf of Mexico since Friday, the
National Weather Service said. It it has been blamed for at least
83 deaths from the Plains to the East Coast since Dec. 15.
   It was a painfully cold Christmas for thousands of homeless. In
New York, despite the efforts of volunteers infused with the
holiday spirit, an estimated 38,000 homeless men, women and
children were expected to be without shelter today, said Peter
Smith, president of Partnership of the Homeless, a private shelter
network. He estimated New York city's homeless population at 82,000.
   Across the nation, Smith estimated, there are 720,000 people
without shelter _ 36 percent of the total 2 million homeless.
   The cold combined with a low-pressure system off the
mid-Atlantic coast Sunday to create blizzards in the Carolinas.
   Drifts stood up to 8 feet high in South Carolina, and
Wilmington, N.C., recorded its greatest snowfall ever, 15 inches,
eclipsing the record of 12{ inches on Feb. 9-10, 1973.
   The last white Christmas in Wilmington was in 1870, and for
North Carolina's Outer Banks it was 1874. Along the Georgia coast,
it was the first since at least 1871, the weather service said.
   The blizzard caused a 600-foot Navy tanker to run aground on the
Outer Banks. No fuel spilled and nobody was injured.
   The cold wave stranded travelers and overloaded power plants in
Florida.
   Transformers and electric cables overloaded despite rotating
blackouts. About 300,000 of the 3 million customers of Florida
Power &amp; Light Co. were without power Sunday, some for more than 10
hours, said Palm Beach district manager Bill Ellis.
   With many businesses and restaurants closed for the holiday,
utilities planned fewer blackouts overnight, but slow-cooking
turkey dinners on Christmas remained a problem, said Rick Janka,
spokesman for Florida Power Co. on the Gulf Coast.
   ``The Christmas tree lights won't be too much of a problem now,
but we still have to conserve higher energy uses like dishwashers
and ovens,'' Janka said.
   Among places recording temperatures in the single digits Sunday
were Ocala, Fla.; Athens, Atlanta and Columbus, Ga.; and Mobile,
Ala.
   Florida's governor mobilized National Guardsmen and other state
workers to rescue motorists from gridlocked, icy highways.
   But warmer weather in the Midwest began moving eastward.
Temperatures rose to 40 at Chamberlain, S.D., and into the 20s in
Minneapolis after nearly five straight days below zero.
</TEXT>

</DOC>