<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0113 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1634EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Harvard-Trademark 1stLd-Writethru a0607 12-28 0508</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Harvard-Trademark, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0607,0516</SECOND>
<HEAD>The Question Is: Will They Spell it Hahvud? ^Eds: SUBS last graf
to DELETE `a year.'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALLISON J. PUGH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAMBRIDGE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Harvard University, the first Ivy League
school, has become the last to try to protect its name with a
trademark after years of seeing it emblazoned on sweatshirts and
other goods around the world.
   Under new licensing procedures, towels, watches and boxer shorts
for the Crimson may still be allowed.
   But string bikinis? Maybe not.
   ``We just don't want it to be outrageous,'' said Ellen Mitchell
of the Harvard Office of Patents, Copyrights and Licensing. ``We
don't want to look silly.''
   More than 100 U.S. colleges and universities already issue
licenses for the use of their names, including the seven other Ivy
League colleges, according to the office of Robert Scott, vice
president for finance.
   Margot Naulleau, international licensing coordinator for
Champion Products Inc., one of the main suppliers of athletic wear
with college insignias, said Harvard _ America's oldest college _
was one of the last major schools in the nation to seek a trademark.
   ``It's simply that we are very old and very conservative. It
took us a long time to decide if it was something that we ought to
do,'' said Joyce Brinton, director of the Harvard patent office.
She said there was no incident that led to the decision to apply,
such as a particularly egregious product on the market.
   ``It was just that the time has come,'' she said.
   Before the Harvard Corporation decided in June to apply for a
trademark on their name from the U.S. Patent and Trademarking
Office, Brinton's office had inquiries from many manufacturers
about getting a license.
   Brinton said the trademark has not yet been approved but she
didn't anticipate any problems.
   ``I think most of the companies have felt uncomfortable that
they don't have a license from Harvard,'' she said. Those companies
worried about being left with hundreds of products if the school's
lawyers suddenly cracked down, she said.
   Harvard ran a few trial programs before moving toward licensing
on a broad scale. At the school's 350th anniversary in 1986,
Harvard wanted to ensure commemorative items were of high quality.
Another program licensing the trademark in Japan has been booming,
bringing in $130,000 in royalties annually.
   Under the new licensing procedure, if someone wants to make a
product bearing the name Harvard, Harvard University, or the
school's insignia, he must first show designs and samples to
demonstrate the quality of the product before Harvard will grant a
license.
   And the cost of renting the Harvard name? A bargain, Mitchell
said. Brinton said companies that market Harvard products pay a
flat fee of $300 and sales royalties of 7{ percent.
   Only a few licenses have been distributed so far. After a couple
of years, officials expect from $300,000 to $500,000 to come in a
year. But with an endowment of some $4.5 billion, the income from
licensing is a drop in the bucket.
</TEXT>

</DOC>