<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0548EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Romania-Timisoara     12-23 0737</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Timisoara,0763</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bittersweet Celebrations in Timisoara Over Ceausescu's Fall</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The first revolts against Nicolae Ceausescu that
led to his downfall occurred in the western Romanian city of
Timisoara, where thousands were said to have been killed by troops.
Here is a report from the city by an AP correspondent who traveled
overland from Yugoslavia.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By DUSAN STOJANOVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TIMISOARA, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The people who began the revolution
that toppled Nicolae Ceausescu danced and cheered when he fled
Bucharest, then cried bitterly over mass graves filled with the
victims of the dictator's henchmen.
   The bittersweet celebration occurred Friday in Timisoara, the
western city where thousands were reported killed in protests that
spread nationwide.
   Residents hurled the omnipresent portraits of Ceausescu onto
bonfires that blazed around town. They fed the flames with signs
ripped down from buildings that praised him and bore his platitudes
on building Communism.
   ``This is something we never expected to happen,'' said resident
Ingeborg Kziraska. ``The dictator is gone.''
   The streets of the Transylvanian city still showed signs of the
bloodbath that occurred when Ceausescu's security forces opened
fire on demonstrators last weekend. Shops were burned out and
official buildings heavily damaged.
   Kziraska spoke outside the cathedral where she said 30 children
had been gunned down.
   Inside the cathedral, a memorial service was under way with
about 2,000 people attending. Religious freedom _ and other civil
liberties _ were severely curtailed under Ceausescu's draconian
rule.
   Residents in the city estimated Friday that 2,000 to 4,500
people had been killed, although there was no way to verify those
figures. Police reportedly had opened fire on crowds shouting
``Bread!'' and ``Down with Ceausescu!''
   But Romanian radio, which was in the hands of the people who
toppled Ceausescu, said today that more than 12,000 people were
killed in Timisoara alone since the uprising began Dec. 15 with
demonstrations in the city.
   Yugoslav media said soldiers and police who refused to fire on
anti-government protesters in Timisoara were executed.
   The city itself became a symbol and its name was chanted at a
huge anti-Ceausescu protest in the capital of Bucharest on Thursday.
   Hundreds of people were digging up mass graves discovered in the
forest district of Timisoara, trying to find the remains of their
friends and relatives killed in last weekend's crackdown.
   Three such mass graves are believed to be holding up to 4,500
corpses of people massacred by the dreaded security forces on
Saturday, Sunday and Monday.
   Vasile Todorescu, an electrician, said he was trying to find his
20-year-old son, who disappeared during the unrest. He said corpses
had been transported by garbage trucks to the area and the drivers
were later shot by the police so that no witnesses whould be left.
   Civilians wearing ribbons on their sleeves were attempting to
maintain order in Timisoara, as people danced joyfully in the
streets and flashed ``V'' for victory signs.
   Many rode around in trucks. People waved Romanian flags with the
socialist emblem cut out of the middle. Others carried banners
calling for an end to repression.
   On Thursday, Timisoara was reported in the hands of a strike
committee that reportedly had occupied factories and official
buildings.
   But on Friday all 350,000 residents of the city that is 30 miles
from the Yugoslav and Hungarian borders and 500 miles from
Bucharest seemed to be on the streets.
   Intellectuals had formed a Committee for Socialist Democracy
this week that presented to Premier Constantin Dascalescu a series
of demands for Ceausescu's resignation, free elections and full
investigation of the weekend shooting.
   The intellectuals had also demanded the admission of foreign
journalists to Romania and publication of its demands.
   Western reporters, allowed into Romania on Friday for the first
time since the unrest was reported and the Bucharest leadership
sealed the country's borders, saw that nearly every other shop in
Timisoara had been gutted. Several official buildings had been
devastated.
   The protests in Timisaora grew out of an attempt by a few
hundred people Dec. 15 to prevent the arrest of a Reformed Church
pastor who had sought refuge in his church.
   The whereabouts of the ethnic Hungarian clergyman, the Rev.
Laszlo Toekes, was unknown until Friday, when Hungarian radio
reported that he was alive and was on his way to the Transylvanian
city of Tirgu Mures to celebrate services. Nearly half of the
population in that city is ethnic Hungarian.
</TEXT>

</DOC>