<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0757EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Vatican-Noriega     12-30 0394</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Vatican-Noriega,0405</SECOND>
<HEAD>Vatican Defends Action in Noriega Case, Says Talks with U.S. Continuing</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY BETH SHERIDAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VATICAN CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Vatican today declared it did not intend
to ``block the course of justice'' by giving refuge to ousted
Panamanian dictator Manuel Noriega, who is wanted in the United
States on drug trafficking charges.
   The Vatican Secretariat of State also said in a communique that
it was continuing to examine the case with U.S. authorities ``in a
spirit of serene collaboration'' in hopes of finding a
mutually-acceptable solution.
   It was the second day in a row that the Vatican issued
statements defending its actions in the Noriega case, but it was
the first official comment by the Secretariat of State, the Holy
See's highest administrative body.
   The Vatican has been under pressure by U.S. authorities to hand
over Noriega, who sought asylum in the Vatican Embassy in Panama
City on Christmas Eve after eluding thousands of American troops
who invaded Dec. 20.
   Vatican spokesman Joaquin Navarro said Friday the Vatican could
not hand over Noriega to the Americans but was urging him to leave
the embassy on his own.
   Today's statement said the Vatican and U.S. authorities ``have
agreed to continue to remain in close contact to examine together,
in a spirit of serene collaboration, the various aspects of the
complex case and the possibility of arriving at a just solution
which will be mutually satisfactory.''
   The communique stressed that in giving refuge to Noriega the
papal nuncio in Panama ``did not intend to block the course of
justice regarding a person accused of serious crimes but to promote
the end of a conflict that ... could have gone on indefinitely in
the form of guerrilla warfare.''
   Navarro declined to comment on the state of the negotiations. He
said the Vatican still had not received a formal request from the
new Panamian government to hand over Noriega.
   Earlier, Navarro said the loud music played by U.S. troops
outside the Vatican Embassy in Panama was not helping talks on what
to do with Noriega.
   ``If this is going to continue, further steps will be taken'' by
the Vatican, Navarro said without elaborating.
   The rap and rock music, which has included numerous taunting
songs, seemed intended to torment Noriega.
   U.S. troops turned down the volume late Friday afternoon.
</TEXT>

</DOC>