<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0290 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1934EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Braniff     12-22 0550</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Braniff,0569</SECOND>
<HEAD>Braniff Moves to Install New Chief Executive</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ORLANDO, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Braniff Inc. asked a federal bankruptcy
judge Friday to install an interim chief executive officer, only a
day after the struggling carrier's top two executives resigned.
   David Murchison, 41, who himself stepped down last month as
Braniff's vice president, general counsel and secretary, was
recommended for the top job by both creditors and management, said
Braniff spokeswoman Ann Cook.
   U.S. Bankruptcy Judge C. Timothy Corcoran in Orlando will review
the recommendation and make the final decision. He has not set a
date to consider the motion.
   ``Braniff has a very strong mid-level management that is capable
of running the company until the judge makes his decision,'' Ms.
Cook said.
   Murchison was a vice president with Piedmont Aviation for three
years before joining Braniff in 1988. The plan is for him initally
to serve as an interim chief executive and he may take over the job
permanently, Ms. Cook said.
   The management changes come at a time when the carrier is
struggling through bankruptcy proceedings, and both creditors and
employees are calling for new management.
   Orlando-based Braniff, which filed for Chapter 11 protection
Sept. 28, has only 275 of its 4,800 pre-filing workers and has
trimmed its schedule to just charter flights.
   ``We don't want liquidation,'' said Tom Burnette, chairman of
the Teamsters union's Braniff committee. ``We want to preserve some
jobs, if there's a possibility at all.''
   William McGee, Braniff's chief executive officer, and W. Howard
Mackinnon, chief financial officer, submitted their resignations
Thursday of their own accord, Ms. Cook said.
   ``They simply feel the company has reached the point where their
services are no longer needed, and they left to pursue other
interests,'' Ms. Cook said.
   The resignations came the same day Braniff announced a drop in
earnings. For the third quarter ended Oct. 31, Braniff showed a net
loss of $134.9 million, compared with a loss of $7.8 million for
the same period in 1988.
   Braniff also announced it's giving up its rights to five leased
Airbus jets rather than go to court over the aircraft.
   Ireland's GPA Group Ltd. had sued Braniff for the five jets
because the airline owed $3 million in lease payments. Braniff said
the Airbuses are being returned as a ``gesture of good faith.''
   Scott Hamilton, editor of the Commercial Aviation Report in
Dallas, said Braniff had little hope of keeping the planes once GPA
sued.
   ``Yes, Braniff could have fought tooth and nail, but to what
end?'' he said. ``They would have lost the airplanes, and meanwhile
they would have lost the legal fees.''
   The return of five Airbuses does not affect Braniff's agreement
to lease and purchase another 45 jets, according to a statement
issued jointly by Braniff and GPA. The undelivered Airbuses are the
airline's chief asset.
   Braniff, whch has been sustaining itself recently by selling off
assets, is trying to find a customer for the lease agreements and
purchase options.
   Braniff lost $175.7 million in the first nine months of its
fiscal year on revenue of $391.8 million. The $134.9 million
quarterly loss is equivalent to $9.15 a share and includes a $64
million writeoff for intangible value the company lost when it
filed for bankruptcy protection, plus $22.4 million related to the
bankruptcy filing.
</TEXT>

</DOC>