<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0213 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1624EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-WorldMarkets 1stLd-Writethru   12-29 0776</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-World Markets, 1st Ld-Writethru,0796</SECOND>
<HEAD>Foreign Stock Markets Register Impressive Gains in '89</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: SUBS 5th graf to CORRECT Nikkei percentage gain to 29 pc sted
35 pc; uppicks 6th graf pvs: Analysts in ...</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARIANN CAPRINO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The planned 1992 unification of Europe and the opening of the
Eastern bloc created the prospect of economic opportunities that
propelled major foreign stock markets to double-digit gains in 1989.
   Investors worldwide scrambled to put money on the Continent _
U.S. investors pumped money into mutual funds that invest in Europe
and the Japanese set up their own stock funds invested specifically
in West German companies, seen as the most immediate beneficiaries
of the Iron Curtain's collapse.
   In the past two months, foreign appetite for German stocks has
helped boost the Frankfurt market to an annual net gain of 35
percent.
   But Germany's market performance was not an isolated one. Key
stock indices in London and Milan also rose impressively, as did
the world's largest stock market, Japan.
   Japan's stock market seemed to be on a record-setting spree
throughout the year. The 225-issue Nikkei Stock Average opened the
year at a record high of 30,243.66; it finished the year Friday at
38,915.87, the fourth consecutive day of record closings and a 29
percent gain over 1988.
   Analysts in Tokyo said the market overcame a number of obstacles
this year, including the death of Emperor Hirohito in January,
political instability, currency fluctuations and fear of creeping
inflation.
   The market's strength was underscored in October when the Nikkei
failed to follow Wall Street's precipitous Oct. 13 drop, when the
Dow Jones industrial average fell 7.1 percent in value.
   The key British stock index fell 3.2 percent and the Frankfurt
market lost 13.2 percent in response to Wall Street's drop, but
Tokyo shares declined only 1.8 percent before rebounding.
   Despite the mini-crash, ``the biggest event of the year is the
opening up of Eastern Europe,'' said Robert Rolland, executive vice
president at Shearson Lehman Hutton Inc., in New York. ``That's
definitely the theme going into the '90s, and it obviously
overshadows any one-day drop in the stock market.''
   In Frankfurt, the FAZ 100-share index rose 35 percent to finish
the year at 740.90, up from 549.86 at the start of 1989.
   Rolland characterized the recent buying of German stocks and
stock funds _ particularly by the Japanese _ as ``almost a
frenzy.'' Because German stocks typically are not split, their
prices can become prohibitively expensive. Deutsche Bank, for
example, is trading in the $490-a-share range.
   But the Germany Fund, a closed-end mutual fund that trades on
the New York Stock Exchange, can be had for $19 a share, Rolland
said. About a year ago the Germany Fund sold for $6.62{ a share.
   In London, the Financial Times-Stock Exchange 100-share index
finished the year at 2,422.7, up from 1,793.1 at the beginning of
1989. Investors were attracted to British companies because they
have issued little debt in comparison to their American
counterparts.
   But volume was disappointing, prompting investment firms to cut
costs through layoffs and other measures.
   Elsewhere in Europe, takeover fever gripped France in 1989 and
helped push the CAC-40 index up 27 percent on the year.
   ``Not only was it takeovers driving the market, but the
possibility of takeovers ... ahead of 1992,'' when Europe will meld
into a single, barrier-free market, Rolland said.
   Among the larger deals, the bank holding company Cie. Financiere
de Suez took over Cie. Industrielle and its insurance subsidiary
Groupe Victoire for about $4.1 billion after a brief but bitter
fight.
   In Italy, the key BCI index rose 17 percent, from 589.72 to
687.44 on Friday. Italy also is positioning itself for 1992, but
the country's overwhelming debt _ which roughly equals its gross
national product _ has created drag on the stock market, experts
say.
   ``There's a perception of negativity'' in Italy, said Guy Stern,
an analyst at ABD Securities Corp. in New York. ``They have to
reevaluate their national strategy and how they will expand.''
   The Italian market began to rally in late May when giant Fiat
announced a major share buyback program but stumbled later over an
Italian bank's unauthorized loans to the Iraqi government. The
country was dealt a further blow when Fiat failed to strike a deal
with the Swedish automaker Saab, which instead allied itself with
General Motors Corp.
   The unheralded growth market was Spain. It is not yet attracting
much foreign capital, and the Madrid General Index rose just 8
percent this year. But Stern noted that Spain has the fastest
growing gross domestic product of any European country with the
exception of Portugal.
</TEXT>

</DOC>