<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0136 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2033EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-IowaProbe     12-21 0620</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iowa Probe,640</SECOND>
<HEAD>Psychologists Question Iowa Conclusion</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAWRENCE L. KNUTSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A panel of mental health experts cast doubt
Thursday on the FBI conclusion that Clayton Hartwig triggered an
explosion on the U.S.S. Iowa because he wanted to commit suicide
and kill his shipmates.
   ``I do not believe that Clayton Hartwig was suicidal and I
certainly do not believe he was suicidial-homicidal,'' Dr. Douglas
Jacobs told the House Armed Service Committee.
   The FBI, however, said it stood behind its findings.
   Jacobs, a professor of psychiatry at the Harvard University
Medical School and director of the Suicide Education Institute of
Boston, was on a 14-member panel of mental health experts that
examined the FBI findings after the April 19 blast that killed
Hartwig and 46 crewmembers.
   The panel consisted of 12 psychologists appointed on a pro bono
basis by the American Psychological Association at the request of
the Armed Services Committee and two psychiatrists named by the
committee. Seven of the 14 panel members appeared at Thursday's
hearing.
   Members of the House committee, which is investigating the
Navy's conclusion that Hartwig most likely caused the explosion in
the battleship's No. 2 gun turret, attacked the methods the FBI
used to reach its conclusion.
   Lawmakers criticized the fact that no independent interviews
were conducted and that analysts relied entirely on interview
summaries and other material supplied by the Navy Investigative
Service.
   Hartwig's parents and a sister attended Thursday's hearing.
   When asked why no review had been made of such primary documents
as Hartwig's personnel and medical records, Robert Hazelwood of the
FBI's National Violent Crime Center, replied: ``We were satisfied
with the information we received.''
   ``I find it mind-boggling that you are asserting
criminal-homicidal conduct and do not go to the primary
documents,'' said Rep. Frank McCloskey, D-Ind. ``I think it is
almost fatally flawed.''
   ``We are very comfortable in our honest assertion,'' Hazelwood
responded.
   Eight of the psychologists and both psychiatrists took serious
exception to both the FBI's methods and the conclusions drawn.
   ``It is my conclusion that the data is qualitatively and
quantitatively weak and does not warrant the conclusion that was
drawn,'' said Dr. Ronald S. Ebert, senior forensic psychologist at
McLean Hospital in Belmont, Mass.
   ``I got the impression that there was a determination that had
been made and then data had to be gathered (by Navy investigators)
to support that determination,'' Ebert said.
   Norman G. Poythress, professor of psychology at the University
of Alabama, said that while suicide could not be ruled out
arbitrarily, ``I don't think the conclusion is nearly as strong as
has been characterized.''
   He noted that Hartwig had told a friend in an April letter that
his service aboard the Iowa was soon to end, that he had strong
attachments to the ship and its crew and that he wanted to stay in
port to wave the Iowa goodbye when it sailed in June.
   ``This is not a man in my judgment who had willing disregard for
his shipmates,'' Poythress said.
   However, Alan Berman, professor of psychology at American
University, said he was ``comfortable'' with the conclusion that
Hartwig committed suicide.
   ``Unfortunately, I am uncomfortable with the procedure that led
to the data,'' Berman said.
   Robert P. Archer, professor of psychiatry at the Eastern
Virginia Medical School at Norfolk, outlined the reasons for the
inadequacy of the data the FBI reviewed.
   There was no information on Hartwig's early development, family
environment or family history, including suicide, legal history,
medical and psychological records and alcohol or drug abuse, he
said.
   ``It is my opinion that the evidence is not sufficient to say
the explosion was the result of a homicidal or suicidal act by
Hartwig,'' Archer said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>