<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0169 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 2330EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Patterson     12-29 0351</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Patterson,0364</SECOND>
<HEAD>Church of God in Christ Bishop J.O. Patterson, 77, Dies of Cancer</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MEMPHIS, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Presiding Bishop James Oglethrope (J.O.)
Patterson Sr., leader of the 3.7 million-member Church of God in
Christ, died of cancer Friday. He was 77.
   Patterson retired earlier this year because of the illness but
retained his title as leader of the Memphis-based international
church, the world's largest black Pentecostal Holiness denomination.
   He died about 6 a.m. at William F. Bold Hospital in Memphis,
said Bishop H. Jenkins Bell, adjutant general of the COGIC.
   Patterson was elected presiding bishop of the church in 1968
when founder Charles H. Mason died in 1961.
   ``He (Patterson) brought creditability to the church,'' said
Elder Calvin Burns. ``He help make us a recognized and respected
denomination and not just a sect.''
   Patterson will be succeeded by Bishop E. H. Ford of Chicago, the
denomination's first vice president, who will preside over its
12-member board of bishops until the next convention election in
1992.
   Patterson was diagnosed with pancreatic cancer in April but
refused to be treated for the disease because, he said ``the
treatment of prayer is better than chemotherapy.''
   For the past 48 years Patterson served as senior pastor of the
Pentecostal Temple Institutional Church of God in Christ in
Memphis, where his son, J.O. Patterson Jr., will succeed him as the
church's pastor.
   Patterson is also survived by a daughter, Janet Patterson, and
second wife Mary Patterson. Patterson's first wife, Deborah, the
daughter of COGIC founder Charles Mason, died in 1985.
   The church was established in 1906 in Jackson, Miss., by Mason,
then an independent Baptist minister who said he had been affected
by the Holiness movement.
   Its doctrine is similar to that of the Pentecostal Holiness
Church. Members believe in the trinity, nonmedical or ``holiness''
healing, baptism by immersion, the Lord's Supper and foot-washing.
   In 1987 the church reported 10,500 congregations and 3,896
ministers in the U.S.; 21 congregations and 33 ministers in Canada.
The church has about 3 million members in the United States and
700,000 in 43 other countries around the world.
</TEXT>

</DOC>