<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0016EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-FireFatalsRdp 3rdLd-Writethru a0408 12-25 0802</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fire Fatals Rdp, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0408,0819</SECOND>
<HEAD>Christmas Eve Fires Kill At Least 32</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS lead, 6th graf, `In Johnson ...,' to UPDATE with 14 now
dead in Johnson City fire for total of 46.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Christmas Eve fires killed at least 46 people in seven states
Sunday, including 12 people at a Tennessee retirement home, six
people at a family reunion in Atlanta, and a mother and four
daughters in a Dallas suburb.
   Five other fires had tragic consequences in Pennsylvania, New
York, New Hampshire and Wisconsin.
   Four members of a Pittsburgh family died and eight others,
including a pregnant woman, were injured. In Little Falls, N.Y., a
man tried in vain to save his wife and three children from a fire
that destroyed their trailer home.
   A mother and her two sons died in an early-morning blaze that
gutted their West Conshohocken, Pa., rowhouse; four people died in
an early morning bungalow fire in Swan Lake, N.Y.; and three
children died and their mother was seriously injured in an
apartment fire in Manchester, N.H.
   A 6-year-old boy died of smoke inhalation in Milwaukee when a
fire broke out in a bedroom in his apartment, and a 45-year-old
schoolteacher died when the torch he was using to thaw water in a
pipe apparently started a fire that destroyed a shed behind house
trailers he owned in Ashland, Wis.
   In Johnson City, Tenn., fire broke out at the 10-story John
Sevier Retirement Center around 5:30 p.m. and firefighters were
still battling it nearly six hours later, officials said.
Authorities said at least 14 people died and more deaths were
expected.
   At least 26 people were injured. About 145 people lived at the
center.
   The Atlanta fire gutted a one-story wood frame home, leaving
relatives who gathered for the reunion stricken, grieving and
homeless.
   ``We were all there for a family Christmas. Now, five of my
relatives are dead, and the others lost everything,'' said family
member Juanita McColumn. ``They ran out with just their night
clothes on, and they have no clothes and nowhere to stay.''
   Ms. McColumn identified the dead as LaVerne Willis, 30, her
sister; Latoya Willis, 6, Ms. Willis' daughter; Xavier Wilson, 4, a
nephew; Ernestine Strozier, 28 and her son, David, 8, both cousins
of the Willises; and Leroy Bain, 37, LaVerne Willis' boyfriend. All
lived in Atlanta.
   The fire lasted about two hours, said Sgt. C.A. Graham of the
Fulton County medical examiner's office. The cause was not known,
Graham said.
   In the Dallas suburb of Garland, a 31-year-old mother and four
daughters, ages 2 to 9, died when a fire that apparently began
around a Christmas tree engulfed their home.
   The woman's husband and two sons escaped the fire, officials
said.
   ``The firefighters were unable to get into the house to locate
anyone, the fire was so intense,'' said Ron Smith of the Garland
Fire Department.
   In Pittsburgh, fire tore through a home at 5:45 a.m., killing
Clarence Blakemore, 60, his 26-year-old daughter, and two
grandchildren, ages 2 and 4.
   Eight other Blakemore relatives were injured. Two were in
critical condition and three were in serious condition, including a
23-year-old woman who was eight months pregnant.
   The fire in Little Falls consumed Robert E. Thomas' trailer home
in a matter of minutes, state police said. Thomas struggled to save
his family through a rear door, but his 27-year-old wife and their
three sons, ages 2 to 6, died.
   ``He thought he kept hearing (son) Robby's voice calling `Daddy'
through the door. He kept yelling `Help me, help me get my babies
out!''' next-door neighbor Theresa Gressler said.
   In Swan Lake, four people died when a propane heater apparently
exploded around 3:30 a.m., destroying their bungalow, state Trooper
Mark Brown said. The four, all Brazilians, could not be identified
immediately, Brown said.
   Another Sunday morning fire in a single-family home in the
Albany, N.Y., suburb of Watervliet claimed one man's life, police
said.
   Fire officials in West Conshohocken, Pa., believe Sevilla Smith,
27, died while trying to save her two children, aged 15 months and
5 years, from a fire in their three-story home shortly after 3:30
a.m.
   In Manchester, N.H., two boys and a girl, ages 2 to 5, were
killed in their apartment in a three-story wood building, said
police Lt. James Stewart. Their mother, Jessica Lunderville, 30,
was hospitalized in critical condition Sunday night. Stewart said
the father and two other children were not home at the time.
   Also in Manchester, firefighters Sunday afternoon rescued 26
elderly nuns from a fire at a convent nursing home. The fire was
caused by an electrical malfunction at the Nativity scene in the
convent's chapel, said Manchester Police Chief Francis Monnelly.
Two nuns suffered smoke inhalation and were hospitalized in
satisfactory condition.
</TEXT>

</DOC>