<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0112 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1241EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-TV-Panama     12-20 0325</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-TV-Panama,0334</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two News Producers Seized, Networks Ask U.S. Protection</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two American news producers were seized from a
hotel in Panama today, prompting the major U.S. networks to ask the
Pentagon and White House for more protection for Americans and
journalists, an ABC spokeswoman said.
   Pentagon spokesman Pete Williams confirmed that some Americans
were seized at the Marriott Hotel in Panama City and taken away as
hostages. ``We will make efforts to take care of that,'' he said.
   The networks' request came after CBS' Jon Meyersohn and ABC's
Robert Campos were seized by rifle-carrying men said to be
followers of Panamanian leader Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   The two producers had been in the hotel lobby, discussing
satellite transmission to New York of video of the U.S. attack, and
were about to leave when four or five heavily armed men pulled up
in a truck and took them hostage, ABC spokeswoman Elise Adde said.
   It isn't known where they were taken, Adde and a CBS spokesman
said.
   About 100 journalists who have been trying to cover the fighting
in Panama are at the Marriott but are unable to leave because of
gun-carrying Noriega loyalists roaming the streets outside, ABC
correspondent John Quinones reported by phone from the hotel during
a newscast today.
   Meyersohn, 33, is based in New York and is a producer for the
``CBS Evening News.'' Campos, 31, is based in Miami and works for
various ABC News broadcasts. The two are U.S. citizens.
   Williams declined to say whether American troops were moving on
the hotel, citing the U.S. practice of not detailing military
movements.
   Asked why U.S. troops had not taken steps earlier to protect
Americans at the Marriott, Williams said, ``There are 23,000
Americans down there. There are a lot of other places there, too.''
   He said he had no information on the number of Americans that
had been taken hostage from the hotel.
</TEXT>

</DOC>