<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0151 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0932EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APArts:Britain-Rock Adv02   12-28 0731</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP Arts: Britain-Rock, Adv 02,0748</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv 02</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Tues PMs, Jan 2 and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>What's in a Name? For Some Rock Bands, a Lawsuit</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JESSICA BALDWIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For some of the rock groups of the 1960s and '70s,
the comeback trail includes a gig in the courtroom to try and
reclaim their household names.
   Lineups have changed, founding members have retired, died or
gone solo, and in some cases, the reunion has entailed lawyers
poring over dusty old files to establish who owns the name of the
group.
   Members of the British group Yes, which won popularity in the
'70s, have just fought through tortuous litigation to win a
Solomonic ruling on use of the name. Another British group, Pink
Floyd, suffered similar tribulations.
   The American rock-pop group the Byrds had to reunite temporarily
for three concerts in California last January just to lay renewed
legal claim to their name, because three different groups, all
fragments of the original, were calling themselves the Byrds.
   ``A lot of acts are getting back together again and touring, so
the name is absolutely crucial,'' said Patrick Isherwood, a music
industry lawyer at Frere Cholmeley, the London-based law firm that
represents the Beatles. ``In a sense that's your passport to make
money or not.''
   ``The names count for a lot. That's why Pink FLoyd had their
battle with Roger Waters,'' said Brian Howard, a lawyer at
Russells, a London law firm that represents Waters. ``At the end of
the day if you've got a good name you sell albums before people
have even listened to them.''
   Pink Floyd illustrates the power of the name.
   Forbes magazine estimates that the group's reunion tour and
album, ``Momentary Loss of Reason,'' pulled in $56 million and put
Pink Floyd among the 10 biggest entertainment earners of 1989.
   Meanwhile, the latest album by Waters, who founded Pink Floyd in
1967 but went solo five years ago, sold fewer than 1 million copies.
   Had Waters kept the name Pink Floyd and used different artists,
he might have been much more successful, says Chris Gilbert, a
London-based music industry manager, because, ``You could argue
that Waters was the creative spearhead of that band from day one.''
   Waters sought a court order to dissolve the band, calling it ``a
spent creative force.'' He lost, but the giant pig that has been
one of the group's best-known stage props is still in litigation.
   Nostalgia buffs provide a large market for oldies, and
middle-aged classic rock bands are taking advantage of the
nostalgia wave.
   The Rolling Stones are touring North America, selling out four
Shea Stadium shows in six hours. The Kinks are on the road, as are
Crosby, Stills and Nash. Jefferson Airplane and the Stray Cats are
reuniting, while The Who has just completed a successful tour.
   In Yes's case, a U.S. District court ruled in July that four
former members of the rock band led by singer Jon Anderson cannot
use the name. The judge awarded ownership to bass player Chris
Squire, who said he paid a hefty sum for it. The four musicians are
touring under their own names but billboards advertise ``an evening
of Yes music.''
   A band's name is particularly important when it comes to
merchandising.
   `It's the ultimate brand name,'' Gilbert said in an interview.
``It's as valuable as Kit Kat, or Gordon's gin. When you think of
the sums of money going into those brand names and then multiply
them by the creative care and measure that's gone into a group's
name you can see why someone is upset not to be able to use that
name.''
   Entertainment industry lawyer Alexis Grower said the name
battles began with Fleetwood Mac in the late 1960s, when their
manager, who had registered ``Fleetwood Mac'' under his name,
attempted to retain it after the band had replaced him.
   ``Fleetwood Mac got the name even though the ex-manager went out
and hired four other people,'' Grower said. ``The court established
the precedent that it doesn't matter who has the ownership of the
name. What matters is who the public thinks the name is.''
   The image of bands that once stood for the counterculture now
surrounding themselves with high-priced lawyers may not sit well
with hard-core fans. But some rockers may wish they had been with
lawyers from the beginning.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv</NOTE>

</DOC>