<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0145 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 2145EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Panama-Funerals 2ndLd-Writethru a0672 12-27 0844</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Funerals, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0672,0867</SECOND>
<HEAD>3 Soldiers, Sailor Killed in Panama Are Buried</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS leads with 2 grafs to UPDATE with fifth funeral in Alabama;
SUBS 18th graf, `In Seneca..., with 2 grafs to add circumstances of Lear's
death. ADDS 3 grafs to give details of fifth funeral.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos CBS1, JO1, BX2, BX3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Four soldiers and a sailor were buried with full military honors
and 21-gun salutes Wednesday, one week after they were killed in
the U.S. invasion of Panama.
   The funerals, held in West Virginia, South Carolina,
Massachusetts, Rhode Island and Alabama, drew scores of military
personnel from each branch as well as high-ranking elected
officials and clergymen. Altogether, 23 American troops died in the
fighting last week.
   In Princeton, W.Va., Army Pvt. 2 Kenneth Douglas Scott, 20, was
buried in the snowy mountains he called home as about 100 mourners
looked on, including his foster parents and the woman he had
planned to marry next month.
   ``I believe when he joined the military, he wanted to believe in
something. I want to remember him as a soldier, steadfast and
unmovable, who died for what he believed in,'' said the Rev. Dwight
Palmer, pastor of St. Paul's Holy United Church of Woodlawn, Va.
Palmer is the son of Scott's guardian, Ruth Palmer.
   A military honor guard from Fort Knox, Ky., saluted Scott's
casket one by one at a Princeton funeral home. The guard fired a
21-gun salute, traditionally reserved for special burials, at
Roselawn Memorial Gardens cemetery a few blocks from the funeral
home.
   Scott, who joined the Army in June and was stationed at Fort
Polk, La., died serving with the 6th Infantry Division in early
fighting in Panama City on Dec. 20, according to the Defense
Department.
   In Central Falls, R.I., some 300 mourners filled Notre Dame
Church for the funeral of Army Cpl. Ivan Perez, a native of
Colombia who grew up in Rhode Island.
   The 22-year-old Perez was killed in an ambush by forces loyal to
Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega, the Army said. The Rev. Dennis Reardon
told mourners that his death ``shatters the superficial beauty of
Christmastime.''
   ``This isn't the Christmas that any one of us planned,'' Reardon
said. ``We are grateful to him for the sacrifice he made. We value
and appreciate all the honors and awards being given to him today.''
   Gov. Edward D. DiPrete and U.S. Sen. Claiborne Pell were among
those at the ceremony.
   Pell, D-R.I., chairman of the Foreign Relations Committee, said
he was ``here to honor someone who has fallen in the line of duty
for his country, and to comfort his family.''
   At St. Agnes Parish church in Arlington, Mass., about 550
family, friends and sympathizers, including Roman Catholic Cardinal
Bernard Law, mourned Navy Lt. j.g. John Connors.
   Connors, a 25-year-old Arlington native, had volunteered for
service in Panama. He had joined the Navy in 1987 and served in the
special operations unit known as the SEALS, or Sea, Air and Land
teams. The Pentagon did not release the circumstances of his death.
   ``We celebrate a common loss and recognize a common grief,''
said the Rev. John McIntyre, one of Connors' teachers at Boston
College High School. ``We do not come here this morning to find
anything like sense, because there is no sense.''
   Law picked up on the theme of the search for meaning in Connors'
death.
   ``It is a senselessness,'' Law said. ``The senselessness of sin,
and sin works itself out in Romania and elsewhere.''
   Among the mourners was the new Panamanian ambassador to the
United Nations, Eduardo Vallerino, who lives in the neighboring
town of Belmont.
   In Seneca, S.C., more than 300 people attended the funeral of
Army Specialist Phillip S. Lear, one of three South Carolina
natives killed during the invasion.
   The infantryman died Dec. 20 of gunshot wounds while American
troops were mopping up an area near Rhiohato Air Force Base, about
65 miles west of Panama City.
   The service at the United Assembly of God Church for the
21-year-old Westminster native was attended by scores of military
personnel from each branch of the service. Lear was buried at the
Oconee Memorial Park and, like the others, given a 21-gun salute.
   Maj. Gen. John A. Renner handed an American flag to Lear's
mother after the burial and thanked her ``on behalf of the
president of the United States and a very greatful nation ... for
the selfless and honorable service of your son.''
   At Fort Mitchell National Cemetary in Alabama, two military
brothers buried a third brother, Army Sgt. Michael DeBlois, at a
ceremony attended by about 40 friends and relatives.
   DeBlois, 24, of Columbus, Ga., was eulogized as a good soldier
who turned in an honorable performance in Panama, despite an
earlier flesh wound he received when hit by debris from an
exploding building.
   The radio operator was one of two soldiers killed when someone
tossed a grenade inside a building in Panama City that had been
``cleared'' by U.S. troops, according to DeBlois' squad leader.
</TEXT>

</DOC>