<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1147EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-MarijuanaBroker     12-27 0320</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Marijuana Broker,0329</SECOND>
<HEAD>Guilty Plea of Marijuana Broker Caps Sting Operation</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man prosecutors called the biggest single
broker of Southeast Asian marijuana pleaded guilty to smuggling
nearly 200 tons into the United States over a four-year period.
   Brian Peter Daniels, 43, appeared before U.S. District Judge
John Coughenour on Tuesday to plead guilty to one count of
operating a continuing criminal enterprise and two counts of
conspiracy to import and distribute marijuana.
   Daniels, a New York native who had lived in Thailand for about
10 years until his 1988 arrest in Switzerland, could be sentenced
to life in prison and fined up to $6.25 million.
   Sentencing was set for May 25. Daniels is being held without
bail in the Pierce County Jail.
   Daniels admitted in court documents that he masterminded some of
the biggest marijuana shipments from Southeast Asia to the United
States from 1984 to 1988.
   The shipments included multiton deliveries to Seattle, southern
California, Oregon, Nevada, British Columbia and Mexico. Among them
was the shipment of 72 tons of high-grade Laotian marijuana seized
in June 1988 aboard the Encounter Bay, an oil-supply vessel, off
the Washington coast.
   ``As far as I'm aware he was the single biggest broker of
Southeast Asian marijuana,'' said Assistant U.S. Attorney Peter
Mueller.
   The guilty plea was part of an agreement in which some charges
in Seattle, San Diego, and Reno, Nev., were packaged into a single
plea agreement filed in Seattle.
   The guilty plea capped a ``sting'' operation by the federal Drug
Enforcement Administration, in which DEA agents in Seattle, Reno,
Miami, Hong Kong and Bangkok collaborated to ensnare Daniels.
   Dozens of other defendants have been prosecuted in Seattle, San
Diego and Reno and arrest warrants have been issued for other key
figures who are still fugitives.
   Swiss police and DEA agents arrested Daniels in July 1988 in
Zurich, Switzerland, where he had gone for medical treatment.
</TEXT>

</DOC>