<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0114EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-Streets     12-23 0588</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Streets,0610</SECOND>
<HEAD>Panamanians Take Arms, Seek Shelter, Food, Medicine</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RAFAEL CANDANEDO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   People took up arms and formed
vigilante squads to combat looting and thousands jammed churches,
stadiums and schools to flee fighting that has ravaged the capital.
Food and medicine were in short supply.
   As the U.S. military occupation entered its fourth day today,
weary and frightened residents stayed behind locked doors to avoid
street battles between fighters loyal to ousted Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noriega and American forces.
   Much of this city of 1 million people was in ruins after air
strikes by U.S. warplanes and mortar attacks by Panamanian fighters.
   Residents in many neighborhoods organized vigilante groups to
ward off the looters of homes and businesses who roamed the streets
at will.
   Citizens erected tire barricades and armed themselves for
protection against the anarchy, which spread to middle-class
neighborhoods on Friday.
   ``The only way to protect what little we have left is to protect
it ourselves,'' said Jorge Perez, a 36-year-old homeowner in the
suburb of San Francisco.
   The city's police, part of the Panamanian Defense Forces,
disbanded or collapsed when the invasion began at midnight Tuesday.
   The three-day looting spree left most businesses and grocery
stores depleted of basic foods. Streets were littered with broken
glass and trash.
   Many shopkeepers kept looters at bay with guns. Paying customers
who lined up outside the few supermarkets that opened their doors
complained of shortages.
   Motorists looted some gas stations that failed to open for
business.
   Thousands of people fleeing the fighting sought shelter in
stadiums, churches or schools.
   In the city of Balboa, at the Pacific entrance of the Panama
Canal, about 3,000 refugees jammed a high school sports stadium.
   In the capital, 500 refugees were at the Revolution Soccer
Stadium, 200 at the capital's Venezuela high school, 100 at another
school and 100 more at the Santa Ana Roman Catholic Church.
   Untold thousands slept in public parks and streets. Many just
knocked on stranger's doors and begged to be let in.
   ``First I fled to a stranger's home. But then I had to leave,
and I made my way through the fighting until I was able to reach my
mother's house,'' one man said by telephone from his mother's home,
where 15 others had taken refuge.
   A Red Cross official appealed for food donations as shortages of
many basics worsened. He noted that many people were donating ``as
much as they can spare'' and that many U.S. troops provided
rations, but said much more help was needed.
   Hospitals staffed by doctors and nurses working 16- and 24-hour
shifts were overcrowded with the wounded and the dead and ran short
of everything from alcohol to analgesics to surgical gauze.
   ``Besides everything, not only is there no transportation but
the staff is scared to go outside,'' said Dr. Elmer Miranda, deputy
director of the Santo Tomas Hospital.
   ``The United States only gives us bullets,'' he said.
   He complained that supply flights still were prevented from
entering Panama because the country's airports remained closed
under U.S. military control.
   Miranda said there were 200 bodies in the hospital's basement
morgue. One hospital official estimated there were 1,000 wounded,
most of them civilians.
   One resident surveyed the destroyed building of Noriega's
Defense Forces headquarters. Ringed by tanks, the surrounding area
remained off-limits to civilians, and U.S. soldiers warned people
over loudspeakers to stay away.
   ``Why did they do this?'' the resident asked. ``Just because
they wanted to get Noriega?''
</TEXT>

</DOC>