<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0170 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 2035EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WKD--Manchester Adv05-07   12-26 0874</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--Manchester, Adv05-07,0896</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv05-07</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Weekend Editions, Jan. 5-7, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WEEKEND ENTERTAINMENT AND ARTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Music Makers: Let's Sing the Standards</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HILLEL ITALIE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sting did it. Linda Ronstadt did it. Even Marvin
Gaye and Lou Reed did it. So, Melissa Manchester reasoned, let's do
it, let's sing standards.
   ``This music has been out in the universe for decades,'' said
Manchester, whose first album in four years, ``Tribute,'' includes
``Stardust,'' ``Over the Rainbow'' and other lushly produced songs
from the pre-rock 'n' roll era.
   ``These are magnificent melodies and long, intricate stories. To
wrap your voice around them makes you want to rise to the occasion
of these songs. It's different than singing short bits of rock 'n'
roll phrases, which I find more difficult.''
   In 1985, Manchester had had enough. A dozen years of making
records had erased the thrill. There were children to raise, an
interest in theater to pursue. It seemed a good time to finish the
career that took off in 1975 with the ballad ``Midnight Blue.''
   But this show business veteran, once a backup singer for Bette
Midler, has seen how tentative ``retirements'' usually are. A few
years away and Manchester got the urge to belt 'em out again. Not
new material, however, old material.
   ``When I gained distance and perspective from the music
industry, it came to me as to what I was really up to doing,'' she
said. ``Once I became clear it was the right thing to do and it was
basically in my truth, all the details fell into place.''
   Having grown up on Manhattan's Upper West Side, the 38-year-old
Manchester was drawn to sophisticated ladies of jazz such as Billie
Holiday and Ella Fitzgerald and the polished compositions of Hoagy
Carmichael and George Gershwin. She knew, however, that it was best
to step lightly into shoes so large.
   ``I felt I was ready and had grown enough to pay tribute to
these women who were heroines in my youth,'' she explained. ``It
was not at all about competing with these women _ that would be
folly. It was simply to acknowledge their greatness, and the
greatness of their songs.''
   So Manchester wasn't looking to ``cover'' the songs, just polish
them up a little. On ``Over the Rainbow,'' she wrestled with the
memory of Judy Garland's anguished performance at Carnegie Hall in
1961, a sad departure from the innocence of the ``The Wizard of
Oz.''
   ``To this day, it's riveting and gut-wrenching and a testimonial
to her experience,'' Manchester said.
   ``I'm bringing my own experience and I see it as an anthem-like,
optimistic song. There is an inner life to songs, particularly if
you have signature songs that you're going to have to sing all your
life. It's interesting how your life affects a song you're
singing.''
   Young singers wishing to pay tribute to Manchester might skip
the 1982 Grammy winner, ``You Should Hear How She Talks About
You,'' and go back to ``Midnight Blue,'' which Manchester co-wrote
with Carole Bayer Sager.
   They wanted Dionne Warwick to sing it, but producer Vini Poncia
was so impressed with the demo that he used Manchester instead.
``Midnight Blue'' peaked on the charts at No. 6.
   ``I was really unconscious in those days. `We're on the charts?'
`What does that mean?' `Are we all suppose to do something, open a
bottle of champagne?' I was very young and I had no sense of
packaging. I just wanted to write and sing. I didn't care what I
looked like, that I looked a mess or not.''
   ``Talks About You,'' with its snappy, updated ``girl group''
sound, wasn't her idea, Manchester insists. By then, her career
needed a boost and she agreed to take chances with a slicker, more
aggressive sound. It worked, but at a price.
   ``The risk is you shave off a little slice of your soul. I was
shaving more and more pieces and in real danger of giving the whole
thing away. My soul was too important to me. Stevie Wonder wrote,
`Where is my spirit, I'm nowhere near it.'''
   Fourteen years after ``Midnight Blue,'' Manchester is still
thinking about Warwick, capping her tribute record with the hit
``Walk on By,'' which first came out in 1964.
   ``I was always touched by `Walk on By.' It was always this very
traumatic and dark and moody song about what's not said in a
relationship. I wanted to produce the record to be deeper and more
spacious and more dramatic.''
   And when it was time to make a video, Manchester resisted a
straight romantic interpretation, transferring one of today's
issues onto one of yesterday's hits.
   ``I thought of the title, `Walk on By.' The description of what
we did in society when we pass images that are disquieting, such as
homelessness,'' she said.
   ``I came up with this idea of playing a homeless woman with two
children and having to leave the two children at the shelter. We in
fact filmed at a shelter in Los Angeles and I got to speak to
several of the women there. It semed like a good idea and turned
into a real educational experience.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Weekend Editions, Jan. 5-7</NOTE>

</DOC>