<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0110 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1857EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ClipADealer     12-28 0365</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Clip A Dealer,0374</SECOND>
<HEAD>Newspaper Readers Can Drop a Dime on Dealers By Clipping a Coupon</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MILFORD, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Reporting suspected drug dealers here is
as easy as clipping a coupon.
   Newspaper readers fill in the blanks on the coupon and mail it
to police under a program started by a citizen group a month ago in
this city of 52,000 outside New Haven.
   Police have received 15 report-a-dealer coupons, and the
complaints are being investigated, Officer Edward Kelly, a police
spokesman, said Thursday.
   ``Just because there is information on the coupon doesn't mean
we can go right out and make an arrest,'' Kelly said. ``We have to
make sure it is valid. People are going to have to be a little
patient.''
   The campaign was organized by Drug Free Milford Inc., a group
trying to help police fight drugs. The coupons, marked by a
hypodermic needle with a slash through it, are published daily for
free in the Milford Citizen.
   ``We will make it extremely uncomfortable for the dealers. We
are going to eradicate this poison by getting everyone involved,''
said DeForest Smith, president of Drug Free Milford.
   Topped by a bold black box that exclaims ``ENOUGH!'' the coupons
read: ``I've had enough of drugs in my neighborhood. I've reason to
believe that (blank) is using (or) dealing drugs. I'm suspicious of
activities at (blank). I've noticed the following license plates on
cars in the vicinity of suspected drug activity.''
   Tipsters are given the option of identifying themselves for a
possible reward of up to $1,000 if there is a conviction resulting
from the information.
   The report-a-dealer coupons could cause expose the anti-drug
group to lawsuits if someone decides to turn in a name just to
embarass that person, said William Olds, executive director of the
Connecticut Civil Liberties Union.
   But Smith said the group has liability insurance. ``We
anticipate lawsuits _ dealers will do their best to derail this
program,'' he said.
   Drug Free Milford has also helped set up a drug hotline, but has
received only six calls, police said. The coupons are more
effective, Kelly said, because many people are hestitant to talk on
the phone about illegal activity.
</TEXT>

</DOC>