<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 2121EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Cold-Jacksonville     12-24 0327</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cold-Jacksonville,0341</SECOND>
<HEAD>City's Disruptions Numerous From Cold, Ice</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Cold Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JACKSONVILLE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Disruptions of everything from bus
service to church services made life a chore Sunday while this
northeastern Florida river city fought record cold and treacherous
ice.
   ``It's a winter wonderland in Jacksonville. It's a beautiful
sight for a city that doesn't get snow very often, and it's also a
very dangerous situation for the same reason,'' said Mayor Tommy
Hazouri.
   Throughout late Saturday and early Sunday, most of
Jacksonville's bridges were closed to traffic. Police responded to
dozens of traffic accidents, most fender-benders from skidding cars.
   For the first time since Hurricane Dora in 1964, the
Jacksonville Transportation Authority suspended bus service.
   Worrying that heavy use of electricity might force power
reductions to some neighborhoods, electric utility officials asked
that outdoor Christmas lights and hot water heaters be shut off.
   ``That may not sound like much, but if you multiply that several
thousand times ... it can make a difference,'' said Clyde
Montgomery, a spokesman for the Jacksonville Electric Authority.
   The authority had a record for power use for the year Saturday
at 2,100 megawatts, Montgomery said.
   Interstate 10 between Jacksonville and Tallahassee was closed
for hours.
   All flights were cancelled at Jacksonville International Airport
on Saturday and Sunday.
   Many passengers were stranded while carrying colorfully wrapped
Christmas packages intended for friends and relatives elsewhere.
   Some hospitals were short on nurses because many could not get
to work.
   Numerous churches canceled Sunday's regular and special
Christmas Eve services.
   An 8-year-old boy died after a malfunctioning kerosene heater
started a fire in a bedroom where he, his mother and three other
children were sleeping, authorities said.
   Cindy Mosling, operator of BEAKS, a bird emergency care center,
said she had received more than 100 calls from people who had
sighted birds injured by the cold and ice.
   However, icy bridges to her bird sanctuary prevented her from
rescuing any of the birds.
</TEXT>

</DOC>