<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0133 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1703EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-LebanonSplit 330   12-18 0324</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon Split, 330</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ousted Lebanese Ambassador Refusing to Leave Post</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RUTH SINAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lebanon's ousted ambassador to the United
States said Monday that he still regards himself as his country's
official envoy and that only a court order will remove him from the
embassy and official residence.
   Abdallah Bouhabib, who was removed by Lebanon's new government
several weeks ago, said he no longer sees State Department contacts
in an official capacity but is continuing to deal with them outside
their offices.
   ``I am in a very strong position, I am not going to get out,''
he said in a telephone interview. ``If anybody wants me out of
office and the embassy, they have to go to court.''
   The State Department was told last week that Bouhabib had
resigned effective Dec. 11 and that the No. 2 diplomat at the
embassy, Sleiman Rassi, was in charge. The department announced
that it would only deal with Rassi because he represents the
U.S.-recognized government.
   However, Bouhabib said he does not recognize the government of
Prime Minister Salim al-Hoss and President Elias Hrawi.
   ``I don't take orders from them,'' he said.
   Bouhabib, who has been ambassador since 1983, said there was ``a
dispute about the legality and legitimacy of the Hrawi government''
and until the problem is resolved he and other Lebanese diplomats
abroad should remain in office.
   The former World Bank economist is a supporter of Christian Gen.
Michel Aoun, whom Hrawi removed from all his posts but who
continues to hold out with 20,000 troops at the presidential palace
in Beirut.
   In an attempt to resolve the embarrassing embassy standoff, the
Arab League's Ambassador Clovis Maksoud urged the Lebanese
government to give Bouhabib a two-month transition to hand over the
embassy's affairs, said sources who spoke on condition of anonymity.
   The sources said Bouhabib had asked Maksoud to intervene, but
Bouhabib denied he had made such a request.
</TEXT>

</DOC>