<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0091 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1638EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-EnergyShortages     12-23 0476</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Energy Shortages,470</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Seeks to Ease Heating Fuels Transportation Problems</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Christmas weekend cold snap has stretched
the nation's energy system to the maximum and created ``spot
shortages'' of heating fuels in some areas, the Energy Department's
chief of emergency preparedness said Saturday.
   ``At the moment we think we can get through this abnormally cold
weather,'' without widespread energy shortages, but the outlook
could darken if refineries break down or other unforeseen problems
develop, said John J. Easton Jr.
   Easton, the assistant energy secretary for international affairs
and energy emergencies, said the government was not considering
imposing any price or allocation controls.
   Easton spoke to reporters at Energy Department headquarters
during a break in a day-long meeting with about 80 representatives
of oil companies, electric utilities, natural gas distributors,
state energy offices and other federal departments.
   The meeting was called Thursday to exchange information about
localized distribution problems and to consider easing federal
rules affecting energy transportation. Easton said, for example,
that the Department of Transportation was waiving certain limits on
working hours by fuel truck drivers.
   The Energy Department has begun processing applications for
waivers of the Jones Act, which prohibits the use of foreign ships
to carry U.S. oil products in domestic waters, Easton said, adding
that some exceptions could be granted so that foreign ships heading
overseas with U.S. fuel products could reverse course to U.S. ports.
   Easton said the main problem in heating fuels as of Saturday
afternoon was distribution of propane.
   ``In propane there are spot shortages, and it will be tight for
the next 10 days or so,'' he said. Later he said these shortages
were ``in many parts of the country,'' mainly the Northeast and
Midwest.
   Easton said the department wanted to reassure the public that
``the federal government is concerned'' about the hardships posed
by heating fuel shortages, and that it is actively trying to ``cut
the red tape to relieve the bottlenecks.''
   ``This is not an emergency,'' Easton said, stressing that
supplies of heating oil and natural gas as of Saturday were
adequate, although refineries were operating at maximum capacity to
meet ``unprecedented demand'' for heating fuels.
   ``We do not expect any shortages in natural gas, although I can
say the system is producing at the maximum at the present time,''
Easton said. He said some parts of Texas were experiencing
``rotating blackouts'' due to electricity shortages but that power
supplies in most areas were generally adequate.
   Easton said the meeting was told by a National Weather Service
official that extreme cold weather was expected to continue at
least through the end of December in the Northeast but that some
relief was likely soon for other regions. The January outlook was
for abnormal cold in the north central states but less harsh
conditions elsewhere, he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>