<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0180 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0810EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Cuisinarts-Conair     12-28 0396</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Cuisinarts-Conair,0413</SECOND>
<HEAD>Conair Buys Cuisinarts Product Line</HEAD>
<DATELINE>STAMFORD, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Conair Corp. officials say they have
gained a major asset in purchasing Cuisinarts Inc.'s product lines
for an undisclosed price.
   The transaction, announced Wednesday, also included the purchase
of trademarks, patents, inventory and equipment of the world-famous
food processor maker, Conair announced.
   The purchase came five months after Stamford-based Cuisinarts
Inc. filed for protection from creditors under Chapter 11 of the
U.S. bankruptcy code. The case remains pending in U.S. Bankruptcy
Court in Hartford.
   At the time of the bankruptcy filing in August, Cuisinarts
stated that it owed $43.2 million and had assets of $34.5 million,
most of it in inventory in a Norwich warehouse.
   Cuisinarts officials have blamed the company's financial
troubles on a failure to capitalize on its famous name by using it
on other products. Only recently had it begun to branch out to such
things as cooking utensils, hand blenders and other cookware.
   Rachel Litner, a Conair spokeswoman, said Conair did not assume
Cuisinarts' liabilities.
   With the purchase, Stamford-based Conair will have five product
divisions. These include the kitchen line involving Cuisinarts
products; consumer appliances, consumer toiletries, consumer
electronics and professional beauty salon products.
   Conair officials said the company would also be expanding its
international market with its participation in a 50 percent
ownership in a Cuisinarts-Japanese joint venture to market the new
Cuisinart line.
   Cuisinarts product lines include food processors, stainless
steel cookware, accessories, and other kitchen appliancess such as
hand mixers.
   Leo Rizzuto, chairman and president of Conair, said Cuisinarts
will prove to be a ``major asset'' to Conair.
   Rizzuto said Conair hopes to double Cuisinarts sales within two
years by expanding the business.
   ``We will expand the business by applying the same manufacturing
and marketing expertise to Cuisinarts as we have to our other
businesses,'' Rizzuto said in a statement. ``We intend to spend
significant dollars to advertise and promote exclusive, top-quality
features of the Cuisinarts brand.''
   Rizzuto said Conair will broaden the Cuisinarts line with
professional quality products in other kitchen categories in the
future.
   The first Cuisinarts products available through Conair will
reach store sheleves in February, the company said.
   Cuisinarts was founded 18 years ago by Carl Sontheimer, a
retired inventor who holds dozens of patents, and his wife,
Shirley, both of Greenwich. Sontheimer sold the company in 1988 to
a group of investors.
</TEXT>

</DOC>