<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0106 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1400EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-IceRefugees     12-29 0514</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ice Refugees,0528</SECOND>
<HEAD>Big Chill Boosts California Winter Tourist Season</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By E. SCOTT RECKARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   December's record deep freeze has Easterners
and Midwesterners clogging phone lines at desert resorts and
Universal Studios as they seek escape in the Southern California
sun.
   ``We have an 800 number to call for information about Palm
Springs and it's been ringing off the hook. And most of the calls
have been from back East,'' said Carolyn Patten of the Palm Springs
city tourism office.
   ``They want to know `Can we get some sun?' They are so tired of
the snow. I don't know how they're going to feel in March, but they
hate it now,'' Patten said Thursday.
   It's too early to cite statistics, but a survey of resort hotels
in the Coachella Valley surrounding Palm Springs indicated this
winter tourist season looks like a scorcher, with a hot streak of
early bookings.
   ``The phones are just going crazy on us,'' said Jim Lopez,
marketing director at the 860-room Marriott Desert Springs Resort
in Palm Desert. ``We've seen an increase in reservations within a
two-week time period, and I think that's because it's been pretty
darn cold around the country.''
   Typical high temperatures last weekend were 12 in Detroit, 14 in
Indianapolis, 44 in Miami Beach and 37 in Orlando, Fla.
   It was 82 in Palm Springs, part of unseasonably warm weather in
what forecasters say may be the driest December since 1876.
   Since then, things have averaged out again, with temperatures in
both Florida and Southern California running in the 60s and 70s.
But the earlier news of the big chill that extended into Florida
had its effect.
   ``Some of the people coming from back East this year have
remarked they were coming here instead of Florida because the
weather is better,'' said Ken Irwin at La Mancha Private Villas,
where amenities such as private swimming pools and tennis courts
come at a price tag of up to $895 a night.
   Overall, Southern California tourism has been slowing despite an
increase in foreign visitors, said Jack Kyser, chief economist for
the Greater Los Angeles Chamber of Commerce.
   Americans are traveling less because of fears of a weaker
economy, higher air fares ``and there is a lingering fear of
earthquakes,'' Kyser said.
   But at the Universal Studios tour, where a fake quake is a
popular ride, the flood of calls has been greater than usual this
post-Christmas season, said spokesman Jim Yeager.
   ``The tour guide person says the last two to three days the line
has been ringing off the hook with people from the East Coast,''
Yeager said.
   ``We are getting a lot of calls coming in and the first question
asked is, `What is the weather?''' said Rolfe G. Arnhym, executive
vice president of the Palm Springs Chamber of Commerce.
   All that interest could disappear, he points out, with just one
cold snap or a few stories about desert storms.
   ``We've had situations where the weather has done a 180 on us
and our tourists have scampered off elsewhere.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>