<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0183 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2123EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SecretTaping     12-18 0744</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Secret Taping,0766</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Union Says Police Monitored Telephone Tapes</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Police Taping</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JUDD EVERHART</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HARTFORD, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A retired union leader said Monday that
state police officials used tape recordings of telephone
conversations at state police barracks to gather evidence against
union members.
   ``Every (grievance) hearing I ever went to, I think they had a
transcript of some call. They did that all the time,'' said the
retired union leader, who spoke on condition he not be quoted by
name and is also a former state trooper.
   However, the former union leader said he sometimes used the
tapes to gather information when he was putting together a case for
a grievance.
   The revelations were the latest in the secret taping scandal
since Nov. 7, when The Hartford Courant reported that state police
routinely recorded all calls into and out of state police barracks,
including those between suspects and their attorneys.
   Gov. William A. O'Neill's counsel, Howard G. Rifkin, said Monday
there had been no evidence any calls were monitored to gather
union-related evidence on anyone.
   He and Tom Gariepy, spokesman for Attorney General Clarine Nardi
Riddle, said they had found that some calls were monitored to make
sure phones weren't being abused.
   ``We didn't find anything to show that there was an intentional
effort to ... use tapes against a trooper,'' Rifkin said.
   State police Commander Bernard R. Sullivan said through a
spokesman he would have no comment on the newest allegations.
   The taping issue prompted a hearing Monday before a
congressional subcommittee in Washington. The panel was told that
state or local police or corrections officers in at least 12 other
states routinely record lawyer-client conversations.
   Federal laws prohibit taping telephone calls without the consent
of one of the two people using the telephone. State and federal
laws prohibit the recording of any lawyer-client conversations.
   The taping disclosures have prompted an FBI and federal grand
jury probe and at least five civil lawsuits have been filed.
   State police officials have said the tapes were only used for
authorized purposes, and were seldom listened to. They have
insisted that calls were taped to provide a record of emergency
calls.
   The officials have said only a few authorized members of the
department had access to the tapes. But union sources speaking on
condition of anonymity said the tapes were sometimes not guarded
and that many department members had access to them.
   Disclosure of the taping led to the removal of Lester J. Forst
as state police commander and public safety commissioner by
O'Neill, who ordered an immediate halt to taping of attorney-client
calls. The governor ordered an investigation by state officials
into the practice that determined that the taping was inexcusable,
but was not used to illegally gather evidence against suspects.
   The former union leader said he recalled one instance where an
argument between a sergeant and a trooper could be heard in the
background on the tape of a call between another trooper and
someone else. The argument was transcribed and used as evidence of
insubordination, he said.
   He said he sometimes called department officials and got them to
say incriminating things on a taped phone line to be used when he
was putting together a grievance case against the department.
   He said he would go into a barracks after midnight and
transcribe portions of the tape he wanted.
   The Courant on Monday described a 1979 incident of monitoring
tapes when troopers at the Bethany barracks decided to protest
manpower shortages through a sickout, in which troopers falsely
claim to be sick and refuse to go to work.
   A copy of an internal investigation report on the sickout
obtained by The Courant shows that state police officials listened
to hours of the tapes and transcribed and summarized parts of them.
The transcripts were then used as evidence in disciplinary actions
against a sergeant and several troopers.
   Other monitored conversations include a trooper talking about a
grievance he filed, and troopers talking to friends outside the
department.
   Robert J. Krzys, a union lawyer, said the union is trying to
determine whether similar monitoring of tape recordings has been
going on during the past three years.
   Krzys said he only knows of one recent case in which a
transcript was introduced, involving a sergeant's call from the
Bethany barracks.
   The union has filed a lawsuit saying its members were as much
victims of the illegal taping as the public.
</TEXT>

</DOC>