<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0120 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1608EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People Sub a0592 12-18 0453</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People, Sub, a0592,0463</SECOND>
<HEAD>CBS Officially Names New Programs Chief</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 5th item in AM-People to add details. Adds byline.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAY SHARBUTT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Television Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   CBS, fallen on hard prime times and hoping to
change that, on Monday named as its chief programmer Jeff Sagansky,
a movie executive who worked at NBC when that network was making a
comeback to first in ratings.
   Sagansky's job is ``to put on contemporary, successful
programming and to do it with some flair and imagination ...,'' CBS
Broadcast Group president Howard Stringer said in an interview.
   The appointment of Sagansky, 37, president of Tri-Star Pictures
since March, had been expected. But it was delayed a week while CBS
and Columbia Pictures, Tri-Star's parent company, negotiated a
release from his Tri-Star contract, which had a year to go.
   On Jan. 1, Sagansky will become the third president CBS
Entertainment has had in as many years. He succeeds Kim LeMasters,
who resigned Nov. 30 after only two years in the job.
   He will be the counterpart of his former boss at NBC, Brandon
Tartikoff, whose network has led prime time ratings for four
seasons and is expected to be first again this season. Sagansky was
NBC's senior vice president for series from 1983 to 1985, when he
joined Tri-Star as production president.
   CBS has been third in evening ratings for two consecutive
seasons, posted its worst-ever November ratings this year, and is
expected to conclude this season in third again, adversely
affecting CBS's revenues.
   But Sagansky, who previously worked in a CBS finance post two
years after graduating from Harvard in 1974, said in an interview
from Los Angeles that he had no trepidations about rejoining the
network.
   And, he said, ``I think you've got to be really audacious,
innovative and aggressive'' because of fierce competition not only
from NBC and ABC but also from cable, the young Fox network, and
other viewing alternatives.
   Although the time for mid-season changes is approaching,
Sagansky said he had no immediate fixes of CBS' schedule in mind.
   ``I don't think there are any immediate fixes,'' he said. ``I
think this is a case of targeting your (program) development for a
specific time period. There's a lot more competition now than when
NBC did it.''
   CBS previously considered Sagansky for the job in 1987.
   Sagansky was again wooed before and after CBS unsuccessfully
last week tried to lure to its vacant job a top TV production team,
Marcy Carsey and Tom Werner, whose company makes NBC's ``The Cosby
Show'' and ABC's ``Roseanne.''
   Stringer called CBS' talks with Carsey and Werner ``a brilliant
detour'' that ``almost came to fruition. But Jeff is the guy we
wanted ...''
</TEXT>

</DOC>