<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0195 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0501EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DigestBriefs     12-18 0725</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Digest Briefs,0752</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Initiating the painful process of
dismantling a centrally run economy, the Solidarity-led government
has introduced legislation to break up state monopolies and turn
industry over to the private sector.
   It will be the most radical economic reform ever attempted in
the East bloc _ and massive unemployment and steep price increases
are initially expected as state subsidies to industry end, forcing
unprofitable enterprises to close.
   The Warsaw Pact country whose people led the way in forcing an
end to four decades of Communist domination now faces the daunting
task of rebuilding a wrecked economy from the ground up.
   Finance Minister Leszek Balcerowicz announced the program to a
special Sunday session of Parliament's lower house, asking that it
be approved in time to be implemented Jan. 1.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Six months into its review of federal energy
policy, the Bush administration has come to at least one clear
conclusion: the Reagan-era theme of ``just keep the oil flowing and
keep it cheap'' is too simplistic for the 1990s.
   Energy Secretary James D. Watkins says oil inevitably will be
the dominant fuel well into the 21st century. He has become
convinced, though, that the federal government must do more now to
begin curing the nation of its costly oil addiction.
   It's not yet clear how the new federal role will be written, but
almost certainly it will emphasize the virtues of conservation and
renewable energy resources.
   That alone would be a major change from the eight years of the
Reagan administration, which tried to abolish the Energy Department
and, failing that, consistently cut its budget for energy
conservation. The department's 1989 conservation budget was less
than one-third its 1980 level, adjusted for inflation.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Rev. Bruce Ritter has long been synonymous
with Covenant House, the Times Square shelter that grew into a
world-renowned refuge for street kids through the Franciscan's
vision, savvy and tenaciousness.
   Now, Ritter is faced with allegations that threaten not only his
reputation but also the very viability of the institution he
created.
   Last week, Ritter was forced to call a news conference to deny
reports that he had sex with a young man he had helped, and that he
improperly spent Covenant House funds on the man.
   ``It's every organization's nightmare,'' said E. Jeff Baron,
executive director of Emergency Shelter, which also helps runaway
youths. ``It basically strikes at the very heart of what you're
trying to accomplish.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>AUGUSTA, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Attempts to reintroduce caribou to Maine
have been thwarted by disease and bears, but based on the success
of a hearty doe named Daisy, officials will keep trying to
``transplant'' animals from Canada.
   ``We were amazed she was in as good condition as she was in''
after a 600-mile trek into and out of Canada, said wildlife
biologist Mark McCollough, leader of the privately funded Maine
Caribou Project.
   Of a dozen North American reindeer released last spring in
Baxter State Park, only Daisy is known to be alive, although a
second caribou that lost its radio collar may also be, said Richard
B. Anderson, project coordinator.
   Five caribou died after being attacked by bears, and five died
of the ``brainworm'' parasite. Others still being kept in pens have
been ravaged by brainworm and ulcers, said Anderson. More than two
dozen caribou that were used as a breeding herd remain in pens at
the University of Maine at Orono.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>HOLLYWOOD (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In a season when too many smiling cherubs and
sugar plum fairies can make your teeth ache, movie makers are
offering a respite from cheerfulness with the most serious batch of
Christmas films in recent memory.
   Holocaust survivors, a paraplegic Vietnam war veteran and a
platoon of black Civil War soldiers are arriving at theaters for
the holidays.
   Some observers see the blitz of ``message'' films as contrary to
conventional Hollywood wisdom.
   ``It used to be: `You don't open Hamlet at Christmas,' just as
you don't open heavy drama in the summer,'' said Art Murphy, who
follows the industry for the trade paper Daily Variety.
   ``I remember 20 years ago when Columbia opened `In Cold Blood'
at Christmas. It was a great movie. But did people really want to
say `Merry Christmas, let's go see the family get slaughtered?'''
</TEXT>

</DOC>