<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1219EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Romania 4thLd-Writethru a0510 12-27 1110</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0510,1144</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Government Begins Taking Control, Promising Not To Betray Revolution</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE with new comments from president, gunbattle
at television headquarters. This subs for outdated 3rd Ld-Writethru.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DUSAN STOJANOVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Romania's new president today defended
the swiftness of Nicolae Ceausescu's trial and execution and said
there had been indications forces loyal to the ousted dictator
might try to free him.
   Pro-Ceausescu security police today attacked Bucharest
television headquarters, where the provisional government was
based, but were driven off by army units supporting the revolution.
   ``After a gunbattle of a half an hour, the army regained firm
control of the situation,'' Hungary's MTI news agency reported from
the scene.
   MTI said the army was in control of most of the capital but that
there were fears the security police would strike again.
   Overall, however, things appeared to be quiet, and businesses
and factories began resuming operations after the 12-day-long
revolt that ousted Ceausescu after 24 years of strict Communist
rule.
   The governing National Salvation Committee demanded that
security police surrender by Thursday and indicated they face the
same fate as Ceausescu and his wife, Elena, if they do not.
   The government set up military courts Tuesday to try members of
Ceausescu's vicious security police.
   Ion Iliescu, named president by the governing National Salvation
Committee, today defended the secrecy surrounding the Ceausescus'
trial and execution on Christmas Day.
   ``We are people carried away by a very spontaneous process. So
there was a general demand which pushed us to follow this
process,'' he told French television. He said the security police
could have tried to rescue Ceausescu.
   Romania's Agerpres news agency said Tuesday night that Romania's
interim leaders set up special military courts to try ``all cases
of terrorist acts'' and said sentences would be carried out
``immediately.''
   It said the interim government demanded all members of the
security police surrender by Thursday afternoon or they will be
``tried and condemned.''
   Romanian television Tuesday night showed the first videotape
footage of the trial of Ceausescu and his wife.
   ``Everything that was said here is false, and I don't want to
talk anymore,'' Ceausescu told his accusers, insisting he was still
in power and refusing to acknowledge either the severe hardships he
forced on his people or the massacre of thousands of people by his
security forces.
   Earlier in the day, state television showed pictures of the
bullet-riddled bodies of Nicolae and Elena Ceausescu, who was
second-in-command in Romania.
   Ceausescu, unrepentant right up until his execution, did not
tolerate even the mildest dissent in 24 years of rule, and many
Romanians are concerned that the bloody 12-day-old revolution that
toppled him will not lead to democracy.
   Iliescu, in a speech Tuesday night, stressed that the 37-member
National Salvation Committee intends to govern only until ``new
structures'' can be established under a new constitution.
   The leadership promised free elections in April, which would be
the first in Romania since 1937.
   The committee, comprised of dissidents, disaffected government
officials and army commanders, has run the short and bloody
revolution since taking over television headquarters Friday.
   Sporadic gunfire still rang out through parts of the capital
after proof of the execution was broadcast, but Bucharest radio and
Romanian sources said Ceausescu loyalists were surrendering by the
hundreds.
   Many buildings in Bucharest were burned out or pocked by the
thousands of bullets and shells fired in earlier battles between
the army _ which sided with the people _ and security forces
sniping from windows and rooftops.
   The provisional government appointed its leaders on Tuesday and
said it was repealing many hated laws that held Romanians in a
straitjacket of repression, including one that required the
registration of all typewriters.
   Some members of newly founded political parties demanded that
all Communists be excluded from the government.
   The committee said Iliescu, 59, a senior Communist official
until his demotion by Ceausescu, would remain chairman as well as
president. Petre Roman, a 43-year-old professor of hydroengineering
with no political background, was named prime minister.
   In one of the government's first acts, Iliescu and Defense
Minister Gen. Nicolae Militaru ordered the dreaded state security
department placed under the jurisdiction of the defense agency,
leaving only traffic police, firefighters and prison guards under
the jurisdiction of the Interior Ministry.
   Other decrees repealed laws forbidding unauthorized contact with
foreigners and requiring the intelligentsia to live in the same
city where they work _ a statute frequently used to banish critical
voices to remote towns.
   ``What we have achieved so far is to solve only emergency
problems,'' Prime Minister Roman told the Soviet television news
program ``Vremya.''
   ``The questions I'll be dealing with are connected with
restoration of the economy under new conditions.''
   In a late night television address reported by Agerpres, Roman
said his new government would be formed ``quite soon.''
   ``We are not in a desparate situation,'' he was quoted as
saying. But he noted that ``the Ceausescu clique'' left the economy
a ``disaster.''
   ``The economy and social organization were ... at (the) beck and
call of two primitive minds, with no perspective, but with the
thirst for power,'' Roman said of the Ceausescus.
   At his trial, the 71-year-old Ceausescu lashed out at his
accusers as the charges were read against him and refused to reply
when asked who ordered that demonstrators be shot on Dec. 17 in the
western city of Timisoara, where the revolt began.
   ``This was a coup d'etat, and I don't answer your questions,''
he said.
   The Ceausescus were convicted of killing more than 60,000 people
during their years in power, stashing more than $1 billion in
foreign banks and ruining the national heritage and economy.
   Romania's standard of living has plunged in recent years because
of Ceausescu's harsh campaign to pay off the foreign debt, which
included exporting the vast bulk of the nation's crops.
   A military officer who asked not to be identified said 300
soldiers volunteered for the firing squad to kill the former ruling
couple but only three were chosen. The Ceausescus' were granted
their last wish, to die together, the officer said.
   ``Down with tyranny!'' a radio announcer proclaimed after the
executions. ``Romania is free ... the supreme moment has come.''
   For some, death was not enough.
   ``He should be stripped naked, and his body paraded through the
streets,'' said Dimitru Minca, 70, whose 14-year-old grandson was
among those killed in the unrest.
   The Ceausescus were reportedly captured in an underground bunker
after fleeing the capital in a helicopter. Their son and daughter,
Nicu and Zoia, and other family members were arrested and
reportedly face trial.
</TEXT>

</DOC>