<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0221 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0219EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Panama-Business Bjt   12-21 0738</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Business, Bjt,0765</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Businesses Close Offices, Assess Impact Of Panama Action</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARIANN CAPRINO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   American corporations closed offices in Panama and tried to
assess the damage from the surprise U.S. military action that
resulted in the first closing of the Panama Canal in many years.
   Citibank closed its branches in Panama City on Wednesday,
soap-making at the Colgate-Palmolive Co. factory halted and Borden
Inc. shut an ice cream plant.
   Shippers remained calm in the face of the rare closing of the
Panama Canal, which has been shut only for landslides in its
75-year history. A prolonged closure could delay exports of South
American fruit, raise some prices in the United States and force
importers to find alternate routes.
   The number of U.S. businesses operating in Panama has declined
by roughly 30 percent in recent years because of the unstable
political environment and a deteriorating economy. Merrill Lynch &amp;
Co., for example, moved its Panama operations to the Cayman Islands
last year.
   Direct U.S. investment in Panama is insignificant, said
Nathaniel Leff, a business professor at Columbia University.
   ``It's not a country like Brazil, where there are (U.S.)
carmakers and drug companies,'' he said. Companies that operate
plants there market Panama-made goods mostly within the country.
   Borden's two factories in Panama City were closed because of
fighting, a spokesman said, but a third factory that makes
processed cheese in the northwest province of Chirique was
operating as usual.
   ``All our properties and people are safe,'' said spokesman Jim
McKinley. ``We don't have a feel for when they will open,'' he said
of the shuttered plants, which make ice cream and powdered drink
mixes.
   A spokesman for Colgate-Palmolive said he did not know when the
company's Panama factory, which makes soap, toothpaste and
cleaners, would reopen.
   Citibank closed its six branches in Panama City early Wednesday.
Spokesman Ken Campbell said the bank was trying to find out how
employees were affected.
   United Brands Co., which owns the Chiquita banana brand, said
operations were normal. But spokesman Peter Fay said the company
``feared for the general safety of our employees.''
   United Brands ships 30 million boxes of bananas each year from
Panama. Fay would not say what percentage travel through the Panama
Canal.
   Exporters found good news in President Bush's announcement that
the United States was lifting economic sanctions against Panama.
   The U.S. military action followed the secret swearing-in of
opposition leader Guillermo Endara as Panama's president. Endara
was widely regarded the winner of May elections but Gen. Manuel
Antonio Noriega blocked him from taking power.
   At the Port of Houston, where about 15 percent of foreign trade
moves through the Panama Canal, spokesman Lee Vela said exporters
would benefit, but ``we won't know exactly how much until April or
May.''
   According to the Commerce Department, the major U.S. exports to
Panama are cigarettes, aluminum, fuels and perfume.
   The 51-mile canal lost some strategic importance in the 1950s
with the development of supertankers and other ships too large to
traverse its six locks.
   Still, roughly 14 percent of U.S. international sea trade passes
through the canal, government sources said. The canal remains
critical to the shipment of raw materials as well as fruits
exported from South America.
   ``If you're putting copper ore on a freighter that has to go to
Western Europe, it has to go through the canal. Iron ore from
Brazil to Japan has got to go through the canal,'' said George
Zimmerman, an analyst with Gruntal &amp; Co., a New York securities
firm.
   But because traveling through the canal can add as much as a
week to shipping time, only goods that are not time-sensitive move
through the waterway. A hot consumer electronics product from Asia
that has retailers clamoring probably would not move through the
canal, experts say.
   The canal continues to do a lot of business because it is among
the lowest-cost routes. Air transportation is costly, and not all
goods can be shipped from South American ports up the east and west
coastlines.
   Shippers were optimistic that the canal would reopen today.
   General Motors Corp. spokeswoman Karen Longridge said a ship
loaded with Geo Metro and Storm automobiles from Japan was just
outside the canal, resting at sea.
   ``If things don't change in a short period of time, we will
probably send it to the West Coast, unload it and ship it by rail
back to the East,'' she said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>