<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0220 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0818EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APArts:OscarRace Adv26   12-22 0745</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP Arts: Oscar Race, Adv 26,0757</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv 26</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Tues PMs, Dec 26 and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Academy Award Race Will Feature More Modest Movies</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BOB THOMAS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The entries for the 62nd Academy Awards have
all made their appearances, and the race shapes up as a contest
between the little people and the giants.
   Critics' awards have already appeared, and although they tend to
be more esoteric than the Oscars, the choices indicate a trend
toward more modest films.
   Spike Lee's ``Do the Right Thing'' was named best picture by the
Los Angeles critics, edging out ``Drugstore Cowboy.'' The New York
Film Critics Circle chose ``My Left Foot,'' and the National Board
of Review selected ``Driving Miss Daisy.''
   Observers believe that Academy voters will nominate many of the
independent and minor-budget films and pay little heed to the
multimillion-dollar grossers of 1989, such as ``Batman,'' ``Indiana
Jones and the Last Crusade,'' ``Honey, I Shrunk the Kids,'' ``Look
Who's Talking'' and ``Ghostbusters II.''
   Victory for the independents would mirror the 1985 awards, when
two low-budget films won acting honors: Geraldine Page in ``The
Trip to Bountiful'' and William Hurt in ``Kiss of the Spider
Woman.''
   Here's how the Oscar race appears to this onlooker:
   _ Best Picture. The question is: Will Academy voters remember
well-praised films released earlier in the year? If they do, such
pictures as ``sex, lies and videotape,'' ``Do the Right Thing,''
``When Harry Met Sally...'' and ``Field of Dreams'' might be
recognized. But the voters have notoriously short memories, and
they may select such recent arrivals as ``Enemies, A Love Story,''
``Glory,'' ``Driving Miss Daisy'' and ``Born on the Fourth of
July.'' Two imports, ``My Left Foot'' and ``Henry V'' also stand a
chance.
   _ Best actor. Morgan Freeman seems a certain nominee for his
role as the devoted chauffeur in ``Driving Miss Daisy,'' rather
than his supporting role as a Union soldier in ``Glory.'' Daniel
Day-Lewis is a favorite as the cerebral palsy victim in ``My Left
Foot.''
   However, oldline Academy members may want to reward the
veterans: Gregory Peck as the iconoclastic Ambrose Bierce in ``Old
Gringo''; Jack Lemmon as the befuddled oldster in ``Dad''; Jack
Nicholson as the Joker in ``Batman''; Paul Newman as roistering
Earl Long in ``Blaze.'' Then there are the noteworthy newcomers:
Tom Cruise, the Vietnam veteran in ``Born on the Fourth of July'';
Kenneth Brannagh as the ruler ``Henry V''; Ron Silver as the
much-married Holocaust survivor in ``Enemies, A Love Story.''
   _ Best actress. The leaders present a marked contrast: Jessica
Tandy, the cantankerous widow in ``Driving Miss Daisy'' and
Michelle Pfeiffer, the sexpot chanteuse in ``The Fabulous Baker
Boys.'' Other favorites are Andie MacDowell, the betrayed wife in
``sex, lies and videotape''; Pauline Collins, the liberated
housewife in ``Shirley Valentine''; and Meg Ryan, the career woman
looking for love in ``When Harry Met Sally...''
   Kathleen Turner could attract votes for her battling wife in
``The War of the Roses,'' as well as Sally Field for her grieving
mother in ``Steel Magnolias.'' Other contenders could very well be
Jessica Lange, the lawyer defending her father in ``Music Box,''
and perennial nominee Meryl Streep, the romance novelist of
``She-Devil.''
   _ Best supporting actor. Denzel Washington and Morgan Freeman
could both be contending as the Union soldiers in ``Glory.'' Martin
Landau and Alan Alda might compete for their roles in ``Crimes and
Misdemeanors.''
   Other possibilities include James Earl Jones, ``Field of
Dreams''; Danny Aiello, ``Do the Right Thing''; Armin
Muehller-Stahl, ``Music Box''; Robert Loggia, ``Triumph of the
Spirit''; and the late Ray McAnally, ``My Left Foot.''
   _ Best supporting actress. There's a mixed field including Julie
Roberts, ``Steel Magnolias''; Laura San Giacomo, ``sex, lies and
videotape''; Anjelica Huston and Lena Olin, ``Enemies, A Love
Story''; Diane Wiest, ``Parenthood''; Mary Stuart Masteron,
``Immediate Family''; Olympia Dukakis, ``Dad''; and Brenda Fricker,
``My Left Foot.''
   _ Best director. This category is usually dictated by the
choices for best picture. The leading candidates are neophyte
Steven Soderbergh, ``sex, lies and videotape''; Paul Mazursky,
``Enemies, A Love Story''; Oliver Stone, ``Born on the Fourth of
July''; Bruce Beresford, ``Driving Miss Daisy''; Costa-Gavras,
``Music Box''; and Jim Sheridan, ``My Left Foot.''
   Some of the above will receive the best possible Valentines when
the Academy nominations are disclosed on Feb. 14. The winners will
be announced from the stage of the Los Angeles Music Center on
March 26.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv PM Mon Dec. 26</NOTE>

</DOC>