<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1043EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ColdRdp 1stLd-Writethru a0452 12-27 0832</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Cold Rdp, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0452,0857</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pipe Breaks Leave Communities Dry Across South</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Frozen Crops, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 3rd graf, `It's unbelievable ..., to UPDATE
with service being restored in Jackson; SUBS 12th graf, `Particularly hard
..., to conform; SUBS grafs 15-16 pvs, bgng, `Ten crews ..., with 3 grafs
to UPDATE with mayor's comments today; picks up 17th graf, `Houston residents
...</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GARTIES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of people across the South were left without water or
found their taps producing a trickle too weak for a decent shower
because the Christmas weekend freeze cracked pipes.
   Texas plumbers called for out-of-state reinforcements, hotels
with water offered special rates to folks desperate to bathe, and
the National Guard trucked water in to Pollock, La.
   ``It's unbelievable, unbelievable,'' said Bennie Payne, who was
busy dispatching plumbers from his Central Plumb It Yourself Supply
in Baton Rouge, La. ``Our guys are working till they drop. I don't
know how much longer they can keep up this pace.''
   However, in one of the hardest hit cities, Jackson, Miss.,
officials said today that they were making rapid progress toward
fixing the broken pipes and restoring normal service.
   From Dallas to Raleigh, N.C., a strange sort of spring thaw
followed the rare weekend freeze: Pipes, unprotected from the cold,
cracked open as freezing water expanded, then began dripping and
gushing as temperatures rose Monday and Tuesday.
   The worst of the South's cold wave appeared over, with the
National Weather Service predicting lows today at or above freezing
in much of the region and rising to the 50s and 60s today and
Thursday.
   Elsewhere, freezing rain was forecast today across the Plains
and light snow from the Great Lakes and Ohio Valley east into West
Virginia, western Pennsylvania and New York state and into New
England.
   The wintry weather has been blamed for the deaths of 97 people
since Dec. 15.
   The cold destroyed much of Florida's valuable citrus crop and
froze an estimated 65 percent of Texas' oranges and grapefruit on
the trees.
   Louisiana fishermen were astounded to see ice in the shallows
where they earn their living.
   ``We have banks that are solid white with fish and frozen fish
floating everywhere,'' said Joe Buras, president of the Delta
Commercial Fishermen's Association of Plaquemines Parish. ``We have
islands with ice sticking 2 or 3 feet high and bays that are frozen
solid.
   ``It looks like Alaska it's so bad right now.''
   Particularly hard-hit with water problems were Jackson, with an
estimated 60,000 homes and businesses left dry, and Houston, where
one official guessed the number affected may have topped 100,000.
   Jackson officials asked laundries, car washes and other
businesses that use large amounts of water to stay closed a second
day today, and non-essential government workers were ordered to
stay home.
   Residents who had water were warned to boil it for three minutes
to kill germs that are a threat when levels are low. Low pressure
also hampered firefighters' in battling blazes.
   However, Mayor Kane Ditto said today that conditions were
quickly returning to normal.
   ``We are in much better shape this morning,'' Ditto said on
ABC's ``Good Morning America.'' ``We suspect that about 20 percent
of the homes might now be out of water and hopefully those will be
back up sometime during the day.''
   Ditto said 10 crews were restoring service to the remainder of
150 major breaks reported since Saturday.
   Houston residents hankering for showers were obliged _ at
$25-a-douse _ in the downtown Holiday Inn and the Ramada Inn near
the Astrodome.
   Low pressure plagued much of the city and homeowners found
waiting lists as long as two weeks for plumbers.
   The John Moore Plumbing Co., with a backlog of 2,000 trouble
calls, was recruiting out-of-state plumbers to bolster its staff of
28, said Shirley Kurtz, sales manager.
   Plumbing breaks also caused problems in places including Dallas,
Baton Rouge, Mobile, Ala., Meridian, Miss., Charleston, S.C., and
Raleigh.
   In West Ashley, S.C., Linda Singletary said her water pressure
was so low it took 45 minutes to run a sinkful to wash the dishes.
   ``The shower, you can't soap yourself down because it wauld take
you three hours to get the soap off,'' Ms. Singletary said.
``Washing your hair is out of the question.''
   More serious problems abounded.
   Four National Guard trucks from Camp Beauregard, La., hauled
6,000-gallon water trailers to the desperately dry town of Pollock.
   Water gushing from broken pipes ruined 240,000 pounds of food
intended for distribution to the needy, said Ron Prado, director of
the Bay Area Food Bank.
   Cold-caused property damage in the Dallas area, most of it from
broken pipes, could total $25 million, an insurance industry group
predicted.
   Among Dallas businesses with water damage was The Hard Rock
Cafe, where a pipe broke, pumping 900,000 gallons of water into the
basement Christmas Day.
   ``We lost all our food, computers and amplifiers,'' said
assistant general manager Rob Perez. ``It was pretty brutal.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>