<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1225EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Panama-Wounded 1stLd-Writethru a0493 12-21 0360</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Wounded, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0493,0367</SECOND>
<HEAD>Planes Bring Wounded From Panama to Texas Base</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: UPDATES throughout with more than 190 reported in San Antonio,
conflicting figures from Pentagon. No pickup.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KELLEY SHANNON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN ANTONIO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Doctors and nurses at San Antonio military
hospitals postponed holiday leaves and worked extra shifts today
treating more than 190 soldiers hurt in Panama, the biggest influx
of casualties here since Vietnam, officials said.
   Two C-141 transport planes carrying 85 soldiers arrived today at
Kelly Air Force Base; two planes on brought 108 to Kelly on
Wednesday, hospital spokesmen said. Four of the soldiers died en
route here or after arrival.
   The Pentagon today reported 19 dead, one missing and 117
wounded; there was no immediate explanation of the discrepancy in
the number hurt.
   Kelly officials were told their base would receive all the
soldiers injured in the fighting in Panama.
   The wounded were taken by ambulance, bus and helicopter from
Kelly to 1,000-bed Wilford Hall Medical Center at adjacent Lackland
Air Force Base and to Brooke Army Medical Center, the military's
leading burn unit.
   ``The biggest and the most extensive injuries are gunshot-type
wounds, schrapnel-type wounds, leg wounds, broken bones, this sort
of thing,'' said Lackland spokesman Lt. Col. Johnny Whitaker.
   Whitaker said it is the largest surge of injured at the San
Antonio hospitals since the Vietnam War.
   He said the military would not release the names of the dead or
injured until family members were notified. However, Whitaker said
patients range in condition from fair to critical.
   Doctors and nurses were called in on extra shifts and some
holiday leaves were delayed, he said.
   More than 200 military doctors and 500 nurses are stationed at
Wilford Hall. The hospital, the Air Force's largest, also treated
victims of the U.S. invasion of Grenada and the bombing of the
Marine headquarters in Lebanon in 1983.
   Motels near Wilford Hall were offering complimentary rooms for
relatives of wounded soldiers, Whitaker said.
   Reporters were kept outside a Lackland gate about a half-mile
from the hospital, but ambulances could be seen shuttling between
Wilford Hall and the Kelly tarmac.
</TEXT>

</DOC>