<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0206 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 2051EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f BC-Week'sBusiness Adv30-31   12-29 1034</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Week's Business, Adv 30-31,1065</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv30</HEAD>
<HEAD>$adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release weekend editions Dec. 30-31</HEAD>
<HEAD>Unfinished Business of '89 Comes Back to Debt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICK GLADSTONE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   From the budget deficit to bad loans, from
bankruptcies to unsaleable junk bonds, one of the biggest
unfinished stories of 1989 boils down to borrowed money.
   The consequences of selling, trading and repackaging debt are
only now beginning to bubble to the surface, economists and
financial strategists say.
   ``What's still unfinished is determining how excessive was the
excess lending,'' said James Grant, a credit-market analyst who
writes a newsletter about interest rate trends.
   ``That's not just the unfinished business of the year but of the
decade,'' Grant said. ``So what we'll discover as the `90s roll in
is just how reckless was reckless.''
   The final weeks of the year left the federal budget deficit
growing so fast it could bump against the $100 billion Gramm-Rudman
annual ceiling eight months before the fiscal year ends,
threatening to provoke a new round of cuts in government aid
programs at a time when the ranks of the poor are growing.
   Bankers on both coasts have suddenly realized what their
counterparts in the oil and farming regions have known for years: A
declining property market makes mortgages to many homebuyers and
developers unprofitable, compounding the default problems raised by
other risky lending.
   ``I think our society is debt fragile,'' said Robert Dugger,
chief economist of the American Bankers Association in Washington.
``And a major part of the unfinished business left over for the
1990s is correcting the statutory (tax) incentives we have to use
debt rather than equity to finance.''
   Some banking analysts now worry that a severe economic decline
could cause an alarming number of bank failures, forcing the
government to rescue depositor funds with the kind of
megabillion-dollar bailout it faces from the savings and loan
crisis.
   On the corporate level, the twilight of 1989 left some
high-profile companies in almost hopeless hock and others battling
for time to pay their bills, a partial result of an unprecedented
era of debt-financed takeovers.
   The end of the year also cast a shadow on the $200 billion
market for high-yield, high-risk IOUs known as junk bonds, once
considered the wonder-drug of finance but now shunned by many
investors and banks, fearful of getting burned.
   Investment firm Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Co., an aggressive
user of junk bonds for takeovers, watched one of its debt-financed
companies retreat to bankruptcy court this past week. Hillsborough
Holdings Corp., formed by Kohlberg to acquire building materials
maker Jim Walter Corp. for $2.4 billion, sought Chapter 11
protection.
   Perhaps the biggest junk bond casualty is Campeau Corp., the
giant retailer now facing relentless pressure from creditors and
suppliers who want reassurances they'll get paid. Campeau's stores
owe more than $7 billion, which has forced the parent company to
put its crown jewel, the swank Bloomingdale's chain, up for sale.
   Such problems tend to set off chain reactions. For example,
Campeau's inability to pay suppliers could derail another big
debt-financed takeover, the $3 billion acquisition of
sheet-and-towel maker West Point-Pepperell by Chicago industrialist
William Farley, maker of Fruit of the Loom underwear.
   If Campeau can't pay West Point-Pepperell, Farley might have to
sell Fruit of the Loom to pay his debts _ the financial equivalent
of selling the underwear off his back.
   ``All these fellows need nice, pliable suggestable lenders, who
have belatedly woken up,'' Grant said. ``In the debt financing
business, the kneebone's connected to the thighbone.''
   The financing vacuum has frozen the frenetic pace of takeovers,
making the future of that trend another piece of unfinished
business for the year. Few deals over $2 billion _ a paltry sum by
last year's standards _ were completed in 1989.
   ``The megadeals are pretty much gone,'' said Steven P. Galante,
managing director of Buyout Publications, a Needham, Mass.,
newsletter that tracks developments in corporate mergers.
   ``Primarily it has to do with the lenders,'' Galante said.
``They're under intense scrutiny. They're not making loans at
prices that have been paid in the past.''
   Fears that debt and bankruptcy will be the business legacy of
the '80s are by no means universal. Many economists reject this
thinking as outdated and overblown. Some say the U.S. economic
position at the end of the year was stronger than ever and that
most corporate borrowing remains healthy.
   ``I don't believe the trouble in the junk bond market means that
deals that aren't appropriate on their merits won't get done,''
said Giulio Martini, economist at Sanford C. Berstein &amp; Co., a New
York investment firm.
   ``The junk bond market is a $200 billion market in a $5 trillion
economy. You'd have to have more severe problems to have much of an
effect,'' said Martini, who has forecast a relatively strong
economy for 1990.
   Others believe the problems faced by businesses that have risked
their existence through debt are simply paying the price of
surviving in a capitalist economy. The net result, they say, is
more efficiency.
   ``Most of the companies that go bankrupt continue to produce
goods and services,'' said Allan Meltzer, an economist at the
Carnegie-Mellon University in Pittsburgh. ``When people get wiped
out, somebody takes their place.''
   In other business and economic news during the last week of the
year:
   _Signs of trouble in the domestic auto industry intensified with
the announcement that General Motors Corp. would cut 3,200
production jobs. The three U.S. automakers plan to idle most of
their plants temporarily because of slow sales, which some
economists see as evidence of a possible recession.
   _The Securities and Exchange Commission named a new top cop to
police the stock and bond markets. Twelve-year SEC veteran lawyer
William McLucas will preside over a major expansion of the
enforcement division, which led the crackdown on Wall Street
corruption in the 1980s.
   _Japan unveiled a major reform package of economic steps
designed to make the world's wealthiest country an importing
powerhouse in the next decade. The Japanese have been persistently
criticized by the United States and other major economic partners
for running up large trade surpluses and arousing protectionist
feelings.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End adv for weekend editions Dec. 30-31</NOTE>

</DOC>