<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0147 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1945EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Ethiopia     12-18 0361</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Ethiopia,0372</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israel Opens Embassy in Ethiopia in Bid for More Jews</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israel has opened an embassy in Ethiopia and
intends to establish a consular section to encourage the emigration
of more Jews to Israel, the Foreign Ministry said Monday.
   Israeli officials have declined comment on persistent reports
suggesting the renewal of ties would lead to Israeli military aid
to Ethiopia in exchange from allowing more Jews to leave.
   The Israeli Embassy was opened Sunday under the supervision of
temporary representative Meir Yoffe, and an ambassador in Addis
Ababa will soon be appointed, a Foreign Ministry spokesman said.
   Yoffe said his first priority would be establishing a consular
section to deal with Jewish emigration.
   Speaking on Israel Radio in a telephone interview from Addis
Ababa, Yoffe indicated Foreign Minister Moshe Arens may visit
Ethiopia for the official opening ceremony. He did not give a date
for the ceremony.
   A Foreign Ministry statement said earlier this month that Israel
hoped more Jews would emigrate from Ethiopia once Israel
established its embassy there.
   Ethiopia renewed diplomatic relations with Israel on Nov. 3. It
was one of more than 12 black African nations that severed ties
with Israel over the 1973 Middle East war. Several have renewed
relations since 1982.
   ``It is a wonderful and exciting feeling,'' said Yoffe, who was
the last Israeli diplomat to leave Ethiopia in 1973. ``We are
received with joy and sympathy by the government and in the
streets, in all the places we go ... people remember us.''
   The Sunday Times of London has said Israel agreed to supply
spare parts for Soviet weapons in Ethiopia in exchange for
emigration of Jews. Israel has captured Soviet weapons from Arab
countries and Palestinian guerrillas in Lebanon.
   Ethiopian immigrants in Israel say up to 18,000 Jews want to
flee the East African nation, which has suffered from drought and
civil war.
   There are already about 16,500 Ethiopian Jews in Israel. About
8,000 of them were brought to Israel in a dramatic U.S.-assisted
``Operation Moses'' airlift in November 1984-January 1985. But
reports of the airlift leaked out and embarrassed the Ethiopia's
Marxist government, which ended the operation.
</TEXT>

</DOC>