<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1119EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Durenberger     12-28 0687</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Durenberger,0706</SECOND>
<HEAD>More Questions Raised About Durenberger Condo Deal</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MINNEAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. Sen. Dave Durenberger signed backdated
real estate partnership documents to justify collecting living
expense reimbursements from the Senate in 1983, according to a
published report today.
   The Star Tribune of Minneapolis said the backdating made it
appear that the Minnesota Republican's partnership with a local
businessman was operating as the official owner of his Minneapolis
condominium in mid-1983, when in fact legal documents were not
drawn up until months later, apparently in the spring of 1984.
   Durenberger's chief of staff, Bert McKasy, said an oral
partnership agreement between Durenberger and Roger Scherer had
been reached in 1983, and that backdating official documents ``is
done'' in that kind of circumstance.
   ``What in fact happened was that in July of 1983, Mr. Scherer
and the senator agreed to form a business partnership, and their
lawyers did not reduce the partnership to writing until sometime in
December of that year,'' McKasy said.
   The backdating was disclosed in documents Durenberger filed
voluntarily with the Senate Rules Committee last week.
   Durenberger sold his downtown Minneapolis condominium to a
partnership, in which he was a member, and later to a company owned
by his former campaign manager. In both instances, he continued to
live there, but used Senate expense account funds to pay his rent.
According to previous reports, Durenberger collected at least
$9,947 in living expense payments from the Senate for time spent in
Minneapolis from July 1983 to June 1987.
   Durenberger has asked the Senate Rules Committee to review the
propriety of using his Senate expense account to pay rent for his
condominium and has said he will repay any improper expenditures.
   The Rules Committee staff believes that the senator apparently
did not violate Senate rules with his deal, but tentatively
determined that questions about the matter should be referred to
the Senate Ethics Committee.
   The Ethics Committee already is investigating a book deal in
which Durenberger made $100,000 between 1984 and 1986, and trips to
Boston in 1987 paid for by lobbyists.
   Durenberger apologized to Minnesotans at a news conference last
week, saying he did nothing illegal but acknowledging mistakes and
``lapses of judgment.''
   State Sen. Bill Luther announced Wednesday that he and other
Democrats will ask the Senate Ethics Committee to investigate the
condo arrangement, including the backdating of documents.
   ``It appears that the deed has actually been backdated in order
to justify payments that were made out of the public treasury,''
Luther said.
   According to the Star Tribune, deeds turning over the
Durenberger condo to the partnership are dated July 28, 1983. They
were notarized by Hennepin County Commissioner Randall Johnson,
then a legal adviser to Durenberger's campaign.
   However, documents Durenberger turned over to the Rules
Committee indicate that, as of March 1984, Durenberger had not
signed documents setting up the partnership. He signed them
sometime in mid-1984 and dated them July 1983 to reflect an oral
agreement made in 1983 with Scherer, the newspaper said.
   Senate records show Durenberger began filing for reimbursement
for rent in August 1983.
   In a Dec. 28, 1983, letter to Durenberger, which he gave to the
rules panel, Johnson told him: ``It is important that you conclude
the condominium transaction in order to justify the per-diem
(per-day) reimbursement you received during the August recess.'' He
added, ``Everything should be dated before Aug. 1, reflecting the
oral agreement between you and Roger.''
   On May 15, 1984, a deed signed by Durenberger, notarized by
Johnson and dated July 28, 1983, was filed at the Hennepin County
courthouse, the Star Tribune said.
   Johnson declined to comment because the matters concern a
relationship with a client, the newspaper said.
   Because Minnesota law requires a written document to make
property transfers valid, Durenberger would still have been the
legal owner of his condominium in August 1983, when he began filing
for reimbursement under the partnership arrangement that had not
yet been signed, the Star Tribune said.
   Four months later, Durenberger filed papers with the Senate
changing his official Minnesota residence to Avon, his family's
hometown, retroactive to July 28, 1983, the newspaper said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>