<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0107 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1911EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-NorthwestFlight 4thLd-Writethru a0585 12-30 0903</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Northwest Flight, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0585,0927</SECOND>
<HEAD>Threatened Plane Lands in Detroit After Most Passengers Cancel</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: SUBS 4th graf, ``We landed...' to DELETE redundant reference
to Whalen. Picks up 5th graf, ``No one...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PAR1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOSE MARTINEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ROMULUS, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Northwest Airlines DC-10 landed without
incident Saturday despite a bomb threat that prompted more than
three-quarters of the passengers to cancel their reservations on
the flight from Paris.
   ``This is probably a safer flight than any other to be on,''
said Jennifer Ruskin, a 20-year-old junior at the University of
Michigan in Ann Arbor. ``The interviews now with all the media are
probably the scariest part of the flight.''
   Only 22 passengers and nine crew members were on board Flight
51, said Northwest spokesman Kevin Whalen, who was on the flight.
Airline officials in Paris said earlier that the plane carried 28
passengers and 14 crew members.
   ``We landed on the runway, then we taxied out at least a quarter
of a mile, then we were bused to the terminal,'' Whalen said.
   ``No one on board was forced to work this flight,'' Whalen said
of the crew. ``I slept. Most passengers enjoyed a lot of personal
attention. It was almost like having a private airplane.''
   The plane left Charles De Gaulle airport in Paris earlier
Saturday and landed at Detroit Metropolitan Airpiort in Romulus
shortly before 5 p.m. EST, an airport spokesman said. The jet can
hold 284 passengers.
   A telephone caller said the flight would be targeted to avenge
the life sentences given two Palestinians convicted in a series of
European bombings, including an attack on a Northwest Airlines
office.
   The plane's departure was delayed two hours by fog and intensive
security checks.
   ``I wasn't worried a bit, especially after all the security we
went through to get on the flight,'' said Mike Matour, 22, of
Philadelphia. ``They checked our bags two and three times and then
they checked us.''
   Norman Luck, a reporter sent on the flight by the London Daily
Express, said he was a little concerned after the plane took off.
   He said Whalen told the passengers that ``once we were on board
and those doors shut, that the plane was safe, but I don't really
know about that because throughout the flight I watched the
attendants keep checking the sky cabs, the cupboards and underneath
the seats.''
   Some of the 105 passengers who canceled said in Paris that
Northwest should have informed them earlier of the threat.
   ``They've had my telephone number since yesterday morning
locally and nobody had called me with any information of any
kind,'' said Ken Reichenbach of Portsmouth, Va. ``What I've
learned, I've learned from third-hand information.''
   The airline said Friday it would rely on the media to spread
early word of the bomb threat. Some passengers learned of it only
upon arriving at the airport Saturday.
   ``I would have been on pins and needles the whole way,'' said
Camille Major, 21, of Madison, Wis., who was headed home after
three weeks in Europe. ``Six hundred dollars isn't worth my life.
My vacation was bad and this just tops it off.''
   Northwest said passengers could change to other flights or
airlines with no penalty, and most accepted the offer.
   Security officers inspected every piece of hand luggage before
the passengers boarded, causing a brief initial delay from the
scheduled 12:40 p.m. departure.
   Armed officers of the air and border police and riot police with
dogs shepherded passengers through scrupulous check-in procedures.
Each piece of luggage was X-rayed on freeze-frame video machines.
   Even a small souvenir bust of Napoleon was put on the belt and
X-rayed separately.
   All carry-on luggage was searched by hand. The Hsia family of
Foster City, Calif., near San Francisco, waited 45 minutes before
they were cleared for passage to the departure lounge.
   On Thursday night, ABC News, quoting sources it did not
identify, reported that a man with a Middle Eastern accent called
Northwest's Detroit office and said Flight 51 would be bombed in
retaliation for the convictions and life sentences given two
Palestinians convicted in Sweden this month in a series of bombings.
   One of the two, Mohammed Abu Talb, is a suspect in the December
1988 bombing of Pan Am Flight 103 over Lockerbie, Scotland.
   He and co-defendant Marten Imandi were sentenced to life in
prison for their parts in the 1985 bombing of a Northwest office in
Copenhagen that killed one person and wounded 20. They also were
convicted in three other bombings in Denmark and the Netherlands.
   It was not clear when the threat was received.
   Pierre Quilici, deputy chief of France's Air and Border Police,
said U.S. authorities passed on word of the threat several days ago.
   Northwest spokesman Douglas Miller in St. Paul, Minn., said
Northwest informed the FAA, FBI, CIA and foreign agencies of the
threat and was advised by the FBI not to disclose any other details
about the threat, including where or when it was made.
   The airline announced the threat Thursday after reports of it
emerged in Europe.
   The Federal Aviation Administration and airlines have come under
pressure to disclose security risks after the Lockerbie bombing,
which killed 270 people. A threat against Pan Am before that flight
was circulated within the U.S. government but was not made public.
   FAA spokesman John Leyden said Friday U.S. airlines receive
about 300 threats each year.
</TEXT>

</DOC>