<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0320EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-PeskyPants     12-30 0386</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Pesky Pants,0399</SECOND>
<HEAD>Moleskin Pants Destroyed in Fire; Tradition, Too</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OWATONNA, Minn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When a pair of yellow moleskin pants went
up in flames, so did a 25-year holiday tradition.
   Every Christmas, the trousers were hauled back and forth across
the southern Minnesota community between the homes of
brothers-in-law Larry Kunkel and Roy Collette. Every year, the
packaging was goofier.
   This year, an epitaph delivered with the ruined pants Saturday
told the story:
   ``Sorry Old Man, here lies the pants ... An attempt to cast the
pants in glass brought about the demise of the pants at last.''
   Back up to 1964, when this got started.
   Kunkel's mother gave him the pants, yellow moleskin, a strong,
cotton-twill fabric supposedly good for Minnesota winters. Kunkel
found out they stiffened up in the cold, so he gave them to
Collette. The pants weren't warm enough to suit Collette so he
handed them back to Kunkel.
   Back and forth the pants went each Christmas, until Collette
upped the ante: One year he encased them in concrete.
   That's when the wrapping began to get out of hand: a truck tire
filled with nine tons of concrete, a welded-up 600-pound safe, a
17-foot concrete-filled rocket, a crushed automobile, a 225-pound
steel ashtray, a four-ton Rubik's cube, a totaled station wagon
jammed with 170 steel generators.
   Along the way, news stories about the ``pesky pants'' attracted
attention from all over the U.S. and from as far away as Europe and
Australia.
   This year, it was Collette's turn to deliver the pants. His
inspiration: Encase them in 10,000 pounds of jagged glass that he
would deposit in Kunkel's front yard. ``It would have been a great
one, really messy,'' Kunkel said Thursday.
   Collette shipped the pants to a friend in Tennessee who manages
a glass manufacturing company. While molten glass was being poured
over the insulated container that held the pants, an oversized
chunk fractured, transforming the pants into a pile of ashes.
   So, the ashes were deposited into a brass urn that now graces
the mantel in Kunkel's home.
   ``It's over,'' he said. ``Too bad, but once they were destroyed,
that's it.''
   Collette isn't so sure.
   ``Listen, Larry's the most competitive person I know. I won't be
surprised if I get the ashes back _ in something _ next year.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>