<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0103 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1555EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Poland     12-19 0591</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland,0610</SECOND>
<HEAD>Letter of Intent With IMF Completed, Poles Say</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DANISZEWSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government and International Monetary
Fund on Tuesday finished drafting a letter of intent on an economic
adjustment plan leading to $700 million in standby loans to Poland,
a Finance Ministry official said.
   The letter should be signed after it is reviewed by senior
government officials, said Deputy Finance Minister Janusz Sawicki,
dismissing suggestions that a delay had arisen.
   ``There are no disappointments. I can say it is going on
schedule,'' Sawicki said. ``Of course, you could always wish for
miracles.''
   An IMF mission headed by European Department head Massimo Russo
left Poland on Tuesday after completing the agreement that requires
Poland to embark on tough economic reforms to get the IMF credits.
   There was no reason to initial the letter right away, said
Sawicki, who took part in the negotiations on the Polish side.
   Asked whether the IMF aid will arrive in time to assist Poland
as it undertakes economic reform scheduled to begin Jan. 1, Sawicki
said several Western countries probably would offer a bridge loan
in the interim before the first IMF installment arrives.
   He said he also hoped a $1 billion stabilization loan being
prepared by Western countries to back the Polish currency would be
ready early next year.
   ``Every hour is now being counted,'' he said.
   The letter of intent is to be reviewed by senior members of the
Solidarity-led government of Prime Minister Tadeusz Mazowiecki
before its signing, Sawicki said. After it is signed, it is to be
sent to IMF Managing Director Michel Camdessus and the IMF board of
executive directors in Washington.
   Deputy Prime Minister Leszek Balcerowicz and Polish National
Bank president Wladyslaw Baka will sign the letter for the Polish
side, the state PAP news agency reported.
   The agreement, which Mazowiecki's government has been
negotiating since it took office in September, is tied to the
sweeping economic reform program that the governent introduced in
parliament Sunday.
   It calls for strict measures to balance the budget, decontrol
prices, limit wages, break monopolies, introduce partial
convertibility of the zloty and privatize state industries.
   The agreement will certify to Western leaders that Poland is
making serious efforts to put its economy in order, and is expected
to result immediately in $300 million in World Bank loans and about
$3 billion in other Western aid.
   The holders of Poland's $40 billion Western debt also are
expected to agree to rescheduling part of that debt.
   The progress in talks with the IMF came on the third day of a
Parliament debate concerning the radical economic reform program
Balcerowicz submitted Sunday.
   For the second straight day, the debate was dominated by
deputies from rural areas complaining the budget does not do enough
to help farmers obtain agricultural inputs such as farm machinery,
pesticides and fertilizers, and that the government should set
minimum prices for farm produce.
   Agriculture Minister Czeslaw Janicki said he sympathized with
many of the complaints about lack of government funds for
agriculture. But he said that the state's finances would not allow
anymore at present.
   ``It is impossible to do everything overnight,'' he said.
   As the Sejm, or lower house of Parliament, debated throughout
the day, a 43-member extraordinary commission set up to review the
government's economic package was meeting behind closed doors.
   Deputies said the commission would be doing much of the real
work on analyzing the package, which would then be put to a vote of
the full Sejm sometime after Christmas.
</TEXT>

</DOC>