<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1100EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Soviet-Politics 2ndLd-Writethru a0526 12-19 0584</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Soviet-Politics, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0526,0596</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Survives First Parliamentary No-Confidence Vote</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 11 grafs to UPDATE with quotes by Gorbachev and Ryzhkov;
Picks up 10th graf, `The vote ...'; ADDS 1 graf at end with other action.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANDREW KATELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Parliament put the government through its first
no-confidence vote today over an economic reform plan that retains
heavy central planning, but Premier Nikolai I. Ryzhkov and his
ministers easily survived.
   In the dramatic confrontation, the normally sophisticated
Ryzhkov's voice cracked with emotion as he pleaded for support.
Progressives have criticized his economic package as inadequate to
the task of ending a grave economic crisis.
   They say it doesn't go far enough to overhaul a plodding
bureaucractic system and encourage greater productivity and
efficiency by embracing free market mechanisms.
   ``The Congress should not avoid making an evaluation. It must
express its firm position: either to support the government's
proposals, of course considering the remarks made here, or some
other formulation,'' Ryzhkov told the 2,250 members of the Congress
of People's Deputies, the Soviet Parliament.
   After his appeal, the no-confidence motion was rejected by tally
of 1,685 to 199 with 99 abstentions. The ruling Communists hold 87
percent of the chamber's seats.
   Yuri Andreev, a parliamentarian from Moscow, proposed the
no-confidence vote after a heated debate in which progressives
attacked the government plan as inadequate to the task of effective
reform.
   Ryzhkov's plan shifts traditional central planning from an
emphasis on heavy industry to consumer goods. It speaks of
developing a market but says little about concrete measures for
freeing products from the iron control of ministries for free sale
on the market.
   Andreev urged Parliament to express its lack of confidence in
the government by asking it to draft a new economic reform plan and
to fire the officials who drafted the original version.
   Just before the vote, Ryzhkov took the floor and in an emotional
statement with a cracking voice, rejected a proposal that the plan
merely be taken into consideration and asked for a straight yes or
no vote.
   President Mikhail S. Gorbachev, who was presiding over the
session, agreed that Parliament should take a firm decision. But,
he added that congressional committees would consider changes in
the plan suggested by the deputies.
   ``It's a political question: Will we support this government,
that which it introduced, or will we keep the government in such a
state all the time that it cannot start its work?'' Gorbachev asked.
   The vote on approving the economic plan was 1,532 to 419, with
44 abstensions. Ryzhkov stood and clasped his hands in an
expression of victory as deputies applauded approval of the plan.
   In Sunday's Sovietskaya Rossiya newspaper, Ryzhkov implied he
would resign if the deputies did not accept his economic proposal.
   Asked what would happen if the program did not pass, Ryzhkov
said, ``Then other people will work it out. Then, it will not be
Ryzhkov going to the rostrum, but somebody else.
   ``I am responsible for my program, I believe in it, and I will
never deny anything that is signed by me. If I ever feel fear, then
there is no place for me in the government.''
   In other action, the leadership failed to muster the required
majority to alter the constitution to allow the Communist Party and
other officially approved organizations to continue to fill a third
of the Congress seats themselves. The current Constitution
guarantees a third of the seats to those groups.
</TEXT>

</DOC>