<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0203 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1914EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     12-20 0440</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0452</SECOND>
<HEAD>Winter Cold Reached Many Of The Gulf Of Mexico States</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Cold weather extended deep into the South and the Southwest on
Wednesday, with record lows in the nation's midsection, and heavy
snow fell around Lake Erie.
   Overnight temperatures reached 32 degrees or lower as far as
much of North Carolina, south carolina, northern Georgia, northern
Alabama, northern Mississippi, much of Louisiana, northern
two-thirds of Texas, New Mexico, northeastern two-thirds of
Arizona, east-central and north-central California, eastern
two-thirds of Oregon, and the eastern half of Washington state.
   Below zero temperatures extended from across the upper half of
the Plains, western Ohio, northern Maine, and the northeastern half
of Montana.
   Wednesday's low for the Lower 48 states was 34 below zero at
International Falls and Warroad, Minn. Unofficially, Embarrass, in
northeastfern Minnesota, reached 37 degrees below zero.
   Wednesday's record lows were 2 at Calico Rock, Ark.; 9 at Hot
Springs, Ark.; 4 at Paducah, Ky.; 12 below zero at Peoria, Ill.; 14
below at Springfield, Ill.; and 11 below at Waukesha, Wis.
   More than 100 low temperature records for the date have been
broken or tied during the past week.
   At noon, wind chill effects over South Dakota ranged from 20
below zero in the south to 50 below zero in the north. Wind chills
reached 45 below zero in Upper Michigan.
   Snow fell at midday over northeastern New York state, from
northwestern through east-central Pennsylvania, across northeastern
Ohio, over western Lower Michigan, from northwestern Illinois
across southwestern Wisconsin, Iowa, southern Minnesota, South
Dakota, Nebraska, northwestern Wyoming and Montana.
   In the snow belt of western New York state, where the moisture
of Lake Erie contributes to ``lake effect'' snow, a highway was
closed by 4-foot snow drifts between Holland and Sardina in
southern Erie County.
   In northwestern Pennsylvania, also near Lake Erie, 12.4 inches
of snow fell overnight at Erie, 4 of that in one hour, and the
airport was closed. That contributed to a total 30-inch snow cover.
   A heavy snow warning in effect through Thursday was posted over
northern Upper Michigan, and a winter storm watch in effect through
Thursday was posted over western and northwest Lower Michigan.
   A high wind warning was posted for this afternoon and tonight
over east central and southeast wyoming. A wind chill warning for
tonight was posted over north central through northeast wyoming.
   Elsewhere, rain was scattered over the central Florida
Peninsula, and from southern Mississippi into southeastern
Louisiana.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EST ranged from 22
degrees below zero at Roseglen, N.D., Warroad, Minn., and
Williston, N.D., to 84 at Homestead, Fla.
</TEXT>

</DOC>