<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1305EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-BudgetGimmicks Bjt   12-28 0845</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Budget Gimmicks, Bjt,820</SECOND>
<HEAD>1990 Budget Gimmicks Put Forthcoming 1991 Hoopla in Perspective</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALAN FRAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   If there were a truth-in-packaging law for
federal spending, President Bush's forthcoming budget proposal
might have to carry this warning label: ``This plan is optimistic
at best and is likely to bear only a partial resemblance to
reality.''
   Bush is expected to propose $30 billion to $40 billion in
savings when he submits his $1.2 trillion spending blueprint for
fiscal 1991 in late January. That would meet a requirement in the
Gramm-Rudman deficit-reduction law that the projected 1991
shortfall not exceed $64 billion.
   The numbers make the proposal sound like a tough attempt to mop
up the government's red ink, which has been about $150 billion
annually for the last three years. But a look back at how the
administration and Congress went about their budget work for this
year is instructive in assessing how the plan for next year may be
translated into reality.
   White House and legislative budget writers began the year by
agreeing to use a set of optimistic economic assumptions that let
them shrink the size of the anticipated 1990 deficit.
   By projecting 1990 economic growth of 3.4 percent and inflation
of 3.5 percent _ both of which now seem rosey _ they were able to
calculate lower government spending and higher revenues than are
likely to occur. Look for a repetition of the age-old tactic next
year.
   Fiscal planners were also able to take advantage of technical
budget rules to chip away at their projections of red ink.
   In one case, the Pentagon ``saved'' nearly $3 billion by
shifting a payday from a Monday in early October to a Friday in
late September. The reason: the new federal fiscal year begins Oct.
1.
   In another instance, of the many billions of dollars the
government expects to spend to bail out bankrupt savings and loan
associations this year, only about $1.4 billion of it will show up
on the budget. The reason: Bush and Congress agreed that the bulk
of the operation would be ``off-budget.''
   ``We did a better job than we have in most previous years in
trying to achieve some deficit reduction, but much of what we did
was to redefine or take advantage of scorekeeping options that
didn't give us real savings,'' concedes Rep. Bill Frenzel of
Minnesota, ranking Republican on the House Budget Committee.
   Last February, a month after outgoing President Reagan submitted
a proposed 1990 budget to Congress, President Bush presented a
$1.16 trillion spending plan of his own.
   Bush said his blueprint would leave a $91.1 billion deficit _
well within the $100 billion target the Gramm-Rudman law required
for fiscal 1990, which began last Oct. 1. It relied heavily on
domestic program cuts, user fees, and new revenues Bush believes
would be generated by reducing the tax rate on capital gains.
   The plan was shrugged off by Congress, which complained that
Bush failed to specify which domestic programs would be slashed.
Serious budget work did not begin until April, when administration
officials and congressional leaders agreed to a plan that would
reap a $99.4 billion shortfall.
   But when Congress adjourned for the year on Nov. 22, lawmakers
and the White House had achieved less than half of what they had
agreed to do. The two sides shook hands in April on $28 billion
worth of deficit-cutting, but in the end wrote only about $13
billion of it into law.
   ``The targets they set were modest,'' says Robert Reischauer,
director of the non-partisan Congressional Budget Office, which
studies fiscal issues for lawmakers. ``And they had a difficult
time even coming to those targets.''
   Indeed, practically one-third of the $13 billion was not a true
bite out of the deficit at all, but rather book-keeping tricks and
changes in federal payment schedules.
   Budget-writers claimed savings of $1.8 billion by not counting
the money the Postal Service is likely to lose this year; $800
million by slowing the rate with which Medicare claims are paid;
and $700 million by delaying for a year some of the payments
federal retirees can collect.
   They also took credit for saving $400 million by moving some
assistance to farmers off-budget; $250 million by accelerating the
payment of gasoline and airline taxes to the government; and $50
million by delaying some federal payments to farmers.
   Few of the savings that were written into law were part of the
April budget pact, or Bush's February budget.
   The president's coveted capital gains tax reduction was gone.
And $4.6 billion of the savings _ a third of the total _ came from
letting indiscriminate cuts in most federal programs imposed by the
Gramm-Rudman law remain in effect for the first 130 days of the
fiscal year.
   The threat of those automatic cuts has been seen since the 1985
enactment of the law as a terrible alternative that would prod
Congress and the White House to work out a better deficit-reduction
deal. Now, they could become a regular part of the budget process.
</TEXT>

</DOC>