<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0144 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1833EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-DisabilityEarnings 1stLd-Writethru a0564 12-29 0355</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Disability Earnings, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0564,290</SECOND>
<HEAD>Disability Benefits To Rise Jan. 1</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: New throughout to CORRECT that `substantial gainful activity'
level for SSI applies only to eligibility, picks up last graf</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   On the first day of the new year, new rules
will raise the amount of money recipients of government disability
benefits can earn, the Department of Health and Human Services
announced Friday.
   HHS Secretary Louis Sullivan said the increases ``will serve as
an additional incentive for many disabled Americans to return to
work and improve the quality of life for themselves and their
families.''
   The rules will affect recipients of Supplemental Security Income
program and the Social Security Disability Insurance program who
are not blind.
   Under the disability insurance program, recipients are allowed
to earn up to a certain amount and still receive benefits. On Jan.
1, that allowed earnings levels will increase for the first time in
more than a decade.
   The new rules will change the trigger for the ``trial work
period'' during which a disability insurance recipient continues to
receive benefits for nine months after returning to work. Since
January 1979, a recipient has entered a ``trial work period'' when
he earns more than $75 per month or works more than 15 hours per
week. That will increase to $200 or 40 hours.
   Also under the disability insurance program, when the
recipient's earnings reach the ``substantial gainful activity''
level, which has been set at $300 per month since January 1980,
benefits can continue only under certain conditions. That trigger
will rise to $500.
   The ``substantial gainful activity'' gauge is also used to
determine eligibility in the Supplemental Security Income program
as well as in the disability insurance program.
   The allowed earnings level for blind recipients of disability
insurance is set by another regulation, and is now $740 per month.
That will rise to $780 on Jan. 1, a Social Security spokesman said.
   The disability insurance program pays about $1.7 billion each
month to 2.8 million workers and 1.2 million dependent spouses and
children of disabled workers. About 3 million blind and disabled
workers receive SSI benefits.
</TEXT>

</DOC>