<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0116 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 2125EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Panama-Wounded 1stLd-Writethru a0639 12-23 0721</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Wounded, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0639,0741</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gifts, Greetings Pour in to Soldiers Wounded in Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 13th graf, `The Pentagon ...,' to UPDATE casualty count.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto SA6</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KELLEY SHANNON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN ANTONIO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A flood of holiday gifts and get-well wishes
overwhelmed scores of wounded soldiers recuperating Saturday from
injuries they suffered in the fighting in Panama.
   ``Who are these people from California?'' Army Cpl. Joel Reyes
asked from his hospital bed as he looked through a gift basket and
read a Christmas card signed by a family.
   A Brooke Army Medical Center official said get-well wishes had
poured in from across the country for the wounded soldiers.
   ``This has been a tremendous outpouring of caring and concern,''
San Antonio Mayor Lila Cockrell told soldiers at Brooke. ``We hope
you'll come back when everything is more peaceful and enjoy our
city ... We hope for each of you a very speedy convalescence.''
   Reyes and more than 100 other soldiers being treated at Brooke
and at Wilford Hall Medical Center were loaded with gifts from
department stores, restaurants and businesses.
   A platter of shrimp from a seafood restaurant sat on a stretcher
in the hallway of one ward at Brooke. The San Antonio Chamber of
Commerce delivered fruit baskets and shopping bags full of gifts _
including chunks of the Berlin Wall.
   Reyes said he injured his arm when it became caught in static
lines while he parachuted from an aircraft. The 19-year-old from
Warden, Wash., is a member of the 2nd Ranger Batallion, 75th Ranger
Regiment.
   Army Spec. 4 August Schomburg of Chicago, who was shot in the
arm, described the difficulty of fighting in Panama.
   ``It was scary _ you never really knew who you were up
against,'' said the 23-year-old father of three. ``Every now and
then someone would wave and blow a kiss. Then someone would shoot
at you.''
   At Dover Air Force Base in Delaware, a cargo plane arrived with
the bodies of three soldiers killed in the fighting.
   Two of the dead were identified as Chief Warrant Officer 2
Wilson B. Owens, 29, of Myrtle Beach, S.C., and Spec. Alejandro I.
Manriquelozano, 30, of Lauderhill, Fla. The third was not
immediately identified.
   The remains of 21 servicemen have been returned to the base
since U.S. troops invaded Panama early Wednesday.
   The Pentagon said 25 American soldiers have died, 241 have been
wounded and one was missing. Two U.S. civilians also have died.
   Dozens of wounded servicemen have been transferred from San
Antonio back to their home bases, including 37 soldiers who
returned to the Army's Fort Bragg, N.C., Friday night.
   ``We're glad you're back, and we're glad you're doing as well as
you are,'' Col. Mark Blaedel, acting commander of Womack Army
Community Hospital at Fort Bragg, said at a news conference
Saturday.
   Most of the soldiers suffered minor wounds, and Blaedel said 22
of them were released from the hospital by Saturday afternoon.
   Sgt. Berry Kelly, a 23-year-old squad leader in the 82nd
Airborne Division, said he was injured when another paratrooper
went over him, collapsing his parachute and causing him to freefall
the last 150 feet to the pavement below. He suffered torn ligaments
in his right ankle.
   The paratrooper from Goodwater, Ala., said he thought he did
well to fall as far as he did ``and only mess up my ankle a
little.''
   Spec. Ronald Stacey, 21, of Kings Mountain, N.C., said he spent
``a good day'' in Panama before he was hit in the arm by shrapnel.
   Both Kelly and Stacey, who wore the Purple Hearts they received
in San Antonio, told reporters their training had prepared them for
combat duty.
   ``I knew what to expect,'' Stacey said. ``It's scary. Quite
scary. You know it's real when somebody shoots back at you.''
   Elsewhere at Fort Bragg, the families of some of the base's more
than 3,000 soldiers in Panama looked to each other to overcome the
hardship of separation.
   ``It's important for the wives and families to stay together,''
said Pam Hall, whose husband, Lt. Col. Wayne Hall, was in Panama.
   ``Some of the ladies who have never been through this are
understandably unnerved. But morale is good. We miss our husbands,
but we are proud of them and respect what they are doing.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>