<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1202EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Philippines-Communists     12-24 0455</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines-Communists,0467</SECOND>
<HEAD>Upheaval Prompts Calls To End SE Asia's Last Major Insurgency</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT H. REID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The unraveling of communism in
Eastern Europe should serve as a warning to Marxist rebels who for
20 years have tried to topple the Philippine government, newspapers
said Sunday.
   The insurgents waging Southeast Asia's last major Marxist
rebellion should consider ``a complete and permanent cessation of
hostilities,'' the Philippine Daily Inquirer said in an editorial.
   ``For its part, Congress should think seriously about legalizing
the Communist Party of the Philippines to give its leaders and
members an opportunity to participate freely and legally in the
politics and government of the country,'' the newspaper added.
   It said the historic changes sweeping the Soviet Union and its
allies had undermined the ideological foundation of Marxism.
   Several major newspapers and a political columnist urged an end
to the insurgency just days before the 21st anniversary of the
creation of the Maoist Communist Party of the Philippines, which
was founded Dec. 26, 1968.
   Columnist Jesus Bigornia, writing in The Manila Bulletin, noted
the bloody overthrow of the 24-year regime of Romanian President
Nicolae Ceausescu, the last Warsaw Pact holdout against reform.
   ``The fate of Ceausescu and his Romanian Communist Party could
serve as a warning to the Philippines,'' Bigornia wrote.
``Possibly, the time has come for the Communist Party of the
Philippines to dissolve its New Peoples Army, lay down their arms
(and) join the mainstream of Philippine society.''
   On Thursday, the rebel National Democratic Front hinted it would
be willing to resume peace talks, which broke off in February 1987.
The Front, an umbrella organization of 12 Marxist groups, declared
a Christmas and New Year's cease-fire but expressed no willingness
for a peaceful settlement of the insurgency.
   ``Let the silence of our guns this Christmas deliver this
message loud and clear,'' the Front said. Similar statements were
issued by the Front during the Christmas seasons of 1987 and 1988.
   ``The (Communist) and government forces have declared unilateral
cease-fires during the holiday season,'' said The Manila Chronicle.
``But come January, it's back to mutual destruction; tough luck for
whomever's in the way.''
   President Corazon Aquino has repeatedly insisted that the
Communists and their estimated 19,000-strong New Peoples Army lay
down their arms before talks can begin.
   The government's hard-line position may reflect a perception
that the rebels do not constitute as great a threat as they
appeared to in the months following the 1986 ouster of President
Ferdinand Marcos.
   In the last three years, the greatest immediate threat to the
Aquino government has come not from the Communists but from
soldiers who have launched six armed coup attempts, most recently
this month.
</TEXT>

</DOC>