<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0091 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1503EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ScienceContest     12-19 0310</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Science Contest,0322</SECOND>
<HEAD>Science Contest Reverses Course, Accepts Late Entries</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Westinghouse national science contest for
high school seniors bent the rules today and agreed to accept 90
entries that arrived late because of a screw-up by Federal Express.
   ``It just wasn't fair, so we're going to admit them,'' said
Westinghouse Electric Corp. spokesman Charles Carroll in Pittsburgh.
   The box of 90 entries from students at Stuyvesant High School in
New York City was due in Washington on Friday but got there Monday.
Seventy other Stuyvesant entries sent in a separate batch at the
same time arrived before the deadline.
   Carol Luszcz, program director for the prestigious Westinghouse
Science Talent Search, initially said the deadline had been clear
and ``we don't make exceptions.''
   But Federal Express admitted it misrouted the box of entries and
sent Westinghouse an affidavit to that effect, said Armand
Schneider, a spokesman for the overnight delivery service.
   News that their entries were disqualified had dashed the
students' dreams of college scholarships.
   ``I cried,'' said Ming Ling Peng, 17. ``It's the ticket to
college for most of us.''
   Stuyvesant is nationally known for academic excellence. Each
year, its students reach the semifinals or better of the talent
search, which began in 1942.
   ``We take extra courses at Columbia and N.Y.U.,'' Miss Peng said
of New York University. ``I know someone who did a physics paper he
had been working on since eighth grade.''
   Eileen Finkelstein, whose son Steven's project was late, said he
was ``devastated'' at being disqualified.
   ``Why should their blood, sweat and tears go down the drain?''
Mrs. Finkelstein asked. ``These kids are the creme de la creme of
the New York system. These are 90 kids who had no control over what
was done to them. Certainly rules can be changed a little bit.
We're talking about children's destinies.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>