<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0088 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1457EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Lithuania     12-30 0519</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Lithuania,0533</SECOND>
<HEAD>First Legal Non-Communist Party Registered in Soviet Union</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANN IMSE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A political party that favors Lithuanian
independence from the Soviet Union has been formally recognized by
the republic, making it the first legal non-Communist party in the
country, acvitists said Saturday.
   The new party is the 2,000-member Party of Democrats of
Lithuania, which advocates full autonomy for the Baltic republic of
3.7 million people, said Pyatrus Pechelunas, a member of the party
presidium.
   The party supports neither socialism nor capitalism but believes
Lithuanians should choose an economic system after the republic
achieves independence, he said from the Lithuanian capital, Vilnius.
   Alternative political parties were illegal until early December,
when the Lithuanian Parliament eliminated a section of the
constitution guaranteeing the supremacy of the Communist Party and
substituted a multiparty system for the small republic.
   Non-Communist parties have cropped up elsewhere in the Soviet
Union but remain illegal. Lithuania's Baltic neighbors, Latvia and
Estonia, are expected to vote in January on similar constitutional
amendments permitting multiple political parties.
   Also registered Friday was the independent Communist Party of
Lithuania. A party congress voted 855-160 last week to break away
from the Soviet Communist Party and support independence for the
Baltic republic.
   The registration of the two Lithuanian parties also was reported
Saturday in the Moscow-based Sovietskaya Rossia newspaper.
   The moves in Lithuanian have brought furious complaints from
Kremlin leaders, who delegated President Mikhail S. Gorbachev, head
of the Soviet Communist Party, to travel to Lithuania in the near
future to discuss the controversy.
   Meanwhile, conservative Communists formed a provisional
leadership for a Communist Party that would remain an integral part
of the Soviet one, Tass reported Saturday. The group opposes
independence, said Vladislav Shved, a secretary of the
``provisional Central Committee,'' in an interview with the Defense
Ministry newspaper Red Star.
   The newspaper quoted Shved as saying the group hoped Gorbachev's
visit would swing wavering Communists back into the Kremlin's
embrace.
   Gintautas Alksninis of Sajudis, the main Lithuanian activist
group, estimated the pro-Moscow group has the support of
approximately 20 percent of the 204,000 Communist Party members in
Lithuania.
   Alksninis, speaking by telephone from Vilnius, said numerous
political parties are signing up members in Lithuania and they
should be registered soon. The Social Democrats are the largest of
the non-Communists, he said.
   The first election pitting alternative parties in Lithuania will
be the republic's parliamentary election Feb. 24.
   In the first election with multiple candidates in March, those
backed by Sajudis trounced conservative Communists who had held
positions of power for decades. Sajudis, as a broad-based
pro-democracy group, includes members of various parties, including
progressive Communists.
   The growing independence of the Baltic nations and other Soviet
republics presents Gorbachev with one of his most pressing
problems. His advocacy of reform since taking power in 1985 helped
fuel movements that toppled hard-line governments in Hungary,
Poland, Czechoslovakia, Romania, East Germany and Bulgaria this
year.
   But Gorbachev, faced with the same sort of reform movements that
he encouraged elsewhere, is trying to slow such nationalism to
prevent the breakup of the Soviet Union.
</TEXT>

</DOC>