<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1306EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-Cuba-Panama 1stLd-Writethru a0534 12-26 0501</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Cuba-Panama, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0534,460</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cuba Accuse U.S. Of Blocking Diplomatic Activity; U.S. Officials
Deny It</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 2 grafs after 1st graf to include State Department response.
pickup 2nd graf, Angel Pino.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. troops at the Cuban Embassy and the
ambassador's residence in Panama City are refusing Cuban diplomats
the right to leave or enter either location and are engaging in
threatening military activities, a Cuban official said today.
   In response, the State Department said U.S. forces ``do not
intend to prevent normal diplomatic activity by Cuban personnel.
Charges to the contrary are not true.'' The department said U.S.
troops are stationed around the Cuban Embassy and several other
places in Panama for security reasons.
   The statement did not address the specific question of access to
the Cuban missions or the Cuban claim that the troops were engaged
in threatening activities.
   Angel Pino, spokesman for the Cuban diplomatic mission here,
said the situation is particularly serious at the ambassador's
residence, where the Cuban diplomats and their families have been
staying since the U.S. invasion last week.
   Supplies of food and medicine are running low and the sense of
unease among those at the residence has been aggravated by
overflights of U.S. warplanes and helicopers, he said.
   The situation is ``becoming grave,'' Pino said, adding that any
incident could provoke ``unforeseeable consequences.'' He said his
government has ``protested insistently'' to American authorities.
He had no estimate of the number of Cubans at the residence.
   In a telephone interview, Pino said the Cuban government was
informed by U.S. officials in Washington and Havana over the
weekend that the situation would be resolved shortly. But there was
no change as of late morning today, Pino said.
   A State Department official said he had no information that
Cubans in Panama were being denied the right to enter or leave the
embassy grounds.
   He said a Cuban diplomat in Panama reportedly told a Cuban radio
station on Saturday that access to and from the residence was not a
problem. But Pino said U.S. troops began blocking access both ways
that same afternoon.
   The State Department official, asking not to be identified, said
the troops outside the residence and the chancery are providing
security at those locations.
   But Pino said Cuban diplomats were told by a U.S. military
officer in charge outside the residence that his instructions were
``to prevent anybody from leaving or entering the embassy.''
   He identified the U.S. officer only as Major Acksun.
   Initially U.S. officials had been concerned that Panama's Gen.
Manuel Antonio Noriega might try to seek refuge in either the Cuban
or Nicaraguan embassies in Panama City. The installations of both
countries were surrounded late last week, prompting the Nicaraguan
government to dispatch two tanks to the American Embassy in Managua.
   Noriega turned himself in to the Vatican Embassy in Panama City
Sunday afternoon. Pino said the U.S. troop presence at the Cuban
ambassador's residence has been reinforced since then.
</TEXT>

</DOC>