<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0208EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-GrinchStrikes     12-25 0470</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Grinch Strikes,0484</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hundreds of Needy People Left Empty-Handed By Theft of Food Packages</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHARLES J. GANS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of needy people were turned away
empty-handed from a community center after a real-life Grinch stole
thousands of dollars worth of food, toys and clothing collected for
a traditional Christmas Eve giveaway.
   Volunteer workers at the Paul Hall Community Services Center
were distributing whatever food and toys were left by burglars who
broke into a storage shed early Sunday morning, said Willie Hall,
director of the center.
   ``We did distribute about 400 food baskets today, but we had to
turn away about 300-400 people this afternoon,'' Hall said.
   ``People were very distressed, but they did understand the
problems. We assured them we are doing the best we can to try to
get some food to accommodate them.''
   The center also had planned to distribute toys to about 1,000
children Christmas Eve, but there were only enough toys left for
500 children, Hall said.
   Frank Campbell, a spokesman for the center, said the theft
disappointed many of the needy _ some of whom had been waiting in
freezing temperatures as early as 7 a.m. for the afternoon
distribution.
   ``Some Grinch came in and stole Christmas for these kids,''
Campbell said. ``Our main goal was to supply a nice meal for people
who are poor and homeless throughout the city.''
   The thieves also stole train sets, remote-controlled cars and
other toys donated by local businesses, Hall said.
   The burglars must have been prepared for the theft, Campbell
said, because in four hours they stole several hundred 10-pound
turkeys, hams and chickens as well as several hundred toys.
   Campbell said he didn't know the exact value of the items taken
because most were donated, but estimated at least $3,000 worth of
property had been taken.
   As news about the theft spread, hundreds of people came to the
South Side center throughout the afternoon and evening to donate
hams, turkeys and canned goods, Hall said.
   He said organizers planned to distribute food baskets today to
those who were turned away.
   ``The theft did kill the Christmas spirit earlier, but people
have come throughout the day to show the Christmas spirit,'' Hall
said. ``Hundreds of people in the Chicago area have come ... to
help us out in our plight.''
   Police were working to find the culprit or culprits, said
Officer John Crotty.
   ``We're not looking for anything from these (burglars),''
Campbell said. ``What we would like is whoever broke in today to
bring the food back.''
   The community center, originally called the Paul Hall Boys Club,
was founded in the 1960s by the Rev. Paul J. Hall, who gained
national attention for his efforts to help poor youngsters and
their families through such projects as Christmas food giveaways.
</TEXT>

</DOC>