<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1335EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-PropaneBlast 6thLd-Writethru a0509 12-28 0705</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Propane Blast, 6th Ld - Writethru, a0509,0721</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands Evacuated After Propane Explosion, Fire Allowed To Return
Home</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserGraphic</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 9 grafs to UPDATE with revised estimate of number
of evacuees, small number of employees resume work at plant, CORRECT that
tank did not explode, leaking propane did. Picks up 9th graf pvs, `Earlier,
officials...'.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RON FOURNIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BATESVILLE, Ark. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 4,800 residents who were evacuated
after a propane explosion and fire were allowed to return to their
homes this morning when firefighters extingished the remaining
flames.
   No injuries were reported at White-Rodgers Co. when propane
surged from a faulty tank and exploded shortly before 4 p.m.
Wednesday. Workers were evacuated and people who live within a mile
of the plant were ordered from their homes, said Dale Rust of the
Independence County Office of Emergency Services.
   Officials in this town of 9,000 lifted the evacuation order
shortly after 8 a.m., and by midday a skeleton staff of about 30
had resumed work in the plant's payroll and shipping operations.
   Dean Kent, vice president for human resources for the company,
said a small amount of vapor was still leaking from the
38-foot-long tank. It was not dangerous but it prevented
investigators from immediately examining the tank.
   ``Until that completely goes out, we won't be able to determine
what happened,'' Kent said. ``Hopefully, we'll find out what caused
it and do what we can to prevent it from happening again.''
   The fire, which had burned into the night, ebbed this morning
after workers managed to shut off one of the leaking valves that
fed the flames, Mayor Jim Shirrell said.
   ``We're on our way,'' said Amy Boister of Batesville as she left
a shelter set up in a church. Her husband, Lewis, had two green
pillowcases under one arm and a worn plaid sleeping bag under his
other arm.
   Sheriff's officers began pulling back some of the roadblocks in
the evacuated area, at first only allowing residents living in
areas farthest from the plant to return. Later, everyone was
allowed back to their homes.
   Workers using gas meters had determined that there were no
significant propane vapors lingering at the plant or in the
evacuated neighborhood, while firefighters kept their hoses trained
at the tanks to cool them.
   Earlier, officials had expressed fears that the heat could set
off blasts among other nearby tanks.
   The explosion sent a large plume of smoke and fire into the sky
over the town about 80 miles northeast of Little Rock.
   Ten state troopers were sent to the city to help control
looting, after Independence County Sheriff David Hunter said there
had been some reports of burglaries in the evacuated area.
   ``We're having people ripping us off out here,'' Hunter said.
   Emergency workers withdrew from the fire site about 9 p.m. after
gas was detected in the air near the burning tank, County Judge
David Wyatt said. The eight firefighters who had been battling the
blaze retreated to Batesville High School, about a mile away.
   They left three unmanned trucks with their hoses trained on the
fire and adjacent tanks. The mayor said each of the trucks pumped
1,000 gallons of water a minute.
   ``We think we've got it stabilized right now. It should burn
itself out ... if it doesn't rupture and explode before then,''
Rust said. ``We're trying to keep the tanks cool to keep them from
rupturing.''
   Police erected roadblocks to keep people from entering the
evacuated area. Emergency officials drove through some
neighborhoods using loudspeakers to urge residents to leave.
   The eight tanks at the plant contained about 12,000 gallons of
propane, Rust said, which could inflict damage within a mile if it
all exploded.
   The fire was burning about 500 gallons of propane an hour, he
estimated.
   Several churches opened facilities to accommodate people forced
from their homes, Rust said.
   Spokesmen at the city's three motels said they had rented nearly
all of their total of 216 rooms, about half of them to evacuees.
   Officials do not know what caused the tank to rupture and
explode, Rust said.
   The plant, a division of Emerson Electric, manufactures water
heater and gas controls and employs about 1,000 people.
</TEXT>

</DOC>