<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0253EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-Nicaragua 4thLd-Writethru a0434 12-30 0648</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Nicaragua, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0434,0665</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nicaragua: U.S. Searched Envoy's Residence; U.S. Diplomats To Be
Expelled</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 3 grafs to CORRECT that 20 diplomats to be expelled,
220 support staff to be cut. Pickup 3rd graf `It was not...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nicaragua's ambassador to Panama said
U.S. troops searched his residence Friday, and the Managua
government responded by ordering 20 U.S. diplomats to leave
Nicaragua.
   President Daniel Ortega, in Managua Friday night, also ordered
the embassy to cut its service and administrative staff from 320
people to 100 people. It was not known how many staffers are
American.
   Ortega said the diplomats will be given 72 hours to leave the
country after their names are made public.
   It was not immediately known if the head of the embassy, charge
d'affairs John Leonard, was among those to be ordered to leave.
   Nicaragua's ambassador to Panama, Antenor Ferrey, said American
troops searched his residence for about two hours. He said he and
several other people waited outside during that time.
   The troops seized five rifles that Ferrey said were kept at the
residence for self-defense. A U.S. Army colonel in charge of the
operation later apologized and returned the rifles, Ferrey said.
   U.S. Embassy and military officials said they had no information
on the incident.
   American troops have surrounded the embassy since the Dec. 20
invasion that toppled dictator Manuel Antonio Noriega. But they had
not assembled outside the the residence, a cluster of three homes
in an upper-middle class neighborhood. People living near the
residence said Friday they heard gunfire and shouts ordering people
to come out of the residence.
   Ferrey said Ortega told him by telephone that Nicaragua's
Sandinista government planned to protest the incident at the United
Nations and the Organization of American States.
   Ortega said in announcing the expulsions that the incident was
``unheard of. ... They acted arrogantly, like Rambos!''
   ``This violates the principal foundations of the
extraterritoriality of diplomatic missions,'' Ferrey told a news
conference. ``The North Americans are going to pay for it.''
   Ferrey said he returned from Nicaragua's embassy at 6:10 p.m.
EST to discover about 60 U.S. troops had cordoned off several
blocks surrounding the residence.
   The unidentified U.S. Army colonel told Ferrey to go inside the
residence, then the troops used a megaphone to order everyone
inside to evacuate within five minutes, Ferrey said.
   The colonel said he had been given orders to search the
residence for weapons, Ferrey said. A U.S. C-130 transport plane
and a helicopter flew overhead.
   The Nicaraguans eventually came outside and about 30 of the
American soldiers went inside, Ferrey said, adding he was prevented
from accompanying the troops. ``They searched the whole house,'' he
said.
   Ferrey described the five rifles as ``only light arms used to
defend ourselves.''
   He said the colonel ordered the arms placed in a U.S. military
truck but later gave them back and apologized, saying there had
been a mistake.
   The troops left the area of the residence shortly before 9:30
p.m. EST. Ferrey said the U.S. troops had fired shots into the air
before he arrived.
   In the Nicaraguan capital of Managua, a state-run Voice of
Nicaragua report cited embassy employees as saying the troops
``fired in the air and intimidated the people inside and forced
them to come out with their arms in the air.''
   On Thursday, Cuba protested that its ambassador and another
diplomat had been detained an hour by troops surrounding the Cuban
Embassy. U.S. officials denied the ambassador had been detained and
said the other official had forgotten his diplomatic credentials,
which eventually were retrieved.
   A senior U.S. Embassy official said Thursday that under the
terms of the Vienna Convention governing diplomatic procedures,
U.S. troops had the right to search those entering and leaving
missions for weapons and non-diplomatic personnel.
</TEXT>

</DOC>