<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1154EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-Justice-Noriega     12-29 0466</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Justice-Noriega,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>Department Acknowledges Oversight In Drawing Up Noriega Charges</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By W. DALE NELSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Justice Department acknowledged today it
failed to follow its own guidelines for considering national
security problems when it brought drug charges against Panamanian
leader Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   ``It now appears that there was some rush to draw up the Noriega
indictment'' and guidelines requiring a review of national security
implications ``may not have been completely followed,'' spokesman
David Runkel told reporters.
   He added, however, ``We believe there is a strong case against
General Noriega and that case can be successfully brought to
trial.''
   In making the statement, Runkel backed away from his assertion
on Tuesday that concerns about the disclosure of state secrets in
the Noriega case ``have been grossly exaggerated.''
   He said national security issues in the case are being or will
soon be reviewed by prosecutors in the case and their departmental
supervisors.
   Noriega was ousted as Panama's ruler in a U.S. military invasion
Dec. 20 but has found shelter at the Vatican's embassy in Panama
City. A major goal of the operation was to return him to the United
States for trial on the drug charges.
   Runkel said the Justice Department policy that may have been
overlooked requires that when drawing up indictments on matters
involving national security, ``those issues be reviewed prior to or
during the process of drawing up the indictment.''
   He said such a review would include examination by prosecutors
of classified documents.
   ``I had been informed that that was the policy that had, in
fact, been followed in this case,'' Runkel said, adding that this
no longer appeared to be the case.
   He declined to elaborate on the nature of the ``rush'' to draw
up the indictment, saying, ``I haven't determined the reason'' for
it.
   Runkel said the department's decision to review the national
security issues was an outgrowth of a Dec. 14 meeting of
prosecutors in the case with representatives of the Drug
Enforcement Administration, FBI and CIA.
   He said the meeting was called to discuss drug-trafficking
indictments returned in 1988 against Noriega in Miami and Tampa,
Fla., and a decision was made to proceed with the Miami case.
   The Washington Post today quoted Richard D. Gregorie, who
directed the federal grand jury investigation in Miami that led to
one of the indictments, as saying he was never allowed to review
all the pertinent CIA files on Noriega.
   Runkel said Gregorie's statements were also a factor in the
Justice Department's decision to review the matter.
   Concerns about disclosure of secrets in the Noriega case have
arisen from reports that he worked closely with the CIA and the
Pentagon while he served as the head of Panama's military
intelligence service and after he became commander-in-chief in 1983.
</TEXT>

</DOC>