<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0194 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1832EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-Panama-KellyText ??Takes   12-20 0637</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Panama-Kelly Text, ?? Takes,510-up</SECOND>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is the transcript of a Pentagon briefing
on the Panama situation conducted Thursday afternoon.
   PETE WILLIAMS (Defense Department Spokesman): Good afternoon,
ladies and gentlemen. We have an update for you on the situation in
Panama. And here to speak to you are two experts. The person who
will answer most of your questions is Gen. Tom Kelly, who is the
Director of Operations for the Joint Staff. And also with him is
Admiral Ted Sheafer, also of the Joint Staff, whom many of you have
met before.
   I know you have a lot of questions. Our main purpose here today
is to update you on the situation on the ground in Panama. Gen.
Kelly has been following this moment by moment since it began last
night. So he is very familiar with the details and has been at it
the whole time. And we'll go for about half an hour or so.
   General?
   GEN. KELLY: It's very nice to be here, and I appreciate the
opportunity. What I would like to do is show you what our forces in
Panama have done during the day. The Chairman briefed you this
morning on the point at which we had arrived then. Operations have
continued; they have gone fairly well for us.
   We'll start out here in Rio Hato where the two infantry
companies were. You might recall that the infantry companies were
instrumental in putting down the coup on the third of October,
therefore they were considered to be very loyal. The Rangers went
in, took them out; that's been completed. They took their arms
room. They got 250 prisoners, roughly. The rest fled.
   And that's a problem we're having in a lot of areas, in that
much of the PDF (Panamanian Defense Forces) is fleeing in the face
of the U.S. military units. That presents us with a dilemma: Are
they, in point of fact, going to go into the jungle or the woods
and represent a force in the field? Or are they going to resolve on
a life of crime and use their weapons to just raid the people? Are
they going to lay their weapons down and go back and try and get a
job and participate in the hoped for economic prosperity? We don't
know that. That's one of the things we've got to be watching and
one of the things we have to do.
   Over here in the Task Force Semper Fi area everything is pretty
quiet. All of the PDF resistance within that area has been reduced.
As you may recall; there was never very much in the first place,
although I can't guarantee you again, because this is a big open
area with a lot of vegetation, that there aren't some people out
there.
   Let me just sneak out here a little bit. (Moves toward map.)
   Up in the Task Force Atlantic area, everything up there has been
reduced. First, the 8th Company elected not to fight very much in
the first place, and the naval infantry company, which did fight,
has been reduced. Therefore, the situation is calm up there. We
used one battalion to do that, and as you may recall, another
battalion came down into this area, Punta Gamboa, where there's a
housing area and a prison, and protected the housing area and
unprotected the prison; went to Cerro Tigre, where there's an
electrical distribution grid, and secured it; and went to Madden
Dam, possibly the most chief facility along the canal, because as
you know, that's the water that's used to fill the locks that make
the canal functional. If we lost that and the dam had to be
rebuilt, I've seen estimates where it could take a year or longer
to fill back up.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>