<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0127 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 2107EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RetirementHomeFire 1stLd-Writethru a0593 12-26 0479</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Retirement Home Fire, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0593,0493</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nursing Home Fire Began on First Floor, Investigation Continues</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Recasts throughout. ADDS 4 grafs with people to be allowed into
building later in week, Red Cross helping those displaced.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JOHNSON CITY, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A fire that killed 16 people in a
high-rise retirement center started on the first floor, but
investigators have not narrowed down the cause, the city's fire
chief said Tuesday.
   ``I don't think we are looking at arson here. I don't think
we're looking into anything criminal,'' said Paul Souder, assistant
to Chief Doug Buckles.
   The Christmas Eve blaze, the second fatal fire in the John
Sevier center in two months, spread to the second floor and parts
of the third floor of the 10-story building. Smoke traveled to all
floors before firefighters brought the fire under control.
   Grant Trivett and his father, U.G. Trivett Jr., managed the
retirement center, which was renovated as an apartment hotel for
the retired in 1979, a year after the hotel closed. It was built as
a hotel in 1924.
   ``This was an apartment house, with the residents all supposed
to be able to care for themselves, cook their own meals and keep
their own places clean,'' Grant Trivett said. It was not a nursing
home, he said.
   ``We were planning to upgrade our facility with a sprinkler
system,'' he said. ``We didn't feel uncomfortable about it. We felt
it would be a good investment.''
   Souder said a sprinkler system ``would have held (the fire) in
check until we got there.''
   The center, which housed 145 residents, has long concerned city
officials, said City Manager John Campbell.
   ``You have to be concerned any time you have so many elderly
people in a 10-story building,'' Campbell said.
   When the building was opened as a retirement center in 1979 it
was brought up to code, Campbell said, but the building code at
that time did not require sprinklers.
   Sprinklers are required under present code only if renovations
are being done.
   State Rep. Bob Good said the Tennessee Legislature may have to
consider requiring sprinkler systems in older buildings after it
reconvenes Jan. 9.
   In October, a 76-year-old resident, Joseph England, died of
smoke inhalation a few days after a kerosene heater flared, caught
his fifth floor apartment on fire. All residents were evacuated.
   Police said people wanting to retrieve personal belongings would
be allowed inside the building later in the week.
   ``City crews are working to remove equipment and ice from the
building to make it safe for citizens to enter the facility,''
Police Chief Ron Street said.
   The American Red Cross was assisting those displaced by the
fire. The agency said it received a donation of $10,000 from
Mor-Flo Industries, a water-heater manufacturer based in Cleveland
with a factory in Johnson City.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   The Red Cross number for donations is (615)-928-3561.
</TEXT>

</DOC>