<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0117EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WarCrimePapers     12-22 0775</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-War Crime Papers,0796</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eyewitness Accounts of Holocaust Donated to Israeli Archives</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Friday AMs report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRIAN MURPHY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SUNRISE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In cardboard boxes and carefully sealed
envelopes, Leibl Koniuchowsky carried with him tales of the
Holocaust for more than four decades.
   The files, which meticulously document civilian Nazi
collaboration through eyewitness testimony, were known only to a
few Yiddish-speaking scholars and researchers as publishers
rejected Koniuchowsky's queries over the years.
   But his recent decision to donate the records to a Holocaust
archives in Israel has given Nazi hunters new leads on war crime
suspects and drawn attention to the civilian role in the mass
killings of European Jews during World War II.
   ``The Nazis signed the death papers, but the common people who
pulled the triggers are the greater murderers,'' the 80-year-old
Koniuchowsky said in an interview Wednesday at his home west of
Fort Lauderdale.
   ``It's something different to aim the gun and look into the eyes
of someone about to die,'' said Koniuchowsky, who lived in the
Lithuanian city of Kovno.
   His records are now at Jerusalem's Yad Vashem memorial, which is
documenting the slayings of an estimated 6 million Jews by Nazi
Germany.
   Koniuchowsky keeps a silver medal from Yad Vashem in its wood
and velvet case. English translations of some of his records are
stored under a bookshelf in his condominium.
   Nearby, a photograph shows a 19-year-old Koniuchowsky standing
behind his parents, who died in one of the killings of Jews across
Lithuania.
   ``Why I survived is just a miracle,'' he said. ``Long ago, I
stopped looking for answers.''
   The Baltic states were annexed into the Soviet Union under the
secret Molotov-Ribbentrop treaty of 1939. Following the war,
Koniuchowsky, a civil engineer, took a government job traveling the
Lithuanian countryside looking for salvageable machinery.
   He began to keep a diary of his conversations with Jews in the
villages. He would transcribe their descriptions of the executions
and record names of civilians the witnesses said had participated.
Hand-drawn maps and photographs of the mass grave sites were made.
Each page was signed by the person who was interviewed.
   Lithuania, a center of Jewish culture in Eastern Europe, had a
Jewish population of nearly 1.5 million at the turn of the century.
About 26,000 were left after World War II, according to Yad Vashem
records. More than 200,000 Jews are believed to have been killed by
the Nazis in Lithuania.
   ``Some places there were only one or two Jews left,'' said
Koniuchowsky. ``Their stories would have died with them if someone
didn't listen.''
   Koniuchowsky quit his job and spent four years traveling through
villages and refugee camps collecting stories from Jewish survivors
in Poland, Germany and Austria.
   The testimony of 153 Jews was gathered in nearly 1,700 pages
written in Yiddish. The records included the names of about 1,300
alleged Nazi collaborators and sympathizers.
   Koniuchowsky emigrated to New York in 1951 then moved to Israel
in the mid-1970s. He returned to the United States following a 1983
heart attack.
   Koniuchowsky's files are significant because few records exist
of Jewish killings in the small villages, said Efraim Zuroff,
director of the Jerusalem office of the Los Angeles-based Simon
Wiesenthal Center, which compiles records of the Holocaust and
assists in tracking down suspected war criminals.
   ``Based on our past experience this can lead us to numerous Nazi
war criminals now living in the United States, Canada, Australia
and the United Kingdom,'' Zuroff said Tuesday in Israel.
   Zuroff said the center will add names from Koniuchowsky's
records to the list of sought-after war criminals.
   ``After the war, everyone wanted to get the big guys, the top
Nazis,'' said Koniuchowsky. ``But I know that the real criminals
mostly got away. The people who did the killing walked away.''
   John Loftus, an author and former Justice Department war
criminal prosecutor, said the cvilian role in Nazi atrocities has
never been fully examined. Loftus's 1982 book ``The Belarus
Secret'' chronicles the paths to the West taken by those involved
in the massacre of nearly 40,000 Jews in the Belorussian section of
Eastern Europe.
   ``For every known war criminal there are many others who
committed horrible acts but were simply passed over because no one
was there to tell the story,'' said Loftus from his St. Petersburg
home.
   Koniuchowsky says he doesn't seek revenge. He decribes himself
only as a messenger with a sad tale.
   ``I did what I did because it was an order. It was an order
directly from those who were being taken to die,'' he said. ``They
would look back and shout, `Please remember us. Please don't
forget.'''
</TEXT>

</DOC>