<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0131 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1355EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Panama-Treaty     12-20 0387</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Panama-Treaty,0408</SECOND>
<HEAD>Provisions of Panama Canal Treaty</HEAD>
<HEAD>With Panama Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a summary of the two Panama Canal treaties signed in
September 1977 by President Jimmy Carter and Panamanian leader Omar
Torrijos:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>CONTROL</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The United States and Panama will administer the canal jointly
until the expiration of the treaty on Dec. 31, 1999. At that time,
control, management and maintenance of the canal go to the
Panamanian government.
   The U.S. president was to appoint a Panamanian nominated by his
government as administrator to take charge of the canal on Jan. 1,
1990. But the United States refuses to recognize the government of
Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega, and has spurned his choice for the
post.
   President George Bush announced Dec. 5 he asked the canal's
deputy administrator, Panamanian Fernando Manfredo, to take over as
acting administrator. Manfedo accepted.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>DEFENSE</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   For the duration of the treaty the United States has primary
responsibility for the defense of the canal. A board of U.S. and
Panamanian military officers was established to consult on defense
matters and every five years reviews military resources made
available by both countries. During the life of the treaty, the
United States decides on its own how and when to reduce its forces
in the Canal Zone and schedule the closing of its bases.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>COMPENSATION</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The United States pays Panama $50 million to $60 million from
canal revenue and an additional $10 million a year for the canal's
operation. Panama also received $50 million in military assistance
over a 10-year period.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>LANDS AND WATERS</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   About 70 percent of the 500-square-mile Canal Zone reverted to
Panama after the treaty was ratified. The United States retained
temporary control over the rest, including areas considered vital
to running the canal.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>JURISDICTION</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Three years after ratification, American civilian employees in
the Canal Zone became subject to Panamanian law instead of American
law. Panama took responsibility for public and social services,
including schools, the Canal Zone police force, and postal service.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>NEUTRALITY</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Under a separate treaty, the two countries agreed to a guarantee
that the canal would remain open to ships of all nations and that
the canal's neutrality would be respected ``in times of war as in
times of peace.'' American and Panamanian warships and other
vessels were given priority to use the canal.
</TEXT>

</DOC>