<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0128 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1642EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Poland     12-18 0825</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland,0851</SECOND>
<HEAD>Radical Economic Program Debated, Farmers Attack Plan</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DANISZEWSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Solidarity-led government's sweeping
economic reform program came under attack Monday from farmers'
representatives, who said they preferred guaranteed minimum prices
to the risk of a free market.
   Farmers became the first major interest group to object to the
government economic program that was introduced Sunday. The plan
aims to transform Poland into a market economy after 45 years of
Communist economics and calls for sharp cuts in state spending and
subsidies to balance the budget and cure Poland's 900 percent
inflation.
   But while the discussion on farm policy was sharp, the
government's economic reform program as a whole was not considered
to be in serious trouble.
   Agriculture Minister Czeslaw Janicki told the Sejm, the lower
house of Parliament, that the government would create an agency to
intervene in the market if farm prices fall too low, but that it is
essential to move away from government-mandated prices.
   Janicki also promised to curb monopoly food processors to whom
farmers sell, and pledged to try to increase the flow of farm
machinery, fertilizer and other agriculture inputs to the
countryside.
   The reassurances did not satisfy Parliament members from rural
areas who argued for guaranteed prices and more direct state
investment in farming.
   Farmers in food-poor Poland are angry that the government wants
to abandon guaranteed minimum prices for their produce, arguing
that their costs are rising and they need to be assured of
profitability.
   About 75 percent of Poland's farming is in private hands, mainly
on small holdings of only a few acres. Productivity per acre is
about half that of Western Europe.
   In the past, the government fixed prices at what it determined
was a profitable level, often one that rewarded even inefficient
farmers. Lat year, the government moved toward a system in which
prices are to be negotiated freely between farmers and purchasers.
   But farmers have complained that the buyers _ mainly nationwide
Communist Party-dominated food and processing cooperatives _ are
monopolies that dictate unfavorable prices.
   They also complaim that city dwellers unfairly blame them for
1,000 percent price increases in recent months, and that most of
the money has been pocketed by the intermediaries.
   Ryszard Smolarek, a Communist deputy, argued for maintaining
minimum guaranteed prices at least until July.
   ``Agriculture cannot be dumped into the deep water,'' he said.
``Farmers' incomes are going to be left without any protection.''
   ``Opinions are getting more and more radical in the
countryside,'' Deputy Jacek Szymaderski said, arguing for greater
government investment in agricultural development.
   The government did not ``take into consideration the specific
nature of agriculture,'' said Deputy Jozef Zych, a member of the
Peasant Party.
   Over the weekend, Jozef Slisz, the head of the independent
farmers union Rural Solidarity, was ousted at the union's congress
and replaced by Gabriel Janowski, a farmer-senator who was
perceived as more willing to criticize the government.
   ``Our farmer knows a lot and he could do a lot, but his
capabilitiies and his possibilities are limited by a lack of
means,'' Janicki told the chamber.
   ``The state of agriculture, like the whole economy, is a result
of the piling up of problems in the system over several decades,''
he said.
   On the issue of supporting minimal prices of agricultural
products, Janicki said it would be done through intervention in the
market by a new Agency for Agricultural Market Affairs.
   ``This agency will be equipped with essential means and
authority which will allow it to better stabilize the food
market,'' he said. It will make ``intervention purchases'' at the
local level if necessary to support set price levels for grains,
meat and milk, he said.
   The governent will use new anti-monopoly legislation to break up
monopolies in agricultural services and food processing, he said.
   ``As long as there are monopolies in procurement of agricultural
products there will be problems'' in creating a free market,
Janicki said.
   The Sejm is to meet again Tuesday and possibly Wednesday.
   After Sunday's meeting, a 43-member commission of deputies was
formed to review the whole package. Charied by Solidarity Deputy
Andrzej Zawislak, it is to speed review of the package to meet a
Jan. 1 government deadline.
   Asked whether the more than a dozen bills and resolutions could
be approved, Zawislak said, ``There is a chance, because the
extreme situation causes an explosion of social energy that can
carry out great changes.''
   The government has acknowledged the program will lead
temporarily to unemployment and lowered living standards, but says
it is necessary to choke off inflation and make the economy
efficient.
   The plan includes balancing the deficit-ridden state budget
through strict austerity; cutting off most state subsidies; freeing
prices; limiting wage increases; turning the zloty into a
convertible currency; attacking monopolies; reforming the banking
and tax systems; establishing a social safety net for the poor and
jobless; and selling off state industries to the private sector.
</TEXT>

</DOC>