<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0050EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     12-18 0479</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0503</SECOND>
<HEAD>On the Light Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It took Jay Brewer an entire day to put up his
Christmas tree, but you won't find any presents near its base.
   The tree is suspended upside down from a ceiling.
   ``Every day I come home and hope and pray it's still up there,''
he said.
   Brewer decorated the 7-foot-tall artificial tree with bulbs,
1,400 white lights and garland. It is attached to a small motor
that rotates it constantly.
   ``I like to get off the beaten path,'' said the 27-year-old
hairdresser.
   Brewer's Christmas presents are on the ground, stacked by the
tip of the tree.
   It has become a popular holiday attraction in his neighborhood,
with only one drawback.
   ``Most people get dizzy watching it,'' Brewer said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>EVANSVILLE, Ind. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Christmas tree buyers here are learning
a lesson from the Boy Scouts. It's called the honor system.
   ``When lot is unattended drop money in mail slot,'' reads a
hand-lettered sign on the lot where Troop 399 sells about 3,000
trees each year for $6 to $28.
   After 9 p.m., troop members leave the lot unattended.
   ``We pretty much trust everybody in Evansville,'' said Andy
Tenbarge, a 13-year-old Scout working Saturday.
   Troop members don't even count how many trees are gone each
morning.
   ``If someone needs to steal a Christmas tree, they need it worse
than we do,'' said John Rae, a Scout leader who helped sell trees
when the troop started doing so more than 30 years ago.
   That year the troop earned $300. Rae said the sale now generates
enough money to pay for the troop's entire camping program. Last
year, 50 boys were able to spend 10 days in New York, a week skiing
in West Virginia, and about 15 other weekends canoeing, spelunking
and camping.
   On Wednesday, in a show of Christmas spirit, remaining trees
will be offered to those who can't afford to buy one, Rae said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Most square dancers wear brightly colored shirts
and swirling skirts, but one group of performers puts on only
bandanas. They're dogs.
   Called the Promenade Pups, the dog square dance troupe has been
performing in the Dallas area for about a year. During most
performances, eight people dance with eight dogs at their sides.
Sometimes it's dos-a-dos with four people and four dogs.
   Dogs and people wear matching red bandanas.
   The dogs have mastered much more than the dos-a-dos. They also
do a modified version of the Cotton-Eyed Joe, a popular country
music dance. During some of the more difficult steps, the pooches
stand still while their owners dance around them.
   Sally Browning, a professional dog training instructor who
organized the troupe, said the dogs are great performers _ most of
the time.
   ``Every now and then a dog won't do it quite right,'' she said.
``We know it. But you don't.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>