<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0139 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1732EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Corcoran-Resignation     12-18 0682</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Corcoran-Resignation,650</SECOND>
<HEAD>Corcoran Gallery Director Resigns in Dispute Over Show Cancellation</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT M. ANDREWS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Christina Orr-Cahall resigned Monday as
director of the Corcoran Gallery of Art because of a barrage of
criticism over her decision last summer to cancel a photography
exhibit containing sexually explicit pictures.
   The board of trustees of the 120-year-old gallery, the oldest in
Washington and third oldest private museum in the country, agreed
overwhelmingly to accept the resignation in the hope of laying the
controversy to rest.
   In a letter to the 54-member board, Ms. Orr-Cahall said she was
resigning effective Feb. 1 ``in the hope that my decision will help
to eliminate or abate those extraneous and disruptive
difficulties'' that have plagued the Corcoran for the past six
months.
   Gallery president Freeborn G. Jewett Jr. said at a news
conference that ``in all of Dr. Orr-Cahall's actions and
recommendations to the board of trustees, she acted in the utmost
good faith'' and had ``displayed qualities of professional skill,
courage and loyalty.''
   The Corcoran became the target of nationwide criticism in June
when Ms. Orr-Cahall canceled a traveling exhibition by the late
photographer Robert Mapplethorpe two weeks before it was scheduled
to open July 1.
   The Corcoran trustees subsequently twice endorsed her decision.
   Ms. Orr-Cahall said she canceled the Mapplethorpe show, which
contained homoerotic and sadomasochistic images and pictures of
nude children, to avoid embroiling the Corcoran in a looming
congressional battle over the grant-making policies of the National
Endowment for the Arts.
   The endowment, an independent federal agency, had partially
financed the Mapplethorpe exhibit's national tour, organized by the
Institute of Contemporary Arts in Philadelphia. The show had
appeared in Philadelphia and Chicago without incident.
   Ms. Orr-Cahall's decision, however, brought the wrath of the
artistic community, which accused the Corcoran of stifling freedom
of expression. Artists withdrew plans for two exhibitions of
contemporary art at the Corcoran, and a third exhibition was left
in limbo.
   Artist Lowell Nesbitt announced he had withdrawn a $1.5 million
bequest to the Corcoran from his will and would give the money
instead to the Phillips Collection, another private Washington art
gallery.
   Staff morale at the Corcoran plunged with the resignation of
Jane Livingston, the museum's chief curator who had arranged for
the Mapplethorpe show to appear there.
   Ms. Orr-Cahall, former chief curator of the Oakland Museum in
California, previously had rejected a request by a representative
of the Corcoran staff that she resign.
   But in her resignation letter Monday, she said that ``the time
has arrived for the Corcoran to turn its eyes to the future and to
make every effort to assure that it is not consumed by the kind of
contention that distracts the institution from achieving its
goals.''
   The controversy also was noted by Jewett.
   ``Events of the past several months have embroiled the Corcoran
in continuing public controversy, a controversy that has interfered
with the Corcoran's capacity to address its full energies and
attention to the curatorial and educational tasks of the museum and
the school that are the institution's fundamental
responsibilities,'' he said.
   Board Chairman David Lloyd Kreeger, a member of a special
trustees' committee appointed Sept. 25 to study ways to repair the
damage, said the panel was split on whether Ms. Orr-Cahall should
leave the gallery or remain.
   He said the panel was ready to leave the decision on her fate up
to the full board, which he said also was divided over the issue.
Kreeger and Jewett said the director signaled her intention to
resign during negotiations with board members last weekend.
   Kreeger said the trustees were not concerned about the
Mapplethorpe cancellation, but were upset by the ``continued
barrage'' of criticism that dogged the Corcoran.
   The director's decision, he said, ``was blown into a symbol ...
of repression, or pornography vs. license, freedom of speech,
political issues, the future of the endowment'' and other issues.
   ``Mapplethorpe no longer is the issue because the director has
resigned,'' said Kreeger, who vowed that ``there is going to be a
resurgent and a new and dynamic Corcoran.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>