<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1927EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-BoeingOvercharges     12-24 0591</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Boeing Overcharges,0611</SECOND>
<HEAD>Boeing Computer Services Investigated For $25 Million In Overcharges</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Boeing Co.s' Computer Services division is under
investigation for allegedly overcharging the federal government
about $25 million for research work, a published report said Sunday.
   Boeing confirmed that it was being investigated by the Defense
Criminal Investigative Service and Air Force Office of Special
Investigations, but disputed the results of a Pentagon audit that
said it had exceeded government limits on billable research costs,
the Seattle Times reported.
   An ``investigation is ongoing ...'' said Boeing Chairman Frank
Shrontz in an interview with the Times. ``We don't think there's
been any evidence uncovered to date of any kind of willful fraud or
mischarging.''
   The investigation could result in felony or lesser charges,
administrative action or no action at all.
   There was no answer at the offices of Boeing spokesman when a
reporter called for further comment Sunday.
   The government allows companies to charge some research costs,
within limits, even if the research is used to develop and sell the
companies' own products.
   But auditors from the Pentagon's Defense Contract Audit Agency
said in an April 1988 report that Boeing had exceeded those limits
and improperly charged the expenses to a different account paid by
the government, the Times said.
   About $5.9 million of the $25 million in alleged research
overcharges was publicly revealed in July when Rep. John Conyers
Jr., D-Mich., chairman of the Legislation and National Security
subcommittee, released an audit of Boeing Computer Services by the
General Accounting Office, a congressional watchdog agency.
   Parts of the investigation also have been previously revealed,
including a subpeona last summer for documents.
   If Boeing has to repay the costs, it would be a major setback
for the company's money-losing military side. Boeing has faced
numerous allegations of fraud and overcharging related to its
military contracts this year.
   Boeing has agreed to pay $11 million for overstating aluminum
prices in Wichita. It paid more than $5 million in restitution and
fines after pleading guilty to receiving classified Pentagon budget
documents in Virginia.
   Boeing also is facing a critical audit and criminal
investigation of $20 million in charges related to leases with
developer David Sabey in Seattle.
   Shrontz told the Times his company emphasizes ethics, and blamed
Boeing's trouble on ``a significant ... resentment by both the
public and maybe some of the procurement people'' toward the
defense contracting business.
   Boeing was the country's 10th largest defense contractor last
year, with $4.79 billion in government contracts. Military work
accounted for only 25 percent of Boeing's total sales this year.
   The subpoena concerned both Boeing Aerospace and Electronics and
Boeing Computer Services documents, Boeing spokesman Paul Binder
has confirmed.
   Binder told the Times the criminal investigation into billing
practices was not new, but there has been no previous official
acknowledgement of it.
   Maj. Gen. Charles Skipton, commander of the Air Force Contract
Management Division based in New Mexico, wrote in a letter to the
Seattle regional GAO office in September that he had been told
collection of the overcharged amount was being held up for two
reasons, the Times said.
   He wrote that he had been told the investigation was holding
payment up and also that a recent analysis by the Air Force Plant
Representative Office, or on-site contracting officials, did not
totally support the findings of the final GAO report.
   Kent Godfrey, Defense Contract Audit Agency manager in charge of
the Boeing audit work in Seattle, and Phillip Rogers, the agency's
executive officer in Alexandria, Va., declined any comment.
</TEXT>

</DOC>