<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0248 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1450EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-StrideRite     12-21 0430</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stride Rite,0444</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shoemaker Says It Needs Time to Consider $900 Million Takeover Offer</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAMBRIDGE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sride Rite Corp., the leading U.S. maker
and retailer of children's footwear, said Thursday it will ignore a
Dec. 28 deadline for a response to an investment company's $900
million takeover offer.
   John J. Phelan, treasurer and executive vice president of Stride
Rite, released a letter saying his company would not make an
immediate decision on the $32 per-share offer from a group led by
Walsh, Greenwood &amp; Co. of Greenwich, Conn.
   Walsh, Greenwood had requested that Stride Rite come to a
conclusion on the matter by Dec. 28.
   ``That request is quite unreasonable as it would provide us with
only four business days to consider the matter,'' Phelan wrote in
the letter addressed to Walsh, Greenwood Managing General Partner
Stephen Walsh.
   Phelan wrote that the Stride Rite board would discuss the matter
in early January and would respond to Walsh, Greenwood at that time.
   Walsh, Greenwood and FS Champ Associates, representing the Minda
Bronfman de Gunzburg family trusts as a limited partner, made the
offer Wednesday.
   Walsh, Greenwood, which has owned 4.9 percent of Stride Rite
since last February, announced Wednesday it would consider other
options after the Dec. 28 deadline and might go directly to
stockholders with an offer.
   As the offer was made some analysts lowered their estimates of
Stride Rite earnings, partly because of the volume of shoes the
company sells to financially troubled Campeau Corp., which owns
department store chains that may seek Chapter 11 federal bankruptcy
protection because of heavy debts.
   On the New York Stock Exchange Thursday morning, Stride Rite
stock was up 3], to 26~.
   The Walsh, Greenwood offer was announced just before the market
closed Wednesday.
   Stride Rite reported earnings of $34.7 million, or $1.27 a
share, for the fiscal year ended Nov. 30, 1988.
   Phelan predicted the company's earnings for the 1989 fiscal year
will be at the lower end of estimates, from $1.70 to $1.80 per
share, and for the 1990 fiscal year from $2 to $2.20 per share,
which is lower than Wall Street estimates.
   In its purchase offer, Walsh, Greenwood said, ``We have no plans
to change the manner of the company's operation or the location of
its headquarters and principal facilities.''
   Stride Rite, based in Cambridge, Mass., is the leading
children's shoemaker and retailer in the country, with more than
180 stores and more than 60 sections in department stores. It also
manufactures boating and outdoor recreational shoes and adult
workboots, and imports athletic and casual wear.
</TEXT>

</DOC>