<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0185 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1016EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Hillsborough-Bankruptcy     12-28 0347</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hillsborough-Bankruptcy,0363</SECOND>
<HEAD>KKR Company Files Chapter 11</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TAMPA, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A company owned by leveraged buyout
specialists Kohlberg, Kravis, Roberts &amp; Co. filed for Chapter 11
bankruptcy protection after bondholders rejected a restructuring
plan.
   Hillsborough Holdings Corp.'s Wednesday filing in U.S.
Bankruptcy Court in Tampa marks the first Kohlberg Kravis private
holding to seek bankruptcy protection. The action will be closely
watched for its impact on the ``junk bond'' market.
   Junk bonds, used to finance corporate takeovers, have been
battered in recent months because of problems facing numerous
heavily indebted companies.
   New York-based Kohlberg Kravis formed Hillsborough last year as
part of its $2.4 billion takeover of Jim Walter Corp., a building
materials company. Jim Walter, which is not involved in the
bankruptcy filing, was later sold by Kohlberg Kravis.
   Hillsborough is expected to file bankruptcy petitions for its 31
subsidiaries, said bankruptcy court clerk Chuck Kilcoyne. By 8 p.m.
Wednesday, Kilcoyne had received Hillsborough's petition and those
of nine subsidiaries.
   Hillsborough's bankruptcy petition did not list creditors, and
reported assets of $304.2 million and liabilities of $347.6
million, he said.
   Hillsborough's case has been assigned to the court's Chief Judge
Alexander P. Paskay, said Kilcoyne.
   Kilcoyne said he had not yet received word from Paskay if a
court date had been set.
   Earlier this month, Hillsborough officials said they would file
for bankruptcy if an exchange offer for $624 million worth of the
company's bonds was not accepted by at least 80 percent of the
company's bondholders.
   Hillsborough said it could not repay its bonds in full.
   Hillsborough is the third company owned by Kohlberg Kravis to
encounter financial difficulties in recent months.
   In August, Kohlberg Kravis confirmed that Seaman Furniture Co.,
a leading furniture retailer, could not meet its debt payments and
might not be able to continue operating. The company's debt
payments were later rescheduled successfully.
   SCI Television Inc., of which Kohlberg Kravis owns 45 percent,
is also involved in a bond exchange offer that is facing resistance
from bondholders.
   But neither of those Kohlberg Kravis holdings is as large as
Hillsborough.
</TEXT>

</DOC>