<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0926EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Ethiopia-Rebels 1stLd-Writethru   12-30 0341</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Ethiopia-Rebels, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0478,0349</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ethiopian Rebels Claim Big Victory</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Inserts 1 graf after 9th pvs, `The Tigrean...' to ADD background
on the insurgency. Pickup last pvs, `The government...'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NAIROBI, Kenya (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rebels in northern Ethiopia claimed today
that they killed or wounded 8,200 government soldiers and captured
2,220 more while overrunning the garrison town of Debre Tabor.
   The rebels announced the fall of the garrison in northwestern
Gonder Province earlier this week in addition to the capture of two
towns in Shoa Province to the south.
   The government has made no comment on the reported fighting, but
diplomats in the capital, Addis Ababa, say the rebel claims of
capturing the three communities appear to be true.
   Reporters have been denied access to the region, and the
reports, especially regarding casualties, cannot be independently
verified.
   In clandestine radio broadcasts earlier in the week, the rebels
of the Tigre People's Liberation Front put the government toll for
all three towns at nearly 3,000 killed, wounded or captured.
   But in a broadcast monitored in Nairobi today, the insurgents
claimed far higher government losses in Debre Tabor alone.
   None of the broadcasts heard through the week mentioned rebel
losses.
   If the rebel reports of government losses are true, the
seven-day battle for Debre Tabor would mark the biggest defeat in
more than a year for the forces of President Mengistu Haile Mariam.
   The Tigrean rebels opened a new offensive in late August after a
six-month lull in their 14-year-old war to topple Mengistu's
government. They now control all of their home province of Tigre
and have made signigicant advances into Wollo, Gonder and Shoa
provinces to the south and west.
   Like the government, the Tigrean insurgents are Marxists. Their
leaders have spoken frequently and paradoxically of wanting a
democratic government patterned after that of Communist Albania.
   The government faces an even older insurgency in the
northernmost province of Eritrea, where rebels have been fighting a
seccessionist war for 28 years. However, there has been little
activity in that region in recent months.
</TEXT>

</DOC>