<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1530EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-MercyKilling Bjt   12-26 0546</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mercy Killing, Bjt,0562</SECOND>
<HEAD>Neighbors Say Ex-Cop Accused of Killing Ailing Wife Doted on Her</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LINDSEY TANNER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Retired policeman Gerald Williams doted on his
ailing wife for years. But, faced with heart surgery and worried
that he could no longer care for her, he shot and killed her on
Christmas Eve, police say.
   Both authorities and neighbors say Alice Williams had begged him
to end her suffering, but he still faces first-degree murder
charges.
   ``He was a very loving, caring man,'' said neighbor Marie
Kitzmiller. ``He took care of her from morning until night, around
the clock.''
   Williams, 67, appeared briefly in court Tuesday, accused of
shooting his wife of 44 years in the head with a .38-caliber
revolver while she sat in a wheelchair in the dining room of their
brick bungalow.
   Williams declined to comment to reporters after his appearance
before Criminal Court Judge David Erickson. The judge scheduled
another appearance for Jan. 12, and Williams remained free on a
personal recognizance bond.
   Mrs. Williams, 64, had suffered for 20 years from multiple
sclerosis, a degenerative disease of the nervous system, and also
had heart and kidney problems, said police Sgt. Ronald Palmer.
   After the shooting, Williams telephoned police to turn himself
in and waited for them at home, the officer said. He was released
into his daughter's custody after a Christmas Day court hearing.
   ``His health wasn't the best and hers was deteriorating,''
Palmer said. He said Williams had learned that a heart problem for
which he had to undergo surgery two years ago had recurred.
   ``He said he would be unable to take care of his wife and
himself,'' Palmer said. Palmer said Williams told police that ``all
his wife did was complain about how much she was suffering and she
begged him to end it.''
   Williams' daughter told police she had spoken to her father
earlier Sunday and that he told her his doctor had advised him that
he required a second major heart operation and he wouldn't be able
to care for his wife, Palmer said.
   ``I know Gerry was taking her to the doctors quite frequently,''
said Ms. Kitzmiller. ``She was totally confined to a wheelchair,
and she had taken a turn for the worse in the last six months.''
   Williams joined the force in 1957 and retired in 1985, said
Officer Patrick Camden.
   During his 28-year career, Williams was awarded 30 honorable
mentions, one department commendation and five complimentary
letters, ``about average for an aggressive policeman,'' Camden said.
   Calls to Williams' home went unanswered Tuesday and his
attorney, James E. Gorman, did not return several telephone
messages.
   ``He was a very nice man,'' said Chester Ciezczak, another
neighbor. ``He seemed to always help his wife. ... He cared for her
very much.''
   Ciezczak, who lives across the street from the Williams home,
said he did not hear the shooting Sunday.
   ``We ... saw all the squad cars and the ambulance and the fire
department,'' he said. ``The first thing that came to my mind was
that she had died, like on her own, because everybody knew that she
was in very bad health.''
   Said Ed Hearnes, another neighbor: ``To take a life that way, I
couldn't visualize Gerry doing that.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>