<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0233EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r e BC-Opera     12-29 0418</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Opera,0439</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dom DeLuise Makes Met Opera Debut</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: No PMs Planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY CAMPBELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Metropolitan Opera's light-hearted
production of Johann Strauss' ``Die Fledermaus'' was especially
effervescent in its second appearance this season.
   On Thursday, German baritone Hermann Prey, respected for
bringing importance to weighty music, cavorted merrily and seemed
to be having as good a time on stage as though really at Prince
Orlofsky's Act 2 party. It was Prey's first time to sing Eisenstein
at the Met.
   In the speaking role of Frosch, the jailer, the Met has had, in
recent memory, Jack Gilford, Otto Schenk, who devised this
production in 1986, and Sid Caesar. On Christmas night, in this
season's first ``Die Fledermaus,'' actor-comedian Dom DeLuise made
his Met debut.
   At the Met, singing is in German and speaking _ thus, most of
the jokes _ are in English.
   DeLuise's timing and body language were wonderful.
Traditionally, some of the jokes are changed each season. DeLuise
held a beer bottle which crumbled in his hand when he sang a couple
of high notes.
   And, he told a series of Leona Helmsley one-liners, concluding,
``She thinks she owns the place.''
   DeLuise's exchanges with the excellent Franz Mazura as the
jail's warden were genuinely funny.
   Carol Vaness sang Rosalinde, who gets the best of her husband
Eisenstein in an elaborate practical joke set up by his friend
Falke, well sung by Lenus Carlson. Miss Vaness also handled the
flamboyance well when she pretended to be a Hungarian countess.
   Neil Shicoff sang a tenor who adores Rosalinde, throwing himself
into the fun wholeheartedly. Barbara Kilduff sang sweetly as Adele
the maid and Grace Millo sparkled as her pert sister.
   Brigitte Fassbaender sang Prince Orlofsky for the first time at
the Met. She dressed simply for the part, red sash across a tuxedo.
The distinctive edge on her speaking voice turned shrill on her
sung high notes. But Miss Fassbaender commands a stage easily and
is an agreeable, distinctive Orlofsky.
   Hermann Michael, who has been Herbert von Karajan's assistant at
the Vienna State Opera and has conducted Wagner operas in Seattle,
made his Met debut on Christmas day. His timing was unrushed and
fine and the orchestra sounded very lyrical under his baton.
   Act 2 remains among the Met's most delightful sets, as the
outside of Prince Orlofsky's glass conservatory room moves on the
Met turntable until it becomes the room's interior, ready for
dinner and lively dancing to Strauss.
</TEXT>

</DOC>