<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0129 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1334EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-Judge-Explosion 2ndLd-Writethru a0708-a0428 12-20 0776</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Judge-Explosion, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0708-a0428,750</SECOND>
<HEAD>Four Letters Declaring War on Courts Being Examined</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Combines pvs.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES ROWLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four anonymous letters mailed in August to
declare war on various federal appeals courts are being examined
for possible links to mail bombings that killed a judge and a civil
rights lawyer, the FBI said today.
   The letters may be an important clue in the FBI's investigation
of the parcel bombs that killed Judge Robert S. Vance, a member of
the 11th Circuit Court of Appeals in Atlanta, and Robert E.
Robinson, a Savannah, Ga., alderman and civil rights lawyer, said
FBI spokesman Greg Jones.
   ``We are examining those letters to try to determine whether or
not there is a link between those threats in August and the matters
at hand today,'' Jones said.
   One letter declaring war on the 11th Circuit was received Aug.
24 by WAPT-TV in Jackson, Miss., the station reported Tuesday night.
   Similar letters were received that month in Minneapolis,
Milwaukee and California that made threatening statements against
other federal appellate circuit courts, Jones said.
   Attorney General Dick Thornburgh said in a statement Tuesday
that the investigation is focusing on the possibility that race
motivated the killings and the sending of similar package bombs to
the 11th Circuit and the NAACP in Jacksonville, Fla.
   Vance ruled in favor of the Jacksonville NAACP on Sept. 15 in a
school desegregation case.
   The letter received in Jackson bore an Atlanta postmark dated
Aug. 21, the day before a tear-gas cannister exploded in that
city's NAACP office, injuring eight people. Jones declined to
describe the postmarks on the other letters, except to say they
were sent in late August.
   All four letters were examined by the FBI laboratory in
Washington but yielded no further physical clues, such as
fingerprints, Jones said. U.S. Marshals in the various
jurisdictions were told of the threatening letters, Jones.
   The letter attacking the 11th Circuit threatened poison gas
attacks on large cities to force the court to ``adopt fair and
impartial treatment of all.''
   Entitled ``Declaration of War,'' the letter said the 11th
Circuit ``does deliberately and wrongfully refuse to fulfill its
obligation to protect the innocent.''
   ``The court's failure to render impartial and equitable
judgments is due to rank bias and the mistaken belief its victims
cannot effectively retaliate,'' the letter said.
   The Jackson television station said it immediately turned the
letter over to the FBI.
   Three weeks after the letter surfaced, the 11th Circuit
published Vance's opinion for the unanimous three-judge panel in
the Jacksonville school case. It reversed a lower-court ruling that
Jacksonville schools could stop busing to achieve racial
integration.
   On Saturday, Vance was killed in his Mountain Brook, Ala., home
after opening a parcel mailed to him.
   On Monday, a similar bomb was found at the 11th Circuit
courthouse in Atlanta and removed without incident. Hours later,
Robinson was fatally injured in his Savannah law office when he
opened the parcel mailed to him.
   On Tuesday, authorities found a similar bomb at the office of
the Jacksonville NAACP, which brought the school case.
   FBI Director William Sessions told reporters Tuesday he would
not be surprised if the Vance murder was related to cases he had
worked on as a federal appellate judge.
   Sessions said Vance's court docket would be carefully studied to
determine if his rulings may have sparked a racially motivated
murder.
   Sessions implied that the bureau did not have a suspect, and
indicated there might be more than one perpetrator.
   ``As far as I know there's been no claimant of responsibility at
all,'' Sessions said at a news conference at the Justice Department.
   Sessions said investigators found no similarities between the
bomb incidents and the actions of extremist white groups but ``it
is something you cannot rule out.''
   ``We would hope the patterns of these types of groups when
studied carefully and compared will yield fruit,'' Sessions said.
   Asked about racial motivation, Sessions said: ``When the NAACP
headquarters receives a suspicious package, an alderman is killed,
you have to have that in the back of your mind.''
   The package containing the bomb that killed Vance bore the
return address of another 11th Circuit judge, Lewis F. Morgan, a
government source said in Washington.
   Morgan, who had previously sent packages to Vance, is not a
suspect but the evidence suggests that the killer was familiar with
the two judges' friendship, said the source, who spoke on condition
of anonymity.
   Thornburgh called the incidents ``an affront to our nation's
commitment to the rule of law'' and said he had assured civil
rights leaders the case would be thoroughly investigated.
</TEXT>

</DOC>