<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1245EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Work-ReleaseEscapes     12-19 0392</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Work-Release Escapes,0403</SECOND>
<HEAD>Corrections Officials to Investigate Work-Release Escapes</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRADENTON, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   State officials will review the prison
work release system in Bradenton after an escapee was arrested on
rape charges in the second such incident in six weeks.
   One rape suspect was on work release; the other was assigned to
the minimum-security work release center but was not authorized to
work outside the facility, Chief Rod Groom, administrator of the
center, said today.
   David Tune, head of the state's work release system, and a team
of corrections officials will review the backgrounds of all inmates
in the Bradenton center to ensure they qualify for work release,
the Bradenton Herald reported today.
   Officials said some changes in the system are likely after the
latest escape _ the fourth in six weeks.
   The inquiry follows an attack Sunday morning on a Bradenton
woman. Sheriff's deputies charged Gilbert Diamond, 30, of Tarpon
Springs with breaking into her home and attacking her at knifepoint.
   Diamond, who was convicted of burglary and aggravated assault,
had left his work-release job as a dishwasher at an all-night
restaurant early and did not return to the center.
   Work release is a kind of correctional halfway house; convicts
are allowed to finish their sentences while holding jobs outside
jail. The only time they are permitted to be away from the center
is during working hours.
   The program is open to almost all inmates with less than two
years left to serve. Only sex offenders and kidnappers are
automatically excluded.
   Kidnappers were also excluded earlier this month after a man
convicted of that offense, Craig Allan Mrozowski, 30, escaped from
the Bradenton center where he worked as a cook and trusty and was
later accused of raping an Oneco woman.
   Corrections Department spokesman Bob Macmaster said the first
thing the inspection team will look at is whether to let inmates
work late-night shifts. Skeleton staffs make it difficult for
employers to keep tabs on them, and darkness makes it hard to track
down escapees, officials said.
   The exclusion of all violent felons from the program would have
a substantial impact, but officials did not know how many of the
3,020 work release prisoners statewide would be returned to jail.
   Only four or five of the 101 inmates at the Bradenton center
work nights, said the facility's administrator, Rod Groom.
</TEXT>

</DOC>