<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0156 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1651EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Zimbabwe     12-22 0453</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Zimbabwe,0468</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ruling Party Rejects Calls Against Marxist-Leninist Dictatorship</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN EDLIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HARARE, Zimbabwe (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The ruling party Friday ignored calls to
heed the collapse of Communism in eastern Europe and pledged to
create a one-party Marxist-Leninist state.
   The decision, on the final day of the four-day Patriotic Front
congress, was contained in a document approved by 4,200 delegates.
   It restated the dream of President Robert Mugabe to transform
one of Africa's few Western-style democracies into a single-party
nation, which he may do next year.
   The party's aim is ``to establish and sustain a socialist
society guided by Marxist-Leninist principles but firmly based on
our historical, cultural and social experience and to create
conditions for economic independence, increased productivity and
equitable distribution of the wealth of the nation,'' it said.
   Mugabe, who led the former white-ruled British colony of
Rhodesia to independence as black-governed Zimbabwe on April 18,
1980, strenuously urged delegates to reject calls to abandon this
goal in favor of multiparty democracy and a free enterprise economy.
   The debate behind closed doors was ``heated but healthy,'' said
party spokesman Nathan Shamuyarira, who is also minister of foreign
affairs.
   Pro-democracy groups had hoped Zimbabwe would follow some other
African states that abandoned radical leftist policies in line with
events in eastern Europe.
   In Benin, a former French territory in West Africa, the
leadership early this month denounced Communism and promised
constitutional reforms.
   In Ethiopia, Africa's most rigid Marxist state, President
Mengistu Haile Mariam has been forced to hold peace talks with
guerrilla chieftains since the Soviet Union began reducing military
supplies to fight secessionist wars. This has raised the prospect
he might pursue political liberalization.
   More and more African countries also are jettisoning outdated
economic policies in favor of reforms proposed by the World Bank
and the International Monetary Fund.
   In recent months, as pro-democratic movements have swept eastern
Europe, Mugabe has come under pressure to abandon the aim of a
one-party state.
   Mugabe's Patriotic Front has been avowedly Marxist-Leninist
since independence. Former opposition leader Joshua Nkomo was more
centrist.
   But the two decided two years ago to merge forces, a move that
was formalized by their first joint congress this week.
   The ruling party can pass laws and rewrite sections of the
British-drafted constitution, a document signed by all parties 10
years ago.
   Those constitutional talks ended nine decades of white minority
rule, halted a seven-year war waged by guerrillas loyal to Nkomo
and Mugabe, and steered Zimbabwe to independence.
   The constitution guaranteed Zimbabwe would be a multi-party
democracy for the first 10 years of independence.
   After the 10th anniversary, Mugabe may ban opposition and
establish a single-party state with two-thirds of the votes in
Parliament.
</TEXT>

</DOC>