<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0136 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1616EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Justice-Noriega     12-29 0323</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Justice-Noriega,310</SECOND>
<HEAD>Department Admits Shortcomings In Legal Work On Noriega</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By W. DALE NELSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Justice Department acknowledged Friday it
was in such a rush to indict Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega on drug
charges that it may not have followed its own rules for making sure
state secrets would not be disclosed in court.
   However, said department spokesman David Runkel, ``We believe
there is a strong case against General Noreiga and that case can be
successfully brought to trial.''
   Some legal experts have said there could be problems in trying
Noriega because he would seek to use classified information
stemming from his past cooperation with the Central Intelligence
Agency.
   Runkel said on Tuesday that such concerns ``have been grossly
exaggerated.''
   At a press briefing on Friday, he told reporters that the
department may not have followed its usual policy of reviewing, in
drawing up an indictment, any classified documents that might be
used in a trial.
   ``I had been informed that that was the policy that had in fact
been followed in this case,'' he told reporters.
   ``It now appears that there was some rush to draw up the Noriega
indictment and those guidelines may not have been completely
followed,'' he said.
   Runkel declined to elaborate on the nature of the ``rush'' and
said, ``I haven't determined the reason'' for it.
   He said the department's decision to review the national
security issues was an outgrowth of a Dec. 14 meeting of
prosecutors in the case with representatives of the Drug
Enforcement Administration, Federal Bureau of Investigation and CIA.
   That meeting was called to discuss drug indictments against
Noriega in Miami and Tampa, Fla., and a decision was made to
proceed with the Miami case, Runkel said.
   Noriega reportedly worked closely with the CIA and the Pentagon
while he served as the head of Panama's military intelligence
service and after he became commander in chief in 1983.
</TEXT>

</DOC>