<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 2343EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Deaths 1stLd-Writethru a0840 12-22 0717</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Deaths, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0840,0740</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eds: ADDS Bailes; Seperates moved for AMs as a0663 on Greenough,
a0627 on Belushi, a0865 on Sisto and as a0868 on Bailes. Greenough also
moved on the financial wire.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>William Greenough</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   William C. Greenough, developer of the
variable-annuity pension and one-time head of the biggest pension
fund in the United States, died Wednesday of complications from a
heart attack. He was 75.
   Greenough was president and then chairman of the Teachers
Insurance and Annuity Association-College Retirement Equities Fund
from 1957 until his retirement in 1979.
   He put forward the idea of a variable-annuity stock fund in the
early 1950s when he was vice president of the fund. The approach
was based on his perception that over the long run a diverse
portfolio of common stocks would outperform traditional pensions.
   Greenough was also a director of the New York Stock Exchange for
10 years beginning in 1972 and in 1979 served on President Carter's
Commission on Pension Policy.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Agnes Belushi</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Agnes Belushi, mother of actor Jim Belushi and
the late actor John Belushi, died Thursday after a bout with
cancer. She was 64.
   She and her husband, Adam, raised their four children in
Wheaton, where Belushi owned a restaurant and Mrs. Belushi worked
in a pharmacy.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Ernest Sisto</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ernest Sisto, an award-winning photographer who
spent 49 years with The New York Times, died at his home Friday at
age 85.
   Sisto was known for his baseball photos, and he was friendly
with New York Yankees stars Joe DiMaggio and Phil Rizzuto. He
covered many major sporting events, including the World Series and
the Kentucky Derby.
   Sisto was honored for his work by everybody from the Press
Photographers Association to a cigar manufacturer.
   He is survived by his wife, Amelia, and two sons, Daniel and
Ernest Jr.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Theodore Richeson</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SACRAMENTO, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Theodore ``Ted'' L. Richeson, a
retired account representative for Westinghouse-KFWB Radio in Los
Angeles, died Thursday of heart failure. He was 68.
   Most of Richeson's career was in broadcasting. His resume
included such stations as KREM in Spokane, KCRA in Sacramento and
KMPC and KFWB in Los Angeles. He retired from KFWB in 1986.
   While working in Sacramento as station manager for KCRA radio,
Richeson set up KCTC-FM radio, one of the first FM stations in the
area. He also served a term as president of the Better Business
Bureau.
   Richeson is survived by his wife of 45 years, Josephine, and
three children, Ted, Kelly and Lisa Kalcking.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Thomas McCarthey</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SALT LAKE CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thomas Kearns McCarthey, vice president
and director of Kearns-Tribune Corp., parent company of The Salt
Lake Tribune, died Friday afternoon at age 69.
   The cause of death was not available.
   McCarthey was a corporate executive and advertising employee of
the Tribune and Newspaper Agency Corp. for more than 40 years.
   Kearns McCarthey was well-known in newspaper circles, prominent
in thoroughbred racing in recent years and active in support of
scholarship and athletics at the University of Utah and Judge
Memorial Catholic High School.
   He also was an officer and director of Kearns-Tribune
Investments Inc. and Silver King Mining Co.
   McCarthey is survived by his wife, Jane; three sons, Thomas K.
Jr., Philip G. and Shaun McCarthey; two daughters, Sarah Jane and
Maureen McCarthey; a sister, Sheila McCarthey Wood; a brother, John
P. Brophy; and four granddaughters.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Johnnie Bailes</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAVANNAH, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Johnnie Jacob Bailes of Macon, a regular
with the Grand Ole Opry in 1943, died Saturday after an extended
illness. He was 71.
   Bailes was a member of the original Bailes Brothers Singing
Group formed in 1937. The group appeared regularly on the Grand Ole
Opry broadcasts from Nashville, Tenn., in 1943.
   ``Dust On the Bible,'' one of the Bailes Brothers' songs, is in
the Smithsonian Institution. In 1983, the group received a star on
the walkway of stars at the Country Music Hall of Fame in Nashville.
   Bailes was also one of the founders of the Louisiana Hayride
radio show. He moved to Swainsboro in 1956 and worked at WJAT Radio
and the Peach State Jamboree. Bailes later became general manager
of WJAT, WBRO in Waynesboro and WSNT in Sandersville.
</TEXT>

</DOC>