<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1139EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Romania-Reaction     12-21 0784</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Reaction,0811</SECOND>
<HEAD>European Leaders Condemn Continued Repression</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROLAND PRINZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   East Germany recalled its ambassador and
Czechoslovakia issued a formal protest as European nations formed a
united front today to condemn the bloody repression of protesters
in Romania.
   The international outcry came after reports that security forces
for the second time in a week fired on crowds of protesters in
Romania, and that shooting also occurred in the western Romanian
city of Arad.
   East Germany, where the hard-line government was toppled by
reformers in October, condemned what it called the ``brutal action
of the Romanian state power against peaceful citizens demonstrating
to assert their elementary human rights.''
   In a statement, the government called on Romania to halt
immediately all violence against its people. East German Ambassador
Herbert Plaschke was recalled from Romania for consultations in
East Berlin.
   Czechoslovakia also summoned a senior Romanian diplomat to
receive a protest from the Foreign Ministry in Prague.
   Massive protests in Czechoslovakia and East Germany in recent
months have toppled the old hard-line regimes in those nations and
ushered in new eras of breathtaking reforms.
   But the regime of Romanian President Nicolae Ceausescu has tried
to crush the protests with bloodshed, according to reports reaching
the West. Last weekend, security forces fired on protesters in the
western city of Timisoara.
   Government protests against the Ceausescu regime continued in
Hungary, which has long had tense relations with Bucharest because
of alleged harassment of the 1.7 million ethnic Hungarians in
Romania.
   ``There exists or has developed in Romania a serious political
movement,'' said Hungarian Foreign Minister Gyula Horn. ``I do not
know exactly wheter it is comprehensive. It is an anti-Ceausescu
movement.
   ``There is no accurate information on its strength, on the
extent to which it has spread,'' he said.
   The Soviet Union officially reacted with caution, but the
state-run Tass news agency stepped up coverage of the Romanian
events, giving vivid accounts of violence against demonstrators by
the government.
   ``If we do receive information on victims among people we, of
course, will be extremely sorry for them,'' said Soviet Foreign
Ministry spokesman Vadim Perfiliev.
   ``We should emphasize that we do have opinions on what is
happening, but in my place as an official representative of the
Ministry of Foreign Affairs, I cannot go into comments without
having all-inclusive information and orders in that regard.''
   In East Berlin, French President Francois Mitterrand was far
more blunt.
   ``It is a regime of personal, family power that has no honest
reason to remain,'' he told reporters. ``I think that the days of
this regime, in a Europe in full movement, are numbered. But at
what price?''
   Ruling out foreign intervention, Mitterrand said, ``the response
has to come from Romania.''
   In Bonn, Chancellor Helmut Kohl's chief spokesman Hans Klein
said Kohl was ``deeply shocked over the brutal repression of the
justified and peaceful protests of the (Romanian) people.''
   ``He strongly condemns the massive use of weapons and the
reprehensible attempts by the Romanian leadership to suppress the
efforts for freedom and democracy,'' Klein said, quoting Kohl.
   Klein said Kohl ``appeals to those responsible at all levels in
Romania to halt repression by the military and security police, and
to open a dialogue on the justified demands of people.''
   In London, the Foreign Office said Common Market countries were
considering a withdrawal of ambassadors from Romania in the wake of
the weekend massacre of civilians during anti-government
demonstrations.
   But the spokesman stressed that this was only one of a number of
options under consideration by the 12 member states as a response
to the crackdown.
   Meanwhile, Italy announced it has recalled its ambassador to
Romania, Luigi Amaduzzi, for consultations.
   The Greek government also condemned the suppression of the
Romanian protests, and all political parties also expressed outrage.
   The Athens Academy of Sciences stripped Ceausescu's wife, Elena,
of her membership, awarded in 1976.
   In Austria, President Kurt Waldheim expressed his ``deep
concern'' over bloody repression of the ``peace movement'' in
Romania.
   He spoke of a ``serious violation of human rights.''
   ``The Communist regime in Romania is very brutal, and the
Western countries, whose unity in this matter could be greater''
should use all possibilities in order to help set afoot reforms in
Romania, Austrian Foreign Minister Alois Mock said.
   Dutch Foreign Minister Hans van den Broek Wednesday on summoned
Romanian Ambassador Constantin Statescu and told him of the Hague
government's ``grave concern about the repression of defenseless
demonstrators.''
   Van den Broek also appealed to the Ceausescu government ``not to
turn a dead ear to the population's call for change'' and
threatened ``further measures'' in line with the other 11 nations
of the European Community.
</TEXT>

</DOC>