<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0186 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2212EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-AndeanPact     12-18 0480</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Andean Pact,0494</SECOND>
<HEAD>Andean Presidents Agree to Promote Economic Integration</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GALAPAGOS ISLANDS, Ecuador (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The five presidents of the
Andean Pact, meeting on the remote Galapagos Islands, agreed Monday
to help promote the integration of their countries' economies and
eventually use a common currency.
   The presidents of Ecuador, Colombia, Venezuela, Peru and Bolivia
signed the ``Declaration of the Galapagos'' in a ceremony in Puerto
Ayora on the island of Santa Cruz.
   Presidents Rodrigo Borja of Ecuador, Virgilio Barco of Colombia,
Carlos Andres Perez of Venezuela, Alan Garcia of Peru and Jaime Paz
Zamora of Bolivia were to return to the Ecuadoran mainland, 600
miles away, before nightfall.
   But first the leaders planned to visit several of the
archipelago's islands to see the unique plant and animal life,
including giant tortoises, land and marine iguanas, seals and
species of birds found nowhere else on Earth.
   Upon their return to the mainland city of Guayaquil late Monday,
the four visiting presidents were scheduled to immediately fly home.
   The five presidents arrived Sunday in the Galapagos and met in
seclusion aboard a navy ship.
   The document signed Monday was prepared last week by the foreign
ministers of the five nations meeting in Guayaquil, Ecuador's most
populous city and its primary port.
   In the document the five presidents also agreed to forsake ``the
use of force'' to resolve disputes among member nations of the
Andean Pact and to ``abstain from actions against the territorial
integrity'' of members.
   In 1981 Ecuador and Peru fought a four-day border war. It was
sparked by Ecuador's long-standing claim of sovereignty over a
large tract of Amazon jungle in northeastern Peru.
   The five presidents also signed a separate document in which
they set goals they hoped to achieve in integrating their
countries' economies, including a common currency. No date for the
common currency was divulged.
   ``The creation of the European Common Market has indicated to us
the direction in which the world is advancing,'' Perez said in a
press conference in Puerto Ayora's municipal headquarters, where
the signing ceremony took place.
   Garcia called the Galapagos' summit ``the most important meeting
the Andean Pact has had'' in its 20 years of existence.
   In a press conference in Guayaquil Sunday before the presidents
flew to the Galapagos Islands, Paz Zamora said, ``If we don't make
a great effort, the Andean Pact is going to die on us.''
   In an attempt to rejuvenate the Andean Pact, the five presidents
agreed this year to meet every six months. The last meeting was in
May in Cartagena, Colombia, where President Bush is scheduled to
meet in February for a drug summit with Barco and other Latin
leaders.
   It is one of the oldest of a half dozen regional organizations
that have tried unsuccessfully to achieve economic integration.
   In recent years trade among the five Andean nations has declined
due to high tariffs.
</TEXT>

</DOC>