<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0123 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 2252EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GamblingShip     12-30 0341</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gambling Ship,0351</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fog Forces Gambling Ship To Make Long Stay at Sea</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GALVESTON, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 700 passengers on a day-cruise
casino vessel were dealt a bad hand when dense fog prevented them
from returning to port for 28 hours.
   Weary and disheveled passengers lined the Pride of Mississippi's
rails and cheered Friday afternoon as deckhands tossed lines ashore
and ended what was supposed to have been an eight-hour excursion
into the Gulf of Mexico.
   Some passengers cursed Pride Cruise Lines for taking them out on
a foggy day, but others said they had a ball.
   ``It was real nice,'' said Gerald Shelton, a Houston landscaper,
who was with his wife, Bonnie, and son, Gerald, 12. ``They took
real good care of us. I lost a little bit, but I didn't mind being
stuck out there.''
   Tracy Pekovsky of Washington, D.C., said the trip was ``a
nightmare.''
   ``It was foggy when we left the channel and they should never,
ever have taken us out,'' she said.
   ``They need to go and take a look at some other cruise lines,''
said Renee Banks of Houston. ``Even down to a Coke, they were
charging for everything. We had a cabin but there were people
wandering around wondering where they could get a blanket or a
pillow from. I never heard any announcement. To me, that's a little
tacky.''
   Chief Purser Murdock MacRae said he made several announcements
Thursday night, but some people may not have heard them because of
noise in the lounges or casino.
   ``With 744 passengers, there are going to be a few
complainers,'' he said. The vessel stayed in international waters
all night, allowing the casino to remain open, passengers said.
Cruise officials said bands, vocalists and other entertainers
worked throughout the trip and movies played continuously.
   The cruise got off to a bad start when it left three hours late
on Thursday and had a minor collision with a shrimp boat in the
port. There were no injuries.
   Hours later, fog banks shrouded the vessel.
</TEXT>

</DOC>