<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0118 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1954EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania 2ndLd-Writethru a0647 12-26 1180</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0647,1216</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Videotape Shows Ceausescu, Wife Defiant to the End</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 27 grafs to UPDATE with Ceausescu quotes from trial;
picks up 25th: `Thousands of ...</HEAD>
<NOTE>LaserPhotos BUCH2,10; PAR4,7,9; LaserColor PAR6</NOTE>
<NOTE>By MORT ROSENBLUM</NOTE>
<NOTE>AP Special Correspondent</NOTE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Deposed dictator Nicolae Ceausescu
defiantly denounced the revolt that toppled him from power and
refused to recognize the legitimacy of the tribunal that sentenced
him to death, a videotape of his trial showed late Tuesday.
   Waving his arms and shouting with his forlorn wife, Elena,
seated nearby, Ceausescu branded as lies the charges that the
couple was responsible for the deaths of 60,000 during their
24-year reign and the crackdown on protesters last week.
   ``Everything that was said here was false, and I don't want to
talk any more,'' he declared at one point.
   ``I'm not guilty, I'm not guilty. I will answer only in front of
the Grand National Assembly and in front of the working-class.
These are lies,'' he said as the couple sat behind a table, with no
other people in the room visible.
   Later, the videotape broadcast on Romanian television showed the
bodies of the couple sprawled by a wall after their executions
Monday by firing squad, the first confirmation for Romanians that
their revolution had been won.
   An official said the couple that ruled their country together
were granted their last wish: that their executions be carried out
simultaneously. Hundreds reportedly volunteered for the
three-member firing squad.
   The revolutionary National Salvation Committee, which says it is
a provisional government until free elections can be held in April,
chose Ion Iliescu as chairman of a new 37-member governing council
on Tuesday.
   It also named as prime minister a professor who said he
convinced the army to join the revolt.
   Additionally, the new government issued a decree that throws out
some of Ceausescu's most vicious and oppressive laws _ including
those prohibiting contact with foreigners, free travel and even
ownership of typewriters.
   The government also ordered the Interior Ministry's brutal
security forces be put under control of the Defense Ministry, which
oversees the army that sided with the revolutionaries.
   According to radio and Romanian sources, security forces loyal
to Ceausescu were surrendering by the hundreds Tuesday, apparently
convinced of defeat by news of their ousted ruler's execution.
   But sporadic gunfire still rang through parts of the capital,
where many buildings were burned or battered by the fighting
between army units backing the revolution and secret police loyal
to Ceausescu.
   Ceausescu and his wife were reported captured on Saturday and
tried and executed two days later. Television early Tuesday
broadcast the first footage of the couple in captivity, along with
the film of their bodies.
   The 71-year-old Ceausescu looked gaunt and unshaven and denied
that he ordered the brutal suppression during last week's protests
against his rule.
   His wife, sometimes restrained from speaking by her husband,
defiantly blasted back at unseen prosecutors accusing the family of
stashing hard currency in Swiss banks.
   ``Prove it,'' she retorted. ``This is a base provocation.''
   Ceausescu denied that there were deaths in Bucharest's Palace
Square on Thursday, when there were reports that troops fired on
protesters who turned out for his failed pro-government
demonstration.
   ``Nobody was shot in the Palace Square,'' Ceausescu said.
   ``Do you know that you were sacked as president and as supreme
commander of the army?'' the court asked at point.
   ``No, I do not recognize this. I am the president of the
Socialist Republic of Romania,'' he replied.
   The government said the couple was tried by a secret military
tribunal for grave crimes against the Romanian people, including
genocide and ruining the economy. It said the genocide involved the
deaths of more than 60,000 people during their 24 years in power.
   The government also said the couple had stashed more than $1
billion in foreign banks.
   A military officer who asked not to be identified said 300
soldiers volunteered for the firing squad, but only three were
chosen. The Ceausescus' last wish was to die together, he said.
   ``All of us wanted to see the dictator shot. You have seen it,
the dictators have been executed!'' exulted a Bucharest Radio
announcer.
   For some, however, even death was too good for Ceausescu, who
ran a network of terror with 700,000 secret police and imposed
rationing on his people while exporting food to pay for monuments
to his own glory.
   ``He should be stripped naked, and his body paraded through the
streets,'' said Dimitru Minca, whose 14-year-old grandson was among
Ceausescu's victims.
   Still in custody and facing trial was Ceausescu's eldest son,
Nicu, and a daughter, Zoia.
   Thousands of people were reported killed as Ceausescu tried to
crush burgeoning protests that began Dec. 15. The army joined the
uprising Friday, forcing Ceausescu to flee, and thousands more are
believed to have been killed during the fighting with pro-Ceausescu
forces.
   A group of dissidents, intellectuals, disaffected government
officials and rebellious army commanders have been trying to run
the nation under the umbrella name National Salvation Committee.
   On Tuesday, the committee said Iliescu, 59, would remain
chairman of the committee. Reputed to be a college chum of Soviet
President Mikhail S. Gorbachev, he was an early rising star under
Ceausescu but was demoted in 1971 after disagreements over the
dictator's style and his pace of reform.
   It also named Petre Roman, a 43-year-old professor of hydraulic
engineeering with no political background, as prime minister.
   The government has been headquartered at the TV station, scene
of some of the heaviest fighting. During one attack Friday, Roman
told reporters he was on the committee because he helped persuade
the army to join the revolt.
   Named as defense minister was Gen. Nicolas Militaru, who retired
eight years ago from the army as commander of the Bucharest
garrison, one of many military men toppled by Ceausescu, whose
distrust of the army grew after an attempted military coup in 1984.
   Because of the new decree, Militaru's duties now will include
command of all security troops. Under the new law, the only
paramilitary units under the Interior Ministry will be traffic
police, firefighters and prison guards.
   The changes also scrap laws forbidding unauthorized contact with
foreigners requiring intellectuals to live in the same city where
they work _ a measure frequently used to banish outspoken voices to
remote towns.
   Laws prohibiting abortions to women with less than five children
and requiring registration of typewriters also were abolished, as
were Ceausescu's plans to destroy thousands of villages and force
people into shoddy new housing in towns.
   About 10 new political parties have been formed since Saturday,
all weak and badly organized, and a small but noisy demonstration
has already denounced the new government, some of whose members
have promised free elections.
   About a thousand people gathered outside of the Central
Committee building to demand that no Communists be included in any
new government. They objected that the television station refused
to cover them.
   ``These are the first days of liberty and already they are
suppressing us,'' said Christian Radulescu, a doctor.
</TEXT>

</DOC>