<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0133 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1550EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-Colon Bjt   12-29 0725</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Colon, Bjt,0754</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dictator's Slush Fund Taxes International Traders</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CANDICE HUGHES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>COLON, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A trading company owned by Gen. Manuel
Antonio Noriega's former presidential candidate was a slush fund
that siphoned millions of dollars a year from international
merchants in the free port of Colon.
   Authorities think Transit S.A., owned by Carlos Duque, was also
a conduit for the drug deals that enriched Noriega as well as many
Defense Forces henchmen.
   ``The company is suspected of trafficking in drugs and arms,''
said Colon's provincial governor, Leopoldo Benedetti.
   With Noriega's downfall, the inside story of Transit is slowly
coming to light.
   U.S. troops seized the company, raided its warehouse and sealed
the unmarked office. Like many Noriega associates, Duque is on the
run, wanted for questioning by U.S. and Panamanian authorities.
   Transit's manager, Rafael Ceballos, has turned himself in, eager
to spill his secrets and professing unbridled enthusiasm for the
U.S. forces that occupy Colon, home of the world's largest
duty-free port after Hong Kong.
   After 18 years with Transit, he says he has a lot to tell.
   ``Everything is in the books,'' he said. ``Everything. I'm no
jerk.''
   Ceballos was interviewed after surrendering to Benedetti
Thursday.
   ``He wants to talk. He wants to tell everything. He's tired of
hiding. He wants to keep on living,'' the new governor said.
   Estimates of how much money Transit collected vary.
   The new director of the Colon Free Zone, Jimmy Ford, a nephew of
new Second Vice President Guillermo Ford, estimates it at $1
million a month. Ceballos says it averaged from $3 million to $4
million annually.
   Others, like Colombian consul Alfonso Esquivel, say Transit
collected tens of millions of dollars a year.
   ``It is the only private company in the world that levies
taxes,'' Esquivel said.
   Transit charged traders 1 percent of the value of a shipment's
freight on board and an additional $1.50 for every crate on board,
Ceballos said.
   The duty-free port at the northern end of the Panama Canal
operates as a marketplace to distribute goods throughout the
hemisphere. It's particularly important to Japanese and other Asian
nations who sell in South America.
   Ceballos said Transit's funds and import-export facilities were
at the service of Noriega and a few high-ranking officers.
   ``For example, if they asked for $150,000 and the company only
had $100,000, it would have to get a bank loan for $50,000 to get
the money for them,'' he said.
   ``If they wanted to buy a refrigerator, some champagne, some
liquor, whatever, the company bought it, the company paid because
of the connection between Carlos Duque and the Defense Forces.''
   Many of the goods Transit imported were for Noriega and his
family, Ceballos said.
   He denied that Transit, which had trading concessions for
Colombian coffee, Cuban cigars and Nicaraguan rum, was involved in
the cocaine trade.
   ``No. Not for a moment,'' he said as he awaited questioning by
U.S. Army intelligence officials.
   Army Col. John Brooks, the commander of the U.S. occupation
force in Colon, said looters had emptied Transit's warehouse before
the raid Wednesday, but that at one point a drug-sniffing dog was
brought in to sniff the residue.
   ``It went crazy. It was running around in circles,'' Brooks said.
   U.S. forces surrounded the city of 12,000 as part of the
invasion but did not enter for two days, during which time it was
sacked by looters.
   Transit was created in 1972 by Noriega's predecessor, Gen. Omar
Torrijos, and given the legal right to charge ``documentation
fees.''
   He said Noriega demanded more of Transit than Torrijos had.
   ``Noriega was possessive. His daughters were always asking for
something,'' Ceballos said, recalling huge shipments from China for
the Noriega family, whose home is stuffed with delicate porcelain,
jade and ivory carvings and furniture inlaid with mother-of-pearl.
   Ceballos said all decisions were made by Duque. He said only
Duque, his son and his wife could sign company checks.
   Duque, a longtime business associate of Noriega's, ran for
president in the May 1989 election that Noriega voided after
international observers said the opposition had won in a landslide.
The opposition leader, Guillermo Endara, was installed as president
following Dec. 20 invasion.
   Transit is despised by traders in the duty-free zone. Officials
of the zone's merchants' association say it has stifled growth by
siphoning off money from the traders.
</TEXT>

</DOC>