<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0135EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-FarmScene     12-19 0881</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Farm Scene,880</SECOND>
<HEAD>Consumers Want Ready-Made Meals</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DIANE DUSTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Women in the work force and the popularity of
microwave ovens are pressuring the food industry to convert farm
products not just to food, but to ready-made meals, says an
agriculture publication.
   ``Retailers, distributors and processors are the first to be
buffeted by changes in consumer demands,'' says the article in
``Choices'' written by Benjamin Senauer, University of Minnesota
professor of agriculture and applied economics.
   ``But in many cases these consumer-driven changes work their way
through the food system back to the farmer.''
   Senauer points out that consumers got so hot for oat products,
which are supposed to reduce cholesterol, that farmers couldn't
keep up, leading food processors to turn to imports.
   ``Women in the labor force jumped from 35 percent in 1960 to 55
percent in 1987,'' says the author. ``For married women 35-44 years
old, it doubled from 36 percent to 72 percent during the same
period.''
   Some 75 percent of American households own microwave ovens and
over 60 percent of all the workers in the United States have access
to a microwave on the job, he said.
   These statistics have contributed to a new category of eater
that one food company calls the ``Chase and Grabbits,'' also known
as yuppies, considered 26 percent of the market.
   Other categories into which the Pillsbury Co., according to
Senauer, put consumers and the share of the market they hold are:
   _Functional Feeders, 18 percent, older couple with husband in
blue-collar job, interested in traditional meals in convenient ways.
   _Down Home Stokers, 21 percent, lower income, traditional
regional or ethnic eaters.
   _Careful Cooks, 20 percent, better educated, older, frequently
retired, higher income, want a healthy, nutritious diet with
emphasis on enjoyment.
   _Happy Cookers, 15 percent, a couple in which one or both enjoy
cooking or baking, want basic ingredients and will pay for quality.
   The Happy Cookers and Chase and Grabbits are the growing
segments of the market, says Senauer.
   Another food trend that affects farmers more directly is the
movement away from products sprayed with chemicals toward
organically grown fruits and vegetables.
   Senauer cites a 1989 survey by the Food Marketing Institute that
said 82 percent of the consumers who responded rated pesticides and
herbicide residues as a serious health hazard.
   However, 81 percent said they were completely confident or
mostly confident that the food in grocery stores is safe.
   Senauer said that to avoid consumer panic that can hurt farmers
and food-related businesses, the government and food industry
``both need to be sensitive to the public's need for adequate and
accurate information about the safety of food and thereby actively
work to maintain consumer confidence in the food system.''
   Besides worrying about chemicals, consumers are more concerned
than ever about the nutritional value of their food.
   ``The average American consumes 37 percent of his or her
calories in the form of fat, down from 40 percent in 1977,'' said
Senauer.
   This shows up on the farm in decreased demand for products high
in saturated fat, such as animal shortening, butter and whole milk.
   More cuts can be expected if Americans ever get to the
recommended 30 percent fat content in their daily diet, said
Senauer.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Cattle being fed for the slaughter market as
of Dec. 1 in the seven major beef states totaled 8.13 million head,
up 2 percent from a year ago but 3 percent below the level of two
years ago, says the Agriculture Department.
   Marketings of ``fed'' cattle in November totaled 1.50 million
head, fractionally below a year ago but 1 percent below two years
ago, according to the report Monday.
   The placement of new cattle and calves in fattening pens last
month was reported at 1.99 million head, up 18 percent from a year
ago and 22 percent more than two years ago.
   This was the largest November placement total since 1977, and
the result of cattle moving into feedlots rather than going onto
wheat pastures.
   State feedlot cattle inventories are listed here for the seven
states, which account for about three-fourths of the nation's beef.
The first number is the number of cattle, in thousands, as of Dec.
1, and the second number is the percentage of a year earlier.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Arizona          251  93
California       490 89
Colorado         960 101
Iowa             665 109
Kansas         1,600 106
Nebraska       2,100 106
Texas          2,060 97
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Americans smoked less in 1989 than the year
before, according to a tobacco report from the Agriculture
Department.
   ``Despite record exports of about 130 billion cigarettes, output
is down,'' said the report released Monday by the department's
economic research service.
   U.S. cigarette consumption may be off about 4 percent from last
year, the report said.
   ``Use of cigars and smoking tobacco continues to decline, but
snuff production is up,'' it also said.
   The Agriculture Department says the U.S. tobacco crop is larger
this year than last, but 1989-90 supplies are lower because of
smaller beginning stocks.
</TEXT>

</DOC>