<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0130 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1651EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Salvador     12-18 0541</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Salvador,570</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Denies Salvadoran Witnesses Mistreated</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The State Department said Monday that it
``absolutely and unequivocally'' denied assertions by a Salvadoran
couple who said they were mistreated by interrogators after they
linked the Salvadoran army to the deaths of six Jesuit priests last
month.
   Jorge Cerna, and his wife, Lucia Barrera de Cerna, told The New
York Times that U.S. and Salvadoran investigators repeatedly
accused them of lying, and that at one point were threatened with
deportation from the United States.
   Mrs. Barrera de Cerna worked as a housekeeper for the priets.
   Martha Doggett of the Lawyers Committee for Human Rights said
the woman was so intimidated by FBI agents and a Salvadoran colonel
that she recanted her story.
   After the couple's allegations appeared in Monday's editions of
The New York Times, the State Department reaffirmed the denials it
issued last week after charges by a Salvadoran cleric.
   Department spokeswoman Margaret Tutwiler said Mrs. Barrera de
Cerna was treated with ``respect and courtesy'' during the
interviews, which were conducted in the United States over a period
of several days in late November.
   ``Every effort was made to make the witness feel comfortable and
secure,'' Ms. Tutwiler said about Mrs. Barrera de Cerna, adding
there was no threat to deport her.
   William Walker, the U.S. ambassador to El Salvador, also denied
that U.S. government officials had subjected Mrs. Barrera de Cerna
to pressure.
   ``Full professionals do not involve themselves in psychological
torment,'' Walker told reporters in Washington.
   However, he also said she gave differing versions of what she
saw the night the priests were slain and a subsequent lie-detector
test could not corroborate any of her testimony.
   ``This does not mean she is not a credible witness or that she's
trying to deceive us, but we are just trying to put together what
she did see,'' he said.
   Justice Department spokesman David Runkle said a review of the
transcript indicated the interviews were carried out in a
professional fashion.
   As part of the U.S. effort to help Salvadoran authorities bring
the killers of the Jesuits to justice, American officials arranged
for Mrs. Barrera de Cerna to be flown to Miami after learning she
may have been a witness.
   ``She was considered as someone with information which could be
useful in solving these horrible crimes,'' Ms. Tutwiler said. ``She
was never treated as a criminal suspect.''
   Ms. Doggett said the interrogators cast doubt on the couples'
allegation that they had seen Salvadoran soldiers moving to and
from the priests' residences.
   ``Who put you up to this?'' they were asked, according to Ms.
Doggett.
   Ms. Doggett said Mrs. Barrerr de Cerna was told, ``Depending on
what you say, you may or may not have to go back to El Salvador.''
   The Salvadoran officer, Lt. Col. Manuel Antonio Rivas, also
yelled at Mrs. Barrera de Cerna: ``I'm ashamed of you! You're a
Salvadoran! You're a liar!'' Ms. Doggett said.
   Rivas is head of the U.S.-trained Special Investigative Unit,
which was designed to handle human rights cases.
   Ms. Doggett, who coordinates Latin American and Caribbean
affairs for the Lawyers Committee, was one of two representatives
from the organization to interview Mrs. Barrera de Cerna recently.
</TEXT>

</DOC>