<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1415EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Mandela 1stLd-Writethru a0510 12-25 0467</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mandela, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0510,0476</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mandela Spends 28th Christmas in Prison</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to UPDATE with Mrs. Mandela quotes. Pickup
5th pvs, ``The family ...''</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-South Africa, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SAHM VENTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE TOWN, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jailed black leader Nelson
Mandela, whose 28th Christmas behind bars will almost certainly be
his last in custody, opened presents and had a quiet dinner with
his family Monday.
   Mandela's wife, Winnie, their daughter, Zindzi, and her three
young children spent most of the day at the comfortable
three-bedroom home where Mandela is held at the Victor Verster
Prison outside Cape Town.
   ``He would have loved to spend Christmas at home with us,'' said
Mrs. Mandela, who had tears in her eyes when she spoke to reporters
afterward.
   ``He regrets to advise that he has no new information whatsoever
about his release,'' she added. ``As far as he knows, there have
been no further developments that point to his immediate release.''
   The family brought a cake with icing in the green, gold and
black colors of the African National Congress, the outlawed
guerrilla movement Mandela heads.
   The family gave Mandela shirts from a Johannesburg tailor who
made suits for seven of Mandela's ANC colleagues released from
prison in October.
   Mrs. Mandela said telling the grandchildren, ages 9, 6 and less
than 1 year, that their grandfather could not leave with them was
``particularly painful.''
   The family planned another visit Tuesday before returning to
their home in Soweto, the huge black township outside Johannesburg.
   Mandela, 71, is the country's best-known black leader and the
world's most famous prisoner. He has been jailed since 1962 and is
serving a life sentence for plotting an anti-government sabotage
campaign.
   His release is widely expected within weeks, and there was
speculation he might be freed on or around Christmas. The
government quashed those rumors Friday by saying Mandela would not
be freed this year.
   Mandela has had a steady stream of visitors in recent months,
ranging from anti-apartheid activists to government leaders. He met
Dec. 13 with President F.W. de Klerk at the presidential offices.
   The freeing of the seven ANC leaders was seen a trial run for
Mandela's release. The seven, who have been active in promoting the
ANC since their release, were to have Christmas dinner at the
Johannesburg home of Helen Joseph, an 84-year-old white
anti-apartheid activist.
   Ms. Joseph, one of Mandela's co-defendants at a 1956-61 treason
trial, visited Mandela on Thursday. It was their first meeting in
28 years.
   The Mandelas have another daughter, Zeni, who is married and
studying in the United States.
   Mandela also has a son and a daughter from his first marriage,
which ended in divorce. Another son from that marriage was killed
in a traffic accident.
</TEXT>

</DOC>