<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0167 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 2141EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-NorthonStage     12-29 0367</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-North on Stage,340</SECOND>
<HEAD>Oliver North Gets Raves as `Peter and Wolf' Narrator</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WX15</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT M. ANDREWS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iran-Contra figure Oliver L. North won hearty
applause for his musical stage debut Friday night as narrator of
``Peter and the Wolf,'' but among the youngsters in the audience he
was clearly upstaged by the wolf.
   ``It was right nice,'' said Aquil Robinson, 12. ``What I liked
best was when the wolf ate the duck.''
   North, 46, who is appealing his May 4 conviction on three felony
charges in connection with the Iran-Contra affair, accepted an
invitation from Maria Fisher, president of the Beethoven Society,
to read the narration for Sergei Prokofiev's musical tale for
children.
   The retired Marine colonel and former White House national
security aide wore a tuxedo for his half-hour performance in the
main ballroom of a downtown hotel before about 1,000 spectators.
   The audience included North's probation officer, Ralph Ardito,
and 100 inner-city children from the Save Our Youth anti-drug
program in Washington, where North is serving his sentence of 1,200
hours of community service. He also was given two years' probation
and fined $150,000.
   North read with lively expression and never missed a cue from
the orchestra conductor. He said it was his first stage appearance
since he played ``the bad guy'' in a high school production of
``How the West Was Won'' in his hometown of Philmont, N.Y., nearly
30 years ago.
   ``It was wonderful,'' said former North associate Robert W.
Owen, who saw the show with his 2-year-old daughter Katie. ``Ollie
may have a new profession,'' said Owen, who once served as North's
liaison with the Nicaraguan Contra rebels.
   ``He was very good,'' said conductor Richard Weilenmann. ``Some
narrators are exaggerated and overblown, but North read very
naturally, as if he were reading to his own children.''
   ``Ollie's doing it because he's a friend of mine,'' said Mrs.
Fisher, whose musical society sponsored the concert. She said she
has admired North since she watched his televised testimony at the
congressional Iran-Contra hearings in 1987.
   North, who reportedly charges $25,000 for every speech he makes,
narrated ``Peter and the Wolf'' for free, Mrs. Fisher said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>