<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0221 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1336EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--BroadwayConductor Adv31-1stAdd   12-18 0736</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Broadway Conductor, Adv 31-1st Add,0750</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 31</HEAD>
<HEAD>NEW YORK: taking effect.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   ``This is 34th Street. How does it serve us? Let me count the
ways: Penn Station, the Long Island Railroad, Amtrak, Madison
Square Garden and much else. Times Square is next on our quest for
Van Cortlandt Park.
   Nugent regularly gets applause, cheers, flowers and thank-you
notes. A homeless woman told him, ``You've given me 40 minutes of
happiness.'' A punk rocker said he dug his rap. One man obtained
Nugent's schedule and began planning his trips accordingly.
Sometimes tourists throw money into his conductor's booth. ``They
think I'm some sort of street performer,'' he complains.
   ``This is Times Square, a station that celebrates transfers _ to
the 2, 3 and 7, the N and R, the Grand Central Shuttle. Up one
track and down the other _ not one dull or idle moment.''
   That line comes from Nugent's father, who ran away from home as
a boy to join the circus, and went on to become a magician,
puppeteer and side-show barker. Sometimes he feels like a pitchman
himself, a tout for 38 stations.
   ``Our station is 50th Street. It's several blocks from
Rockefeller Center, but you can walk there if you have a yen for
it.''
   Nugent often slips in references to current events, in this case
the sale of a majority interest in Rockefeller Center to a Japanese
corporation. But you have to be careful, he says, because people
don't pay their $1 to be offended.
   ``We're arriving at 96th Street. Here we have a parting of the
ways with our running mates, the 2 and the 3, so it's your last
chance to transfer. Heading our way? Perhaps we should join forces.
We're the 1 to Van Cortlandt Park.''
   Nugent's conducting has opened doors for himself, too, including
offers to perform on radio and in nightclubs. He passed on the
former _ his line has 38 stations, and he's on all of them. As for
stand-up comedy, he asks, ``How would I get the train in a club?''
   The problem with notoriety is that people now expect the unusual
from Nugent. ``One day I was just making standard announcements,
nothing special, and a guy came up and said, `What's wrong? I
brought my wife to hear you.'''
   ``This is 110th Street, also known as Central Park North and
Cathedral Parkway. Does a street with three names sound magical? No
surprise. Harry Houdini used to get off here. If you just joined
us, we're going uptown to Van Cortlandt Park.''
   Some riders ask Nugent if the voice they hear is a tape
recording. He tells them, ``Yes, I'm state-of-the-art.'' Others,
who assume they've been listening to the motorman in the front of
the train, tell Nugent, ``He's great!''
   ``He's happy to hear that,'' the conductor responds.
   ``We're at 215th Street, a station that is gradually winning
acceptance from the newly erected Allen Pavilion of Presbyterin
Hospital.''
   Nugent stole that line from Bob and Ray; he often twists the
language's logic, as when he says that the 79th Street station is
``cleverly arranged to be only two blocks from the Museum of
Natural History.''
   His routine also includes an assortment of puns. Sixty-sixth
Street station serves ``the medley of theaters known in concert as
Lincoln Center.'' When the train emerges from the tunnel and runs
on elevated tracks after 116th Street, he says, ``You may get the
impression we're gaining altitude, but we never rise above our
station.''
   ``Our next stop will be 225th Street in the Bronx. We're now
crossing the Broadway Bridge, the bridge they put the Harlem River
under. If you look west, you'll see one of our better views.''
   Nugent would like a new audience _ ``I thought I'd have died by
now on this line'' _ and the chance to talk about other stations.
But he plans to stick to the Broadway line until he retires,
because its northern terminal is near his home in Yonkers, just
over the city line. It also has the best trains _ and the best PA
systems.
   ``This is 242nd Street, Van Cortlandt Park, the gateway to
Westchester County. Here, our journey usually draws to a
conclusion. But that's fine, because we've run out of track. We'd
like to thank you for riding the No. 1. Have a good day.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>

</DOC>