<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0142EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Bush-Notebook     12-18 0688</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bush-Notebook,680</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Flies to West Indies for Lunch With Mitterrand</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM RAUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MARIGOT, St. Martin (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush confesses ``only one
complaint, one regret'' about his seaside soiree with the president
of France: ``that we have to leave this beautiful paradise on such
a short notice.''
   But it's not exactly as if someone were about to order the
president of the United States to leave this tropical Caribbean
island and return to the nation's capital _ caught in the grips of
sub-freezing weather.
   After all, the French West Indies is a bit of a trek just for
lunch and a walk on the beach _ even for globetrotting diplomats
like Bush and Francois Mitterrand, who jets about in a supersonic
Air France Concorde.
   In his more sedate Air Force One, a 25-year-old Boeing 707, Bush
had to leave Washington before dawn and fly for three and a half
hours for Saturday's brief Franco-American encounter.
   Their meetings lasted just over three hours _ and that included
a beach walk, lunch and a 45-minute news conference.
   Then, Bush left this land of gentle trade winds, palm trees and
a temperature in the 80s to fly another three and a half hours back
to Washington, where the temperature when he landed at snow-covered
Andrews Air Force Base was 5 degrees.
   ``I'm disappointed the meeting didn't break apart so we could
have spent a week here,'' said Secretary of State James A. Baker
III, shaking his head in mock dismay.
   But nobody was about to tell Bush to slow down, not even Baker.
   Why did Bush travel so far for such a short meeting?
   ``It's not much different than going to Houston for the
weekend,'' offered press secretary Marlin Fitzwater.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>___</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   ``It doesn't hurt, just can't talk,'' was how Bush described his
most recent bout with laryngitis. French President Mitterrand came
to the rescue _ by dominating their joint news conference and
giving Bush plenty of time to rest his raspy voice.
   Not only did Mitterrand, the host on this French island for the
weekend get-together, decide whom to call on, but he also tended
toward lengthy, expansive answers.
   Several times, as Mitterrand droned on, Bush looked to U.S.
reporters sitting in the first row and shrugged his shoulders.
   One of the few times Bush called on a reporter, he requested
Mitterrand's permission to pick ``the man who thought he had been
recognized'' for the previous question. But the reporter Bush
selected turned out to have a question in French for Mitterrand.
   The two leaders had headphones so they could listen to
translations of questions and answers into their respective
languages.
   Bush, who sometimes likes to blurt out phrases in high-school
French, decided to trust instead to the official translator and
spent much of the news conference with one earpiece held tightly to
his ear.
   And, for his part, Mitterrand seemed temporarily taken aback
when questions turned to whether Bush's ``special relationship''
with him was on a par with U.S. friendship with Britain's Margaret
Thatcher.
   ``There is room enough for several friendships in life,'' he
said.
   Then he was asked if his response would have been the same
before last Jan. 20 _ Bush's inauguration day.
   Mitterrand looked confused and asked what was the significance
of Jan. 20. To rising laughter, it finally dawned on him. ``I need
a triple translation,'' he joked.
   Then he said that he had gotten along just as well with former
President Reagan.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>___</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Tim McBride, Bush's personal aide, is seldom more than a few
paces from the president's side. But he found some rare time on his
hands during the Bush-Mitterrand meeting.
   So he went for a dip in the warm, inviting Caribbean. However,
the beach had been closed because of the high-level gathering and
French security officers wasted little time in ordering McBride out
of the water.
   Clad only in a bathing suit, the embarrassed aide had a hard
time persuading the gendarmes he really worked at the White House.
He was briefly taken into custody until he could get the U.S.
Secret Service to vouch for him.
</TEXT>

</DOC>