<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1924EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-Tension     12-17 0663</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Tension,0684</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shooting Occurs At Height Of Government Anti-U.S. Campaign</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The fatal shooting of a U.S. military
officer over the weekend came after months of a vitriolic,
government-sponsored campaign against Americans and their
government.
   The campaign peaked Friday when a member of the People's
Assembly, which named Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega as chief of
government, asked for guns for the people ``because what we have to
do here is kill gringos and pro-gringos.''
   ``We have to kill all gringos,'' a Panamanian soldier guarding
the Defense Headquarters told reporters earlier, pointing to a U.S.
Army helicopter hovering a short distance away.
   He spoke before the Assembly declared Panama ``in a state of war
as long as the U.S. aggression lasts.''
   Saturday's shooting death of the American officer near Panama's
defense headquarters was ignored by the Panamanian military. Its
communique on the incident referred only to a ``provocation'' by
the U.S military.
   The U.S. Southern Command said the officer and three others, all
off duty, unarmed and in civilian clothes, were detained by
Panamanian soldiers near the checkpoint. According to an official
statment, the officers were ``hassled'' and tried to flee by car
and the Panamanian soldiers shot at the car.
   For nearly two years, the U.S. government has tried to force
Noriega's ouster. Noriega, commander of the Panamanian Defense
Forces, was indicted in Florida in February 1988 on U.S.
drug-trafficking and money-laundering charges. Noriega denies the
charges.
   The U.S. government has tried to isolate Noriega
internationally, accusing him of annulling presidential elections
in May because his handpicked candidate lost.
   U.S. and Panamanian forces have faced each other several times
when the Panamanians tried to block U.S. military maneuvers that
Washington claims are necessary to train forces here to defend the
Panama Canal.
   Yet, until two years ago, these same forces regularly
participated in joint military exercises and their officers
socialized together.
   It all ended abruptly after the first military coup attempt
against Noriega on March 16, 1988. Noriega accused the United
States of trying to infiltrate the Defense Forces and brought back
Panama officers attending special training programs at U.S.
military bases.
   As the United States imposed economic sanctions on Panama, the
government-controlled news media began a campaign aimed at
discrediting the U.S. government, all U.S. officials and U.S.
military officers here.
   Newspapers depicted U.S. soldiers as cowards and drug addicts
and carriers of the AIDS virus and other sexually transmitted
diseases.
   The United States was shown in column after column as a country
where discrimination is practiced against blacks and Hispanics.
   But mostly, the columnists said the United States was trying to
back out of the treaties that call for transfer of the Canal
adminstration to Panama and the closing of U.S. bases at the end of
the century.
   They whipped up nationalistic fervor, portraying Noriega as the
leader of the resistance to U.S. attempts to revoke the treaties.
   No opposition or independent news media exist in Panama.
   A Southern Command source, speaking on condition of anonymity,
said of the Saturday shooting, ``This is the result of
anti-American propaganda and the totally unprofessional attitude of
the Defense Forces.''
   Ricardo Arias Calderon, leader of the Christian Democratic Party
and former opposition vice presidential candidate, said, ``It is
the result of the psychological war and the escalation of the
confrontation between the countries' military.
   ``We had warned that the series of confrontations would produce
incidents like this. The danger is that this can provoke a greater
confrontation.''
   The climate of confrontation was new in a country where the
official currency is the U.S. dollar, where relations with the
United States have been close since the United States built the
Canal at the beginning of the century and where thousands of U.S.
soldiers and their dependents used to live off-base in Panama City.
   About 13,000 American troops are stationed in Panama, and a
total of about 40,000 Americans live here.
</TEXT>

</DOC>