<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1108EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SAfrica-Chronology     12-25 0367</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SAfrica-Chronology,0380</SECOND>
<HEAD>Major Events in de Klerk's Administration</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-South Africa, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Major events since F.W. de
Klerk was inaugurated as president on Sept. 20.
   Sept. 20 _ De Klerk takes the oath of office at the Union
Buildings in Pretoria, pledges to seek a South Africa ``free of
domination and oppression.''
   Oct. 2 _ Officials of the national government negotiate for the
first time with activists on possible solutions to a three-year
rent boycott in Soweto, the country's largest black township.
   Oct. 11 _ De Klerk confers for three hours with Anglican
Archbishop Desmond Tutu and two other anti-apartheid church leaders.
   Oct. 15 _ On de Klerk's orders, the government unconditionally
frees eight prominent long-term political prisoners, including
Walter Sisulu, a senior leader of the outlawed African National
Congress.
   Oct. 29 _ More than 70,000 cheering, chanting blacks attend a
welcome home rally for Sisulu and his colleagues, the largest
opposition meeting ever in South Africa, after de Klerk decides to
allow it.
   Oct. 30 _ The president tells his Cabinet that all departmental
budgets, including the military, will be cut.
   Nov. 9 _ De Klerk meets leaders of two white extremist groups,
tells them right-wing violence won't be tolerated.
   Nov. 16 _ De Klerk declares that all remaining whites-only
beaches will be opened to blacks and says the Separate Amenities
Act, which allows segregation of lcoal facilities, will be scrapped
``as soon as possible.''
   Nov. 28 _ De Klerk announces the scrapping of the National
Management System, a controversial bureaucratic network which
enabled police and army commanders to exercize control over black
townships.
   Dec. 1 _ De Klerk travels to a summit meeting with President
Houphouet-Boigny of the Ivory Coast.
   Dec. 7 _ De Klerk cuts mandatory military service for white men
from two years to one and says some military bases and units will
be eliminated.
   Dec. 13 _ De Klerk confers with jailed African National Congress
leader Nelson Mandela at the presidential office in Cape Town.
   Dec. 15 _ De Klerk travels to a summit meeting with President
Joaquim Chissano of Mozambique, whose leftist government in the
past has accused South Africa of supporting a rebel insurgency.
</TEXT>

</DOC>