<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0157 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1145EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f PM-OntheMoney Adv28   12-27 0631</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-On the Money, Adv 28,0646</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv28</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release PMs Thurs Dec 28</HEAD>
<HEAD>Tough Choices For Income-Minded Savers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHET CURRIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The financial menu looks pretty skimpy as
income-conscious investors consider where to put their money for a
new year and a new decade.
   No matter how far in time you are willing to extend yourself,
alluring returns on certificates of deposit, bonds and other
interest-bearing investments are hard to find these days.
   Certainly, you are unlikely to come across anything now that
matches the two-digit yields on low-risk securities that were so
commonly available in the early 1980s.
   But inflation has also declined in recent years, and so has the
maximum rate at which the federal government taxes most people's
interest income. So, in the view of many analysts, the ``real''
returns offered now aren't as stingy as they might look.
   Suppose as 1990 begins that you can get a yield of 8.3 percent
from a CD or money-market mutual fund. If your income tax bracket
is 28 percent _ the top rate that applies to most savers and
investors _ you have a return of 6 percent left over after Uncle
Sam takes his cut.
   After taking into account consumer inflation in the 4 percent to
5 percent annual range, you still emerge with a positive return.
   On paper at least, that beats the results you might have
achieved at a nominal interest rate of, say, 13 percent a decade
ago, when inflation and taxes together would have left you actually
in the red.
   Of course the current returns savers and investors can get are
only part of the story. The ideal investment choice also must keep
looking good through the future ups and downs of inflation and
interest rates.
   Right now, many analysts are predicting at least a modest
decline in interest rates over the next several months. That would
argue in favor of longer-term investments such as CDs or bonds
rather than short-term options such as money market funds.
   Unfortunately, interest rates at present are such that you get
paid little or nothing for making that kind of longer-term
commitment.
   A recent tally by the Bank Rate Monitor showed three-month CDs
yielding an average of 7.87 percent; two-year CDs 7.71 percent, and
five-year CDs 7.73 percent.
   This is known in financial circles as a flat, or slightly
``inverted,'' yield curve, and it is abnormal although by no means
unprecedented in modern history.
   The yield curve has been out of kilter for more than a year now.
But some analysts think it is slowly beginning to resume a more
orthodox shape.
   For now the Value Line Investment Survey, the nation's largest
independent investment advisory service, recommends keeping your
options open by sticking mainly with short-term commitments. ``A
bit more patience,'' the firm urges, ``a wait until the long rate
offers more of a yield advantage to warrant the added risk.''
   Staying short-term, of course, also gives you protection should
interest rates pull a surprise by heading higher. In that event,
yields on vehicles such as money market funds would stand to move
up as well.
   What if interest rates should neither rise nor fall, but hover
around present levels for some indeterminate period?
   That would create few opportunities for investors to pull off
heroic coups of market timing. But it would leave enough goodies to
go around that hardly anyone need be entirely dissatisfied.
   ``The sideways scenario isn't bad for either camp,'' observed
Edward Yardeni, economist at the Wall Street firm of
Prudential-Bache Securities.
   ``The bulls earn the coupon (or nominal interest rate on
long-term investments), and since the yield curve is flat, the
bears earn a comparable return in the short-term money markets.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv PMs Thursday Dec 28</NOTE>

</DOC>