<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0197 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0854EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a w PM-CensusForms Adv19   12-18 0776</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Census Forms, Adv 19,0799</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv19</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Tue PMs Dec 19</HEAD>
<HEAD>New Decade Means It's Census Time</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RANDOLPH E. SCHMID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For the 20th time since the founding of the
republic, your government is setting out to learn something about
each of you _ and quite a lot about many of us.
   Where do you live? How old are you and what's your race? Are you
single, married or living with an ``unmarried partner''? How big is
your house, what's it worth and is it paid for?
   Yes, it's time once again for a new decade and another census.
   Even now, massive printing presses are churning out the more
than 100 million forms that will be needed to count over 250
million Americans April 1.
   Originally required as a count of the population to help divide
up seats in the House of Representatives, the census has become an
effort to assess the state of the nation.
   The debate about what to ask in 1990 has been under way for most
of this decade. Since 1984 there have been 65 public meetings
around the nation to get the public's comments and suggestions.
More than 5,000 people attended.
   Suggestions that the Census Bureau ask people about their
religion, their pets and their sexual preference come up often _
and are rejected every time.
   A proposal to ask about citizenship, in an effort to determine
the number of illegal aliens, was also not included on the short
form intended to enumerate everyone living in the United States.
Few people in this country illegally would be likely to admit as
much to the government, officials said.
   In choosing what to ask, census officials considered the needs
of government agencies, tried to repeat as many questions as
possible from the past to maintain consistent statistics and
realized that asking too much would result in people refusing to
cooperate.
   Indeed, the Office of Management and Budget, complaining of a
``paperwork burden'' for the public, fought a battle wth the Census
Bureau over some of the questions.
   The bureau produced a 150-page study justifying the questions it
is asking. After finding little support for some of the information
collected the last time, the agency has dropped questions about
marital history and home air conditioning.
   Most homes will receive the form in the mail in late March and
are expected to mail it back after April 1. Census takers will go
only to some rural homes and to other places from which the mailed
forms were not returned.
   As in 1980, when mailed forms largely replaced census takers,
the Postal Service will deliver forms to more that four out of five
homes in the country, based on address lists purchased from
commercial firms and compiled by the Census Bureau. Census takers
will go to areas where no adequate address lists could be obtained.
   Over the years, hundreds of federal programs have developed that
disperse money and projects on the basis of census statistics, and
thus need specific information collected every 10 years.
   Welfare programs and highway funds, job training and mass
transit projects, education and urban renewal all depend on the
census for raw data.
   Simple pride results in some data being kept when statisticians
want to drop it.
   This time, for example, the Census Bureau wanted to leave a
blank for people to write in their ethnic group if they had checked
off ``Asian or Pacific Islander'' under race.
   In 1980 that question offered a list of possible Asian and
Pacific Island groups and a check-off box beside each.
   Members of Congress representing areas with many Asians and
Pacific Islanders didn't like the proposed change and got a bill
through Congress to restore the 1980 style. So, in April, the
census form will have a list of check-off boxes for such groups as
Chinese, Filipino, Hawaiian, Korean, Vietnamese, Japanese, Asian
Indian, Samoan and Guamian as well as the write-in space for folks
who don't fit any of those categories.
   The end result is two census forms, just as in 1980.
   One form will be sent to every home in the nation _ more than
106 million. That form contains seven questions about individuals
and seven about housing.
   One household in six will receive a long form, which amounts to
a massive random sample of the nation.
   Besides the questions on the short form, the long one asks 26
more about individuals and 19 more about housing.
   The personal questions include ones dealing with ancestry, work
and income; the housing questions include ones asking about
plumbing, telephones and building age.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Mon PMs Dec 19</NOTE>

</DOC>