<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0038EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Christmas-Jesus'KinI     12-20 1240</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Christmas-Jesus' Kin I,1277</SECOND>
<HEAD>Part I: Jesus Descended From Checkered Ancestry</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Wednesday AMs report.</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   This first installment of a three-part Christmas
series about the relatives of Jesus deals with his ancestral roots.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE W. CORNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Religion Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Everyone is a special sum of ancestry _ to enhance or diminish
through a lifetime. That was so for the child of Christmas, the
product of a heritage.
   Some biblical passages cloak his origins in utter mystery,
before time itself. But others accord him a thoroughly natural
family tree.
   ``He was in the beginning with God,'' says one account, a
``Word'' or ``Logos,'' a vitalizing wisdom inherent in the Creator
before the world began. Yet other passages say he was ``made like
his brethren in every respect.''
   ``Son of man,'' he usually called himself, but also ``Son of
God.''
   He combined ``universality with particularity,'' the ``divine
and human model,'' writes church historian Jaroslav Pelican in his
book ``Jesus Through the Centuries.'' It says a key question put to
him was, ``Where do you come from?''
   Although seldom noted, he had a long string of forebears as well
as contemporary relatives who gave him both problems and help. His
lineage ran deep into Jewish history.
   As with most people if their descent is traced back far enough,
he had a checkered ancestry, good and bad, the lowly and great,
kings, betrayers, heroes, adulterers, warriors and prostitutes.
   It was an odd assortment, like humanity itself, alien Gentiles
and fellow Jews, the weak and strong, upright and corrupt. The fact
that he shared these common roots is considered theologically basic
to his purpose: becoming identified with all humankind.
   They ``were all members of Jesus' family, his great-great-great
grandaddies and grandmamas in the faith,'' wrote church scholar
William H. Willimon. ``For all their weaknesses and shortcomings,
this motley but richly human crew were indeed his people.''
   Two genealogies of Jesus are recorded, one in the first chapter
of the Book of Matthew, the other in the third chapter of the Book
of Luke. They vary in some detail and some interpreters debatably
assume Luke gives the line of his mother, Mary, and that Matthew
gives that of Joseph, legally the father.
   ``It is possible that the original genealogy did interpret
Joseph as the father of Jesus, that is, that it had been formulated
before the understanding of Jesus as the divinely generated son of
God,'' writes New Testament scholar Henrikus Boers in his book
``Who Was Jesus?''
   Some progenitors are on both lists, including olden patriarchs
of Judaism and Israel's great King David, along with other lesser
figures of sundry character.
   Matthew lists 41 ancestors, starting back at the time of
Abraham, ancient father of Israel, and other early patriarchs,
Isaac and Jacob.
   Luke lists 77 progenitors in reverse order, starting with Joseph
and enumerating others going back to the first man, Adam, and
finally to his creator, God.
   Other figures out of dim antiquity also are included, such as
Noah, and that legend of longevity, Methuselah, who lived 969
years, all designated ancestors of Jesus.
   In the mostly male lists, four women are named, and they're a
mixed group _ a soldier's beautiful wife, Bathsheba, seduced by
King David; the harlot of Jericho, Rahab; the sexually maneuvering
Cananite, Tamar; and the loyal Mohabite, Ruth.
   Tamar was the daugher-in-law of Judah, son of the patriarch
Jacob. Her husband died and after prolonged widowhood, she
disguised herself as a prostitute and enticed her father-in-law to
lie with her. She bore twins, one named Perez, also among Jesus'
forbears.
   Rahab was a harlot who sheltered two scouts sent by the
Israelite warrior-leader Joshua to spy out Jericho before taking
it. She hid them from searchers in flax stalks on her rooftop.
   She later helped the pair escape, lowering them on a rope from a
window in her house, which was built into the city wall. By
agreement with the two, her clan was spared when Jericho was
destroyed, her house marked by a scarlet cord hung from a window.
   The devoted woman of Moab, Ruth, widowed by her Hebrew husband,
insisted on returning with her mother-in-law, Naomi, to Israel,
with these memorable words: ``For where you go I will go ... your
people will be my people, and your God my God.''
   On Naomi's advice, Ruth worked in the harvest, sleeping at the
feet of the owner, Boaz, thus winning him as her husband. They were
parents of Obed, father of Jesse, who fathered King David.
   His philandering with Bathsheba, the gorgeous wife of an absent
military officer, Uriah, produced sons Nathan and future King
Solomon, alternatively listed in Jesus' line of descent.
   Other men on the lists also displayed foibles, such as Jacob's
deceiving his father to gain an inheritance, and even Abraham
fearfully palming off his lovely wife, Sarah, as his ``sister'' to
placate the ruling pharaoh while temporarily in Egypt.
   Nevertheless, those honored patriarchs also displayed courage,
initiative and devotion in their covenant with God to lead a people
that would be a promised ``light to the nations.''
   The great Israelite military commander, Joshua, successor to
Moses, also is listed, along with a long succession of kings,
decent and debauched, in addition to charming, psalm-singing David
and wise Solomon, credited with the Book of Proverbs and builder of
Jerusalem's first Temple.
   Other kings include Rehoboam, whose oppressions, idolatrous
rites and immoralities stirred a revolt that divided the kingdom;
Uzziah, stricken with leprosy in a prosperous reign, and Hezekiah
who led reforms under guidance of the prophet Micah.
   Also listed is Manasseh, described as ``the most wicked king of
Judah,'' whose religious deviations included Baalism, exaltation of
the idol Astarte, wizardry and Molech worship that involved forcing
children through fire.
   Tradition has it that Manasseh had the great prophet Isaiah
sawed asunder.
   One king listed, Josiah, took the throne at age 8 when his
father, Amon, was murdered. But Josiah had a long, just reign,
ousting corrupt priests and recovering the lost ``Book of law'' in
repairing the Temple.
   Of many others named, some are clouded, uncertain figures, while
others are notable in Jewish annals, such as Judah, founder of a
main Israelite tribe, and the prophet Nathan who rebuked David for
his illicit affair.
   The mixed lot of people, with their sundry faults and strengths,
were all ``part of the promise fulfilled'' by the Christ child,
Willimon writes. They, ``for all their weaknesses, ... were
instruments of the promise.''
   On the other hand, Jesus' descent also is traced directly to the
Godhead, adding an unfathomable engima to his humanity.
   ``In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and
the Word was God,'' says the distinctively interpretative gospel of
John. ``And the Word became flesh and dwelt among us, full of grace
and truth.''
   He is ``fully God and fully man,'' classic Christian doctrine
says. His conception by the virgin Mary is ascribed by the gospels
to divine intervention. St. Paul calls him the ``image of the
invisible God.''
   Jesus himself, though he was generally elusive about it and
though he identified closely with common folk, sometimes laid it
out plainly, as related by John's gospel:
   ``Truly, truly, I say to you, before Abraham was, I am,'' he
said. ``I and the Father are one ... the Father is in me and I am
in the Father.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Tomorrow: John the Baptist, Cousinly Forerunner</NOTE>

</DOC>