<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0113 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1759EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DigestBriefs     12-25 1715</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Digest Briefs,1782</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eds: Retransmitting to CORRECT numbering sequence.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ousted President Nicolae Ceausescu and
his wife were executed Monday after a secret military trial that
found them guilty of genocide and ``grave crimes'' against Romania,
Bucharest Radio reported.
   Ceausescu, the last hard-line Communist leader in the Warsaw
Pact, was chased from power Friday after his dreaded security
forces massacred thousands protesting his repressive 24-year rule
and harsh economic policies.
   The radio also blamed the Ceausescus for the deaths of more than
60,000 Romanians and said they plundered the poor country of more
than $1 billion that they deposited in foreign banks. The report
did not make clear whether the deaths occurred during the 11-day
uprising that toppled Ceausescu or during his entire tenure.
   Ceausescu, 71, and his wife, Elena, who served as a virtual
second-in-command, were executed after a trial at an undisclosed
location. Executions usually are carried out by firing squad in
Romania.
   ``Oh, what wonderful news!'' an unidentified announcer said on
the radio, which is controlled by the provisional government, the
National Salvation Committee.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Romania's revolution against Communism,
unlike others in Eastern Europe, has exploded in volatile emotions
and violence against the repression enforced by the 24-year
dictatorship of Nicolae Ceausescu.
   Ceausescu and his wife, Elena, were reported to be executed on
Monday after a secret trial on charges of particularly grave crimes
against the people.
   No other East European country revolting in the name of
democracy has reacted in this way. But no other East European
country had a Ceausescu, whose unparalleled personality cult
trumpeted his ``golden era'' while imposing more and more hardship.
   As mandated debt repayment and industrialization programs
brought hardship to every Romanian, dissent was largely repressed
by his dreaded Securitate, a massive network of at least 700,000
people.
   Workers who dared to protest disappeared mysteriously.
Intellectuals, with a higher profile in society, faced prison,
mental hospital, internal exile or house arrest.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. troops kept a vigil on the
Vatican Embassy where Gen. Antonio Manuel Noriega sought asylum as
officials debated what to do with the man who once ran this country.
   Dozens of U.S. soldiers, armored vehicles and helicopters
encircled the embassy after Noriega turned himself in Sunday, five
days after the U.S. invasion overthrew his government, blasted his
headquarters and drove him into hiding.
   Panamanians living in refugee camps and Americans on patrol
found something to celebrate. Near Santo Tomas Hospital,
infantrymen put up a tiny Christmas tree at their post and a sign
saying ``Feliz Navidad,'' merry Christmas. They shared their food
with people from the neighborhood.
   President Guillermo Endara, the U.S.-backed leader who took
power minutes after the U.S. invasion, visited refugees during a
Christmas Mass at a camp in a soccer stadium. Endara refused to
comment on Noriega's status, saying, ``It is a very delicate
diplomatic matter with the papal state.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Manuel Antonio Noriega's decision to seek
asylum at the Vatican's embassy in Panama City forces President
Bush into the thicket of diplomacy and international law in pursuit
of his goal of bringing the deposed dictator to trial on drug
trafficking charges.
   ``Now it's up to the lawyers and the diplomats,'' summed up
Pentagon chief Dick Cheney, whose troops tried but failed to
capture the elusive dictator in more than four days of searching.
   When Noriega drove up to the Vatican embassy in Panama City on
Christmas Eve, Bush accomplished a central goal of the invasion he
ordered last week: removing the indicted drug trafficker from all
power in Panama.
   But how Bush, Panama's U.S.-backed government, the Vatican and
other nations handle the next step could determine not only
Noriega's fate, but the future of the strategically placed isthmus
for years to come.
   U.S. interests appear to be best served by Noriega's speedy
removal from the Papal Nunciature, where he is protected by
diplomatic immunity and by the spotlight of international
attention. As long as he stays, attention could be diverted from
U.S. efforts to restore order to the devastated country.
   The White House said Sunday it still hopes to bring Noriega to
justice. He was indicted in Florida on federal charges in 1988.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Manuel Blanco rummaged through the
ashes that had been his home and salvaged a balpeen hammer with a
charred handle and a blackened pair of pliers.
   The two tools and the clothes on his back are what remains of
his earthly possessions. Even so, the 70-year-old retired auto
mechanic says he is glad U.S. forces invaded Panama and overthrew
the dictatorship of Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   ``It hurts that I've lost everything, but what are you going to
do? The gringos had to do it like they did. I only wish they would
have done it long ago,'' he said.
   He stood on blackened sheets of corrugated zinc that had been
the roof of the two-story wooden apartment building, where he lived
with his wife and their granddaughter. The only remnants of the
building are two masonry columns that supported the communal
bathrooms.
   Blanco and his neighbors had the misfortune to live a block from
the headquarters of the Panamanian Defense Forces, Noriega's
command center.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Millions of Eastern Europeans celebrated their first free
Christmas in four decades: Political prisoners rejoined their
families, East Germans and Czechoslovaks watched Mass on TV, and
Romanians listened to carols long-banned on state radio.
   Pope John Paul II prayed for Romanians ``celebrating this
Christmas in fear and trembling,'' mourned the thousands killed
overthrowing their Communist leaders, and praised the democratic
reforms remaking his native Eastern Europe.
   The Soviet Union's Baltic republics enjoyed the first official
Christmas holiday allowed by the Communists.
   Panamanians and U.S. soldiers spent Christmas on the lookout for
snipers.
   Church bells pealed across Czechoslovakia to mark the new
freedoms won in a pro-democracy movement that toppled Communist
leaders, created a free press and brought promises of free
elections.
   ``I feel like this is a miracle,'' said Ivan Martin Jirous, who
was reunited with his family after being released from prison one
month ago.
   On Prague's 15th century Charles Bridge, young carolers sang
haunting, traditional Christmas melodies. In previous years, police
chased carolers from the broad, cobbled King's Road.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   He goes as he came, possibly the most
effervescent politician of the dying decade.
   To effervesce, Mr. Webster says, is to ``bubble and hiss.'' If
anything, the unretiring retiring mayor of New York now leaves
office after 12 noisy years with more bubble than hiss.
   ``God has been very nice to me,'' Ed Koch concludes, without
suggesting that God ever got a single word in edgewise.
   American leaders cross the bridge from power to private life in
a variety of moods. Ulysses S. Grant worried about money. William
Howard Taft felt like a ``giant locomotive suddenly pulling a toy
train.'' Herbert Hoover and Jimmy Carter felt dejected and rejected.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   There's still doubt whether
President F.W. de Klerk will personally oversee the end of
apartheid, but his performance since his inauguration has raised
hopes higher than ever for peaceful change.
   Even the white-run government's most militant opponents
acknowledge a dramatic shift in mood since P.W. Botha quit the
presidency. They say de Klerk's conciliatory moves resulted from
pressure rather than conviction, but many anti-apartheid leaders
now believe _ for the first time _ that the government sincerely
wants to negotiate with them.
   ``Exit a president named P.W., to be replaced by one named F.W.
Remarkable what a difference that one letter made,'' wrote The
Weekly Mail, an anti-apartheid newspaper, in its year-end issue.
   ``Suddenly the logjam seemed to break. Good intentions twinkled
around the country. ... For the first time, people of widely
differing views agreed: there is hope in our land.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>JOHNSON CITY, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Christmas Eve fire that killed 16
and injured dozens at a high-rise retirement home might have been
worse if so many people hadn't been away for the holiday,
authorities said Monday.
   Officials accounted for 10 of 11 residents who had been listed
as missing after the blaze at the 11-story John Sevier Retirement
Center. The 11th person is also believed to have been away at the
time, they said.
   ``I can't think of a worse time, on Christmas Eve,'' said P.C.
Snapp, mayor of this town of 40,000. ``On the other hand, it could
have been a good time because a number of people had gone to visit
relatives.''
   The blaze surged through the lower floors of the brick building,
sending thick smoke to the floors above. Residents of upper floors
waved flashlights and screamed for help from the windows of their
smoke-filled apartments.
   About 50 people were injured, including about 15 firefighters,
some of whom also suffered frostbite. Most were treated for smoke
inhalation and released. At least one person was seriously burned,
said Dan Blevins, spokesman for Northside Hospital.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>JACKSON, Wyo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Some advertisers promoting vacation spots
hundreds of miles from Wyoming have the power to move mountains.
   The picturesque Grand Teton and its sister mountains have been
used in ads for Amtrak, which doesn't run through Wyoming; and such
places as a resort in Montana and even a condominium in the heart
of the Rockies in Colorado.
   For the record, the Tetons have been standing firm in
northwestern Wyoming for eons.
   And while imitation may be the sincerest form of flattery, the
Jackson Hole Chamber of Commerce isn't happy to see the craggy
peaks plastered on brochures touting destinations that don't have a
view of the range even on a clear day.
   ``The Tetons are one of the most recognizable mountain ranges in
the world and we are more than a little miffed that our competitors
continue to use our assets to promote their areas,'' said Carol
Waller, the chamber's director of marketing. ``We are seriously
considering trademarking the Tetons _ I'm only half-joking.''
   While managers of those out-of-sight resorts responded with
shock or embarrassment when queried about their use of the Tetons,
none offered any apologies. Not even resort managers in Colorado,
which boasts of being home to the greatest skiing in the world.
</TEXT>

</DOC>