<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0125 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1812EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Panama-CivilAffairs     12-27 0394</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Civil Affairs,400</SECOND>
<HEAD>Army Reserves Looking For Panama Volunteers; Get Many</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSANNE M. SCHAFER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Military Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Army has been flooded with offers from
volunteers who want to go to Panama and help restore battered
public services, a spokesman said Wednesday.
   ``It's unbelievable,'' said Maj. Henry Fitts, a spokesman at the
U.S. Army Reserve Special Operations Command at Fort Bragg, N.C.
   ``Call it patriotism, call it boredom, call it what you will,
but we've had to set up a 24-hour operation just to screen the
volunteers,'' Fitts said.
   The Pentagon already has dispatched 25 reserve civil affairs
specialists along with 107 active duty experts to Panama.
   Civil affairs specialists act as liaison officers between the
military and the civilian government to help re-establish public
services disrupted by fighting, such as utilities and
transportation.
   Virtually all the Army's civil affairs specialists are in
reserve units, and the Pentagon paged those units for volunteers,
Fitts said.
   ``We've (in the reserves) been requested by the (regular)
Special Operations Command to augment the active duty civil affairs
officers in their effort to rebuild and restore order in Panama,''
he said.
   The Army particularly sought specialists, such as engineers or
people familiar with transit systems or sanitation programs.
   So many have volunteered, Fitts said in a telephone interview,
that he's been unable to get a count.
   The number to be chosen to go to Panama probably will be ``in
the dozens, rather than hundreds, because we really need people
with specific talents,'' he said.
   Most people can be expected to put in about two weeks, but
regulations permit a tour of duty of up to 139 days, a bit less
than 20 weeks.
   In Florida, soldiers from the 361st Civil Affairs Bridgade in
Pensacola and a subordinate unit, the 478th Civil Affairs Company
in Perrine, near Miami, will leave Friday for Panama, said Maj. Tom
Bechtell, a member of the brigade.
   Lt. Col. Richard Randall, plans and operations officer of the
brigade, said his unit will ``help the government with certain
expertise our individuals have in banking, utilities, medical
(matters), public transportation, law enforcement and education.''
   The 361st trains in Panama every year and routinely works with
the civil government and U.S. military there, Randall said.
   About 25 percent of the Pensacola-based reservists and half of
those in Perrine speak Spanish, he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>