<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0150 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1504EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-BusCrashTrial 3rdLd-Writethru a0718 12-20 0543</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bus Crash Trial, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0718,0552</SECOND>
<HEAD>Defense in Bus Crash Says Vehicle's Manufacturer Was to Blame</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 6 grafs with deliberations under way. PICKS UP 8th
graf pvs, `Hildebrand and ...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHARLES WOLFE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CARROLLTON, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A jury today began deliberating whether
Larry Mahoney is guilty of murder for each of the 27 people killed
in a fiery 1987 collision between his pickup and a church bus.
   The jury received the case after Mahoney's lawyers contended in
closing arguments that the bus was unsafe and that the factory
worker is not responsible for the deaths. Prosecutor Paul
Richwalsky countered that bus safety was not the issue, adding,
``The apologies ... are too late. Now it's time to pay.''
   Mahoney is charged with 27 counts of murder, 12 of assault, 42
of wanton endangerment and one of drunken-driving in what
authorities have called the nation's deadliest alcohol-related
traffic accident.
   Twenty-four youngsters and three adults from a church group died
in the fire that engulfed the former school bus after Mahoney's
pickup rammed it on Interstate 71, five miles south of Carrollton,
on May 14, 1988.
   The chassis of the 1977 school bus was made by Ford Motor Co.
Mahoney's attorneys argued during his murder trial that the bus was
unsafe because of a vulnerable gas tank and combustible interior
materials.
   ``Somebody should pay for it,'' said Jack Hildebrand, one of
Mahoney's three attorneys. ``But Larry Mahoney should not have to
pay for something Ford Motor Company did.''
   Hildebrand and another defense attorney, William Summers, told
the jury that Mahoney was intoxicated and was driving on the wrong
side of the interstate. That caused the collision but not the fiery
deaths, they said.
   ``Larry has the rest of his life, every waking minute, to
remember this,'' Summers said. No one ``can do anything to punish
him worse.''
   The prosecutor argued that Mahoney's attorneys mounted an attack
on the safety of the school bus out of desperation because no one
could deny that Mahoney caused the crash.
   ``School buses don't have anything to do with it,'' Richwalsky
said. ``The elements of the alleged crime would be the same if
Mahoney had collided with a motorcycle or a family car.''
   The jury received instructions from Judge Charles Satterwhite on
Tuesday.
   Satterwhite gave the jury two alternatives to the 27 murder
charges _ second-degree manslaughter, punishable by five to 10
years in prison, and reckless homicide, punishable by one to five
years. Murder is punishable by 20 years to life.
   To convict the 36-year-old Mahoney of murder, the jury would
have to find that he had acted with ``extreme indifference to the
value of human life,'' Satterwhite told the panel.
   Richwalsky contended that Mahoney's actions _ driving drunk and
on the wrong side of a highway _ fit that description.
   The defense has claimed that Mahoney did not intentionally get
drunk and that the former school bus, manufactured by Ford and
Sheller-Globe Corp., was unsafe. Autopsies showed the fire, not the
crash, killed the victims.
   Satterwhite told jurors they would be sequestered, spending
nights in a motel under sheriff's guard, until reaching a verdict.
Once sequestered, jurors could not be released, even for Christmas,
the prosecutor said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>