<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1115EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Panama-Wounded 2ndLd-Writethru a0503 12-23 0571</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Wounded, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0503,0583</SECOND>
<HEAD>More Injured Arrive In Texas, Others Transferred to Bases</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: UPDATES throughout with more wounded soldiers arriving early
today in San Antonio, new figures for hospitalized, transfer of injured
to bases in Georgia and North Carolina. No pickup.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos SA1, SA3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SCOTT ROTHSCHILD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN ANTONIO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soldiers wounded in Panama kept a close watch
on events unfolding there and said they wanted to be back fighting
instead of spending Christmas in military hospitals.
   Army Chief of Staff Gen. Carl Vuono visited with the wounded men
Friday. He handed out 200 military decorations and told the men
President Bush was proud of what they had done.
   ``He wanted me to tell you and every other troop down here how
proud he is of each and every one of you for your sacrifice,''
Vuono said.
   More than 170 soldiers were being treated today at Wilford Hall
Medical Center and Brooke Army Medical Center, San Antonio military
hospitals. A sixth transport plane carrying 18 wounded arrived
about 2 a.m. today, said Kelly Air Force Base spokesman Frank
Weatherly.
   Some soldiers treated in San Antonio were flown Friday to bases
in Georgia and North Carolina. Fifty soldiers have been transferred
to other military hospitals or released back to their units.
   Alexis Pinero, 24, stationed in Fort Bragg, N.C., said Friday
that despite his injury _ a broken foot suffered during a paratroop
jump _ he and his buddies recovering from an assortment of wounds
wanted to return to Panama.
   ``Everybody on our ward would go back, it's a consensus,'' said
Pinero, of Raleigh, N.C., hospitalized at Brooke Army Medical
Center.
   ``I'm doing pretty good now. They're taking pretty good care of
us,'' said Pvt. Richard Turner Jr., 19, of DeSoto, Texas, who
suffered a concussion when a sniper's bullet grazed his helmet.
   Turner and the other servicemen in his ward have been constantly
watching television news reports about the fighting in Panama, said
his mother, Linda Turner _ except for a brief respite.
   ``Well, they watched a little smut thing on Showtime the other
night,'' she conceded.
   At Pope Air Force Base in North Carolina, 37 soldiers hurt in
Panama arrived from San Antonio late Friday. Three soliders were
seriously wounded, said Maj. Doug Foster, a spokesman at Fort Bragg.
   ``All were in good spirits when they arrived,'' he said. ``Most
of the soldiers are being treated for fragment wounds or small arm
wounds.''
   Other soldiers and their families were making plans to remain in
San Antonio through Christmas.
   Lee Olivera of Cincinnati, Ohio, visited his brother, Staff Sgt.
Louis Olivera, a 25-year-old who suffered bullet wounds to the
chest and head. The soldier's parents also were on the way to spend
Christmas with him.
   ``He did say that he wanted to go back _ I don't think that's
possible,'' the soldier's brother said.
   Air Force Capt. Peter Debusmann, commander of a C-141 transport
plane that brought 21 injured servicemen to Kelly Air Force Base,
said the soldiers aboard were in good spirits.
   ``They're just glad to be coming home, back to the States, and
home for Christmas. And they're worried that their parents are
worried about them,'' Debusmann said.
   As of today, 93 soldiers were being treated at Wilford Hall and
85 at Brooke Army. President Bush was to visit the wounded on New
Year's Eve, officials said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>