<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0205EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Italy-Priests     12-19 0867</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Italy-Priests,0895</SECOND>
<HEAD>Catholic Church Faces Life Without Guaranteed State Supplement</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY BETH SHERIDAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ROME (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In the past 20 years, Italy's Roman Catholic Church
has lost battles on divorce and abortion. Now it is facing a
challenge to its affluence as well as its influence.
   Starting Jan. 1, the Italian government will no longer provide a
guaranteed stipend to the church, ending a system that has been in
place in one form or another for 300 years.
   Instead, the government will create a special pool, made up of
.8 percent of tax revenues, or about $650 million.
   When filling out their tax returns in May, citizens can check
whether they want the money to go to the Catholic Church, other
churches or to the government for its social and cultural programs.
   ``We are moving toward self-sufficiency for the church,'' said
Monsignor Tino Marchi, president of the Italian bishops
conference's Institute for the Maintenance of Clergy. ``The
faithful were used to thinking that priests could be helped by
offerings but that the state would take care of them.''
   The development is the latest result of the revised concordat,
or church-state agreement, that took effect in 1985. The accord
abolished Catholicism as the state religion and reduced the
emphasis on religious instruction in public schools.
   The church hierarchy says it's glad at the cut off in government
funding, which sometimes made servants of the Lord feel more like
civil servants. But it is concerned about how the church will fare
relying on its often wayward flock.
   ``It's a new thing,'' said Archbishop Camillo Ruini,
secretary-general of the Italian bishops conference. ``Nine
Italians out of 10 don't know about it. It's a long road.''
   More than 90 percent of Italians are Catholics, but religious
practice has plunged in recent years as Italy has become more
wealthy and secular. Only about 25 percent of Italians regularly
attend Mass and the church was rebuffed in its efforts to ban
divorce and abortion in public referendums in 1974 and 1981.
   Still, Catholic leaders say, the church remains important for
Italians and is respected for its extensive social-service network
that aids the handicapped, the elderly, recovering drug addicts and
youth.
   ``Although many people don't go to church, they approve of the
responsibilities of the church, and understand that it must be kept
up,'' Ruini said in an interview.
   But the leadership is taking no chances. To promote the new
system, Catholic authorities have distributed more than 10 million
flyers in churches and hung up hundreds of posters.
   Catholic leaders have appealed to accountants to advise their
clients of tax-free deductions to the church, and a special insert
about the new system was published in Italy's top business
newspaper, Il Sole-24 Ore.
   But there is reason for concern.
   The church estimates it will need about $280 million a year to
take care of the 40,000 Italian priests. It hopes most of the money
will come from offerings to a central fund, which are
tax-deductible up to $1,500, starting with returns for 1989.
   However, the fund will probably raise less than $8 million in
its first year.
   The tax pool pie will be split according to the proportion of
check-offs each group gets. The Catholic Church hopes to use its
share for social services and maintainence of churches, in addition
to paying priests.
   Italy's small Jewish community, which has been self-financed,
chose not to receive money from the tax pool and is counting on
contributions.
   Marchi admits not all priests are happy about the new system.
   ``Like all changes, especially for those people of a certain
age, it can cause difficulty, unease,'' he said.
   Priest salaries in the past year, which were mostly paid out of
government funds, ranged from $680 to $1,240 a month, depending on
expenses, responsibility and age.
   Church officials say contributions have been steadily increasing
and they are counting on their information campaign. But they say
it is not easy to change a mentality that has existed for centuries.
   Convincing people to give is especially difficult in southern
Italy, where the church used to enjoy a wealth of possessions and
priests generally lived much better than their parishioners, who
were mostly poor.
   ``People have never been responsible for taking care of their
own parish,'' said the Rev. Giovanni Borrelli, who is in charge of
promoting the new finance system in the Naples area.
   ``Until the end of the last century, if one was doing well, or
had a well-paying job, people would say they `had a priest in the
house' _ it was a way of saying they had a significant source of
income.''
   The church in overwhelmingly Catholic Spain was shocked this
year to find that only 35 percent of taxpayers had chosen to check
off the Catholic Church to receive a tax fund like the one to be
set up in Italy.
   Italian officials say they expect to do better. They point out
that 96 percent of Italian parents made the choice to keep their
children in religion classes in public schools.
   ``I am not living this in a state of anxiety,'' Ruini said. ``In
Italy the church is seen well.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>