<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0033EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-RobotLove Bjt   12-25 0522</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Robot Love, Bjt,0542</SECOND>
<HEAD>Robot Has Long-Distance Affair</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto CX2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SHERA GROSS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHRISTOPHER, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Each month Jim Barclay's robot, Toby,
receives a love letter full of yearning from a mysterious
girlfriend as she travels the country.
   Nobody has seen the girlfriend called Jodi, but her letters
arrive about once a month bearing postmarks from all over.
Sometimes she even takes the robot along.
   Barclay, a practical joker himself, doesn't know who's behind
the elaborate scheme that began with the robot's arrival last
Christmas at the Rea Clinic in this southern Illinois town of 3,000.
   ``I don't want to know whose doing it,'' he said. ``I'm having a
ball out of it.''
   Barclay, a printer and maintenance worker at the clinic, said he
came to work one morning and found the foot-high, gold-toned,
plastic robot in his chair.
   An accompanying note read: ``Jim, maybe Toby can work the second
shift and help catch up. Santa.''
   Barclay said his wife, Margene, and each of the clinic's 50
employees denied any involvement. So began the string of 19 love
letters, gifts and even Toby's temporary disappearance.
   Every month to six weeks, another card comes to the clinic for
Toby, Barclay said.
   ``When we get a card everybody at the clinic gets excited,''
Barclay said recently.
   The letters have come from as far away as Eagle, Colo., and
Tampa, Fla.
   ``That one we got from Florida, it was a tear-jerker. I sat here
and tears came to my eyes. He was standing over there doing
nothing,'' Barclay said, nodding in Toby's direction in mock
disgust.
   Toby walks and plays a programmed message but doesn't do much
else around the shop, Barclay said.
   The postmarks give clues about Jodi's travels, but the gifts and
disappearances have confused him.
   Barclay came to work one morning and Toby was gone, replaced by
a note saying the robot was with Jodi. A week later, Barclay
arrived at work to find Toby back along with a note saying the
robot and Jodi had enjoyed a trip to Wisconsin. Wisconsin cheese in
the refrigerator was for Barclay, the note said.
   The intrigue continued in September when Jodi and Toby took off
to Wausau, Wis., and spent a week at the Marshfield Clinic, a
regional rural health center, Barclay said.
   When Toby reappeared, he was accompanied by a note from a Dr.
Paul Stamer declaring the robot to be in fine health.
   But employees at the health clinic said Stamer doesn't exist,
Barclay said.
   As Christmas approached, the Barclays nearly decided to take
Toby home because of concerns that Jodi would take him away for
good during the holiday weekend. They decided against it.
   ``We don't want to interfere with their love life,'' Barclay
said.
   Their trust was rewarded.
   In a Christmas card with the usual confessions of love from Jodi
and a message for Barclay to look in an old car at his home.
   Inside the car was a plaster elephant painted gold _ Barclay
collects toy elephants _ and a 15-pound ham with a tag wishing the
couple Merry Christmas from Jodi and Toby.
</TEXT>

</DOC>