<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0150 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 2247EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MobilDismissal     12-27 0759</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mobil Dismissal,0782</SECOND>
<HEAD>Documents: Mobil Attorneys Wanted to Shield Execs from Pollution
Consequences</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DANIEL J. WAKIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEWARK, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Attorneys for Mobil Oil Corp. wanted to
shield top executives from details of environmental problems at
chemical plants to protect them from legal action, according to
court papers filed in a lawsuit against the oil giant.
   The papers were filed in federal court here in a lawsuit against
the nation's second largest oil company by Valcar Bowman Jr. of
Riverdale, Ga., Mobil Chemical Co.'s former environmental affairs
manager.
   Bowman claims he was fired in April 1986 because he refused to
go along with a cover-up of pollution problems. Bowman had been the
division's second ranking environmental official.
   The court papers also quote a memorandum by a company lawyer as
saying attorney-client privilege can be used to keep documents out
of the hands of government agencies.
   The papers shed new light on wording changes sought by Mobil
lawyers in confidential reports about environmental conditions at
plants nationwide.
   Those reports, filed with the court, remain sealed. U.S.
District Judge Harold A. Ackerman unsealed them Friday but delayed
his order when Mobil said it would appeal.
   The company denies covering up pollution problems, argues that
the changes were minor and and contends that Bowman was fired in an
economic cutback.
   Ackerman ruled Dec. 11 that enough evidence existed for the case
to go to trial, denying Mobil's summary judgment motion. Briefs
submitted by both sides for the motion were released this week and
contain the disclosures.
   Mobil Chemical Co.'s then-environmental counsel, Winfred T.
Colbert, ``voiced concern'' in a 1985 memorandum about the
company's ``longstanding practice'' of distributing the
environmental reports to upper-level management, according to a
brief by Bowman's lawyer, Stephen B. Wiley.
   The memo concerns a report about the company's Jacksonville,
Ill., plant.
   ``I note that the report contains several admissions of
non-compliance, which in some cases are unavoidable,'' the memo
read. ``The principal concern I have in this regard relates to the
potential liability which can attach to all managers who receive
the report.''
   Colbert said only plant managers, Mobil environmental officials
and lawyers should see whole reports. Others would receive
summaries on a ``need-to-know basis.''
   ``This revised procedure will properly focus direct
responsibility for necessary actions at the plant level and
minimize the potential exposure of higher level management,'' the
brief quoted Colbert as writing.
   ``What Colbert said there, I think, is general lawyering,'' said
Mobil spokesman Allen Gray in New York, denying it was company
policy.
   Mobil Chemical Co.'s president, Art E. Biggs, wrote a letter at
about the same time that required line managers to report
``significant'' environmental problems to him, said the division's
general counsel, Ron Neill.
   Colbert ``wasn't trying to shield anybody from liability,''
Neill said, but was only making sure that responsibility for plant
operations was properly delegated.
   Bowman also charges that Mobil removed records from its
Bakersfield, Calif., plant, which was under scrutiny by
environmental officials, to keep the records out of regulators'
hands. The records were given to an outside attorney, Lawrence J.
Straw Jr., to ``cloak'' them in the attorney-client privilege, said
Wiley's brief.
   The brief cited a May 30, 1985, memo from another Mobil Chemical
lawyer, Charles S. Lindberg, to Bowman explaining that the
attorney-client privilege ``is much broader and receives greater
protection under the law than most of our company documents which
are not protected by legal privilege.
   ``In fact, it would be more difficult for any governmental
agency to obtain any of the information delivered to Mr. Straw than
it would for them to obtain that information from Mobil directly
under a subpoena,'' Lindberg wrote.
   ``I'm not going to excuse what Lindberg said,'' Gray commented,
calling the statement another example of ``lawyering.''
   He said all papers required by law to be at the Bakersfield
plant never left there. Two or three boxes of documents were sent
to Straw, but have never been subpoenaed, he said.
   As an example of alleged ``sanitizing'' of environmental reports
by lawyers, Bowman's brief refers to Colbert's Jacksonville memo.
   Colbert wanted the word ``fully'' placed before ``acquainted''
in the sentence, ``Plant personnel have not had time to become
acquainted with'' Superfund reporting procedures, according to
court papers.
   In a report about the Frankfort, Ill., plant, Colbert added
``Records do not indicate that'' to the sentence, ``the plant is
not consistently reporting excursions within five days of becoming
aware of the incident.''
   Mobil says the second ``not'' was accidental and that the other
two changes made the reports more accurate.
</TEXT>

</DOC>