<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0285 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1811EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-MeredithSale Bjt   12-22 0819</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Meredith Sale, Bjt,0845</SECOND>
<HEAD>Meredith-Burda to be Sold for About $570 Million</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEVEN P. ROSENFELD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   R.R. Donnelley &amp; Sons Co., the leading
commercial printer in North America, agreed Friday to buy the
Meredith-Burda printing business jointly owned by Meredith Corp.
and the Burda family of West Germany in a deal valued at about $570
million.
   Meredith, a Fortune 500 company that publishes Better Homes and
Gardens magazine and also has interests in television stations and
real estate, said it would use its share of the proceeds to
strengthen and expand its core businesses.
   ``It's a continuation of a trend that's been going on for some
time. The industry is consolidating,'' said Robert A. Dunlap, who
follows Donnelley for the New York Securities firm of Brown
Brothers Harriman &amp; Co.
   Analysts said the deal should benefit both companies.
   On the New York Stock Exchange Friday, Donnelley rose 87{ cents
to finish at $48.75 a share and Meredith jumped $3.37{ to $35.25 a
share.
   Donnelley said it would pay $487.5 million in cash, to be
divided between Meredith, and Franz and Frieder Burda of West
Germany. It also agreed to assume $80 million in Meredith-Burda
debt.
   The deal, subject to government antitrust review, is expected to
be closed early in 1990, the companies said. Jack Rehm, the
president of Meredith, said he anticipated no objections on grounds
of restraint of trade.
   Donnelley, based in Chicago, accounts for an estimated 6.4
percent of the $50 billion U.S. commercial printing market and
should expand its share to about 7 percent through the acquisition,
Dunlap said.
   Donnelley prints and binds many national publications, including
Time, Newsweek, TV Guide and Business Week. It also prints
telephone books, encyclopedias and school and religious books and
has about 25,000 employees at nearly 100 factories and offices in
the United States, Britain, Ireland, the Caribbean and Asia.
   In 1988, Donnelley earned $205.3 million on sales of almost $2.9
billion.
   Meredith-Burda, formed in 1969, generated $456.7 million in the
fiscal year ended June 30 and employs 3,205 people nationwide,
including about 1,100 in Des Moines. It has printing plants in Des
Moines; Newton, N.C.; Lynchburg, Va.; and Casa Grande, Ariz. Its
photo preparation centers are in Lynchburg and at Hickory and
Greensboro, N.C.
   Meredith-Burda also owns 40 percent of plants in Lynchburg and
at Greenfield, Iowa, where Siegwerk Inc. manufactures ink.
   Donnelley spokesman James Ratcliffe said there are no immediate
plans for cutbacks, although some sales and administrative
positions at Meredith-Burda may be eliminated in the future if they
overlap with Donnelley operations.
   ``We did not buy this to dismantle anything,'' Ratcliffe said in
a telephone interview.
   Meredith, which earned $33.2 million on revenue of $792 million
in the latest fiscal year, already had a working relationship with
Donnelley, which prints Meredith's Ladies' Home Journal and SAIL
magazines and several Meredith books. Rehm said Donnelley would be
printing other Meredith publications, the bulk of them at the Des
Moines plant.
   Rehm said Meredith officials began considering the sale of the
capital-intensive printing business early in 1989 and soon began
discussions with Donnelley.
   ``It's a solid financial decision for our stockholders,
employees, customers and communities,'' Rehm said. ``Our long-term
goal and our vision for Meredith Corporation is to create growth
through acquisitions and new product development. With this
decision, we can focus our energy, our skills and our capital
resources on our core businesses.''
   Rehm said Meredith was receiving about twice the amount it had
been carrying on its books as the value of the operation.
   He told reporters that no decisions had been made on how to
spend the money, which will be divided about evenly between
Meredith and the Burdas. But he noted that acquisition
opportunities in the media business tended to surface at a moment's
notice.
   ``If a television station came up in the foreseeable future and
if we thought it was a good fit at the right price, we'd probably
look at it,'' Rehm said.
   He also said the company was exploring launching new magazines
as well as acquiring existing publications.
   ``I think everybody makes out on this deal,'' Dunlap said.
   Dunlap said Meredith gets out of a business that has had a low
return on investment and gets some needed cash for its other
operations. He said Donnelley gets plants that fill voids in its
operations.
   John Walter, chairman and president of Donnelley, said: ``The
acquisition of Meredith-Burda by Donnelley is an outstanding
opportunity for both parties. Meredith-Burda is a strong,
high-quality printer with an excellent customer base and a leading
market reputation. The fit with Donnelley's existing facilities is
remarkably good.''
   Cornelius Sewell, who follows the printing business for Argus
Research in New York, called Donnelley a consistent performer.
   Sewell said Donnelley is so broad-based that it can avoid the
damage that cyclical swings cause smaller printing operations.
   ``They're pretty smart guys,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>