<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1146EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania-Forces     12-23 0621</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Forces,0639</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romanian Army Outnumbered by Security Troops</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIOREL URMA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After Nicolae Ceausescu took power in
Romania in 1965, the armed forces saw their role diminished and
watched the dreaded security forces receive the best equipment,
training and pay.
   The entire army of 180,000 men turned against Ceausescu in the
popular revolt that ousted him Friday and was fighting some of the
most loyal pro-Ceausescu security forces, Bucharest radio reported.
Other ``Securitate'' troops were reported to have gone over to the
army.
   While territorial defense was emphasized under Ceausescu,
defense expenditures were reduced, and the government greatly
expanded the army's role on building sites and in ``militarized'
sectors of the mismanaged economy, such as the mines and
coal-fueled power stations.
   The army also was used in Romanian agriculture and on
Ceausescu's pet projects, such as the the Black Sea Canal, which
turned out to be unprofitable.
   ``After more than 20 years of Ceausescu's rule ... (the army of)
Romania has the oldest and poorest equipment of any East European
state, and it is not maintained at high standards,'' Thomas O.
Cason said in a 1982 study of East European military forces
published in Wilmington, Del.
   Ceausescu had reason to distrust his army, after several
generals plotted to overthrow him in 1984.
   Romanian officials have said privately that the generals were
apprehended, killed and their bodies were thrown from a helicopter
into the Black Sea.
   Knowledgeable Romanians say the army is outnumbered by specially
trained and recruited security troops numbering some 700,000 men,
equipped with the most sophisticated warfare and paid three times
the average Romanian's monthly salary of about $300.
   ``The army is nothing compared with the degree of training of
these shock troops, which Ceausescu disguised as military units
wearing almost the same kind of uniform,'' Mirceas Stoica, a
professor of law at Bucharest University, told The Associated Press
after fleeing to Hungary last week.
   He said he learned this from a friend who is a security colonel
and from other sources.
   They said Ceausescu kept thousands of these troops in each of
Romania's 40 counties, and that he had several security force
divisions around Bucharest ``ready to intervene.'' They were
equipped with tanks, helicopters and guns.
   ``Ceausescu grew increasingly security-conscious over the years,
as the number of public protests to his harsh rule intensified,''
said Mihnea Berindei, an exile historian living in Paris.
   Army officers, speaking on Bucharest radio, said Friday they
discovered a network of secret tunnels running for 2.5 miles
between the party headquarters and Ceausescu's new palace ``Casa
Republicii'' in downtown Bucharest, up to a lake in the northern
part of the city.
   Entrances to some tunnels were masked by nondescript panels in
subway stations. The tunnels contained weapons caches and were used
only by Ceausescu's most loyal security troops, the radio said.
   The radio appealed repeatedly to architects who had been
involved in building such secret caches to come forward and divulge
the layout to the army and other forces behind the anti-Ceausescu
revolt.
   Romania for many years has been one of the main training camps
for Arab and African commandos trained in guerrilla warfare, as
Ceausescu formed cordial relations with PLO leader Yasser Arafat
and Libyan leader Moammar Gadhafi.
   Several years ago, Ceausescu ``borrowed'' Arab terrorist troops
as a security precaution, including Arafat's body guard of about 50
men, Stoica said.
   A Romanian radio announcer Saturday appealed to army units and
the population to help defend the national radio station against
``Arab troops.''
   ``Foreign mercenaries arrived by helicopter during the night.
They were prepared in a secret training camp near Bucharest by the
biggest enemy of our nation, Ceausescu,'' the announcer said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>