<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0034EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AlaskaVolcano 4thLd-Writethru a0810 12-18 0802</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Alaska Volcano, 4th Ld - Writethru, a0810,0816</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rescuers Reach Trapped Family ^Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 12th , `The
10,197-foot...,' to give background on Thursday burst from Mount St. Helens.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL JENKINS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rescuers on Sunday evacuated a family
that had been trapped at a lodge in the shadow of Redoubt Volcano
as it continued to belch ash and steam over much of south-central
Alaska.
   The volcano, which had been fuming and sputtering in a
continuous low-level eruption since Saturday afternoon, erupted
with greater force Sunday afternoon, the U.S Geological Survey
said. An ash plume was spotted by an airline pilot at 27,000 feet,
drifting northeast toward Anchorage.
   Shortly before the eruption, pilots of Alaska Helicopters Inc.
evacuated Nancy Jones, her husband and 2-year-old son from Tuwalaka
Lodge, 10 miles south of the volcano. For two days ash clouds and
poor weather had stymied efforts to reach the Joneses, who are
caretakers at the lodge.
   Mrs. Jones said Sunday she and her family could see little of
the volcano until Saturday, when fog and snow near the peak cleared.
   ``We could see the big billow going up into the air,'' she said.
``We watched it all day. The wind was blowing it away from us. We
didn't get too much ash.
   ``It was a little bit worrisome,'' she said. ``We were worried
the top might blow off our way and give us a bad time that way.''
   She said she was unsure whether her family would return to the
lodge if the volcano quieted.
   ``We really like it out there; it's beautiful,'' she said.
``It's a perfect place to spend the winter, barring the volcano.''
   The family was taken to Drift River, a petroleum facility 20
miles southwest of the lodge, said Byron Wallace of Alaska
Helicopters. ``They're at Drift River now, but when they'll get
back to town we're not sure,'' he said.
   Another caretaker couple, Mike and Sandy Coulter, remained at
Big River Lake Lodge nearly 30 miles north of the volcano, though
they had reported hunks of pumice as large as softballs falling on
their roof Saturday.
   They reported no serious problems and intended to stay, said the
lodge's owner, Dennis Branham.
   The 10,197-foot volcano, located about 115 miles southwest of
Anchorage and quiet since the '60s, started erupting Thursday. Ash
drifted as far south as Oregon. It had been expected to reach
California or Arizona by Sunday, but officials said there were no
reports of ash reaching those states.
   The continent's most notorious volcano, Mount St. Helens in
Washington state, also showed signs of life on Thursday after more
than three years of silence. The volcano issued a small burst of
steam, gas and ash, but scientists said an eruption did not appear
to be imminent.
   Alaska Volcano Observatory geologist Steve Brantley said two
other pilots reported a strong sulfur smell between 15,000 and
19,000 feet, about 25 miles west of Anchorage.
   ``Given the wind direction, it is certainly possible we'll get
some ash fallout here in Anchorage,'' Brantley said. ``But that
depends on the volume of ash that erupted, whether there is enough
of it to be carried by the winds this far.
   ``The earthquake activity at the mountain continues at
significant levels and does not show a trend toward increasing or
decreasing strength, or vigor.''
   Before Sunday afternoon's eruption, the USGS described the
amount of ash sent up this weekend as ``low to moderate,''
significantly less than Friday, when Redoubt had its largest
eruption since emerging from a 23-year dormancy.
   Haze from the volcano on Saturday drifted across Anchorage,
Alaska's largest city with more than 200,000 people, triggering
power outages, health alerts and disrupting air traffic. At midday
Sunday, snow was falling with no ash apparent in the city.
   Prior to Saturday, fallout had been swept past Anchorage but
blanketed smaller communities such as Talkeetna and Delta Junction
to the north. The Kenai Peninsula south of Anchorage also had
escaped the ash until Saturday, when the peninsula towns of
Soldotna and Nikiski got hit.
   The ask was disrupting life in a state heavily dependent on air
travel. Daily deliveries of newspapers flown from Anchorage and
Fairbanks were halted Saturday, and some teachers from schools in
outlying villages found themselves stranded in Barrow, unable to
get flights out for the start of Christmas vacations.
   The Anchorage International Airport was open Sunday, but service
remained spotty, with some airlines grounding their aircraft and
others offering limited service. Some businesses covered sensitive
equipment for fear ash would filter into buildings.
   The ash in the sky over Anchorage during the weekend came at a
time when daylight is in short supply: The city is so far north
that it gets only about 5{ hours of light at this time of year.
</TEXT>

</DOC>