<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0003EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-SouthAfrica     12-26 0788</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-South Africa,0807</SECOND>
<HEAD>100 Days Into de Klerk Presidency, Optimism Seems Contagious</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Tuesday AMs report.</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID CRARY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   There's still doubt whether
President F.W. de Klerk will personally oversee the end of
apartheid, but his performance since his inauguration has raised
hopes higher than ever for peaceful change.
   Even the white-run government's most militant opponents
acknowledge a dramatic shift in mood since P.W. Botha quit the
presidency. They say de Klerk's conciliatory moves resulted from
pressure rather than conviction, but many anti-apartheid leaders
now believe _ for the first time _ that the government sincerely
wants to negotiate with them.
   ``Exit a president named P.W., to be replaced by one named F.W.
Remarkable what a difference that one letter made,'' wrote The
Weekly Mail, an anti-apartheid newspaper, in its year-end issue.
   ``Suddenly the logjam seemed to break. Good intentions twinkled
around the country. ... For the first time, people of widely
differing views agreed: there is hope in our land.''
   Walter Sisulu, a leader of the outlawed African National
Congress freed by de Klerk in October, said in a remarkably
optimistic Christmas message that he had reason to hope for
``relaxation of tension'' throughout South Africa in the coming
year.
   De Klerk took over as acting president in mid-August after
winning a power struggle with Botha. Even before his inauguration
Sept. 20, two weeks after general elections, de Klerk made his mark
by approving the first mass anti-government marches in decades.
   He marks 100 days from the inauguration on Thursday.
   Since his inauguration, in the words of Johannesburg political
writer Peter Fabricius, de Klerk ``has been a blur of movement,
making a major announcement almost every other day, unraveling the
security establishment, going some way to unbanning the ANC,
consulting a vast spectrum of political figures.''
   Among those consulted was the world's best-known political
prisoner: African National Congress leader Nelson Mandela. The Dec.
13 meeting at de Klerk's Cape Town office was seen as further proof
that Mandela's release is inevitable, probably before de Klerk
opens the new Parliament on Feb. 1.
   During Botha's 11 years in power, the ANC was depicted as a
communist-led terrorist group that had no right to enter
negotiations unless it formally renounced violence.
   De Klerk, by meeting Mandela and unconditionally freeing Sisulu,
has begun the process of acknowledging the guerrilla movement's
legitimacy. The government now says it will talk with any group
committed to peaceful solutions _ the demand for renunciation of
violence has been dropped.
   Seeking to remove obstacles to negotiations, de Klerk has
ordered the abolition of whites-only beaches, proposed repeal of
the law that allows segregated local facilities, and hinted that
the state of emergency imposed in 1986 will be lifted.
   James Selfe, an official of the anti-apartheid Democratic Party,
said de Klerk _ despite a past reputation as a conservative _ has
proven vastly different from previous National Party leaders.
   ``It might even be that the man had an ideological change of
heart after coming into office,'' Selfe said.
   De Klerk has vowed to end discrimination and negotiate a new
constitution that would extend political rights to South Africa's
28 million blacks. But he remains wedded to the concept of racial
groups, and his critics believe he will balk at any steps that
jeopardize the power held by the 5 million whites.
   ``In the process (of defending white control), de Klerk is even
prepared to put apartheid in jeopardy,'' said Fikile Bam, a legal
aid director in Port Elizabeth.
   Wrote The Weekly Mail's editor, Anton Harber: ``By now, de Klerk
has done enough to convince most people that he is sincere in
wanting some form of change. ... However, few of these people are
certain he has the strength or the vision to carry through even
this limited vision.''
   The country's most powerful black moderate, Zulu leader
Mangosuthu Buthelezi, is less skeptical.
   ``There are now few who do not take the state president
seriously when he talks about bringing reform,'' Buthelezi said.
``1990 is probably the year in which the government is going to
strike out in the direction of establishing justice and equality
for all.''
   Perhaps de Klerk's most significant move was curbing the
influence of police and army commanders. He halved mandatory
military service for white men from two years to one, proposed
defense spending cuts, and scrapped a bureaucratic network through
which security force officers controlled black townships.
   ``His achievement has been to go a long way to civilianizing the
country again and creating a spirit of glasnost ... as a prelude to
the real challenge of thrashing out a true democracy,'' wrote
Fabricius, political correspondent for The Star newspaper.
</TEXT>

</DOC>