<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0205 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1658EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Japan-Imports 1stLd-Writethru f0203 12-28 0873</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Imports, 1st Ld-Writethru, f0203,0901</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Outlines `Unparalleled' Measures to Promote Imports</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 4 new grafs to UPDATE with further U.S. reax from
trade representative. Picks up 3rd graf pvcs, The trade...</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ERIC TALMADGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Government officials on Thursday outlined a package
of tax incentives, tariff eliminations and other measures aimed at
reversing past trade policies and making Japan an importing
powerhouse in the 1990s.
   Trade experts in the United States welcomed the plan as a sign
Japan has recognized it must import more goods. But they were
hesitant to comment on how much of an impact the program ultimately
might have on the availability of U.S. goods in Japan.
   Reacting to the Japanese announcement, U.S. Trade Representative
Carla Hills said, ``We applaud any efforts to open markets.'' But
she cautioned that U.S. officials would be watching for actual
results.
   ``The tax program appears to be quite complicated and we will
have to wait and see whether and how it affects importing
behavior,'' she said.
   The trade program comes as the United States is pressuring Japan
to remove what it considers impediments to free trade, which the
United States blames for worsening its huge foreign trade deficit.
   A report released by the Ministry of International Trade and
Industry called the package of import expansion measures _ which
will be submitted to Parliament early next year _ ``unparalleled in
history.''
   ``It is a 180-degree turnaround from the old (export-oriented)
policies of the 1960s,'' said Masahisa Naito, director general of
the ministry's International Trade Administration Bureau. ``We will
try to assure that imports, which are a latecomer into the Japanese
marketplace, will take root.''
   The report said MITI plans to boost the import-expansion related
budget to $50 million in fiscal 1990, which begins April 1, from
$13.5 million this fiscal year.
   The money would be used to finance a nationwide information
network and computer databank, promote trade missions and boost the
exchange of trade experts to act as ``match-makers'' for potential
exporters and importers.
   MITI also intends to eliminate tariffs on 1,004 items, and
reduce levies on four more. The value of imports of these items
currently totals $13 billion, the report said.
   The total package, Naito said, would cost the government $1
billion a year in lost taxes.
   The tariff-cutting measures are the first of their kind since
1986, when the government slashed levies on 1,800 items as part of
its market-opening ``action program.''
   Naito said the plan includes a tax cut for companies that import
10 percent more than their highest previous level, and an
additional depreciation rate of 10 percent to 20 percent on some
imported machinery and equipment.
   Retailers and wholesalers would be allowed to set aside 20
percent of the increased import value, tax-free, to be used for
marketing imported goods.
   The report said more than half of all capital goods, including
semiconductors and computers, qualify for import promotion under
the program. Other items covered include automobiles, electrical
appliances and sporting goods.
   The government also would offer $1.5 billion in loans and import
credits.
   In Washington, some trade experts said it could be too early to
determine how effective the plan would be once it actually was
implemented.
   ``I think we should welcome this as recognition by Japan that
there is a problem,'' said Ronnie Goldberg, senior vice president
at the U.S. Council for International Business. ``But whether it's
as good as it sounds, I really don't know.
   ``In the past there has been less than what met the eye coming
out of these kinds of initiatives,'' said Goldberg, whose group
represents U.S. businesses in international economic organizations.
   Willard M. Berry, vice president of the National Foreign Trade
Council, a lobbying group for U.S. companies, had a similar
reaction. ``Is this really market access? I can't say without
studying'' the plan.
   Naito said MITI expects the measures to eliminate discrepancies
between the costs of products in Japan and abroad, make the
Japanese distribution system more efficient, and lead to the
breakdown of the ``keiretsu'' system in which many Japanese
companies are clustered in tightly knit groups.
   All of those issues are on the table in the U.S.-Japan
``Structural Impediments Initiative'' trade talks.
   Naito said a government economic forecast for fiscal 1990
approved by the Cabinet on Thursday predicted a $3 billion decline
in Japan's trade surplus next year, from the current $81 billion to
$78 billion.
   ``This (prediction) reflects how sincere and convinced we are of
the effects these measures will generate,'' Naito said.
   He said the forecast was based on an estimated 10.3 percent
increase in imports in the coming year, bringing their total value
from $195 billion in fiscal 1989 to $215 billion.
   The government also estimated exports will grow from $276
billion to $293 billion next year, an increase of 6.2 percent, he
said.
   Naito said the Japanese government has realized the need to
drastically reduce its huge trade surplus, which has been roughly
$90 billion a year for the past three years.
   ``We believe that it is not appropriate for Japan to continue
with such a large trade surplus, and that if it does continue, the
preservation of the free trade system could become difficult,'' he
said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>