<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0130 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 2259EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-ColdRdp 2ndLd-Writethru a0634 12-23 1003</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cold Rdp, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0634, 2 Takes,1022</SECOND>
<HEAD>The Record Cold Wave Hits Florida, Utilities Ask For Conservation</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 3rd graf, `The National...' to UPDATE with
73 deaths blamed on cold; INSERTS 1 graf after 13th graf, `Authorities
closed ...' to UPDATE with Fla gov. asking Guard to help stranded motorists;
INSERTS 1 graf after 23rd graf, `Growers in ...' to UPDATE with estimate
of $100 million crop damage in Texas.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos RA1, RAC1, SA4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROGER PETTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Cold and snow burst into Florida on Saturday, threatening fruit
and vegetable crops, as Arctic air forced temperatures to more
record lows that had utilities and fuel companies scrambling to
keep up with demand.
   Three utilities in Texas had to institute ``rolling blackouts''
because they couldn't keep up with demand for power, with Houston
most seriously affected with 150,000 without service Saturday
afternoon. Other utilities asked customers to conserve power and
shut off service to some commercial clients, and heating oil and
propane were high priced and in short supply in some areas. Power
was also in short supply in Virginia and Florida.
   The National Weather Service reported 112 record or record-tying
lows, including 31 below zero at Yankton, S.D., the official
coldest spot in the Lower 48 states.
   The frigid weather has been blamed for the deaths of at least 73
people in 26 states since Dec. 15. The toll included 89-year-old
Arthur Howze, who was found dead of hypothermia Saturday lying on
the floor of his home in front of a small space heater, Lauderdale
County Coroner Marl Cobler said.
   Saturday's low of 26 degrees below zero at Topeka, Kan., was the
coldest there for any date since record-keeping began in 1887; the
previous record was 25 below in February 1899. Kansas City, Mo.,
had an all-time low of 23 below zero. The low of 2 below zero at
San Angelo, Texas, also was an all-time record. Thirteen Texas
cities posted record lows.
   Low-temperature records for the date also were set or tied in
Alabama, Arkansas, Connecticut, Delaware, Florida, Georgia,
Illinois, Indiana, Iowa, Kansas, Kentucky, Louisiana, Michigan,
Mississippi, Missouri, Nebraska, New Jersey, New York, North
Carolina, Ohio, Oklahoma, Pennsylvania, Rhode Island, South
Carolina, South Dakota, Tennessee, Vermont, Virginia, West Virginia
and the District of Columbia.
   But temperatures in many areas were not quite so low as Friday,
and a change was edging in from the West.
   Jordan, Mont., had a low Saturday of 31, compared with 45 below
zero just two days earlier, thanks to Chinook winds blowing down
the eastern slopes of the Rockies. At Cut Bank, Mont., on Friday,
the temperature rose from 11 below at 11 a.m. to 36 above at noon.
   Temperatures also rose dramatically Saturday in western South
Dakota when a warm front moved through. By 10 a.m., Lemmon, which
had dropped to 33 below zero during the week, had a temperature of
37 above zero. Rapid City, which had a record low of 29 below zero
Friday, reached 44 above zero by early afternoon Saturday.
   Snow closed the airport at Wilmington, N.C. ``We've had 10 to 12
inches, but snow drifts are as high as 3 feet,'' said Chuck
Holtzinger of the weather service in Wilmington.
   Two inches of snow fell overnight on the coast of South
Carolina, and inland Columbia was forecast to have its first white
Christmas since 1935. Snow also fell on parts of southern Georgia.
   The airport at Savannah, Ga., also closed, because of ice and
small snowdrifts, said airport police Officer Lewis Stamper.
   The Florida Panhandle cities of Pensacola, Tallahassee,
Apalachicola, Milton and Crestview were whitened by snow overnight,
and 2 inches were forecast for Jacksonville, according to the
National Weather Service. Flurries were expected as far south as
Miami.
   Authorities closed icy roads and bridges Saturday across
northern Florida, and warned drivers to stay at home. Saturday's
low in Pensacola was 18 degrees. Tallahassee and Jacksonville both
had 31 degrees.
   Ice halted traffic on Interstate 75 between Gainesville and the
Georgia line, prompting Gov. Bob Martinez to order the National
Guard and state agencies to find shelter for stranded travelers,
Martinez spokesman Brian Ballard said.
   The airports in Jacksonville and Gainesville closed Saturday
because of ice-covered runways and several flights in and out of
Tallahassee were canceled. ``We're taking it hour-by-hour,'' said
Ron Beason, Tallahassee manager for USAir.
   ``People can't get anywhere if they wanted to, so they might as
well just stay home,'' said sheriff's spokesman Asa Higgs in
Jacksonville, a city of bridges.
   The Coast Guard rescued 27 hunters and fishermen from bayous and
marshes in southern Louisiana, Texas and Mississippi between 7 a.m.
Friday and Saturday evening, said Petty Officer Gene Maestas. One
fisherman near death from exposure told rescuers in Mississippi his
boat sank Dec. 20, Maestas said.
   In New Orleans, 98 fires, several of them major and most
probably caused by portable heaters, broke out between noon Friday
and noon Saturday, said fire department Capt. Bob Whitman.
   ``Pipes are frozen all over town,'' said Joe Giglio, a plumber
in Shreveport, La. At Complete Plumbing, Sewer and Drain Service in
the New Orleans suburb of Jefferson, 350 people called during the
first six hours of business Saturday, but four of the business's 12
plumbers couldn't get their cars started, said secretary Cynthia
Peterson.
   The cold frightened Florida farmers and citrus growers who
suffered $3 billion in damages during hard freezes in 1983 and 1985.
   Must of the citrus crop was still on the trees.
   ``We've done everything we can to protect it. We've watered it
down, got wind machines set up and flash pots fueled up and ready
to light if need be,'' said Ben Abbitt, general manager of the
Haines City Citrus Growers Cooperative, representing 7,000 acres of
citrus groves.
   ``If it gets cold enough long enough, we've got a disaster,''
said William Moon, sales manager for Zellwin Farms, which has
everything from carrots and lettuce to parsley and radishes in the
ground in northwestern Orange County.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>