<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0113 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1617EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-Scene     12-21 0681</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Scene,690</SECOND>
<HEAD>Snipers Shooting at U.S. Soldiers in Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDITOR'S NOTE: Steven Komarow is a member of the Pentagon media pool
that accompanied U.S. troops into Panama.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEVEN KOMAROW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Roving bands of Noriega loyalists
``getting their last licks in'' shot from the rooftops, and the
U.S. ambassador predicted life in Panama will continue to be
dangerous for some time.
   A continuing firefight prevented a helicopter from dropping off
a small U.S. media contingent at Patilla Airport. The chopper
touched down briefly but was waved off.
   Reporters saw American soldiers pressed behind concrete walls
and running between buildings near the control tower. Officials
said there were snipers on rooftops in the area.
   Military officials of the Southern Command confirmed that a
journalist had been killed near the Marriott Hotel, but could not
say immediately who it was.
   However, Spanish ambassador Tomas Lozano said Juan Antonio
Rodriquez, a photographer for Spain's largest newspaper, El Pais,
was killed Thursday during a cross fire between U.S. troops in the
hotel parking lot.
   Troops from the 82nd Airborne Division freed 29 U.S. citizens
and 35 foreign nationals from the Marriott, where they had been
trapped for 36 hours since the military operation began early
Wednesday, military officials said.
   U.S. Ambassador Arthur Davis, back in Panama after a seven-month
absence, predicted there would be retaliation from troops loyal to
Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega, who was ousted by U.S. forces.
   ``I think this is a very difficult time for security because of
retaliation,'' Davis said.
   The ambassador left Panama in May, the day after Noriega voided
elections observers said he lost. Davis said he was bringing an
economic recovery proposal to Panama's new leaders, including the
$700 million in assets freed by President's Bush's decision to lift
economic sanctions.
   The sporadic gunfire in Panama was attributed by U.S. military
officials to roving bands of Noriega loyalists ``getting their last
licks in,'' rather than to fighting between Noriega forces and
American troops.
   Panamanian civilian leaders had wanted Panamanian forces, not
those from the United States, to oust Noriega. But John Bushnell,
the U.S. charge d'affaires, said that after a failed coup Oct. 3,
``there was a feeling that, well, there weren't many more
Panamanians left with guns that might do it, so it was becoming a
hopeless situation.''
   ``They never said it so many words, `We wish you would really
send the 82nd Airborne to do it,' but they clearly indicated their
frustration that if we didn't, the situation was just going to go
on and get worse,'' Bushnell said.
   The new leaders' main concern, he said, was that if Noriega were
shot, another Panamanian Defense Force colonel might take his place.
   Indeed, it was by pretending that Noriega had been killed, U.S.
soldiers bluffed Panamanian soldiers into freeing two American
women held hostage more than six hours in an airport terminal.
   Mary Rebhan, 24, of Hollywood, Fla., and Tara King, 25, of
Dallas, told reporters they were used as shields by 30 armed
Noriega loyalists who holed up in a sweltering customs room at Omar
Torrijos International Airport when American forces moved in.
   The two women had gone to the airport Tuesday evening to pick up
Rebhan's brother, flying in for her wedding at the end of the month.
   ``They had us in choke holds for most of the time,'' Rebhan said.
   ``They made us kneel down and held guns to my back and to her
head,'' King said.
   American troops began to arrive in force to take over the
airport, but the Panamanians held them off with the women.
   ``For six hours they made us keep shouting, `Go away. We're
Americans. They're going to kill us and the children if you
come,''' Rebhan said.
   Just before dawn, the Americans set a deadline of 6:30 a.m. for
the men to surrender and told them they were surrounded and that
Noriega was already dead. In fact, Noriega's whereabouts was not
known.
   The Panamanians gave up, leaving the room with the women held in
front of them.
</TEXT>

</DOC>