<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1212EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BusCrashTrial 1stLd-Writethru a0498 12-19 0530</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bus Crash Trial, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0498,0540</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prosecution Attacks Mahoney Defense Theories As Trial Nears End</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs to UPDATE with today's testimony; PICKS UP
7th graf, pvs, `Mahoney, a ...'; DELETES 11th graf, `Later Monday, ...'
to conform.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHARLES WOLFE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CARROLLTON, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The driver accused in a collision that
killed 27 people on a church bus gulped down a vodka drink shortly
before the crash, a witness testified.
   Kelly Osborne, testifying for the prosecution Monday, ``blew
away'' defense attorneys' argument that Larry Mahoney was tricked
into getting drunk, said Special Prosecutor Paul Richwalsky.
   Mahoney ``just picked up the cup ... and he just drank it
straight down,'' Osborne testified. ``He coughed a couple of times.
I figured it was just because he had drank it so quick.''
   Later Monday, William Boehly, a statistician for the National
Highway Traffic Safety Administration, said there was never a
comparable disaster with a school bus and that no child had died
from a fire aboard a school bus since 1975.
   Rebuttal testimony continued today, with an auto safety
consultant for the defense disputing the prosecution's contention
that the bus was safe.
   Byron Bloch of Potomac, Md., testified that school buses were
safe only from Boehly's ``narrow statistical perspective.'' ``It
would be erroneous to conclude that his data rubber-stamp the
accident bus as a safe bus,'' said Bloch.
   Mahoney, 36, is accused of causing the nation's worst
drunken-driving accident: on May 14, 1988, when he drove his pickup
truck on the wrong side of Interstate 71 five miles south of
Carrollton, striking the bus.
   The case was expected to go to the jury on Wednesday.
   Mahoney, a factory worker, is charged with 27 counts of murder
for the 24 children and three adults; 12 counts of first-degree
assault, representing the most severely injured survivors; 42
counts of wanton endangerment for other survivors and motorists who
dodged his pickup on the wrong side of the divided highway; and one
count of drunken driving.
   The bus, a 1977 model built by Ford Motor Co. and Sheller-Globe
Corp., was owned by the Radcliff First Assembly of God church in
Hardin County, 100 miles southwest. The victims had been on a
church outing to an amusement park near Cincinnati.
   Prosecution testimony Monday began with Osborne, who said
Mahoney had asked him for the ``mixed drink'' of vodka and Sprite
that he downed at the home of Jay Gibson, Osborne's neighbor.
   Hildebrand and other defense attorneys disparaged Osborne's
testimony, pointing out that he failed to mention vodka _ he only
talked of Mahoney drinking beer _ in at least three interviews with
investigators on both sides.
   Autopsies showed the 27 died of smoke inhalation.
   Eugene Sober, a fire safety engineer for the National
Aeronautics and Space Administration, testified for the defense
last week that many of the victims could have survived if the bus'
seats had been fire resistant.
   But Hugh T. Spencer, a University of Louisville chemical
engineering professor and accident consultant, said the victims
were doomed from the instant that fuel from the ruptured gas tank
ignited.
   ``It was over at that point,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>