<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0533EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-RetirementHomeFire     12-27 0338</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Retirement Home Fire,0350</SECOND>
<HEAD>Residents of Retirement Home Trying to Cope in Blaze's Aftermath</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JOHNSON CITY, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For six months, Brian L. Cozad had
lived with and cared for his grandmother. On Christmas Eve, he died
with her in a high-rise retirement home fire that killed 16 and
injured dozens.
   Cozad, 29, who returned to Johnson City last summer after
working in Florida, found his grandmother in failing health and
moved in with her at the John Sevier Retirement Center.
   His 79-year-old grandmother, Carman L. Baughan, a retired
bookkeeper, suffered from cancer and emphysema.
   ``She was bedfast and on oxygen,'' said Baughnie Brumit, the
woman's daughter and Cozad's mother. ``For the past six weeks, he
had more or less waited on her hand and foot.''
   ``They were very close and she was getting sicker,'' Mrs. Brumit
said. ``He was very caring where she was concerned.''
   While authorities continued investigating the cause of the fire
in the 11-story center, building residents tried to deal with their
feelings about the Christmas Eve disaster.
   ``It breaks me up to talk about it,'' said Herman Rankin, who
had lived in the center for six months.
   Mental health professionals have volunteered their time to
counsel survivors, said Jane Harris, a disaster worker with the Red
Cross.
   Red Cross officials said some people have been so upset, they
have not been eating.
   ``I've been torn up about it,'' said Duaine Hampton, an 11-year
resident.
   Rankin and Hampton were among 23 people from the center staying
at a hotel. Forty-five others are staying with relatives, Red Cross
officials said Tuesday.
   Paul Souder, an assistant to Fire Chief Doug Buckles, said
investigators do not suspect arson.
   The fire was the second fatal fire in the center in two months.
In October, a 76-year-old resident died of smoke inhalation, but
all residents were evacuated.
   Firefighters quickly extinguished the October blaze through an
internal piping system that brought water through the building.
   By the time firefighters arrived Sunday night, the fire was out
of control.
</TEXT>

</DOC>