<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0136 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1358EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Panama-Eyewitness 1stLd-Writethru a0701 12-20 0585</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Eyewitness, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0701,0600</SECOND>
<HEAD>RETRANSMITTING a0701 to restore 1st Ld - Writethru designation.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Precede BOSTON</HEAD>
<HEAD>Witnesses Report Seeing Bodies, Heavy Damage in Area of Noriega HQ</HEAD>
<HEAD>LEADS with 9 grafs with other witness' account; PICKS UP 4th graf
pvs, `Backalt, a ...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EVE EPSTEIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.S. attack in Panama City early today left many civilians
dead in the streets and touched off a fire that leveled a slum area
around a Panamanian Defense Forces stronghold, witnesses said.
   U.S. troops in helicopters warned townspeople in Panama's
capital of the impending attack, assuring them by loudspeaker that
the soldiers ``didn't have a problem with the government,'' said
one witness.
   The witnesses spoke to reporters in Boston by telephone.
   ``They burned everything down,'' Manuel Backalt said in an
interview from a Salvation Army office near the Defense Forces
headquarters where he fled with his wife and three children. ``I
see plenty people dead in the street.''
   He said the bodies _ he did not know how many _ were mainly
members of the dignity battalions, civilian paramilitary groups
loyal to Noriega.
   Speaking through an interpreter, Rolando Diaz, 32, who also took
refuge in the Salvation Army office, said there were warnings in
the night of the coming attack.
   ``Before they started to bomb, they warned (those in the area of
Panamanian Defense Forces headquarters) to come out,'' he said.
``They were shouting down over the PA system saying ... they didn't
have a problem with the government.''
   At that point residents of the slum area surrounding the
headquarters, a section of mostly wooden homes, headed into the
streets, he said.
   ``They came out when they heard the announcement, and American
soliders led them to a neighborhood church,'' Diaz said. He said
the American soldiers moved in as he was heading to the church.
During the attack a fire began, destroying the area, he said.
   Backalt, a self-employed stove repairman, said he was sleeping
when he heard gunfire. He said his house caught fire, and he and
his family went out into the street. None of his family was injured.
   As they walked the streets, he said, they saw a helicopter
crash. He said he didn't know if it was an American or Panamanian
helicopter.
   Allan Wiltshire, head of the Salvation Army office, said Backalt
was one of about 40 people near the office who were looking for
assistance. He said it would be difficult to care for those
displaced and injured in the attack.
   ``They want a place to stay because they are all burnt out. It's
mounting up,'' he said.
   Wiltshire said pro-Noriega forces were commandeering cars
throughout the morning from people driving during the attack.
   ``They say, `We're the police. We need your car,''' he said.
   His wife, Marjorie, said they saw several families scurrying
about with their possessions.
   ``They were carrying TVs and their belongings on their heads,''
she said. ``We're just about to get some meals cooked so we can
service them.''
   The Salvation Army office is about two miles from Fort Amador,
an American base, and is near the headquarters of the Panama
Defense Forces.
   Wiltshire's daughter, Avonnie, said she was awakened by the
sound of shooting.
   ``I thought it was firecrackers. We realized after that it was a
lot of gunfire,'' she said. ``We tried to stay away from the
windows and doors.''
   The Wiltshires said the Armed Forces radio station broadcast
warnings throughout the early morning, advising people stay indoors.
</TEXT>

</DOC>