<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0101 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1552EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-FlightCapital     12-28 0568</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Flight Capital,0581</SECOND>
<HEAD>Swiss Banks' Role Questioned Again After Ceausescu, Noriega</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LORENZ WOLFFERS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BERN, Switzerland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Whenever authoritarian rulers are
toppled, the question invariably arises: What about their Swiss
bank accounts?
   The role of Swiss banks, traditional havens of capital from
other countries, has prompted criticism following the recent
ousters of Romanian dictator Nicolae Ceausescu and Gen. Manuel
Antonio Noriega of Panama. Both are alleged to have stashed
personal fortunes in Switzerland.
   ``Once more, the reputation of the Swiss financial center is
being dragged through the mud,'' said the Geneva newspaper Tribunbe
de Geneve on Thursday.
   Sergio Salvioni, a Swiss lawyer representing the Philippine
government in its efforts to recover Ferdinand Marcos' funds, said,
``If this continues, (the Swiss) will be considered as ...
receivers of stolen goods.''
   The government, concerned about its image, swiftly slapped a
freeze on any accounts Ceausescu may hold, even without waiting for
a formal request by the new Romanian leadership. It also responded
immediately to a Washington request to block assets linked to
Noriega.
   But tracking down the funds won't be enough. If similar cases in
the past set a pattern, a long and complicated legal battle is
likely before any assets are repatriated. And estimates of their
size vary widely.
   Ceausescu, according to Romanian exile sources, is believed to
have transferred $400 million, much of it in gold, to Switzerland
during his reign. The Romanian National Bank asked all countries to
freeze any Ceausescu accounts.
   Ceausescu had denied that any such accounts exist. Credit
Suisse, one of the two Swiss banks that received the freeze order,
has said it had no evidence of Ceausescu funds. The other, Union
Bank, declined comment, citing banking secrecy rules.
   Noriega's alleged accounts might be easier to come by because
the U.S. request for assistance names the banks where funds are
suspected. U.S. Justice Department spokesman David Runkel said
Noriega was thought to have transferred at least $10 million into
various accounts in Europe.
   In both cases, Swiss reaction was as prompt as it was following
the ousters in 1986 of Marcos and of Haiti's Jean-Claude Duvalier.
But efforts by new leaders to recover the allegedly ill-gotten
wealth drag on.
   Assets held in Switzerland by Marcos and his associates are
estimated by the Manila government at hundreds of millions of
allegedly ill-gotten dollars. They remain frozen since 1986 pending
completion of complex proceedings.
   Lawyers for the Marcos family filed appeals at virtually every
level so that a final decision is likely to have to come from the
Federal Tribunal, the Swiss supreme court. Last week, however, an
initial $2.3 million returned to Manila.
   No appeal was filed in the proceedings concerning Duvalier
assets, suggesting that only minor amounts were involved. In
November, the supreme court formally granted legal assistance to
the Haitian authorities. But so far there have been no word of any
funds being repatriated.
   In 1974, the military leaders who overthrew Emperor Haile
Selassie of Ethiopia claimed that he had transferred $15 billion
abroad, much of it to Switzerland. But they never addressed a
formal request to the Swiss government and did not renewed their
claim later.
   Similarly unconfirmed reports about secret Swiss accounts
allegedly held by Third World leaders have abounded in the Swiss
press for decades. Former presidents Juan Peron of Argentina,
Anastasio Somoza of Nicaragua and Hugo Banzer of Bolivia were among
many names mentioned.
</TEXT>

</DOC>