<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0435EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Panama-Noriega Bjt   12-27 0708</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Noriega, Bjt,0727</SECOND>
<HEAD>Strongman Roared Like Lion But Scurried Like Mouse</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   He roared like a lion, but when it
was time to fight he scurried like a mouse, running from hole to
hole as U.S. paratroopers tried to trap him.
   ``He repressed us for years and then he humiliated us by giving
up without a fight,'' said taxi driver Pedro Hernandez. ``I never
supported him, but he should have fought.''
   There was no final power play and Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega
didn't go down in a blaze of bullets, a fitting end for someone to
be romanticized in Latin American folklore once his political
crimes and other sins are forgotten.
   ``He did not even have the guts to kill himself,'' said
housewife Martiza Martinez.
   Instead of the name ``commander of dignity'' his cronies gave
him because he stood up to Americans, Mrs. Martinez said he was the
``commander of indignity.''
   Although most Panamanians were opposed to the military strongman
who named and fired six presidents like shop supervisors, they
almost believed his nationalist rhetoric of fighting to the death.
   He was said to enjoy a crisis, and it seemed that was the case
as he survived threat after threat to his reign. Many expected him
to die fighting, to be ``carried out of the barracks face up.''
   Noriega was defiant and mocking when the United States indicted
him in 1988 on drug trafficking charges. He vowed ``our life for
Panama'' and said the U.S. accusations were masking designs to
renege on the Panama Canal treaties and maintain the U.S. military
presence in Panama.
   For more than a year Noriega repressed all dissent, silenced all
opposition, survived two coup attempts and got away with annulling
the May 7 election his candidates lost. He portrayed himself as
David fighting the American Goliath, arms in the air, ever the
winner.
   In the end, even his government-run newspapers and radio
stations almost believed the propaganda. Noriega became a hero, a
man who could do no wrong, the savior of Panama while the Americans
were stupid, their soldiers cowards, drug addicts and AIDS carriers.
   So his flight to the Vatican's embassy on Sunday to seek asylum
was an anticlimax not only for his supporters, who hoped he would
take to the hills and lead an insurgency war, but also to
detractors who wished him dead.
   ``I did not think he was going to be such a coward,'' said a
government official who had sympathized with Noreiga and requested
anonymity bacause he wants to keep his job in the new U.S.-backed
government.
   ``It was a big bluff,'' said Judith Alvarez, who said she was
still ``nervous'' even though Noriega was closeted in the Vatican
mission. ``I will feel safe when I see him behind bars.''
   Many Panamanians felt it was more a question of the Americans
suffering him until their patience ran out. That happened on Dec.
16 when members of Noriega's security forces killed an American
soldier in civilian clothes near Panamanian military headquarers.
   U.S. Army South commander Maj. Gen. Marc Cisneros, a
Mexican-American from Texas who considered Noriega an affront to
Latin America, angrily demanded an explanation and an apology and
threatened military reprisal.
   But when 26,000 U.S. troops invaded the country one week ago,
Noriega was surprised. And there were not many in his 15,000-member
Defense Forces willing to fight for him.
   Most units surrendered, although the 1,800 or so who fought back
surprised the Americans with their stubborn resistance.
   But according to U.S. officials, Noriega never led the troops in
battle. When the first shots were fired, he fled and spent the next
six days running from place to place as U.S. soldiers combed the
city looking for him and his associates, most of whom were turned
in by angry neighbors.
   And Panama City paid a high price.
   El Chorrillo, a populous low-income barrio of old wooden
structures around the Panamanian military headquarters, was leveled
by the guns of the U.S. Army's Sheridan tanks. The number of dead
in the neighborhood, known for its Friday night street
celebrations, will never be known.
   Moaned taxi driver Hernandez: ``All those people died because of
this coward.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>