<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0090 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1035EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-PentagonText 4thAdd   12-20 0738</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Pentagon Text, 4th Add,740</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON: the actions.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Q: Well, when you went into Grenada you had _ we had support
right at the outset, the people were brought in to say they
supported this action. But here, you're not able to say that at
this point?
   Cheney: Well, this was a different situation.
   Q: Why?
   Cheney: I mean, there's always a tendency to want to compare
this operation with the last operation, and obviously, both are
military operations. But in the case of Grenada, there were no U.S.
forces present on the Island; we were invited by the governments of
the Eastern Caribbean to come in and provide support. In the case
of Panama, there is a major U.S. presence there; we are in Panama
with significant military force because we have a right to be under
the Panama Canal Treaties. It's just a different set of
circumstances. In this case the president felt very strongly, and
this was the basic justification for undertaking the operation,
that it was necessary in order to safeguard American lives and, at
the same time, to restore democracy to Panama.
   Q: Will this hurt us, though, with other Central American
countries _ once again, Uncle Sam imposing his will?
   Cheney: Well I would hope not. I would hope that other Central
American countries would recognize that what we have done is to
participate in the removal of a drug trafficker, a man who was a
dictator, a self-described Maximum Leader of Panama, a man who had
brutally treated not only Americans but also Panamanian citizens, a
man who had annulled the last election and defied the will of the
people of Panama to be governed by Mr. Endara, and that our action
is justified and will produce a democratic government in Panama. I
think that's a _ the way for it to be viewed, and I would hope that
other governments in the hemisphere recognize the reasons why the
president took the action and the result that will come from it.
   Q: Mr. Secretary, following the failed coup in Panama, you came
into this room and you made a number of arguments justifying our
decision not to get more heavily involved. You pointed to the risk
of inserting American forces in Panama City, and you said it wasn't
up to the United States, I think as you put it, ``To the
willy-nilly around the world knocking off governments, this was
something the Panamanians would have to do for themselves.'' Why is
your earlier assessment, which you made in this room two months ago
not valid anymore?
   Cheney: No, I am not sure I'd agree with your assessment of my
earlier assessment, but I think that there were significant changes
as a result of the actions of the past week, and that what was
different was that on Saturday, for example, an unarmed American
officer was shot and killed by the PDF, that this came about after
Gen. Noriega had had himself declared Maximum Leader and then
indicated that a state of war existed between Panama and the
government of the United States. I think we as a government bent
over backwards to avoid having to take military action. I think the
record is replete with the patience and forbearance of the United
States government in this instance. When it reached the point
however, when it was clear that American lives were at risk, when
it reached the point where it was clear that Gen. Noriega had
created an environment in which his troops felt free to terrorize
and brutalize Americans who had every legitimate and lawful right
to be in Panama, that was a fundamentally different set of
circumstances.
   Q: Mr. Secretary ... what sort of threat do the `dignity
battalions' now pose for these operations?
   Cheney: I'd defer to the general on that.
   Powell: Well, we're watching them carefully. It's not clear _
it's not clear how many of them are real battalions and how many
are just thugs and rabble rousers that would simply melt away. They
have not caused us any difficulty yet, but they have the potential
of sniping and things like that.
   Q: Isn't the fact that there are so many _ there are 23,000 U.S.
citizens in Panama, some dependents, some of military personnel
living there, there, do you think this is a particularly dangerous
operation, and what was done to protect them?
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>MORE</BYLINE>

</DOC>