<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0226 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 2127EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-TickerTalk Adv25   12-22 0586</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Ticker Talk, Adv 25,0602</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv25</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Monday Dec 25</HEAD>
<HEAD>Fewer Deals Getting Done at '80s' End</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHET CURRIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After a binge of corporate buyouts and takeovers
for much of the 1980s, Wall Street investors have gone on a spartan
diet in recent months.
   Along with shrinking profits and payrolls at many securities
firms, the results have produced a slower pace of turnover in the
ranks of companies holding a dominant position in the stock market.
   To reach that conclusion, Thomas Doerflinger, an analyst at
PaineWebber Inc., examined changes in the roster of names that make
up Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock composite index _ the yardstick most
commonly used by professionals to measure market trends.
   In 1988, Doerflinger found, deals were announced for 26 of the
S&amp;P 500, with an aggregate market value of $44.7 billion before the
bids were made.
   Over the first 11 months of this year, by contrast, only 14,
with a total value of $26.9 billion, attracted offers to buy.
   The most commonly cited cause of the slowdown has been a
prolonged slump in the market for high-yielding ``junk'' bonds,
which rose to prominence in the mid-1980s as a primary means of
financing takeovers and buyouts.
   Lenders shied away from further deals that might go the way of
Campeau Corp.'s troubled retailing empire or the
employee-management group that would-but-couldn't buy UAL Corp.
   Though that did indeed play a prominent part, Doerflinger
observes, it wasn't the only wilting influence on the takeover boom.
   ``In 1988,'' he noted, ``U.S. companies were on the
international bargain counter.
   ``In the wake of the 1987 market crash, stock prices were
depressed, even though corporate cash flow was very strong. U.S.
equities looked even cheaper to foreigners, because the U.S. dollar
was depressed.
   ``This process reversed in 1989, as stock prices rose, cash
flows weakened, the dollar appreciated, and turmoil in the junk
bond market slowed deal acitivity.''
   Although it has tapered off, the takeover wave promises to have
some lasting effects in the 1990s.
   For one thing, Doerflinger points out, it has significantly
altered the personality of the S&amp;P 500, which is used as a sort of
role model by many managers at investing institutions.
   Pension assets of millions of Americans these days are invested
in funds set up to duplicate the ups and downs of the 500
(``index'' funds) or in porftolios that play off the 500 with
computer models in the hopes of beating its performance.
   From January 1984 through November 1988, Doerflinger says, 121
stocks were displaced from the index _ and so were 16 of the names
that replaced them.
   ``It is very important to remember that S&amp;P does not attempt to
replace a deleted company with another company in the same
industry,'' he said.
   ``As a result, the structure of the S&amp;P 500 has changed over
time, as large companies in mature industries have been replaced by
fast-growing mid-sized companies, which tend to be in the consumer,
financial, technology and service sectors.''
   Instead of old-line industrial America, Doerflinger says, ``the
index looks more and more like a highly diversified growth stock
portfolio.''
   It remains to be seen whether that might help or hurt the
results turned in by the S&amp;P 500 in the 1990s.
   But it is already evident that the takeovers and buyouts of the
'80s forced a ``modernization'' of the 500, even as it did many
areas of the corporate world the index represents.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Mon Dec 25</NOTE>

</DOC>