<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0125 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1350EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Grain-China     12-20 0305</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Grain-China,320</SECOND>
<HEAD>China Buys More U.S. Wheat</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   China has bought additional U.S. wheat under a
price subsidy program, the Agriculture Department said Wednesday.
   F. Paul Dickerson, general sales manager for the department's
Foreign Agricultural Service, said seven private exporting
companies made the deals for a total of 410,000 metric tons under
the department's Export Enhancement Program, or EEP.
   Delivery of the wheat is scheduled for February and March, he
said.
   The sales were part of 1 million tons authorized China under EEP
on Dec. 5. A previous allocation of 2 million tons made Feb. 27 had
been exhausted, except for 10,000 tons.
   With the latest EEP approvals, China has 600,000 tons remaining
to be used under the current authorization.
   A metric ton is about 2,205 pounds and is equal to 36.7 bushels
of wheat. The latest sales would be about 15 million bushels. At
current prices estimated by USDA at $3.85 per bushel, the wheat
would have a farm value of about $58 million.
   Under EEP arrangements, private exporters may sell U.S.
commodities at reduced prices to meet foreign competition in
selected overseas markets and then collect free government
surpluses of grain or other commodities as bonuses, or subsidies.
   Dickerson said the latest subsidies averaged $19.26 per ton, or
about 52 cents per bushel.
   The subsidized sales were handled by Cargill Inc., 125,000 tons;
Continental Grain Co., 80,000; Coprostates Inc., 50,000; Louis
Dreyfus Corp., 40,000; Peavy Co., 40,000; Tradigrain Inc., 40,000;
and Mitsubishi International Corp., 35,000.
   With the latest sales, China has bought about 5.1 million tons
of U.S. wheat for delivery in the 1989-90 marketing year that began
June 1, most of it without subsidies. In 1988-89, China bought more
than 8 million tons of U.S. wheat, all of it under the EEP program.
</TEXT>

</DOC>