<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0816EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-DrugTesting 1stLd-Writethru a0416 12-18 0779</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Drug Testing, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0416,770</SECOND>
<HEAD>Random Drug Tests Begin Among 4 Million Transportation Workers</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Inserts 2 grafs after 4th graf, Transportation Secretary, with
new Skinner quotes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID BRISCOE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four million transportation workers face the
prospect of being required to give urine samples on short notice as
random drug testing begins today.
   In some cases, computers are selecting pilots, flight attendants
and other employees to be tested. Rules in the airline industry
take effect first, with maritime, railroad, trucking, transit and
pipeline companies to follow over the next several weeks.
   Some airlines indicate they will delay random testing until
early next year, but others say employees could be subject to
unannounced tests beginning today for marijuana, cocaine, opiates,
amphetamines and phencyclidine, also known as PCP.
   Transportation Secretary Samuel Skinner, who is considering the
addition of testing for alcohol, has said he expects the drug tests
to uncover ``alarming'' drug use by people responsible for
travelers' safety.
   ``If the results that we've received with the military over the
last five years are any indication, we'll be able to reduce drug
usage, if in fact it occurs, as much as 80 percent,'' Skinner said
today on ABC-TV's ``Good Morning America'' program.
   He said the military began random drug testing five years ago,
``and usage was about 10 percent across the board in the military,
and it's down now to less than 2 percent.''
   But employee groups, noting that 25,000 random tests on
Transportation Department employees resulted in a minuscule number
of positive results _ about 0.5 percent _ say the random testing is
a waste of time and money and an intrusion. The rules also require
pre-employment, post-accident, reasonable cause and periodic tests.
   ``We expect full compliance, even though we still very much
disagree with the concept of random testing,'' said John Mazor,
spokesman for the 40,000-member Air Line Pilots Association, which
has filed one of more than 20 lawsuits against the new rules.
   The Federal Aviation Administration denied a pilots' petition to
delay implementation of the testing. A federal court in San
Francisco refused a move for an injunction but has not yet ruled on
the testing.
   Skinner said government enforcers will not be out in the initial
stages of the testing, but all transportation companies are
expected to set up programs. Companies with fewer than 50 employees
have an extra year to comply.
   Testing in aviation will include pilots, flight engineers,
flight navigators, aircraft dispatchers, mechanics, repairmen,
flight attendants, aviation security screeners, ground security
coordinators, controllers and ground instructors. Private and
corporate pilots are not included, although pilots who fly
commercial crop dusting planes, tow banners or conduct training
flights are.
   Transportation Department officials eventually expect half of
the work force in safety-related transportation jobs to be tested
each year.
   Testing rules for mariners, truckers, and transit workers go
into effect on Thursday, for railroad employees on Jan. 16 and for
pipeline workers on April 20.
   Congress also is considering whether to enact legislation
requiring drug and alcohol testing for transportation workers. But
the department is starting the program without legislation.
   The National Transportation Safety Board earlier this month
criticized the department's post-accident testing rules, calling
for uniform rules for all types of transportation. The board said
the testing should also cover alcohol and require both urine and
blood tests within four hours after any accident or serious
incident.
   Department rules require that tests be performed by outside
laboratories certified by the Department of Health and Human
Services and that companies follow stringent procedures for
collecting urine samples and preventing access to them prior to
testing.
   Samples are tested twice. Those that test positive in an initial
screening are scanned with what the department calls ``a virtually
error-free gas chromotography and mass spectrometry confirmatory
test.''
   Positive results are sent to a medical review officer who must
discuss the results with the employee to determine whether there
might be a legitimate explanation for the result.
   Jeff Kriendler, spokesman for Pan American, said the airline
would begin the drug testing program today at all of its U.S.
stations. Employees in safety-related jobs as well as their
supervisors would be included, he said.
   Trans World Airlines' Jim Faulkner said about 17,000 of TWA's
31,000 employees would be subjected to possible random testing, to
begin Jan. 15 under an FAA waiver.
   David Messing of Continental said random testing would begin
Jan. 1.
   United's Sara Dornacker said testing of pilots is to begin Jan.
2 and other employees Jan. 12.
   Jim Lundy, spokesman for Delta, said the airline's testing plan
was sent back by the FAA for some minor adjustments and is awaiting
final approval.
</TEXT>

</DOC>