<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0236 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2159EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Panama-Markets 1stLd-Writethru a0846 12-20 0659</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Markets, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0846,0677</SECOND>
<HEAD>Financial Markets Have Muted Reaction to Panama Invasion</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 5th graf, `On Wall ..., to CORRECT that advancing stocks
outnumbered declining issues; picks up 6th graf: `Analysts said ...; a
version also moving on the financial wire.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIVIAN MARINO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Only a few blips registered on financial markets Wednesday as
investors took the U.S. invasion of Panama in stride.
   The dollar, oil and many stocks moved higher on the news of the
surprise U.S. military operation, but prices later receded amid the
usual concerns about interest rates and the economy.
   ``The initial reaction is one of a non-event,'' said Dennis E.
Jarrett, a stock analyst with Kidder, Peabody &amp; Co. in New York.
``It might have an impact if it becomes a prolonged situation.''
   President Bush ordered troops into Panama following several days
of tension triggered by the weekend shooting death of a U.S.
military officer by defense forces controlled by Gen. Manuel
Antonio Noriega.
   On Wall Street, the Dow Jones industrial average, a key
barometer of financial reaction to outside events, closed down 7.68
points to the 2,687.93, following an initial rise. Stocks advancing
in price narrowly outnumbered declining issues on the New York
Stock Exchange.
   Analysts said the Panama confrontation's economic effects were
unclear, but investors remain worried about the health of the U.S.
economy in general.
   Most experts did not view the Panamanian situation as a reason
for making big changes in their investment strategies.
   ``We've been involved in limited engagements before. This looks
like a military engagement that will be over shortly,'' said Larry
Wachtel, a vice president for Prudential-Bache Securities Inc. in
New York.
   Some analysts said they looked upon the assault as generally
positive because it showed the Bush administration meant business.
   ``I think people are encouraged by the forceful action by our
government,'' said Michael Metz, a technical analyst with New
York-based Oppenheimer &amp; Co. ``But there's a lot of anxieties on
Wall Steet ... worries about the real estate market and a looming
recession.''
   In another sign that the economy was dominating investor
thinking, some U.S. Treasury bond prices moved slightly higher in
late New York trading after the Federal Reserve signaled it might
lower interest rates. The prospect of lower rates on government
issues often spurs demand for existing bonds, pushing prices higher.
   Speculation about lower rates also helped depress the dollar in
foreign exchange trading.
   The U.S. currency initially rallied on the news of the Panama
action because in times of international tension investors buy
dollars and precious metals as safe havens for their money.
   The dollar closed sharply higher in Tokyo, but was mixed in
Europe and New York.
   Gabriele Schmitt, a trader with the Bank of New York, said the
dollar still had room to rise because of the uncertainty in Panama.
   ``There are still a lot of question marks,'' she said. ``Noriega
still has a lot of support in his country ... I wouldn't rule him
out entirely.''
   Gold prices were not affected significantly by the Panama news
but managed to finish slightly higher in New York trading.
   The oil futures market initially rallied, but prices fell back
later in the day.
   On the New York Mercantile Exchange, the February contract for
West Texas Intermediate, the leading grade of U.S. crude oil, was
down 7 cents to settle at $21.21 per 42-gallon barrel.
   The January home heating oil contract, supported in recent days
from a cold spell that hit parts of the nation, was up 0.75 cent to
settle at 75.76 cents a gallon.
   ``I think the reaction to the Panama closure was totally
irrational,'' Bob Baker, an energy analyst with Prudential-Bache,
said of the early rally.
   Prices jumped over concern that the closing of the Panama Canal
might disrupt oil shipments. But as most analysts noted only a
small percentage of crude shipped to the United States passes
through the Panama Canal.
</TEXT>

</DOC>