<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0139 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 2121EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Argentina-Economy     12-28 0434</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Argentina-Economy,0447</SECOND>
<HEAD>Interest Rates Soar; Price, Wage Turmoil Predicted</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUENOS AIRES, Argentina (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Interest rates skyrocketed to 600
percent a month at Argentine banks Thursday as economic turmoil
continued to undermine the credibility of the government of
President Carlos Menem.
   Banks resorted to paying their largest depositors a 600 percent
annual rate to retain funds that otherwise might be withdrawn and
converted to U.S. dollars.
   Investors here traditionally covet dollars for stability and
safe returns but the last two months have increasinly bought as
many dollars as are on the market, driving down the austral,
Argentina's national currency, to 1,950-1 on Thursday from 728-1 on
Nov. 1 _ 63 percent lower.
   During that time, one economy minister and two Central Bank
presidents were sacked, two economic stabilization plans were
launched and financial institutions were closed four times by
government order.
   Said local historian Felix Luna, ``There is no reason to be
optimistic, even if one wants to be.''
   Analysts attribute the turmoil in financial markets to a lack of
public confidence in the ability of Menem, who took office in July,
to carry out his proposed program of economic reform because of
opposition by powerful unions, businesses that sell to the state
and his own labor-based Peronist Party.
   He is seeking reduction of state expenditures that contribute to
chronic inflation and the sale of public companies that annually
ring up huge deficits.
   A survey by the Federation of Commercial Centers meanwhile
indicated that in the capital Buenos Aires, medicine prices soared
by an average 334 percent in December; food, 210 percent; hardware
items, 240 percent; clothing, 200 percent.
   Pharmacies reported their distributors were refusing to deliver
goods, particularly imported medicines, for fear of charging too
little and not being able to cover the cost of resupplying.
   Wages, linked to the government's calculation of inflation, have
failed to keep pace. Many public and private employees received
raises of 6.5 percent in early December to compensate them for the
cost of living in November.
   Economy Minister Antonio Gonzalez predicted that inflation in
December may top 50 percent.
   Ground crews at Aerolineas Argentinas staged a surprise strike
Thursday that resulted in the suspension of outgoing flights. They
demanded immediate wage hikes and participation in the proposed
sale of the state-owned carrier.
   Bus drivers, subway and commuter train operators, court clerks,
doctors and nurses at municipal hospitals, teachers and other
public employees all have conducted job actions in recent weeks in
demand of higher pay.
   Inflation for the first 11 months of 1989 increased by 3,731
percent, according to the National Institute of Statistics and
Census.
</TEXT>

</DOC>