<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0255 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0232EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-RealEstateSlump Bjt   12-20 0788</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Real Estate Slump, Bjt,0814</SECOND>
<HEAD>Real Estate Slump Was Long Time Coming, Analysts Say</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TONY ROGERS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The soft New England real estate market has made
Wall Street jumpy in recent days, but analysts say the slowdown has
been coming for a long time and isn't likely to disappear soon.
   The nervousness began Friday, when Bank of New England Corp.
announced it expected to report a ``substantial'' loss for the year
because it had to boost reserves to cover bad real estate loans.
   The bank, the nation's 15th largest, also said it might rescind
a stock dividend and would consider possible mergers and sales of
assets.
   The weekend seemed only to increase worries, and on Monday the
stock market took its sharpest drop in five weeks, with the Dow
Jones industrial average falling 42.02 points to 2697.53.
   Although the market stabilized Tuesday, brokers said investors
remained uneasy about the outlook for real estate, finance and
regional banks.
   ``It's probably too early to say `recession,''' said Mark Lynch,
a banking industry analyst with Bear, Stearns &amp; Co. ``But some of
the banks are going to be disasters. The fears in the market aren't
groundless.''
   The question on many minds was whether a regional real estate
slump could precipitate a full-scale nationwide recession, so far
averted after seven years of economic growth.
   ``Economic factors feed on each other, and it's hard to say
whether this leads to other declines,'' said Mas Kakutani, a
director of bank analysts for Moody's Investors Service Inc., a
credit-rating agency. ``But along with real estate we're seeing
slowdowns in manufacturing and the service industries.''
   One real estate group said Tuesday that talk of regional real
estate problems having national economic implications was overblown.
   ``Many of these `doom and gloom' analyses are authored on the
Eastern Seaboard, where median home prices in some cities have
declined over the past year,'' said Norman D. Flynn, president of
the National Association of Realtors. ``At any given time, some
housing markets are hot, some are not.''
   Analysts said the real estate problem began when zealous
regional banks courted too many deals during the construction boom
of the mid-1980s.
   ``There was too much money chasing too few good deals,'' said
George Fantini, senior vice president of the Boston Financial
Group, a real estate service company. ``There was a lot of money in
the hands of some inexperienced lending officers. People who had
made only $100,000 loans were suddenly making $5 million loans.''
   The big money fueled competition, and a herd mentality.
   ``Everyone got bullish on New England,'' Fantini said. ``It was
viewed as a wonderful market. Few people thought it would end.''
   The building continued, but buying stopped. The state's
high-tech industry, the juggernaut behind much of the
``Massachusetts Miracle,'' sputtered. Today, office buildings that
computer firms thought they could fill lie empty along Route 128
west of Boston.
   Kakutani of Moody's said real estate's dire straits could be
traced back at least 18 to 20 months, but banks are just starting
to take it seriously, he said.
   ``There's no question the banks were slow to respond,'' Kakutani
said. ``But banks often reflect the perceptions of the market.
Three months ago, most banks would have said this was part of a
periodic boom-and-bust cycle. They're not saying that anymore.''
   The only immediate solution for banks, Lynch said, is to keep
bad loans to a minimum, and to cut costs _ layoffs, in other words.
   Fantini admitted the situation was bad, but said federal
regulators were making it worse by forcing lending institutions to
liquidate their real estate assets too quickly.
   ``Regulators say to banks, `Sell your real estate assets.' I
say, `To who?''' Fantini said. ``There's no capital out there for
liquidation.''
   To dig themselves out of their financial quagmire, Fantini
suggested banks offer incentives like low-interest mortgages to
first-time home buyers.
   The only bright spot in New England's real estate market may be
cheaper homes for some buyers. Optimists hope declining interest
rates will support the real estate market via lower mortgage rates
for buyers and refinancings at lower costs for some existing
homeowners.
   ``This will provide opportunities to buy condominiums or
houses,'' Kakutani said. ``It will make home buying a more viable
option for some.''
   And the future? In all likelihood housing demand will continue
dropping, if population figures are any indication.
   Harvard University economist Gregory Mankiw, who has studied
population trends, said in the next decade there won't be many home
buyers to replace the baby-boomers, who drove housing prices up in
the 1970s and early '80s.
   ``We're coming into an unprecedented time in terms of low
population growth,'' Mankiw said. ``The 1990s will be a slow time
for housing.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>