<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0165 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1954EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Panama-OAS 1stLd-Writethru a0658 12-21 0601</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-OAS, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0658,590</SECOND>
<HEAD>OAS Divides on Resolution to Condemn US Attack in Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDs: SUBS 3rd graf: ``Nicaragua's leftist,'' to CORRECT that Nicaragua
did not call the session; SUBS 9th graf: ``It's even,'' to CORRECT ``excepts''
to ``accepts.''</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-US-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRYNA BRENNAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Organization of American States suspended
its Thursday session five minutes after it opened, as
representatives divided on the wording of a resolution to condemn
the U.S. military intervention in Panama.
   OAS Chairman Angus Albert Khan of Trinidad and Tobago said he
had been approached by several delegations asking for more time
before beginning debate on a resolution submitted Wednesday by
Nicaragua. He did not say when the session would resume.
   Nicaragua's leftist government on Wednesday introduced a
resolution calling on the members to condemn the use of force and
demand the immediate withdrawal of American troops. As written, the
measure could be interpreted to include the more than 10,000 U.S.
soldiers permanently based in Panama.
   The members held firm to OAS procedures Wednesday and put off
debate on that resolution for 24 hours. They also used established
procedures to rebuff a request by the U.S.-recognized government of
Guillermo Endara in Panama to accept a new representative.
   Instead, Panama is representated by Jose Maria Cabrera, who
decried ``the brutal and criminal aggression'' against his homeland
and de facto ruler Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   Traditional U.S. allies, in speech after speech Wednesday, spoke
out against the use of force in the region. But the agreement
stopped there.
   OAS sources, speaking Thursday on the condition of anonymity,
said at least two other resolutions were being prepared by the
Latin countries. The sources said the new drafts would include a
condemnation of Noriega, who is wanted in the United States on drug
trafficking charges but eluded capture when troops stormed into
Panama City.
   The Caribbean members said they did not have enough time to
consult their governments on an appropriate response.
   ``It's even more fragmented that that,'' U.S. ambassador Luigi
Einaudi said after the session. He declined to comment further,
saying only that the United States ``obviously won't accept
condemnation.''
   The OAS has not been asked to decide which government it
recognizes in Panama. The United States announced Wednesday that
Endara was sworn into office hours after the first troops arrived.
He was elected in May in balloting later nullified by Noriega.
   During the Wednesday evening session, member nations long
considered U.S. allies read statements condemning the assault on
Panama. The criticism came from Chile, Brazil, Ecuador, Guatemala,
Haiti and Costa Rica.
   ``We see abusive practices have not been forgotten and we do not
accept it. We protest it,'' said Peruvian ambassador Edmundo Haya
de la Torre. ``This does not mean we support General Manuel Antonio
Noriega.''
   Defense for the U.S. assault came from El Salvador, which said
the U.S. action supported the freely elected government. Backing
also came from Canada, which holds observer status until it becomes
a member next year.
   Canadian representative Richard Gorham said his government
``regretted the use of force'' but added: ``We must nonetheless
again highlight the extraordinary circumstances which have caused
the United States to act as it has, and to support its objective of
restoring constitutional, democratic government to the republic of
Panama.''
   Cabrera accused the United States of ``slaughtering defenseless
civilians'' and said Panamanians would not back Endara.
   ``He will stay thanks to the bayonets, the gunships and the
tanks of the U.S. Army,'' he said. ``No worthy Panamanian, no
Panamanian who is aware of his homeland can accept Guillermo Endara
as president.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>