<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0183 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0944EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-AirFares 1stLd-Writethru   12-28 0542</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Air Fares, 1st Ld-Writethru,0557</SECOND>
<HEAD>United To Match Midway Fare Cuts; Northeast Shuttles Hike Fares</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: edits grafs 6-8 to ADD Trump confirmation, comment; uppicks
8th graf pvs: United's fare ...</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Winter travelers around the country may start the new year with
lower air fares, as several airlines announce cuts in the cost of
flying for the first months of 1990.
   But the two principal air shuttle services in the Northeast,
which cater mostly to business passengers, are raising their fares
for the first time since August 1988.
   Chicago-based United Airlines, the nation's second-largest
carrier, followed the lead of cross-town rival Midway Airlines and
said Wednesday it would lower some fares as much as 30 percent.
   ``We have matched them in most markets,'' United spokesman Joe
Hopkins said.
   Northwest Airlines and Trans World Airlines followed suit late
Wednesday, announcing they were matching the fare cuts. It wasn't
immediately clear whether other major carriers also planned to join
the move.
   Separately Wednesday, Trump Shuttle told travel agents it was
raising fares from $99 one way to $119 on weekdays and from $69 to
$79 on weekends, agents said. Pan Am Corp. spokeswoman Pamela
Hanlon said that company's shuttle service, which competes with
Trump's, was matching the increase, effective Jan. 3.
   The hourly shuttle flights link New York with Boston and
Washington. Billionaire developer Donald Trump bought his service
from Eastern Airlines for $365 million in early June.
   Trump spokeswoman Joan Fudala today cited increased costs for
fuel, labor and aircraft maintenance as the reason for the increase.
   United's fare reductions are effective immediately and require a
14-day advance purchase and a Saturday night stay, said Rob
Doughty, another spokesman for the airline.
   The new United fares are based on mileage. Round-trip fares for
flights of up to 1,000 miles are $198 for peak times and $178 for
off-peak times. Peak times are Saturdays, Sundays and Mondays;
off-peak fares apply other days.
   For flights from 1,001 to 2,000 miles, fares will be $258 peak
and $238 off-peak, the airline said in a statement. Flights of more
than 2,000 miles will cost $318 peak and $278 off-peak.
   United's action spread the fare-cutting that began last week
when Southwest Airlines reduced prices on its longer routes, a move
other carriers followed on a limited basis.
   Midway, which operates its main hub at Chicago's Midway Airport,
had announced one-way fares ranging from $19 to $99 across its
50-city route system within the continental United States.
   ``The entire industry is seeing soft bookings (for) the first
quarter,'' said Midway spokeswoman Laura Podlesny, explaining the
fare cuts.
   Passengers wanting to take advantage of United's lower fares
must make reservations by Jan. 31 and may travel through March 6.
The fares are available only on a round-trip basis and are not
refundable.
   Midway cut its Chicago-Los Angeles round-trip fare from $318 to
$198, and its Chicago-Washington round-trip fare from $228 to $158.
   Midway's new $38 round-trip fares _ $19 one way _ apply to
routes connnecting Chicago with Detroit and Kansas City, Mo. The
fares previously were $43.
   Midway waived minimum-stay requirements that usually apply to
discount tickets, but said the reduced-rate tickets must be
purchased by Jan. 20 and travel completed by March 31.
</TEXT>

</DOC>