<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0147 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2012EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-OfficerKilled 1stLd-Writethru a0710 12-19 0769</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Officer Killed, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0710,0789</SECOND>
<HEAD>Accused Cop Killer Surrenders After Taking Hostages</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 6th graf, `Cole, who ..., with 4 grafs to UPDATE with three
others charged.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LESTER PRAIRIE, Minn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man accused of killing a police
officer surrendered Tuesday after holding a family hostage and
telling a television station he shot the officer in the head
because he ``was calling me a worm.''
   Police arrested Phillip Cole, 29, after Cole tossed out his gun,
raised his hands and walked out of a rural Lester Prairie farmhouse
around 5:15 a.m., said Hutchinson police Sgt. Scott Schwartz.
   During the standoff, Cole spoke on the telephone with WCCO-TV in
Minneapolis, telling the station that he shot police officer
Michael Hogan.
   ``He was calling me a worm. He was calling me a punk. He said he
was going to take me in. I shot him in the head,'' Cole told the
station.
   ``It was the stupidest thing I did in my life because it's
costing me my life,'' Cole said.
   Cole, who is charged with second-degree murder in the death last
Friday, was taken under heavy security to McLeod County Jail in
Glencoe, Schwartz said.
   Second-degree murder and theft charges also were filed Tuesday
against two women and a man arrested Friday in Hutchinson, a town
of about 10,000 people 60 miles west of Minneapolis, in connection
with Hogan's death.
   The three others, whom authorities allege were part of a
shoplifting ring with Cole, were each held in lieu of $125,000
bail, McLeod County Attorney Michael Junge said.
   Junge said murder charges were filed because ``they should have
and could have foreseen that, based on Mr. Cole's violent nature
and the fact that he carried a weapon, their shoplifting could
easily escalate to a shooting.''
   He said more than $1,000 in merchandise was recovered from the
van the three were in when they were arrested.
   Police would not say what charges were being considered.
   Hogan, a 16-year police veteran, was shot to death in a private
room at the J.C. Penney store in Hutchinson while he was
interviewing Cole as part of a shoplifting investigation.
   The funeral for the 43-year-old officer was held in Hutchinson
on Tuesday. About 600 people attended, at least half of them law
enforcement officials from around Minnesota.
   After Hogan was shot, Cole allegedly escaped by commandeering a
car to the Twin Cities, authorities said. On Sunday and Monday,
police surrounded three different Minneapolis homes, believing Cole
was hiding in each. But they failed to find him.
   As police surrounded the third home late Monday night, Cole was
able to get away and take a car driven by a woman who also became a
hostage, authorities said.
   Officers began chasing Cole after an officer tried to pull his
car over for a minor traffic violation in Minnetonka, said McLeod
County Sheriff Duane Kopesky.
   Cole's car rolled over and Cole, who has a long record of
violence and imprisonment, ran from the accident to a farmhouse,
forcing a woman to go with him, authorities said.
   He then took Alan and Sandy Otto and their 2-year-old daughter
hostage in their home, Kopesky said.
   During the five-hour standoff, Kopesky said Cole's mother,
Grace, and one of his sisters were brought to the scene to talk to
him by telephone. The strategy helped convince Cole to give up,
Kopesky said.
   Steve Geiger, a police psychologist who assisted in the
negotiations, said, ``There were extreme threats to the hostages in
the house and it was very clear that Cole wavered between homicidal
and suicidal moments.''
   WCCO-TV reported that during the standoff Cole said he wanted to
say goodbye to his mother and sister and commit suicide.
   ``All I wanted was to talk to my family, you know, my family
members. And say goodbye to my friends and I was gonna let these
people walk out the door and I was gonna take my own life,'' Cole
told the station.
   ``I just want to tell them that, `Hey, I love ya, ya know. And
I'm sorry that this had to happen. I'm sorry it came down to
this,'' he said.
   The Ottos did not immediately return a telephone call Tuesday.
   Cole also told WCCO-TV that a police officer helped him avoid
capture by warning him of searches, but police Sgt. Phil VanTassel
said Cole's claim was ``ludicrous.''
   ``I believe it's a little outlandish,'' said Minneapolis Police
Chief John Laux, ``but on the other hand, I am having my internal
affairs commander review the tape and we'll look into it. ... I
haven't drawn any conclusions so early.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>