<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0157 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2058EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Royals-Press     12-21 0469</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Royals-Press,0482</SECOND>
<HEAD>Princess Diana's Brother Excoriates Tabloid Press</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Princess Diana's brother and his wife said in a
television program broadcast Thursday that Britain's tabloid
newspapers harassed them and fabricated stories in the weeks before
they were married Sept. 16.
   Viscount Althorp, 25, and his wife, the former Victoria
Lockwood, 24, said events and remarks attributed to them were
manufactured.
   In an interview on ``Hard News,'' a Channel 4 television program
about the news industry, Viscountess Althorp said tabloid
journalists harassed her and her friends and invaded their privacy.
   ``I think they're really totally insensitive, evil, evil
people,'' she said. ``I don't know how they go home to their wives
and children and talk about their day with a clear conscience and
have any self-esteem or self-respect.''
   Viscount Althorp, who works as a reporter for the NBC-TV show
``Today'' as Charles Althorp, said of the tabloid reporters: ``They
were not content with the story as it stood. They wanted to make it
juicier, nastier.
   ``Everyday people are bruised by the press and they haven't got
any recourse to speak out, and I am doing this because I think I
ought to and because I am in the position to do so.''
   His wife criticized a cover story in the Sunday Mirror of Sept.
10, on which the headline was ``Charlie's Bride in Sexy Clinch with
Ex-Lover.''
   ``If I were going to smooch with an ex-flame, I certainly
wouldn't do it in a nightclub in front of everybody,'' she said.
   A spokesman for Maxwell Communications, which owns the Sunday
Mirror, said company officials had not seen the program and could
not comment until they had done so.
   Althorp said he once found a photographer hiding in bushes
beside his house when he and Miss Lockwood were outdoors.
   ``We had a drink on the lawn and I heard this clicking from a
bush at the end of the garden,'' he said. ``So I raced there and I
hauled out this photographer who was weighed down with cameras.''
   Darius Guppy, the couple's best man, said a News of the World
journalist tried to get him to agree that the bachelor night party
``degenerated into an orgy.''
   ``They were interested in inventing a story that would
compromise Lord Althorp, which I think was unforgivable,'' he said.
   Stuart Kuttner, the News of the World managing editor, said his
paper was interested in covering the Althorp engagement and
wedding, but ``the allegation that the paper was interested in
inventing a story that would compromise Lord Althorp is utterly
without foundation.''
   ``Indeed, the claim does not bear examination, since to invent,
without foundation, a compromising story would expose the paper to
the risk of legal proceedings which it would be unable to defend,''
Kuttner said. ``In short, this serious charge is wholly rejected.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>