<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0914EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-US-Panama 3rdLd-Writethru 1stAdd 12-21 0496</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-Panama, 3rd Ld-Writethru, 1st Add, a0531,490</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON: the operation.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Dozens of guests hiding in the seaside luxury Marriott Hotel in
Panama City cheered when a battalion of elite U.S. airborne troops
shot their way through a neighborhood to reach the building late
Wednesday night, ending a day of terror.
   Cheney said the Pentagon had received conflicting reports about
American hostages.
   ``It's sort of a floating crap game,'' he said. ``There may well
still be some Americans held, but at this point we haven't been
able to confirm specific identities or specific numbers.''
   Bush ``is pleased by the military precision and smoothness of
the operation,'' said spokesman Marlin Fitzwater. He said Bush
would take a planned vacation in Texas next week.
   Cheney gave this situation report today:
   ``The organized resistance by the Panamanian forces has
virutally ended. What we still have, though, is a situation in
which there are a fairly large number of so-called Dignity
Battalion members that are loose in the streets, many of them armed.
   ``So it's still a somewhat chaotic situation. Our forces are
still involved in some cases in firefights. And it's not complete
yet, but we've made major progress.''
   In his speech, Bush extended official diplomatic recognition to
a new Panamanian government headed by Guillermo Endara, the
opposition candidate in last May's elections voided by Noriega _
and moved swiftly to bolster him.
   Ambassador Arthur Davis returned to Panama for the first time
since the elections. At a heavily guarded news conference on a
military base attended only by a poo of Washington-based reporters,
Davis said he was bringing an economic recovery plan for discussion
with Panama's new leaders.
   He made no promise of U.S. aid except to point out that $700
million in assets would be returned as a result of Bush's decision
to lift economic sanctions.
   Davis added that ``deep down'' he thought leaders of other
regional countries would be happy to have Noriega gone, despite
their stated opposition to U.S. military intervention.
   The United States defended its decision at the United Nations
and at the Organization of American States meeting in Washington.
   Vice President Dan Quayle spoke by telephone with Endara's vice
presidents, Billy Ford and Ricardo Arias Calderon, and
administration officials also said privately he might visit Panama
next month in a gesture that would dramatize administration support.
   White House spokesman Roman Popadiuk said the bounty on
Noriega's head would come from an existing drug enforcement fund.
   The reward is coupled with an offer of $150 per weapon to
Noriega loyalists who surrender their firearms.
   The assault was the first time U.S. military force had been used
against a foreign government since the 1986 air raid on Libya and
the first full-fledged assault since the invasion of Grenada in
1983.
   It came after American forces sat by, inactive, on Oct. 3 when
dissident Panamanian officers attempted a coup and briefly held
Noriega _ an incident that subjected Bush to congressional
criticism for timidity and indecision.
</TEXT>

</DOC>