<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0351EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ChristmasRdp     12-25 0583</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Christmas Rdp,0599</SECOND>
<HEAD>Santa Takes Many Forms as Nation Celebrates Giving</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY19</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Children across America ripped open Christmas wrappings today,
and gifts and cards poured into military hospitals for GIs wounded
last week in the U.S. invasion of Panama.
   But on the nation's streets, an estimated 720,000 of the
country's 2 million homeless men, women and children spent the
holiday without shelter, said Peter Smith, president of Partnership
of the Homeless, a private shelter network in New York.
   Around the nation, many tried to make the holiday brighter for
the homeless. In Los Angeles, Alex Trebek, host of the TV game show
``Jeopardy,'' waited on tables at a shelter that expected to serve
5,000 meals.
   ``Hey, this isn't much,'' said Trebek. ``We all should be doing
more. We shouldn't have this problem in this rich country.''
   In Atlanta, 5,500 volunteers prepared to set tables and hand out
gifts for 40,000 of the city's less fortunate residents.
   And one Manhattan restaurant served meals to 45 homeless women
and their children, who were also visited by a Santa bearing gifts.
   ``I know we're doing something small but it's our personal
start,'' said Michael Miele, co-owner of the Amsterdam Bar and
Rotisserie.
   Gifts and cards poured into military hospitals for the GIs in
San Antonio, Fort Bragg, N.C., and Fort Lewis, Wash.
   At a supermarket in Clark, N.J., last-minute shoppers greeted
the news of Panama strongman Manuel Noriega taking refuge in the
residence of the Vatican's representative in Panama City. The news
was announced over the store intercom.
   ``That's a nice Christmas present,'' said a checkout clerk.
``Now let's hang him.''
   Sen. Jesse Helms, R-N.C., said it was ironic that Noreiga sought
asylum on Christmas Eve in a church. ``At least we know where the
bum is,'' Helms said late Sunday. ``It is the height of irony that
this man, who has got to be one of the most barbaric terrorists in
history, is now running to the church for sanctuary.''
   In a Cajun celebration more than two centuries old, residents of
St. James Parish, La., upriver from New Orleans light bonfires
shaped like wooden boats, fire trucks and medieval castles and
teepees filled with kindling so Pere Noel _ Father Noel _ won't get
lost in the dark on Christmas Eve.
   In Wichita, Kan., a Vietnamese couple planned to spend Christmas
with their 11-year-old son following a tearful reunion Saturday
with the child they left behind when they fled their homeland 10
years ago.
   When Quang Vu walked off an airplane and into a Wichita airport,
his mother Anh Le clutched him to her chest and burst into tears.
She last saw her son when he was 7 months old, before she and her
husband, Tom Vu, escaped from Ho Chi Minh City in Vietnam.
   ``We'll talk, maybe tonight we won't sleep,'' Ms. Vu said. ``We
feel a big relief. We don't have to worry anything about it
anymore. We have more time to concentrate on our future.''
   In East St. Louis, Ill., Santa's helper was a psychologist who
remembers her own Christmases in an orphanage, and has been handing
out toys since 1966.
   Rita Swiener said she expected to give out presents to 1,300
children and adults. She said she had spent $6,000 of her own money
and had gotten many donations.
   ``I keep telling myself next year I'll put a limit on and stick
to it, but I just can't say no to these people,'' she said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>