<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0171 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2218EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PoliceProbe     12-21 0477</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Police Probe,0491</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ex-Deputy Chief Arrested on Wire Fraud Charge</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAN DESMOND</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A former police deputy chief accused of cheating
investors and stealing money from the Detroit Police Department was
arrested Thursday on a federal charge of wire fraud, officials said.
   Kenneth Weiner was held without bond after a heariang before
U.S. Magistrate Virginia M. Morgan, after prosecutors argued
successfully that there was a risk the former civilian deputy chief
would flee.
   Weiner was carryng had dozens of blank checks, credit cards and
valid flight coupons when he was arrested early Thursday at Detroit
Metropolitan Airport in Romulus, said Assistant U.S. Attorney
Sheldon Light.
   The wire fraud charge is related to a pyramid investment scam in
1985 and 1986, U.S. Attorney Stephen Markman said.
   Earlier this month, Weiner was accused of stealing from a $1.4
million police secret service fund used for undercover operations.
He had access to the fund from 1980 to 1986, when he left the
department.
   The FBI, under a warrant issued by Morgan on Wednesday, arrested
Weiner without incident as he stepped off a plane from Los Angeles,
FBI Special Agent in Charge Hal Helterhoff said.
   Weiner's troubles began in 1986 when Caine Steel Co. of Detroit
filed a civil lawsuit against him, charging that he defrauded the
company of $379,000.
   He is suspected of duping as many as 90 investors out of about
$20 million in a scheme that involved gold and silver trading.
   Weiner, 43, resigned as a deputy police chief in 1986 in the
wake of allegations about the investment scheme. In his six years
with the department, he advised police on security and
anti-terrorism practices.
   Caine Steel's suit claimed Weiner said he represented COMSEC
Corp. and could turn ``a sizable profit above current market
interest'' on its investment. The alleged investment scheme used
new investors' cash to provide large returns to previous investors.
Such plans collapse when new investors can't be found.
   Earlier this month, Police Chief William Hart said Weiner stole
money from the police secret service fund. Phony corporations set
up by Weiner in California received checks from the fund.
   Weiner's companies paid $72,000 in rent for a Beverly Hills,
Calif., house occupied by Hart's daughter and son-in-law. Hart
signed checks to the corporations, but denies knowing anything
about the rent paid on his daughter's home.
   Weiner disappeared in recent weeks as federal and city officials
investigated the $1.4-million secret police fund. As of Thursday,
no charges had been filed against him on alleged theft from the
police department.
   Mayor Coleman Young this week reluctantly turned records of the
fund over to city auditors, who found that key documents needed to
trace money were missing. Police officials said a theft report was
filed.
   Young initially balked at turning over the records because he
said it could jeopardize undercover operations.
</TEXT>

</DOC>