<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0713EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-OAS-Panana 1stLd-Writethru a0540 12-22 0652</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-OAS-Panana, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0540,590</SECOND>
<HEAD>OAS Calls for U.S. Withdrawal From Panama ^Eds: INSERTS two grafs
after 5th graf, The OAS, to ADD Spanish-language release uses `deplore'
sted `regret'; picks up 6th graf pvs, The resolution</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARY MOLEON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Latin American states voted today an
expression of deep ``regret'' of U.S. military force in Panama and
urged an immediate end to fighting there.
   The vote after a marathon emergency session of the Organization
of American States also called for the withdrawal of troops used in
the U.S. action, but it did not condemn the intervention outright
and sought no timetable for the American troops to leave.
   A resolution by Nicaragua to condemn the use of force to oust
Panamanian Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega from power was not formally
considered.
   John Maisto, the U.S. deputy permanent representative to the
OAS, called the final resolution ``a mixed bag. ... We're a little
disappointed. It certainly wasn't an extreme resolution, but it's a
little detached from what is really happening in Panama.''
   The OAS political council voted 20-1 with six abstentions ``to
deeply regret the military intervention in Panama.''
   The Spanish-language version of the resolution distributed after
the vote used the words ``deplorar profundamente,'' which
translates more closely to ``deeply deplore.'' But James Todd, a
spokesman for the U.S. delegation, said the stronger Spanish
language was a mistranslation of a resolution drafted in English
and he expected a clarification later in the day.
   ``The English version was circulated and voted on. We're using
the English,'' said Todd.
   The resolution noted ``the serious events (in Panama),
especially the armed clashes resulting from the military
intervention by the United States and the deplorable loss of lives
and property.''
   U.S. Ambassador Luigi Enaudi cast the only negative vote on the
motion engineered by Peru, Brazil, Mexico, Colombia, Uruguay and
Argentina.
   The resolution urged ``the immediate cessation of hostilities
and bloodshed (in Panama) and the launching of negotiations between
the various political sectors of that country that will lead to a
concerted solution of the Panamanian institutional crisis.''
   ``There was not a condemnation,'' said Maisto. ``It was just an
expression of the need for withdrawal (of troops), which is not
unlike what President Bush has called for _ when the job is
completed.''
   A U.S. attempt to term the invasion a ``military action'' failed
with only three votes among the 26 delegates who attended the
17-hour debate and negotiation. Only Honduras and Costa Rica
supported the United States.
   Another amendment by Costa Rica and Guatemala to blame Noriega
for the ``chaos and anarchy'' that prompted the U.S. move was also
defected by a 7-2 vote with 12 abstentions.
   Venezuela was the only leading Latin democracy to abstain from
the final vote. Venezuela has urged the OAS to express some form of
recognition to the U.S.-installed government of President Guillermo
Endara.
   The OAS said it ``reaffirmed that solving the crisis Panama is
undergoing at this time necessarily requires the full respect for
the right of the Panamanian people to self-determination without
outside interference and faithful adherence to the letter and
spirit of the treaties'' under which the United States is to turn
the Panama Canal over to Panama in 2000.
   The security of the canal is one of the reasons cited by the
Bush administration for launching the invasion.
   Enaudi also failed by an 11-4 vote with two abstentions in an
attempt to add to the resolution a mention that the OAS charter
itself allows each nation the right of self-defense.
   Enaudi said that once Noriega declared a state of war against
the United States, the U.S. government ``clearly have the
legitimate right of self-defense''.
   Enaudi also said the U.S. has tried to work out a peacefully
solution of the Panamanian situation thought the OAS but ``it is
impossible to reason with a dictator. At the end, Noriega has got
what he deserved.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>