<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0154 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1927EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     12-21 0402</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0416</SECOND>
<HEAD>United States Has A Cold First Day Of Winter</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Winter left no doubt about its arrival Thursday as it continued
to pour arctic air out of Canada, setting record low temperatures
in at least 17 U.S. cities.
   Morning lows were colder than 20 degrees below zero from
northwest upper Michigan through the Dakotas to northeastern
Montana, and plunged more than 30 degrees below zero in western
North Dakota and northeastern Montana.
   Strong northerly winds brought wind chill readings to as low as
80 degrees below zero.
   The latest northerly flow of air out of Canada and the arctic
regions brought the coldest weather of the season to the
north-central United States, where at least 17 cities reported new
record low temperatures for the date Thursday morning.
   Montana, Havre, reported a record-setting low of 43 degrees
below zero, breaking a 105-year-old record.Chicago set a new record
with a minus 13, colder than in 1872, when the previous record of
12 below zero was set.
   Readings dipped below zero fom the northern and central High
Plains to the upper Great Lakes, and the frigid air was ushered
deep into the heart of Texas.
   Numerous record lows were likely to be established east of the
Rockies by Friday night, and before the cold wave ends many parts
of the country may experience their coldest night of record, the
National Weather Service siad.
   Afternoon temperatures were below zero across the northern and
central Plains region and the middle and upper Mississippi Valley,
and the the subzero cold is entering the Great Lakes region.
   Afternoon readings were colder than 20 degrees below zero in the
Dakotas and eastern Montana, with readings still near 40 degrees
below zero in north- central Montana.
   Strong northerly winds produced squalls with heavy snow in the
Great Lakes region. In western New York state, the town of Pulaski
was buried under four feet of snow in one night. Two feet of snow
was reported at Barnes Corners, N.Y.
   Snow generated by the cold front blew across much of the High
Plains and parts of the central Rocky Mountain region, the Ohio
Valley and the central Appalachian region in the afternoon.
   Sunny skies and seasonable temperatures prevailed across much of
the West, with the Rocky Mountain range serving as kind of a
protective barrier from the arctic invasion into the central and
eastern United States.
</TEXT>

</DOC>