<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0088 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1415EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel     12-28 0542</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel,0558</SECOND>
<HEAD>Army Orders Inquiry in Shooting of Four Palestinians</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By G.G. LaBELLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The army ordered an investigation into the
shooting of four Palestinian youths who reportedly were fired on
early Thursday as they drove a donkey cart to market in the Gaza
Strip.
   The youths, age 12 to 16, were among 10 Palestinians reported
shot and wounded by troops in the occupied West Bank and Gaza
Strip. The 12-year-old boy was in serious condition.
   In the West Bank city of Nablus, a leaflet signed by PLO chief
Yasser Arafat's Fatah faction called for a halt to the killing of
accused collaborators with Israel and said only Arafat had
authority to order such slayings.
   The slayings of 163 Palestinians by fellow Arabs during the
2-year-old uprising have prompted Israeli charges that Arafat is
using the label ``collaborators'' to get rid of political
opponents. Palestinians deny the accusation.
   At least 640 Palestinians have been killed by Israelis during
the revolt, and 43 Israelis have been slain.
   Thursday's shooting of four Palestinians by soldiers came
shortly after 3:30 a.m. in Gaza City.
   An army spokesman said an initial report indicated soldiers
opened fire on four masked Palestinians. It said the Palestinians
were barricading a road, refused orders to halt and ignored warning
shots in the air.
   But the spokesman, who was not identified under army
regulations, said an investigation was ordered into whether
soldiers acted properly following Arab reports the four victims
were driving a cart to a wholesale vegetable market.
   One of the youths said neither he nor his companions were
wearing masks, but that one of the wounded youths ran away in fear
as the soldiers approached.
   Arab reporters said the 16 year old who was driving the cart
went to the market each morning to pick up vegetables to sell door
to door. One reporter said he counted 10 gunshots after being
awakened by the soldiers' fire. He said the donkey was killed.
   One of the boys, Khaled Salim Shawwa, 12, was in serious
condition with gunshot wounds to the chest and stomach.
   In the biblical town of Bethlehem, paramilitary border police
shot and seriously wounded Fadi Khalil Zabagli, 18, during a
protest. The army said he was wearing a mask.
   An army statement said one youth was shot when soldiers opened
fire at the eight Palestinians, who were armed with axes and ran
away despite orders to halt and warning shots.
   Army regulations allow soldiers to open fire at the legs of
masked men if they disregard such warnings and flee.
   The Fatah plea against killing suspected collaborators came
after earlier leaflets by PLO-backed uprising leaders failed to
stop such killings, especially in Nablus, where masked attackers
have shot, stabbed or beaten to death 20 Palestinians.
   ``In the name of the brother, the leader, the president Yasser
Arafat, we call on national forces and all our organizational units
to stop immediately and finally the killings of collaborators,''
said the leaflet signed by the Fatah unit in Nablus.
   ``Only the president of the state of Palestine has the authority
to issue a decree to execute collaborators,'' it said. Arafat was
named president of the self-declared Palestinian state by the PLO's
parliament in November 1988.
</TEXT>

</DOC>