<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0235 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2332EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BingoSuicide     12-20 0582</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bingo Suicide,0598</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tennessee Secretary of State Dies From Dec. 12 Gunshot Wound</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BILL RAWLINS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Secretary of State Gentry Crowell, who
shot himself in the head last week as a corruption probe tightened
around his office, died Wednesday after doctors declared him
brain-dead.
   Crowell, who was not implicated personally in the investigation,
had been in a coma since shooting himself once with a .38-caliber
revolver at his home Dec. 12.
   His condition worsened Tuesday night as tests showed a
restricted blood flow to the brain. Final tests showed little blood
flow, and doctors decided Wednesday to remove him from life-support
systems, said Dr. Joseph C. Ross, an associate vice chancellor at
Vanderbilt University Medical Center.
   ``He essentially was found to have no brain function,'' Ross
said. ``It was comparable to an extensive or massive stroke.''
   Crowell, 57, never regained consciousness after the shooting. He
had remained in critical condition and was treated with intravenous
injections of a drug designed to remove fluids from the brain and
reduce swelling.
   Gov. Ned McWherter issued a statement of condolence to Crowell's
family, who were at the hospital when he died at 1:19 p.m.
   ``This is a sad and unfortunate time for his wife, Terrijean,
and their children, Melissa, Chris and Brooks,'' McWherter said.
   James W. Simmons was appointed by McWherter on Tuesday to fill
Crowell's role until the Jan. 9 convening of the Legislature, which
can appoint a successor.
   Controversy, much of it growing out of his passionate devotion
to the Democratic Party, followed Crowell during most of his 18
years in state government.
   He was once known as ``The Godfather'' on Capitol Hill because
of his absolute, partisan control over legislation in the dual
roles of chairman of the House Democratic Caucus and the House
Calendar Committee.
   As secretary of state, he was in charge of regulating bingo and
spending by lobbyists and political campaigns, all of which were
involved in the federal-state investigation into public corruption.
   He testified in September and November 1989 before federal grand
juries in Nashville and Memphis investigating bingo corruption in
Tennessee. He said he was told by federal agents that he was not a
target of the investigation.
   As a result of the probe one former Crowell aide, former chief
bingo inspector W.D. ``Donnie'' Walker, has gone to federal prison
in Alabama; his longtime aide, Mary Sue Wright, has been named an
unindicted co-conspirator and given immunity from prosecution.
   Ms. Wright kept the books on a campaign fund started by Crowell
and two other constitutional officers on behalf of Democratic
candidates for the Legislature. She admitted taking thousands of
dollars from the fund, and a federal grand jury in Memphis has
subpoenaed records from it.
   The secretary of state's office had regulated charitable bingo
since it was legalized for charity fund-raising in 1971. It did not
become controversial, however, until 1979, when the Legislature
outlawed bingo on the final day of the session.
   After protracted negotiations between the House and Senate, the
game was made legal again in 1980 and the Office of Charitable
Solicitations was put in charge. Every year thereafter, the
Legislature amended the bingo law in an effort to weed out
professional gambling.
   In October 1987, Crowell revoked the bingo license for a
Kingsport AmVets post on grounds the group gave little of its
profits to charity. The case was appealed up to the state Supreme
Court, which ruled bingo an unconstitutional lottery in February
1989.
</TEXT>

</DOC>