<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1344EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ProfessionalMoms 1stLd-Writethru a0551 12-28 0629</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Professional Moms, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0551,0643</SECOND>
<HEAD>Welfare Mothers Paid to Care for Disabled Children</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 8th graf, `Sharobeem said...,' to CLARIFY that family of
four costs state $16,000 a year, rather than receives that amount. SUBS
12th graf, `The mothers ...,' to CLARIFY average age of children.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAN DESMOND</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ROYAL OAK, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fourteen mothers who were once on
welfare have found jobs doing what they know best _ being moms.
   The women have been taken off government assistance and receive
$21,000 annual salaries for being foster mothers to disabled
children under a state program called LIFE, or Living in Family
Environments.
   ``These women are capable of doing something, but for the most
part they're best at being moms, and they're happy being moms,''
said state Rep. Shirley Johnson, who helped win funding for the
program.
   ``I was scared to death at the beginning _ how would you match
the right mom with the right child? But it has worked beautifully.''
   The 3-year-old program, which operates primarily on a $200,000
grant from the state Department of Mental Health, was the idea of
Mounir Sharobeem, president of the Judson Center in Royal Oak, a
Detroit suburb. The center helps abused and neglected children and
disabled adults.
   ``Instead of stereotyping welfare recipients as lazy, let's
train the families, let them select a developmentally disabled
child and use their time and energy more effectively,'' Sharobeem
said.
   ``People said we would be endangering handicapped children by
putting them with welfare families. But these families have been
doing a great job with them, and it's not easy.''
   Sharobeem said one disabled child in an institution costs the
Mental Health Department $45,000 a year. A welfare family of four
costs the Department of Social Services $16,000 a year.
   The children are also given more personal care inside a home,
even though most of the mothers are single parents, Sharobeem said.
   The mothers are screened and licensed by the Judson Center and
receive training in caring for disabled children, said Diane
Devine-Abdullah, LIFE director.
   ``They go through a seven-day, 28-hour training, then 20 hours
home training in a current foster home,'' Devine-Abdullah said.
``We have four more families ready and waiting for placement.''
   The mothers are then matched with children from Michigan
institutions. The average age of most of the children is between 15
and 16, Devine-Abdullah said.
   DSS Director C. Patrick Babcock said the state is looking to
expand the program. But Johnson said budget constraints won't allow
a full-scale program.
   One mother, Darlene Gisel of Warren, cares for 11-month-old
William, who was born with tuberculosis of the brain. The condition
was stabilized but could result in a learning disability or
retardation.
   ``He was in the hospital six months before I took him,'' Gisel
said. ``He didn't respond at all. He's gotten farther than they
ever thought he would.
   ``There's a lot of joy in watching them grow. These are kids who
probably wouldn't have had a chance in life.''
   Gisel said her mother also was a foster mom and worked with
handicapped children.
   ``I knew I wanted to deal with handicapped kids,'' she said.
``They need a little more of a chance. I think we can show that
they can learn and they can live a normal life with a disability.''
   Mothers in the LIFE program also find that the salary allows
them to provide more for their own children.
   Bertha Crawford is foster mother to Dorothy, 17, who can't dress
herself and can't talk. Crawford also has two high-school-age
children of her own.
   ``I feel good about helping someone else,'' Crawford said. ``It
also gave me the chance to send my daughter on her senior trip. I
couldn't have afforded it without the program.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>