<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1630EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-PanamaPool-Prison     12-23 0382</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama Pool-Prison,390</SECOND>
<HEAD>Anti-Noriega Military Prisoners Take Over Prison</HEAD>
<HEAD>Editors Note: The following is from pool dispatches filed by Steven
Komarow of The Associated Press, Kathy Lewis of the Houston Post, Kevin
Merida of The Dallas Morning News, Bill Clayton of the Houston Chronicle
and Dick Thompson of Time magazine.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A group of Panamanian prisoners,
including a military officer involved in the ill-fated coup in
October, took over an island penitentiary and asked for help from
the United States, U.S. military officials said Saturday.
   The prison, which had been run by loyalists to Gen. Manuel
Antonio Noriega, is on an island off Panama's Pacific coast about
60 miles from the capital.
   U.S. officials said the prisoner revolt was led by a man
identified only as ``Major Pajaro'' who was said to be one of the
leaders of the unsuccessful coup against Noriega on Oct. 3.
   No other details of the prison revolt were available.
   Meanwhile, U.S. military officials said small bands of Noriega
supporters were continuing harassing attacks in the capital.
   Lt. Col. Jerry Marguila, spokesman for the U.S. Southern
Command, said the hit-and-run Noriega loyalists are ``increasing
their activities of harassing attacks with small arms and mortar
fire, threatening the civilian population, and hostage-taking.''
   When pressed for specific numbers, Marguila replied ``I don't
have in my mind an increase in numbers between today and yesterday
of dignity-battalion efforts. It's just that they are becoming more
of a concern, because they are taking more of our time as opposed
to the PDF (Panama Defense Force).''
   Marguila said the task of the U.S. troops is turning from
conventional warfare to counterterrorism and police duties.
   The U.S. military spokesman said ``armed bandits'' continue to
roam many parts of Panama City and that looting has moved from
shopping districts into some upperclass residential neighborhoods
where residents have been arming themselves.
   Marguila said that with the neutralizing of the PDF by the U.S.
military the country is without an adequate police force to deal
with the lawlessness.
   ``The PDF was involved in just about every nook and cranny of
the government. Since that element is gone, there is a void and a
gap, especially in the police force ... and that is something we
need to rebuild,'' the spokesman said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>