<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0184 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2139EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Sihanouk     12-18 0448</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sihanouk,0460</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sihanouk to Vacate U.N. Seat Only Under Certain Conditions</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prince Norodom Sihanouk, the exiled Cambodian
leader, said Monday that his resistance coalition will vacate its
U.N. seat only if the Vietnamese-installed government in Cambodia
is dismantled.
   Austalia's deputy secretary of foreign affairs, Michael
Costello, briefed Sihanouk and Chinese leaders separately on
Australia's suggestion that the United Nations set up an interim
administration in Cambodia so free elections can be held.
   Costello also met with Premier Li Peng, who said he hoped
friendly relations could be restored between Australia and China.
Relations have been strained following China's June crackdown on
pro-democracy demonstrators, which like most Western countries
Australia condemned.
   Sihanouk has said free elections are not possible in Cambodia
while the Vietnamese-installed government under Hun Sen remains in
office. Hun Sen, however, has demanded the resistance vacate
Cambodia's seat in the United Nations to ensure U.N. impartiality
while it acts as trustee.
   Costello's meeting at Sihanouk's residence in Beijing was
closed, but the prince later issued a 27-page open letter to
Costello, condemning Hun Sen's government and specifying his terms
for any U.N. trusteeship.
   ``I don't accept declaring Cambodia's seat vacant before the
simultaneous dismantling of the (resistance) and Hun Sen's `State
of Cambodia,' and the replacement of the illegal, pro-Vietnamese
administration of Hun Sen with a purely U.N. administration in all
villages and provinces,'' the letter said.
   Vietnam invaded neighboring Cambodia in late 1987 and ousted the
ruling Khmer Rouge, who had imposed a reign of terror. However, the
United Nations and many governments, including that of the United
States, recognize Sihanouk's three-party resistance coalition as
the rightful Cambodian government.
   Hun Sen has said he is willing to allow elections, but has
rejected Sihanouk's demand that he first dismantle his government
and set up an interim government representing all Cambodian
parties, including the Khmer Rouge. The Khmer Rouge are part of
Sihanouk's coalition.
   The issue remained stalemated until Australian Foreign Minister
Gareth Evans suggested in November that the United Nations
administer Cambodia during elections.
   Costello has met with officials in Cambodia, Vietnam and
Thailand to explain the proposal.
   The Australian Embassy said Costello's talks would be limited to
the problem of Cambodia and would not cover bilateral issues.
However, China's official Xinhua News Agency quoted Li Peng as
saying that although the two countries differ on some issues, ``We
still hope friendly, cooperative relations are restored.''
   He said, ``We stand for the forward-looking attitude and hope
both sides will join hands for this.''
   Australia suspended high-level exchanges with China following
the Chinese army attack on pro-democracy protesters in Beijing. The
embassy said Costello's visit did not indicate an end of this
sanction.
</TEXT>

</DOC>