<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0051EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     12-19 0702</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0734</SECOND>
<HEAD>On the Light Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GRAND RAPIDS, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Milton Halverson has sent the same
birthday card to his longtime pal Arleen Carlson for 50 years.
   And she sends it right back.
   Mended over the years by strips of transparent tape now yellow
and brittle, the card is the kind that could put a greeting card
company out of business.
   Known as a ``thrifty card,'' it features a piece of glazed paper
on which the giver writes his or her name in pencil. The idea is
explained in a Scottish verse inside that ends, ``Ye can just wash
off my name, write in your own ye see. Then when my birthday comes
around, ye can send it back tae me.''
   ``And that's what we've been doing for the past 50 years,'' said
Halverson, who on Monday mailed the card for the 100th time.
   Carlson, who turns 72 on Saturday, has been friends with
Halverson since the two grew up together in Amery, Wis., where
Carlson still lives.
   She remembers buying the card in an Amery drugstore for 5 cents,
and mailing it for 2 cents. Halverson first received the card when
he was 10.
   ``I even received this (in Germany) when I was in the Army,''
the 59-year-old telephone repairman said. ``And I'd fire it right
back.''
   They'll keep firing away, too.
   ``I wouldn't want a new card. That would take all the fun out of
it,'' Halverson said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CAPE GIRARDEAU, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Last-minute Christmas shoppers, if
you're looking to splurge there's something big on the market: two
entire villages.
   New Hanover and Arnsberg, replicas of 19th-century European
villages built in the Black Forest in southeastern Missouri, are
for sale.
   The villages, which are unincorporated and uninhabited, were
built by the late Burton Gerhardt as a tribute to the early German
settlement of the area.
   In September, they were sold for $493,500 to East Perry Lumber
Co., along with the 1,041-acre forest. Company officials don't want
the 29 quaint buildings, the covered bridge or the 600 feet of
railroad track. They only want the trees.
   ``We don't want to get into the tourist business and it is too
nice just to sit idle,'' said Sonny Lueders, East Perry's
secretary-treasurer.
   The company has received about 10 inquiries but no offers since
the towns went up for sale. Lueders isn't revealing the asking
price.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WEST HOMESTEAD, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pennsylvania's 69-year-old entry in
this spring's Ms. Senior America Pageant has her racy routine down
pat. It's from all the practice at nursing homes.
   Dorothy Hileman said audiences seem to like her delicate shimmy
to ``Itsy Bitsy Teenie Weenie Yellow Polka Dot Bikini.''
   So far, the West Homestead woman has performed the dance at
about 35 nursing homes.
   ``I'm very careful,'' she said Monday. ``Dignity is a very
important criterion in the pageant.''
   She won her state title two months ago, entering as Ms. Senior
Steel Valley under the sponsorship of a company that operates
senior citizen centers in southwestern Pennsylvania. Forty-four
friends traveled to the pageant and rang cowbells in support.
   The former ninth-grade science teacher begins her dance in a
blue gown. She then pops behind a screen and comes out modestly
wrapped in a yellow towel. When daintily dropped, a fringed black
and gold polka dot outfit is revealed.
   She never undresses to a ``itsy bitsy'' bikini, however.
Underneath she wears a full-length beige leotard.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A manufacturing mistake has struck a sour note
with the Dallas Symphony Orchestra.
   The producer of compact discs for the Pro Arts record company
mislabeled up to 1,000 compact discs, according to the orchestra's
music administrator, Victor Marshall.
   ``I found out about it when members of the orchestra bought the
recording of Gustav Holst's `The Planets' to see how they sounded
and discovered that they had bought a Christian rock group album,''
said Marshall.
   Many of the discs have been recalled, but Marshall said he still
has 50 of them.
   ``I don't even know who the rock group is, but I don't really
want to throw the discs away,'' Marshall said. ``I may string them
on a wire and turn them into a mobile for my office.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>