<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0206 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1025EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-WallStreet10am     12-19 0335</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Wall Street 10am,0352</SECOND>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The stock market declined broadly today amid
lingering worries about the future course of the economy.
   The Dow Jones average of 30 industrials, down 56.10 points in
the past two sessions, slipped 1.50 to 2,696.03 in the first half
hour today.
   Losers outnumbered gainers by more than 2 to 1 in nationwide
trading of New York Stock Exchange-listed issues, with 295 up, 713
down and 541 unchanged.
   Volume on the Big Board came to 24.50 million shares as of 10
a.m. on Wall Street.
   Analysts said the latest economic reports from the government
hadn't done much to pull the market out of its recent slide,
induced to a great extent by worries about the real estate market
and mortgage debt.
   The Labor Department reported that the consumer price index rose
0.4 percent in November, or at an annual rate of 4.9 percent. That
appeared to put a new obstacle before any fresh moves by the
Federal Reserve to relax its credit policy.
   Separate government figures showed a 4.7 percent decline in
housing starts last month.
   Brokers said that left stocks in the grip of recession fears and
of talk that a slump in business conditions might be exacerbated by
a weak market for homes and other real-estate properties.
   But a few recently depressed banking and mortgage stocks staged
a rebound. Federal National Mortgage rose ] to 31{, and Bank of New
England gained ] to 7~.
   The NYSE's composite index of all its listed common stocks
dropped .47 to 189.70. At the American Stock Exchange, the market
value index was down 1.52 at 369.34.
   On Monday the Dow Jones industrial average fell 42.02 to
2,697.53, for its biggest single-day loss since it dropped 47.34
points on Nov. 6.
   Declining issues outnumbered advances by more than 7 to 2 on the
NYSE, with 350 up, 1,279 down and 359 unchanged..
   Big Board volume came to an estimated 187 million shares,
against 240.39 million in the previous session.
</TEXT>

</DOC>