<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0120 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1331EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Bush-AIDSPatients 1stLd-Writethru a0456 12-22 0569</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bush-AIDS Patients, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0456,560</SECOND>
<HEAD>President Visits Children in NIH AIDS Wards</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 10 grafs to UPDATE with Bush's visit at NIH AIDS
wards; PICKUP 7th graf, bgng ``I think.'' Preced WASHINGTON</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BETHESDA, Md. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush appealed today to Americans
to demonstrate compassion for victims of AIDS, saying that a
``misplaced fear'' of the deadly disease was preventing some people
from helping.
   Bush underscored his point by touring the clinical wards of the
National Institutes of Health, meeting children ranging in age from
less than a year to early teens who are being treated with
experimental AIDS drugs. He was accompanied by his wife, Barbara.
   Later, addressing health professionals involved in fighting
AIDS, Bush said, he wanted to educate ``Americans who don't want to
help, don't want to become involved because of a misplaced fear.
   ``They're afraid of holding an AIDS patient because they're
frightened of getting AIDS,'' the president said.
   ``Barbara and I want to say and we hope we can continue to
demonstrate this: They are wrong. They are simply uninformed. They
are wrong about that.''
   He praised the courage of doctors and nurses and parents and
counselors who are working against AIDS.
   Bush said that after being ``in a room full of kids with AIDS
... I thought of how there is no reason to fear for your health _
just their health,'' the president said.
   ``And I want to thank those who are not afraid, especially
foster parents who have opened their homes and their hearts and
those of you here today who do so much for so many.''
   Bush said, ``Only together can we wage all-out war against this
terrible killer.''
   There are about 30 children in the NIH AIDS wards now. They are
all being treated experimentally with a variety of doses and types
of drugs designed to fight the human immunodeficiency virus, or
HIV, that causes AIDS, or acquired immune deficiency syndrome.
   ``I think the visit is to cheer up the troops who work with AIDS
patients,'' said spokeswoman Ann Thomas.
   Health and Human Services Secretary Louis D. Sullivan and his
wife, Ginger, were accompanying the president and Mrs. Bush on the
45-minute NIH tour.
   An HHS source said Bush asked Sullivan to arrange the visit ``to
say think you to the NIH staff.''
   ``He really wants to acknowledge the hard work and dedication of
these people,'' the source said.
   Sullivan told reporters that Bush is making the tour ``to
demonstrate his personal support for biomedical research and NIH.''
   No personnel announcements were expected during the presidential
visit. The directorship of NIH has been vacant since James
Wyngaarten resigned last July.
   The children infected with the AIDS received the virus from
their mothers at birth or from blood transfusions.
   They are being treated with zidovudine, commonly called AZT, and
with a new experimental AIDS drug called DDI.
   ``All of the patients are here as voluntary research subjects,''
said Ms. Haske.
   It was research of this type that led Sullivan in October to
approve distribution of AZT for treatment of children with AIDS.
AZT, which now is the only approved AIDS drug, formerly was
reserved only for adult patients because there was concern that
side effects from the drug would be more severe among children.
   DDI is now in advanced clinical trials, but has not been
approved for general prescription use.
</TEXT>

</DOC>