<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0118 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2012EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-FarmScene 1stLd-Writethru a0600 12-21 0791</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Farm Scene, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0600,0795</SECOND>
<HEAD>Farmers Earning Less Than Economists Said</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf pvs `It doesn't ...' with 1 graf to CORRECT spelling
of Gajewski, sted Gajeweski</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also moved for PMs</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Newly revised income figures by the
Agriculture Department show that farmers haven't been making as
much money the last few years as agency economists had been
reporting.
   The Economic Research Service, the department's professional
agency that keeps the financial books on agriculture, on Wednesday
issued revised estimates reflecting higher expenses than had been
used in the earlier computations.
   ``It doesn't change what actually happened, of course,'' said
agency economist Greg Gajewski. ``It changes our perception ... but
I can't see that it changes the direction of anything.''
   One of the effects was to reduce the net cash income of farmers
_ the money left over after deducting cash expenses from gross cash
proceeds during the calendar year. It includes government payments
and proceeds from crops grown in earlier years.
   The revisions, based on 1987 figures from the federal census of
agriculture, showed that net cash income in 1987 was $54.5 billion
instead of the $57.7 billion reported as recently as a month ago.
   In 1988, according to the revisions, net cash income of farmers
rose to $57.2 billion _ not to the $59.9 billion stated previously.
   This year, according to the agency's new report, the net cash
income of farmers may be in the range of $52 billion to $57
billion. That is unchanged from the earlier forecast.
   Gajewski, who oversees preparation of the monthly report, said
that the 1987 census benchmark now being used showed that farm
expenses turn out about 3 percent higher than had been estimated
earlier.
   ``It suggests farmers did a little less well than we thought
they were doing,'' Gajewski said in a telephone interview.
   But he noted that despite the downward revisions, the new income
numbers for those years are still records and that ``the rebound
from the financial crisis is still very real.''
   The revised figures also prompted changes in another method of
farm accounting used by the agency. That involves ``net farm
income'' which measures the value of production, including federal
payments, in a specific year. Changes in the value of crop and
livestock inventories are part of the annual accounting.
   Under this method, net farm income in 1987 was $43.5 billion
instead of the $47.1 billion reported previously. In 1988, net farm
income was revised to $42.7 billion from $45.7 billion.
   This year's estimate was pegged at $48 billion instead of in a
range of $48 billion to $53 billion used a month ago.
   Gajewski said the revisions are ``part of the profession'' of
economics and are done regularly, year after year.
   ``When the government stops revising numbers, that's when you
have to start really worrying,'' he said. ``To some extent, it take
a lot of courage to go back and lower income numbers.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Agriculture Department says China has
bought additional U.S. wheat under a price subsidy program.
   F. Paul Dickerson, general sales manager for the department's
Foreign Agricultural Service, said Wednesday seven private
exporting companies made the deals for a total of 410,000 metric
tons under the department's Export Enhancement Program, or EEP.
   Delivery of the wheat is scheduled for February and March, he
said.
   The sales were part of 1 million tons authorized under EEP on
Dec. 5. A previous allocation of 2 million tons made last Feb. 27
had been exhausted, except for 10,000 tons.
   With the latest EEP approvals, China has 600,000 tons remaining
to be used under the current authorization.
   A metric ton is about 2,205 pounds and is equal to 36.7 bushels
of wheat. The latest sales would be about 15 million bushels. At
current prices estimated by USDA at $3.85 per bushel, the wheat
would have a farm value of around $58 million.
   Under EEP arrangements, private exporters can sell U.S.
commodities at reduced prices to meet foreign competition in
selected overseas markets and then collect free government
surpluses of grain or other commodities as bonuses, or subsidies.
   Dickerson said the latest subsidies averaged $19.26 per ton, or
about 52 cents per bushel.
   The subsidized sales were handled by Cargill Inc., 125,000 tons;
Continental Grain Co., 80,000; Coprostates Inc., 50,000; Louis
Dreyfus Corp., 40,000; Peavy Co., 40,000; Tradigrain Inc., 40,000;
and Mitsubishi International Corp., 35,000.
   With the latest sales, China has bought about 5.1 million tons
of U.S. wheat for delivery in the 1989-90 marketing year that began
on June 1, most of it without subsidies. In 1988-89, China bought
more than 8 million tons of U.S. wheat, all of it under the EEP
program.
</TEXT>

</DOC>