<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 2338EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania 10thLd-Writethru 1stAdd 12-25 0684</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania, 10th Ld-Writethru, 1st Add, a0401,0700</SECOND>
<HEAD>BUCHAREST: War II.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Heavy explosions boomed near the Hotel Intercontinental and
volleys of sniper fire were answered immediately with staccato
bursts of automatic weapons.
   There were widely conflicting reports on the number of
casualties claimed by the revolution.
   Hungarian radio named unspecified ``authoritative sources'' as
saying that between 70,000 and 80,000 people had died. Then it
cited Victor Ciobanu, health minister under Ceausescu and now in
opposition to him, as denying that such a large number of people
had died.
   While unable to provide overall casualty figures, he told
reporters 500 people had died in Bucharest alone over the past four
days, and 2,000 were wounded.
   That was on the low end of several estimates offered by
officials and appeared to contradict figures given by doctors
operating on the wounded. There was no way to independently verify
the casualty figures.
   At Bucharest Emergency Hospital, doctors who had not slept in
three days said they had treated 2,000 civilians since Thursday, a
fraction of the city total. By Sunday afternoon, 90 bodies had
arrived at one of several morgues.
   Army troops sealed off wide areas of the battle-scarred capital
in preparation for a building-to-building search of other
Securitate snipers supporting Ceausescu.
   A member of the new National Salvation Committee said his
transitional government was in control of Romania, but acknowledged
that much remained to be done.
   ``Even myself, I spent all night at the emergecy hospital,'' Ion
Grigorescu said, lifting a cuff to show a bandage and producing the
sniper's bullet that caught him in the leg as he went to the radio.
   By Monday, at least 12 nations _ including the United States _
had recognized the new leadership.
   Christmas dominated Bucharest despite the turmoil, with radio
broadcasting Mass and Christmas carols for the first time in
decades, and churches filled to overflowing.
   At the Patriarhie Orthodox cathedral in downtown Bucharest,
worshipers caught an agent of the security police trying to sneak a
hand grenade into Christmas Mass, after a woman started shouting,
``We know this man! He's a terrorist!'' He was led away by soldiers
armed with automatic rifles.
   Weekend reports that foreigners had been fighting alongside
Ceausescu's elite troops appeared to be gaining some credence
Monday.
   Doctors at the Emergency Hospital said they treated two men they
identified only as Arabs, and two more believed to be North Koreans.
   One of the Arabs admitted under sedation to being part of a
400-man elite Ceausescu guard committed to holding out until death
if needed for the defense of Ceausescu, said one of the doctors,
asking that he not be named.
   The crackling of machine-gun fire could be heard from some
Bucharest suburbs, but did not deter crowds from taking to the
streets.
   People clustered around spontaneous soapbox speakers denouncing
communism and generally enjoying their first chance to sound off in
public in four generations.
   The media, under the stern grip of censorship for more than four
decades, also was showing a freer face.
   Spark, the rigidly loyal Communist Party newspaper that was
dominated by pictures and reports of Ceausescu up to his fall,
appeared under the name of The Truth. Monday's edition published an
appeal of the National Salvation Committee _ the interim leadership
of the country _ for all civilians to surrender their arms,
alongside letters from former Ceausescu officials expressing
support for the committee.
   Among the array of new newspapers sprouting up over the weekend
was one called Free Youth, which denounced Ceausescu as the
``world's most atrocious criminal'' _ language unthinkable just 11
days ago.
   ``We have lost an epic of darkness and unthinkable terror on
Earth, we have also lost the fear to go out on the steets and
defend Romania with our hearts,'' a front-page editorial in Free
Youth proclaimed.
   Thousands of Romanians reportedly were massacred by security
officers who opened fire on unarmed anti-government protesters in
the western Romanian city of Timisoara Dec. 17, two days after the
start of demonstrations. The revolt spread across the country and
reached Bucharest Thursday when students defied gunfire to chant
for freedom.
</TEXT>

</DOC>