<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0202 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0712EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-Hugo-Christmas Adv22-24   12-21 0773</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Hugo-Christmas, Adv 22-24,0796</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv22</HEAD>
<HEAD>$adv23</HEAD>
<HEAD>$adv24</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Weekend Editions, Dec. 22-24, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Christmas After the Hurricane: Spirit Shines in Lights, Donated Toys</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leea in 9th graf is cq</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRUCE SMITH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, S.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For thousands in the area devastated by
Hurricane Hugo, the traditional Southern Christmas Day feast will
come in a cardboard box donated by the Salvation Army. So much has
been lost by so many, and yet the spirit of the season shines
through.
   It's there in Christmas lights twinkling for the first time in
Charleston's Historic District; it's there in acts of kindness,
small and large.
   ``I wanted to do something to help. This seemed the best thing
to do,'' Ray Cook said as he helped wire a new house in Mount
Pleasant for Elizabeth Edwards, who lost her home to Hugo's 135 mph
winds.
   Cook, who lives in Aiken, and a friend, Bruce McLauchlin of
Hopewell, Va., spent a week of this month helping build the
832-square-foot house. Both the home and their labor were donated.
   The new house is ``the best thing that's happened in my whole
life,'' said Mrs. Edwards, who hopes to move in with her niece and
her niece's daughter by Christmas.
   Meanwhile, donated toys are pouring into the state from across
the nation to provide a brighter Christmas for other families hit
hard by the storm.
   At least 30,000 toys have been contributed and social service
officials say the total should climb much higher as Christmas nears.
   Five days before Christmas, the Toys for Tots campaign in
Charleston had received 18,000 toys _ 10,000 more than it
distributed last year _ and hundreds more were expected, said Staff
Sgt. Ozell Register, chairman of the Marine Reserve-sponsored
effort.
   Another collection effort was launched by a Beaufort couple, Bud
and Evelyn Culbertson, after their 6-year-old daughter, Leea,
started crying when she saw pictures of Hugo's devastation.
   ``She was concerned about the kids. She wanted to give away all
of her toys,'' Culbertson said.
   The family has collected about 15,000 toys since late September,
he said.
   Meanwhile, there's still a keen demand for food, furniture,
blankets and kerosene heaters among storm victims three months
after Hugo slammed into South Carolina at Charleston on Sept. 21,
said Capt. Jim Worthy, the Salvation Army commander for Charleston.
   The storm left 29 dead in South Carolina and $6 billion in
damage.
   Last Christmas, the Salvation Army donated about 1,600 Christmas
baskets containing food for a family of four for a week. This year,
about 4,500 will be distributed. But, Worthy said, the demand will
continue long after Christmas.
   ``We have adequate food right now. We're getting a lot of
Christmas help. Traditionally, after Christmas it will stop and
that's when the real crunch will come,'' he said.
   In Charleston, Christmas lights have blossomed in places they
were never seen before _ on the palmettos along Broad Street and
lining the old Citadel building on Calhoun Square, making the
structure look like a fairy tale castle.
   ``We decided to do everything possible to show Christmas,'' said
Howard Chapman, coordinator of the city's relief effort. ``I think
people appreciate that. It gives them something to look forward to
and the children the hope the community is coming back.''
   Part of the display is the 89-foot Norway spruce which dominates
King Street. Strung with a mile of lights, the tree is believed to
be among the largest Christmas trees in the nation.
   ``This is a very special Christmas for all of us in our
community,'' Mayor Joseph P. Riley Jr. told thousands who turned
out for the tree lighting. ``Our community has shown we have the
Christmas spirit. I saw people who lost their homes who were
concerned about their fellow man. This year we have so much thanks
_ so much to be thankful for.''
   While the displays are helping weekend shopping business,
there's concern that seasonal business is lagging because of a
misconception that downtown buildings were gutted by the storm.
   Kris Holmes of the Market Area Merchants Association said the
association's 250 members are taking out ads _ in addition to
regular holiday advertising _ to dispel that misconception.
   Meanwhile, business at suburban shopping centers is brisk.
   Sales are up from last year, said Shirley Webb, assistant
manager of the Children's Palace store in West Ashley.
   ``My personal opinion is it's because of the hurricane,'' she
said. Customers are ``making up for some of the inconveniences,
especially for the children, and they're going to make this
Christmas better than before.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Dec. 22-24</NOTE>

</DOC>