<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0092 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1314EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-JailDesign     12-29 0320</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jail Design,0329</SECOND>
<HEAD>Frank Lloyd Wright Colleagues Blast New Jail Design</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN RAFAEL, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Associates of Frank Lloyd Wright have
asked Marin County officials to redesign a proposed $23 million
jail rather than ``denigrate'' the memory of the renowned architect.
   The two-story jail, with up to 219 cells, would be built in
front of one of Wright's most famous works _ the Marin County Civic
Center, whose pale pink arches sweep across three small knolls
along busy U.S. Highway 101.
   The center is the only government building designed by Wright
that actually was built.
   William Wesley Peters, senior architect and chairman of the
board of trustees of the Frank Lloyd Wright Foundation, and San
Francisco architect Aaron Green, who worked closely with Wright,
wrote to the county Board of Supervisors last week, saying they
were appalled by the jail design. They asked that it be redone to
harmonize with the Wright's building.
   The rectangular jail would stand 24 feet high and would obscure
much of the view of the civic center.
   The project is ``callously different from the soft and graceful
lines of Frank Lloyd Wright's Hall of Justice and Administration
Building'' and would be ``the antithesis of what Frank Lloyd Wright
had so creatively conceived,'' Green wrote.
   Peters told supervisors the project ``would seriously denigrate
Frank Lloyd Wright's legacy to Marin County, to California and to
the world.''
   But county supervisors, who are under court order to relieve
jail crowding, say it is unlikely the design will be significantly
changed.
   ``We just don't have time,'' said Supervisor Al Aramburu. ``It's
the best we could do, given the site.''
   Construction must begin by next fall so the county can qualify
for state money for the project.
   ``If the board is to stop this, its members should be thrown in
jail. It would be criminal to lose the state bond money,'' said
Robert Stockwell, president of the board.
</TEXT>

</DOC>