<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0124 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1718EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SAC-Soviets     12-18 0349</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SAC-Soviets,0359</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Students To Tour SAC Headquarters</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARYANN MROWCA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>OMAHA, Neb. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eight Soviet students will tour the
underground Strategic Air Command headquarters Friday in what may
be the first such tour of the nuclear weapons command center,
officials said Monday.
   Col. Larry Greer, a SAC spokesman, said it was coincidental that
the tour comes amid changes in Eastern Europe and improved
Soviet-American relations.
   But school officials might have never considered asking SAC for
the tour if it weren't for the apparently improving relations, said
Di Saggau, a spokeswoman for the Westside Community Schools.
   The tour of SAC underground is apparently the first by a Soviet
group, and it will be a little different from other tours, Greer
said.
   ``We're not going to bear down on nuclear deterence,'' although
that is part of SAC's mission, Greer said. ``It's a fact. It's well
known. If they can read, they know it.''
   SAC is the Air Force's long-range strike force of manned bombers
and intercontinental ballistic missiles. Since 1961, it has flown
round-the-clock flights in project Looking Glass, which would take
charge of nuclear forces if the president and other leaders were
killed.
   Five Soviet girls and three boys, ages 15-17, have been in the
United States since Nov. 27 in an exchange program with Westside
High School. They are to leave Dec. 27, and a group of Westside
students is to visit the Soviet Union in March.
   The Soviet students' teacher-interpreter and eight American
students will accompany them on the SAC tour, Saggau and Greer said.
   SAC, at Offutt Air Force Base near Omaha, will follow its normal
security precautions for civilians, including keeping the group
together on the tour, Greer said.
   SAC officials will modify the Soviet briefing because of
language concerns and because they think teen-agers are more
interested in the technological gadgets and wizardry than in broad
policy, he said.
   The students also will make radio contact with a base in Alaska.
``I want to remind the Soviet kids that we're just a few miles west
of them,'' Greer said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>