<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0186 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2356EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Wallace     12-21 0382</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Wallace,0395</SECOND>
<HEAD>Aviation Pioneer Dwane Wallace Of Cessna Aircraft Co. Dies At 78</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Dwane is CQ</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL BATES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WICHITA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Aviation pioneer Dwane Wallace, who guided
Cessna Aircraft Co. to dominance in the light plane industry, died
Thursday. He was 78.
   ``He was a shy, modest American hero,'' said William Wentz,
director of the Institute for Aviation Research at Wichita State
University, Wallace's alma mater. ``He was happier talking to
engineers and pilots than he was a bunch of company presidents,
university trustees and such.''
   Wentz credited Wallace with being the first to sell
single-engine aircraft as a tool for businessmen. He said Wallace
also was a trailblazer in the transition to all-metal from
cloth-covered planes.
   Wallace had been hospitalized about six weeks at HCA Wesley
Medical Center. The family asked hospital officials not to release
information about his condition. He reportedly had suffered a
stroke.
   until recent months, he had remained active supervising his
business investments and piloting airplanes on trips.
   Wallace worked briefly as an engineer for Walter Beech, founder
of Beech Aircraft Corp., after graduating from WSU in 1933. He
assumed control at Cessna after his uncle, company founder Clyde
Cessna, was forced to close by the Depression.
   Wallace and his attorney brother, Dwight, reopened the company
in 1934 in Wichita. Clyde Cessna, who had started it in 1927, was
installed as president. Dwane Wallace was general manager.
   The first Dwane Wallace design Cessna manufactured, the C-34,
was a classic monoplane that became world reknowned as the Cessna
Airmaster.
   In the early years, Wallace did selling, test flying and was
known occasionally to enter air races when finances were tight to
meet the payroll with his winnings.
   Wallace relinquished his board chairmanship at Cessna in 1975,
staying on as a $75,000 a year consultant and a board member. He
later cut all ties with the company following a dispute with
current chairman Russ Meyer, his hand-picked successor. Wallace and
Meyer kept silent about the disagreement.
   ``Dwane left a legacy at Cessna which will continue to have a
positive effect for many years,'' Meyer said. ``He was an extremely
professional engineer who set high standards throughout the
company.''
   Wallace is survived by his wife, Velma; a sister, four daughters
and 11 grandchildren.
</TEXT>

</DOC>