<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0240EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Vessel-CoastGuard     12-20 0521</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Vessel-Coast Guard,520</SECOND>
<HEAD>NTSB Blames Deaths on Lack of Coast Guard Rules</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID BRISCOE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Federal safety investigators are blaming the
boat accident deaths of four people in Oregon last year on the
Coast Guard's failure to require lifeboats and a signal beacon on
the vessel that carried them.
   The National Transportation Safety Board has tried for years to
get the Coast Guard to toughen requirements for an estimated 4,700
small commercial vessels that are equipped to carry 300,000
passengers.
   ``There has been a long, documented absence of regulatory
action,'' said board member Jim Burnett.
   The NTSB's 3-0 decision Tuesday was the first time it has said
the service's lack of regulations contributed to deaths in an ocean
accident. The Sept. 15, 1988, incident off the coast of Oregon
involved the sinking of the Cougar, a 46-foot vessel used to carry
passengers on a fishing trip.
   After the boat took on water and sank, passengers and crew were
left in the cold Pacific Ocean, clinging to float devices and
debris, for 18 hours as searchers tried to locate them. The
captain, a deckhand and two passengers died. A ship's mate and four
other passengers survived.
   The last victim drowned 15 minutes before a helicopter rescued
the others about 35 miles out into the ocean, west of Depoe Bay,
investigators said.
   The board also blamed the Coast Guard for failing during
inspections to confirm the watertightness of hatchcovers on boat's
deck.
   Its report said the probable cause of the accident was the
captain's failure to ensure that his hatchcovers were watertight,
that the bilge pump was operating properly and that rubber flaps
designed to let water flow off the deck were correctly installed.
The captain was not identified in the report.
   The flaps were on the wrong side, preventing water from flowing
off the deck, investigators said. The ship sank in moderately heavy
seas while returning from a fishing trip, after its crew and
passengers tried for 90 minutes to remove water with buckets.
   The board for years has recommended that the Coast Guard require
all passenger boats to carry lifeboats that will keep all
passengers and crew out of the water if the ship sinks and that
emergency position indicating radio beacons, or EPRIBs, be carried
on all vessels so they can be quickly located by searchers.
   In the last five years, the board has investigated five
passenger vessel accidents, including two collisions, one fire, one
capsizing and one grounding. In each case, Coast Guard survival
craft requirements were found inadequate, but there has been no
change in the regulations.
   The board recommended that the Coast Guard require that within
five years all flotation devices and buoyant apparatus be replaced
by lifeboats, life rafts or inflatable devices that can keep people
out of the water.
   Passengers using flotation devices remain in the water where
they can suffer from a rapid loss of body heat, or hypothermia.
   The board also advised the Coast Guard to improve its testing
rules and procedures and require all passenger vessel operators to
file sailing plans before they set out.
</TEXT>

</DOC>