<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0249 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0149EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-BusinessHighlights     12-20 0789</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Business Highlights,0829</SECOND>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   American Airlines has reached agreement with
Eastern Airlines to buy Latin American routes and certain other
assets from the struggling carrier for $471 million.
   The deal, announced Tuesday, will give American Airlines 20
destinations in 15 Central and South American countries.
   In addition, American gets the Miami-London route authority of
Eastern's sister carrier, Continential Airlines, as well as
Eastern's routes from Miami and Tampa, Fla., to Toronto. Plus,
American gets Eastern slots at John F. Kennedy Airport in New York,
at Miami International Airport and San Juan, Puerto Rico.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government reported a 0.4 percent rise in
consumer inflation last month despite a drop in gasoline costs.
   November's seasonally adjusted increase in the Consumer Price
Index, which translated into an annual inflation rate of 4.9
percent, followed a brisk 0.5 percent rise in October and
relatively modest hikes from June through September, the Labor
Department reported Tuesday.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Housing starts dropped 4.7 percent in
November, pulled down by a big dip in multifamily construction, the
government said.
   The Commerce Department said Tuesday that new houses and
apartments were built at a seasonally adjusted annual rate of 1.36
million units in November, down from 1.43 million units in October.
   Total housing starts for the first 11 month of the year were
down 6.5 percent from the same period of 1988. Applications for
building permits, a barometer of future housing activity, edged
down 1.7 percent in November after rising 2.8 percent in October.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation's dominant long-distance telephone
company, American Telephone &amp; Telegraph Co., announced it will cut
basic, daytime interstate rates an average of 1.3 percent Jan. 1.
Evening rates will drop an average of 2.0 percent.
   AT&amp;T said Tuesday the lowered rates reflect reduced expenses,
mainly from reduced fees that AT&amp;T will pay in 1990 to local
telephone companies for access to local exchanges.
   AT&amp;T said the reductions were necessary under changes earlier
this year in the Federal Communications Commission's regulation of
long-distance charges. The FCC now imposes caps on AT&amp;T's
long-distance rates based on the company's long-distance expenses,
as opposed to a preset rate of return.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Federal antitrust regulators have cleared
investor Carl C. Icahn to acquire a bigger stake in USX Corp., the
Federal Trade Commission said.
   The agency said Tuesday it had granted Icahn early termination
of the waiting period required under federal law to ensure that
certain mergers and acquisitions do not violate antitrust law.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Michael R. Quinlan, president and chief executive
of McDonald's Corp., will succeed Fred L. Turner as chairman of the
world's largest restaurant chain on March 31, the company has
announced.
   Quinlan, 45, said Tuesday he wants to put the Golden Arches in
China and that McDonald's customers will likely see more
dinner-type entrees added to the menu in coming years.
   Turner, 56, will become senior chairman and continue as chairman
of the board's executive committee, McDonald's said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Environmental Protection Agency said it
has obtained court agreements calling for polluters to foot
estimated cleanup costs totaling $69.5 million at nine hazardous
waste sites targeted by the Superfund program.
   In addition, the polluters involved also will reimburse the
government $11.6 million for past costs, EPA officials said Tuesday
at briefing on recent Superfund enforcement cases.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush worked toward a final version
of a 1991 budget plan that sources said would include a record
$1.24 trillion in spending.
   Meanwhile, Bush on Tuesday signed a deficit-fighting bill
trimming the budget for this year.
   Despite Bush's ``no new taxes'' vows, the new federal budget
also is likely to propose a series of new excise taxes, including a
fee on the sale of certain recreational equipment and vehicles,
said officials who spoke on the condition of anonymity.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Federal engineers have upgraded an
investigation of a possible steering deficiency in the 1988
Chevrolet Beretta, the government said.
   The National Highway Traffic Safety Administration also said
Tuesday it was investigating reports of exploding heating systems
in Coachmen Industries recreational vehicles and of cruise control
failures in the Ford Taurus and its twin, the Mercury Sable.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Stock prices continued to sag Tuesday amid persistent worries
about the future course of the economy. The Dow Jones industrial
average slipped 1.92 to 2,695.61, extending its loss over the past
four sessions to 65.48 points.
   The dollar finished slightly higher.
   Bond prices were mixed and Treasury bill yields rose.
   Forecasts for a frosty weekend in Florida's citrus belt drove
orange juice futures prices up sharply, while grains and soybeans,
livestock and meat, and precious-metals futures were mixed.
</TEXT>

</DOC>