<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1541EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Lebanon-Israel     12-26 0577</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon-Israel,0595</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israelis Destroy Two Guerrilla Posts in Lebanon, 9 Killed</HEAD>
<HEAD>By RODEINA KENAAN</HEAD>
<HEAD>Associated Press Writer</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RMEILE, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israeli warplanes destroyed a Communist
Party command post south of Beirut Tuesday, hours after
paratroopers backed by tanks and air cover wiped out another
Communist base in southeastern Lebanon.
   Police said nine people were killed and 26 wounded in the two
attacks.
   In Beirut, the Lebanese army defused a car rigged with 165
pounds of explosives near Prime Minister Salim Hoss' office 30
minutes before it was set to go off, police said.
   ``A bloodbath has been averted,'' said a police spokesman. Hoss,
a Sunni Moslem, was at home five blocks away when the bomb was
discovered and did not appear to be the target, the spokesman said
on condition of anonymity.
   Police said at least seven people were killed and 23 wounded in
the five-minute air raid that wrecked the two-story Communist Party
headquarters in the coastal town of Rmeile, 20 miles south of the
capital.
   The building took at least two direct rocket hits as six Phantom
F-4 fighter-bombers attacked it. Rescuers searched the wreckage for
more victims late Tuesday. Reporters heard moans and screams from
beneath the debris.
   Among those killed was Communist commander codenamed Abu Rabei,
who just before his death screamed for his 22-year-old daughter,
still buried in the ruins.
   In Jerusalem, the Israeli military command said its warplanes
returned to their bases. It said the Communists had organized and
launched attacks on Israeli forces and the South Lebanon Army, an
Israeli-backed Lebanese militia.
   Police said two other Communist guerrillas were killed and three
wounded as Israeli paratroopers earlier destroyed the Communist
base at Nabi Safi, in the foothills of Mount Hermon 7{ miles north
of the zone Israel occupies in south Lebanon.
   The two-hour assault was the Israeli army's heaviest ground
operation in Lebanon since an assault against the Syrian-backed
Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine-General Command Dec.
9, 1988.
   The attack force of 100 commandos advanced from the border
enclave, occupied by Israel since 1982, in four tanks and eight
armored personnel carriers behind a massive artillery barrage,
police reported.
   The attackers stormed through the villages of Kfar Meshki and
Lebbaya in the eastern Bekaa Valley after two helicopter gunships
blasted the villages with eight rockets, destroying many houses,
the spokesman said.
   Forty other paratroopers were then dropped by helicopters in
Nabi Safa, where they blew up the Communists' two-story command
post, the spokesman added.
   The Israeli military said their side suffered no casualties. But
a Communist Party statement in Beirut said ``the enemy suffered
heavy losses in lives and ammunition at the hands of our heroes who
fought hand-to-hand to repulse the attack.''
   The villages have long been used by the Communists and other
leftist Lebanese and Palestinian guerrilla factions allied with
Syria to attack the Israeli-held zone.
   Also Tuesday, police said heavy artillery duels raged Tuesday in
south Lebanon about 15 miles west of Nabi Safa between the
Iranian-backed Hezbollah, or Party of God, and the Syrian-allied
Amal.
   The two militias also clashed with machine guns and
rocket-propelled grenades in the Shiite slums of Hay el-Lija in
west Beirut after midday. There were no reports of casualties in
Beirut.
   Police have reported at least 38 people killed and 150 wounded
in the south since Saturday in a renewed power struggle between the
rival groups for control of Lebanon's 1.2 million Shiites, the
country's largest sect.
</TEXT>

</DOC>