<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0152EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-SchoolProjections     12-28 0373</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-School Projections,370</SECOND>
<HEAD>Number of Teachers, Students to Rise by Year 2000</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By W. DALE NELSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation will need 15 percent more classroom
teachers by the year 2000 to cope with a dramatic increase in the
number of pupils, the Department of Education says.
   The teachers are expected to be better paid than today, said a
department study released Wednesday.
   Total elementary and secondary school enrollment is expected to
reach 49.5 million by the end of the century, a gain of about 9
percent, said the study titled ``Projections of Education
Statistics to 2000.''
   Enrollment has declined 4 percent in the past 11 years. The
expected turnaround is attributed to an increase in births that
began in 1977 and has continued in most years since then.
   Its impact will be felt most strongly at the secondary school
level, which has lower student-teacher ratios and a greater range
of subjects. Enrollment in secondary schools is expected to climb
to 14.8 million, an increase of 18 percent.
   The pupil-teacher ratio will continue to drop, although not as
steeply as in the 1980s, the study said. By the year 2000, the
ratio for elementary and secondary schools, both public and
private, is expected to be 16.1 students per teacher. It is now
16.9, and in 1978 it was 19.2.
   The average public school teacher is expected to earn 14 percent
more in real purchasing power, after adjusting for inflation, in
the year 2000 than now, the study said. The national average today
is $31,200.
   ``This publication will be a useful planning tool for our
nation's governors, federal, state and local leaders and members of
the business community,'' Education Secretary Lauro Cavazos said in
a statement.
   College and university enrollments are expected to increase from
12.8 million to 13.4 million, a gain of 4 percent. Faculty also
will increase by 4 percent, from 741,000 in 1988 to 771,000 in 2000.
   In 1999, for the first time, more doctoral degrees are expected
to be awarded to women than to men. Women have led men in
associate, bachelor's and master's degrees for several years. Men
are expected to continue to dominate first professional degrees in
such fields as medicine and law.
</TEXT>

</DOC>