<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1228EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DryNewYear     12-26 0685</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dry New Year,0703</SECOND>
<HEAD>Blue Laws Have Liquor Sellers Singing New Year's Blues</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MITCHELL LANDSBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   It's 9:59 p.m. on New Year's Eve in Little Rock, Ark. At a
downtown bar, the revelers are already chanting the countdown:
``... four ... three ... two ... one ... It's closing time!''
   New Year's Eve or not, when it's Sunday in Arkansas, the bar
closes at 10.
   Most states have some sort of law restricting liquor sales on
Sundays. So when New Year's Eve falls on a Sunday, as it does this
year, it's a less-than-festive holiday for those who make a living
selling alcohol.
   ``I think it will hurt the industry,'' said Ray Brezzo, who owns
a liquor store in Glastonbury, Conn. ``We're very, very
pessimistic.''
   In Connecticut, as in many states in the Northeast, bars and
restaurants can serve alcohol on Sundays but liquor stores cannot.
For New Year's Eve, Brezzo is hoping his customers will buy what
they need on Saturday _ but he's far from confident.
   ``Nobody knows what to expect,'' he said. ``Everybody's sort of
sitting on the edge of their seat.''
   Liquor stores in New York City are posting signs to remind their
customers to buy early. In Grand Forks, N.D., Happy Harry's Bottle
Shop is taking out newspaper advertisements with a similar reminder.
   Still, owner Hal Gershman said, ``No matter how much advertising
you do, and how much you try to tell people, there are still 60
percent of the people who don't pay attention and will show up at
the last minute.''
   Although North Dakota has among the nation's toughest blue laws,
the Legislature did agree this year to allow bars and taverns to
apply for special Sunday permits.
   But some communities, such as Minot, opted against issuing the
permits, much to the dismay of bar owners.
   ``We're put in an unfair disadvantage to the other major
cities,'' complained Jim Mellow, manager of the International Inn
in Minot, which caters to Canadian tourists. ``The people I have
talked to are bypassing Minot and heading to Bismark or Williston.''
   In Alabama, where restaurants and nightclubs can't sell alcohol
between 2 a.m. and midnight Sunday, some places will hold parties
the night before. Others will start their festivities at midnight.
As in several other Southern states, private clubs are exempted
from the law.
   Chris Fuller, general manager of American Pie, a 2-month-old
Montgomery nightclub without a private license, said he'd throw a
bash on Saturday night.
   ``But it's just not going to have the same whiz-bang as New
Year's Eve,'' he said. ``Obviously, it's a big loss. A
day-before-New Year's Eve party, that sounds pretty goofy.''
   Some states, such as Pennsylvania, specifically exempt New
Year's Eve from blue laws. In Baltimore County, Md., liquor store
owners successfully sued this year to open, arguing that a
convoluted liquor law was intended to exempt New Year's Eve from
Sunday restrictions but unintentionally had the opposite effect.
   ``We're real happy. The customers are happy,'' said Craig
Button, president of the Baltimore County Licensed Beverage
Association, after a judge ruled that the stores could open. ``It's
the second biggest day of the year for us (after Christmas Eve). It
would have cost us a lot of money.''
   In South Carolina, the executive director of the state Hotel and
Motel Association said she feared that restrictions on public
venues selling liquor on Sundays would lead to an increase in
drunken driving.
   ``What happens is so many people ... might have spent the night
in the hotel rather than drinking and partying and driving on the
road,'' said Susan Young, the association's executive director.
   Others noted that South Carolina's blue laws send some people
over the border into less-restrictive North Carolina to drink.
   Not all liquor sellers are upset about being forced to close.
Robert McIntyre, the owner of Old Town Liquor in Englewood, Colo.,
said he was quite content to spend this New Year's Eve in the quiet
of his own home.
   McIntyre said he wasn't worrying about any loss in business.
``It's just going to be nicer for me,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>