<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0102 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1549EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Bush-Romania     12-27 0473</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Romania,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Congratulates New Romanian President</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM RAUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CORPUS CHRISTI, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush on Wednesday
congratulated Romania's new president, Ion Iliescu, and said he was
``amazed and respectful'' of the changes there. The White House
said more humanitarian aid is on the way.
   ``My concern is for tranquility and freedom in Romania,'' Bush
said at an airport news conference here as he began a six-day
hunting and fishing vacation.
   At the same time, he declined to criticize harshly the quick
executions of former dictator Nicolae Ceausescu and his wife.
   ``We did say that we were concerned that the trial of Ceausescu
should have been more open, but that's their matter,'' Bush said.
   He said he was ``just amazed and respectful of the change that
has taken place'' in the final hardline East bloc nation to undergo
democratic upheaval.
   The president said he was especially ``touched'' at hearing
about a Christmas carol being sung on the state-run television for
the first time in 40 years.
   ``It made a dramatic statement to me,'' Bush said.
   Bush said the army appeared to be restoring stability in the
violence-torn country.
   Bush also sent a congratulatory message to Iliescu.
   ``The president expressed his sympathy over the tragic bloodshed
during the past two weeks and his hope that Romania will now move
along on a peaceful path of democratic change,'' the vacation White
House said in a statement.
   In his message, Bush ``expressed the hope that the new Romanian
government will move quickly to implement democratic reforms based
on the rule of law.''
   ``He pledged U.S. support and assistance as Romania meets these
challenges during the difficult transition ahead.''
   The administration was sending a C-141 cargo plane loaded with
medical supplies from West Germany to Romania on Thursday, the
Agency for International Development (AID) said.
   The cost of the flight and supplies, about $250,000, was in
addition to the $500,000 in cash the administration was giving to
the International Red Cross for medical supplies and other
humanitarian aid, and $25,000 from an embassy contingency fund in
Romania.
   AID also said a team of experts from Washington was to arrive in
Romania Thursday ``to assess humanitarian needs to distribute the
relief flight's cargo.''
   At the State Department, spokesman Mark Dillen said the U.S.
ambassador to Bucharest, Alan Green, had requested an appointment
with the provisional president, Ion Iliescu, but no appointment had
been scheduled.
   Commenting on reports of an anti-Communist rally in the Romanian
capital, Dillen said the embassy had said the demonstration was
attended by 500 to 1,000 students and that a student leader had
appeared on Romanian television.
   ``We encourage the government of Romania to allow all voices to
be heard as the process of reform and the transition to a new
government progresses,'' said Dillen, reading a prepared statement.
</TEXT>

</DOC>