<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0098 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1545EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Yeltsin     12-28 0315</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Yeltsin,0325</SECOND>
<HEAD>Yeltsin Reported Running for President of Largest Soviet Republic</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Maverick Communist Boris N. Yeltsin is running for
president of the Russian republic, it was reported Thursday.
   Yeltsin won more than 5 million votes in a landslide victory
last spring to become Moscow's representative in the national
parliament.
   He will have to win a second legislative seat in the regional
parliament of Russia _ the largest of the Soviet Union's 15
republics _ to seek the presidency. The Russian parliament will
elect the president from among its members.
   Yeltsin has won wide popularity with his anti-establishment
stance and calls for more radical reform. He rejected a suggestion
last spring that he run against Mikhail S. Gorbachev for presidency
of the Soviet Union.
   Russia is the largest republic in the Soviet Union, stretching
from Leningrad through the vast spaces of Siberia to the Pacific
coast. About half the nation's 286 million people live in Russia.
   Voters in Ramenki, a town near Moscow, nominated Yeltsin, said
the Interfax news service, which is affiliated with state-run Radio
Moscow.
   Yeltsin was dumped from his job as Moscow Communist Party chief
in 1987 after his outspoken criticism of party leaders. He was
later given a state post in construction.
   The 58-year-old former engineer parlayed his image as a fighter
for justice and victim of the party bureaucracy into a sweeping
victory in elections for the Soviet Congress of People's Deputies
last March, when he won 89 percent of the Moscow vote.
   As a national legislator, Yeltsin has emerged as a leader of the
fledgling opposition to Communist Party leaders and has continued
to push for faster reforms.
   Elections are scheduled for this March in the Russian republic.
No other prominent candidates for the presidency have been
announced.
   The current president of the Russian republic is Vitaly I.
Vorotnikov, a member of the party's ruling Politburo.
</TEXT>

</DOC>