<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1443EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Zimbabwe     12-19 0429</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Zimbabwe,0443</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ruling Party, ex-Opposition Formally Merge to Map New Policy</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN EDLIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HARARE, Zimbabwe (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The ruling party and main opposition
merged Tuesday with their first national congress, charged with
framing a new constitution.
   Since independence a decade ago, President Robert Mugabe's
dominant Zimbabwe African National Union (Patriotic Front) has been
avowedly Marxist-Leninist. Former Zimbabwe African People's Union
opposition leader Joshua Nkomo was more centrist.
   About 4,200 delegates from the two parties gathered for the
four-day congress that will decide which ideological path to tread
in the light of changes in Eastern Europe, long Mugabe's role model.
   Conferees also will be asked to rule whether the new alliance
should continue to pursue Mugabe's dream of creating a one-party
state in one of Africa's few Western-style democracies.
   The congress effectively formalizes a decision by Zimbabwe's two
main political figures two years ago to unite their parties, ending
decades of interparty feuding.
   The alliance also seeks to bury 200 years of tribal hostilities
between the majority Shona tribe, which largely backs Mugabe, and
the Ndebele people who traditionally support Nkomo.
   The birth of the reconstituted ZANU arms Mugabe with the support
of all but two lawmakers in the 100-seat National Assembly and the
40-member rubber-stamp senate.
   The ruling party can pass laws and rewrite sections of the
British-drafted constitution, a document signed by all parties at
London's Lancaster House 10 years ago Thursday.
   Those constitutional talks ended nine decades of white minority
rule, halted a seven-year war waged by guerrillas loyal to Nkomo
and Mugabe and transformed the British colony of Rhodesia into
black-governed Zimbabwe at independence April 18, 1980.
   The constitution guaranteed Zimbabwe would be a multiparty
democracy for the first 10 years of independence.
   After the 10th anniversary, Mugabe can, constitutionally, ban
opposition and establish a single-party state with two-thirds of
the votes in Parliament.
   But in recent months, as pro-democratic movements have swept
Eastern Europe, Mugabe has come under mounting pressure to renounce
what he calls his Marxist-Leninist policies and to abandon the aim
of killing the multiparty system.
   Opening the congress, Mugabe indicated his stand was flexible.
   ``While we must be clear as to the ideological direction we take
... namely Marxist-Leninist socialist principles, we must also take
full cognisance of the environment and the concrete realities in
which we seek to achieve social transformation,'' he said.
   The congress, which ends Friday, is being attended also by
Presidents Quett Masire of Botswana and Kenneth Kaunda of Zambia as
well as observers from 20 countries including Cuba, North Korea and
Nicaragua.
</TEXT>

</DOC>