<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0114 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 2110EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-WorldReax 2ndLd-Writethru a0590 12-23 0840</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-World Reax, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0590,0858</SECOND>
<HEAD>World Prays and Offers Support For Embattled Romanians</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 8 grafs for 5-10 pvs, `Britain said...' to UPDATE with
reaction in China, Romanian embassy there supports new gov't. Pick up 11th
pvs, `In Washington...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EDITH M. LEDERER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The world prayed and offered support Saturday for
the embattled Romanian people who ousted Nicolae Ceausescu and were
fighting to preserve their newly won freedom.
   As army units backing the popular uprising fought elite police
squads supporting Ceausescu, the widespread euphoria over the
downfall of the hard-line Communist dictator turned to anxiety over
the continuing bloodshed.
   In Moscow, Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev told lawmakers
that his country was standing by with unspecified aid for the
anti-Ceausescu forces.
   Premier Nikolai I. Ryzhkov all but ruled out military
intervention, saying, ``We have to support them from the point of
view of medical help and maybe some other kinds of help, but to
bring in forces, I think that's impermissible.'' In Eastern and
Western Europe, appeals were launched for money, food and medical
supplies. The French government announced it was sending two planes
carrying 30 tons of medical equipment and a medical team to Romania.
   China, apparently taken by surprise by the loss of one of its
strongest allies, has made little comment. A Foreign Ministry
statement Saturday said the political struggle in Romania was an
internal affair of that country and it hoped the turmoil would not
affect good relations with China.
   Britain said it was sending emergency medical supplies,
including equipment for treating gundshot wounds and providing
blood transfusions.
   Sweden's government said it had allocated $3.1 million in
medical and food assistance.
   However, East bloc news reports and the International Committee
of the Red Cross in Geneva reported Saturday that emergency
supplies were being blockaded.
   Yugoslav Foreign Secretary Budimir Loncar instructed the
Yugoslav Embassy in Bucharest to contact the National Salvation
Committee to express his country's support for the ``courageous
struggle of the Romanian people for democracy,'' the Tanjug news
agency reported.
   In Czechoslovakia, the Social Democrats opposition group said in
a statement that it ``resolutely condemns brutal repressions of the
Stalinist regime in Romania, welcomes the fall of bloody dictator
Ceausescu and wishes the Romanian people many successes on the path
toward a democratic society.''
   The Romanian Embassy in China, a longtime supporter of
Ceausescu, announced Sunday it fully backs the provisional
government that has ousted him from power.
   Also throwing allegiance behind the new government were the
Romanian diplomatic missions in Iran, the Netherlands, Libya,
Switzerland, Jordan, Sweden, Turkey, Greece, Poland, Sudan, Spain,
Italy, France, East Berlin and Bangladesh.
   In Washington, Michael Hornblow of the State Department's Task
Force on Romania said Romanian Ambassador Ion Stoichici informed
the department in writing that he and the embassy staff were
aligned with the new government.
   In Israel, Vice Premier Shimon Peres said, ``Ceausescu was, as
you know, on world matters a man for peace; on internal matters a
man who used very strong measures like nobody since Stalin.''
   From a Jewish point of view, he said, a judgment is not simple
because ``he is the only one who recognized Israel from among the
Communist countries and continued diplomatic relations.''
   The Foreign Office in London announced that it had evacuated
nine Britons including the wives and children of some diplomats
from Romania.
   Many East German political, church and citizens groups expressed
solidarity with the Romanian people and many called for aid to be
sent to Romania.
   Some set up special bank accounts to collect donations, and one
church group appealed to all East Germans with access to foreign
currency to give one West German mark for victims of Ceausescu's
terror.
   Poland's pro-Solidarity Gazeta Wyborcza published a four-page
special edition Saturday exclusively on the Romanian situation and
distributed it free, with a request that 100 zlotys be donated
instead to the Polish Red Cross for aid to Romania.
   The Polish Red Cross broadcast a radio request for humanitarian
aid for Romania in the form of money, clothing and medical
supplies, especially bandages. It also appealed to blood donors,
saying the Polish blood banks would be open late Saturday and on
Christmas Eve.
   The British Red Cross launched a Help Romania appeal and the
relief organization Oxfam made an immediate initial grant of
$160,000 for medical supplies.
   Christian Aid said it made a grant of $32,000 through the World
Council of Churches to churches in Romania and Hungary.
   Ion Ratiu, president of the World Union of Free Romanians, said
he hoped to return to Bucharest soon and start a mass circulation
newspaper.
   Regarded as a possible future leader, Ratiu told Britain's
domestic news agency Press Association from his home in Switzerland
that ``if they give me leadership I would be delighted to do it,
but I don't want to impose myself on anyone.
   ``My heart is bleeding for the thousands and thousands of people
who have been killed. It is a terribly high price to pay.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>