<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0213EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Panama-Casualties 2nd-LdWritethru a0804 12-22 0405</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Casualties, 2nd - Ld Writethru, a0804,0409</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bodies of Servicemen Killed in Panama Begin Arriving at Dover Air
Force Base</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: UPDATES throughout with 14 more bodies arriving in Dover. No
pick up. ^LaserPhoto DV1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By THERESA HUMPHREY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DOVER AIR FORCE BASE, Del. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The bodies of 18 U.S.
servicemen killed in the invasion of Panama were returned Thursday
to Dover Air Force Base and honored during a brief planeside
ceremony.
   Shortly before midnight, the remains of 13 soldiers and one
Marine arrived on a C5 Galaxy in windy, 7-degree weather.
   Secretary of the Army Michael P.W. Stone said the servicemen
returned ``to a nation that is grateful, both for their duty in the
cause of liberty, and above all, for their sacrifice'' in defense
of demoracy.
   Earlier Thursday, the bodies of four U.S. Navy men killed during
the invasion of Panama were returned to the base and also honored
during a brief planeside ceremony.
   ``The four brave men we mourn here today now rest in the quiet
arms of a grateful nation and a loving God,'' said Navy Secretary
H. Lawrence Garrett III said. ``These magnificent young men have
made the greatest sacrifices for us all.''
   Garrett said the four men returned to ``our embrace'' having
fought for the liberty and dignity that Americans enjoy.
   Cmdr. Bob Prucha, a Navy spokesman, said the four were members
of the Navy special operations unit known as the SEALS. They died
leading the assault on Tortilla Air Field in Panama. Prucha did not
know if they were killed at the field or died later from wounds
suffered in the attack.
   ``All we can do is honor their memory by never forgetting that
our lives, under the banner of democracy, have been further
protected with their deaths,'' Garrett said.
   The four dead were identified as Boatswain's Mate 1st Class
Christopher Tilghman, 30, of Kailua, Hawaii; Lt. j.g. John P.
Connors, 25, of Arlington, Mass.; Chief Engineman Donald L. McFaul,
32, of San Diego, Calif.; and Torpedoman's mate Second Class Issac
G. Rodriguez III, 24, of Los Angeles.
   All four were stationed at the Naval Amphibious Base in Little
Creek, Va., near Norfolk.
   The base mortuary opened in 1968 and has handled the remains of
servicemen killed in the Vietnam War, Marines killed in a terrorist
bombing of their headquarters in Beirut and the remains of Navy men
killed in the USS Iowa explosion.
</TEXT>

</DOC>