<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0204 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1804EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-CommodityRdp     12-26 0765</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Commodity Rdp,0790</SECOND>
<HEAD>Orange Juice Futures Rocket After Florida Freeze</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID DISHNEAU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Orange juice futures prices soared Tuesday after a weekend
freeze in the South that damaged a portion of the Florida orange
crop and wiped out 70 percent of the Texas citrus crop.
   Heating oil futures prices also climbed dramatically following
an explosion at the nation's second-largest petrochemical refinery.
   On other commodity markets, coffee and cotton futures rose
sharply, precious metals futures fell, livestock and meat futures
advanced and grains and soybeans retreated.
   On the New York Cotton Exchange, the contract for January
delivery of frozen concentrated orange juice jumped 16.1 cents to
$1.531 a pound, an 11.8 percent gain. The contracts for March and
May delivery rose their permitted daily limits of 5 cents a pound.
   Florida officials said it was too early to estimate the damage
that occurred to the state's $3.5 billion citrus crop when
temperatures plunged below freezing over the weekend.
   Celeste Georkakis of Cargill Investor Services Inc. said her
firm's early assessment was that 20 percent to 30 percent of the
Florida orange crop had been destroyed, which would be less than
was lost in Christmas Day 1983 freeze.
   But the market's reaction Tuesday indicated the damage was
probably worse than most traders had expected, Ms. Georkakis said.
   Orange juice prices had been falling before the freeze threat
surfaced last week, a reflection of increased Brazilian orange
production, which is expected to reach a record 290 million boxes
in 1990.
   Analysts said imports of Brazilian orange juice should make up
for damage to the Florida crop. So instead of a sharp price
increase at the retail level because of the freeze, Ms. Georkakis
said, U.S. consumers may simply see a halt to falling prices or
only a slight rise.
   But Robert Behr, economic research director for the Florida
Department of Citrus, said he had heard rumors that at least one
Florida processor planned to raise its wholesale price of frozen
concentrated orange juice to $1.50 from $1.37 a pound because of
the freeze.
   Heating oil futures prices surged on the New York Mercantile
Exchange in the wake of a weekend explosion at an Exxon Corp.
refinery in Baton Rouge, La., raising prospects of further spot oil
shortages.
   The accident at the plant aggravated a price spike caused by the
record-setting cold snap that has hit much of the nation. Supplies
of home heating oil already were tight before the explosion and the
accelerated demand has pushed retail prices as high as $1 a gallon
in some areas.
   Heating oil futures climbed 1.75 cents to 10.74 cents with
January settling at 92.48 cents a gallon; crude oil settled 53
cents to 63 cents higher with February at $21.91 a barrel; unleaded
gasoline was 1.9 cents to 5.49 cents higher with January at 60.94
cents a gallon.
   Coffee futures climbed above 80 cents a pound for the first time
since Oct. 2 on New York's Coffee, Sugar &amp; Cocoa Exchange amid
reports of a weekend freeze in Mexico's coffee-growing region.
Coffee settled 4.18 cents to 4.5 cents higher with March at 82.67 a
pound.
   Cotton futures rose sharply on the Cotton Exchange on a
combination of technical factors and rumors that China had
purchased a large amount of U.S. and Pakistani cotton. Cotton
settled 1.13 cents to the limit 2 cents higher with March at 70.71
cents a pound.
   The easing of tensions in Panama and Romania prompted a sell-off
of precious-metals futures on New York's Commodity Exchange.
   Gold futures finished $6.40 to $6.70 lower with December at
$406.80 a troy ounce; silver was 4.8 cents to 5 cents lower with
December at $5.512 a troy ounce.
   Live cattle settled .33 cent to .95 cent higher with February at
77.75 cents a pound; feeder cattle were .13 cent to .48 cent higher
with January at 85.25 cents a pound; live hogs were .18 cent to .53
cent higher with February at 49.15 cents a pound; frozen pork
bellies were unchanged to .70 cent higher with February at 49.77
cents a pound.
   Grain and soybean futures moved modestly lower on the Chicago
Board of Trade as temperatures in U.S. growing areas rose, slowing
feed-grain demand and easing transportation problems.
   Wheat futures settled 1{ cents to 1} cents lower with March at
$4.10 a bushel; corn futures were { cent to 1\ cents lower with
March at $2.38{ a bushel; oats were 1\ cents to 1{ cents lower with
March at $1.53 a bushel; soybeans were 1{ cents to 3} cents lower
with January at $5.68{ a bushel.
</TEXT>

</DOC>