<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1244EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SpillSecrecy     12-28 0574</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Spill Secrecy,0597</SECOND>
<HEAD>Oil Companies Want Spill Facts Kept Secret</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Exxon Corp., Alyeska Pipeline Service
Co. and other defendants in more than 150 lawsuits resulting from
the Exxon Valdez oil spill are asking that all evidence be kept
secret until the cases go to trial.
   The order, requested earlier this month, has come under fire
from the state and other plaintiffs, who contend that Alaska's
legislative responsibilities and the public's right to know demand
release of such information.
   Superior Court Judge Brian Shortell is scheduled to rule on the
secrecy order next month. Violating the secrecy order would result
in contempt charges.
   As requested by the oil companies, the order would bar all
parties from disclosing virtually anything learned during the
discovery phase of the litigation.
   It would apply to legal motions, corporate records and sworn
statements of company officials.
   Attorneys say the lawsuits may not go to trial for a decade, and
most probably will be settled out of court.
   A secrecy order could prevent the public from learning exactly
what caused the March 24 wreck of the Exxon Valdez, or why efforts
to contain and clean up the nearly 11 million gallons of crude oil
from Prince William Sound failed.
   Even the state would be forbidden to disclose what it had
learned about the spill. Critics of the request said that would
impair the ability of lawmakers and environmental officials to do a
better job of regulating the industry.
   National Wildlife Federation President Jay Hair calls the
proposed order a ``blatant and outrageous attempt to hide the facts
from the American people.''
   ``These oil companies are terrified that the public could learn
the complete details about what they have done,'' he said.
   John Anderson, a management consultant for Exxon, said release
of large quantities of internal business records could result in
disclosure of trade secrets _ even if the individual documents
contained no secrets.
   Competitors could piece together millions of bits of
information, creating a mosaic of Exxon operations that would
betray trade secrets, he said.
   Alyeska is owned by a consortium of seven oil companies that
pump about 2 million barrels of oil a day to the Valdez tanker
terminal and into tankers.
   All of the state court cases have been consolidated for pretrial
motions and discovery, the evidence-gathering stage of a lawsuit.
   Plaintiffs in the cases range from the state of Alaska, which
wants to prove Exxon and Alyeska were negligent in preparing for
and responding to the spill, to fishermen, tourism companies and
environmental groups.
   ``The idea that this will all be done behind closed doors is
unacceptable,'' said Dave Oesting, a counsel for the plaintiffs.
   The state wants Exxon and Alyeska to prove confidentiality on a
document-by-document basis.
   ``Basically, we just think this case is a uniquely public case
and affects a broad section of the public, virtually the entire
state of Alaska. And the public does have a broad right to know
what is going on,'' said Assistant Attorney General Craig Tillery.
   If Exxon obtains a blanket secrecy order, the state will seek an
exception for the Legislature and administration ``so they have
access to make policy regarding future spills,'' he said.
   Oil companies' trade secrets are protected by state and federal
rules of evidence. But courts have ruled in several major cases,
such as the Agent Orange suits and claims against cigarette makers,
that the public has a right to know.
</TEXT>

</DOC>