<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 2029EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Panama-Wounded     12-24 0508</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Wounded,0524</SECOND>
<HEAD>Christmas Dinner, Carols Planned for Wounded Troops</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KELLEY SHANNON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN ANTONIO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two military hospitals treating more than 100
soldiers who suffered wounds while fighting in Panama were
festooned with holiday decorations on Christmas Eve, as gifts
poured in from around the country.
   ``Everybody's been sending them Christmas cards, flowers and
fruit baskets,'' said Senior Airman Cynthia Fontenot of Lackland
Air Force Base, where Wilford Hall Medical Center is located.
``There's cases of cookies, potato chips, chocolate candies,
shaving cream, razors and different things.''
   Twenty-five injured Army Rangers returned to Fort Lewis, Wash.
Thirty more GI's were treated at a Fort Bragg Army hospital Sunday,
bringing to 67 the number of servicemen brought back to North
Carolina in time for the holidays.
   ``The wounds are not that serious. We're able to pretty quickly
give them treatment,'' said Fort Bragg spokesman Doug Foster.
``Their morale is good.''
   In San Antonio, 65 patients wounded in Panama were being treated
at Wilford Hall and Brooke Army Medical Center across town at Fort
Sam Houston was treating 47 soldiers, officials said.
   Cooks at both hospitals began preparing a traditional Christmas
meal for the patients.
   The soldiers' relatives have been treated to free lodging and
rental cars from local companies, Sgt. Maj. Raymond Morris said at
Brooke.
   ``All this is really unsolicited. We have asked for nothing and
we have received so many things,'' Morris said.
   About 20 families have used an assistance center at Brooke, he
said.
   At Saturday night's San Antonio Spurs basketball game, the
city's Chamber of Commerce asked for donations of sweatshirts and
tennis shoes for the soldiers. The number donated could not
immediately be determined and chamber officials did not return a
phone call Sunday.
   Since Wednesday, 244 soldiers have been flown to San Antonio in
seven transport planes. The latest were 11 patients flown in
Sunday. Three died en route and one died after arriving. Dozens
have been transferred to other military hospitals or released to
their units, officials said.
   At Fort Bragg, the original estimate of 3,000 soldiers from that
base still in Panama by Christmas Eve had been revised to 4,000.
   At Fort Lewis, one soldier, a foot in a cast, was asked how his
mission in Panama City had gone. He smiled, and yelled back, ``It
was great!''
   ``To a man, they all want to get well and get back to their
units,'' said Lt. Gen. Calvin A. H. Waller, commander of Fort Lewis
and I Corps, who shook each soldier's hand as they returned. ``They
are outstanding young Americans.''
   Most of the injuries sustained by the members of the 2nd Ranger
Battalion, 75th Regiment, were to the lower back and legs, caused
from parachuting from C-141 transport planes at an altitude below
500 feet to avoid being detected by radar, said Capt. Martin
Eckert, Fort Lewis spokesman.
   ``If they are considered to be fully recovered and forces are
still needed in Panama, the soldiers would probably be sent back
down,'' Eckert said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>