<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0111 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1623EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Panama-Canal     12-27 0387</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Canal,0401</SECOND>
<HEAD>Panama Canal Increasing Hours, 125 Ships Backed Up</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DORALISA PILARTE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BALBOA HEIGHTS, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Panama Canal has been
increasing its working hours gradually as employees return to work,
but 125 ships were backed up Wednesday waiting to cross the
isthmus, a canal official said.
   The canal was shut down to all ship traffic for the first 48
hours after U.S. troops invaded Panama Dec. 20. It resumed
operation during daylight hours, but halted work at night because
not enough employees could get to work.
   ``Some people are actually walking to work, as much as 15 miles,
because there's no public transport,'' said Willie K. Friar, a
spokeswoman at Panama Canal Commission headquarters just west of
Panama City.
   But there is still a bottleneck of ships from around the world
at the Atlantic and Pacific entrances waiting to pass through the
canal, she said.
   ``We have 125 ships waiting,'' Ms. Friar said.
   Buses and taxis have begun cruising Panama City streets, but
gasoline is hard to find following a looting spree.
   U.S. Army Lt. Col. Jerry Murguia said gasoline was being
distributed to service stations as life slowly returned to normal.
   Panama City is on the canal's southern end along the Pacific
Ocean, and the town of Colon is on the canal's northern mouth on
the Atlantic coast.
   The canal normally can handle 42 ships a day. Under its 12-hour
daylight operations, only 12 ships a day passed through, Ms. Friar
said.
   On Tuesday, as more employees returned to work, the canal began
work at 3 a.m. and stopped operations 16 hours later.
   ``Today (Wednesday) we're hoping to go to 24 hours, but we don't
know,'' Ms. Friar said. ``We are now assessing the number of
employees'' that have shown up for work.
   Neither the canal nor any ships suffered damage during the
fighting, she said.
   In 1988, 12,261 ships went through the canal. There are 7,602
full-time employees, of whom 86 percent are Panamanians.
   Last week's closing was the first time the canal has shut down
for anything but natural disaster since its opening in 1914.
   The commission has both U.S. and Panamanian members. Under a
1977 treaty, the United States will turn over operation of the
canal to Panama at the end of 1999.
</TEXT>

</DOC>