<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0913EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Romania 3rdLd-Writethru a0503 12-19 1088</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0503,1117</SECOND>
<HEAD>More Gunfire Reported, Borders Sealed After Rioting</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 24 grafs to UPDATE with Westerner likening violence
to Tiananmen square, seeing corpses, other eyewitness accounts; Picks up
17th graf, `The Hungarian ...'; DELETES last 3 grafs to tighten.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIOREL URMA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gunfire was reported early today in the
streets of a western Romanian city where witnesses say security
forces have shot and killed dozens of people in anti-government
rioting that began over the weekend.
   Unconfirmed reports have put the death toll at up to 400 and one
witness was quoted as saying he saw helicopters fire on crowds in
the city of Timisoara.
   Romania has virtually sealed its borders in an apparent attempt
to prevent details from emerging of the unrest, which a Hungarian
newspaper said had spread to two other Transylvanian cities _ Arad
and Brasov.
   The unrest is the most serious since November 1987 in the
country whose leaders have refused to stray from orthodox Communism.
   State-controlled Romanian media have made no mention of the
unrest, and Western reporters have been prevented from entering the
country. Most reports have come from travelers leaving Romania or
from news agencies able to reach residents by telephone.
   In Timisoara beginning on Saturday, thousands of people have
violently vented rage at hard-line President Nicolae Ceausescu for
his intolerance and the hardships he has forced Romanians to endure.
   Greek dental students, who had been attending school in the
city, said late Monday after crossing into Yugoslavia that they had
seen soldiers shoot indiscriminately at protesters, ``killing
dozens.''
   The students said they heard protesters shout ``Freedom!''
``Down with Ceausescu!'' and ``Bread!''
   A Western resident of Timisoara who crossed into Yugoslavia told
The Associated Press that the extent of the weekend violence was
``horrifying'' and that he saw several corpses on the streets.
   ``Tiananmen is nothing compared to Timisoara,'' he said,
speaking on condition he not be further identified. At least 500
people were killed in June when Chinese troops crushed the
pro-democracy movement in Beijing.
   Budapest radio said a caller from Timisoara _ 30 miles from the
Hungarian and Yugoslav borders _ this morning reported renewed
gunfire but that the phone then went dead.
   The radio quoted a Hungarian who said he had several physician
relatives working in Timisoara hospitals. He said he talked to them
by telephone and estimated from their reports that between 300 and
400 people were killed in the city by troops, with 250 bodies taken
to one hospital.
   About 20 percent of the dead and wounded were ethnic Hungarians,
others ethnic Romanians, he told the radio.
   That would substantiate other accounts trickling out of the
country that the protest grew from a few hundred ethnic Hungarians
defending a local pastor into a massive demonstration against
Ceausescu's harsh policies.
   Romania's crackdown drew protest from other countries including
Hungary, which has long been at odds with Bucharest over the
treatment of the 1.7 million ethnic Hungarian minority in Romania,
most of whom live in Transylvania.
   A Yugoslav who said he traveled to Timisoara Saturday night was
quoted as telling the Belgrade daily Politika that crowds in the
city were fired on from helicopters.
   ``I was stopped at approach to Timisoara by soldiers, holding
guns at point-blank range, but they let me through,'' Radoslav
Dencic was quoted by the daily as saying.
   ``The same night bursts of automatic weapon fire could be
heard,'' he said. ``Crowds were even shot at from helicopters.''
   A Yugoslav trucker, Frank Zemberi, said he passed through
Timisoara early Tuesday and saw two large fires raging in distant
parts of town.
   ``Countless'' tanks were parked on the outskirts of Timisoara,
Zemberi said, but the city itself appeared calm, with five armored
vehicles parked in the center and a number of police vans cruising
the streets.
   A Yugoslav traveler said Monday he saw two people killed in
Timisoara. Traffic into Romania was virtually halted on the
Yugoslav, Hungarian and Bulgarian borders, and Austrians and West
Germans were informed that, with few exceptions, they were not
allowed to enter.
   The Yugoslav news agency Tanjug said Monda that security forces
had taken full control in Timisoara, Romania's fourth-largest city
with 350,000 residents.
   Hungary's Radio Kossuth quoted an unnamed resident of the city
as saying things were calm during the day, ``but at night it's like
during the war.
   ``All main intersections have roadblocks, everybody is stopped
and checked and people are not allowed to leave town except in
extreme cases,'' the radio quoted the resident as saying.
   The Hungarian daily Magyar Hirlap today quoted unidentified
truck drivers as saying Arad, some 60 miles north of Timisoara,
``is ringed with tanks and traffic is detoured.'' It asserted
without any specifics that there were also clashes in Arad and
Brasov.
   Col. Janos Pal of the Hungarian border guards was quoted as
saying crowds in Curtic, between Arad and Timisoara, broke into
local Communist Party headquarters on Sunday and burned documents.
   In a broadcast Monday on West Germany's Radio Bremen, William
Toetoek, an ethnic German writer from Romania, quoted witnesses in
Timisoara as saying between 300 and 400 demonstrators were killed
in the unrest.
   The bloody clashes were a sign of contempt for Ceausescu, who
has ruled Romania since 1965, stifling dissent with a vast secret
police force and stubbornly resisting reform.
   While other East bloc countries end or relax one-party Communist
rule, Ceausescu's government has maintained strict control of
society and the economy and continues to harass and jail its
critics.
   Ceausescu's crash industrialization programs and drive to repay
the country's entire $11 billion foreign debt have caused
widespread shortages and rationing of basic foods.
   The unrest was the most serious since a protest march by 10,000
workers in Brasov in November 1987. Ceausescu did not comment on it
and on Monday traveled to Iran for a state visit. His his wife,
Elena, the second most powerful person in the country, stayed
behind.
   The unrest apparently began after hundreds of members of the
country's ethnic Hungarian minority formed a ``human chain'' Friday
to prevent the attempted eviction of the Rev. Laszlo Toekes, who
has championed their rights, said Mihnea Berindei, vice chairman of
the Paris-based Romanian League for Human Rights.
   The Protestant clergyman, harassed for months by authorities for
defending ethnic Hungarians against alleged official
discrimination, took refuge with his wife in his church on Nov. 2
after masked assailants tried to attack him, Berindei said. He said
Toekes' whereabouts were not known Monday evening.
</TEXT>

</DOC>