<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1604EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BusCrashTrial     12-23 0488</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bus Crash Trial,0502</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prosecutor Says Inbred Ideas About Murder Determined Bus Crash Verdict</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHARLES WOLFE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CARROLLTON, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A special prosecutor said he was up
against deeply instilled ideas about what is murder when he failed
to persuade a jury that the man who caused a bus crash that killed
27 people deserved life in prison.
   Larry Mahoney, a 36-year-old chemical plant worker, was
convicted Thursday of manslaughter, assault, wanton endangerment
and drunken driving. His jury recommended a 16-year prison sentence.
   The verdict came 19 months after Mahoney, driving drunk and on
the wrong side of Interstate 71, ran his pickup into the front of a
church bus loaded with youngsters on a church outing.
   The impact knocked off the bus' front axle, the gas tank was
punctured, and a fuel fire exploded into the bus' interior, killing
24 children and three adults. Forty people escaped, but 12 children
suffered disfiguring burns.
   Kentucky authorities have been empowered to charge drunken
drivers with murder since the late 1970s. But convictions are rare,
requiring a jury to find that a defendant acted wantonly, with
``extreme indifference'' to human life.
   In the Mahoney case, the murder charge didn't stick even though
the tragedy was compounded by the innocence of the victims and the
horrible way they died.
   Prosecutors must overcome ``a deep-seated, in-bred public
perception of what is murder,'' said Assistant Attorney General
Paul Richwalsky, who prosecuted Mahoney.
   ``Maybe if this crime was called anything else _ vehicular
homicide, or somehow the label `murder' was not attached to it _
the results may have been different,'' he said.
   Though it would have been of great symbolic significance, a
murder conviction probably would have had little real effect on
Mahoney's sentence, Richwalsky said.
   Mahoney's most serious conviction was for first-degree assault,
punishable by 10 to 20 years in prison. The jury recommended a
dozen 16-year sentences and the maximum 10 years on each of 27
counts of second-degree manslaughter. But it also ordered all the
sentences to run concurrently.
   The assault conviction made Mahoney a ``violent offender'' under
Kentucky law, meaning he must serve half his sentence _ eight years
_ before he can be considered for parole.
   A murder conviction, with a minimum 20-year sentence, would have
made Mahoney eligible for parole in 10 years.
   The jury's decisions nevertheless outraged relatives of many of
the crash victims, who said they had been denied even a hollow
victory.
   Janet Kytta had wanted ``just the word `murder''' from the jury.
   ``It was not manslaughter; it was murder,'' she said.
   Her husband, Chuck Kytta, was youth director for the church,
Radcliff First Assembly of God, and had arranged the youngsters'
outing to an amusement park.
   Kytta was standing at the bus' front door, and must have been
killed by fire before he could have passed out from smoke, Dr.
George Nichols, the state's chief medical examiner, testified.
</TEXT>

</DOC>