<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0146 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1417EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--EmbassyBugs Adv07-2Takes   12-26 1081</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Embassy Bugs, Adv 07-2 Takes,1114</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv07</HEAD>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Jan. 7</HEAD>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<HEAD>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 1 graphic.)</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   It was the unfinished symphony of the Cold War,
all sour notes, now a relic of superpower chicanery that Uncle Sam
will spend $270 million to tear down and replace: the office
building of the U.S. Embassy in Moscow, riddled with KGB bugs,
never occupied. AP Special Correspondent Saul Pett records the
bizarre saga of the way things were before the Communist meltdown.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By SAUL PETT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It is now 20 years since the United States and
the Soviet Union agreed to build new embassies for each other in
Moscow and Washington. In that time, it is said, the ancient
Egyptians built the Great Pyramid of Cheops.
   The pharaohs didn't have to deal with the Soviets. The U.S.
Embassy is still not finished and won't be.
   Eight stories up, $170 million spent, water and ice ravaging the
most expensive bricks in the world, the administration in
Washington has now decided to stop there, raze the building to the
ground and start over.
   That will add five more years, an additional $270 million to the
cost of a modern tale of two cities, a lumbering farce of
pachyderms unique to the late unpleasantness called the Cold War.
Walls come down, liberty soars, but in the new age we are left with
monuments to the buffoonery of the old.
   The United States finished the Soviet Embassy in Washington, but
the Soviets couldn't move into their chancery until the United
States moved into its chancery in Moscow. That was by agreement,
one of several that took 13 years to reach in tense, careful
negotiations. Every major move had to be precise, simultaneous and
symmetrical. It was like two Mafia families trying to arrange a
truce for a wedding.
   It took less than two years to build the 102-story Empire State
Building in New York in 1931. In Moscow, the Soviets were into year
seven and still not finished with the eight-story office building
of the U.S. Embassy when the United States threw them out.
   The problem was bugs. Mysterious, multitudinous, ubiquitous,
anti-American, subversive, pre-glasnost, godless Russian communist
bugs.
   In columns and walls, in concrete and steel, in breathtaking
numbers and novel ways that confounded American experts, we were
told, the Soviets had sown the chancery with diabolic devices to
overhear, record and transmit American secrets.
   The United States refused to move in until the bugs were moved
out, but getting them out appeared tougher than evicting a poor
relative. So tough, in fact, two administrations spent four years
figuring out what to do. Both concluded the only safe course was to
build a new building.
   Historically, there is no louder uproar among politicians and
press than the thunder evoked by the suggestion that foreigners,
especially the backward Soviets, had outwitted Uncle Sam. The
devilish dither of the embassies had all the makings.
   Sites. After 10 years of negotiations, we gave them Mount Alto
along Wisconsin Avenue, one of the highest points in Washington.
They gave us a plot along Konyushovskaya Ulitsa down near the
Moscow River.
   Uproar. The United States had given away a strategic height from
which, electronically, the KGB could look down the throats of the
White House and Pentagon!
   ``The view is terrific'' but the intelligence advantage is
``considerably less,'' said James Schlesinger, former director of
the Central Intelligence Agency. What's more, other witnesses
testified, Mount Alto was not the Soviet's first choice for an
embassy and in Moscow, the United States had turned down an offer
of Lenin Hills to be ``downtown.'' The high-low plot wouldn't play.
   Sidewalks. A hearing of the Subcommittee International
Operations of the House Committee on Foreign Affairs. Back from
Moscow, Rep. Dan Mica, D-Fla., reported: ``Where the new building
is, (the Soviets) built us a 16-inch sidewalk so that there is no
place to walk. ... That is harassment.''
   Rep. Olympia Snowe, R-Mass., asked if the State Department
pursued a ``reciprocity'' of harassment in building the Soviet
Embassy in Washington. She seemed to think it should.
   James E. Nolan, director of the Office of Foreign Missions,
replied: ``In the District of Columbia, one does not cut down
sidewalk size in half simply because the State Department thinks it
is a good time to do it or because we think that it is leverage to
do it.''
   Off site. Here was the real trouble. In Washington, Americans
poured concrete for the Soviet Embassy on site where the Soviets
could watch. In Moscow, Soviets poured concrete off site where
Americans couldn't, or didn't, watch.
   ``The Soviet Union works at the problem of security penetration
24 hours a day, 365 days a year,'' testified Schlesinger, who
investigated the embassy muddle for President Ronald Reagan. ``If
one signs an agreement that permits the Soviets to pre-cast columns
and beams off site, the principal party to blame is oneself. ... As
Napoleon once observed, there are limits to rascality, there are no
limits to stupidity.''
   The result, said the expert witness, was ``the best-bugged
building ever built.''
   It contained ``a full array of intelligence devices for which we
do not yet understand either the technology or underlying strategy.
... We failed to allow for the boldness, thoroughness and extent of
the penetration.''
   During the building of their embassy in Washington, the
suspicious Soviets watched every blow of the hammer. For every
American working, said an American official observer of the Soviet
observers, there was a Soviet watching.
   They X-rayed ``every inch'' of steel before it went up, said an
architect. They watched concrete poured on site. If the work went
too fast to watch carefully, they slowed the work. They insisted
that window units assembled off site be disassembled and
reassembled before their eyes.
   One result of their vigilance, the Soviets alleged, was the
discovery of pencil-thin microphones in the walls and bugging wires
in the weatherstripping of the windows put there by their American
hosts.
   Another result: The windows now leak.
   Both embassy complexes include a chancery or office building,
consulate, residential apartments, school, gym, swimming pool,
playground, theater und underground garages.
   The new Soviet compound is in a residential area of Washington.
The new U.S. Embassy in Moscow, like the old U.S. Embassy next
door, is surrounded by high-risers where it is assumed the KGB is
in constant attendance.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>