<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0353EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Colombia     12-30 0497</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Colombia,0514</SECOND>
<HEAD>Authorities Find Explosives, Arrest Top Drug Suspect</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM WELLS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Authorities discovered three tons of
dynamite hidden in washing machines and other appliances warehoused
in an area of the capital where drug barons planned to attack
police, an official said.
   Also Friday, security forces said they captured a top Medellin
drug cartel member wanted in the United States.
   In another case, authorities said a judge illegally freed the
brother of one of Colombia's top cocaine kingpins, both of whom are
also wanted by U.S. authorities.
   The dynamite was found Thursday night inside dozens of washing
machines and other appliances stored in a warehouse in southern
Bogota, the chief of the secret police, Gen. Miguel Maza Marquez,
said Friday.
   ``This entire arsenal belonged to the Medellin cartel,'' he told
reporters outside the warehouse. ``We have dismantled its principal
terrorist network.''
   The explosives were to be used to avenge the Dec. 15 police
slaying of Gonzalo Rodriguez Gacha, the No. 2 man in Medellin
cartel, a police news release said.
   Security was increased in Bogota on Friday because authorities
found evidence at the warehouse suggesting that either a bus or
another large vehicle had already been packed with dynamite and
sent into the city, Maza Marquez said.
   The number of military checkpoints was increased in the capital,
and extra soldiers were posted at the Defense Ministry and police
stations.
   The captured drug suspect, Jose Ocampo Obando, was arrested
Friday in the banana-growing region of Uraba on Colombia's northern
coast, the Defense Ministry said in a news release.
   The ministry did not say where Ocampo Obando is wanted in the
United States. Colombia has extradited 11 suspected traffickers to
the United States in the last four months.
   Ocampo Obando is considered by Colombian authorities to be the
fifth-most important member of the Medellin cartel.
   In the western city of Cali, an army general said a judge
illegally released the brother of the leader of the Cali cartel,
the other main cocaine ring in Colombia.
   The judge had no reason to release Jorge Rodriguez Orejuela, who
was wanted for extradition to the United States, army Gen. Jose
Manuel Bonnett said at a news conference Friday in Cali.
   Rodriguez Orejuela's brother is Gilberto Rodriguez Orejuela,
said by Colombian authorities to be the billionaire leader of the
Cali cartel based in the city of the same name.
   Since the government of President Virgilio Barco declared war on
traffickers on Aug. 18, they have responded with 203 bombings that
have killed 199 people and injured 1,238.
   Maza Marquez said that many of the car bombs used in the attacks
had been prepared in the warehouse raided Thursday night.
   Police also received tips from callers saying they belonged to
bands of criminals fighting for control of Rodriguez Gacha's drug
empire, which generates billions of dollars each year.
   Authorities have said the struggle has resulted in the murders
of 34 people during the last two weeks.
</TEXT>

</DOC>