<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1551EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Shoplifting     12-24 0628</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Shoplifting,0661</SECOND>
<HEAD>Expert: Shoplifting Fight Like `Trying to Dam River with Sand'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARTHUR H. ROTSTEIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TUCSON, Ariz. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The holidays are prime time for the
nation's retailers, but they're also high season for the
storeowners' nemesis, the shoplifter, industry officials say.
   ``Thirty-five percent of store losses happen from Thanksgiving
to Jan. 15,'' said Glenn Ricker, a former Sears, Roebuck and Co.
loss prevention security manager and now a district manager of
investigations for Pinkerton, the nation's oldest private
investigative and security agency.
   Shoplifting is a $40 billion a year scourge for retailers _ and
it is becoming increasingly lucrative for criminals such as
burglars, said Lt. James Hughes, head of the Tucson Police
Department's major offenders unit and burglary task force.
   ``It's newer merchandise, easier than breaking into homes and it
has better resale value when the burglars take it to their fence,''
Hughes said.
   Uniform crime report statistics compiled by the FBI, based on
information from 12,019 law enforcement agencies reflecting a
population of 211.6 million Americans, showed 982,552 shoplifting
offenses in 1988, 3.9 percent more than the 945,671 reported in
1988. The average value of stolen property was $104.
   There was a 35 percent upswing in shoplifting between 1984 and
1988, the FBI said.
   According to Hughes, for every shoplifting incident reported,
another three to four go unreported.
   The National Retail Merchants Association said a study shows
``stock shortages'' _ largely a combination of shoplifting and
employee theft _ account for nearly 2 percent of net retail sales
in department stores.
   The spectrum of shoplifters cuts across age, class and gender
lines, and their methods vary widely, said Ricker.
   ``I've caught 5-year-olds and I've caught 75-year-old ladies,
I've caught guys in wheelchairs,'' he said. ``You don't find too
many 70- or 80-year-olds breaking into houses or cars, but trust
me, you find 70-and 80-year-olds shoplifting.''
   Among shoplifters' schemes:
   _Working in teams, allowing one person to distract a clerk while
the other steals merchandise.
   _Sneaking empty store bags inside the store and filling them
with goods.
   _Detaching electronic alarm tags from merchandise.
   _Loading items into false-bottom bags, coats or loose-fitting
clothing.
   _Razor-cutting the top off a cereal box, emptying the contents
and filling the box with more expensive items, such as cigarettes,
then retaping the top and going through the checkout line.
   An item's size doesn't deter shoplifters. Ricker said he caught
one man who tried to steal a chain-saw.
   Ricker estimated that 75 to 80 percent of all such crime is
drug-related.
   Attempts to combat the problem are almost like ``trying to dam a
river with sand,'' he said.
   Many retailers are turning increasingly to security firms for
help.
   ``We're getting more and more calls from retail sales'' asking
both for uniform security and for undercover investigative
services, said Ronald Janick, Pinkerton senior vice president of
investigations in suburban Philadelphia.
   Said Ricker: ``A lot of corporations now are going to contract
loss prevention agents rather than their own in-house (staff)
because it's a lot more cost-effective.''
   Agencies such as Pinkerton take on responsibility for hiring,
screening and training agents, insurance, turnover and paperwork.
   Pinkerton also supplies undercover operatives who blend in with
regular shoppers and the shoplifters.
   One such is Dianne Ruhl, a private investigator who previously
worked as a security agent in department stores in Tucson.
   Ms. Ruhl said suspicious or unusual behavior is a tipoff to a
trained observer.
   Frequently, those caught shoplifting ask if they can just pay
for the items. But, increasingly, merchants are prosecuting.
   Ms. Ruhl said she recently caught a 25-year-old unemployed man
who had stuffed two packs of Camels between a liner and the outside
part of his coat.
   ``And so he's got a record now for $2.70,'' she said. ``Isn't
that stupid?''
</TEXT>

</DOC>