<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0090 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1108EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Mayor-CarnivalMoney     12-22 0288</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mayor-Carnival Money,0295</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bradley May Have Broken Campaign Limit Law, Paper Says</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mayor Tom Bradley may have broken the law in
his method of reporting tens of thousands of dollars in campaign
funds from a series of inner-city carnivals, it was reported today.
   The fund raisers apparently were held on city-owned land without
permission, the Los Angeles Times reported in today's editions.
   Bradley's campaign accountant has said the mayor told him to
list the money on disclosure statements as anonymous donations of
$100 or less, the report said.
   The City Charter prohibits anonymous contributions totaling more
than $200 for any one campaign. Any surplus must go to the city
treasury, Assistant City Attorney Anthony Alperin said.
   Bradley said in a statement Thursday that he would ``take
whatever steps are necessary to correct any mistakes, if any were
made.''
   ``I relied on the campaign attorneys and accountants to decide
how the carnival contributions should be reported,'' said the
mayor, whose financial dealings have come under city and federal
scrutiny.
   The carnivals were held in 1987 and 1988, as Bradley was gearing
up for a campaign fight against City Councilman Zev Yaroslavsky.
During that period, the mayor's re-election campaign received
$164,000 in anonymous and unattributed donations of under $100 _ an
unusually large figure, campaign experts told the Times.
   The amount of smaller contributions dropped sharply after
Yaroslavsky dropped out of the race, the Times said.
   The paper said it obtained copies of $20,000 in money orders
payable to Bradley's re-lection campaign by one of two firms used
for at least 11 carnivals. Bradley's campaign did not receive
permission to hold two of the fund raisers on city land, several
unidentified officials told the paper.
</TEXT>

</DOC>