<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0233 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2123EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Flight103 1stLd-Writethru a0689 12-20 0884</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Flight 103, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0689,0904</SECOND>
<HEAD>Friends, Relatives Mourn Pan Am Flight 103 Bombing One Year Ago</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 5th graf, `A plaque' with 4 grafs to UPDATE with plaque
ceremony, quotes. Picks up 6th, `On Thursday' SUBS grafs 10-11 `The majority'
with 3 grafs to conform and UPDATE with quote from Ammerman. Picks up 12th
pvs, `The U.S.'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LESLIE SHEPHERD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOCKERBIE, Scotland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Friends and relatives of the 270
people killed on Pan Am Flight 103 gathered in this small Scottish
town Wednesday, the eve of the first anniversary of the bombing, to
join residents in mourning.
   One year ago Thursday, the New York-bound Boeing 747 exploded
over Lockerbie, killing all 259 passengers and crew members. Fiery,
molten wreckage fell 31,000 feet, killing another 11 people on the
ground.
   Dec. 21, 1988 _ the shortest day of the year _ became the
longest for the suddenly bereaved, for the town of 3,500 people
jolted into disaster, and for the rescuers who would give up their
Christmas to search for bodies, wreckage and clues.
   Residents of Lockerbie hope that once Thursday's anniversary
passes, they can get on with their lives and return to quiet
obscurity.
   A group of American relatives in Lockerbie for the anniversary
presented a memorial plaque to Councilman Hugh Young at the town
hall Wednesday night.
   ``There were times when we lost our faith in fellow man,'' said
Joe Horgan of Philadelphia, a board member of The Victims of Pan Am
Flight 103, a relatives' support group.
   ``But you only have to come here to have it restored. This town
was devastated itself. These people reached out in the midst of our
own devastation and guided us,'' said Horgan, whose brother-in-law
was on the flight.
   Another plaque made of three slabs of gray Finnish granite
inscribed with all 270 victims' named will be dedicated Thursday at
a new Garden of Remembrance in Dryfesdale Cemetery outside
Lockerbie.
   On Thursday night, about the time the world learned of the
disaster last year, an ecumenical service will be held outside the
Lockerbie Town Hall that a year ago became a makeshift morgue.
   Organizers have kept both remembrance services simple, and no
formal invitations have been issued.
   U.S. Ambassador Henry Catto and his wife, Jessica, will attend
the plaque dedication, the U.S. Embassy said.
   Pan Am said only about two dozen relatives accepted its offer to
fly them to the services. The airline is not sending an official
representative to Lockerbie, but some employees were expected to
attend in a private capacity, said a Pan Am spokesman in New York.
   ``The majority of families, and particularly the leadership of
the families of 103, plan to remain in the United States,'' he
said, referring to The Victims of Pan Am Flight 103.
   Bert Ammerman, whose brother, Thomas, died on the flight and who
heads the group, said some relatives planned to attend a public
memorial service in Washington on Thursday, while others would go
into seclusion.
   ``Most people wish it would go Dec. 20th to the 22nd and forget
the 21st because the 21st ... is, for I don't know how long, for
some people going to bring back just an awful, awful remembrance of
that particular day,'' he said in a British television documentary,
``The Road to Damascus,'' shown Wednesday.
   The U.S. consulate in Edinburgh said some relatives of victims
decided against coming after the State Department warned last week
of possible activity by Middle East terrorists during the holiday
season.
   Police heading the international manhunt for the Flight 103
bombers have confirmed that one focus of their investigation is the
Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine-General Command,
Ahmed Jibril's radical Syrian-based faction.
   Jibril has denied involvement, but acknowledged his group has
used devices similar to the plastic explosives concealed in a
radio-cassette player that blew the jumbo jet apart.
   Chief Constable George Esson of the Dumfries and Galloway
Constabulary says the bomb suitcase was either checked in at
Frankfurt Airport, where the flight originated, or passed through
Frankfurt from a feeder flight. West German authorities say there's
not enough evidence to pinpoint where the bomb originated.
   The only scar remaining in Lockerbie, 15 miles north of the
English border, is a muddy vacant lot on Sherwood Crescent. The
main part of the plane's fuselage, with enough fuel for the
trans-Atlantic journey, exploded on the crescent, destroying 26
homes.
   The 30-foot-deep crater has been filled in, and 10 homes are to
be built on the site. A mile away in Park Place and Rosebank, where
more than 60 bodies fell from the plane, one house has been rebuilt
and 70 renovated.
   Maxwell Kerr, chairman of Rosebank Residents' Association, spoke
of ``a tension in the town'' as the anniversary approached.
   ``There's the feeling that there was last year. It is all
brought back by the media,'' he said.
   Several residents recently attended a course on how to deal with
the media influx.
   ``The coverage we are getting with the anniversary looming
doesn't really help. It builds up pressure,'' said Robert Riddet,
one of them who attended the course. ``It brings back memories.
Everyone in Lockerbie on the night was affected in some way. But we
are fighting back. The scars are healing both in the people and the
town.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>