<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1634EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Judge-Profile     12-17 0572</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Judge-Profile,0589</SECOND>
<HEAD>Vance Remembered as Thoughtful Judge, Democratic Party Healer</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Judge-Explosion, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BIRMINGHAM, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Robert S. Vance was remembered by
friends and colleagues as a thoughtful federal appeals court judge,
who earlier helped heal racial wounds that threatened to destroy
the Alabama Democratic Party.
   Vance, 58, a judge on the Atlanta-based U.S. 11th Circuit Court
of Appeals, was killed by a mail bomb that went off at his home
Saturday afternoon. His wife, Helen, was seriously injured.
   ``He was a voice of sanity in turbulent times and a leader of
reasoned action,'' said Sen. Howell Heflin, D-Ala., who met Vance
more than 30 years ago when they were young trial lawyers.
``Alabama and America's jurisprudence has suffered a tremendous
loss.''
   In 1977, then-President Carter appointed Vance, a former
chairman of the Alabama Democratic Party, to serve as a member of
the 5th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals. He later was assigned to the
new 11th Circuit, which reviews appeals from trial-level federal
courts in Florida, Georgia and Alabama.
   As a judge, Vance did not receive the attention that his party
chairmanship had given him, but he did have a hand in some cases
heavily publicized regionally.
   ``Bob was intellectually brilliant,'' said Huntsville attorney
Julian Butler, a longtime friend. ``He had an incredibly innovative
mind but was realistic and pragmatic. ... He understood the
realities of politics.''
   Vance, a student body president at the University of Alabama,
first gained statewide notice with his efforts to get the Alabama
Legislature to redraw legislative districts to reflect changes in
population in the early 1960s.
   At that time, the State Democratic Executive Committee was under
the control of a staunchly conservative coalition of states' rights
advocates and Dixiecrats loyal to then-segregationist Gov. George
C. Wallace.
   Vance, then a young lawyer, became the champion for loyalist
Democrats who were afraid that Wallace's growing influence would
cause a split with the national Democratic party.
   The Talladega native was elected state party chairman in 1966
and won re-election twice over the next 11 years. He soon began the
political wrangling necessary to fully integrate the all-white
state Democratic party.
   ``He was just such a fine example of what the Democratic party
needed for leadership,'' former state Sen. George Lewis Bailes
said. ``He was very pro-people, pro-Democrat.''
   ``Bob Vance, more than any other human being in Alabama, was
responsible for keeping the Democratic Party in Alabama a
democratic party,'' Butler said.
   One of Vance's first moves as party chairman was to bring about
the removal of the white rooster _ a symbol of white supremacy with
the slogan ``For the Right'' _ from atop the party's election
ballots.
   ``He felt like we had to move forward out of the racial unrest
we were in,'' Heflin said. ``He believed we ought to approach these
things, not draw a line in the dust.''
   Wallace unsuccessfully challenged Vance's leadership of the
party numerous times, backing candidates he thought could unseat
the chairman.
   Vance never held an elected office other than his party
chairmanship and seat on State Democratic Executive Committee. But
his tenure saw some other changes that left their impact on Alabama
politics.
   The party pushed vigorously for election law reform and later
adopted a rule requiring its candidates to disclose their finances
before the party primary elections.
   Vance was survived by his wife of 36 years and by two sons,
Robert S. Vance Jr. and Charles Vance.
</TEXT>

</DOC>