<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1156EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-US-Panama 2ndLd-Writethru a0501 12-27 1031</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-Panama, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0501,990</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Moves to Freeze Noriega's Foreign Assets</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Top 17 grafs new with papers filed, Bush quotes; picks up at
pvs 9thh graf, `We want'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Justice Department today asked authorities
in four European countries to freeze bank accounts where it
believes ousted Panamanian leader Manuel Antonio Noriega stashed
millions of dollars in illegal drug profits.
   ``We have taken steps today in four European countries to freeze
assets in numerous'' accounts, said David Runkel, the department's
chief spokesman. Officials say Noriega hid at least $10 million in
the accounts.
   As the department sought to gain control of Noriega's money,
U.S. officials in Panama and Washington negotiated with the
Vatican, whose embassy in Panama City took in an exhausted Noriega
and 10 associates sought asylum Sunday. Noriega's regime was
toppled on Dec. 20 by U.S. troops.
   U.S. officials sent letters to authorities in Switzerland,
France, Luxembourg and Britain asking them to halt transactions in
the bank accounts belonging to the deposed Panamanian dictator,
Runkel said.
   The actions were taken under international treaty agreements
that the United States has with the foreign nations, he said.
   Based on records seized in Panama, which was invaded by U.S.
troops on Dec. 20, U.S. officials believe they can document that
the money in the overseas accounts stemmed from Noriega's alleged
drug dealing, Runkel said.
   ``We will have to demonstrate to the banking officials'' that
the money was earned illegally, he added. He said ``preliminary
discussions'' were under way with other countries where Noriega has
money.
   While the Justice Department is trying to freeze $10 million,
the State Department estimates Noriega's worth at about $200
million to $300 million.
   In a speech last August, Deputy Secretary of State Lawrence
Eagleburger alluded to multimillion-dollar transactions Noriega has
made over the past two years involving accounts in West Germany,
Switzerland and Luxembourg.
   Justice attorneys are confident that banking officials in the
four European countries will cooperate with their request. ``We've
had a remarkable display of international cooperation,'' Runkel
said.
   But he added there is a possibility that Noriega, his family or
his bankers have already transferred the money out of the accounts
since the U.S. invasion.
   Freezing the accounts if the first step in a process to seize
the assets, Runkel said. Distribution of the money, however, would
be governed by the laws of the countries where the cash is hidden.
   President Bush, meanwhile, told reporters today he did not think
that he or the U.S. government would be embarrassed if information
about Noriega's past links to the CIA came out during a trial of
the Panamanian.
   ``I think that's history and I think the main thing is he should
be tried and brought to justice,'' Bush said in Corpus Christi,
Texas. ``And we are pursuing that course with no fear of that.
   ``You know, you may get into some release of certain
confidential documents that he may try to blindside the whole
justice process. But the system works, so I wouldn't worry about
that.''
   President Bush's spokesman, Marlin Fitzwater, said earlier that
Noriega can talk ``until he's blue in the face'' about his links
with Bush and the CIA.
   The spokesman was referring to things Noriega might reveal about
his past close ties with the U.S. government, including the period
in the 1970s when Bush headed the CIA. ``It won't hurt anything,''
Fitzwater added.
   ``We want Noriega here because he would cause trouble wherever
he goes ... We want him in a nice jail cell where we can keep an
eye on him,'' Fitzwater told reporters aboard Air Force One en
route with Bush to a fishing and hunting vacation in Texas.
   In Panama City, Gen. Maxwell Thurman, head of the U.S. Southern
Command, met face-to-face three times with Monsignor Sebastian
Laboa, the papal nuncio, on the street outside the embassy.
   Less public diplomatic channels also were used to communicate
with the Vatican, though Bush has not contacted Pope John Paul II.
   While U.S. troops ringed the Vatican Embassy to block Noriega
from leaving, Defense Secretary Dick Cheney indicated the soldiers
could be in for a long wait.
   ``It could be that they'll (the Vatican) have a long-term
resident in their embassy in Panama City,'' he told ABC-TV.
   Cheney, along with national security adviser Brent Scowcroft and
Gen. Colin Powell, chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, briefed
Bush on the Panama situation at Camp David, Md., on Tuesday.
   The Vatican, which has no extradition treaty with the United
States, has refused to hand over Noriega to the United States.
Sources in Rome said the Vatican would rather turn Noriega over to
a third country, while another possibility is having Noriega stand
trial in Panama.
   Fitzwater said administration officials have not ruled out
various options, although the U.S. policy is that Noriega should be
brought to trial in the United States. Should the United States
receive custody of Noriega, he would be brought first to Miami for
an initial court appearance.
   Fitzwater said the United States would keep troops around the
Vatican embassy ``as long as he's there.''
   While U.S. officials rejected the idea that Noriega be given
political asylum, one expert said Noriega's fate is in the
Vatican's hands.
   ``Asylum in an embassy is well recognized,'' said John Lawrence
Hargrove, executive director of the American Society of
International Law. ``If the Vatican says he is entitled to asylum,
he is safe. The Latin Americans are especially strong on diplomatic
asylum.''
   Runkel said Noriega's claims to asylum are invalid because he
doesn't fit into the categories for which asylum is granted:
persecution on the grounds of religious or political beliefs.
   ``His fears are of prosecution in the United States on two
indictments.'' he said.
   Meantime, Cheney, who spent Christmas day in Panama, indicated
some of the 26,000 U.S. troops in the country could be brought back
sooner than expected because the situation is returning to normal.
He gave no timetable.
   Despite occasional sniping incidents, Cheney said the
``overwhelming sense is a return to normalcy.'' Cheney said the
``U.S. military did its job'' and now ``the lawyers and the
diplomats have to take over.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>