<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0155 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2051EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-MissingPlane     12-19 0406</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Missing Plane,0414</SECOND>
<HEAD>Wreckage of Plane That Vanished With Six People Aboard Found, No
Survivors</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CATSKILL, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The wreckage of a small plane missing for
four days was found Tuesday afternoon in a rugged section of the
Catskill Mountains, authorities said. None of the six people aboard
survived.
   A state police helicopter found the wreckage at 2:15 p.m. along
a steep escarpment about 10 miles west of this city about 30 miles
south of Albany, officials said.
   An Air National Guard rescue team was dropped into the crash
site by helicopter, but found no survivors, state police Maj. Carl
Colberg said in Albany. Another team was to climb the mountains
Wednesday morning to recover the bodies, Colberg said.
   The twin-engine Piper Navajo disappeared from radar screens
Friday evening about 30 miles south of Albany while en route from
Glens Falls in the southern Adirondack Mountains to Montgomery
nearly 50 miles northwest of New York City. The plane crashed in
Catskill Park near Blackhead and Thomas Cole mountains, two peaks
more than 3,900 feet high. Radar put the plane at an altitude of
2,300 feet when it disappeared.
   Search efforts were hampered by bad weather and malfunctioning
emergency transmitter in the missing plane's tail, rescuers said.
The area where the plane disappeared has received almost 10 inches
of snow since Friday.
   Emergency transmitters are supposed to emit a signal on impact,
but searchers didn't received a signal from the downed aircraft,
said Tom Moreen, a Civil Air Patrol official in Albany.
   More than 20 aircraft searched a 5,000-square-mile area in the
Catskills and the Hudson Valley on Tuesday, said Civil Air Patrol
spokeswoman Ann MacMillan. The air patrol, state police, the state
Department of Environmental Conservation and the Army provided
aircraft for the search.
   Aboard the plane were pilot Timothy Burns, 27, of Allentown,
N.J., and five people who'd attended a business meeting in the
Glens Falls area, according to Briar Contracting spokesman Dick
Mann, whose company was owned by one of the passengers.
   Mann identified the passengers as Salvatore Arlotta Jr., 42, of
Walkill and Peter Lovi, 33, of Pine Bush, both employees of the
Wehran Engineering environmental consulting firm in Middletown;
Ronald D. Pacchiana, 56, of Pound Ridge, president of Briar
Contracting and owner of Unicorn Industries Ltd., both in
Peekskill; attorney Michael J. Trainor, 45, of New York City; and
Timothy P. Burns, 44, of Yonkers, no relation to the pilot.
</TEXT>

</DOC>