<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1158EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Obit-Martin 2ndLd-Writethru a0516 12-26 1039</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Obit-Martin, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0516,1066</SECOND>
<HEAD>Billy Martin, Former Yankee Manager, Dies in Alcohol-Related Crash</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 22 grafs to UPDATE with cause of death, neither man
wearing seat belt, accident occurred on curve with history of accidents,
add Martin's given name, autopsy canceled, recent bar incident involving
gun, pickup at 17th graf pvs, `Martin was first...' A version moved on
the sports wire.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM KATES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PORT CRANE, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Billy Martin, the hard-drinking,
hard-nosed former Yankee manager whose on- and off-field brawls
overshadowed his accomplishments on the baseball diamond, died in
an alcohol-related traffic accident.
   He was 61.
   Martin was a passenger in a pickup truck that skidded off an icy
road in front of his farm Christmas Day. The driver, longtime
friend William Reedy, 53, of Detroit, was charged with driving
while intoxicted, Broome County Sheriff Anthony Ruffo said.
   Neither man was wearing a seat belt, Reedy told authorities.
   ``It's like losing part of my own family,'' said New York
Yankees' principal owner George Steinbrenner, who hired and fired
Martin five times as manager. ``He was one of a kind.''
   ``If somebody rubbed wrong against him, he'll punch ya in the
nose no sooner than look at him,'' said Yogi Berra, a former
teammate and a friend for 40 years. ``But he was a great man, a
kind-hearted man and he loved baseball.''
   Martin died of a broken neck and spinal cord compression at
Wilson Memorial Hospital in Johnson City after the 5:45 p.m. crash,
according to hospital spokesman Michael Doll.
   The truck went off a hairpin curve and came to rest at the
driveway of Martin's 148-acre farm near Binghamton, about 150 miles
northwest of New York City near the Pennsylvania line.
   Ruffo said the hairpin curve has a history of accidents.
   ``People who live out in that area and use that road know it's
there,'' he said today. ``But Reedy was from Detroit and that could
have been a factor that he wasn't familiar with the area. If you're
not familiar with it, it doesn't take much to end up in the ditch.''
   Reedy, owner of Reedy's Bar near Detroit's Tiger Stadium,
suffered a broken hip and possible broken ribs and was in serious
condition at the hospital, Doll said.
   ``They went way back,'' said Reedy's son, Bill, 19. A distraught
Martin called Reedy just after his mother died 10 days ago, Bill
Reedy said. He said his father didn't hesitate to go to his
friend's side.
   Reedy said he and Martin had gone to a store and then stopped
for a drink, according to Deputy Steve Glanville, who issued the
citation.
   An autopsy scheduled to be performed today on Martin was
canceled at the request of family members, Doll said.
   Alfred Manuel Martin was born May 16, 1928, in Berkeley, Calif.
His Italian grandmother called him ``Belli,'' Italian for pretty,
and it evolved into Billy.
   Martin played second base for the Yankees from 1950-57,
including five World Series championships.
   His lifetime batting average for his 11 seasons was just .257,
but he always seemed at his best in October. He set a six-game
World Series record in 1953 by batting .500 in the series and
hitting safely in all six games. He also set a seven-game World
Series record by hitting safely in every game of the 1956 Series.
   ``He was a great little guy,'' said Yankee legend Joe DiMaggio.
   Martin brought his combative style to the dugout as manager,
arguing with players and umpires and getting his teams to play a
hard-running game dubbed ``Billy ball.''
   But his antics off the field clouded his career. He got into a
fight in a topless bar in Texas on May 6, 1988, hours after being
ejected from a game for arguing a call with an umpire. Six weeks
later, he was fired by Steinbrenner.
   Another barroom incident had him back in the headlines just this
month. Martin, in Terre Haute, Ind., on Dec. 9 to speak at a
fund-raiser, was sitting at a bar when someone knocked over a
woman's purse containing a .38-caliber derringer, causing the gun
to fire. The bullet whizzed past Martin and struck the bar two feet
from him.
   Martin was first hired to manage the Yankees in 1975. During
that stint, he guided the team to a World Series title in 1977, a
season marked by his shoving match with slugger Reggie Jackson in
Boston's Fenway Park in June.
   The next season, Jackson was suspended five days after ignoring
Martin's instruction to bunt.
   Five days later, Martin lashed out at Jackson and Steinbrenner
saying, ``One's a born liar; the other's convicted,'' a reference
to Steinbrenner's guilty plea to violating federal elections laws
for a 1972 campaign contribution to President Nixon.
   Martin resigned in tears a day after his statement. Only five
days later, however, Steinbrenner announced he would bring Martin
back, a promise he fulfilled the next year.
   His latest firing was on June 23, 1988, but Steinbrenner
retained him as a consultant.
   Martin married his fourth wife, the former Jill Guiver, in
January 1988. In an interview last July, Martin said he was
enjoying life on the farm and out of the spotlight.
   During his 16 seasons as an American League manager, Martin's
teams compiled a 1,258-1,018 record, a .553 winning percentage.
   He led the Minnesota Twins to an American League West title in
1969 and the Detroit Tigers to an AL East title in 1970. He led the
Yankees to AL pennants in 1976 and 1977 and the Oakland Athletics
to an AL West title in 1981. He also managed the Texas Rangers.
   A plaque honoring Martin in Yankee Stadium's center field
monument area says: ``Casey's Boy,'' a reference to the special
affection the late Casey Stengal had for Martin. ``A Yankee
Forever,'' the plaque says, ``A man who knew only one way to play _
to win.''
   ``Billy was a true Yankee _ one of the truest ever,'' said
current Yankees manager Bucky Dent, who played for Martin in the
1970s.
   In addition to his wife, survivors include son Billy Joe of
Lubbock, Texas, and daughter, Kelly, both from previous marriages.
   Funeral services were not immediately announced.
</TEXT>

</DOC>