<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0098 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1532EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Congress Bjt   12-19 0819</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Congress, Bjt,0837</SECOND>
<HEAD>Congress Backs Gorbachev's Traditional Economic Plan</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN-THOR DAHLBURG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Premier Nikolai I. Ryzhkov defeated the Soviet
Congress' first try at a no-confidence vote Tuesday and won
overwhelming approval for an economic revival plan based on
traditional socialist methods of state planning.
   Critics say Ryzhkov's plan continues the same bureaucratic
meddling in the economy that after more than 70 years of Soviet
rule has led to widespread shortages of consumer goods, the
rationing of items ranging from meat to matches and a multibillion
ruble state deficit.
   In a dramatic Kremlin showdown, President Mikhail S. Gorbachev
interceded from the dais on behalf of his fellow Politburo member,
asking for a clear pledge of support from the 2,250-member Congress
of People's Deputies, or parliament, that is the centerpiece of his
political reforms.
   ``It's a political question: Will we support this government and
what it has introduced, or will we keep the government in such a
state all the time that it cannot begin its work?'' Gorbachev
demanded of the Congress, meeting in the Kremlin Palace of
Congresses.
   Ryzhkov, 60, and his ministers have been a lightning rod for
parliamentary and popular discontent since the Congress and its
smaller working legislature, the Supreme Soviet, began functioning
this summer.
   Progressives say the plan presented by Ryzhkov to the Congress
Dec. 13 is a triumph for bureaucrats and conservatives, since it
rejects more radical proposals by the premier's top economist,
Leonid Abalkin, for selling off money-losing state enterprises and
urgent measures to free some prices from state controls.
   Although the Kremlin allows its East European allies virtual
free rein in reforming their economies, Ryzhkov's plan shows its
deep-seated reluctance to abandon government levers controlling its
own economy that date to the reign of dictator Josef Stalin and
earlier.
   Instead, Ryzhkov's proposals shift central planning from its
traditional emphasis on heavy industry to consumer goods as a way
of filling chronically empty store shelves.
   Yuri Andreev, a Moscow engineer, called on the Congress to
express its lack of confidence in Ryzhkov's government by asking it
to draft a new economic reform plan and to fire the officials who
drafted the orginal version.
   The normally cool and composed Ryzhkov, his voice cracking with
emotion, pleaded with the deputies for clear-cut support. ``The
Congress should not avoid making an evaluation,'' he said. ``It
must express its firm position: either to support the government's
proposals ... or some other formulation.''
   After his appeal, the no-confidence measure was voted down 1,685
to 199, with 99 abstentions. A separate vote on the economic plan,
which includes emergency measures as well as guidelines for the
1991-95 13th five-year plan, was approved 1,532 to 419, with 44
deputies abstaining.
   Ryzhkov stood and clasped his hands in victory as members of the
Congress applauded. He had hinted in a newspaper interview printed
Sunday that he would leave office if the plan were not approved.
   Abalkin was quoted by the official Tass news agency as saying
all members of the Council of Ministers that Ryzhkov heads were
``ready to resign immediately'' if the proposal failed to win the
Congress' backing.
   Though Andreev's proposal was defeated, it was the latest sign
of feistiness by lawmakers in the Gorbachev age, and a stark
contrast with the unanimous approval once given every proposal the
Kremlin leadership put to a vote.
   In its afternoon session, the Congress showed its combativeness
again by not giving the leadership the needed majority for a
proposed constitutional amendment that would have continued special
parliamentary representation for Gorbachev's Communist Party and
other officially sanctioned organizations.
   So-called ``social organizations'' are now empowered to elect
750 Congress members, with the other two-thirds of the deputies
chosen in competitive elections nationwide. The organizations'
special representation has provoked discontent among deputies who
have to go in front of voters.
   The editorial commission of the Congress, headed by party
ideologue Vadim A. Medvedev, proposed amending the Constitution to
say that special representatives ``may be'' elected by social
organizations, replacing the automatic guarantee of 750 Congress
seats.
   That language was considered too tepid by deputies who want the
special provision eliminated. The proposed amendment received only
1,078 ``yes'' votes, more than 400 short of the two-thirds majority
required for such a measure. Of the other deputies, 810 voted
against and 44 abstained.
   At Gorbachev's urging, the Congress also passed a decree
instructing the Supreme Soviet to pass a raft of laws by February
that are considered crucial to the Kremlin leader's plans for
economic reform.
   Progressives originally wanted the laws on property, land,
leasing and other matters debated at the Congress. Yuri Boldyrev of
Leningrad said Gorbachev's move was a tactical victory for
reformers, since conservatives in the Congress could have stymied
action on the laws. But he said the decree sets a ``dangerous
precedent'' by allowing the Supreme Soviet to do work that should
be done by the Congress.
</TEXT>

</DOC>