<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1032EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Soviet-Lithuania     12-20 0301</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Soviet-Lithuania,0307</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lithuanian Communists Approve Documents on Split with Moscow</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK J. PORUBCANSKY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VILNIUS, U.S.S.R. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lithuanian Communists overwhelmingly
approved a resolution today calling for an end to their
subordination to the Soviet Communist Party.
   A final vote on formally establishing a fully independent
Lithuanian Communist Party was delayed by several hours of debate
on procedural questions.
   By a vote of 838-142, the Lithuanian Communist Party congress _
meeting in the capital, Vilnius _ approved a resolution calling for
``relations of equal partnership with the Soviet Communist Party,
other progressive parties, public organizations and movements.''
   Lithuanian Communists, who supported a legislative move Dec. 7
to strike the leading role of the party from the Baltic republic's
constitution, are spurred by the need to compete with the
grass-roots political movement Sajudis and other newly formed
parties in local elections Feb. 24.
   President Mikhail S. Gorbachev, general secretary of the Soviet
Communist Party, has appealed to Lithuanian Communists not to break
away, saying a split will damage his reform efforts.
   A formal break would run counter to more than 80 years of
Communist Party practice and policy. Since before the 1917 Russian
Revolution, Vladimir I. Lenin demanded a unified party covering the
entire territory of the czarist empire. In 1921, the party outlawed
the existence of factions.
   Sajudis observers say local Communist Parties in other republics
such as Latvia, Estonia, Georgia and Armenia could follow
Lithuania's example soon and present Gorbachev with a splintered
party when he convenes the 28th national party congress in the fall.
   Delegates also approved on a vote of 850-139 a separate
declaration saying Lithuania's Communist Party's relations with the
national party must be based on ``mutual understanding,
restructuring of the Soviet Communist Party and the results of the
28th Soviet Party Congress.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>