<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1036EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-OilPrices 1stLd-Writethru a0473 12-27 0561</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Oil Prices, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0473,0572</SECOND>
<HEAD>Heating Oil Prices Surge In Reaction To Cold Snap, Refinery Fire</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to UPDATE with prices continuing to climb
today; picks up 8th graf, `There's no....' A version moved on financial
wires.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCY GORDON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Heating oil futures jumped higher again today in
early trading, continuing the trend that accelerated after a
weekend explosion at the nation's second-largest petrochemical
plant.
   Heating oil futures prices had surged Tuesday in the wake of the
blast at the Exxon Corp. refinery at Baton Rouge, La. The accident
at the plant, which normally produces about 4.4 million gallons of
heating oil daily, aggravated a price spike caused by the
record-setting cold snap that has hit much of the nation and raised
the prospect of further spot oil shortages.
   The explosion Christmas Eve killed two people and shattered
windows in buildings as far as six miles away. The second body was
recovered Tuesday. An investigation has yet to determine the cause
of the blast.
   Supplies of home heating oil already were tight before the
explosion and the accelerated demand has pushed retail prices as
high as $1 a gallon in some areas.
   Wholesale prices also have surged, as reflected by the futures
market. Heating oil for January delivery, up 10.74 cents on
Tuesday, jumped another 4.02 cents to 96.50 cents a gallon in early
trading today on the New York Mercantile Exchange.
   Crude oil and gasoline futures also rose, adding to gains made
Tuesday in thin trading. Markets were closed Monday for Christmas.
   The February contract for West Texas Intermediate, the benchmark
U.S. crude oil, was up 5 cents at $21.96 a barrel in early trading,
following Tuesday's 62-cent rise. Unleaded regular gasoline for
January, up 5.49 cents on Tuesday, rose 0.06 cent to 61 cents a
gallon in early trading today.
   ``There's no stopping prices for the short term until the
temperatures warm up,'' said Dillard Spriggs, president of
Petroleum Analysis Ltd. in New York.
   Exxon, Mobil Corp. and Star Enterprise, a Texaco Inc. affiliate,
reported last week that some of their terminals in the Northeast
suffered temporary oil shortages and customers were sent to other
suppliers or forced to wait for new shipments.
   On Tuesday, Texaco spokesman Peter Maneri said further
information on the shortages was unavailable. Mobil's offices were
closed for the holiday and telephone calls went unanswered.
   Exxon spokesman Jim Davis in Houston said the company wouldn't
have any problems supplying contract volumes of heating oil to
customers. ``There is some flexibility in the network,'' he said.
   The company has about a week before supplies become a problem,
Davis said, noting that Exxon can increase heating oil production
at its refineries in Baytown, Texas, and Linden, N.J. Davis said it
was impossible to predict when the Baton Rouge refinery would begin
operating normally again.
   He said the crippled plant made a large heating oil shipment to
the East Coast on Saturday and hadn't planned to supply the region
again until after Jan. 1.
   But oil traders appeared skeptical.
   ``The market's factoring in a lot more than that,'' said Peter
Beutel, assistant director of the energy group at Elders Futures
Inc.
   The futures market is betting it will take Exxon five days or
more to get the Baton Rouge refinery operating normally again,
Beutel said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>