<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0455EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-People-Buchwald-Paramount     12-19 0504</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-People-Buchwald-Paramount,0521</SECOND>
<HEAD>Buchwald, Arsenio Hall Testify in $5 Million Suit</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Testimony resumes at noon EST</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LINDA DEUTSCH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Columnist Art Buchwald testified in his
breach-of-contract lawsuit that he based the script idea for the
smash movie ``Coming to America'' on a real African king who drove
a Studebaker.
   But entertainer Arsenio Hall told the court he and comedian
Eddie Murphy brainstormed the 1988 movie.
   Buchwald was to return to the stand today after beginning his
testimony Monday in his $5 million lawsuit against Paramount
Pictures, which optioned the columnist's screenplay ``King for a
Day'' in 1984.
   Buchwald told Superior Court Judge Harvey Schneider that he
wrote his script idea originally titled, ``It's a Crude, Crude
World,'' based on a ``data bank'' of experiences he keeps in his
head.
   The king, he said, may have been based on a Watusi king he
interviewed in Africa in the 1950s. ``He was a real king and he
drove a Studebaker,'' he recalled.
   Soon after he wrote the script idea, Buchwald said, producer and
co-plaintiff Alain Bernheim sold the option to Paramount and the
writer received $17,500, ``less 10 per cent to my agent.''
   The Pulitzer Prize-winning columnist and author said
negotiations began for Louis Malle to direct, and then he heard
that Murphy would star. ``I was delighted,'' he said.
   Buchwald contends that Paramount reneged on the production deal
and used his idea for the film that amassed $300 million in box
office earnings.
   Hall, the late-night TV talk-show host who co-starred in
``Coming to America,'' said he never saw a script idea entitled
``King for a Day.''
   Both stories tell the tale of an African prince who comes to the
United States, falls in love and takes home a bride.
   ``I think a lot of stories have been written about African
princes,'' Hall told reporters outside court. ``I'm offended
because Eddie is a very bright man. I'm a bright guy. Why do we
have to seek a stolen concept? It's insulting.''
   Buchwald, 64, said he was sorry Hall felt insulted.
   ``I like Arsenio. He's a nice fellow,'' he said. ``This is
between Paramount and me.''
   Paramount Chairman Frank Mancuso described Murphy's rich
contract with the studio, which gives him $8 million a picture plus
15 per cent of gross profits. And he indicated Murphy wants more.
   ``Like a good baseball player, we're always negotiating with
him,'' Mancuso said. ``He's a very important star.''
   Hall said he and Murphy set out in 1987 to create the first
black fairy tale. He said they were intent on improving the image
of blacks as well as Murphy's own screen image.
   ``There had never been a black fairy tale,'' Hall said. ``We
wanted to create like a fairy tale _ beautiful _ like the prince
got the girl. We wanted a fairy tale everyone could relate to.''
   Hall said he and Murphy wanted to shape the screenplay
themselves because ``otherwise, it would just be another black
story written by white people.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>