<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0272 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1647EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Ford-Securities     12-22 0257</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ford-Securities,0269</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ford To Offer $1.55 Billion in Debt Securities</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ford Motor Co. intends to sell $1.55 billion
in debt securities to pay for its recent acquisition of Associates,
the nation's third-largest independent finance company, according
to documents filed Friday.
   In a registration statement filed with the Securities and
Exchange Commission, Ford said it is seeking to issue the debt
securities through Ford Holdings Inc., a subsidiary formed in
September to acquire Associates.
   The debt securities will be sold ``to reduce short-term debt,
including borrowings to fund the acquisition of Associates,''
according to the registration statement.
   Ford acquired Dallas-based Associates First Capital Corp. from
Paramount Communications Inc. for $3.35 billion on Oct. 31.
   According to the statement, Ford financed the Associates
acquisition through $2.25 billion in loans and the issuance of $800
million in flexible rate auction preferred stock.
   Last month, a Ford subsidiary began a $2.5 billion cash tender
offer to acquire Jaguar PLC, the British luxury carmaker.
   ``Continued large capital expenditures for new automotive
products and facilities improvements, together with the
acquisitions of Associates and Jaguar, have used and will continue
to use substantial amounts of cash,'' the statement said.
   ``Consequently, Ford and its affiliates may substantially
increase borrowings in 1990 and thereafter.''
   Associates is the third-largest independent finance company
based on total assets of $14 billion. The company has dealings in
real estate-secured loans, credit cards, direct installment and
revolving loans.
   Ford's SEC filing said the debt securities would be sold through
underwriters which may include Goldman, Sachs &amp; Co.
</TEXT>

</DOC>