<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1450EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-EC-Shevardnadze     12-17 0351</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-EC-Shevardnadze,0363</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shevardnadze Arrives For Historic Two-Day Visit</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Czechoslovakia, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRUSSELS, Belgium (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard
Shevardnadze arrived Sunday for a historic two-day visit to visit
NATO headquarters and sign a trade and economic cooperation accord
with the European Community.
   Shevardnadze was greeted at Abelag Airport by Belgian Foreign
Minister Mark Eyskens. He made no statement upon arrival.
   On Tuesday, Shevardnadze will pay a 90-minute visit to the
headquarters of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization for talks
with NATO Secretary General Manfred Woerner and the ambassadors of
the member nations.
   Officials have said there is no fixed agenda for the talks at
alliance headquarters and have described it as a courtesy call that
is indicative of the new East-West climate.
   On Monday, Shevardnadze will meet with the foreign ministers of
the 12-nation EC trade bloc and sign a cooperation agreement.
   He also will meet separately with Belgian Prime Minister
Wilfried Martens and King Baudouin and will discuss the reforms
sweeping acrosss Eastern Europe with government ministers during a
meeting that will continue over lunch.
   The economic agreement with the EC was concluded Nov. 27 and
provides for a gradual lifting of EC import quotas on Soviet
industrial goods by 1995.
   The accord also lists a dozen areas in which the EC and the
Soviet Union plan to establish economic cooperation. These include
science and technology, banking, transport, agriculture,
environmental protection, energy, raw materials and mining.
   The accord excludes trade in goods that are considered
militarily sensitive, according to EC sources.
   The EC-Soviet accord is the fourth between the community and an
East European nation since the EC and the Moscow-led Comecon trade
bloc signed a mutual recognition accord June 25, 1988.
   Since then the EC has concluded trade and economic cooperation
accords with the Soviet Union, Hungary, Poland and Czechoslovakia.
   The EC's trade with Eastern Europe is small. It totalled only
$56 billion in 1987, the last year for which complete figures are
available and about half of that was with the Soviet Union.
   By comparison, the EC's trade with Switzerland that year was
some $66 billion.
</TEXT>

</DOC>