<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0255 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2304EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s f BC-Eastern-Chronology Adv24   12-21 0637</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Eastern-Chronology, Adv 24,0668</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv24</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Sunday, Dec. 24</HEAD>
<HEAD>With BC-Eastern-Then and Now</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are key events in the Machinists union strike against
Eastern Airlines:
   _March 3 _ President Bush refuses National Mediation Board
request to use his authority under Railway Labor Act to delay
strike 60 days. Machinists reject Eastern's latest contract offer.
Talks collapse at midnight.
   _March 4 _ Strike begins, canceling almost 90 percent of Eastern
flights, stranding passengers across nation, in Caribbean and Latin
America.
   _March 5 _ Few Eastern flights take off as pilots honor the
strike.
   _March 6 _ Eastern idles 7,000 non-union workers and cancels
nearly all flights. Airline asks federal judge to order pilots back
to work.
   _March 7 _ Judge refuses to order pilots back to work. Eastern
furloughs another 2,500 employees.
   _March 9 _ Eastern files for protection from creditors under
Chapter 11 in U.S. Bankruptcy Court in New York.
   _March 31 _ Real estate tycoon Donald Trump announces he has
completed a restructured deal to buy Eastern's Northeast shuttle
service for $365 million. The new deal, revised from an October
1988 agreement, provides him with four additional Boeing 727s.
   _April 6 _ A group led by former baseball commissioner Peter V.
Ueberroth announces it will acquire Eastern and a 19.9 percent
stake in the System One reservations system in a deal valued at
$464 million. Under the deal with Eastern's parent Texas Air Corp.,
Eastern employees would own 30 percent of the airline in return for
wage and benefit concessions.
   _April 12 _ Ueberroth and Eastern announce the buyout proposal
has collapsed. Eastern says it intends to reorganize as a smaller
carrier serving roughly 50 percent to 60 percent of its pre-strike
schedule.
   _May 3 _ A group led by William Howard, former chairman of
Piedmont Aviation, discloses that it is interested in making a
buyout proposal for all of Eastern. Chicago businessman Joseph
Ritchie already has expressed interest.
   America West Airlines offers to pay $726 million for Eastern's
shuttle and 10 Boeing 757s.
   _May 23 _ Eastern graduates its first class of new pilots hired
since the start of the strike.
   _May 25 _ Lifland formally approves the sale of the shuttle to
Trump for $365 million, after America West withdraws offer because
of failure to arrange financing.
   _June 1 _ David Shapiro, bankruptcy examiner in the Eastern
case, dismisses the Howard group's offer.
   _June 2 _ Eastern announces an austerity program for non-union
employees.
   _June 5 _ Lifland removes the Ritchie plan from consideration.
   _July 21 _ Eastern submits a reorganization plan to the
bankruptcy court. Creditors express approval.
   _Early August _ The striking pilots vote to continue their
sympathy walkout.
   _Aug. 24 _ Texas Air Chairman Frank Lorenzo says he is
considering selling all or part of Continental Airlines, Eastern's
sister carrier. Scandinavian Airlines Systems, which owns 9.9
percent of Texas Air, reportedly is interested in buying a stake in
Continental.
   _Aug. 31 _ Eastern abandons an earlier plan to sell Latin
American routes, giving it around $370 million less in cash by
yearend than first projected.
   _Sept. 8 _ The striking pilots vote to throw out their leader,
Jack Bavis, for proposing that they consider ending walkout.
   _Sept. 13 _ Lorenzo tells Texas Air shareholders Eastern will
turn a profit in 1990. SAS says it has no ``immediate interest'' in
buying part of Continental.
   _Nov. 22 _ The 2,250 pilots still on strike vote to end it. The
striking flight attendants quickly follow, leaving the Machinists
alone on picket lines. Eastern says few jobs are left because it's
hired replacements.
   _Dec. 19 _ American Airlines announces it will buy Latin
American routes and other assets from Texas Air for $471 million.
The deal shrinks Eastern to about two-thirds its pre-strike size.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Sunday, Dec. 24</NOTE>

</DOC>