<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0631EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Educators'Compact     12-21 0420</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Educators' Compact,0433</SECOND>
<HEAD>Region Agrees to Work Toward Common Market For Teachers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALLISON J. PUGH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An agreement billed as the nation's first common
market for educators has been signed by officials in seven states
seeking to draw talented teachers to the Northeast.
   ``This must be the most attractive section of the country for
teachers if we want to attract the kind of talent we are used to in
New England,'' Harold Raynolds Jr., commissioner of education in
Massachusetts, said Wednesday after the agreement was signed during
a conference here.
   The pact, which goes into effect April 1, 1990, will loosen the
certification restrictions that prohibit teachers from moving
across state lines.
   Under the plan, teachers with a Northeast Regional Credential
who move within the region would have two years to fulfill any
unmet requirements for certification in their new state of
residence.
   The states in the agreement are Massachusetts, Vermont, Rhode
Island, New Hampshire, Maine, Connecticut and New York.
   New Jersey, Pennsylvania, Delaware, Maryland and the District of
Columbia also were making overtures to join the Northeast compact,
said Anne Newton, a director for The Regional Laboratory, a
federally funded educational research group which helped to develop
the agreement with the Northeast Common Market Project. California
also was watching the experiment closely, she said.
   Teacher representatives heralded the agreement as one more step
toward ``professionalizing'' education.
   ``It's very exciting and very forward-thinking,'' said Rosanne
Bacon, president of the 68,000-member Massachusetts Teachers
Association.
   Bacon said the agreement would, among other things, encourage
more competitive salaries for teachers, who could move to states
which offered them more money or benefits.
   ``We're going to have an incredible interest in people moving
from one area into an area where they are truly needed, and the
market will obviously have to reflect that, with higher salaries,''
said Bacon, who teaches at a public high school.
   With 20 years' teaching experience and two masters degrees,
Bacon said she could earn $24,000 more a year if she worked 30
miles away in Connecticut.
   Raynolds and top educators in other states insisted they were
interested in improving teaching in the region, not just in their
state.
   ``We're trying to think and act regionally,'' said Richard P.
Mills, Vermont's education commissioner.
   Not all seven states embraced the agreement wholeheartedly.
Maine has agreed to allow teachers to fulfill their requirements in
one year, instead of two.
   Connecticut agreed to accept out-of-state teachers under the
terms of the agreement only in vocational classes.
</TEXT>

</DOC>