<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0167 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0105EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-BusinessHighlights     12-27 0842</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Business Highlights,0882</SECOND>
<DATELINE>ORLANDO, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Citrus growers were optimistic that trees
suffered little lasting harm from a Christmas frost that caused
widespread damage to Florida fruit and vegetables and could boost
prices for those crops.
   Florida's third major killer freeze in six years was not
believed as disastrous to citrus trees as those in December 1983
and January 1985.
   But near-total losses were reported in winter vegetables _ much
of them destined for Northeastern markets _ in large areas of the
state.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Heating oil futures prices surged in the wake of
a weekend explosion at an Exxon Corp. refinery in Baton Rouge, La.,
boosting prices and raising prospects of further spot oil shortages.
   The accident at the plant aggravated a price spike caused by the
record-setting cold snap that has hit much of the nation. Supplies
of home heating oil already were tight before the explosion.
   Heating oil contracts for January delivery jumped 10.74 cents
from Friday to close at 92.48 cents a gallon Tuesday on the New
York Mercantile Exchange.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>By The Associated Press</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Retailers rang up modest to moderate holiday sales thanks partly
to a late pickup in shopping, but analysts said profits were
impaired by discounts widely used to attract customers.
   Bargain hunters had an abundance of choices because stores
slashed prices on items ranging from clothing to electronic gadgets.
   ``I think the consumer had a very, very merry Christmas and I'm
not so sure that the retailers did from a profit point of view,''
analyst Linda R. Morris of PNC Financial Corp. said Tuesday.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three days before federal bank regulators
approved a delay in seizing Lincoln Savings and Loan in May 1988,
the private accountant whose audits influenced the decision
switched jobs and went to work for the thrift's owner, according to
documents and interviews.
   The two regulators whose votes delayed the seizure for a year
say they did not know at the time that the accountant, Jack D.
Atchison, had taken the new job.
   But in recent statements, former Federal Home Loan Bank Board
Chairman M. Danny Wall and board member Roger F. Martin said their
decision concerning the fate of Lincoln _ the nation's costliest
thrift failure _ might have been different if they had been
informed.

</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Securities and Exchange Commission named
agency veteran William C. McLucas as its new enforcement chief and
unveiled plans for a fraud unit covering the sale of securities by
financial institutions.
   McLucas, 39, succeeds Gary Lynch, who resigned as enforcement
chief in July after heading landmark insider-trading investigations
such as cases against speculator Ivan Boesky and Wall Street firm
Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc.
   The enforcement job is considered the second most powerful
position at the SEC.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>HIGHLAND PARK, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chrysler Corp. Chairman Lee Iacocca
said 1990 could be the toughest year in a decade for the auto
industry, which already is hurting from declining sales and
temporary layoffs.
   Iacocca said Tuesday in a year-end statement that 1989 sales of
9.8 million cars and 5.1 million trucks mark a return to a ``more
normal trend'' after four years of combined industry sales of 15.2
million to 16.3 million vehicles.
   He said sales estimates for 1990 of 9.5 million cars and 5
million light trucks are based largely on costly incentive programs
across the industry.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Business executives, bank officers, attorneys, real
estate brokers and even car dealers have been drafted into the war
on drugs _ whether they like it or not.
   Armed with stiff new regulations passed under the Bank Secrecy
Act of 1988, the IRS and other federal agencies are forcing
businesses and financial institutions to help track the estimated
$220 million in profits generated daily by illegal drug sales in
this country.
   ``All that cash does no good stored in boxes. They have to turn
it around. That necessarily involves legitimate businesses,'' said
Miami lawyer Charles Intriago, who has started a publication that
promises to make sense of the regulatory maze.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BELGRADE, Yugoslavia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first stock exchange in
Communist Yugoslavia was set up in the northern city of Ljubljana,
the state Tanjug news agency reported.
   It said the exchange was founded Tuesday with a total capital of
$17 million, and that 152 stocks representing more than 50 percent
of its capital were owned by 23 Yugoslav banks. The exchange will
list Yugoslav and foreign companies.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Prices closed narrowly mixed Tuesday on Wall Street as rising
oil prices triggered concerns about inflation and interest rates.
The Dow Jones average of 30 industrials closed 2.13 points lower at
2,709.26.
   The dollar declined against most key foreign currencies. Gold
prices fell in U.S. trading after rising in Asia.
   Bond prices tumbled.
   Orange juice futures prices soared after a weekend freeze in the
South, heating oil futures climbed dramatically, coffee and cotton
futures rose sharply, precious metals futures fell, livestock and
meat futures advanced and grains and soybeans retreated.
</TEXT>

</DOC>