<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0201EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-WashingtoninBrief     12-23 0332</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Washington in Brief,330</SECOND>
<HEAD>Justice Rules Menorah May Be Erected</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Jewish group will be allowed to erect a
menorah on the steps of the City-County Building in Pittsburgh for
the start of Hanukkah.
   Supreme Court Justice William J. Brennan Jr. on Friday vacated a
ruling made just hours before by a panel of the 3rd Circuit U.S.
Court of Appeals that would have prevented the display, court
spokeswoman Kathy Arberg said.
   The eight-day Jewish festival of lights began at sundown Friday.
   Brennan's action reinstated a preliminary injunction issued
Wednesday against the city by a federal judge, Arberg said.
   City officials had refused to allow the Jewish group Chabad to
set up an 18-foot menorah next to a Christmas tree. City officials
said they had not authorized the area outside the building to be
used as a public forum.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>U.S. Planning to Resume Loans to Iraq</NOTE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Bush administration plan to lift a
congressional ban on loans to Iraq is likely to antagonize
lawmakers critical of Iraq's human rights abuses and credit
problems.
   Officials say President Bush will exercise his right to lift the
ban, imposed by Congress several months ago, on grounds of U.S.
national interests. The officials, who spoke Friday on condition of
anonymity, said the move is expected within several weeks.
   U.S. oil companies and other businesses have exerted heavy
pressure on the administration to broaden trade ties with Iraq
since the 1988 end of its ruinous eight-year war with Iran.
   Congress voted to suspend $200 million in annual short-term
credits to Iraq by the Export-Import Bank, a U.S. government
institution that promotes the export of American goods. To head off
a presidential veto and respond to pressure from U.S. businesses,
Congress agreed to incorporate the executive branch's right to a
waiver.
   ``But there were many up here who didn't like it and wanted a
flat-out prohibition on Iraq,'' said a congressional source who
spoke on condition he not be named.
</TEXT>

</DOC>