<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0152EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania 8thLd-Writethru 2Takes 12-23 1157</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania, 8th Ld-Writethru, 2 Takes, a0414, a0867,1190</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT ^Romanians Overthrow Ceausescu; Hundreds Dead in Fierce Fighting</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with Saturday fighting, report political
prisoners freed. No pickup. ^LaserPhotos FRA3,4,12,14; NY11; TOK11</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MORT ROSENBLUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Army units joined outraged Romanians
in toppling President Nicolae Ceausescu on Friday, but fierce
battles raged a day later between popular forces and those loyal to
the Soviet bloc's last dictator.
   Hundreds of people were reported killed in the fighting.
   A provisional government, apparently with the military's full
backing, was in control in most places but still encountered fierce
resistance from pro-Ceausescu security forces in several cities,
Bucharest radio reported.
   The popular forces took control of the communications centers on
Friday and arrested key figures from the Ceausescu regime, but
there was no clear word on the fate of Ceausescu and his wife
Elena, formerly the second-in-command.
   The couple's son Nicu was among those held.
   Shortly after 8 a.m. Saturday, Bucharest radio said all
political detainees had been released.
   Earlier in the day, the chief of the dreaded Securitate secret
police, Gen. Iulian Vlad told the nation on Bucharest radio that
the Interior Ministry had rid itself of ``elements loyal to the
Ceaucescu clan.''
   He appealed to security troops _ who long terrorized the
population at Ceausescu's command _ to ``serve the highest cause,
namely the defense of the entire Romanian people's freedom.''
   However, fighting flared in the capital at dawn Saturday,
apparently between army units at television headquarters and
Ceausescu loyalists in surrounding apartment buildings.
   About 2:30 a.m. Saturday, Ceausescu loyalists had tried to seize
radio and television headquarters _ about two miles apart _ but
army troops repulsed the attacks.
   The facilities were take by popular forces Friday and were
broadcasting declarations from the country's newly declared
provisional government that included a vow to embrace democracy and
hold free elections next year.
   Heavy fighting was reported continuing Saturday in Brasov, the
country's second-largest city. It had also reportedly been intense
Friday night in the western city of Timisoara, where the revolt
began on Dec. 15.
   On Friday morning, Ceausescu fled his presidential palace as
hundreds of thousands of Romanians called for his death in
retaliation for the massacre of their countrymen in a military
crackdown unleashed a week ago in Timisoara.
   The Yugoslav news agency Tanjug said Ceausescu was hunted down
and captured, although it gave no details. There was no
confirmation of the capture in Romanian media, and the whereabouts
of the man who ruled Romania with an iron fist since 1965 were
unknown.
   The death toll in the uprising was believed to be in the
hundreds, in addition to the thousands of civilians killed since
the start of the unrest. Television broadcast an appeal to doctors
and medical students to go to city hospitals to help the injured.
   The tumult capped a historic year of change in the Soviet bloc
that elsewhere was relatively bloodless: Solidarity took power in
Poland, Hungary ousted its Communist hard-liners and opened its
borders, and old-guard regimes in East Germany, Czechoslovakia and
Bulgaria were thrown out in swift succession.
   Provisional leader Ion Iliescu appeared on Romanian TV along
with other members of a National Salvation Committee that the media
said was formed to run the country temporarily. Iliescu, an old
acquaintance of Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev, and former
Foreign Minister Corneliu Manescu said free elections would be
sought by April.
   ``In a few days we shall calm down, bury our dead and will be
consciously building new, free and democratic life,'' the Soviet
news agency Tass quoted Romanian poet Mirca Dinescu as saying.
   Besides free elections, the National Salvation Committee said it
was committed to a pluralistic society; continued membership in the
Warsaw Pact; the idea of a ``common European home'' _ an idea
espoused by Gorbachev; abolishment of all structures of the
Ceausescu dictatorship; and placement of the army and the security
apparatus under the control of the civil government.
   Romanian media, now pledging honest reporting, said Ceausescu
and his wife fled the palace by helicopter early Friday. The palace
was later was set ablaze.
   It also was reported they had fled the country. But Tanjug said
late Friday night that they had been captured, along with other
ranking members of the old guard. It was not known where they were.
   China on Saturday denied giving sanctuary to Ceausescu.
   Nicu Ceausescu was shown on TV with a bloody face, his arms held
by a civilian and a man in a uniform. He was then taken away by his
captors.
   When security forces attacked the radio and TV headquarters in
Bucharest during the night, occupants of the TV building ducked as
shots were fired toward the windows and the lights went out.
   Rebel soldiers inside returned fire, pinning down the security
forces, and repulsed the attack after about two hours.
   The TV station stayed on the air during the attack, with
reporter Victor Ionesco exhorting residents of Bucharest to come to
scene of the shooting. ``Come help us,'' he implored. ``We're
helping you.''
   People who had been chanting outside the TV building only
minutes before the shooting scattered briefly during the attack,
but they came back and cheered when tanks on side of the uprising
took up new positions around the building. Rebel troops also were
located on the building's roof.
   A crowd of about 3,000 people then took up a vigil through the
night outside the building, continuing their chants for liberty.
   Maria Elena Ionesco, the TV reporter's wife, said the attack at
the radio station also was put down. ``It's over. We've won. We've
won,'' she said.
   Maj. Gen. Stefan Gusa, the first deputy defense minister who
joined the uprising, said on Bucharest radio Saturday morning that
``the army and the people are in control of the situation, although
there are still scattered pockets of opposition in the country.''
   A source in Timisoara said pro-Ceausescu commandos dropped by
parachute had descended on the town and tanks were rolling into
downtown. Tanjug later reported the fighting had died down.
   In Brasov, official radio broadcasted an urgent appeal for rebel
reinforcements. Bucharest radio reported heavy fighting around the
central telephone exchange.
   The 24-year reign of the East bloc's harshest regime collapsed
in one breathtaking week of protests that began with a small rally
for a persecuted pastor in Timisoara and led to Friday's nationwide
uprising by millions.
   Only last month, Ceausescu was overwhelmingly reaffirmed as
supreme leader by a fiercely obedient Communist Party conference
that paid homage to his personality cult. On Thursday, during a
speech in central Bucharest, he was shouted down by jeering
demonstrators.
   After Ceausescu fled Bucharest Friday morning, hundreds of
thousands of jubilant Romanians rallied in the capital for hours,
even as there were reports of fighting between rebel troops and
pro-Ceausescu forces. About 2,000 pro-Ceausescu forces then
attacked the city later Friday, Romanian TV reported.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>