<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0090 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1750EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-DrugWar-Individuals 1stAdd-SUB a0524 12-25 0649</FIRST>
<SECOND>^AM-Drug War-Individuals, 1st Add-SUB, a0524,630</SECOND>
<HEAD>EDs: FIXES spelling of Spingarn High School in 3rd graf bgng, `_Frank
Parks'</HEAD>
<HEAD>WASHN: and trained.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   _The Rev. C. Jay Matthews and the Rev. Tony Minor, who helped
begin the ``Wings of Hope'' program in Cleveland, a national
church-based anti-drug program that was started earlier this year
in Atlanta by the Rev. Joseph Lowery, president of the Southern
Christian Leadership Conference. The program establishes drug
prevention committees, contacts leaders of public housing units to
recommend ``at-risk'' families for adoption, for care and support
and for training in parental skills, basic needs and spiritual
guidance. Churches are taught community organizing and drug
prevention strategies. Matthews and Minor lead a monthly rally and
``pray-in'' on corners where crack cocaine is sold.
   _Jeffrey Miller, principal of W.R. Thomas Junior High School in
Miami, who implemented an aggressive drug education program and
drug policies for the school once labeled ``Cocaine Alley'' by a
local newspaper. ``Every student knows we have a tough policy, and
they know what the rules are,'' said Miller, whose school has
experienced a 50 percent drop in the number of disruptive incidents
and no drug-related cases.
   _Frank Parks, athletic director of Spingarn High School in
Washington, D.C., which was certified ``drug-free'' by the U.S.
Department of Education last May, just a few years after
``marijuana and PCP were all over the building, and there was a
number of drug dealers in here,'' Parks said. Starting with
athletes ``because one athlete can influence 25 other kids,'' he
enlisted students in his efforts to create a peer counseling group
called SAND, Student Activities, Not Drugs.
   _Erma Scales, chairman of the Acres Homes War on Drugs Committee
in Houston. The community had been overrun with drugs, and Scales
said, ``We decided to stop the madness. We overcame in our
community.'' The neighbors wrote down license plate numbers of
drivers buying drugs, told police of alleged drug dealers, and tore
down abandoned buildings that were used as crack houses. Using
local business donations, the committee also has created an
anti-drug program including education, treatment, neighborhood
patrols and youth activities.
   _Margaret Toomey, manager of the Homes of Oakridge in Des
Moines, Iowa, which a year ago were surrounded by drug dealers. She
organized tenants through community get-togethers and meetings with
police and civic leaders, and she has evicted about 60 families
since 1988 because of drug problems. An ``Up with hope, Down with
Dope'' march attracted more than 1,000 participants, and the
residents have created project HOPE, the Homes of Oakridge
Prevention Effort, to educate young people about the dangers of
drug use and gang behavior. The program also has expanded adult
programs focusing on educational, vocational and career choices.
Toomey calls on residents to ``Stand up and be counted. Do it
cautiously, do it carefully, but do it,'' he urges.
   _Ruth Varnado and Queen Hyler, organizers of Milwaukee's Stop
the Violence Movement, who acted after a 9-year-old boy was killed
while playing in his back yard. With police cooperation, Milwaukee
citizens last July 9 took to the streets to confront the drug
dealers and express their outrage. The movement encourages
residents to report license plate numbers to police and it has
worked to remove drug paraphernalia from local stores. Church
visits to raise neighborhood consciousness often trigger a flood of
calls to the police.
   _Jean Veldwyk and Norm Chamberlain, leaders of the South Seattle
Crime Prevention Council in Seattle, Wash., who were shocked when
crack cocaine invaded their city several years ago. ``We discovered
the community could not simply sit on its hands and expect the
police to do everything,'' Veldwyk said. The council helps
neighborhoods form their own crime prevention programs, runs a
hotline for reports of drug dealing, gang activity and abandoned
cars, directs a graffiti cleanup program, conducts community
support activities, meets with legislators and works with police to
target drug ``hot spots.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>