<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0263 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1031EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-WallStreet10am     12-20 0300</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Wall Street 10am,0317</SECOND>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Stock prices rose slightly today, registering no
strong reaction to the U.S. military action in Panama.
   The Dow Jones average of 30 industrials edged up 4.26 to
2,699.87 in the first half hour of trading.
   Gainers outnumbered losers by about 3 to 2 in nationwide trading
of New York Stock Exchange-listed issues, with 472 up, 321 down and
502 unchanged.
   Volume on the Big Board came to 23.59 million shares as of 10
a.m. on Wall Street.
   Analysts said investors were cautiously watching the situation
in Panama, but apparently not viewing it as any cause to make big
changes in their strategies.
   They noted that the prospective economic effects of the
confrontation, if any, remained unclear.
   At the same time, brokers said, stock traders appeared to draw
some encouragement from an upward revision in the latest government
figures on economic growth.
   The Commerce Department said the gross national product grew at
a 3.0 percent annual rate, after adjustment for inflation, in the
third quarter of the year, up from a previous estimate of 2.7
percent.
   Among actively traded blue chips, General Electric rose \ to 63;
International Business Machines gained [ to 94~; American Telephone
&amp; Telegraph climbed ] to 45~, and McDonald's was unchanged at 33{.
   The NYSE's composite index of all its listed common stocks added
.41 to 189.81. At the American Stock Exchange, the market value
index was up .36 at 368.31.
   On Tuesday the Dow Jones industrial average slipped 1.92 to
2,695.61, extending its loss over the past four sessions to 65.48
points.
   Declining issues outnumbered advances by about 2 to 1 on the
NYSE, with 514 up, 1,016 down and 461 unchanged.
   Big Board volume totaled 186.06 million shares, against 184.79
million in the previous session.
</TEXT>

</DOC>