<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0318EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-SteamLocomotive     12-20 0525</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Steam Locomotive,0541</SECOND>
<HEAD>Exported No More, Steam Locomotives Now Arrive from China</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Steam locomotives built in the Philadelphia
area were exported to railroads around the world years ago. Now,
two companies are importing from China 83-ton locomotives based on
a 1918 American design.
   Two brand-new steam engines were unloaded from a freighter
Sunday at the Beckett Street Terminal in Camden, N.J., for the Knox
&amp; Kane Railroad in northwestern Pennsylvania and the Valley
Railroad in Essex, Conn.
   New steam locomotives haven't been seen in this port since the
1950s, when the old Baldwin Locomotive Works went out of business.
   It's been decades since efficient diesel locomotives made steam
power obsolete on U.S. railroads, but steam engines have survived
on short lines hauling tourists.
   Thousands of people visiting scenic and historic sites line up
each year to ride on old-time trains, but even something as
heavy-duty as a locomotive eventually wears out.
   ``The repairs we found necessary on our existing locomotives got
the railroads thinking about new locomotives,'' said J. David
Conrad of the Valley Railroad, as he waited for the new steam
engine at the marine terminal.
   The last place in the world that still makes steam engines is
the Tangshan Locomotive &amp; Rolling Stock Works, about 140 miles east
of Beijing. The Chinese still rely on steam locomotives because of
their sturdiness, and because China has plenty of manpower and coal
required by the old locomotives.
   Conrad went to the Chinese in 1986 to arrange a sale and soon
afterward, the Knox &amp; Kane followed suit.
   Sloan Cornell, the Knox &amp; Kane general manager, said the new
engine would haul tourists through part of the Allegheny National
Forest.
   The main attraction of the Knox &amp; Kane is the 300-foot-high,
2,053-foot-long Kinzua Bridge, the highest in the world when it was
built. About 17,000 people rode the Knox &amp; Kane in 1988.
   The Valley Railroad carries about 130,000 passengers a year on
its six-mile trip along the west shore of the Connecticut River
from Essex to Chester, Conn.
   Valley Railroad President Lynn Parrott said the $300,000 price
for the new locomotive was worth it.
   A delegation from Valley visited three locomotive factories in
China and decided on the Class SY from Tangshan (SY stands for
Shang You, Chinese characters meaning ``Aiming High,'' according to
Valley).
   Similar engines built in the United States for export to Japan
early this century were nicknamed ``Mikados.''
   Conrad said Valley preferred the smaller model over a larger
locomotive from a plant in Datong. He and his assistants also
preferred Tangshan's construction methods and the willingness of
the Tangshan engineering staff to American boiler codes and
railroad guidelines.
   When the new Chinese locomotive finally arrives in Connecticut,
Ms. Parrott said it will be their primary engine. She doubted that
passengers would mind the locomotive was not an antique.
   ``The majority of people who come here just like to ride behind
a steam engine,'' she said. ``Besides, the engine being new and
coming from China may arouse some curiosity.''
   After clearing customs, the locomotives are to be towed or
hauled on flatcars by Conrail to their new owners.
</TEXT>

</DOC>