<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0170 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1612EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel 1stLd-Writethru a0666 12-20 0800</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0666,0817</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Army's Toughest Measures Failed to Reduce Violence</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 7th, `Forty-three Israelis...,' to UPDATE
with 14 Palestinians wounded.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NICOLAS B. TATRO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TEL AVIV, Israel (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The army's tough measures of house
demolitions, deportations and school closures have failed to reduce
protests by Palestinians and at times have inflamed the two-year
uprising, according to a study published Wednesday.
   The study, part of an annual assessment of Middle East military
developments by Tel Aviv University's Jaffee Center for Strategic
Studies, challenged often-stated army claims that strong reprisals
served as a deterrent to unrest.
   Also on Wednesday, a military court sentenced three Palestinians
to life in prison for an Oct. 30, 1988, firebomb attack on an
Israeli bus that killed a mother and her three children as well as
a soldier who tried to rescue them. Soldiers tried to attack the
three defendants after the verdict and turned on reporters as they
left the court.
   Israel radio reported a Palestinian prisoner in the custody of
the Shin Bet secret service was found dead Tuesday night in his
cell. Arab reporters identified him as Khaled Kamel Al-Sheikh Ali,
27, of Gaza City, and said he was taken for questioning Dec. 7.
   As a new step against the uprising, the army spokesman's office
said the army would begin confiscating property of Palestinian
parents who failed to cover the bail and fines of their children.
   In Bethlehem in the occupied West Bank, a leaflet signed by the
PLO-backed uprising leadership called for a general strike on Dec.
24 to mourn the deaths of the 631 Palestinians killed by Israeli
soldiers and civilians in the revolt.
   Forty-three Israelis also have been slain, and 161 other
Palestinians have been killed by fellow Arabs as alleged
collaborators with Israel.
   On Wednesday, 14 Palestinians were shot and wounded in scattered
stone-throwing clashes with Israeli soldiers in the occupied Gaza
Strip, Arab hospital officials said.
   Monsignor Michel Sabbah, the Roman Catholic patriarch, called
for peace in the Holy Land in his traditional Christmas message:
   ``Peace on Earth is possible only when all people and all states
concerned recognize the legitimate rights of all individuals and
nations to freedom and self-determination.''
   The study on the uprising in the Jaffee Center's annual Middle
East Military Balance was based on army figures and conducted by
Aryeh Shalev, a retired army brigadier general who served as
military governor of the West Bank in 1976-78.
   ``What I discovered is there was no reduction in the number of
incidents,'' Shalev told a news conference. ``It means to my mind
that (such measures) didn't have a serious effect on the strength
of the intefadeh,'' uprising in Arabic.
   Since the uprising began in December 1987, army figures show 244
houses have been destroyed and 116 sealed. But Shalev said they led
to no decrease in violence as claimed by army commanders.
   ``We found no correlation whatsoever between the number of
houses demolisehd and the number of violent incidents recorded, or
the number of Israeli casualties, or even the number of petrol
bombs thrown, in the following month,'' Shalev wrote.
   In fact, his study showed, the number of incidents increased
after the heaviest periods of house demolitions. For example, 24
houses were destroyed in November 1988, and incidents of stone
throwing, barricade building and rioting rose by 1,195, or about 74
percent, to 2,790 in the following month.
   Deportation of Palestinian activists has been considered the
most severe measure against the uprising, but Shalev said it proved
impotent as a deterrent and actually inflamed the situation.
   ``There is a clear correlation between the number of residents
deported ... and an ensuing increase in the number of violent
incidents and Israeli casualties,'' he said.
   In April 1988, 16 Palestinians were deported, the largest number
in a single month, but the number of violent incidents rose by 210,
he said, adding there was a similar rise after 13 deportations in
January 1989.
   In all, 60 Palestinians were deported in the past two years.
   Shalev said closing schools initially appeared to have a
restraining effect on violence in early 1988. But he said
subsequent closures failed to have an effect and by early 1989
seemed to accelerate incidents.
   Universities have been closed since the start of the uprising.
Elementary, junior and high schools were closed in the West Bank
for eights months in 1988 and throughout the first half of 1989.
   ``I don't think it is possible to stop the intefadeh (uprising)
by using these or other means,'' Shalev told a news conference
here, adding the only solution was a negotiated political
settlement.
   Shalev suggested mass deportations and demolitions might reduce
violence but said such practice would not be possible because of
legal and moral restaints.
</TEXT>

</DOC>