<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1309EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-Panama-Military 5thLd-Writethru a0601-a0606-a0529 12-21
1036</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Military, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0601-a0606-a0529,980</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shooting Still Reported in Panama City</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Combines pvs files; CORRECTS rank and spelling of Scheafer's
name in 2nd graf; edits and cuts throughout</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. forces swept into Panama City today on
the second day of a massive military strike, encountering ``some
shooting'' by troops loyal to Manuel Antonio Noriega and searching
for Americans being held against their will, the Pentagon said.
   Rear Adm. Ted Scheafer told reporters ``organized resistance had
pretty much been taken care of.'' He acknowledged sporadic
fighting, saying ``people on the tops of buildings are the kind of
thing I'm talking about.''
   Defense Department spokesman Pete Williams said there had been
``some sightings'' reported of Noriega, but he remained at large
despite a massive military operation involving more than 20,000
U.S. forces.
   Officials said they believed the dictator remained in Panama,
despite reports that placed him in three different countries _
Colombia, Mexico and the Dominican Republic.
   Army Lt. Gen. Tom Kelly said there was a possibility Noriega and
some loyal troops had sought refuge in the jungles, and said ``when
it comes time we'll do what's necessary'' to find him.
   Williams said the latest U.S. casualty count stood at 19 killed
in action, 117 wounded and one missing. He said the first American
dead were being flown back to Dover Air Force Base in Delaware
later in the day.
   Officials at military hospitals in San Antonio, Texas, said they
were treating about 190 wounded troops evacuated from Panama, a
higher count than that reported at the Pentagon.
   Williams said American troops had taken roughly 1,500 prisoners
in the first 36 hours of armed combat.
   Williams said there were three reports of Americans being held
against their will, and added, ``We take them all seriously.'' He
said they included a group of Smithsonian Institution scientists
and John Myerson, a CBS News television producer.
   Officials said American troops evacuated 29 Americans and 35
foreign nationals, mostly Panamanians, from the Marriott Hotel in
Panama City late Wednesday night.
   Williams said U.S. troops had discovered a large cache of
documents in a military headquarters building, and they would be
studied for possible use in any trial against Noriega, who is under
indictment in the United States on drug charges.
   The spokesman put the casualty count for Panamanian Defense
Forces as 59 killed, 66 wounded and more than 1,500 taken prisoner.
   Kelly, director of operations for the Joint Chiefs of Staff,
outlined three goals for the day's military operation: continued
support for the operations of the new government, to secure Panama
City and to ``continue to track Mr. Noriega in an effort to capture
him.''
   He said U.S. forces had secured the legislative building, and he
raised the possibility that Guillermo Endara, the new U.S.-backed
president, would go there during the day.
   The formal briefing came several hours after Defense Secretary
Dick Cheney called the deaths of American servicemen ``a terrible
tragedy,'' but said the number of casualties was low given the
complexity of the operation.
   As for Noriega, who now as a $1 million U.S. bounty on his head,
Cheney said, ``We're getting phone calls coming in from Panamanians
who have suspicions, thoughts or ideas'' about where Noriega may be
hiding.
   ``We will chase down the individual reports, but we do not know
where he is,'' said Gen. Colin Powell, chairman of the Joint Chiefs
of Staff.
   In television interviews, Powell and Cheney said it was unclear
how many Americans were being detained or held hostage in Panama.
   ``You can be sure, however, that this is a primary concern for
us today,'' Powell said on ABC-TV's ``Good Morning America.'' ``We
will do everything we can to determine who is unaccounted for and
do everything we can to locate those individuals.''
   Reinforcements were sent in late Wednesday from Fort Ord,
Calif., and Fort Bragg, N.C., to bolster the U.S. troops
participating in ``Operation Just Cause'' to about 24,000 men.
   Cheney said he hoped some of the troops would be called home by
Christmas, but Powell and other Pentagon officials said it was
unclear when the United States would be withdraw all of the troops
sent in to bolster those already stationed at the Panama Canal.
   The U.S. attack force planned to make sure Panama City's streets
were clear of Noriega loyalists today, Kelly said, adding that most
Panamanian units had dispersed and may have fled into the jungle.
   ``There is every chance that we will go off after them,'' he
added.
   Kelly and Sheafer, also on the staff of the Joint Chiefs, said
Wednesday there were difficult tasks ahead, even though the
Panamanian Defense Forces were largely subdued.
   ``We went after them first. We have reduced them,'' Kelly said.
``That's a problem we're having in a lot of areas in that much of
the PDF is fleeing in the face of the U.S. military units.''
   The Americans' next priority was to ferret out 18 so-called
Dignity Battalions, armed gangs primarily roaming the streets of
Panama City, a metropolis of about 1 million people, officials said.
   The battalions ``vary in size from as few as a couple of dozen
people to about 250,'' said Sheafer. ``They are throughout many
parts of Panama City at this time.''
   The move into the city is designed in part to protect Americans
and others, Kelly said.
   ``Urban operations are possibly the most difficult kind,'' he
said. ``To sweep through, it's going to take a lot of people.''
   Kelly said the Americans, some of whom had been up for three
days traveling and fighting, were exhausted.
   About 7,000 troops, including Army Rangers, Marines,
paratroopers from the 82nd Airborne Division, special units and
military police, were flown into Panama Tuesday evening for the 1
a.m. pre-dawn start-up on Wednesday.
   They joined about 13,000 U.S. troops stationed in Panama with
the primary mission of protecting the Panama Canal. The canal was
open Wednesday with no threat from the Panamanians, Kelly said.
   U.S. troops relied on heavy equipment in their efforts to rout
the PDF. Four light tanks, called Sheridans, were brought to Panama
earlier, Kelly said. The military also used six Apache helicopters
and some Air Force AC-130 gunships.
</TEXT>

</DOC>