<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0328EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-ShockTherapy     12-22 0501</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Shock Therapy,500</SECOND>
<HEAD>Study Supports Limited Use of Electroshock for Mental Patients</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Even though electroshock therapy may have had
a bad reputation in the past, the treatment is safe, effective and
important for a small percentage of mental patients, according to a
new study by the American Psychiatric Association.
   ``Despite its reputation in some circles, ECT (electroconvulsive
therapy, or electroshock) is not justified to be known as an unsafe
procedure,'' Dr. Richard Weiner, chairman of an APA committee that
studied the therapy, said at a news conference on Thursday.
   He said that use of ECT is controversial because ``it has had a
bad reputation in the press and it has had some abuses,'' but in
the hands of competent doctors electroshock is safe and effective.
   About 30,000 mental patients receive electroshock therapy
annually, said Weiner. Eighty percent of these patients suffer from
a profound, major depression that has not responded to drugs and he
said electroshock often represents the only way to put the illness
into a remission that would allow the use of other therapies.
   ``I think in the elderly it is considered the safest treatment
available, particularly for depression,'' Weiner said.
   Dr. Herbert Pardes, president of APA and a former director of
the National Institute of Mental Health, called ECT ``a safe and
very effective treatment for certain severe mental illnesses.''
   ``ECT's effectiveness in rescuing severely ill patients ... is
well accepted by psychiatrists, by the rest of the medical
community and by thousands of patients who are better because of
it,'' Pardes said.
   But, he noted, the therapy ``is not a cure and it does have some
adverse effects, such as memory loss in some patients.''
   Weiner, an associate professor of psychiatry at Duke University
Medical Center in Durham, N.C., directed an APA task-force study of
the use of ECT. The committee report released Thursday proposes
guidelines for the use of electroshock and details the type of
training health care workers need to receive before administering
it.
   Electroshock, in one form or another, has been used to treat the
mentally ill for more than 50 years. Its popularity with
psychiatrists has risen and fallen, but is enjoying renewed use.
   The therapy consists of using electrodes to send small charges
of electricity through select portions of the brain. The shocks
cause short seizures, similar to epileptic convulsions, that, for
reasons not understood, have a beneficial effect on some patients.
   In a typical course of treatment, patients receive six to 12
treatments at the rate of three a week. If the therapy puts the
illness into remission, doctors then use other treatment, such as
drugs, in an attempt to gain a cure.
   Despite its renewed use, Weiner said electroshock will continue
to be used for only 1 percent to 2 percent of all mental patients.
   ``For the majority of patients with significant depression,
there is an effective drug,'' he said. ``Only a very small
percentage have to go to ECT.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>