<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0145 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1726EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Czechoslovakia 1stLd-Writethru   12-29 1024</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Czechoslovakia, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0605,1053</SECOND>
<HEAD>Vaclav Havel, Once Jailed Dissident, Named President</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS four grafs after 21st `Havel's appearance...' to UPDATE
with later rally; picks up 22nd, `Czechoslovakia's president...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PRA1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SYDNEY RUBIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vaclav Havel, the defiant
playwright who rode a gentle revolt from a prison cell to the halls
of Parliament, assumed the presidency Friday in an emotional climax
to an electrifying year.
   The masses who chanted ``Havel to the castle!'' during the angry
rallies of November thrilled to the sight of the dissident actually
in Hradcany Castle, taking the oath beneath the nation's red, white
and blue flag. Cannons boomed and a military band played the
national anthem.
   ``I promise I won't betray your trust. I will take the country
to free elections and that's a task for us all,'' the 53-year-old
president told the adoring crowds from the balcony of the towering
medieval castle.
   Havel, whose plays and essays in defense of civil liberty earned
him jail terms totaling five years, languished in a cell eight
months ago. On Friday, a special session of Parliament elected him
Czechoslovakia's ninth president.
   The election by 323 deputies, most of whom are Communists, was a
historic victory for the pro-democracy movement that in 41 days has
broken the party's stranglehold on power.
   Among his first acts of office, Havel named as chief of staff
Josef Lzicar, the attorney who defended him and other prominent
dissidents.
   Havel also is planning an amnesty program, the details of which
are to be announced New Year's Day, the state news agency CTK
reported.
   Havel's election is part of a sweeping series of accords between
the opposition and the Communists that are to lead to free
elections next year.
   It came one day after Alexander Dubcek, the ousted Communist
Party chief who led the ``Prague Spring'' reforms that were crushed
in 1968, was named head of Parliament in another stunning rebuke to
the repression of the past.
   It also comes two days after the Bulgarian government agreed to
talks with the opposition, seven days after the government was
overthrown in Romania, seven weeks after the Berlin Wall was opened
by East Germany, five months after a Solidarity activist became
prime minister of Poland, seven months after Hungary opened its
borders to the West, and eight months after the Soviet Union held
its first competitive elections in 70 years.
   During his somber inauguration, Communist Prime Minister Marian
Calfa praised him as ``a man who is faithful to his beliefs despite
persecution.''
   ``He never accepted offers from his friends or recommendations
by his enemies to emigrate where the conditions of his life would
have been more comfortable,'' Calfa said in a nominating speech.
   Havel walked the aisle with Dubcek as Communist deputies
applauded decorously, camera bulbs flashed and the band played a
stirring fanfare.
   The playwright signed the oath of office, which was amended just
Thursday to delete a pledge of allegiance to socialism.
   Tears filled the eyes of a few opposition members and old
friends of Havel who watched the 20-minute ceremony from the back
of the hall.
   Twenty cannon salvos fired from the castle on the Plain of Letna
boomed over central Prague below.
   Havel, whose plays have been banned in Czechoslovakia since
1968, agreed to take the presidency for six months leading to free
elections in mid-1990.
   ``This must happen in a decent and peaceful way so that the
clean face of our revolution is not sullied. It is a task for us
all,'' he told the crowd from the castle balcony after taking the
oath of office.
   ``Long live Havel!'' they chanted as he and, Olga, his wife of
30 years, left the balcony to walk across the courtyard to St.
Vitus Cathedral for a special Mass of thanksgiving.
   Then, Havel became the first president since the Communists took
power in 1948 to attend the Roman Catholic Mass, traditionally part
of the inaugural ceremony.
   Havel's appearance at the nationally televised Mass was
significant for the country's 9 million Catholics, who suffered
repression for their faith under the Communists.
   After the brief Mass, the towering vaults of the cathedral
filled with the voices of the Prague Philharmonic Choir singing
Dvorak's ``Te Deum.''
   After dark, Havel briefly joined several thousand people waiting
in the cold on Prague's Old Town Square. The blonde, mustachioed
president wore a dark blue overcoat, blue suit and striped tie
rather than his usual cardigan and corduroy slacks.
   He made no speech, but smiled and waved from the castle balcony
to those below on the baroque square.
   Strangers grabbed each other and danced, while others broke out
in spontaneous song. Folk groups played and danced on the stage and
in small groups around a giant Christmas tree. Among the Czech
flags waving on the square was one with 12 gold stars on a blue
field of the European Community.
   Czechoslovakia's president traditionally has little real power
but people are looking to Havel to restore stability and inspire
confidence in Western investors.
   President Bush was among foreign leaders sending congratulations
to Havel. He pledged U.S. support for democracy in Czechoslovakia
and the White House said his election ``marks a fitting end to a
year of astonishing change in Eastern Europe.''
   In Warsaw, Poland, Solidarity leader Lech Walesa welcomed ``with
great joy'' Havel's election and wished him strength in his new
responsibilities.
   Immediately after Havel's election, students declared an end to
their strike that began in mid-November.
   It was the students who sparked the revolution when their
peaceful march on Nov. 17 was brutally crushed by police. The
violence prompted mass protests, forcing the Communists to
negotiate their own demise over the next several weeks with the
democratic opposition group Civic Forum, led by Havel.
   Talks that lasted until Dec. 23 between Communists, opposition
leaders and other political forces led to the creation of a new
reform government that included several former dissidents.
Hard-line President Gustav Husak, who took over after the Soviet
invasion, quit Dec. 10.
   Havel's first foreign visit, announced Friday, will be to East
and West Germany on Jan. 2, the state news agency reported.
</TEXT>

</DOC>