<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0189 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1126EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f BC-Peru-PrivateArmy Adv02   12-28 0661</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Peru-Private Army, Adv 02,0685</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv02</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Tuesday Jan. 2</HEAD>
<HEAD>Private Army Guards Legitimate Business in Rebel-Controlled Jungle</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOSE GONZALES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PALMA DEL ESPINO, Peru (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In a remote jungle region infested
with drug smugglers and radical guerrillas, Peruvian entrepreneurs
have enlisted a private army to protect their struggling palm oil
business.
   About 1,200 workers at one of the wrld's largest palm oil
plantations go about their tasks protected by a hundred men dressed
in jungle fatigues and armed with automatic rifles.
   The guards, most of them ex-Peruvian marines, are deployed to
repel guerrilla attacks on the Palma del Espino complex, a model
project that Peru hopes will help solve its shortage of vegetable
oils.
   The private fighting force is an example of the security that
more and more legitimate businesses in this impoverished South
American nation have been forced to organize to protect themselves
from rebel sabotage.
   Located near the town of Uchiza in Peru's Upper Huallaga valley,
245 miles northeast of Lima, Palma del Espino and its 16,000 acres
of African palm trees form an oasis in a region under the domain of
cocaine traffickers and fanatical Maoist insurgents who call
themselves the Shining Path.
   The entire complex is ringed by a 6-foot-high fence and its
managers come and go by plane to avoid ambushes.
   Begun in 1979, the project is intended to help eliminate Peru's
imports of 80,000 metric tons of vegetable oils each year, which
cost more than $30 million and drain the country's foreign-exchange
reserves.
   When the first trees were planted in 1982, the company's major
concern was draining swamps, said Ruperto Raygada, the plant's
chief of operations.
   But today the illegal coca fields that stretch up and down the
150-mile-long valley have reached the plantation's doorsteps, and
rebels who prowl the surrounding jungle pose a serious threat.
   The Shining Path guerrillas have been fighting Peru's government
since 1980. They expanded into the valley from Ayacucho, their
stronghold in Peru's Andean mountains.
   The Upper Huallaga valley generates about 70 percent of the
world coca-leaf supply, the raw material for cocaine. Police say
the jungle surrounding the plantation contains 13 drug trafficking
organizations and nearly a thousand guerrilla fighters.
   Government officials say the rebels ``tax'' coca growers and
smugglers for permission to operate in the area. In return the
guerrillas provide protection from police.
   The $56 million project is proceeding and expanding despite
terrorist threats. The complex includes a processing plant, a
barracks for the workers and 18 technicians, offices and security
equipment.
   Squadrons of workers toiling by hand cultivate the African palm,
which produces 20 times more vegetable oil than any other plant.
They lug it to the processing plant using 250 mules. The result is
a red, dense liquid transformed into vegetable shortening, oil and
cosmetics ingredients.
   Palma del Espino, owned by a Peruvian industrial group, expects
to produce 20,600 tons of palm oil in 1989, more than twice what it
produced in 1987, its first year of production.
   The biggest threat, however, appears to be the insurgents who
ring the plant's perimeters. Besides their threat of attack, they
demand payment of protection money from the truckers who take the
oil to the cities.
   Some trucks have been turned back at guerrilla blockades,
forcing the plantation to store the oil in big tanks that can
accomodate 4,000 tons. The plantation recently began running out of
room, so workers gouged pits in the ground and lined them with
plastic sheets to store the excess.
   Last year the rebels dynamited nine bridges along the 70-mile
stretch of road that connects the plantation with Tingo Maria, the
largest town in the area.
   Since 1984, when the plantation was attacked for the first time,
the rebels have burned 14 trucks. The last major attack occurred in
March 1988.
   ``When they attacked us the first time, we only had one guard,''
Raygada said. ``Now we have constant patrols.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End adv for Tuesday Jan. 2</NOTE>

</DOC>