<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 2056EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Noriega-Analysis 2ndLd-Writethru a0811 12-24 0804</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Noriega-Analysis, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0811,790</SECOND>
<HEAD>Built-in Risks Accompany Policy Focusing on Noriega</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 21st graf, `Noriega's surrender...' to delete reference
to surrender; picks up 22nd graf pvs, `Now that...</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WALTER R. MEARS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Manuel Antonio Noriega is the perfect villain
_ but there are drawbacks in a policy heavily hinged on the capture
of one man, whatever his crimes.
   One nagging administration problem was resolved on Christmas Eve
when Noriega turned himself in to Vatican diplomats in Panama City,
seeking asylum.
   In power and in hiding, the Panamanian strongman had been
taunting the United States for nearly three years.
   That dilemma was resolved Sunday night, after a five-day U.S.
manhunt in Panama, complete with a million dollar bounty.
   The U.S. commander in Panama, then the White House announced
that Noriega had turned up and turned himself in, not to U.S.
forces but to envoys of the Roman Catholic church.
   The White House said ``the demise of General Noriega'' was a
signal that the forces of democracy and freedom in Panama were on
the rise.
   Noriega apologists are certain to note that he was not captured
and did not surrender to the American troops sent to Panama.
They'll call it sanctuary, not surrender.
   It also leaves open the question of whether Noriega ever will
stand trial on U.S. drug indictments.
   But those are technicalities; the administration already had
indicated a willingness to spare him prosecution if he would yield
power and get out of Panama.
   And it hardly seems likely that a man like Noriega would have
surrendered himself even to the sanctuary of the church had his
position not become impotent and impossible.
   Noriega had slipped away when the U.S. intervened early last
Wednesday and had eluded American forces for five days as the most
wanted of men.
   The plot in the Panama story has taken bizarre turns before, and
the crafty, elusive target of a manhunt ordered by the White House
could have gained a sort of a perverse popularity among some Latin
Americans had he remained at large, evading the Yankees.
   The United States posted a $1 million bounty for information
leading to his arrest. President Bush said he wouldn't be satisfied
until Noriega was brought to justice.
   Noriega's capture was a major objective from the moment the
American troops moved in at 1 a.m. last Wednesday.
   ``His picture will be in every post office in town,'' Bush said
Thursday. ``That's the way it works. He is a fugitive drug dealer
and we want to see him brought to justice.''
   Noriega's pockmarked face, brandished machete and defiance of
his own countrymen when they voted for his opponents all add to the
image of the prototype dictator. U.S. officials say there is
evidence he meant to attack unarmed American civilians, that he was
involved in voodoo or Satanism, that he admired Adolf Hitler, that
he plotted a terrorist takeover of the Panama Canal.
   Overall, hardly a sympathetic figure.
   But there was a risk in a superpower policy centered on one man,
even a man such as Noriega.
   The White House bounty had made him a million-dollar man.
American troops by the thousands couldn't take him, although the
likelihood is that unless they had been closing in, Noriega would
not have turned in his hand.
   One man against all that might was one man who could become a
Latin legend, as outlaws sometimes do.
   Noriega's decision to seek refuge with Vatican authorities
should ease the crisis in Panama; he and his henchmen prolonged the
agony with sniping, raids, looting, urban guerrilla warfare. Had he
escaped to sanctuary with his Nicaraguan allies, it could have
pointed to a war of words, even raids, against the new government
in Panama.
   Now that danger has eased.
   Stripped of power and confined to an embassy sanctuary, Noriega
should fade to insignificance.
   In the first Pentagon briefing on the Panama operation, Gen.
Colin Powell, chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, said Noriega
had been decapitated as the leader of Panama. ``Yesterday's maximum
leader is today's fugitive,'' Secretary of State James A. Baker III
said later.
   Bush said Thursday that Noriega ``controls no forces, and he's
out.''
   If all of that is so, and Noriega is powerless, his arrest would
seem a side issue, one that could wait.
   The capture of that one, elusive fugitive had remained a major,
declared objective in the biggest military operation since the
United States withdrew from South Vietnam.
   He wasn't captured by the Americans who sought him, but he is no
longer at large. And that is a major break for the Bush
administration.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Walter R. Mears, vice president and columnist
for The Associated Press, has reported on Washington and national
politics for more than 25 years.
</TEXT>

</DOC>