<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0256EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-S&amp;LLosses     12-22 0684</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-S&amp;L Losses,680</SECOND>
<HEAD>Analysts Say Bush Should Speed Bailout</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVE SKIDMORE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation's thrift institutions will continue
to suffer heavy losses unless the Bush administration speeds up its
savings and loan bailout, private analysts contend.
   The country's 2,903 S&amp;Ls, including 256 under government
control, lost $3.8 billion in the July-September period, down only
slightly from a record $4.1 billion in the second quarter, the
Office of Thrift Supervision said Thursday.
   For the first nine months of 1989, industry red ink totaled
$11.5 billion, on track to top the $13.4 billion loss for all of
1988, a post-Depression record.
   About two-thirds of third quarter loss, $2.6 billion, came in
institutions already under government management and earmarked for
liquidation or sale. All but $275 million of the remaining $1.2
billion loss occurred at 223 institutions targeted for government
takeover but still under private management.
   ``I just don't really see any hope of turning around the overall
profit numbers ... until we get these insolvent institutions out of
the market,'' said economist Catherine England of the Cato
Institute, a conservative research organization.
   About half of the red ink at government-controlled thrifts, $1.3
billion, was from non-operating losses, mostly from recognizing
sour loans that had long ago gone bad. But, the other half was from
current operations.
   ``The faster we get the ... depositors paid off and those
institutions closed, the lower the ultimate cost of the cleanup is
going to be and the sooner we'll be able to turn around the
marginal and healthy thrifts,'' Ms. England said.
   Only about 35 failed S&amp;Ls have been dealt with since the Aug. 9
enactment of President Bush's rescue plan. The others are open and
continue to lose money.
   Economist Edward Kane of Ohio State University said managers at
weak, but still open, institutions have every incentive to take big
risks in hopes of staving off closure.
   ``When you get desperate people doing desperate things, on
average they tend to lose money,'' he said.
   The S&amp;L bailout law provided $50 billion through 1991 to close
or rescue failed thrifts, but many analysts say mounting industry
losses show that won't be enough.
   ``We still have as much as $20 billion in losses out there that
haven't come to the surface,'' said Bert Ely, a financial
institutions analyst in Alexandria, Va. ``It's like a water
torture. It's going to continue quarter after quarter after
quarter.''
   Ely estimated that third quarter losses would have been about
$1.6 billion greater if not for what amounts to a continuing
government subsidy to 220 institutions rescued in 1988.
   Also, as part of the Bush plan, the government poured $8.5
billion into thrifts under its control during the last half of the
third quarter, paying off high-cost deposits. Although that reduced
costs at those institutions, Ely said it probably did little to
blunt total industry losses.
   Thrift office economist James Freund attributed losses at S&amp;Ls
outside government control to restructuring taking place in
response to stricter capital requirements that took effect Dec. 7.
   Many institutions must shrink to meet the standards and when
they sell assets, they often are forced to recognized embedded
losses, he said.
   Non-operating losses at S&amp;Ls outside government control were
$1.9 billion, up from $1.4 billion in the previous quarter.
   Meanwhile, operating profits at the non-government thrifts
slipped from $900 million to $800 million because of the recent
pattern of interest rates, he said. Short-term rates paid on
deposits are almost as high as long-term rates S&amp;Ls can earn on
loans.
   Texas, as usual, recorded the biggest loss by any state, $998
million. However, that was an improvement from the $1.7 billion
loss a year ago. The second biggest loss came in Arizona $443
million, followed by California $426 million, Pennsylvania $322
million and Arkansas $246 million.
   Twenty-nine states recorded losses while 21 and the District of
Columbia and Puerto Rico reported profits. The largest profit, $24
million, came in Washington state.
   Former thrift office economist, James R. Barth of Auburn
University, warned that real estate problems once confined largely
to the Southwest were spreading.
</TEXT>

</DOC>