<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0150EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-SearchforNoriega     12-22 0629</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Search for Noriega,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Calls Jam US Military Switchboards in Hunt for Noriega</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RUTH SINAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After days of scouring Panama for Manuel
Antonio Noriega, U.S. forces still don't have their quarry. But
they do have a surplus of tips and rumors about the whereabouts of
the fugitive general, thanks largely to the posting of a $1 million
reward.
   The number of calls jamming U.S. military switchboards in Panama
rose sharply on Wednesday in response to the White House's
announcement that the money was available for anyone providing
information leading to Noriega's capture.
   ``We got lots of nibbles. A lot of it turned out to be very
bogus,'' said Rear Adm. Ted Sheafer, an intelligence specialist for
the Joint Chiefs of Staff.
   Sheafer said callers reported sighting Noriega in at least 12
locations throughout Panama, 10 sites in Panama City and in three
foreign countries _ Colombia, the Dominican Republic and Mexico.
U.S. officials said, however, they believed Noriega had not left
the country.
   Noriega's wanted poster ``will be in every post office in
town,'' President Bush told reporters jokingly at a White House
news conference Thursday, adding that ``that's $1 million bucks I'd
be very happy to sign the check for.''
   But Noriega proved an elusive target for the commando forces and
intelligence analysts who set their traps for him.
   After rumors spread that Noriega or other members of the
Panamanian Defense Forces high command were in the Nicaraguan and
Cuban embassies, U.S. troops in armored personnel carriers
surrounded the two missions.
   But despite the massive dragnet for Noriega, aided by a force of
24,000 troops, U.S. hopes lay almost solely on reliable
intelligence information.
   ``We're looking for him very hard,'' said Lt. Gen. Tom Kelly,
the Pentagon's operations chief. ``Of course, that's all contingent
on intelligence.''
   American interrogators questioned hundreds of captured
Panamanian soldiers for clues about Noriega's plans, said one
official who asked not to be named.
   Kelly said American forces were ``turning on all our looking,
listening, and hearing devices to see if we can't pick'' up Noriega.
   The man in charge of the Panama strike, Lt. Gen. Carl W. Stiner,
who now commands the 18th Airborne Corps at Fort Bragg, N.C.,
formerly headed the U.S. Special Operations Forces which are tasked
with commando-style activities.
   Special Forces units reportedly were deployed to look for
Noriega, aided by infantry troops of the 7th Army which are
especially trained for urban warfare.
   White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater conceded that finding
Noriega in Panama City would be difficult. ``In a city of a million
people, it's not hard to hide out,'' he said.
   Pentagon officials also held out the possibility that U.S.
troops may have to stalk Noriega or his loyalists in Panama's
jungles.
   Although he is vastly outnumbered by the 24,000-strong U.S.
strike force, Noriega _ former head of military intelligence and
paid informer for the CIA in the 1970s _ is hard to outmaneuver,
officials said.
   ``He's a crafty devil, as you know,'' said Kelly. ``He grew up
in a very tough academy, so he's been used to this for many years.''
   It was unclear how many forces Noriega still has under his
command although Sheafer said, ``We do not think he is effectively
in command of anything at this time.''
   Bush said he would not be satisfied until Noriega was brought to
justice in the United States, and would keep up the search as long
as it took.
   But Noriega has vowed to fight to his death, and those who know
him well say he would resist capture at all costs.
   Said reserve Col. Charles Stone, who served in Panama until 1987
and often met with Noriega: ``I think before he'd face that, he'd
take his own life.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>