<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0154EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-FamilyFeud 1stLd-Writethru a0418 12-29 0487</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Family Feud, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0418,0499</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Women Must Learn To Live With One Name</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 6th graf to CORRECT that woman changed name to Bledsoe
sted Lloyd. Pick up 7th graf pvs: `Shirley Jean...</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURA REHRMANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Is little Salt Rock too small for two
Shirley Bledsoes?
   Shirley Jean thinks so. Shirley Rae thinks not. And the West
Virginia Supreme Court doesn't want to get involved.
   ``The feud has gone on for 12 years, and I think it's about time
for it to end,'' Shirley Rae Bledsoe, 47, said Thursday from her
home in the Cabell County community of 900 in the western part of
the state.
   The two Shirleys have been at odds with each other since the
1977 death of Lloyd Bledsoe, who was Shirley Rae's common-law
husband and Shirley Jean's brother. Shirley Rae continued using
Lloyd's surname on her credit cards and driver's license.
   The feud intensified in May when Shirley Rae _ then Shirley Rae
Lambert _ went to Circuit Court to legally take Lloyd's name.
Shirley Rae said she had lived with Lloyd Bledsoe for 20 years, and
that he was the father of two of her children.
   The court allowed her to change her name to Bledsoe.
   Shirley Jean, who says the similar names have resulted in mail
problems, then appealed the lower court's ruling to the state
Supreme Court, which refused in a 4-1 ruling to hear the case
earlier this month.
   ``I'm not the one that's caused the confusion. She is,'' Shirley
Rae said. ``She had been told by the post office a long time ago to
put her middle initial or her box office number on her mail, but
she bulled up and wouldn't do it.''
   Shirley Rae said any problems with the name change have been
strictly Shirley Jean's.
   ``I know I wasn't in the wrong and everybody else around Salt
Rock knows it too,'' she said. ``You can change your name to
anything you want as long as you don't hurt anybody and I wasn't
hurting her.''
   Shirley Jean refused to comment on the matter.
   ``I don't want to get involved,'' Shirley Jean said Thursday.
   The town's postmaster isn't taking sides, but said mail delivery
hasn't been a hassle with the Bledsoes or any of the town's other
six people who have similar names.
   ``We've had both of them ever since I've been here and we've
never had any problem,'' said Leah Gill, Salt Rock's postmaster for
19 years. ``If it's addressed correctly, then they get it.''
   And while names of a different sort continue to be exchanged
between the two Bledsoes, most of the town refuses to take sides.
   Leonard Bledsoe said he may be distantly related to one of the
Shirley Bledsoes, but he won't get in the middle of their feud.
   ``That's their problem,'' he said. ``They'll just have to fight
it out.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>