<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0097 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1831EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Panama-Troops     12-25 0479</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Troops,0497</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Troops Give Rations, Phone Home, Patrol Happy Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CANDICE HUGHES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A long way from home on Christmas,
U.S. soldiers in Panama shared food with children, gave rations to
refugees and found themselves surrounded by swarms of residents
pouring out words of gratitude.
   Clad in their familiar camouflage fatigues and helmets, the
troops were warmly greeted by Panamanians during military patrols
Monday.
   Sgt. 1st Class Phillip Baker of Fayetteville, N.C., was one of
dozens on guard duty near the Vatican mission, where Gen. Manuel
Antonio Noriega sought refuge Sunday.
   As troops ringed the building near Panama Bay, residents left
their homes to jot down names and telephone numbers of dozens of
soldiers so they could call the soldiers' families in the United
States and wish them a merry Christmas.
   ``I can't believe they offered to call home for us,'' Baker
said. ``Some kids came by with Christmas cards they'd made for us.
I'm going to take them home and frame them.''
   At an Army command post near Santo Tomas Hospital, infantrymen
put up a tiny Christmas tree and a sign saying ``Feliz Navidad.''
They were sharing their food with neighborhood children and
families.
   ``Last night, people came over and wished us a Merry Christmas.
It's been a real nice Christmas,'' said Sgt. Clay Carnahan of
Lubbock, Texas. ``It makes you feel real good.''
   In David, 200 miles west of Panama City, troops, helicopters and
warplanes took over an airport and a military outpost that had
housed Noriega loyalists.
   As news of their arrival spread, many residents came out and
cheered the passing soldiers. One resident offered a soldier beer.
   ``No, we want Coca-Cola,'' a resident said a soldier told
passengers in a bus. ``So people came out of the bus and gave them
Coke and soft drinks.''
   In the former Canal Zone city of Balboa, troops passed out
rations to refugees in a soccer stadium and put up large tents.
   The homeless formed orderly lines for Army rations.
   ``We served more than 8,000 meals last night,'' Boston-born Army
Col. William Connolly reported.
   Thousands of Panamanians, escaping the gunfire, bombings and
sniper attacks that began with the American invasion last Tuesday,
were being housed in churches, schools and stadiums throughout the
capital.
   As the fighting waned and Noriega's men surrendered, Panamanians
were grateful for peace on Christmas.
   Panamanian insurance adjuster Bill Heron was one of those taking
down names and U.S. phone numbers of soldiers on neighborhood
patrols.
   ``It's the least we can do,'' he said. ``It's our Christmas gift
to them.''
   Heron said the U.S. troops had made this the best Christmas he'd
had in 21 years, since Noriega's predecessor, the late Gen. Omar
Torrijos, took over in a coup.
   ``God. I don't know how to express it,'' he said. ``But we're so
grateful.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>