<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0102 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1408EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-PoliceKillings     12-18 0649</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Police Killings,0670</SECOND>
<HEAD>1978 Police Killings Called Puerto Rico's `Watergate'</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSANA HAYWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN JUAN, Puerto Rico (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eleven years ago, police shot to
death two independence advocates on a desolate mountaintop,
sparking a case compared to the Watergate scandal and an
investigation that still goes on.
   The island's governor at the time hailed the police as heroes,
but it was later determined the two young nationalists surrendered
and were shot while pleading for mercy, not in a shootout with
officers.
   The killings and subsequent cover-up led to the imprisonment of
10 police officers and contributed to the fall of a government.
   The case _ known as Cerro Maravilla after the mountain in
southern Puerto Rico where the killings occurred _ is the subject
of a film to be released next year.
   The movie, which stars Amy Irving, Robert Duvall and Lou Diamond
Phillips, was filmed in Puerto Rico last summer.
   Samuel Dash, who was the chief counsel to the Senate Watergate
Committee, said Cerro Maravilla ranks with Watergate for its
``breach of basic rights for citizens'' and degree of official
cover-up.
   Dash, a special adviser to the Puerto Rico Senate's
investigation of the killings, said in an interview from Washington
``there is belief police had support all the way up.''
   Investigations continue to this day into whether the previous
island government and the U.S. Justice Department conspired to
suppress the truth.
   Sen. Marcos A. Rigau, chairman of the Puerto Rico Senate
Judiciary Committee, said he expects the case to be resolved in
1990 with new evidence. Senate hearings are expected to resume in
June or July.
   Carlos Romero Barcelo, who was governor when the killings
occurred, has called the continuing investigation a ``political
witch hunt'' spearheaded by Gov. Rafael Hernandez Colon. The
governor's pro-commonwealth Popular Democratic Party controls the
Senate, which is carrying out the inquiry.
   Police claimed the two nationalists, Carlos Soto Arrivi, 18, and
Arnaldo Dario Rosado, 24, went to Cerro Maravilla on July 25, 1978,
to blow up a 400-foot TV transmission tower. They said the two
refused to surrender and were killed in a shootout.
   That account was upheld in two federal grand jury inquiries and
two Puerto Rico Justice Department investigations spanning five
years.
   But questions raised by Senate President Miguel Hernandez Agosto
and two reporters for The San Juan Star, Manuel Suarez and Tomas
Stella, cast doubt on the official version.
   Taxi driver Julio Ortiz Molina, who was abducted by the
nationalists on their way to the mountain, revealed that the two
men were captured after an exchange of gunfire. He said he later
heard a second volley of shots.
   In 1983, three police officers who had turned state's evidence
provided a riveting account of the killings during televised Senate
hearings.
   They said Soto Arrivi and Dario Rosado surrendered and were
beaten and then shot by three police officers at close range while
on the ground pleading for their lives.
   The revelation was a key reason Romero Barcelo lost his
re-election bid in 1984. He had maintained police acted in
self-defense and had been ``heroic.''
   The killings occurred during a turbulent period in which
pro-independence groups had carried out a flurry of bombings in
their campaign to end Puerto Rico's status as a U.S. commonwealth.
   Eventually, 10 police officers were convicted on various
charges, including second-degree murder, conspiracy and perjury,
and sentenced to prison terms ranging from six to 30 years.
   It remains unclear why Soto Arrivi and Dario Rosado went to
Cerro Maravilla.
   Alejandro Gonzalez Malave, a police agent who infiltrated the
small band of reputed terrorists calling themselves the Armed
Revolutionary Forces, notified police they were planning to blow up
the tower, but no explosives were found.
   Gonzalez Malave was facing perjury charges in April 1986 when he
was gunned down outside his mother's house. The separatist group
Los Macheteros claimed responsibility.
</TEXT>

</DOC>