<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0233EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-US-PanamaStatement     12-20 0288</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-US-Panama Statement,290</SECOND>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is the text of the statement by White
House press secretary Marlin Fitzwater announced early Wednesday
that President Bush had ordered American troops in Panama to seize
dictator Manuel Antonio Noriega.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   The president has directed U.S. forces to execute at 1 a.m. this
morning pre-planned missions in Panama to protect American lives,
restore the democratic process, preserve the integrity of the
Panama Canal treaties and apprehend Manuel Noriega
   The situation in Panama under Gen. Noriega has reached a crisis.
Democratic elections have been thwarted; American lives have been
endangered.
   The integrity of the Panama Canal treaties is at risk.
   Gen. Noriega is under indictment for drug-related charges and
the president has made every effort peacefully to resolve the
situation through negotiations under the auspices of the
Organization of American States and Latin American leaders.
   Gen. Noriega has rejected all of these efforts. Last Friday,
Noriega declared a state of war with the United States. The next
day the PDF (Panamanian Defense Forces) shot to death an unarmed
American serviceman, wounded another, seized and beat another
serviceman and sexually threatened his wife.
   Under these circumstances, the president decided he must act to
prevent further violence. Our troops will use only the force
necessary to achieve the objectives and will be withdrawn as
quickly as possible.
   At approximately midnight tonight, the democratically elected
leaders of Panama, President Endara, and vice presidents Calderon
and Ford, were sworn in and assumed their rightful positions. They
welcome and support our actions and have stated their intention to
institute a Democratic government immediately.
   The United States has recognized that government and will
restore normal relations and will cooperate to rebuild a free and
prosperous Panama.
</TEXT>

</DOC>