<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0101EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-US-Mideast     12-18 0609</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-Mideast,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Delay Possible in Mideast Peace Talks</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BARRY SCHWEID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Diplomatic Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A senior Israeli diplomat is beginning
preparations today for an opening round of Mideast peace talks here
next month, but there is growing doubt the U.S.-sponsored meetings
will get off the ground without delay.
   Diplomatic sources cited moves by the Palestine Liberation
Organization as the reason it is no longer certain the talks, to be
hosted by Secretary of State James A. Baker III, will be held.
   Still, Israeli cabinet secretary Eliakim Rubinstein, who played
a leading role in negotiations that led to the 1979
Egyptian-Israeli peace treaty, was sent here Sunday from Jerusalem.
   He is meeting at the State Department with Dennis Ross, head of
the State Department's policy planning staff and Baker's closest
adviser on the Middle East, and with Richard Haass and other
National Security Council staffers.
   Ross broke away from Baker's trip to Europe last week to prepare
for the meeting with Rubinstein.
   Egypt, meanwhile, is sending no special representative from
Cairo to make preparations. Ambassador Sayed el Reedy is available,
as needed.
   The three-way talks Baker hopes to have with Foreign Ministers
Moshe Arens of Israel and Esmat Abdel Meguid of Egypt would be the
first step toward Palestinian elections on the Israeli-held West
Bank and in Gaza.
   Both Israel and Egypt have agreed to the meeting, reserving some
issues to be settled once Arad and Meguid saw Baker.
   But since the State Department announced Egypt's qualified
acceptance 12 days ago, problems have arisen between the Arab
country and the PLO. They raise questions whether Egypt would be
speaking for Yasser Arafat's organization.
   Israeli Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir assured President Bush and
Baker on a visit here in mid-November that he was committed to his
plan for elections among the 1.4 million Palestinian Arabs in the
territories.
   The idea is to choose negotiators to work out limited self-rule
with Israel, a plan that has the support of the Bush administration
but is challenged by the PLO as a ploy to prevent establishment of
a Palestinian state.
   When Egypt agreed to Baker's proposal for a planning meeting
here in January it registered some reservations, as Israel had done
earlier. They were to be taken up at the meeting.
   Essentially, Egypt reserved the right to promote a role for the
PLO in selecting a Palestinian delegation that would hold
pre-election talks with Israel in Cairo.
   Israel, meanwhile, reserved the right to try to exclude the PLO
from having any meaningful role.
   On Dec. 6, Margaret D. Tutwiler, the State Department
spokeswoman, announced that Egypt had accepted Baker's proposal.
She called it a ``step forward'' in the peace process.
   But the PLO asserted a more direct role by giving its qualified
acceptance to Robert Pelletreau Jr., the U.S. ambassador to Tunisia
who has been the U.S. contact with the PLO since a dialogue was
opened a year ago.
   And then Arafat sent a private letter to Bush indicating his
willingness to make peace.
   While the president did not reply, the opening of a PLO channel
to the White House serves to undercut the idea that the United
States is negotiating with Egypt, not the PLO.
   Still, Shamir is standing by his commitment to proceed, despite
concerns by more conservative members of his Likud coalition that
the PLO's prestige and power might be enhanced.
   Within hours of receiving a summary _ but not the text _ of
Egypt's acceptance of Baker's proposal, Shamir and other members of
the Israel ``inner cabinet'' notified the State Department it would
go ahead with preparations. The cabinet designated Rubinstein for
the job last Sunday.
</TEXT>

</DOC>