<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0114 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1530EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India     12-18 0469</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India,0484</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Indian Parliament Begins First Session</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DILIP GANGULY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The new Parliament began its first
session Monday, setting in motion the process for a crucial vote of
confidence that Prime Minister V.P. Singh must seek for his
minority government.
   President Ramaswamy Venkataraman set Jan. 1 as the deadline for
Singh to prove his majority in Parliament when he invited him to
form the government on Dec. 2.
   Former Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi's Congress Party won more
seats than any single party in the Nov. 22-26 elections _ 193 _ but
fell far short of the 263 needed for an absolute majority.
   Singh's National Front got only 144, but its pledges of
post-election support from right-wing Hindu fundamentalists and a
leftist array of Communists and socialists give it 283 votes _ more
than enough to carry the motion which is likely to come up for vote
Thursday.
   Singh was the first of the 525 members of the Lok Sabha, or
House of the People, to take the oath of allegiance to the
Constitution and sign the roll of legislators.
   Across the floor members of the Congress Party sat in the
opposition benches for only the second time in Indian parliamentary
history.
   Singh's supporters cheered and slapped the palms of their hands
on their tables as he was sworn in. He then walked across and shook
hands with Gandhi.
   As soon as Singh's Cabinet ministers took their oaths, Gandhi
was sworn in to a new burst of cheers.
   Gandhi was surrounded by supporters as he entered the Parliament
building. ``Long live Rajiv Gandhi!'' they chanted as a red and
yellow roses bouquet was thrust into his hands.
   Singh entered the building well ahead of others and before
crowds could gather.
   After he was sworn in, he said he would continue the dialogue
initiated Sunday to find a political solution to Sikh separatism
that has claimed more than 7,000 lives in Punjab in the past eight
years.
   Sikh militants elected to the new Parliament did not take the
oath Monday, but a militant spokesman said they will do so Thursday.
   Spokesman Gurtej Singh Brar said in Punjab's capital of
Chandigarh that Sikh militant members will vote for Singh when the
motion seeking confidence in Singh's government is put to vote.
   ``We shall not let the government fall,'' he said.
   For the first time Sikh militants, who are campaigning for an
independent homeland in Punjab state, have entered the national
political mainstream by winning Parliament seats in the election.
Militants won six of the 13 seats in Punjab. Three independents
backed by the militants also were elected.
   Singh ousted Gandhi from the prime minister's job on a platform
of clean government and vows to repair the cracks in the country's
religious harmony.
</TEXT>

</DOC>