<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0153 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0911EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a PM-ReligionintheNews Adv29   12-27 0826</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Religion in the News, Adv 29,0853</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv29</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Fri. PMs Dec. 29, or thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Decade Unleashes Religious Right And East European Believers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE W. CORNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Religion Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   In religion, the decade of the 1980s started with a plunge into
politics by America's ``religious right'' and is ending with a
burst of new freedoms for believers within the Soviet orbit.
   Over the past 10 years, the religion domain also has been jolted
with scandals, hit with jail terms for ``sanctuary'' workers and
shaken with conflicts over homosexuality, the Bible and abortion.
   Simultaneously the quest for Christian unity, though flagging
from its earlier euphoria, nevertheless made substantial strides.
So did closer Jewish-Christian relations, despite rocky moments.
   But the main religious hallmarks of the 80s were the burst into
U.S. political activism by church conservatives and the burgeoning
of religious rights in lands long shackled under atheist statism.
   The freshening spiritual breath in Eastern Europe emanated in
part from the churches themselves and from that surprising Soviet
President Mikhail Gorbachev.
   Capping the trend was the unprecedented friendly meeting this
year between Gorbachev and Pope John Paul II. The Vatican was
scorned by previous Soviet leadership as impotent for lack of
military power.
   But while religious opportunities grew in most Communist areas,
even in China despite the brutal anti-democracy suppression last
summer, the churches met persistent harassment in Latin American.
   But they also became bastions of human rights there, although a
long line of Christian workers were slain, particularly El Salvador
and Guatamala, along with thousands of civilians.
   The decade there began with the assassination of El Salvador's
Roman Catholic Archbishop Oscar Romero in 1980 and ended in 1989
with the murder of six Jesuit priests.
   U.S. churches entered a sanctuary movement to shelter refugees
fleeing the strife-ridden area. But the formerly open movement
edged underground after several participants were convicted in 1986
of smuggling aliens.
   A key religious development of the decade was the emergence into
public affairs of the long insular religious right, which had
previously denounced such activity as meddling in politics.
   But they surged from their spiritual closet in l980, along with
their paragon, former President Ronald Reagan, claiming credit for
electing him that year and again in 1984.
   The changed mode was sparked by a suave Virginia preacher, Jerry
Falwell, who founded Moral Majority in l979, and led it through 10
years of robust politicking, closing it down only this year.
   ``Mission accomplished,'' he said, adding that other
conservative Christian lobbying groups had evolved to handle the
cause.
   The movement's prime objectives _ public school prayer, tuition
tax credits for church schools and stopping abortion _ remained
unaccomplished. But ferment continued about them.
   A conservative tide also swept the Southern Baptist Convention,
where fundamentalists gained the presidency in 1979 and held it
through l989, broadening control throughout that biggest Protestant
body.
   It was a battle for the Bible, fundamentalists contended,
gradually imposing their demand for literalist ``biblical
inerrancy'' _ historically and scientifically _ on denominational
agencies.
   Meanwhile, mainline denominations suffered declines in
membership, and their chief cooperative organization, the National
Council of Churches, fell into operational and financial disarray
late in the decade.
   But remodeling work was underway, with efforts to bring more
evangelical churches and Roman Catholicism into full membership.
   Also, quiet but steady progress continued on the ecumenical
front.
   Northern and Southern Presbyterians, separated since the Civil
War, united in 1983 into the Presbyterian Church (U.S.A) and three
branches of Lutherans united in 1987 into the Evangelical Lutheran
Church in America.
   Of wider significance, a stream of world-wide, largely favorable
responses flowed into the World Council of Churches to a remarkably
inclusive ``convergence agreeement.''
   Dealing with key issues dividing churches _ baptism, eucharist
and ministry _ the ``BEM'' document was produced by representatives
of Protestantism, Roman Catholicism and Eastern Orthodoxy at a l982
meeting in Lima, Peru.
   The deepening ties were dramatized at a giant largely Baptist
rally in Columbia, S.C., where the pope preached on his 1987 U.S.
trip, flanked by leading figures of most U.S. denominations.
   But he had a tense session with his U.S. hierarchy in Los
Angeles, where bishops told him Americans were used to being
persuaded rather than told what to believe. But he insisted
dissenters were't good Catholics.
   Seeking to tighten Vatican controls, he stripped noted moral
theologian Charles Curran of teaching credentials in 1986 and
temporarily curtailed the authority of Seatle Archbishop Raymond
Hunthausen, restoring it in 1987.
   The Vatican's mid-decade repudiation of homosexualty as a
``moral disorder'' continued to stir sharp resentments and
disruptions in Catholic churches.
   Sex scandals hit two prominent television evangelists, Jimmy
Swaggart and Jim Bakker. Baker resigned his PTL network in 1987
over a sexual tryst and in 1989 was convicted and imprisoned for
defrauding contributors.
   Swaggart was defrocked in 1988 for sexual misbehavior after he
refused to to accept disciplines imposed by his denomination, the
Assemblies of God.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Fri PMs Dec. 29.</NOTE>

</DOC>