<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0945EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-BoatPeople 1stLd-Writethru a0502 12-29 0487</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Boat People, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0502,0496</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Fire Tear Gas After Refugees Refuse To Cooperate In Weapons
Search</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to UPDATE number of injured, arrests; picks
up xth pvs, `Although officials...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CINTY LI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HONG KONG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police in riot gear fired tear gas into a
detention center today to quell unrest by Vietnamese boat people
who refused to cooperate in a search for homemade weapons.
Officials said 40 people were injured.
   Police found more than 700 weapons in the early afternoon search
and arrested 27 Vietnamese.
   The violence came a day after fights broke out between two
groups of Vietnamese in a second center. One person was killed and
10 injured in the clashes.
   Vietnamese at the Chi Ma Wan center threw stones and set fire to
blankets after security forces arrived for the weapons search,
government spokesman Timothy Li said.
   Television showed police equipped with helmets and shields
firing tear gas, and smoke from fires could be seen rising above
the center.
   Police said 14 Vietnamese and 26 guards and policemen were
injured in the camp on outlying Lantau Island.
   ``The boat people, in order to make the operation more
difficult, pushed their women and children to the front,'' Security
Secretary M. Geoffrey Barnes said in a government statement.
   Although officials refused to say how many police were used in
the operation, government-funded radio put the number at about 300.
   Five hours of counseling by staff of the U.N. High Commissioner
of Refugees and voluntary agencies failed to persuade the
Vietnamese to cooperate, the government statement said.
   The radio reported that the resistance may have been prompted by
reports that some of the Chi Ma Wan inmates may be in the next
group of boat people forced to return to their impoverished
homeland.
   That fatality occurred at the Shek Kong Detention Center late
Thursday when two fights broke out between two rival groups of
Vietnamese boat people armed with homemade weapons, police said.
   No one was arrested at Shek Kong but police found homemade
weapons such as swords and lances after the battles.
   Police say five people have died this year in factional fighting
in the crowded, squalid camps housing the boat people in this
British colony.
   The residents of both camps are among about 44,000 boat people
who have sailed into Hong Kong since mid-June 1988 and are
considered illegal immigrants unless they can prove they fled
persecution.
   Hong Kong forcibly repatriated 51 boat people to Hanoi against
their will earlier this month and reports have said another group
will be forced home next month.
   Meanwhile, the eighth batch of boat people to volunteer to
return to their Communist homeland flew back to Hanoi today. The 72
men, 29 women and 10 children took a chartered flight. Their
departure brings to 874 the number of Vietnamese who have returned
home voluntarily since March.
</TEXT>

</DOC>