<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0175 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1400EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-PRI--UntietheElderly-Florida Adv28   12-26 0788</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-PRI--Untie the Elderly-Florida, Adv 28,0808</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv28</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Thursday, Dec. 28, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Florida Nursing Homes Cutting Back On Use Of Restraints</HEAD>
<HEAD>With BC-PRI--Untie the Elderly</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JACKIE HALLIFAX</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TALLAHASSEE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Connie Cheren doesn't like the phrase
``untying the elderly,'' but she wholeheartedly supports the
concept.
   Cheren, who oversees 4,300 health care facilities, has led an
effort to reduce nursing home use of restraints, untying 3,000
people in four months. ``The only thing that I feel bad about is
that I didn't do it ... earlier.''
   When Cheren became director of the state Office of Licensure and
Certification two years ago, 41 percent of the 55,000 people in the
state's 550 nursing homes were restrained at least part of the day
by vests that fasten to beds or chairs, wrist ties, lap belts and
specially designed chairs. Several elderly people had strangled in
recent years struggling to free themselves.
   Use of restraints rose to 43.7 percent by April 1989, but was
down to 39 percent last month, federal statistics show. Cheren did
not have statistics on the use of tranquilizers, but said
regulators would try to ensure that chemical restraints are not
overly used and do not replace physical restraints.
   Cheren stepped up regulation of restraint use in August, when
she told Ambrosia Nursing Home in Tampa it could not admit new
residents until it stopped illegally using restraints simply to
prevent wandering.
   Under Florida law, restraints can be used to keep people from
falling or from disturbing medical equipment, such as feeding
tubes. They cannot be used without a doctor's permission, and
people must be released every two hours.
   Restraint reduction has caught on in the industry ``because
first of all it's right,'' she said. ``Second, it feels good.
Nobody likes to put somebody under restraint. You interact
differently with somebody in restraint. Three, it's working, and
success builds on success.''
   Cheren, a registered nurse with 20 years' involvement in
long-term care, dislikes the phrase ``untying the elderly'' because
it casts the elderly in a passive role _ ``just like `release
women' or `free the blacks,''' she said.
   Also, physical restraints came into use out of sincere concern
for safety. However, she said, it is time to focus on better
nursing home care that involves helping peple keep and restore
their abilities.
   About 1,000 nursing home owners and operators attended three
workshops on restraints in October and November. Instead of being
apprehensive about meeting new standards, people were bragging
about the progress they had made.
   ``People called me afterwards ... and told me their goal for
this year was to completely move toward a restraint-free
environment,'' said Mary Ellen Early of the Florida Association of
Homes for the Aging.
   The 454-bed Miami Jewish Home and Hospital for the Aged, for
example, cut use of restraints 18 percent, said associate executive
director Terry Goodman. ``The residents are much happier, less
agitated and the staff has noted a significant decrease in the
amount of agitation and less acting out.''
   Many operators have reported resistance from families who think
nursing home residents are safer if they are restrained, Early said.
   But Cheren and other advocates of reducing restraints say the
losses that occur in mobility, bladder control and dignity far
outweigh the small risk of a serious injury due to a fall.
   ``The bottom line really is that the risk of falling really
ain't so bad,'' said Martin Casper, executive director of 250-bed
Greynolds Park Manor in North Miami Beach, which now restrains four
people, compared to 85-90 this summer.
   And while there has been concern that restraint reduction would
increase costs _ Florida homes operate on a profit margin of less
than 0.5 percent _ Casper said he has found the cost of staff
supervision remained the same.
   Cheren can even count among her supporters the administrator of
Ambrosia Nursing Home, which lost an estimated $60,000 because of
the moratorium, the toughest stricture possible short of license
revocation.
   ``I think Connie Cheren has done a fine thing,'' said Albert
Shepard, who had 10 of 80 beds empty during the 60-day penalty.
``Connie Cheren having zeroed in on this particular thing ... has
made the difference.''
   The home has fixed an alarm system that sounds when a door is
opened and set up a ``buddy'' system in which workers _ even office
and housekeeping staff _ adopt a resident for special daily
attention, including walks. Except for six or eight ``geri-chairs''
for people who can't sit alone, it has no restraints.
   ``We're very much in agreement with the whole philosophy of
non-restraint facilities,'' Shepard said. ``It's an excellent thing
to give people the freedom of movement.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Dec. 28</NOTE>

</DOC>