<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0147 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1647EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Chernobyl     12-20 0439</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Chernobyl,0451</SECOND>
<HEAD>Children From Chernobyl Area Arrive For Holiday In Israel</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SERGEI SHARGORODSKY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A group of 52 Soviet teen-agers who were
exposed to radiation during the Chernobyl nuclear accident arrived
in Israel on Wednesday for a three-week holiday.
   The children, guests of Israel's United Kibbutz Movement, came
under an agreement on youth exchanges signed by Israel's
Agriculture Minister Abraham Katz-Oz in Moscow this month.
   Katz-Oz and Vice Premier Shimon Peres were waiting at the Ben
Gurion Airport near Tel Aviv for the excited children, brought by a
special Soviet Aeroflot airlines flight from Moscow.
   ``We know what you have suffered and we all hope the warm sun of
this country will be of benefit to you,'' Peres said. ``What we,
the older people, have lost, you the young ones can regain by
bringing understanding between our two peoples.''
   ``We shall pray that you should gain complete freedom, you pray
for us that we should achieve complete peace, and we both shall
pray for better understanding between our countries,'' he said.
   The Soviet children, aged 14 to 16, were also greeted by Israeli
youths of their own age from five kibbutzim, or collective farms,
in the southern Negev desert.
   The young guests will spend several days in the Negev and will
also visit Negev's capital of Beersheba and the Galilee,
Agriculture Ministry spokesman Naftali Yaniv said.
   The Soviet children are not suffering from any radiation-related
diseases following the April 1986 accident at Chernobyl, the worst
ever involving a nuclear reactor. But they will be under medical
observation by local doctors and some may undergo closer check-ups
in Israeli hospitals.
   Another group of 50 children from the Chernobyl area is due to
arrive in Israel next year. The exchange program would encompass
1,000 youths aged 15 to 17 from both countries.
   ``This is only one of the agreements signed by Katz-Oz,'' Yaniv
said. ``We hope that next week we can start to implement the second
agreement, on the supply of fresh Israeli agricultural products to
Moscow region.''
   Katz-Oz, the first Israeli minister to travel to Moscow in at
least 22 years, was invited there by the Soviet Academy of Sciences.
   The $30 million agricultural agreement stipulates export of
90,000 tons of fresh fruits and vegetables to the Moscow region,
which consumes 2.5 million tons a year. A third party, in return,
would sell Soviet goods for hard currency and transfer the money to
Israel.
   The Soviet Union cut diplomatic ties with Israel following the
1967 Middle East War. The countries exchanged low-level diplomatic
missions in 1987-88 and are developing cultural and economic ties.
</TEXT>

</DOC>