<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0110 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1229EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Yugoslavia-Strike     12-20 0335</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Yugoslavia-Strike,0344</SECOND>
<UNK>650,000 Strike in Belgrade to Protest Austerity Measures</UNK>
<DATELINE>BELGRADE, Yugoslavia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 650,000 workers staged a brief
warning strike Wednesday after the Serbian republic rejected a
package of reforms proposed by the country's reformist government
headed by Premier Ante Markovic.
   Laborers in Belgrade, which is both the national and the Serbian
capital, stopped working for half an hour to protest the
government's austerity measures, the state Tanjug news agency said.
   Drivers, store assistants and others gathered at their
workplaces to read a demand by Belgrade trade unions for easing new
austerity measures.
   The unions said the strike was designed to warn the federal
government to pay more attention to ``impoverished people,'' who
may find their low standards of living dip even lower with the
proposed reforms.
   Markovic's program calls for a six-month wage freeze and
creation of a convertible dinar, along with other unprecedented
sweeping economic and political reforms designed to pull Yugoslavia
out of its economic slump.
   The program, which requires approval by the legislature at its
current session slated to end later Wednesday, also calls for an
end to state subsidies to money-losing companies which may result
in laying off of at least 150,000 workers, according to official
government sources.
   Serbia's officially controlled media unanimously condemned the
proposed reforms.
   Filip Grujic, Serbia's vice premier, told the Serbian parliament
Tuesday the program will ``drastically imperil the position of the
most impoverished people in the entire country.''
   All five other constituent republics, however, gave green light
to Markovic's proposed reforms and plans for political pluralism in
the country.
   Serbia is calling for short-term measures to curb inflation,
such as price freezes. Such price freezes have previously succeeded
in holding down consumer costs, but when the restrictions were
lifted, inflation soared to record levels.
   A prolonged dispute between the leaderships of Yugoslavia's
constituent republics over the country's political and economic
future came to a head in November when the conservative Serbian
government broke off all business and political ties with liberal
Slovenia.
</TEXT>

</DOC>