<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0138 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1803EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Poindexter1stLd-Writethru     12-21 0731</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poindexter 1st Ld-Writethru,a0727-a0728-a0731-a0742,700</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge Postpones Poindexter Trial, Demands Reagan's Notes</HEAD>
<HEAD>Combines pvs: SUBS 3rd graf: ``Greene moved,'' and 11th graf pvs,
now 12th graf: ``Poindexter separately,'' to CORRECT that second subpoena
not yet approved; INSERTS 11th graf: ``Executive privilege,'' to explain
the notion; ADDS two grafs on documents sought</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETE YOST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal judge Thursday delayed the start of
John Poindexter's Iran-Contra trial and demanded to see excerpts
from former President Reagan's diaries and notes, which Poindexter
wants to use in court.
   U.S. District Court Judge Harold Greene said, ``President Reagan
shall produce for the court's ... inspection'' by Jan. 7 some of
the materials sought by Poindexter. Greene will then determine
whether the material is relevant to the criminal charges against
Reagan's former national security adviser.
   Greene moved back the Jan. 22 starting date of Poindexter's
trial until Feb. 20, saying a delay is necessary because of pending
issues. Those include Poindexter's subpoenas, approved by the
court, seeking Reagan's documents.
   Greene quashed major portions of Poindexter's subpoenas for
documents from the former president, but kept in place the most
sensitive sections, those dealing with Reagan's diaries, notes and
notebooks.
   ``The court is not disposed to requiring President Reagan to
make wholesale production of documents which ultimately may turn
out to contain little or no material evidence,'' said the judge.
   ``The obvious answer to this dilemma ... is an ... examination
by the court of the relevant excerpts from the former president's
diaries, notes and notebooks to determine whether they contain
specific evidence that should be produced,'' said Greene.
   Greene said ``legal and historical precedents indicate'' that a
review by the judge is appropriate ``of the presidential papers at
issue.''
   The judge said that he will review the Reagn documents and
``render a decision on the ... parts of the Reagan diary, notes and
notebooks that must be made available'' to Poindexter.
   Poindexter obtained court approval to issue the subpoena for
Reagan's documents by submitting a secret paper outlining what he
believes they contain.
   The judge said that Reagan and President Bush will be permitted
to see that paper next month, if Reagan invokes executive privilege
in response to any decision by Greene to turn Reagan documents over
Poindexter.
   Executive privilege is the legal concept by which presidents can
shield from public disclosure documents used in carrying out their
constitutional duties. In the Watergate cases involving President
Nixon, courts ruled that the privilege could not be used to protect
evidence needed in a criminal trial.
   Poindexter separately sought approval to subpoenaed Reagan
earlier this week, seeking testimony from the former president in
person.
   Greene set up a schedule for Reagan's lawyers and President Bush
to file objections to that testimonial subpoena and for
Poindexter's lawyers to respond to the objections. Greene said he
will rule on the matter sometime after Jan. 8.
   The judge in October outlined Poindexter's statement of what he
expected to discover, filed in support of a request to issue a
subpoena to Reagan for documents.
   Reagan met Poindexter daily, frequently alone, and they
discussed specific matters which now are connected to the criminal
charges against Poindexter, the former national security adviser
says.
   The subjects discussed with Reagan include the accuracy of a
chronology prepared by former White House aide Oliver North and
reviewed by Poindexter, according to Greene's outline.
   The chronology falsely says no one in the U.S. government knew
until 1986 that a CIA-assisted November 1985 shipment to Iran
contained Hawk missiles.
   Four of the five criminal charges against Poindexter relate to
allegedly lying about the 1985 shipment.
   Reagan also discussed the administration's view of a House
resolution inquiring into whether North was raising money and
supplying military advice to the Contras.
   Poindexter is accused of obstructing Congress by sending letters
endorsing earlier White House denials that North was assisting the
Contras.
   Poindexter had subpoenaed documents from reagan touching on 67
meetings or events involving the former president and his national
security adviser. Fifty of the meetings or events involved the
Contras and 17 involved the administration's secret arms sales to
Iran, according to papers filed in the case.
   Poindexter also served a subpoena on the archivist of the United
States, who holds presidential documents. Greene quashed that
subpoena after the archivist asserted that he already had turned
over to the prosecutors the documents Poindexter was seeking.
</TEXT>

</DOC>