<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0162 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1355EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s w BC-WalterMears Adv31   12-28 0732</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Walter Mears, Adv 31,0753</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 31, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Hostages the Decade's Great Unresolved Dilemma</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WALTER R. MEARS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   On the eve of a New Year and a new decade, an
agonizing image haunts the emblems of hope, for the 1980s are
ending as they began, with Americans held hostage.
   And the scrapbook of the '80s could hardly be complete without a
collection of out-of-focus instant photographs of long-held
hostages in Lebanese captivity, sent out from time to time by men
waging what they deem to be holy war.
   For most of the decade there have been American hostages in the
Middle East. The names and faces have changed, but not the torment.
   Ten years ago there were 52, in Tehran, and the hostage impasse
was a crisis that helped undo a president, ending only as another
came to office.
   Now there are eight, in Beirut, and the air of crisis has long
since yielded to a grim, seldom spoken concession that for all its
might, there seems to be nothing the United States can do to force
the safe release of its people.
   The standing government statement is a demand that
hostage-takers and their sponsors free all the captives, and that
the United States is pursuing every possible avenue to that end.
   But there are no known avenues.
   President Bush calls the situation one of enormous frustration.
``It's on my mind an awful lot,'' he said in a review of his first
year in office.
   The U.S. hostages are among 18 Westerners kidnapped and believed
held in Lebanon. Terry Anderson, chief Middle East correspondent of
The Associated Press, has been held longer than any other hostage _
nearly five years now. He was seized in Beirut on March 16, 1985.
   They are held by militant Shiite Moslems aligned with Iran, with
different factions claiming to control groups of hostages. Anderson
and Thomas Sutherland are held by a group calling itself Islamic
Jihad, or holy war. It has made one demand from the beginning,
offering to free them in exchange for 15 Shiite Moslems jailed in
Kuwait for terrorist bombings.
   The administration stands firm on the no-deals policy declared
by Ronald Reagan, who secretly breached it with the Iran
arms-for-hostages dealings disclosed in 1986.
   The new Iranian government said at one point last fall that it
would seek to help gain the hostages' release if the United States
would free assets frozen during the Tehran hostage crisis. Assets
disputes are in the hands of an international tribunal in The
Hague, which has been releasing funds it determines to belong to
Iran. The administration insists there is no link, although after
one decision releasing assets to Iran, Bush said he hoped it might
help the situation.
   It hasn't so far. Nor have administration suggestions of
improved relations that could benefit Iran should the hostages be
released.
   One American hostage, Lt. Col. William R. Higgins, was killed,
and his captors issued a photograph of his hanging body last summer
after Israel kidnapped a Shiite leader in southern Lebanon. While
Bush denounced the brutality, there was no retaliation. He was said
to have been preparing reprisals in the event death threats against
a second hostage were carried out.
   But the plight of the other American hostages limits U.S.
options.
   A week after he took office, Reagan had said he wouldn't stand
for hostage episodes. ``Our policy will be one of swift and
effective retribution,'' he said in welcoming the Tehran embassy
hostages seized on Nov. 4, 1979, and held until his inauguration
day, Jan. 20, 1981.
   It was a warning on which he could not deliver when his own
hostage problems began three years later with the kidnappings in
Lebanon.
   Lacking options or answers, Bush has uttered no such warnings,
and has played down the hostage situation he inherited.
   The number is small, the victims are isolated and unseen. It is
an unrelenting problem, but not a crisis forcing its way onto the
national agenda.
   Nevertheless, the haunting figures of Americans held hostage
stand as symbols of the 1980s, and as unfinished business in the
new year.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Walter R. Mears, vice president and columnist
for The Associated Press, has reported on Washington and national
politics for more than 25 years.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, Dec. 31</NOTE>

</DOC>