<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1206EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Japan-Budget     12-24 0463</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Budget,0474</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Approves Fiscal 1990 Draft Budget</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERRIL JONES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government Sunday approved a draft $466.7
billion budget for fiscal 1990 that for the first time in 15 years
does not rely on deficit-financing bonds.
   The Cabinet held a special meeting to accept the Finance
Ministry's draft budget for the fiscal year beginning in March. The
budget represents a 9.7 percent increase over current spending.
   It calls for increases of 5.5 percent in defense spending, to
$29.1 billion; 5.9 percent in aid to developing countries, to about
$5.6 billion; and 6.2 percent in social security spending, to $81.5
billion.
   The increases reflect growing tax revenues flowing from Japan's
booming economy, which just entered its fourth year of continuous
expansion.
   Further negotiations will fine-tune specific allocations for the
final version of the budget, which is expected to be approved
Friday.
   The Cabinet also approved a supplementary budget for the current
fiscal year. The $41.5 billion budget is the largest stop-gap
budget ever.
   ``The greatest thrust of this year's budget is the desire of the
government to end its dependence on deficit-financing bonds,'' a
Foreign Ministry official said, speaking on condition of anonymity.
``Since they were first introduced in 1975, we have made earnest
efforts to end this dependency. We were finally able to rid
ourselves of this unhealthy system.''
   The government issued $9.3 billion worth of deficit-financing
bonds last year to cover the budget's red ink. That amount will be
made up in part by an infusion in fiscal 1990 of $9.15 billion from
government sales last year of its shares in Nippon Telegraph and
Telephone Corp., as well as increased tax revenues, the official
said.
   Defense spending will rise to $29.1 billion, but because of
economic expansion, the defense budget will dip below 1 percent of
Japan's gross national product for the first time in four years,
standing at 0.991 percent of the GNP.
   In the mid-1970s Japan adopted a policy of keeping defense
spending to within 1 percent of the GNP, but since 1986 it has
hovered just above that figure.
   Spending on public works will rise 0.3 percent to $43.8 billion
next fiscal year. Although the United States has urged Japan to
increase such publicly funded projects to help ease Tokyo's trade
surplus with Washington, the marginal increase ``is sufficient,''
the Finance Ministry official said.
   The draft budget was compiled on the basis of government
estimates that the economy will grow an inflation-adjusted 4
percent next year, a brisk pace despite a slowdown from the
estimated 4.6 percent growth in fiscal 1989.
   An unusual addition to the fiscal 1990 budget was $39 million
for the formal enthronement ceremonies of Emperor Akihito, and
$958,000 for the wedding of Akihito's second son, Prince Aya.
</TEXT>

</DOC>