<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0209EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Japan-Markets     12-19 0305</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Japan-Markets,0314</SECOND>
<HEAD>Share Prices, Dollar Fall</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The key index on the Tokyo Stock Exchange fell
today after a week of consecutive gains, while the dollar inched
down against the Japanese yen.
   The dollar ended trading at 143.80 yen, down 0.42 yen from
Monday's close of 144.22 yen. It opened at 143.55 yen and ranged
between 143.15 yen and 143.97 yen.
   The Nikkei Stock Average of 225 selected issues shed 147.08
points, or 0.38 percent, ending at 38,489.10. It had gained 315.14
points to a record-high close of 3,8586.18 the previous day.
   Dealers attributed the fall in the Nikkei to the market's
speculation that Japan's central bank may raise its official
discount rate this week, partly to shore up the value of the yen
against the dollar.
   ``Since the market already is reacting to the reports, impact of
the reaction would be minimal if and when the central bank actually
announces the hike,'' said Masahiro Umemori, an analyst with Nomura
Securities Co.
   ``We consider today's 149.43-point decline as small, considering
the negative impact of the rumor,'' he said.
   The Yomiuri Shinbun and the Asahi Shinbun, Japan's two largest
newspapers, reported that the Bank of Japan will hike its official
discount rate by 0.5 percentage point to 4.25 percent.
   But Finance Minister Ryutaro Hashimoto said he had no plans to
discuss a rate increase with the Bank of Japan officials ``today or
tomorrow at least.''
   The official discount rate is the rate the central bank charges
on its loans to commercial banks and often influences other
interest rates. Higher interest rates discourage stock investors,
but it makes a country's currency more attractive to currency
investors.
   A trader with a major Japanese commercial bank anonymously said
the yen is likely to soar against the dollar if the Bank of Japan
raise the discount rate.
</TEXT>

</DOC>