<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0092 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1140EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-MailBombs 1stLd-Writethru a0499 12-22 0637</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mail Bombs, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0499,0651</SECOND>
<HEAD>Threatening Letters Sent to Two Mail Bomb Targets</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 12th graf, `There were...', with 3 grafs to add detail
on report of letter to broadcasters. Picks up 13th graf pvs, `One was...'.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Threatening follow-up letters have been sent to
at least two of the four targets of mail bombs that killed a
federal judge and a lawyer, investigators said.
   In revealing the existence of the letters Thursday,
investigators said they may have been sent by those responsible for
the bombings, which are believed to be linked to civil rights cases
in the South.
   Officials refused to reveal where the two letters were sent or
their contents.
   The four targets of the bombs were federal Judge Robert S.
Vance; his court, the 11th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals in
Atlanta; Savannah attorney Robert Robinson; and the Jacksonville,
Fla., NAACP.
   Vance was killed in his suburban Birmingham, Ala., home Saturday
when a nail-studded bomb exploded; Robinson was killed in his
office by a bomb Monday. The packages sent to the court and the
NAACP office were defused safely.
   Vance's wife, Helen, was in serious but stable condition today
with injuries received in the bombing.
   ``There have been follow-up letters sent since receipt of the
bomb parcels,'' said Leo Shatzel, postal inspector in charge in
Atlanta. ``It appears they may have been sent by the individual who
sent the parcels.
   ``They were threatening additional mailings to other
individuals.''
   Asked if the letters specifically threatened further bombings,
he said, ``No.''
   None of the letters specifically claim responsibility for the
bombings on behalf of a person or group, said William Hinshaw,
chief of the FBI's Atlanta office; nor do they describe ``to a T''
the details of the four mail bombs, which would lead investigators
to believe the follow-up letters were sent by the bomber.
   ll four packages have been linked to civil rights cases: Vance
and other 11th Circuit judges have handled school desegregation and
other civil rights cases from Georgia, Alabama and Florida; the
Jacksonville NAACP recently won a school desegregation case in the
Atlanta court; and Robinson had represented the Savannah NAACP in a
school desegregation case.
   The Atlanta Constitution reported today that the FBI is
investigating threatening letters mailed to at least 13
broadcasting stations nationwide last summer, which could be
related to the bombings.
   One of letters was mailed to WAPT, an ABC affiliate in Jackson,
Miss. Vickie Taylor, news assignment editor at the station, said
today that the letter, postmarked Atlanta, was received Aug. 24. It
used the term ``declaration of war'' and threatened poison gas
attacks in densely populated areas because of unspecificed
``biased'' rulings by federal appeals courts, she said.
   In Alabama, there were bomb scares at two court buildings
Thursday, but nothing was found.
   One was at the Birmingham court of U.S. Bankruptcy Judge
Clifford Fulford of Birmingham, who gave the eulogy at Vance's
funeral Wednesday.
   In Decatur, Ala., a suspicious package was found outside the
building which houses the post office and bankruptcy court. It was
detonated, but found to contain only clothing, said Decatur police
Sgt. Johnny Coker.
   In Savannah, Robinson's family scheduled his funeral for
Saturday.
   Security will be tight, said Savannah Police Capt. Dan Reynolds,
adding that police have been told to expect NAACP Executive
Director Benjamin Hooks.
   An FBI behavioral psychologist with experience in serial killing
cases has joined the investigation of the bombings, said bureau
spokesman Tom Moore.
   The psychologist, FBI agent William Hagmaier, has gone to
Birmingham to help develop a profile of the person who sent the
package to Vance, Moore said.
   Hagmaier interviewed mass killer Theodore Bundy before Bundy's
execution and worked on the ``Night Stalker'' case in California,
in which Richard Ramirez was convicted of a string of grisly
slayings.
</TEXT>

</DOC>