<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0162 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 2027EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Abortions     12-29 0367</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Abortions,0379</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Thousands of Women Died from Illegal Abortions</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of Romanian women died over
the past few years from illegal or botched abortions because of
deposed leader Nicolae Ceausescu's near-ban on the procedure, a
report said.
   The report Thursday came after Romania's new interim government
lifted Ceausescu's ban, which permitted few legal exceptions.
   Ceausescu instituted the abortion ban in 1966 to encourage
procreation. He also banned the sale of contraceptives.
   Even before Ceausescu's ouster and execution, there had been
reports in the official press of illegal abortions and doctors
charging phenomenal sums for the service.
   ``The criminal act (the abortion restrictions) caused the death
of thousands of women, many of them mothers of two to four
children,'' the official Agerpres news agency said.
   Agerpres also quoted a leading medical official as saying ``a
great many crippled babies were born'' because of inadequate
maternity care, malnutrition and other complications.
   Under the 1966 law, abortions were permitted only for mothers
who already had at least five children, in cases where childbirth
could endanger the woman's life, when the pregnancy resulted from
rape or incest, or when one of the parents suffered from serious
disease that could result in birth defects.
   Mothers were given monthly allowances that varied according to
the number of children they had.
   Still, the entire population was impoverished by the Ceausescu
regime and for many, having children made their situation even
worse.
   Dr. Bogdan Marinescu, head of the Giulesti Maternity House in
Bucharest, said that over the last eight years nearly 1,400 women
died from complications related to abortions in the capital alone,
Agerpres said.
   The figure for Bucharest is apt to be even higher, Agerpres
said, suggesting that hospitals and clinics attempted to hide the
fact they had conducted abortions.
   ``Their number is by far bigger ... because, when in agony, many
of them (pregnant mothers) were transferred to die in other medical
departments,'' Agerpres said.
   It was not clear from the report how many of the purported
deaths were a result of illegal abortions.
   Agerpres said Ceausescu's abortion ban was ``an aggression
against millions of women, children and, ultimately families, the
very national being.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>