<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0180 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1638EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-BusCrashTrial Bjt   12-20 0698</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bus Crash Trial, Bjt,0719</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jury Gets Case of Church Bus Accident That Killed 27</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHARLES WOLFE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CARROLLTON, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A jury began deliberating the fate of
Larry Mahoney on Wednesday, after a prosecutor said ``it's time to
pay'' for the 27 deaths he allegedly caused in an alcohol-related
head-on collision with a crowded bus.
   Mahoney's lawyers said he will forever be tormented by last
year's fiery disaster on Interstate 71, but argued that the real
culprit was the builder of the bus, in which victims died of a fire
rather than the crash itself.
   Special prosecutor Paul Richwalsky said Mahoney must be held to
account for his decision to drink and drive.
   ``I know that (Mahoney) regrets it. But that's got nothing to do
with this case,'' Richwalsky said in closing arguments in Carroll
Circuit Court.
   ``The apologies ... are too late. Now it's time to pay.''
   Defense attorneys Jack Hildebrand and William Summers said Ford
Motor Co. manufactured a bus with a vulnerable fuel tank that made
it a rolling ``bomb.''
   Mahoney sobbed at times while his attorneys appealed to the jury
to free him from 82 criminal charges _ 27 counts of murder, 12 of
first-degree assault, 42 of wanton endangerment and one of drunken
driving.
   Mahoney, 36, could be sentenced to 20 years to life in prison if
convicted of murder. The jury was given options of second-degree
manslaughter, five to 10 years, or reckless homicide, one to five
years, on those counts. Conviction of first-degree assault carries
a penalty of 10 to 20 years and the term is one to five years for
wanton endangerment.
   Hildebrand said Mahoney admittedly was drunk and driving on the
wrong side of I-71 when his pickup collided with the former school
bus owned by the Radcliff First Assembly of God church in Hardin
County.
   Twenty-four children and three adults died in the explosion and
fire that followed the collision. Of the 40 who escaped, 12
suffered severe burns.
   The crash occurred on May 14, 1988, a Saturday, when a church
youth group was returning home from a Cincinnati amusement park.
   Hildebrand repeated the defense's claim that Mahoney, after a
day of casual beer drinking, was tricked that night into drinking
vodka, then allowed by supposed friends to drive away.
   Mahoney could not have made a conscious decision to drive north
in the southbound lanes of I-71, exhibiting the ``extreme
indifference to human life'' that a jury must find to support a
murder or first-degree assault charge, Hildebrand said.
   Nor was it Mahoney's fault that the bus _ its chassis built by
Ford, its body by Sheller-Globe Corp. _ was susceptible to fire in
a collision, Hildebrand said.
   ``Should Larry Mahoney have known ... he was going to hit a
bomb?'' Hildebrand said. He caused the collision, but ``Larry did
not cause the fire, the explosion, the deaths, the injuries,''
Hildebrand said.
   Richwalsky said the defense theory of involuntary intoxication
and a dangerous bus was an ``attempt to mask and cover (Mahoney's)
responsibility.''
   ``Do you think if you drink all day and pour yourself behind the
wheel or your vehicle that something bad isn't going to happen?''
Richwalsky said.
   ``This was a predictable disaster,'' he said. ``Drunk drivers
going the wrong way happen every day. This time, he hit a bus.''
   Richwalsky pressed the jurors for a conviction on each murder
count.
   ``These 27 people are just as dead (as if) they had been shot or
stabbed. They're just as dead from his conduct,'' he said.
   Summers, in an emotional closing argument, said no one ``can do
anything to punish him worse'' than Mahoney already punishes
himself.
   ``Larry has the rest of his life, every waking minute, to
remember this,'' he said. ``The punishment in his heart will never,
never go away.''
   But Richwalsky said Mahoney sought to blame others _ Ford Motor
Co. and his drinking buddies.
   Richwalsky then showed the jury the identification picture on
Mahoney's driver license.
   In the picture, Mahoney wore a cap with a four-word slogan _
``Ride Hard _ Die Hard'' _ and added: ``On that Saturday night, ...
he rode hard. Those people died hard.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>