<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1430EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Britain-ChristmasSales Bjt   12-17 0652</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Christmas Sales, Bjt,0677</SECOND>
<HEAD>Many Scroogy Shoppers in Britain's Stores</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By COTTEN TIMBERLAKE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Britain's 15 percent interest rates are
discouraging shoppers from splurging on Christmas gifts and
threatening the country's retailers with the worst selling season
in nine years.
   Many stores are packed with people, but many seem to be
modern-day Scrooges and aren't buying much. Christmas sales are
patchy.
   A last-minute flurry of purchases is expected, but this won't
salvage the crucial season, experts say.
   ``The vote on this Christmas will be that it was a very poor
Christmas,'' said Nick Bubb, a retail analyst with the investment
firm Morgan Stanley International in London. ``It's going to be
flat.''
   The disappointing pre-Christmas season has prompted many stores
to start slashing prices before Britain's traditional January
sales. Many also likely will defy the law requiring them to close
on Sundays and risk a fine of $1,600 to stay open on the day before
Christmas.
   The poor sales trend reflects a months-long downturn, and it's
bad news for retailers' profits, and their stock prices, which
generally have been depressed on London's Stock Exchange.
   But it's good news for consumers, who are benefiting from sales
in jewelry, consumer electronics, clothing and home furnishings.
   It's also positive for Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher's
Conservative government because slower sales are a sign that its
anti-inflation policy is working.
   ``It's been a bad year. Christmas will make or break some
people,'' said Harry Shepherd, director of the Oxford Street
Association. Oxford Street is London's main shopping street.
   Shepherd said he expects retailers to eke out an overall 1
percent to 2 percent sales gain, but that won't be enough to cover
higher costs.
   ``The Tiffanies of the world appear to be doing OK on the basis
that the very rich will always be rich and the retailers selling
three pairs of knickers for 99 pence are still doing very well.
It's the mass in the middle who are suffering,'' he said.
   Consumer electronics and furniture retailers will be hurt the
most, Bubb predicted.
   Experts agree that trading conditions are tough because of the
higher interest rates, which the government has pushed to an
eight-year peak to fight resurgent inflation. Inflation is running
at an annual rate of 7.7 percent.
   The higher interest rates have squeezed British homeowners, who
mostly hold adjustable rate mortgages and have seen their monthly
payments climb sharply.
   Before the economy began overheating more than 18 months ago,
Britain enjoyed a five-year, steady economic expansion fueled by
consumer demand.
   But growth in consumer spending has slowed from 7 percent in
1988, to an expected 4 percent in 1989, and is predicted to slow to
1 percent in 1990.
   The slowdown has been showing up in the government's retail
sales figures.
   In November, sales declined a sharp 0.8 percent from October,
the government announced recently. That meant sales for the latest
three months rose 1.1 percent over a year ago, the lowest such
growth rate since June 1982, figures from the Central Statistical
Office show.
   The retailers themselves are having to pay the higher interest
rates, and rents are pricey too. Wage costs also are up because
fewer teenage workers are available.
   Although the inflation rate is high, retailers can't raise
prices to enhance their profits, Bubb said.
   Their promotions aren't going to help the bottom line.
   Ratners jewelry stores, for example, are offering the equivalent
of $80 gift vouchers for every $240 worth of sales, while the Tandy
consumer electronics chain has slashed $8 off a radio cassette
player to $48.
   The longer-term outlook is gloomy too.
   The Confederation of British Industry, the country's major
business group, recently said one of its regular surveys showed
that retailers and wholesalers anticipate a deterioration in
business over the coming three months.
   It was the first time since the survey was launched in 1983 that
such a decline was expected.
</TEXT>

</DOC>