<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0203 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0713EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-HostageFamily'sChristmas Adv22-24   12-21 1042</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Hostage Family's Christmas, Adv 22-24,1071</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv22</HEAD>
<HEAD>$adv23</HEAD>
<HEAD>$adv24</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Weekend Editions, Dec. 22-24</HEAD>
<HEAD>First Christmas in America for Wife, Son of Hostage in Lebanon</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos BX2,BX3 of Dec. 20</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE ESPER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MALDEN, Mass (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Like other mothers, Fifi Reed can't give her
son everything he wants for Christmas. She got 9-year-old Tarek his
favorite Transformer robots but his fondest wish is not to be.
   She can't bring his father home.
   ``Christmas was very special for my husband,'' said Mrs. Reed.
This will be the fourth Christmas in captivity for Frank Reed, one
of the eight American hostages in Lebanon.
   ``He would start getting things ready a month ahead of time.
He'd have the Christmas carols on every day and plan on who we're
going to invite. He would cook the turkey himself.''
   For Mrs. Reed, a Syrian national, and Tarek, it is their first
Christmas in America, far from friends and from husband and father.
   ``I miss him a lot,'' said Tarek, who uses the present tense
when relating memories of his father.
   ``He usually sees me when I play with the turtles,'' said Tarek,
referring to his pets. ``We usually walk on the grass and talk.''
   Reed, the American director of the Lebanese International
School, was kidnapped Sept. 9, 1986. Tarek wasn't quite 6 then.
   Now, the boy and his mother plead the case of the hostages
wherever they can, from the Glenwood School where Tarek is in the
third grade to university halls to the White House.
   ``Dear Mr. Bush, please free my father,'' he began a letter to
the president. He signed it, ``Your friend, Tarek Reed.'' His
classmates wore yellow ribbons and wrote similar letters to
President Bush but there has been no reply. Tarek brought in a
9-by-12-inch photo of his father and showed it to his classmates.
   ``That was touching.'' said his teacher, Trudy LaSpina. ``He was
very proud. He was pleased with what we were doing.''
   These are the two faces of Tarek: A boy propelled far beyond his
age trying to face the realities of the civil war in Lebanon (``The
last time when the bombings started, everyone thought it was
thunder,'' he said). A kid in his natural world of fantasy where
toy dinosaurs and robots are the good guys he often talks about in
the games he plays.
   During a religious ceremony, he placed a photo of his father
beneath a ``Tree of Freedom,'' a Christmas tree decorated in memory
of the eight American hostages. In the next instant, while a
private Mass was being said for the hostages in a home, Tarek was
in the next room drawing in a coloring book with 7-year-old
Michael, his newfound friend.
   If anything, Tarek is doing better than his mother in these
painful times. He walks to school alone, something that would have
been unheard of in Beirut. Recently he went around the neighborhood
selling candy bars for a school fund-raiser, astounding his mother.
He's forgotten much of his Arabic.
   ``It's just like he was born here,'' said Mrs. Reed. ``He has
friends. He goes around so sure of himself.''
   But the 38-year-old woman said she is not adjusting well. ``I'm
not young. When you come to a country and you're young, you adjust
easily. ... Everything is so different, the customs, the habits.''
   Mrs. Reed said she is not alive, she is only existing. ``People
tend to think you're fine, you're just as happy as other people
are. But it's not true because we're not. You can pretend to be
happy but deep inside you're not that happy. You want your husband
around and you want the comfort of a family.''
   Mrs. Reed and Tarek came here last summer on vacation but they
stayed when fighting intensified in Beirut and it appeared the
schools there would not open for the fall term. She moved in with
her mother-in-law in Malden and took a job with an insurance
company in Boston, a 30-minute commute.
   As she waits and hopes for her husband's release, her emotions
rise and fall.
   ``There are days when you think it's going to happen and it's
getting close. And there are days when it's just getting out of
hand, it's getting impossible, `Aw come on, come on, come on. What
is going on? Let's do something.'
   ``I'm angry. Who gave them (the captors) the right to do this?
Where's the justice? By what right can the people take somebody's
life and decide they're going to put them in jail? Why?''
   In the midst of these thoughts, she had asked herself, ``How
much more can I take?''
   Jean-Paul Kauffmann, a French journalist who was released by
pro-Iranian Shiite Moslem captors in May 1988, told her about the
treatment of the hostages, and she said it ``just blew my mind.
   ``They'd be blindfolded most of the time. They'd be shoved the
food in a dirty dish under the door a lot of times. If they caught
them talking to each other, they would beat them.''
   She agonizes over how her husband is holding up, the condition
he will be in when he is released. ``How much sanity are they
retaining, being there three years? I don't know. ... Is the person
going to come out normal? Frank is not young. He's 56.''
   The thoughts that race through her mind are not all haunting.
There are the good memories of how they met and married in 1977
when she was in training as a teacher at the International School.
And they were the best of times, as the couple faced together the
objections of her parents because he was American and Protestant
and she was Syrian and Moslem. He later converted to her religion.
   ``We had to try to convince them we wanted to get married. We
were just the right people for each other. This is the time I
remember. We just had a great time together. I used to say, `It's
too nice to be true,' and it was too nice to be true. It ended all
of a sudden.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   George Esper is the AP Northeast regional
reporter, based in Boston.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Dec. 22-24</NOTE>

</DOC>