<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1330EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DrugBalloons     12-17 0426</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Drug Balloons,0438</SECOND>
<HEAD>Anti-Drug Radar Coverage of Entire U.S.-Mexico Border is Near</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto DN1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOEL WILLIAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIO GRANDE CITY, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An anti-drug smuggling project to
create radar coverage along the entire U.S.-Mexico border is nearly
complete, with the last two of six surveillance balloons installed
and undergoing final tests.
   Unavoidable radar scrutiny will stretch from the Pacific Ocean
to the Gulf of Mexico when the two helium-filled aerostats begin
full operation early in 1990 at Eagle Pass and Rio Grande City in
southern Texas, officials said.
   U.S. Customs directs the project and already has radar-equipped
balloons operating at Yuma and Fort Huachuca, Ariz., Deming, N.M.;
and Marfa in West Texas.
   The aerostat at Eagle Pass, southwest of San Antonio, probably
will be fully deployed in two weeks, said Judy Turner, Customs
spokeswoman in Houston.
   Radar testing probably will begin this week at the other site,
north of Rio Grande City in Starr County, said Hood Goodrich, site
manager with contractor General Electric Government Services.
   A rutted dirt road provides the only access to the remote,
treeless base, surrounded by ranches thick with brush and cactus.
   The white, fish-shaped, 241-foot-long aerostat already presents
an imposing sight hovering 50 feet above its base near Rio Grande
City. When placed into duty, expected by the end of March, it will
rise 15,000 feet on its tether and will have a 160-mile tracking
range.
   For federal drug agents, the aerostat system will ease the
frustration of not knowing what flies across the border along the
vast stretches out of the reach of fixed radar installations, Ms.
Turner said.
   ``We would certainly hope that it means less air smuggling, that
the traffickers will be forced to use another method or another
route,'' she said.
   The radar balloons will track planes entering U.S. air space and
feed the data to the federal aviation center in Riverside, Calif.
   ``That gives them the information from which to launch an
interdiction or tracking plane,'' Ms. Turner said.
   Since federal agents began a crackdown in Florida several years
ago, much of the drug traffic, especially cocaine, is believed to
have shifted to the Mexican border.
   Ms. Turner said Customs agents believe a sharp increase in drug
seizures on the ground in Arizona during the past year is related
to the radar balloons there, forcing the drug traffic out of the
air.
   Customs also operates radar aerostats in Florida at Patrick Air
Force Base and Cudjoe Key, and another at Grand Bahama Island. More
are planned along the Gulf Coast.
</TEXT>

</DOC>