<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0133 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1424EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-EastGermany 1stLd-Writethru a0645 12-22 0761</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0645,0780</SECOND>
<HEAD>Brandenburg Gate Opened in Emotional Ceremony</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 6 grafs to include estimate of crowd; picks up 6th
graf ``More than ...''</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BER19</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NESHA STARCEVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tens of thousands of people surged through
two new Berlin Wall openings Friday and celebrated at the
Brandenburg Gate, a monument to German unity that became a symbol
of division when the wall went up in 1961.
   The new passages, immediately north and south of the towering
gate, were opened at 3 p.m. in a ceremony attended by Chancellor
Helmut Kohl of West Germany and the East German premier, Hans
Modrow.
   Berliners rushed through them, back and forth, then uncorked of
champagne and drank to the famous landmark that was sealed inside
East Berlin for 28 years.
   Security on both sides collapsed as the vast crowd broke through
metal barriers and rushed to the gate, filling the vast Paris
Square, where people hugged each other and danced together.
   A sea of people who had waited patiently for hours in
intermittent rain surrounded the 200-year-old sandstone monument.
   West Berlin police said about 30,000 people gathered on the
Western side before the gate was opened. The crowd on the Eastern
side appeared much larger, but there were no official estimates of
its size.
   More than 20 crossings have been cut through the wall since East
Germany opened its borders Nov. 9, but the freeing of the
Brandenburg Gate was the emotional climax of the coming together of
a people divided since the end of World War II.
   In addition to being cut off from West Berliners, the gate also
was inaccessible to East Berliners until Friday because it lay in
the off-limits East German border zone.
   Flags of Berlin, West Germany and East Germany flew above the
huge crowd. Several people who climbed the wall held up a sign
saying ``Come Together.''
   Hundreds of people climbed atop the thick section of wall that
remains directly in front of the gate, dancing and hugging in
chaotic scenes reminiscent of November.
   Kohl called the opening of the gate a ``fantastic thing.''
   He and Modrow met at 3 p.m. on the border, shook hands and
walked together to a platform to address the crowd. They were
nearly mobbed by the exultant crowd.
   National television of both countries broadcast the event.
``This is where the heart of Berlin pounds,'' said a commentator
for the ZDF network of West Germany.
   Modrow said the historic Brandenburg Gate's new function should
be ``to serve the peace.''
   The speeches were drowned out by the mass of people, many with
tears in their eyes, shouting with joy.
   Peter Rebachmann, a 42-year-old East Berliner, said: ``The last
time I was here was as a kid, when I used to play on this very
spot. I never thought I'd come here again; it's really wonderful.''
   ``It's great, but it's too bad my father didn't live to see
it,'' said Hans Achtzehnig, another resident of East Berlin.
   ``What a beautiful Christmas present!'' said a middle-aged woman
who did not give her name.
   Several signs carried by the crowd called for German unity, a
demand made by a growing number of participants in East German
demonstrations.
   ``Berlin, One city, One Nation,'' said one sign.
   People on the eastern side of the wall greeted Kohl with shouts
of ``Helmut! Helmut!'' He and Modrow announced the agreement to
open the gate during a visit Kohl made to East Germany on Tuesday
and Wednesday.
   Thousands of people cheered and set off firecrackers earlier
when East German workers began knocking the new holes in the wall.
   The Brandenburg Gate, its battle-scarred columns are topped with
a bronze chariot of the goddess Victory in a chariot, was the
backdrop for Adolf Hitler's rise to power and his last stand. It
also was where East German workers began an uprising in 1953 that
was crushed by Soviet tanks.
   In East Berlin, the Unter den Linden boulevard ends at the gate.
On the Western side, the avenue that leads to the gate was renamed
June 17, for the date of the uprising.
   Nazi ``brown shirts'' made a triumphant torchlit parade through
the gate when Hitler was named chancellor on Jan. 30, 1933.
   In the final days of World War II, the six-column gate, five
stories high, was badly damaged when Soviet tanks closed in on
Hitler's bunker in the chancellery. It marked the border between
the Soviet and British sectors when the victorious allies divided
Berlin into four sectors.
</TEXT>

</DOC>