<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0163 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2346EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Roger&amp;Me     12-19 0357</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Roger &amp; Me,0366</SECOND>
<HEAD>Controversial GM Documentary Hits Screen Close to Home</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM S. BERGSTROM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BURTON, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ``Roger &amp; Me,'' a documentary about the
devastating effects of General Motors Corp. layoffs in Flint,
preached to the converted Tuesday at its premiere in this
neighboring community.
   Spotlights jabbed snow-filled clouds outside the 14-screen
Showcase Cinemas in Burton, where all 14 screens showed the film
produced, directed by and starring journalist Michael Moore.
   Moore gave away many of the 4,500 premiere tickets at United
Auto Workers union Local 599, where more than 10 percent of its
15,000 members are laid off from GM jobs.
   There were boos and hisses when GM Chairman Roger Smith appeared
on the screen and cheers for UAW President Owen Bieber.
   ``Michael Moore did this town a favor; he gave us a voice in
this world,'' Phil Higgins, 33, a Chevrolet Division metal
fabricator from Flint, said as the crowd filed out.
   ``He hit it right on the head,'' said Steve Cockran, 35, laid
off after 13 years in quality control and production at GM.
   The critically acclaimed film portrays Moore's fruitless efforts
to interview Smith about the elimination of 30,000 GM jobs in Flint
and the resulting evictions and abandonment of entire neighborhoods
in the city.
   GM and city officials have countered that Flint still has 45,000
GM employees, the largest number anywhere.
   Moore said he hoped the film would stir political activism
against sweeping job cuts by a company like GM, which reported $5
billion in profits in 1988.
   ``How 'bout not closing down 10 factories and making only $3
billion?'' he said. ``Can't they be satisfied with that?''
   Moore arrived at the premiere wearing a tweed jacket, open-neck
shirt, blue jeans and sneakers and apologizing about his limousine.
``They made me ride in it,'' he said as he entered the theater
complex to address the cheering crowd.
   ``We wanted to make this film so we can show people what's
happening here,'' Moore said. ``So not only Flint, but the rest of
America would be concerned about the growing gap between rich and
poor these days.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>