<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0130 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1421EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Noriega-Drugs 650   12-22 0648</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Noriega-Drugs, 650</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Searching for Noriega Assets</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Stands for AM-Noriega-Secrecy listed on the AMs digest</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES ROWLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Federal investigators are conducting an
international search for assets they say Manuel Antonio Noriega
amassed from drug trafficking, the Justice Department said Friday.
   Financial documents among records seized by U.S. troops in
Noriega's offices at the Panamanian Defense Forces compound may
help authorities trace assets and bank holdings stashed in foreign
countries, said spokesman David Runkel.
   ``We believe there are assets and we are checking records to
determine where those assets are currently located,'' Runkel said.
`Our concern is for assets resulting from illegal drug trading'' by
Noriega, whom Runkel described ``an international thug.''
   ``The Panamanian government would be interested in assets of Mr.
Noriega which resulted from the looting of the public treasury,''
he said, adding the records may contain such evidence.
   ``We have been in contact with foreign governments and financial
institutions as well as people here'' to trace bank accounts and
other holdings, Runkel said.
   So far, two foreign governments, which Runkel would not
identify, are cooperating. If the documents are useful as evidence,
they will be turned over to federal prosecutors, Runkel said.
   Noriega is accused in two separate U.S. federal indictments of
pocketing $10 million in bribes and drug profits he received in
return for allowing Colombian drug lords to use Panama as a base
for smuggling and money laundering.
   Justice Department officials said the U.S. invasion has
eliminated Panama as a base of operations for the Colombian cartels.
   ``The cartel's mobility is obviously narrowed,'' said Frank
Shults, a spokesman for the Drug Enforcement Administration. ``The
flexibility they have to move large and vast sums of money has been
restricted.''
   Also seized at the compound was 110 pounds of cocaine with an
estimated street value of $1.25 million, the White House said
Friday.
   Meanwhile, officials familiar with the Noriega case say that if
he is captured, he will use his dealings as a CIA informant to try
to scuttle U.S. drug charges against him. However, sources say that
Justice Department prosecutors are confident that the threatened
exposure of intelligence secrets in open court won't hobble the
cases.
   Prosecutors expect Noriega would try to use the same
``graymail'' tactics successfully employed by lawyers for former
White House aide Oliver L. North and other Iran-Contra defendants,
said the sources, who spoke on condition of anonymity.
   Defense lawyers in the Iran-Contra cases won court rulings
requiring the disclosure of secrets the government was unwilling to
release. That resulted in the dismissal of major Iran-Contra
conspiracy charges against North and others.
   The Justice Department has decided Noriega would be prosecuted
first in Miami on charges of helping Colombia's Medellin drug
cartel smuggle cocaine through this country. He also faces federal
charges in Tampa, Fla., of conspiring to smuggle marijuana through
Panama.
   The secrecy issues surrounding Noriega's case were discussed
last week at a meeting held at the Justice Department by
prosecutors and senior officials in the criminal division.
   One official termed the secrecy problems in Noriega's case
``manageable,'' but quickly conceded that Iran-Contra prosecutor
Lawrence E. Walsh probably took the same view of the North case.
   Before Noriega was indicted in 1988, prosecutors consulted with
the CIA and other intelligence agencies, said one government
source. Those agencies posed no objections to proceeding with the
case.
   The government is prepared to offer evidence to refute an
expected claim by Noriega that his alleged drug activities were
sanctioned by the U.S. government because he was a CIA informant,
the source said.
   Prosecutors will argue that just because Noriega may have been
an informant for the CIA or the DEA he is not immune from criminal
prosecution, the source said.
   If convicted of all the charges, Noriega faces a possible
sentence of 145 years in prison and more than $1.1 million in fines.
</TEXT>

</DOC>