<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0090 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1415EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-Vatican Bjt   12-27 0690</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Vatican, Bjt,0714</SECOND>
<HEAD>Vatican Doesn't See How It Can Turn Over Noriega</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FRANCES D'EMILIO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VATICAN CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Vatican on Wednesday said it had not yet
reached a decision about Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega, but it
declared it would not simply push him out of its embassy in Panama
and hand him to U.S. authorities.
   Cuba, Nicaragua and the Dominican Republic have been reported to
be contenders for accepting the ousted Panamanian leader, but
Vatican spokesman Joaquin Navarro said that so far the Holy See had
not contacted any third country.
   ``It's too soon,'' Navarro told a news briefing. He added that
``as of this moment,'' the Vatican has not yet made a decision
about Noriega's bid for asylum status.
   Navarro was pressed repeatedly about Bush administration
assertions that the United States officials forcefully demanded
Noriega be turned over to U.S. authorities so he can be tried on
drug trafficking charges.
   ``The United States has put its case very clearly and with
respect and very cordially,'' Navarro said.
   The Vatican also presented its case ``with the same clarity,''
Navarro said.
   ``Taking into account international law and accepted procedure,
I don't see how the embassy can hand over someone'' to a nation
other than the host country, he said.
   The Vatican spokesman declined to comment on the U.S. criminal
accusations against Noriega.
   But he said, ``he has also been head of government and of the
armed forces. There's something more than a criminal case here.''
   On Wednesday, a Spanish newspaper published an interview with
Guillermo Endara, who was installed as president after the
invasion. Endara, whose election in May was voided when Noriega
seized the ballots, was quoted as saying that Noriega should stand
trial and added: ``Panama cannot permit him to leave the country.''
   Navarro said there had been no request by Panama for Noriega as
of Wednesday morning.
   Despite his estimate that the dilemma could be resolved ``in a
few days, not weeks,'' Navarro offered no evidence that the United
States and the Vatican were close to a solution.
   Noriega has been staying at the Vatican embassy in Panama since
Sunday.
   ``He is not allowed to make telephone calls, not allowed
visits,'' Navarro said. ``He is simply staying'' at the embassy
while his case is debated.
   Navarro said the general, a captain and his wife, and another
Panamanian military officer were allowed to stay after Noriega made
``a very serious commitment to help in easing the situation, the
bloodshed'' in the wake of the U.S. invasion.
   Navarro said it was the papal nuncio, or envoy, who
``autonomously'' decided to give Noriega shelter.
   While Pope John Paul II is not actively involved in the talks he
has been kept informed of the situation, Navarro said.
   The U.S. ambassador to the Holy See, Thomas P. Melady, met
Wednesday with Monsignor Angelo Sodano, a senior Vatican diplomatic
official with expertise in Latin American affairs, Navarro said.
   Navarro expressed hope the case would be resolved to the
satisfaction of both the United States and the Vatican and ``in
accordance with the international right (law) and justice.''
   The Vatican is studying the case in its ``juridical, diplomatic
and humanitarian, and therefore, ethical considerations,'' Navarro
said.
   Seeking to dispel the reports of tense U.S-Vatican relations,
Navarro said the U.S. side had sent a message of appreciation for
Vatican officials' availability during the Christmas religious
festivities.
   Navarro stressed that Noriega's action is seen as part of an
``accepted practice'' in Latin American countries of seeking asylum
in embassies.
   As for cases involving the Vatican, ``no one has ever been
expelled'' from an embassy after seeking asylum, Navarro said.
   He pointed out that just two months ago, the Vatican mission in
Panama City sheltered Endara after he was beaten by Noriega
supporters.
   The late Cardinal Josef Mindszenty took refuge in the U.S.
mission in Budapest after Soviet forces crushed the 1956 Hungarian
uprising. He had been freed earlier from prison by Hungarian
revolutionaries. He had been convicted of treason in 1949 in what
was considered a rigged trial.
   Mindszenty left at the embassy in 1971 under an agreement with
the Vatican.
</TEXT>

</DOC>