<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0943EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-WeaponsPlan 1stLd-Writethru a0425 12-21 0612</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weapons Plan, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0425,620</SECOND>
<HEAD>Scientists Challenge Administration View on Plutonium Needs</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Subs 3rd graf, The Energy Department, with department comment</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United States has plenty of plutonium for
future use in nuclear weapons, and the Bush administration should
drop plans to spend $1 billion to expand supplies of the material,
a government advisory panel concludes.
   The conclusion published Wednesday by a special committee of the
National Research Council contradicts the administration's repeated
assertions to Congress that additional capacity to make
weapon-grade plutonium is vital to national security.
   The Energy Department, which owns the nation's defense nuclear
materials plants, issued a brief statement saying it had not fully
analyzed the document but would respond in detail within 30 days.
It said the report's recommendations ``appear to to fully
consistent with and supportive of'' actions already taken or
planned by the department.
   Former Energy Secretary John Herrington said during the Reagan
administration that the nation is ``awash in plutonium,'' but his
successor, James D. Watkins, had disavowed the statement. Watkins
contends that while current plutonium supplies are adequate, more
capacity will be needed in the coming decade.
   The research council said it saw no good reason either to
produce more virgin plutonium or to increase the capacity for
processing recycled plutonium from old weapons. It also challenged
Watkins' plan to build a $600 million plant in Idaho that would
convert reactor-grade plutonium to weapon-grade material.
   ``The Department of Energy should concentrate on making better
use of existing plutonium processing capacity as required and
postpone plans to construct additional capabilities,'' the report
said.
   Many private arms control groups have long advocated scaling
back plutonium operations.
   ``This is a certification by a semi-official body that you don't
need'' additional plutonium supplies, said David Albright, senior
staff scientist of the Federation of American Scientists.
   The report also criticized some aspects of the Energy
Department's overall management of the weapons complex, which
includes 17 major plants and laboratories in 12 states.
   On the subject of plutonium, the report noted that the United
States already has more than 20,000 nuclear weapons.
   ``The plutonium in these devices, plus that in the supply chain,
is obviously sufficient to supply a nuclear deterrent of the
existing size or even greater,'' it said.
   Official information on nuclear arms materials is classified.
   Watkins has advocated building a Special Isotope Separation
plant at the Idaho National Engineering Laboratory near Idaho
Falls. It would use a new vaporizing technology to convert
reactor-grade plutonium now stored near Richland, Wash., into
plutonium suitable for use in nuclear weapons.
   The scientific panel cited several reasons for scrapping the
Idaho project.
   ``To our knowledge, no compelling need for this material has
been demonstrated,'' its report said.
   It also said the Idaho facility, if built, could complicate
international efforts to limit the spread of nuclear arms. The new
isotope separation technology could be obtained by other countries
to convert fuel used in civilian nuclear reactors into high-grade
plutonium needed to build nuclear bombs, it said.
   John Spratt, D-S.C., chairman of a special House committee on
defense nuclear facilities, said in a telephone interview that the
report's conclusion about plutonium supplies, combined with
congressional resistance to adding more capacity, make it ``very
unlikely that the Special Isotope Separation plant will be built.''
   The report also said the Energy Department should drop plans to
spend $400 million renovating a building at the Rocky Flats plant
near Denver that recycles scrap plutonium into weapons-grade
material.
   The research council is an arm of the National Academy of
Sciences, a congressionally chartered group that conducts special
research at the request of the government.
</TEXT>

</DOC>