<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 0450EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Korea     12-31 0504</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Korea,0520</SECOND>
<HEAD>Legislators Jeer As Ex-President Chun Testifies</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By C.W. LIM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lawmakers hissed, jeered, shouted and
yelled Sunday during the long-awaited testimony of disgraced former
president Chun Doo-hwan as he testified in Parliament after 13
months in self-imposed exile.
   ``Is killing innocent people an exercise in self-defense?''
yelled opposition lawmakers when Chun denied involvement in a 1980
civil uprising.
   Kim Young-bae, a national opposition legislator, marched to a
microphone and said for hundreds of thousands to hear on
television, ``The contents of his testimony and attitude are
incurring the wrath of the people.''
   Kim Dae-jung, a two-time presidential candidate and opposition
party leader who was sentenced to death under Chun's rule for
alleged sedition, was among 200 legislators and spectators at the
National Assembly.
   President Roh Tae-woo appealed to citizens in a New Year's
message Sunday ``to put an end to past affairs once the past
president apologizes for wrong-doings.''
   But by mid-afternoon, newspapers and television stations said
they were flooded with calls protesting Chun's testimony as
disappointing and angry that he had not apologized. The committee
chairman said political party offices also had been deluged by
angry telephone callers.
   Chun returned to Seoul from a remote Buddhist temple early
Sunday to testify on alleged corruption, human rights abuses and
misconduct during his seven years in office that ended in early
1988.
   There have been widespread public demands to make the truth
known about alleged misdeeds of Chun's authoritarian rule to clear
the way for more open government and more democratic reform.
   Thousands of riot police were deployed around the Parliament
building and in nearby streets to prevent attacks by radicals and
students who have staged violent demonstrations demanding Chun be
arrested and punished, but there were no clashes.
   Chun, a former general, took power with military backing in
1980. He has denied any personal corruption but 48 of his friends
and relatives have been tried and convicted of embezzlement and
other crimes.
   The 58-year-old Chun, looking somber, occasionally biting his
tongue and growing more weary as the hearings went on into the
night, said ``the president of a nation is bound to take unlimited
responsibility for the state of affairs during his tenure.''
   Chun did not make an outright apology, as some politicans have
demanded, but said he would take ``moral responsibility'' for
misdeeds under his administration. ``I didn't do anything wrong,''
Chun said.
   Legislators were outraged when Chun said he had not been
involved in the uprising which left 200 dead and at least 1,500
people injured in the southern city of Kwangju. Chun said he was
out of line of command.
   ``Marshall law authorities at that time gave troops on the scene
the discretion to open fire if they faced a war situation,'' he
said.
   ``Testify! Testify!'' lawmakers shouted.
   Some opposition leaders believe the Kwangju incident was a
scheme by Chun and his associates to seize power in the chaotic
days that followed the assassination of President Park Chung-hee in
late 1979.
</TEXT>

</DOC>