<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0113EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Germany-Christmas     12-22 1028</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Germany-Christmas,1058</SECOND>
<HEAD>Still Divided in Spirit, Berliners Count Mixed Christmas Blessings</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Friday AMs report.</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAROL J. WILLIAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It would seem at first glance that Lille
Berger has much to be thankful for this Christmas.
   An amnesty for political prisoners has freed her younger son,
and the parting of the Berlin Wall has brought home the older one
she feared she'd never see after his escape to the West in July.
   Like many East Germans, Mrs. Berger is grateful for the first
fruits of reform that have eased a life of torment and allowed a
holiday reunion of her family.
   But the division of Germany now runs through her heart, with one
son lost to a new life in Hamburg and the other committed to the
revolt for change at home.
   ``I have nothing to be happy about this Christmas,'' said Mrs.
Berger, whose lined face and red-rimmed eyes testify to 53 years of
hardship and worry. ``For me, this year has been like 1945.
Everything in my life has been ruined.''
   Despite the heartening hurtle toward democracy that has
engendered new hope for a united Berlin, an atmosphere of anxiety
pervades both sides of the city deeply scarred by four decades of
division.
   Christmas and the approaching new year are a time for
reflection, and burdened and preoccupied Berliners this year are
counting mixed blessing.
   A glittering consumer wonderland has danced before the eyes of
millions now free to travel West, to see what they cannot yet have.
   Champagne celebrations and the euphoric street party that
erupted when the wall fell on Nov. 9 have given way to West Berlin
resentment of the daily invasions of frustrated consumers.
   ``My daughter is a physician who earns a good salary and has
everything our life has to offer. But she says she feels like a
second-class citizen when she comes here,'' said Maria Schwage, 74,
of Dresden, who was shopping with her grandson at West Berlin's
famed Ka-De-We department store.
   ``As a pensioner I was able to travel before the reforms, and I
must say the atmosphere is now very different,'' she said.
   No East German visitor can miss the discouraging glance of the
red-haired hostess passing out Christmas cake nibbles as inducement
to buy gourmet ``baumkuchen'' for $17, a fortune in the eyes of
most East Germans.
   Cheap goods like $5 umbrellas and fake gold necklaces have been
relegated to sidewalk sales bins, encouraging the crowds of
cash-short East Germans to do their window shopping outside.
   Little remains for the holiday season of West Berliners' spirit
of sharing that choked millions with emotion seven weeks ago, when
Stalinist bounds were broken by the forces for freedom.
   ``There is a lot of dissatisfaction over the hectic nature of
this Christmas,'' said Ziegfried Kasper, a West Berlin cab driver
born in a far corner of the former German empire in what is now
Soviet Russia.
   ``As an immigrant myself, I feel empathy for those coming
over,'' Kasper added. ``But this is not the kind of reunification
many people expected.''
   East and West Berlin have been released from forced division,
but their differences remain apparent and will take years to
overcome.
   West Berlin is awash in light and bustle, its neon-flanked
shopping boulevards strewn with fresh evergreens, its light
standards beribboned in red, gold and green.
   Handmade ornaments are hawked from rustic wooden booths at the
central Christmas market and an aroma of plenty fills the damp,
cold air, pungent with hot-spiced wine and sizzling sausages.
   Along East Berlin's Karl Marx Allee, a monotony of white lights
illuminates the grime of the coal-dusted city that is ominously
quiet in the last days before Christmas.
   Poorly stocked stores are being spurned this year by a people
set free on the West, and political turmoil has cast a shadow of
uncertainty over the very survival of the East German nation.
   ``What I feel mostly is fear,'' said Ursula Engel, a
well-traveled researcher for Leipzig's Institute for Foreign
Studies. ``No one knows where we are going, yet we are racing ahead
with all speed.``
   With the breaching of the wall a bitterness has been loosed
among many of the middle-aged, who have sacrificed their prime
years to a socialist system now being swept into the scrapheap of
history.
   ``No one can give me my life back,'' said Gabriela Kleiner, 42,
a translator of Russian novels who expects little improvement
during her lifetime. ``We have hope for the future, but this will
be enjoyed only by our children and grandchildren.''
   Hope tempered by uncertainty rides higher with the very young,
who have time on their side in the long struggle for prosperity.
And the elderly who have lived through the Nazi period and 40 years
of socialism have little fear of what democracy could have in store
for them.
   Sylvia Deutschmann, 26, a file clerk and mother of two, hasn't
spent much time thinking about the consequences of the reform
movement dominating East German politics and the media.
   ``We're all hopeful that conditions will change for the
better,'' she said, perusing the slim pickings of her neighborhood
grocer's at a grimy corner on Krausnickstrasse. ``But for now life
goes on as normal. I still have to get the kids fed and to bed each
night.''
   Like many young East Berliners, the Deutschmanns have made their
pre-Christmas trek to West Berlin to collect the $55 per person of
``welcome money'' from the West German government.
   The radio and leather fashions bought with the handout may make
their holiday a little brighter. But the drudgery of making ends
meet on small incomes in a ravaged economy will confront them with
reality soon after the start of the new year.
   ``No one would dispute that our lives are better now. We
suffered for 40 years,'' said Kostina Hoeft, an East Berlin
scientist watching workers prepare to cut a new hole in the wall
near the symbolic Brandenburg Gate.
   ``I think we are patient enough to wait through the next hard
years of recovery,'' she said. ``For those who have nothing there
is always hope.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>