<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0184 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0728EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-Japan-Markets     12-26 0381</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Japan-Markets,0397</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stocks Post Record High, Dollar Lower</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Tokyo Stock Exchange's key index closed at yet
another record high today, while the dollar edged down against the
Japanese yen for the fourth consecutive trading day.
   The Nikkei Stock Average of 225 selected issues gained 257.69
points, or 0.67 percent, closing at 38,681.31. The previous record
closing was 38,586.18, set on Dec. 18.
   The dollar closed at 142.37 yen, down 0.35 yen from Monday's
finish of 142.72 yen. It opened at 142.94 yen and ranged between
142.30 yen and 142.95 yen.
   The dollar now has fallen 1.86 yen in the last four trading days.
   Currency trading was inactive as the New York, London and some
other overseas markets were closed for Christmas. An estimated
$4.14 billion traded hands in spot trading.
   The dollar fell in Tokyo on profit-taking and small position
adjustments, traders said.
   Minori Takeuchi, a trader with Chemical Bank in Tokyo, said,
``The yen strengthened despite dollar-buying by some participants
who had taken short dollar positions following yesterday's (central
bank) discount rate hike.''
   Overall, she added, ``there was little incentive to buy the
dollar. ... In the long run, the discount rate hike will make the
yen stronger.''
   The Bank of Japan raised the discount rate, the interest rate it
charges for loans to commercial banks, to 4.25 percent from the
previous 3.75 percent. Higher interest rates usually make a
country's currency more attractive to investors.
   On the stock exchange, the Nikkei, which had lost more than 341
points after last Tuesday's discount rate rumor, climbed more than
640 points in this week's first two days.
   While interest-rate increases usually dampen stock investment,
dealers said the index rose because many investors felt the bank's
action removed a major cause of uncertainty.
   Kazuyuki Suzuki, a dealer with Daiwa Securities Co., said, ``The
market reacted to the hike positively because of the timing and the
amount of the hike, which was exactly what the market had
expected.''
   The index's rise slowed in the afternoon as buying in
anticipation of higher prices was offset by selling to take
profits, he said.
   Trading was moderate, with an estimated 600 million shares
changing hands on the first section, up from Monday's 500 million.
Among gainers were machinery and electrical issues.
</TEXT>

</DOC>