<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0140EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-Stealth     12-29 0520</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Stealth,0537</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stealth Bomber Lights the Sky</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A thunderous roar and a huge light
filled the sky at the Panamanian base in Rio Hato. The building
rattled and shook.
   Pedro, who thought he had too much to drink, later found out he
was on the receiving end of the first attack by a U.S. Stealth
fighter jet.
   ``I was sleeping with this bottle of dry rum,'' said Pedro, a
civilian contractor with the Panamanian Defense Forces. ``I woke
trying to figure out what was causing the commotion, the rum or
something else.
   ``Everybody was running around. Nobody seemed to know what to do
which was kind of strange for a bunch of soldiers who supposedly
were expecting a U.S. invasion.''
   It was Dec. 20, just before 1 a.m., and Pedro was spending the
night at the base in Rio Hato, 80 miles southwest of Panama City.
   What he saw was part of a coordinated attack to dismantle the
regime of military strongman Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   A unit of the U.S. Army 82nd Airborne Division was dropping in
to capture the Panamanian base, and the new supersonic Stealth
F-117 had dropped two 2,000-pound bombs nearby in an effort to stun
the base's defenders.
   The building where he was sleeping shook and it ``felt like the
plane was passing just over the building,'' said Pedro, who was
later captured by the invading U.S. troops.
   He was released within a few days and spoke to The Associated
Press on Thursday on the condition he not be further identified for
fear of reprisals.
   Secretary of Defense Dick Cheney acknowledged last week the use
of the Stealth fighters in the Panama invasion. The U.S. military
said the F-117 was used because it can bomb accurately and that
2,000-pound weapons were dropped to ``stun and disorient.''
   They did.
   ``They were experimenting with us, I guess,'' Pedro laughed.
   ``We were disoriented. I looked outside. It was almost a full
moon and I could see the shapes of the paratroopers coming down.
Then the sky lit up and the helicopters started shooting up the
place.
   ``We grabbed weapons and went out toward the woods. We saw the
Cobra helicopters firing and flying over the area. Then the
soldiers would come in and use loudspeakers to ask people to
surrender.
   ``We came back closer to the barracks and all of a sudden I
heard Americans saying we were there. They must have spotted us
somehow.
   ``I was between the commander and the sergeant and the soldiers.
I started moving and all of a sudden I was almost face to face with
a soldier. I told him `I give up, don't kill me. I am a civilian.'
''
   ``Then they tied me up. I spent the next 12 hours with the other
prisoners ... Then they moved us to Howard Air Base in Panama and
the civilians were separated and we were treated a lot better.''
   ``I cannot complain,'' he ended. ``They even gave me some oxygen
when I suffered an emphysema attack.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>