<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0111 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1312EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Economy     12-22 0513</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Economy,500</SECOND>
<HEAD>Durable Goods Orders Suggest Economy Can Avoid Recession</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN D. McCLAIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Orders to U.S. factories for durable goods
posted the sharpest gain in a year last month, the government said
Friday in a report that analysts said suggests the economy can
avoid a recession.
   ``It's Merry Christmas to the economy,'' said Robert Brusca,
chief financial economist at Nikko Securities Co. Intl. in New
York. ``This report suggests there's more life in the economy than
a lot of people thought.''
   The Commerce Department report of a 5.1 percent jump in durable
goods orders ``shows that reports of an economic demise are
premature,'' added William K. MacReynolds, forecasting director for
the U.S. Chamber of Commerce.
   Orders for durable goods _ ``big-ticket'' items expected to last
more than three years _ increased to a seasonally adjusted $130.7
billion last month after dropping 0.7 percent in October and 1.2
percent in September.
   The gain in orders was spread through all categories and was the
largest since a 7.4 percent jump last December. It averted the
first three-month decline since 1986.
   Brusca said there still are weak spots in the economy, but
added: ``I think we have to really distinguish between saying the
economy is weak and saying it is weakening. I think we can say the
economy is weak, but those who say it is still weakening are
holding on too long to an old forecast.''
   He said the economy apparently hit a trough in late summer,
brought down by high interest rates initiated by the Federal
Reserve to fight inflation. As inflation moderated, the central
bank has gradually permitted short-term rates to drop including a
quarter percentage point this week.
   MacReynolds said the new orders will lead to increased
production in the manufacturing sector of the economy which has
been particularly hard hit by the credit pinch.
   The closely watched non-defense capital goods sector rose 8.3
percent last month to $39 billion, the largest gain since a 10.1
percent increase last December. Economists use this category as a
barometer of business investment plans.
   Transportation orders posted the largest gain in the civilian
category, 10.5 percent to $36.7 billion after rising 2.1 percent in
October. Both aircraft and motor vehicles showed large increases,
the department said, surprising some in view of plummeting
automobile sales since the new models were introduced in October.
   Excluding transportation, durable goods orders would have risen
3.1 percent last month.
   Orders for electrical machinery jumped 7.9 percent to $21.7
billion, virtually all in communications equipment.
   Non-electrical machinery orders, including computers and a wide
variety of industrial equipment, rose 6.6 percent to $22.9 billion
after a 4.7 decline in October.
   Orders for primary metals were up 1.7 percent to $22.1 billion
after a 3.4 percent decrease in October.
   Defense orders rose 15.6 percent to $11.2 billion after a 9.1
percent decline the previous month. Excluding this volatile
category, orders would have gained 4.2 percent in November.
   Shipments of durable goods in November rose 1.5 percent to
$123.7 billion after a 3.1 decline in October.
</TEXT>

</DOC>