<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0162 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1859EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-BushText     12-18 0778</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Bush Text,5th Add, a0650-a0657-a0666-a0678-a0680,650</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHN: so short (</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   BUSH: It's because I'm on the move. I want to keep going.
   Q: If anyone is hurt, will you take responsibility?
   BUSH: Just look over your shoulder. Somebody may be following
you. What?
   Q: Will you be responsible if anyone is hurt? Not you per se. I
mean, you seem to be guaranteed in your security. But there are a
lot of people who have to travel with you.
   BUSH: What we ought to do is arrange for them to have their
local stringers cover it. Give the local guys a chance.
   Q: There's no such thing. You know there's no such thing.
   BUSH: Give them an opportunity.
   Q: You don't know our business if you think we have stringers in
Cartagena. (Laughter.)
   BUSH: You have no coverage coming out ot Colombia?
   Q: We don't have a reporter planted in every _ you know you have
the whole support staff going with you.
   BUSH: But what do you think? Let's have a little OFF THE RECORD
discussion.
   (DISCUSSION.)
   Q: Noriega says that he's in _ that Panama is in a state of war
with the United States. I know we're not in a state of war with
Panama, obviously, but do you consider the United States in a state
of war with Noriega?
   BUSH: That's technical. But I've taken note of the statement.
   Q: And how do you respond to it?
   BUSH: I respond to it _ go to answered question 3BUSH:
(Laughter.)
   Q: So that means no state of war?
   BUSH: You're asked _ your follow-up to her question.
   Q: There is a state of war? What do you think about it?
   BUSH: I've told you what I think about it.
   MR. FITZWATER: Let's go.
   Q: What do you think you've learned the most in this last year?
Was it that you have a responsibility that is more _ I mean, you
act differently now in decision-making?
   BUSH: I think some of what I learned is what I mentioned to Mike
in that long soliloquy. You've got to get the best information you
can. We've got a good team. Take that information onboard, make a
decision, and then _ you know, if you mess it up, say, look I was
wrong. And if you _ but not worry if you draw a little flak; that
just goes with the territory. But I don't want to be in the
position, and I will never be, as long as I am in this job, of the
hand-wringing position of, oh, this is the loneliest job in the
world, and no one understands. It isn't. It's not lonely. We've got
a lot of good support, and so I think you're right _ kind of
fingering that area is something I've learned. Listen, do your
best. I learned that from my mother.
   But as Russell Baker's mother used to say, pull yourself up by
your bootstraps. My mother said, just do your very best. And as
long as I can give that to the American people and act in a prudent
_ not a reckless, but prudent way, knowledgeable way on events,
don't worry about it if everybody doesn't agree. All those people
are telling you that _ expressing some concern about China, fine.
I've got to do what I think is right, and that's what I think I was
elected to do.
   Q: Sounds Trumanesque.
   BUSH: And we'll see how it plays out. We'll see how it works
out. And I'm very confident. So I end the year with more confidence
than I started it, but I hope not arrogance or overconfidence.
   Q: Thank you.
   BUSH: Merry Christmas and a Happy New Year to every little snow
bunny.
   Q _ bed?
   BUSH: Yes, I just can't get rid of this laryngitis. You get a
little tired. I got a little dragged out after that trip down there
because it was so hot at that press conference.
   Q: Was that a problem to communicate with Mr. Mitterrand there?
Any problems communicating with Mr. Mitterrand?
   BUSH: No. It was a very good meeting. Good, strong relationship
where you can discuss differences in private. Don't ask what they
were, Terry. (Laughter.)
   Q: You just planted it.
   Q _ laryngitis the second time this year _
   BUSH: Right after the Inauguration. Remember?
   Q: Remember when you went down to Virginia?
   BUSH: That was more of a flu. That was more of a flu. This, I
don't feel like that.
   Q: You're not going to use a semiautomatic on the quails, are
you? (Laughter.)
   THE PRESS: Thank you.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END BUSH TEXT _ 6 Takes</NOTE>

</DOC>