<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0116 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1925EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Noriega-LastAct 1stLd-Writethru a0660 12-26 0542</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Noriega-Last Act, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0660,0554</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Says Noriega Drove in Circles After Invasion</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: ADDS one graf on U.S. report other Noriega associates also went
to the embassy that day</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, AM-Panama-Military</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DORALISA PILARTE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>QUARRY HEIGHTS, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega
probably went by himself to the Vatican Embassy and decided to seek
asylum after his aides abandoned him or were arrested, the U.S.
Southern Command said Tuesday.
   It said Noriega was never in charge of his Defense Forces after
the U.S. invasion on Dec. 20 and did not contact any of its members
for fear of a trap. During the fighting, military spokesmen had
said the resistance was centrally directed and Noriega was involved.
   In a brief communique released to reporters, Southern Command
gave an account of Noriega's time after the invasion based on what
it said were interviews with his cronies.
   Noriega at one point considered ``fleeing to the mountains to
mount an insurgent attack, but he was concerned about his heart
while living in difficult terrain without the opulent luxuries and
intensive medical care'' to which he had become accustomed,
according to the communique.
   It quoted aides who were interviewed as saying Noriega wore red
underwear to ward off the ``evil eye.''
   The communique said that before the invasion, Noriega had
dismissed the possibility of an attack by U.S. troops and was in
Colon, 50 miles north of Panama City, inspecting a new military
facility.
   ``He was aware of increased U.S. force activities but discounted
the notion of an attack, passing the increased activity off as more
U.S. posturing,'' the communique said.
   It said that about 6 p.m. on Dec. 19, he was dropped off at a
Panamanian Defense Forces club in Tocumen near the Omar Torrijos
airport.
   ``There he was provided a prostitute by one of his aides _
apparently a routine occurrence,'' it said.
   When Tocumen was attacked about 1 a.m., Noriega left the club
and evaded U.S. forces by driving around Panama City, according to
the communique.
   Southern Command said Noriega's first telephone call after the
invasion was to his mistress, Vicky Amado, and that he never tried
to contact his wife, Felicidad.
   It said Noriega was ``agitated'' and spent the days at various
locations, mostly at the home of relatives of his private
secretary, Marcella Tason.
   His supporters tried to make him leave town but he refused, it
said.
   It added that at one point, Noriega was believed to have
contacted the Cuban ambassador and considered going to Cuba's
embassy but backed off because the compound was surrounded by U.S.
troops.
   The Bush administration had set a $1 million bounty for Noriega.
   Southern Command said Noriega decided to go ``single-handed'' to
the Vatican Embassy after one of his commanders, Luis del Cid,
surrendered to U.S. forces in David, 200 miles west of Panama City.
Del Cid was indicted in 1988 along with Noriega on drug trafficking
charges. He was flown to Miami Monday.
   Other people were seen entering the Vatican Embassy at various
times on the same day Noriega went there. Justice Department
spokesman David Runkel said Tuesday in Washington that ``10
associate thugs'' of Noriega sought asylum Sunday afternoon at the
embassy, the Papal Nunciature.
</TEXT>

</DOC>