<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 0036EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Deaths 1stLd-Writethru a0589 12-31 0632</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Deaths, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0589,0654</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eds: ADDS Thomas, Cunningham obits; AMs separate on Pirosh moved
as a0520, on Thomas as a0591.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>Robert Pirosh</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SANTA MONICA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Robert Pirosh, whose 1949 screenplay
``Battleground'' won an Academy Award and who co-wrote the Marx
Brothers' classic ``A Day at the Races,'' died Monday of heart
failure. He was 79.
   Priosh, who wrote, produced or directed a dozen well-known films
and a similar number of television series, remained active through
his later years, most recently teaching writing at the University
of Southern California.
   His 1949 Oscar-winning drama was based on the fighting between
German and Allied troops at the Battle of the Bulge, where he
fought with the 320th Infantry in the 35th Division at Bastogne,
Belgium.
   He was writer or co-writer of the films ``A Day at the Races'';
``I Married a Witch''; ``Hell Is for Heroes''; ``A Gathering of
Eagles''; ``What's So Bad About Feeling Good?''; ``Go for Broke,''
and many more.
   As a TV writer, he wrote the pilot programs for ``Laramie'' and
``Combat.'' He also wrote segments of ``Hawaii Five-O,'' ``Ellery
Queen,'' ``Mannix,'' ``Bonanza,'' ``Ironside,'' ``The Waltons'' and
``Barnaby Jones,'' among others.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>J. Wilcox Dunn</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIRGINIA BEACH, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   J. Willcox Dunn, a retired newspaper
editor and publisher who crusaded against gambling, died Friday. He
was 91.
   Dunn, a native of Suffolk, in 1952, established the weekly
Princess Anne Free Press, serving Virginia Beach and Princess Anne
County. He was its editor, publisher and sole owner until he ceased
its publication on retiring in 1962.
   In 1958, Dunn was awarded the national Elijah Parish Lovejoy
Award for Courage in Journalism for his opposition to political
corruption and racketeering in the region.
   He received his law degree from the University of Virginia in
1922. He practiced law in Lynchburg and worked for Union Carbide in
New York City before moving to Virginia Beach in 1936, where he
entered the real estate business.
   In 1935 he married Lelia Baker Taylor of Norfolk. His wife died
in 1962.
   Survivors include a daughter, Margaret T. Dunn of
Charlottesville; a son, Joseph W. Dunn Jr. of Virginia Beach; two
sisters, Mary D. Wallace of Richmond and Martha D. Lyon of Warren,
Mich.; and three grandchildren.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Thomas Cunningham</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LLANO, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thomas Harold ``Hal'' Cunningham, the
retired editor and publisher of the Llano News and a former
president of the Texas Press Association, died Saturday of cardiac
arrest. He was 81.
   A native of Henrietta, Texas, he earned his bachelor's and
master's degrees in journalism at the University of Texas in Austin.
   After managing Camp LaJunta in Hunt, Texas, in the late 1940s
and early '50s, Cunningham in 1954 became news editor of the
Kerrville Mountain Sun, a post he held for five years before
purchasing the Llano News, a weekly which he published for 25
years. He retired in 1983.
   Cunningham served as president of the state Texas Press
Association from 1982-83.
   Cunningham is survived by his wife, Hazel Cunningham of Llano,
and a nephew.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Madoline Thomas</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actress Madoline Thomas, a veteran of the National
Theater and the Royal Shakespeare Company, died Saturday, three
days before her 100th birthday.
   Miss Thomas had been in a hospital in Weston-super-Mare, on
England's west coast, for more than a week after breaking her hip
in a fall at the nursing home where she had lived for three years,
the British news agency said.
   Born in Abergavenny, South Wales, Miss Thomas spent six seasons
with the Royal Shakespeare Company at Stratford-on-Avon, notably in
``Wars of the Roses,'' and five years at the National.
   In 1982, when she was 92, she appeared in National's ``Uncle
Vanya,'' directed by Sir Peter Hall. Her West End appearances
included ``The Mousetrap'' and ``Three Sisters.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>