<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0301EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Panama-Noriega     12-29 0544</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Noriega,0562</SECOND>
<HEAD>Noriega's Mystique Lives on in Chorrillo</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DORALISA PILARTE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Neighbors of Manuel Antonio Noriega's
former military headquarters say he can turn himself into a snake
or a bird, so they warn U.S. troops ringing the Vatican embassy to
keep a close watch.
   Noriega's mystique as a ``brujo,'' or warlock, survives even
though he was toppled by U.S. invaders and remained holed up in the
embassy. Noriega practiced santeria, a cult that mixes African,
Roman Catholic and American Indian deities and sometimes involves
animal sacrifice.
   ``That man is the devil,'' said a young woman in the poor
neighborhood of El Chorrillo, a few blocks from the ruins of
Noriega's Comandancia headquarters.
   ``They better watch him. I don't want him to escape. He can turn
himself into a boa or a dove and escape from the gringos,'' she
said.
   The woman spoke as she stood in a line for food handouts. Other
housewives nodded earnestly at her remark.
   It had been said that Noriega felt secure having the Comandancia
in El Chorrillo because he believed Panama's poor solidly supported
his nationalism.
   But the women interviewed Thursday disputed that belief and said
they would not feel safe while Noriega remained out of U.S. hands.
   ``We didn't want his dictatorship anymore because he was
bringing in communism,'' said one woman. ``Any Panamanian who did
not agree with him, he would kick them out of their jobs and throw
them in jail. He only had a bunch of thugs working for him.''
   The women refused to give their names as they awaited food bags
distributed by the U.S. military that included rice, cooking oil,
sugar, infant formula and canned goods.
   The U.S. attack on the Comandancia destroyed several blocks of
Chorrillo, but many in line said they did not feel bitter.
   ``The gringos are helping us,'' said one housewife. ``There's
few grocery stores that are open. The Dignity Batallions stole
everything,'' she said in reference to a paramilitary group of
Noriega loyalists.
   The women said they did not want Noriega handed over to the new
Panamanian government. The former strongman sought refuge at the
Vatican embassy on Sunday.
   ``They'll treat him too soft,'' said one. ``There's lots of
Noriega's friends who now are hurrying up to get in the good graces
of the new government. But just wait until the gringos leave. It
could start again.''
   Another said the best solution would to turn Noriega over to the
United States to be tried on drug-trafficking charges.
   ``I don't want that beast in Panama,'' she said. ``We forgive
him, but let the gringos take him away all the same. I'll feel safe
the day I hear he's out of Panama.''
   As a reporter departed, one woman ran up and asked: ``Can you
take this to President Bush?''
   Inside a folder was a handwritten letter on white paper thanking
Bush for the invasion. The letter, dated Dec. 26, had been signed
by 31 people, mostly women from El Chorrillo.
   ``Hallellujah,'' the letter said. ``The communists of Panama and
the internationalists preach the self-determination of the people,
(but) they don't respect it. But (for) the self-determination of
the people of Panama (we) give you thanks for liberating us.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>