<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0208EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-FarmScene     12-29 0738</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Farm Scene,730</SECOND>
<HEAD>Beef vs. Chicken: Preference Level Depends on the Bones</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Beef continues to be No. 1 with American
consumers over chicken, but that is only when the Agriculture
Department doesn't count bones.
   The USDA estimates per capita meat and poultry consumption in
several ways, including the retail weight sold at grocery counters,
and on a retail weight basis without bones.
   If it's the National Cattlemen's Association on an
end-of-the-year campaign to boost beef, the no-bone way is favored.
   Regardless, the association said Thursday that demand for beef
is stabilizing after declining for years. And part of the reason is
that farmers and ranchers have responded to consumer tastes by
producing leaner cuts.
   Looking ahead to 1990, industry leaders said little change is
expected in average per capita beef supplies and average consumer
prices in the coming year.
   According to USDA economists, total beef output may increase
slightly next year but still will remain below production levels in
the 1983-88 period. However, consumer prices are expected to edge
higher by only 1 percent to 2 percent in 1990, compared with 5
percent gains in 1988 and 1989.
   The USDA has figures to prove Americans eat more poultry than
beef. And other figures to prove they eat more beef than poultry.
   Using the method based on bone-in retail weights, USDA says the
per capita consumption of beef in 1990 may drop slightly to an
average of 67.8 pounds from 68.6 pounds in 1989, 72.1 pounds in
1988, and 73.4 pounds in 1987. The peak was 94 pounds in 1976.
   Total poultry, which includes broilers, baking hens and turkeys,
has been setting records annually and is forecast to average 89.4
pounds in 1990, up from 84.4 in 1989, 80.6 in 1988, and 77.8 in
1987, the year when poultry first nudged ahead of beef.
   But the cattle industry said that if you take away the bones,
beef is still way ahead of poultry, and Richard Stillman of USDA's
Economic Research Service agreed.
   Stillman said that on a boneless basis, 1989 per capita beef
consumption may average 67.1 pounds, down from 68.2 in 1988. A
further slight decline is expected in 1990.
   On the same boneless basis, he said, 1989 poultry consumption
may average 59.9 pounds, up from 57.2 pounds in 1988, with another
gain in the works next year.
   Cattle industry leader John Lacey of Paso Robles, Calif.,
president-elect of the National Cattlemen's Association, said the
practice of cutting away fat from retail cuts has helped improve
beef's image. He also cited breeding and feeding advances as
further boosts for the industry.
   Topper Thorpe, general manager of Cattle-Fax, a market
information service, said no dramatic changes are expected in the
nation's cattle herd or in U.S. beef production in 1990.
   But today's total cattle herd of about 100 million head,
including dairy animals, is producing almost as much beef as the
much larger herds of the 1970s, Thorpe told a year-end news
conference.
   Cattle herds peaked at about 132 million head in the mid-1970s
and generally have trended downward because of oversupply, rising
production costs, drought and other factors. Thorpe said the herd
liquidation has ended and a ``modest expansion'' has begun.
   ``Efficient cow-calf operators have made profits during the past
few years,'' Thorpe said. ``Now, if weather is favorable and if
financing becomes cheaper, more producers may hold back heifers and
expand their breeding herds. However, we do not see foresee rapid
expansion.''
   Stillman said in a telephone interview, ``Part of the reason
beef has been declining the last several years was that we've
corrected (the statistics) to allow for a closer trim on retail
cuts.''
   The main reason that today's smaller cattle herd produces almost
as much beef is due to a number of factors, he said.
   ``Genetically, you bred a larger animal,'' Stillman said. ``It's
true in hogs, sheep and lambs ... basically, it's feeding, an
increase in average weights.''
   At last month's USDA outlook conference, economist Steve Reed
said consumer beef prices have set new records each year since
1987. But competition from pork and poultry will have an effect.
   ``With per capita beef supplies beginning to stabilize in 1990,
the higher price of beef compared to competing meats could become a
bigger issue in the coming months,'' Reed said. ``These large
poultry supplies and continued large pork supplies could hold down
beef price gains.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>