<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0121 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1343EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-College-Languages     12-20 0412</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-College-Languages,380</SECOND>
<HEAD>Study Calls For Greater Teaching of Non-European Languages</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By W. DALE NELSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Although Japanese is the most rapidly growing
foreign language course on American college campuses, a major
national program is needed to offer non-European languages to more
students, said a study released Wednesday.
   The study, conducted by Johns Hopkins University foreign
language specialist Richard D. Lambert for the American Council on
Education, said traditional West European languages are still the
heavy favorites among university students.
   The study showed 20.4 percent of college students were studying
Spanish, 16.8 percent French and 7.1 percent German in 1986 at 13
institutions surveyed. Italian was the choice of 2.4 percent and
Russian the choice of 1.8 percent of university students surveyed.
   Japanese was picked by 2.2 percent of the students at 11
universities that offered it but ``has tripled in the last three or
four years,'' Lambert told a news conference.
   ``I was surprised by the spread of the less commonly studied
languages, particularly Japanese, Chinese, Russian and a little bit
of Arabic,'' he said.
   Mandarin Chinese was being studied by 2.1 percent of students at
10 universities. Arabic was the choice of one-half of one percent
of the students at five universities offering it.
   ``While you still get the bulk of students coming in and
continuing in French, German and Spanish, you are getting some
diffusion in the colleges, and in high schools,'' he said. ``Maybe
300 high schools teach Japanese and more teach Russian and
Chinese.''
   One of the problems, Lambert said, is that students ``take
language in the 9th and 10th grades and then it goes fallow in the
11th and 12th grades and is not built upon at the college level.''
   ``You have got a lot of students getting a little bit of
language,'' he said.
   ``What is clearly needed for collegiate level foreign language
teaching is a major national effort dedicated to introducing major
change and upgrading the system.''
   Federal funds for foreign language instruction, he said, go
almost exclusively for programs to teach Defense Department
personnel and other government employes.
   ``It is high time the nation invested the necessary private and
public resources needed to advance foreign language instruction at
the collegiate level,'' Lambert wrote in the study.
   The American Council on Education is a cluster of educational
organizations and institutions. The study was funded by grants from
the Ford Foundation, the Exxon Educational Foundation and the Pew
Charitable Trusts.
</TEXT>

</DOC>