<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0226 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0749EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-AshlandCoalPurchase     12-21 0350</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Ashland Coal Purchase,0361</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ashland Coal Buys Prime Tract</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pending acid rain legislation spurred
Ashland Coal Inc. to spend $143 million to buy the stock of a
southern West Virginia company with low-sulfur coal reserves, the
company said.
   Environmentalists say sulfur in coal contributes to acid rain.
   Ashland Coal agreed late Tuesday to acquire the stock of
Mingo-Logan Coal Co. from BP America Inc., which is selling its
worldwide coal interests.
   Ashland Coal officials said they hope to mine more than 4
million tons of coal annually on the land by 1992, using about 400
employees. It will spend $96 million to develop the land and build
a preparation plant, bringing the total cost of the project to
nearly $240 million.
   ``The Mingo-Logan coal reserves are of exceptional quality,''
said William C. Payne, Ashland Coal's president and chief executive
officer. ``In addition, geologic conditions on the property will
allow us to mine at productivity levels well above industry
averages.''
   The land, owned by a subsidiary of the Norfolk Southern Corp.
railroad, has reserves of about 129 million tons of prime,
low-sulfur coal on about 20,000 acres of land in Mingo and Logan
counties.
   ``Mingo-Logan will give our company access to a new market _ the
power plants served by the Norfolk Southern railroad,'' Payne said.
``Also, it is expected to help us expand our presence in the export
market.''
   A spokesman for BP America said 20 companies made initial bids
for the property. Several sources in the coal industry said there
were three other finalists: A.T. Massey Coal Co., Island Creek
Corp. and AMAX Inc.
   Ashland Coal would break into the nation's top 20 coal producers
for the first time with the additional production, the Charleston
Daily Mail reported. The company expects to mine and sell 10
million tons in 1989.
   Ashland Oil Inc. owns 46 percent of Ashland Coal and 50 percent
of Arch Mineral Corp., another major national coal producer.
   Companies are attracted to southern West Virginia for its
low-sulfur coal reserves, which could prove valuable if Congress
passes strong acid rain legislation.
</TEXT>

</DOC>