<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0179 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2003EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Lover'sDebt     12-20 0379</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lover's Debt,0391</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romance Isn't a Way out Of Debt, Court Says</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE GLOVER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Romance can't be used to avoid repaying
loans to a former lover, the Iowa Supreme Court said Wednesday.
   The loans were not ``accumulated property of cohabiting
parties,'' the court said.
   ``The practical effect of denying recovery under the facts of
this case would be to permit a person to escape payment of a debt
by simply entering into a romantic relationship with the
creditor,'' the court said.
   In a Black Hawk County case, the Supreme Court reversed a lower
court order and ordered Terry Goro to repay money lent to him by
his former lover, Jerri Shold. It sent the case back to the lower
court to determine precisely how much money is owed.
   Court records said the case began in 1977 when Ms. Shold was a
student at the University of Northern Iowa and Goro one of her
teachers. They began an affair, though both were married to others
at the time.
   By 1980, Ms. Shold was divorced and court records said Goro was
anxious to obtain a divorce but pleaded financial difficulties.
   ``Jerri agreed to help,'' the court said. ``Each month Terry
would let Jerri know the amount of his financial needs and she
would give him a check for that amount.''
   The relationship continued for years and included moves together
to Minneapolis and California, and back to Cedar Falls, the court
noted.
   Finally, Goro was transferred to Detroit in 1986 and the
relationship ended, the court said.
   At that point, Ms. Shold sought repayment of the loans.
   ``Jerri acknowledges that there was no specific agreement as to
when the money would be repaid, because they did not know how long
Terry would need the money,'' the court noted.
   Simply because the two had a long-term relationship doesn't
erase the responsibility to repay a loan, the court said.
   ``Jerri's claim does not arise out of the relationship of the
parties, but from loans made to Terry,'' the court said. ``Although
the loans were intended to foster the relationship and, perhaps, to
eventually encourage a more permanent arrangement, they retained
their character as loans.
   ``They were clearly not the accumulated property of cohabiting
parties.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>