<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0199 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0857EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i PM-Taiwan-DogTemple Adv26   12-18 0830</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Taiwan-Dog Temple, Adv 26,0856</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv26</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Tuesday PMs, Dec. 26 or Therafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Taiwan's Dog Temple Does Fast Business for Those Looking for Luck</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto Planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN POMFRET</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TAMSUI, Taiwan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When the clock strikes midnight, strange
things happen at the Dog Temple, which was dedicated to the
fidelity of a dog but now attracts gangsters, prostitutes,
housewife stock whizzes and forlorn lovers.
   Tough guys roll up in sports cars, sauntering to the altar to
pray on their knees. Girls in miniskirts and low-cut blouses,
accompanied by bodyguards in leather jackets, place incense in
sacrificial urns. Their bouffant hairdos bob as they mumble prayers.
   Middle-aged women, clutching copies of stock market listings,
drop wood blocks in a Buddhist ritual as they search for an
ethereal tip.
   ``I'm praying against VD,'' said a prostitute with fluorescent
pink lipstick, who called herself Fragrant Flower. ``We `Little
Misses' need all the protection we can get.''
   Praying has become a big business on this island of 20 million
people, where superstition is pervasive. Thousands of temples
throughout Taiwan do a steady trade in fortune-telling.
Astrologers, palmists and soothsayers have flocked to the big
cities to give advice on Taiwan's huge stock market and the
popular, illegal numbers game.
   Buddhist, Taoist or Confucian, all temples are in on the act.
But perhaps the most famous is the Dog Temple, on a cliff
overlooking the sea about 15 miles from Taipei.
   Legend has it that about 100 years ago, 17 fishermen were caught
in a storm and pitched overboard. Their bodies washed up on the
shore.
   Local villagers dug a grave for them by the coast. As they
buried the fishermen, the vessel's pet dog jumped into the ditch to
be with his masters. The villagers buried the dog alive and hung a
lantern on the grave to commemorate its fidelity.
   For years, fishermen used the grave as a navigation marker when
steering their junks into the harbor in rough weather.
   In 1961, a group of local businessmen built a temple on the
site, equipped with bronze dogs, sacrificial urns with canine
engravings and statues of Taoist sages.
   In 1975, the temple doubled in size and began staying open 24
hours a day. It started a store and hired dozens of people to sell
temple paraphernalia _ clay dogs, incense, paper money that is
burned for the dead.
   When plans were made for a nuclear power plant next door, the
temple appeared doomed. But local pressure saved the site and now
nuclear plant officials come to the Dog Temple to pray.
   Some businessmen opened a replica of the Dog Temple just down
the road to cash in on the excitement. But after a few months, it
lost customers.
   ``They could feel there was no power there,'' explained Wang
Yuan-yuan, a Dog Temple board member, who was working the graveyard
shift at the advice counter recently. ``Only we have the genuine
article _ the dog spirit.''
   Business has been so profitable, said Wang that the temple is
planning a dog theme park just up the hill.
   ``The little dog has been so good to us, we want to pay him
back,'' he said.
   Hsiao Hsin-huang, a professor of sociology at National Taiwan
University, says uncertainty about the future has fanned the prayer
craze on this Nationalist Chinese island. He estimates that temples
make millions selling religious goods and gathering contributions.
   ``Nobody knows what will happen so people naturally turn to the
gods,'' he said. ``People are only interested in fast money and
many of them believe in luck.''
   Over the past few decades, Taiwan's economy has boomed, bringing
its per capita gross national product to the equivalent of $7,518
in 1988, the fourth highest in Asia.
   The growth also has created huge savings but the economy lacks
investment opportunities, so much of the cash floods the highly
speculative stock market. In 1987, the market had an up and down
swing of 450 percent. Record rises and falls were registerd on two
consecutive days in November.
   Proper investment techniques do not seem to work very well
because big players control the market. Many investors resort to
prayer.
   Thick clouds of eye-stinging incense swirl around the temple's
red columns.
   Two elderly ladies, both with pink pocketbooks, pluck sheets of
paper from the wall and head to Wang Yuan-yuan's advice desk.
   ``We're here looking for good bets,'' says one woman. ``We play
the stock market and we need a little advice.''
   ``Mr. Wang says we have to buy stocks tomorrow,'' her friend
says after the consultation ends. ``He gave me two numbers.''
   ``There it is, eighth column, fifth stock,'' she says, pointing
to her stock chart. ``That's what I'll buy.''
   Up the stairs on the altar, 18-year-old Chao Cheng is on his
knees mumbling.
   ``I'm in love with an older woman,'' says the doe-eyed student.
``Dog Spirit says I have hope but I must use special skill.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Tuesday PMs, Dec. 26</NOTE>

</DOC>