<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0095 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1819EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Poet     12-25 0300</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Poet,0306</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ceausescu Court Poet Saved By the Army From Being Lynched</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A poet who had described deposed
President Nicolae Ceausescu as ``the most beloved son of the
Romanian people'' tried to take refuge Monday in the U.S. Embassy
to escape a crowd that wanted to lynch him.
   But army soldiers intervened and took Adrian Paunescu away after
embassy personnel would not let him enter, witnesses said.
   Paunescu, in his mid-40s, for years was responsible for running
``Song to Romania,'' a festival of music and poetry eulogizing
Ceausescu and his wife Elena.
   Ceausescu was overthrown Friday and captured a day later by the
army following a popular uprising. The couple was executed Monday,
state radio said, after being tried and found guilty of ``grave
crimes,'' including the deaths of 60,000 protesters and the
plundering of $1 billion in public money.
   Paunescu, who owns a 10-room villa in downtown Bucharest
complete with a swimming pool and sauna, was considered Ceausescu's
court poet for many years until he fell into disfavor in 1985, when
police reportedly found he was involved in orgies at home and had
illegally built an Alpine retreat at Breaza, north of Bucharest.
   Under Ceausescu, Romanians were allowed to own just one home.
   When it became apparent that Ceausescu's demotion would be
imminent, Paunescu tried to address a rally in the palace square in
front of the Communist Party headquarters Friday to criticize the
dictator, but was booed by the crowd.
   In 1973, when bookstores were filled with volumes bearing
Ceausescu's picture entitled ``Homage,'' Paunescu said the book was
issued ``as a rousing evocation of the reverberations produced in
the mind of the Romanian nation by the anniversary of the most
beloved son of the Romanian people _ President Nicolae Ceausescu.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>