<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1059EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Israel-Jews     12-26 0411</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Israel-Jews,0424</SECOND>
<HEAD>Landmark Supreme Court Ruling: No Citizenship to Messianic Jews</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Messianic Jews are not entitled to automatic
Israeli citizenship, Israel's Supreme Court has ruled, concluding
that their belief in Jesus makes them Christians instead of Jews.
   The ruling, published in Israeli newspapers today, was a boost
to ultra-Orthodox religious interpretations of the state's 1950 Law
of Return. The law forms the basis of Jewish immigration to Israel.
   The law and its subsequent amendments defines a Jew as a person
born to a Jewish mother or who converts to Judaism and professes no
other faith.
   Orthodox politicians have long sought a more precise definition,
and the court's Christmas Day ruling has resolved one issue.
   The 100-page decision said that belief in Jesus makes one a
member of another faith and ineligible for automatic Israeli
citizenship, the Jerusalem Post, Hadashot and Yediot Ahronot
dailies reported.
   Supreme Court spokesman Shmaryahu Cohen declined on two
occasions today to show the 100-page ruling to The Associated Press
or comment on its contents.
   According to the newspapers, Justices Menachem Elon, Aharon
Barak and Avraham Halima acted on an appeal by a South African
couple, Gary and Shirley Beresford, who belong to a Messianic
Jewish sect.
   Members of such sects often are referred to as ``Jews for
Jesus.''
   The Beresfords challenged a recent refusal by the Interior
Ministry, headed by Aryeh Deri of the ultra-orthodox Shas Party, to
grant them citizenship on grounds they were not Jews. Both
Beresfords were born Jewish.
   The Jewish mainstream rejects the central principle of Christian
faith that Jesus was the Messiah. Several small, Messianic Jewish
sects, however, do believe in Jesus as Christ while considering
their followers as Jews.
   In their ruling, the Israeli justices rejected this view.
   ``Messianic Jews attempt to reverse the wheels of history by
2,000 years,'' Elon wrote. ``But the Jewish people has decided
during the 2,000 years of its history that (Messianic Jews) do not
belong to the Jewish nation ... and have no right to force
themselves on it. Those who believe in Jesus are, in fact,
Christians.''
   The law in question has been a repeated source of tension
between secular and religious Jews in Israel.
   The main quarrel is over attempts by religious leaders to amend
the law to recognize only converts to Judaism by Orthodox rabbis.
Such a change would make it more difficult for many American and
Canadian Jews who belong to Reform and Conservative streams to
immigrate.
</TEXT>

</DOC>