<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0299 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1837EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Campeau-Lenders     12-20 0330</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Campeau-Lenders,0344</SECOND>
<HEAD>Clothing Makers Join Companies Suspending Business With Campeau</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CINCINNATI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two clothing makers have joined merchandise
credit firms in suspending business with Campeau Corp.'s Federated
and Allied department stores as a result of Campeau's financial
situation.
   Finity Sportswear Ltd. president Stanley Stern said that if the
retailers seek protection from creditors in U.S. Bankruptcy Court,
his company would have to demand prepayment on its next shipment,
which is Jan. 20.
   ``A delay in our payment would be very devastating,'' he said.
   Federated and Allied, based in Cincinnati, warned in documents
filed with the Securities and Exchange Commission that they could
run out of operating cash as early as January if lenders do not
restructure their $7 billion debt.
   Herman Gordon, senior vice president of Leslie Fay Cos., said
the company wants to continue business with Federated and Allied,
but cannot risk having the retailers seek protection in bankruptcy
court.
   ``We'd have to settle claims with something less than a full
amount. That is a risk we cannot afford to run,'' Gordon said.
   Solo Credit Service Corp. on Tuesday began advising clients,
including clothing manufacturers and companies that lend money to
finance merchandise shipments, not to ship goods to Campeau stores.
   ``Campeau's intention to do business is very sincere, but their
liquidity problem has turned into a very dangerous situation that
needs to be addressed immediately,'' said Richard Hastings, a Solo
credit analyst.
   Solo's advice came after CIT Group-Factoring and Heller
Financial, merchandise lenders, cut off credit to such
Campeau-owned stores as Lazarus, Bloomingdale's and Jordan Marsh.
   Carol Sanger, Campeau's vice president for corporate
communications in Cincinnati, said the company was withholding
comment on the companies' decisions.
   Liz Claiborne Inc., Bernard Chaus and Heckler Manufacturing &amp;
Investing Inc. are continuing shipments.
   ``We strongly believe management there will resolve this
situation and any questions will be answered,'' said Heckler
executive vice president Marcy Allen. The firm makes Calvin Klein
underwear and girl's sportswear under the Adrienne Vittadini label.
</TEXT>

</DOC>