<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0121 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1732EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Iran-Romania 1stLd-Writethru a0673 12-19 0394</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iran-Romania, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0673,0404</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ceausescu Says Iraq Should Withdraw from Iranian Territory</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: RECASTS grafs 1-2; picks up 3d `Iran's official'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANWAR FARUQI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nicolae Ceausescu of Romania, visiting
Iran while his security forces suppress protesters at home, laid a
wreath Tuesday at the tomb of Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini and spoke
of peace in the Persian Gulf.
   The Romanian president said Iraqis should withdraw from Iranian
territory so the rival neighbors can sign a peace treaty.
   Iran's official Islamic Republic News Agency quoted Ceausescu as
saying an Iraqi withdrawal ``is the starting point for
implementation of U.N. Security Council Resolution 598, and we are
trying our best in the Security Council to enforce this
resolution.''
   While Ceausescu was in Tehran, reports from Romania indicated
security forces may have killed hundreds of people during weekend
demonstrations against Ceausescu, who runs the last Stalinist
regime in the Soviet bloc.
   Romania has virtually sealed its borders and official media have
not reported the unrest.
   A U.N.-mediated truce ended an 8-year-old war between Iran and
Iraq in August 1988, but peace talks have not resolved their
differences.
   Iran insists the Iraqis withdraw from territory occupied in the
last weeks of the war. Iraq wants a border that gives it full
control of the Shatt-al-Arab waterway, its sole outlet to the
Persian Gulf.
   Tehran radio said Ceausescu met separately with Vice President
Roghani Zanjani and Foreign Minister Ali Akbar Velayati on Tuesday,
the second day of a three-day official visit.
   He and Zanjani discussed an agreement under which Iran will
export about 1 billion cubic meters of natural gas and 1 million
barrels of oil a year to Romania.
   Romania is Iran's second-largest trading partner in Eastern
Europe. The estimated volume this year is about $1.8 billion.
   According to the radio, Ceausescu expressed readiness to
cooperate with Iran in ``numerous'' fields, stressing cooperation
in mining.
   Earlier Tuesday, Ceausescu laid a wreath at Khomeini's tomb in
the Beheshte Zahra cemetery outside Tehran. The revolutionary
patriarch died June 3.
   In a reference to Ceausescu's resistance to pro-democracy
reforms sweeping the Soviet bloc, Iran's official news agency
praised Romania on Monday as ``the sole east European country
rigidly adhering to its past government.''
   Ceausescu became Communist Party chief March 22, 1965, and now
is the longest-serving leader in Eastern Europe.
</TEXT>

</DOC>