<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0126 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1527EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-HellgateFire 3rdLd-Writethru a0617 12-29 0445</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hellgate Fire, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0617,0453</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gas Fire Rages After Explosion at Utility Station</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 10 grafs to UPDATE with blackouts, subway problems,
four injured. Picks up 10th graf, `A fire....'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LARRY NEUMEISTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An explosion and gas fire at a Consolidated
Edison Co. plant sent flames and black smoke hundreds of feet over
the East River today, injured at least four people and blacked out
at least 128,000 customers.
   ``The lights dimmed really quickly, and then I heard a big
blast,'' said Frank Wiles, 25, who works at a coal yard across the
street from the plant. ``I have two trailers in the yard and it
violently shook them. You could see bricks or debris landing around
the area.''
   The power outages caused extensive transit problems in the
nation's largest city.
   Within an hour after the fire was reported at the Hellgate
Station at 1:10 p.m. in the Bronx, it went to five alarms. By 2:15
p.m., workers had shut off a valve on a gas main that was feeding
the fire and the 10-story flames subsided.
   ``When the valve was turned, the flames got smaller and smaller
and smiles got bigger and bigger,'' said Paul Laddomada, 41, who
works for the Department of Environmental Protection a half-mile
from plant.
   Police Lt. Raymond O'Donnell said a Con Ed crew was working
behind the station when a gas line was ruptured. He said at least
four people were injured.
   At least one man was in critical condition after he was blown
into the river by the explosion, then fished out by rescuers
working in temperatures just below freezing, police said.
   The cause of the fire was undetermined, said Pat Richardi, a Con
Ed spokeswoman.
   The Hellgate facility formerly served as a generating station
then became a switching station and crossover point for electric
and gas lines, she said.
   Electricity was cut off to 58,000 customers in the Bronx and
70,000 on Manhattan's Upper East Side, Con Ed said. The loss of
electricity stopped subway service throughout the Bronx and all the
way to the southern tip of Manhattan.
   A fire official said diesel fuel tanks at an adjacent bus
station were in danger of exploding, and that some may have
exploded.
   The Transit Authority evacuated its 800 to 900 people from a
depot about two blocks from the Hellgate Station, disrupting bus
service on at least 12 routes, said Caren Gardner, a TA spokeswoman.
   There was ``a massive rolling fire and explosion. The heat is so
intense that you can't get within two blocks and police have set up
barricades three blocks away,'' Gardner said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>