<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0128 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 2251EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Romania-Americans 1stLd-Writethru a0618 12-23 0849</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Americans, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0618,0874</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romanian Exiles Rejoice at Ceausescu's Downfall, Mourn Uprising's
Toll</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 2 grafs after 20th graf, ```My mother ...', to UPDATE
with Saturday demonstration in N.Y.; pick up 21st graf pvs, `About 400
...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM BUERKLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Romanian exiles rejoiced Saturday at the downfall of President
Nicolae Ceausescu and the prospect of democracy in their homeland,
but sadness over the uprising's heavy human toll tempered their
celebrations.
   ``I am happy for the Romanian people, but I'm crying for the
thousands of people who have died,'' said Lucien Gozariu, who
joined about 200 people at a rally in downtown Detroit.
   Ceausescu ran his country virtually as a family fiefdom for 24
years, but a popular revolt lasting only a week toppled the Soviet
bloc's last Stalinist dictator on Friday.
   Reform-minded insurgents claimed to control Romania on Saturday
after two days of fighting in which hundreds are believed to have
died. Thousands more were reported killed during crackdowns earlier
in the uprising.
   An Indiana professor who was making his way out of Romania on
Friday after teaching English there said the entire city of
Bucharest seemed to be in the streets after the Ceausescu regime
fell.
   ``I have never seen so much joy, such smiles on their faces,''
Sam Longmire of Evansville said Friday night in a telephone
interview from Frankfurt, West Germany.
   ``One young woman discovered I was American and hugged me and
kissed me and wouldn't let me go until her friends pulled her off
and back into the parade,'' he said.
   At the Detroit rally, Romanians cheered when told of reports
that Ceausescu had been captured by the Romanian army.
   ``They should put him in a cage and march him around the country
and let the people do to him what they want,'' said Ioan Borod.
   Some people carried pictures of Ceausescu with a circle drawn
around his head with the words ``Spit Here'' written in magic
marker.
   Rev. Roman Braga, spiritual advisor to the Romanian Orthodox
convent near Jackson, Mich., cautioned against vengeance.
   ``It will take some time to rebuild,'' Braga said. ``The people
must forgive and forget because with hatred you can't accomplish
anything.''
   Many at the rally weren't in a forgiving mood. At one point
several people threatened a priest, claiming he was an agent of
Romania's secret police.
   ``He is an agent of Ceausescu. Even in the United States they
spy on us,'' said Gozariu, who left Romania in 1977. The priest
fled before violence could erupt.
   A Romanian-American in Chicago remembered the victims in their
homeland and the dictator whose reign of repression had ended.
   ``My heart is with the people who died,'' said Viorel Catarama,
33, who runs a construction company in suburban Hinsdale. ``They
paid the price but it's worth it in a way.
   ``I hope for the best. I hope for democracy. I hope for freedom
of speech, freedom of religion, freedom to express yourself, and
most of all, now I'd like to see the president being brought to
justice,'' Catarama said.
   In New York, exiles who had protested nightly during the past
week outside the Romanian mission to the United Nations celebrated
there Friday night, sipping champagne, waving Romanian flags
stripped of the socialist symbol and chanting ``Victory, Victory.''
   Some had spoken to friends and relatives in Romania earlier
Friday.
   ``My mother was crying _ all she could say was `I'm free,'''
Horia Dugala, 26, said after speaking with his mother in Brasov.
   The members of the New York-based coalition of groups called
Romania 21 held another demonstration outside the mission Saturday
and appealed to the international community to send medicine,
blood, weapons, and United Nations troops to their country.
   ``Our people need weapons,'' said the Rev. Aurel Radulescu, head
of Romania 21. ``We don't want foreign troops in Romania, only U.N.
troops to stop the killing. We cannot do it alone, we need the help
of the American people and of the United Nations to stop the crimes
and killings.''
   About 400 people, including people of Romanian, Hungarian and
Chinese descent, rallied outside San Francisco's City Hall Friday
night and chanted ``Free Romania! Free China! Thank you, America1!''
   Some exiles in south Florida's Romanian community credited
Olympic gymnast Nadia Comaneci for helping trigger the uprising by
defecting last month.
   ``I think that Nadia's escape woke up a lot of people,'' said
Emil Pintilie of Hollywood. ``She was the first step that made
people start protesting so that Ceausescu would go away.''
   Comaneci was in New York and could not be located for comment.
   Emile Popa, who defected in 1987 while working for the Romanian
government in this country, said Ceausescu's fall was the best
Christmas present his family could receive.
   His wife, Cornelia, 35, and their children Maria, 7, and Roxana,
3, waited more than two years for permission to leave Romania and
were reunited with Popa during Thanksgiving week.
   ``I don't care if we don't get anything else. I'm just happy,''
said Popa, who lives near Cary, N.C., and works as an international
sales representative.
</TEXT>

</DOC>