<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0184 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1532EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Holidays-ATMs Bjt   12-27 0827</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Holidays-ATMs, Bjt,0854</SECOND>
<HEAD>ATM Usage During Holidays On The Rise</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserGraphic</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIVIAN MARINO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   For many people, trips to crowded shopping malls, airports or
restaurants this holiday season weren't complete without a stop at
an automated teller machine.
   One of the world's largest ATM networks, Plus System Inc. of
Denver, predicts that between Dec. 1 and New Year's Day consumers
will have used the high-tech bank machines twice as much as last
year, largely for withdrawals.
   That's good news for many financial institutions who charge
anywhere from 10 cents to $3 per transaction for such ATM services
as cash withdrawals, deposits, transfers or balance inquiries.
   ``Consumers have clearly embraced the idea of using ATMs.
They've become more confident in technolgoy,'' said D.Dale
Browning, president of Plus System, which estimates its ATM
customers will withdraw more than $500 million through 6.5 million
transactions this month.
   At the same time usage has risen and the number of available
ATMs has grown since their introduction more than a decade ago, the
likelihood of fraud committed by and against consumers also has
increased, especially during the holidays, experts say.
   ``The potential for it to rise is there just as credit-card
fraud rose as people started to use their cards more and (thieves)
became more aware of how they can beat the system,'' said Marsha
Sullivan, a spokeswoman for the Consumer Bankers Association in
Arlington, Va.
   There are few estimates available on ATM-related losses. But
some experts say it runs as high as $200 million a year and has the
potential to move into the billions as it has in the credit-card
industry.
   Bank of America in San Francisco narrowly escaped $14 million in
potential losses earlier this year after uncovering a scam in which
several insiders planned to use stolen secret codes of ATM
cardholders to withdraw money from 8,000 bank accounts. The group
planned to carry out the scheme with bogus bank cards made of
posterboard.
   A recent survey by the Washington-based American Bankers
Association found that 25 percent of the 1,200 banks polled
reported cases of fraud committed by a customer. Thirteen percent
reported fraud against a customer.
   The average financial institution had 62 cases of ATM fraud, or
about one incident for every 28,070 transactions, last year,
according to another study by Bank Administration Institute of
Rolling Meadows, Ill. That was down sharply from the 390 incidents
reported in 1986, due largely, the BIA says, to increased
safeguards by banks.
   ATM fraud can include from white-collar scams, such as thieves
withdrawing money after stealing bank customers' personal
identification numbers; strong-armed tactics, like robberies at ATM
locations; or overwithdrawals by customers.
   Still, fraud cases involving ATM cards are much rarer than with
credit cards. That's because in order to use an ATM card a thief
must also gain access to the person's personal identification code
_ usually a secret four-digit number punched into an ATM keyboard
to gain access to an account.
   Despite this safeguard, a significant number of ATM cardholders
_ about 25 percent by some accounts _ still make the mistake of
noting their PINs either on the back of their cards or somewhere in
their wallets. Purse snatchers, usually out in full force during
the holidays, often can figure out what the number stands for and
use it long before the card is missed.
   ``While it is important for you to read you monthly credit-card
statement to check for unauthorized charges, it's even more crucial
to read your bank statement to find unauthorized withdrawal through
an ATM,'' said Elgie Holstein, director of the consumer group
Bankcard Holders of America, in Herndon, Va.
   Holstein says consumers receive far less protection on ATM cards
than on credit cards. Liability from losses on an ATM card is $50
for the first two days after it is reported missing, the same as
with credit cards. But it rises to $500 for the next 60 days from
the time a bank statement is mailed out, after which there is
technically no limit.
   Financial institutions have built a number of safeguards into
the ATM system to prevent customers from seeing their savings wiped
out, such as placing limits on the amount of an ATM withdrawal per
transaction.
   In addition, the computers that operate ATMs are kept in high
security areas in financial institutions. The data that travels
across the wires each time a customer uses a machine is
``scrambled,'' meaning the information never travels across the
line the same way twice.
   Boris Melnikoff, vice chairman of the ABA's security and risk
management division, says technology exists to make it virtually
impossible for anybody but the cardholder to withdraw money from
his or her account. Among those being considered are identification
on the basis of fingerprints, handprints or a customer's retinas.
   ``(But) it has to be a practical approach,'' Melnikoff said.
``Not everyone might feel comfortable sticking their face in a
device so their retinas could be examined.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>