<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0127 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1331EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Reax     12-20 0746</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Reax,0768</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pope Expresses `Deep Pain' Over Violence in Romania</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROLAND PRINZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pope John Paul II on Wednesday joined the
condemnation of brutal repression of protesters in Romania, and
prominent Britons demanded that hard-line President Nicolae
Ceausescu be stripped of a knighthood that was bestowed on him.
   ``With deep pain we have all heard the news of dead and wounded
in some Romanian cities,'' the pope said.
   His comment on the violence, in which up thousands may have been
killed, came at the end of his regular weekly audience. John Paul
said he was praying that human rights and religious liberty would
prevail in Romania, which is controlled by the last Stalinist
regime in the Soviet bloc.
   Ceausescu, who has ruled Romania for 24 years, was given the
Knight Grand Cross of the Order of the Bath, the highest honor for
a foreign leader, during a state visit in June 1978.
   Lord Bethell, vice-chairman of the European Parliament's human
rights subcommittee, said ``the Order of the Bloodbath would have
been more appropriate.''
   In Geneva, leaders of the World Council of Churches and
affiliated organizations expressed shock at the crackdown and said
it revealed the ``ruthlessness'' of Romania's leadership.
   ``It is with shock and deep sorrow that we have learned of the
tragedy in Timisoara where violent repression by the armed forces
took the lives of many people,'' a statement said. Most of the
violence, which began last weekend, has occurred in Timisoara, a
city in western Romania.
   In Bulgaria, where the Communist leadership was equally rigid
until last month, several thousand people gathered outside the
Romanian Embassy in Sofia, shouting ``Ceausescu is a shame for
Europe!'' ``Fascists!'' and ``Murderers!'' The embassy refused to
accept a protest letter.
   The independent Union of Democratic Forces, which organized the
rally, urged Bulgaria to ``dissolve all treaties'' with the
Romanian regime and recall the Bulgarian ambassador. The two
nations are allies in the Soviet-led Warsaw Pact.
   President Francesco Cossiga of Italy made his feelings clear
during his annual Christmas meeting with diplomats, telling the
Romanian ambassador, Constantin Tudor: ``I was hoping this meeting
would take place in a different atmosphere. We are very saddened
and worried ... about what is happening in Romania.''
   In Brussels, NATO Secretary-General Manfred Woerner said the 16
nations of the Western alliance expressed ``their dismay at the
serious loss of life.''
   ``The government's use of massive brutal force to suppress these
demonstrations illustrates that the Romanian regime does not rule
with the consent of the people,'' he said.
   At the 35-nation Conference on Security and Cooperation in
Europe in Vienna on Wednesday, Romanian representatives were
isolated.
   Delegates condemned the killing, but the Romanians managed to
prevent the observance of a minute of silence.
   Austria, as host, declared to the conference that ``the Romanian
regime of murderers will be unable to stay in power.''
   Martin Vukovich, leader of the Austrian delegation, said all
delegations condemned the events in Romania, but that the Soviet
condemnation was restrained.
   The Soviets urged their Romanian allies to heed the human rights
provisions of the 1975 Helsinki agreements on European security and
cooperation, he said.
   In Yugoslavia, the Communist Party leadership decided to ``stop
concrete cooperation with the Romanian Communist Party for the time
being.''
   A statement from the party presidency held the Romanian party
responsible ``for last weekend's tragic events and their
consequences,'' the official news agency Tanjug reported, and an
invitation to Romania to send a delegation to the Yugoslav party
congress scheduled for January was withdrawn.
   Hungary gave a note to Romanian Ambassador Traian Pop that
condemned ``the brutal crackdown on peaceful demonstrators.''
Legislators observed a minute of silence for the victims and voted
to drape the parliament building in black.
   Czechoslovakia's parliament condemned the crackdown and said the
government in Prague should ``draw the necessary conclusions'' from
the events. There was no elaboration.
   The Foreign Ministry in Czechoslovakia, where the beating of
protesters started an uprising that ended the Communist Party power
monopoly in less than a month, protesting the use of force on
demonstrators. Czechoslovak air controllers have urged an
international boycott of Romanian plans.
   Eugene Ionesco, the celebrated Romanian-born playwright, said
the Soviet Union should help arrange the downfall of Ceausescu, the
French newspaper Le Figaro reported.
   Ionesco, who lives in Paris, said President Mikhail S. Gorbachev
``alone can do something, because Romania is literally colonized by
the Soviet Union,'' the newspaper reported.
</TEXT>

</DOC>