<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0103 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1240EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-JailSantas     12-22 0329</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jail Santas,0338</SECOND>
<HEAD>Inmates Sacrifice Smokes, Snacks for Poor</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERRY KINNEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CINCINNATI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Christmas menu at the county jail of
turkey, dressing and cranberry sauce started some inmates thinking
that they may be eating better than some people on the outside.
   Len Singleton, who is serving time for disorderly conduct and
resisting arrest, wrote a letter to Sheriff Simon Leis Jr., asking
permission to organize a collection among the inmates.
   Some 500 inmates at the Hamilton County Justice Center and
Cincinnati's Community Correctional Institution responded by giving
up cigarettes and snacks, and Singleton on Thursday presented a
check for $361.41 to the Freestore-Foodbank.
   ``A lot of inmates who will be incarcerated are members of the
community. They still have their hearts there, and they wanted the
community to know that,'' Singleton said.
   ``One of the inmates said to me, `I can remember one time when I
was on the streets and the Freestore helped me out.' They said they
can always get cigarettes, but this is more important,'' he said.
   Prisoners are allowed money accounts, usually a few dollars left
by relatives to buy incidentals. Singleton said some inmates
donated their entire allowance.
   ``We've never been involved with anything like this,'' said
Steve Gibbs, the Freestore's executive director who accepted the
inmates' check Thursday at a jailhouse news conference. ``We
appreciate what they've done.''
   Gibbs said the private operation has a daily budget of $10,000
and will feed about 3,000 families during the holidays.
   ``Some of us will not be going home for Christmas to be with our
loved ones, but that doesn't mean we can't be involved in the
spirit of giving,'' Singleton said in his letter to Leis.
   Leis said he was skeptical, and almost threw the letter away.
   ``On further reflection, I thought it was a very good idea,''
Leis said. ``Going along with it was one of the smartest things
I've ever done as sheriff of Hamilton County.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>