<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0176 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1027EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a PM-TruckStopCampaign Adv02   12-29 0820</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Truck Stop Campaign, Adv 02,0841</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv02</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Tuesday PMs, Jan. 2, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>`Operation Roadblock': National Effort to Rid Truck Stops of Drugs</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELLIOTT MINOR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CORDELE, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When Mel Boggs parks his 18-wheeler at a
truck stop he expects good food, clean showers and a safe parking
lot, free of hucksters, prostitutes and drug dealers.
   ``Get the drugs, alcohol and paid women off the lots and let the
men get the proper rest,'' the 54-year-old Boggs said during a fuel
stop at the Perlis Truck Stop in Cordele. ``If a man's got the
proper rest, he's going to be a safer driver.''
   Boggs, a burly plain-spoken man with 20 years of long-haul
experience, said truckers sometimes are disturbed while parked at
truck stops and rest areas by people selling sex, drugs, jewelry
and other merchandise.
   ``When I'm ready to stop and rest, I don't want people beating
on my doors,'' said the Jamestown, Ohio, driver.
   The truck stop industry, responding to President Bush's call for
a major drug offensive, has launched a nationwide campaign known as
``Operation Roadblock'' to transform truck stops into drug-free
zones. Owners are considering the use of drug-sniffing dogs, sting
operations, counseling programs and random drug tests for truck
stop employees.
   Roger A. King, spokesman for the National Association of Truck
Stop Operators, estimates 3 to 5 percent of the nation's 1 million
commercial drivers either sell or use drugs.
   ``The vast majority of drivers are small businessmen who can't
afford to lose their livelihood because of drugs,'' he said.
   Trucker Denny Austin, 36, of Calhoun, Ky., said he welcomed the
campaign and hopes it cuts down on the number of impaired drivers.
   Austin said truckers can't afford to have muddled brains because
they have to respond quickly to changing highway situations. The
stopping distance for an 80,000-pound rig is five times greater
than for a car.
   ``Drugs can turn a real smart person into a dummy,'' Austin
noted while eating breakfast in the Perlis restaurant.
   Owner Lamar Perlis proposed the truck stop campaign during a
recent NATSO meeting in New York.
   Perlis, a member of NATSO's steering committee, said the
association will evaluate the anti-drug efforts of individual
operators and will consult with the White House staff, the FBI and
drug czar William Bennett before developing specific
recommendations for its members.
   He said NATSO's 1,050 truck stop members and 220 allied members
have been asked to contribute $250,000 to fund the program.
   ``We are aware that drugs have infiltrated every segment of our
society, including the trucking industry and the truck stop
industry and we are trying to mobilize,'' he added.
   Several truck stops already are using drug dogs, one is spending
$7,000 a month for security lighting, others have installed fences
around their lots and many have hired security guards to protect
drivers, rigs and loads, King said.
   The All-American Truck Stop in Carlisle, Pa., has posted signs
warning would-be dealers that they may get caught in sting
operations supervised by the district attorney.
   The New England Truck Stop in Sturbridge, Mass., includes notes
with paychecks, offering help for employees with drug problems,
King said in an interview from NATSO's Alexandria, Va.,
headquarters.
   NATSO and the American Trucking Association have endorsed a U.S.
Senate bill that would authorize strong penalties for selling drugs
within 1,000 feet of truck stops. Congress has passed similar
legislation to protect schools and playgrounds.
   U.S. Rep. Bob Clement, D-Tenn., has sponsored a bill known as
the Drug-Free Truck Stop Act of 1989 that also would designate
truck stops as drug-free zones. Violators would be subject to
maximum sentences of 10 years for selling drugs within 1,000 feet
of truck stops.
   ``This bill targets all people, whether they are commercial
drivers or not, who ply their onerous trade in areas where trucks
congregate,'' said NATSO President William Clower. ``Congressional
action in this area will strengthen our efforts to make America's
highways safer.''
   Perlis believes most drivers will welcome Operation Roadblock.
``They want safe havens just as anyone else,'' he said.
   His truck stop has a security guard six nights a week, its
employees monitor CB radio channels for signs of drug activity, and
the sheriff assists when needed.
   The Perlis Truck Stop is one of the most popular along heavily
traveled Interstate 75, a major route between Florida and the
Midwest. The 14-acre facility has a large restaurant, showers, a
garage, a store, video games, refueling bays for trucks and cars
and a small motel. It serves up to 2,400 trucks a day.
   ``Truckers are basically like you and me,'' said General Manager
Leon Perlis, the owner's son. ``They're family people trying to
make a living. The guy who gets the exposure _ the guy who gets
caught with drugs or the guy who runs over someone _ is the
exception, not the rule.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Tues PMs, Jan. 2</NOTE>

</DOC>