<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0206 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0838EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv29   12-18 0421</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv29,0442</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv29</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Friday, Dec. 29</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is Friday, Dec. 29, the 363rd day of 1989. There are two
days left in the year.
   Today's Highlight in History:
   On Dec. 29, 1890, the Wounded Knee massacre took place in South
Dakota. More than 200 Sioux Indians were killed by U.S. troops sent
to disarm them. About 30 soldiers were slain.
   On this date:
   In 1170, Archbishop Thomas Becket was murdered in Canterbury
Cathedral in England.
   In 1808, the 17th president of the United States, Andrew
Johnson, was born in Raleigh, N.C.
   In 1813, the British burned Buffalo, N.Y., during the War of
1812.
   In 1837, Canadian militiamen destroyed the Caroline, a U.S.
steamboat docked at Buffalo, N.Y.
   In 1845, Texas was admitted as the 28th state.
   In 1851, the first American Young Men's Christian Association
was organized, in Boston.
   In 1913, the first movie serial, ``The Adventures of Kathlyn,''
premiered in Chicago.
   In 1934, Japan renounced the Washington Naval Treaty of 1922 and
the London Naval Treaty of 1930.
   In 1940, during World War II, Germany began dropping incendiary
bombs on London.
   In 1957, singers Steve Lawrence and Eydie Gorme were married in
Las Vegas.
   In 1975, a bomb exploded in the main terminal of New York's
LaGuardia Airport, killing 11 people and injuring several dozen
others.
   In 1986, former British Prime Minister Harold Macmillan died at
his home in Sussex, England, at age 92.
   Ten years ago: Iranian Foreign Minister Sadegh Ghotbzadeh
threatened to try all of the American hostages as spies if the
United Nations approved sanctions against his country.
   Five years ago: Indian Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi claimed
victory in parliamentary elections as his Congress Party captured
more than a two-thirds majority in the lower house of Parliament.
   One year ago: The Federal Aviation Administration, responding to
the bombing of Pan Am Flight 103, announced tightened security for
U.S. air carriers at 103 airports in the Middle East and Western
Europe.
   Today's Birthdays: Los Angeles Mayor Tom Bradley is 72. Actress
Viveca Lindfors is 69. Actress Inga Swenson is 57. Actor Ed
Flanders is 55. ABC newscaster Tom Jarriel is 55. Actress Mary
Tyler Moore is 53. Actor Jon Voight is 51. Singer Marianne
Faithfull is 43. Former Sen. Paul Trible, R-Va., is 43. Jockey
Laffit Pincay is 43.
   Thought for Today: ``The wise man must be wise before, not
after.'' _ Epicharmus, Sicilian Greek comic poet (? - c.450 B.C.)
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Advance for Friday, Dec. 29</NOTE>

</DOC>