<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0219 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1715EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-CommodityRdp     12-29 0697</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Commodity Rdp,0726</SECOND>
<HEAD>Heating Oil Futures Climb to Six-Year High</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID DISHNEAU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Heating-oil futures prices rebounded to close at a six-year high
Friday and gasoline futures climbed sharply on indications that the
push to produce more heating oil is taking a toll on gasoline
supplies.
   Orange juice futures also rose dramatically as temperatures in
Florida continued to warm, threatening further damage to oranges
stricken by last weekend's freeze.
   On other commodity markets, precious metals advanced, grains and
soybeans were mixed, and livestock and meat futures were mixed.
   Heating oil futures settled .60 cent to 5.47 cents higher on the
New York Mercantile Exchange with the contract for delivery in
January up 5.47 cents a $101.87 a gallon.
   West Texas Intermediate crude oil settled .16 cent to .34 cent
higher with February at $21.82 a barrel; unleaded gasoline was 1.1
cent to 3.11 cents higher with January at 63.22 cents a gallon.
   Heating oil last closed higher on Jan. 27, 1984, when it settled
at $1.0497, said Pat Kelly, an exchange official. The contract
traded as high as $1.10 a gallon, an all-time high, before easing
off.
   Trading ended at 1 p.m. EST because of the New Year's holiday.
   Analysts attributed much of the gains in heating oil to
last-minute buying ahead of the January contract's expiration at
the close of trading.
   ``This possibly ends one of the most spectacular bull moves in
heating oil of all time,'' said analyst Peter Beutel of Elders
Futures Inc.
   Wholesale unleaded gasoline futures were boosted by an industry
report that showed a sharp drop in supplies.
   The American Petroleum Institute, in its weekly inventory
report, said gasoline supplies fell 4.8 million barrels last week
to 221.7 million barrels.
   Heating oil and other distillate fuel oil stocks declined 4
million barrels to 112.2 million and crude oil inventories declined
by 4.3 million barrels to 343.5 million.
   ``This is normally the low point of the year for gasoline
prices,'' said William Hinton, an energy broker with Stotler &amp; Co.
``But since they're really so pumped up trying to make heating oil,
I think maybe the gasoline season is on.''
   Orange juice futures rocketed higher on the New York Cotton
Exchange, supported by forecasts for a return to near normal
temperatures this weekend in Florida.
   The warmup poses a new threat to oranges damaged by last
weekend's freeze. Warmer temperatures could cause fruit that is not
promptly picked to fall to the ground and quickly rot.
   All contracts for frozen concentrated orange juice settled up
the expanded daily limit of 8 cents a pound except the contract for
January delivery, which rose 7.65 cents to $1.6565 a pound.
   Gold and silver futures rose strongly on New York's Commodity
Exchange, recovering a small share of the ground lost in the two
previous sessions.
   Prices had fallen sharply on Wednesday and Thursday after
several failed attempts to rally February gold through $420 an
ounce.
   Peter Cardillo, commodity trading adviser with Josephthal &amp; Co.
in New York, called Friday's action ``a small technical bounce.''
   Gold settled $3.80 to $4.60 higher with February at $405.20 a
troy ounce; silver was 4.8 cents to 5.2 cents higher with January
at $5.208 a troy ounce.
   Grain and soybean futures finished mixed in a quiet, shortened
trading session on the Chicago Board of Trade.
   Wheat futures settled \ cent to 3 cents higher with March at
$4.09\ a bushel; corn was \ cent lower to 1{ cents higher with
March at $2.39} a bushel; oats were \ cent to { cents lower with
March at $1.53{ a bushel; soybeans were 2 cents lower to 2{ cents
higher with January at $5.68 a bushel.
   Livestock and meat futures ended narrowly mixed in listless
trading on the Chicago Mercantile Exchange.
   Live cattle settled .10 cent lower to .17 cent higher with
February at 77.37 cents a pound; feeder cattle were .05 cent lower
to .25 cent higher with January at 84.85 cents a pound; live hogs
were .08 cent to .78 cent lower with February at 48.70 cents a
pound; frozen pork bellies were .10 cent lower to .35 cent higher
with February at 49.90 cents a pound.
</TEXT>

</DOC>