<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0319EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-JudgeSlayings     12-21 0770</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Judge Slayings,0793</SECOND>
<HEAD>1987 Gangland-Style Slaying of Judge, Wife Remain Unsolved</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Mail Bombs, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JACK ELLIOTT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BILOXI, Miss. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   While the FBI investigates last week's
bombing death of a federal judge in Alabama, investigators here are
still puzzling over the mysterious 1987 slayings of a Biloxi judge
and his wife.
   The investigation has unearthed links among the Dixie Mafia, an
organized crime group that once flourished on Mississippi's
``Golden Gulf Coast''; a sex and extortion ring allegedly run from
a Louisiana prison; the mayor of this coastal city; and a purported
hitman sitting in a Georgia jail.
   But while there are many pieces to the puzzle, few of them fit
together.
   A federal grand jury has spent months investigating the deaths
of Circuit Judge Vincent Sherry, 58, and his wife, former Biloxi
Councilwoman Margaret Sherry, 57. So far, there have been no
indictments.
   The Sherrys were shot to death Sept. 14, 1987, in their home.
The judge was shot three times in the face, and his wife four times
in the head. Authorities said the same .22-caliber pistol was used.
   Their bodies were discovered two days later by Vincent Sherry's
former law partner, Peter Halat, who has since become mayor of
Biloxi _ and has been implicated in the crime.
   Halat worked with Sherry until Sherry was appointed judge in
1986.
   Louisiana prison inmate Bobby Joe Fabian, a convicted murderer,
has said Halat attended a 1987 meeting at the Louisiana State
Penitentiary at Angola in which the killings were plotted. Halat
angrily denied the accusations last August, saying he wasn't at the
prison when the meeting allegedly took place.
   Fabian claims the Sherrys were killed because inmates believed
the judge kept about $400,000 from an extortion scam that ran ads
in homosexual magazines and newspapers.
   Respondents to the ads were told their ``friend'' was getting
out of the Louisiana prison and needed money for airfare to meet
them. Authorities claim hundreds of thousands were taken in the
scheme.
   An alleged member of the Dixie Mafia, Kirksey McCord Nix Jr.,
has been indicted in the scam. Fabian claims that Nix, who is
serving a life sentence for killing a New Orleans grocer, was a
party to the murder plot.
   Nix, 46, said recently that he'd take a lie detector test as
long as his accusers and investigators would do the same.
   Halat said he represented Nix for nearly 10 years but severed
his ties in May 1988. He said he wouldn't comment further and
``take the chance of compromising the ongoing investigation.''
   ``Number one, I want the case solved. Number two, after it is
solved, I don't want anything to be tainted by publicity,'' Halat
said in an interview.
   Federal and state officials also are keeping mum.
   ``All I can tell you is that we've been trying to hold the press
down so we can do the job the way it ought to be done,'' said U.S.
Attorney George Phillips.
   Another person who has been linked to the case is John Elbert
Ransom, 62, of Smyrna, Ga., who allegedly was paid $35,000 to kill
the couple, according to Fabian.
   Ransom was indicted in November for the July 19 killing of
Rodney Gaddy, 33, in Coweta County, Ga. Investigators in
Mississippi have said that killing had a similar style to the
Sherry slayings.
   In 1979, Ransom was arrested on an unregistered firearm charge
after conviction of a felony and was sentenced to 14 years.
   Ransom, being held without bond in a Newnan, Ga., jail, has
recently denied that he killed the Sherrys or that he was a hitman,
but acknowledged that he knew Nix.
   While speculation persists that mob violence was involved,
others contend the hit on the Sherrys was ordered by enemies the
judge made while representing drug dealers.
   Mississippi and Louisiana authorities have refused to discuss
the details that allegedly link Ransom to the crime. But part of
the documentation comes from investigations by private investigator
Rex Armistead, hired by the Sherrys' family.
   Halat, 46, who became mayor in July, maintains the publicity
about the Sherry killings and grand jury investigation haven't hurt
the city. However, he says the reverse is true about his wife and
family.
   ``I'm a big boy. I can handle this. But who's going to pay my
wife back for the stares and whispers at the grocery store. Who's
going to pay back my children for things that are said at school?
   ``If anybody ... says that I had anything to do with that case,
I'll tell them to their face they're liars, that it's not true,''
Halat said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>