<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0159 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1703EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Reax 1stLd-Writethru a0717 12-22 0925</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Reax, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0717,0953</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ceausescu Downfall Hailed, Leaders Salute Courage of Romanians</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 4 grafs for 11th `In Czechoslovakia' with China, Hungary
remarks; picks up 12th `In our'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MAUREEN JOHNSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Western Europe rejoiced Friday at the downfall of
Nicolae Ceausescu, pledging immediate aid, and Romania's erstwhile
Eastern allies joined in welcoming the demise of the Soviet bloc's
last hard-line ruler.
   The United States said a ``terrible burden'' had been lifted
from Romania.
   Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev read out a news update
from the podium of parliament, and Soviet deputy and space
scientist Roald Z. Sagdeyev declared: ``It's a holiday.''
   Leaders elsewhere saluted the courage of Romanians who were
mowed down by tanks and bullets in the uprisings, the only killings
in the wave of democracy spreading through Eastern Europe. Many
pleaded for an end to the violence.
   ``To win this victory, the people of Romania have paid a heavy
price: the yoke of tyranny throughout long years, the massacre of
innocent people in the course of recent weeks,'' the 12-nation
European Economic Community said from its headquarters in Brussels,
Belgium.
   Britain's Queen Elizabeth II, in a ``a sign of revulsion,'' and
Norway's King Olav V each stripped Ceausescu of royal honors
awarded a decade ago.
   Romania's exiled King Michael, deposed by the Communists in
1947, told his countrymen in a broadcast from Switzerland, ``I am
and will always remain with you.''
   In dozens of countries, national radio and TV interrupted
programs with news from Romania and gave constant updates,
emanating in stunning detail from East bloc news agencies,
including the Soviet Union's Tass.
   Before Gorbachev's policy of openness, reports of any troubles
in an allied country would have taken days or weeks to reach the
official media _ if ever.
   Ceausescu had closed Romania's borders to black out news of
violent suppression of protests ignited a week ago in the western
city of Timisoara, but some reporters were able to reach the
troubled city on Friday.
   There was no immediate comment from China, a Ceausescu ally and
bastion of tough Communist rule. The main Chinese dissident group,
the Paris-based Front for Democracy in China, said: ``The wind of
history blowing in Bucharest will soon reach Beijing.''
   Emerging democracies in Eastern Europe welcomed the news and
appealed for peace.
   Premier Miklos Nemeth of Hungary, a Warsaw Pact ally at odds
with Romania over Ceausescu's treatment of ethnic Hungarians, said:
``At last we have to come to terms with each other. We cannot let
the historic opportunity pass,''
   In Czechoslovakia, opposition leader Vaclav Havel asked with
Romanians, ``in the name of our velvet revolution,'' not to take
violent revenge.
   ``In our country, there was a slogan shouted, `We are not like
them,''' Havel said in a message to Romanians. ``You should ask for
a just punishment for Ceausescu, but not the death penalty. Stop
the wave of violence. Otherwise it will flow over all of Europe.''
   President Bush called the upheaval ``a dramatic change.''
   White House press secretary Marlin Fitzwater said ``a terrible
burden appears to have been lifted'' with the ouster of Ceausescu.
   ``The United States shares the rejoicing of the Romanian people
and joins them in their hopes for a peaceful transition to
democracy,'' Fitzwater said.
   In Brussels, the European Commission of the 12-nation community
announced an immediate $1.2 million grant in emergency aid to
Romania.
   The community's foreign ministers, after a hastily convened
meeting in Paris, promised political cooperation too. They invited
Romania to rejoin the 35-nation Conference on Security and
Cooperation in Europe that drafted the 1975 Helsinki accords on
human rights.
   ``So that Romania can reclaim its destiny, the European
Community and its member states solemnly reaffirm their will to
give it the immediate aid and cooperation of which the Ceausescu
regime has unjustly deprived it,'' the ministers said.
   The International Committee of the Red Cross and two
humanitarian organizations in France said they were flying doctors
and medical supplies to Bucharest.
   West German Foreign Minister Hans Dietrich Genscher declared
that Romanians ``have won a great victory over a dictatorship
contemptuous of mankind.''
   At Friday's opening of the historic Brandenburg Gate in the
once-divided city of Berlin, East German Communist Premier Hans
Modrow welcomed the news.
   Among other fledgling democracies of the East, Poland's
Solidarity-led government said, ``We wish the young republic all
the best.''
   In Yugoslavia, TV and radio devoted virtually non-stop live
coverage and the government said it welcomed ``all efforts leading
to prosperity ... liberty and human dignity'' in neighboring
Romania.
   In London, the Foreign Office announced that the queen in an
unprecendented move has stripped Ceausescu of an honorary
knighthood ``as a mark of revulsion at the abuse of human rights in
Romania for which President Ceausescu is responsible.''
   She will return his award, The Star of the Socialist Republic of
Romania First Class.
   Like the Norwegian monarch, the British queen honored Ceausescu
a decade ago when he was regarded as a sort of liberal in the
Communist bloc.
   British Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher, on the steps of her
No. 10 Downing St. residence, saluted Romanians for having ``taken
liberty for themselves.''
   ``We should spare a thought for the very courageous people who
were not prepared to knuckle under in a bloodstained tyranny ...
and who paid for it with their lives,'' she said.
   French President Francois Mitterrand, current president of the
European Community, said as he arrived home from a two-day visit to
East Germany, ``The Romanians are free, Europe lives, it's great
news for everyone.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>