<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1822EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-China-Prices     12-17 0474</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Prices,0491</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chinese Inflation Down in November; New Loans Made to Industry</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHY WILHELM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prices in November were only 5.9 percent higher
than a year earlier, the government said Sunday in announcing in
the lowest inflation rate China has seen since 1987.
   However, the government was forced again to bail out large
state-owned factories hard hit by the austerity program that has
reduced inflation.
   The official China Daily said the People's Bank of China, the
central bank, granted the equivalent of $638 million in loans last
week to the state sector, which the government says must be
preserved as a pillar of the socialist system despite its
inefficiencies.
   Similar loans totalling $1.9 billion were reported in October
and November.
   The China Daily said the People's Bank and other banks
anticipate making total emergency loans of $21.2 billion to
state-owned industries in the fourth quarter to keep production
from sliding further.
   Industrial production dropped 2.1 percent in October from
October 1988, its first decline in a decade, and in November was up
less than 1 percent over November 1988.
   Some economists have pointed to the sluggish industrial
performance as a sign that the economy has entered a recession.
   The government clamped down on official spending, new
construction and bank loans in September 1988 in an effort to cut
inflation that peaked at about 40 percent, China's highest rate
since the Communists took power in 1949.
   Since then, inflation has dropped sharply, and the China Daily
said vegetable prices in October were actually 4.6 percent lower
than in October 1988, while fruit prices also declined.
   However, the austerity policy has left many companies so short
of cash that they cannot purchase raw materials, forcing the
government to issue special loans to aid priority sectors such as
the large state factories. The austerity also has resulted in a
backlog of unsold consumer goods, including automobiles and
television sets, which were in high demand last year.
   When foreign joint-venture car makers, including Shanghai
Volkswagen and Guangzhou Peugeot, appealed for help, the government
spent $94 million to buy 7,440 cars. The state also issued
emergency loans to grain bureaus so they could purchase the fall
harvest.
   The repeated emergency loans have dealt a blow to the
government's plan to balance its budget. Earlier this year the
government projected a $2.2 billion deficit, but Western economists
say it could be four times that much.
   They say the government's method of controlling inflation, by
clamping down on credit, has only propelled the economy toward a
recession without resolving the causes of inflation, such as the
irrational price structure.
   The official Xinhua News Agency, which reported the November
inflation figure, said retail sales dropped by 1 percent from the
previous November. Bank savings were up more than 25 percent from
January, to $106.8 billion.
</TEXT>

</DOC>