<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0113 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1644EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Romania     12-27 0520</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Romania,0534</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gorbachev Speaks to New Romanian Leader</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Romania's new president thanked Soviet President
Mikhail S. Gorbachev on Wednesday for backing the revolution that
ended 24 years of Stalinist dictatorship in the East bloc nation,
Tass said.
   Romania's provisional revolutionary leader, Ion Iliescu, spoke
with Gorbachev by telephone and expressed appreciation for a
supportive Soviet resolution that came at the height of the revolt,
the Soviet news agency said.
   Iliescu and Gorbachev reportedly are old friends from their
college days in Moscow.
   Iliescu is leader of the National Salvation Committee that took
power in Romania after the downfall of dictator Nicolae Ceausescu.
The revolutionary government says it is a provisional leadership
until free elections are held in April.
   Ceausescu was forced to flee his palace on Friday but fierce
fighting between loyalist and revolutionary forces left the outcome
of the insurrection in doubt for days.
   Gorbachev, speaking to the Soviet Congress of People's Deputies
on Friday, suggested that a resolution be approved urging support
for the Romanian people's ``just cause.'' Iliescu reportedly was
particularly grateful for that support.
   Iliescu also told Gorbachev the situation in Romania was
returning to normal and that 90 percent of the factories were back
at work, Tass said.
   On Tuesday, Gorbachev congratulated Iliescu on his election as
head of the National Salvation Committee at a time when patriots
are trying to rescue the nation from ``forces of terror.''
   Gorbachev's message in the Communist Party newspaper Izvestia
was strikingly different from the usual formal congratulations of a
new leader because it was signed simply M. Gorbachev, with no title.
   ``You have taken the leadership of the country in a very
difficult hour for it, when the Romanian patriots have decisively
moved to rescue the nations from the forces of disorder and terror,
in order to install a truly democratic order in your country,''
Gorbachev's statement said.
   He went on to assure Iliescu that the Romanians ``will receive
the full support of the peoples and the leadership of the Soviet
Union on their road to renewal.''
   Gorbachev and Iliescu reportedly knew each other as university
students in Moscow three decades ago. Iliescu was a leader in the
Romanian Communist Party until criticizing Ceausescu.
   Still, the Soviet recognition of an informal government was
unusual and indicative of Gorbachev's efforts to clear out the
vestiges of Stalinism in the East bloc. Reform movements with tacit
Soviet approval have ousted regimes in Poland, Hungary,
Czechoslovakia and East Germany.
   In East Berlin, a former aide to ousted East German leader Erich
Honecker said Wednesday that Gorbachev had a hand in ousting
hard-line East German leader Erich Honecker. Gorbachev reportedly
urged Honecker to embrace reform during the Soviet leader's state
visit in October. The former Honecker aide said the visit prompted
dissidents on the Politburo to force Honecker from power.
   However, Gorbachev also has not hestitated to issued mild
warnings when the pace of reform threatens the Warsaw Pact
alliance. The Soviets expressed some caution when a non-Communist
government took power in Poland and when West German leaders began
pushing for reunification with East Germany.
</TEXT>

</DOC>