<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0099 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1452EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Panama-Hotel 2ndLd-Writethru   12-21 0727</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Hotel, 2nd Ld-Writethru,a0554,0747</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hotel Guests Cheer Arrival of U.S. Troops</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Inserts 2 grafs after 6th, `He said...' to UPDATE with State
Department denying report that Baker ordered hotel secured. Pickup 7th,
`Guests first...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CANDICE HUGHES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dozens of guests hiding in a seaside
luxury hotel cheered when a battalion of elite U.S. airborne troops
shot their way through a neighborhood to reach the building.
   The troops' arrival late Wednesday night ended a day of terror
for 30 to 40 guests and staff, who had endured several raids and
abductions by armed Panamanians after the U.S. assault to topple
Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   The gunmen seized 15 people, and all but two eventually were
released. Jon Meyersohn of CBS and Daniel Sarria, the hotel's
resident manager, were apparently still being held hostage early
today.
   Lt. Col. Harry Axson, the battalion commander, said his unit,
based several miles away in Old Panama, had received direct orders
from Secretary of State James Baker III to secure the hotel within
three hours. They did it, but not without several skirmishes with
Panamanian forces.
   Three American soldiers were wounded during the trek, Axson said.
   He said he did not know if the combat was with members of the
Panamanian Defense Forces but that he believed at least some were
members of ``Dignity Battalions,'' bands of armed thugs loyal to
Noriega.
   Later today, State Department spokeswoman Margaret Tutwiler
denied that Baker had ordered U.S. forces to secure the hotel.
   She said Baker called Defense Secretary Dick Cheney twice to
relay information on the situation at the hotel. But any contention
Baker was issuing orders to the military is ``100 percent erroneous
and false,'' she said.
   Guests first heard the sound of American aircraft and helicopter
gunships overhead Wednesday night, then the crack of small-arms
fire getting louder by the minute. Then came the voices, but it
wasn't clear who they belonged to.
   Finally, about 90 members of the U.S. 82nd Airborne Division
marched in.
   It was 11:22 p.m. and the guests, huddled together in two rooms,
cheered and applauded the troops.
   The GIs took the guests to the hotel casino, handed out sodas,
cookies and crackers, and settled in for the night as evacuation
plans were made.
   Roger Conners, a Marriott spokesman in Washington, D.C., said
today that the Panama City hotel has been cleared of all guests and
employees and that the only occupants are U.S. troops, who have set
up a command post. He said an Army captain who telephoned him
reported that shots were being exchanged with Panamanians,
apparently members of the Dignity Battalions.
   Axson, a veteran of the 1983 Grenada invasion, said his troops
had not rested since early Monday morning but were in high spirits.
   Officials of the Marriott Corp. said earlier Wednesday they were
pressing the U.S. government to ensure the safety of guests at the
400-room hotel after the military assault to capture Noriega.
   Roger Conner, a spokesman for Bethesda, Md.-based Marriott, said
most of the guests were journalists and airline workers, along with
a few business people.
   At one point, some hotel guests were so fearful of giving away
their position that they refused to let three reporters make
telephone calls for about four hours during the afternoon.
   The first raid on the hotel by Panamanians occurred shortly
after the U.S. military assault began around midnight Tuesday.
   Armed men entered the hotel again about 1 p.m. By then, a few
guests had managed to flee, but drivers were difficult to come by.
One driver fled when he learned his riders would be Americans.
   The hotel is popular with Americans and is less than two miles
from the U.S. Embassy.
   Capt. Jay Skinner, a 23-year Eastern veteran, said he could not
understand why federal officials in Miami said Tuesday it was safe
to fly into Panama.
   Skinner, who makes the Miami-Panama run twice every five days,
said Eastern had been in contact with the Pentagon and the State
Department in addition to the Federal Aviation Administration.
   ``Why did they allow an American flag carrier in?'' asked
Skinner, 45, of Sunrise, Fla. His Boeing 727, with 117 passengers
aboard, landed only a few hours before the fighting began, and he
and his crew were virtual prisoners in the hotel for most of
Wednesday.
</TEXT>

</DOC>