<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0144EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Names     12-29 0681</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Names,0711</SECOND>
<HEAD>Names in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY14</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Olympic star Nadia Comaneci, who fled
Romania just weeks before the government was toppled and leader
Nicolae Ceausescu executed, hopes to visit her homeland after its
crisis ends.
   Ms. Comaneci, 28, said Thursday that her defection Nov. 28 so
embarrassed the old regime that Romania's secret police were
ordered to hunt her down and return her to Romania.
   Comments from Ms. Comaneci were included in a news release
announcing that David Frost's production company would make a movie
about her.
   ``I hope that through the movie and public statements I can be
of more help to my countrymen than by returning to live in
Bucharest,'' she said. ``However, I hope to visit Romania as soon
as the situation returns to normal.''
   Ms. Comaneci has been granted political asylum and plans to
settle in California.

</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fashion designer Oscar de la Renta and socialite
Annette Reed, a couple about town for several years, have tied the
knot.
   They were married Tuesday at de la Renta's home in La Romana in
the Dominican Republic, the couturier's office confirmed Thursday.
   It was the second marriage for each.
   The bride, 50, is an active supporter of a number of cultural
and philanthropic causes, particularly the New York Public Library.
She is the daughter of Jane Engelhard and the late Charles W.
Engelhard, the industrialist and race horse owner.
   Mrs. de la Renta has two daughters and a son from her previous
marriage, which ended in divorce.
   De la Renta, 57, has a son he adopted after the death of his
first wife in 1983.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Texan Brad Johnson, a former professional rodeo
competitor, says ``life experiences'' were more important than
formal training in his acting career.
   Johnson, featured in the Steven Spielberg movie ``Always'' with
Holly Hunter and Richard Dreyfuss, said he sat in on an acting
class for about 90 minutes in Los Angeles one night.
   ``That was all I could take,'' said Johnson in an interview
published in The Dallas Morning News on Thursday. ``I think acting
is just calling upon past life experiences. And, God, I've had a
bunch of those in a full 30 years.''
   Before becoming a rodeo performer, the Irving native had a
variety of jobs, including stints fighting fires, cleaning up a
slaughterhouse, pumping gas and repossessing cars.
   ``So when I pick up a script and read it, I think, `I know that
guy. I met that guy.' I feel like that's my training,'' Johnson
said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CHEEKTOWAGA, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Buffalo Bills fullback Larry Kinnebrew
has been charged with assault after a scuffle outside a hotel.
   Kinnebrew, 29, and a Virginia man were arrested at 2:47 a.m.
Wednesday outside the Ramada Renaissance Inn in this Buffalo
suburb, Officer Michael Dorobiala said Thursday.
   Dorobiala said the charge was lodged by the hotel's security
guards. He didn't have details of the altercation between Kinnebrew
and Vincent White, 22, of Richmond, Va. Nobody was hurt in the
incident, Dorobiala said.
   Kinnebrew is a starting fullback for the Buffalo Bills, who play
the Cleveland Browns in the National Football League playoffs on
Jan 6. His arrest wasn't expected to prevent him from playing in
the game.
   Kinnebrew's telephone number is unlisted and a Bills spokesman
was unavailable for comment on the incident Thursday.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>MADISON, Wis. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sportsman Bob Uecker will be the head
pitchman in Wisconsin's annual effort to attract spring and summer
tourism.
   The former Milwaukee Braves baseball player _ better known for
his appearances in commercials _ agreed to donate his services to
the 1990 campaign, as he has in the past, officials announced
Thursday.
   One of the advertising agencies involved in the project
suggested dumping Uecker this year, but the state Tourism Council,
mindful of the success of previous campaigns, decided to use him
again.
   ``Record responses for Wisconsin tourism information came as the
result of past Uecker spots,'' said Richard Matty, administrator of
the state Division of Tourism Development.
   Uecker broadcasts Milwaukee Brewers games.
</TEXT>

</DOC>