<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 2255EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama 2ndLd-Writethru a0791 12-17 0950</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0791,0977</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Soldiers Man Bases in Panama After U.S. Officer Killed</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 15 grafs, CORRECTING that U.S. troops not outside
bases, UPDATING with reported U.S.-Panamanian meeting. Picks up 13th graf
`The Panamanian...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PAN1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   American soldiers in battle gear
guarded base perimeters Sunday after a U.S. officer was killed, a
second wounded, and a Navy couple beaten in the worst
U.S.-Panamanian confrontation in 25 years, U.S. officials said.
   The White House deplored the killing and termed it a
``consequence'' of Panama's being under the rule of Gen. Manuel
Antonio Noriega.
   Panamanian troopers used trucks and buses to block streets
leading to Noriega's headquarters after the violence Saturday
night. Panamanian officials said the Americans had wounded a
Panamanian soldier and two civilians.
   A U.S. Southern Command statement said the slain officer was
``off duty, unarmed and in civilian clothes when he and three
others were stopped by Panamanian soldiers near the (Panamanian)
Defense Headquarters in the old section of Panama City.''
   The Panamanians tried to drag the Americans from their car and
fired at them as they drove off, killing one officer, it said. His
identity was withheld.
   In Washington, a Defense Department statement confirmed that a
U.S. officer was fatally shot and said a second soldier was grazed
on the ankle by a bullet.
   The Panamanian Defense Forces accused U.S. officers of a
provocation, without mentioning the American's death.
   The Pentagon gave this additional account:
   A U.S. Navy lieutenant and his wife were stopped at the same
roadblock as the other soldiers a half-hour earlier and witnessed
the shooting. The Panamanians then blindfolded both with masking
tape and interrogated them for about four hours.
   They repeatedly beat and kicked the man in the groin and head
and threatened to kill him if he did not give information on his
duties and unit.
   His wife's head was cut when she was slammed against a wall and
she later collapsed. Panamanian soldiers also threatened her
sexually before the pair was escorted back to an avenue that
connects with U.S. military bases and released.
   U.S. Defense Secretary Dick Cheney said in his statement, ``The
lack of discipline and control in the Panamanian Defense Forces is
further evidence that Panama is a country without a government.''
   Panamanian and U.S. military officers were reported Sunday to be
meeting to discuss the incident, opposition politicians said. The
Southern Command refused to comment.
   The contact was reported to be through the Joint Board, a
liaison between the two countries' military forces that deals with
Panama Canal security and defense.
   Col. Ronald Sconyers, a Southern Command spokesman, said the
U.S. officers had made a wrong turn and were lost.
   The Panamanian statement said the U.S. officers had ``broken
through checkpoints and fired at the headquarters building,
wounding a soldier and two civilians, including a 1-year-old girl.''
   President Bush was informed of the situation by National
Security Adviser Brent Scowcroft, White House deputy press
secretary Roman Popadiuk said in Washington.
   ``We deplore this act of violence. We are presently looking into
the circumstances of this incident,'' Popadiuk said. ``The Noriega
regime is isolated both domestically and internationally and has
been using force and intimidation to thwart the will of the
Panamanian people. Acts such as those of last evening are the
consequence of such a regime.''
   Word of the death and rumors of U.S. retaliation spread quickly.
Sunday morning people at a gas station spoke of the imminent
``arrival of the Americans.''
   U.S. soldiers mobilized along the perimeters of U.S.
installations a few miles northwest of Panama City. Lines of
armored personnel carriers and trucks stood at the ready inside the
boundary of Fort Clayton.
   Combat units were not seen at U.S. bases closer to Panama City,
including Southern Command headquarters at Quarry Heights, which
borders the capital to the west.
   The 12,000 U.S. troops stationed in the Panama Canal area were
restricted to base and only authorized movement was permitted.
   A golf course at Fort Amador, a base shared by U.S. and
Panamanian military units, was deserted Sunday. A causeway where
Panamanians picnic near the fort was empty except for a salsa group
rehearsing.
   The nearby Bridge of the Americas across the Panama Canal was
open.
   Panama's opposition leaders refused to comment directly about
the shooting, saying the information they had received was
``confusing.''
   But Christian Democratic leader Ricardo Arias Calderon said the
confrontation was the result of other clashes between Panama and
the United States in recent months.
   The bloodiest previous incident between the nations occurred on
Jan. 9, 1964, in the time of the old Panama Canal Zone, which
consisted of a 10-mile-wide strip across Panama that was considered
U.S. territory.
   U.S. police and soldiers clashed with Panamanian rioters over
the display of the U.S. and Panamanian flags at a high school. Four
U.S. soldiers and 22 Panamanians died, and Panama broke diplomatic
relations with the United States for three months.
   Noriega, who was de facto leader through his control of the
Defense Forces, was named chief of government on Friday by a
rubber-stamp assembly. It said Noriega's leadership was needed to
confront a ``state of war'' caused by U.S. economic sanctions and
other efforts to oust the general.
   Panama and the U.S. government have been at odds since February
1988 when Noriega was indicted on federal drug charges in the
United States.
   He denies the charges and says Washington wants to oust him to
make it easier for the United States to renege on the Panama Canal
treaties, which transfer the canal to Panama at the end of the
century and close U.S. military installations here.
</TEXT>

</DOC>