<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0149 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1757EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Panama 1stLd-Writethru a0591 12-18 0704</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Panama, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0591,650</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Calls Slaying an `Outrage,' Weighs Response</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Inserts 1 graf with Monday incident after 10th graf pvs, During
four; inserts 2 grafs reaction after 14th graf pvs, He said</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERENCE HUNT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP White House Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush said Monday the killing of an
American serviceman in Panama was ``an enormous outrage'' and that
the United States was considering options to deal with Manuel
Antonio Noriega. Bush did not rule out military steps.
   ``I think a president, all presidents, have options, but they
don't discuss what they might be,'' Bush said in an interview. He
repeated that answer when asked if military options were being
reviewed.
   Questioned about Noriega's declaration of a ``state of war''
between Panama and the United States, Bush said, ``I've taken note
of his statement.''
   A high-level interagency group met at the State Department to
discuss options on Panama, said sources who requested anonymity.
   The United States has been trying to force Noriega's ouster
since his indictment in Florida on drug-smuggling charges in
February 1988. The United States supported an unsuccessful coup
attempt against Noriega Oct. 3.
   On Friday, Noriega declared a state of war with the United
States and had himself installed by the national assembly as the
country's supreme leader.
   The next day, violence flared when four American officers,
traveling unarmed, in civilian clothes and in a private car, were
trying to flee a crowd of Panamanian troops and civilians after the
car had been stopped at a Panamanian roadblock, the Pentagon said.
   One serviceman was killed when the Panamanian soldiers opened
fire. Another U.S. officer's ankle was grazed by a bullet.
   After the shooting, the Panamanians arrested a U.S. Navy
lieutenant and his wife who had been stopped earlier at the
roadblock.
   During four hours of interrogation, the Pentagon said, that
officer was repeatedly beaten and kicked in the groin and his wife
was sexually thratened and slammed against a wall.
   Another incident occurred Monday, when an American officer shot
and wounded a Panamanian corporal near a U.S. installation, a
Southern Command official said. The official said the U.S. officer
believed the Panamanian was drawing his weapon and felt threatened.
   Bush, in an interview with The Associated Press and three other
news agencies, said, ``One of the frustrations that I've had during
this year is the whole Panama situation, an enormous frustration.''
   Asked how the United States would respond to the officer's
death, Bush said, ``It's an enormous outrage and a matter of
enormous concern to this president.''
   As for the steps available to him, Bush said, ``For one, I can
tell you how strongly I feel about it, which I've just done, and
two, review whatever options might be available, and three, not
discuss what they might be.''
   He said he wanted to have a free hand ``without having
positioned myself on what it is I want to do.''
   Meanwhile, Rep. Ike Skelton, D-Mo. a member of the House Armed
Services Committee, said the United States ``can't put up with
Noriega's actions'' and will have to take steps to stop the
arrests, detentions, beatings and harassment of U.S. forces.
   ``The question is how do we do it,'' Skelton said. ``Do we wait
for the PDF (Panamanian Defense Forces) to stage another coup or do
we take another step'' of unilateral military action.
   Bush and his predecessor, former President Reagan, have hinted
at military action against Noriega but have refrained from a direct
assault.
   Meanwhile, White House press secretary Marlin Fitzwater said the
United States was ``very concerned'' about Noriega's declaration of
war. He said it ``may have been a license for harassment and
threats and in this case murder.''
   Fitzwater said most U.S. dependents have left Panama or have
been moved onto the U.S. military base there. He said that a 9:50
p.m. curfew had been imposed over the weekend on U.S. military
personnel and that the base was on a high state of alert.
   ``There's no question that it's a dangerous situation,''
Fitzwater said.
   He said the mistreatment of the naval officer's wife ``certainly
goes beyond any previous experience. And the murder is outrageous
in itself.''
   The United States has 12,000 troops stationed in Panama.
</TEXT>

</DOC>