<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0020EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Romania-Freedom     12-29 0816</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Freedom,0813</SECOND>
<HEAD>For Romanians, Freedom Is Still an Exotic Word</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MORT ROSENBLUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In the passion that fueled Romania's
revolution, ``freedom'' was spoken again and again. But to a people
forced to register even their typewriters, the full meaning of the
exotic word was difficult to grasp.
   ``What is it to live free, to travel free, to speak freely?''
mused Ioana Popescu, a 21-year-old medical student. ``We have only
seen dark and silence.''
   Over the moans of the wounded in a crowded hospital ward, she
and some fellow volunteers considered what the term ``freedom''
meant.
   ``We can't realize what freedom is,'' said Anda Preda, also 21,
to an American reporter. ``You grew up in freedom, and you do not
realize what this means to us.''
   She paused and frowned, and apologized for her poor English.
   ``I'm sorry,'' she said. ``I've learned English 11 years, and
this is the first time I speak it.''
   Until young Romanians such as herself helped overthrow Nicolae
Ceausescu, every such contact with a foreigner would have to be
reported to the despised secret police, the Securitate. People
could leave Romania only in the rarest of circumstances.
   Ceausescu's ears were everywhere. People spoke in whispers,
trusting only the closest of friends. An indiscreet word, even the
wrong gesture in delicate moments, could alter an entire life.
   For young Romanians, it had been that way all of their lives.
Most of their parents were born under Stalinism, and their
grandparents lived through a world war.
   Suddenly, it was all over. Or was it?
   ``Even now, it is like a dream,'' said Ms. Popescu, days after
Ceausescu was toppled. ``Maybe I will wake up and it is gone.''
   Bogdan Lazarae did not expect freedom to go away, but he was not
sure what it was. At 21, he is an engineering student with a
searching soul. He has been helping doctors until nightfall and
then manning a subway checkpoint until morning.
   ``We don't know what this means, freedom,'' he said.
   ``We don't know what to do with freedom. We have no experience,
no model, no idea.''
   In his first free moments, Lazarae worked as a translator for
reporters trying to understand Romania. At times he is just as
confused as the outsiders.
   ``I am afraid people will ask me what I am doing with
foreigners, but no one asks. That's a little bit of freedom. I am
afraid to speak the name of Ceausescu in the street, maybe someone
will tell me I'm an enemy, but they don't. That's a little bit of
freedom.''
   Mainly, he said, ``to be free is to talk free, to say what you
want. It is very bad to hide what you are thinking. It is not
healthy. It is not dignified.''
   All over Romania, people are experimenting with the elusive
concept they fought so hard to obtain.
   At the University of Bucharest, historian Stephan Andrescu
described freedom as a lost treasure enjoyed by Romanians for most
of the time between 1865 and the tumult of the World War II.
   At the National Library, where 10 percent of the books were
shown only to people with clearance from the secret police, freedom
has a specific meaning.
   ``What is essential is freedom of the mind,'' said Angela
Brodiceni, library director. ``We will face many problems, many
trials. But now our minds are free.''
   At the hilltop Metropolitan Cathedral, Ionita Victoria thanks
God for freedom of worship. She was afraid to go to church in a
country where police noted names of the religious, but she braved
sniper fire when those police lost their power.
   At the Agerpres news agency, an editor who is still reluctant to
be quoted by name is grateful for the freedom to report without
hiding most of the truth. He wept out of control as he tried to
purge his guilt for not resisting earlier on his own.
   The concept of freedom takes different shapes depending upon the
surroundings. At the Bucharest emergency hospital, it hits hard.
   Ms. Popescu looked at the casualties lying on stretchers in the
narrow hallway.
   ``You have to respect this thing freedom when you think of the
price it carries,'' she said.
   But it takes its broadest meaning on street corners where for
the first time in 45 years people can shout out their opinions to
foreigners.
   Near the bombed-out Communist Party Central Committee building,
a small group of people waited their turn to speak to American
reporters about what they felt they had won.
   Not one could finish his piece with dry eyes.
   Toma Cornelia called out that he had a sister in Loveland,
Colo., named Ilie Botezatu. She went to the United States to flee
Ceausescu's Romania.
   ``You tell her we are starting a new life,'' he said. ``Tell her
we are waiting for her.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>