<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0129 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1842EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Panama-Assets 3rdLd-Writethru a0651 12-27 0556</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Panama-Assets, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0651,520</SECOND>
<HEAD>With AM-Bush Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Administration Moves Against Assets Held By Noriega</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 4th graf pvs, In Bern, with two grafs to update with French
action, picks up 5th graf pvs, The Swiss</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Justice Department asked four European
nations Wednesday to freeze bank accounts where former Panamanian
dictator Manuel Antonio Noriega is thought to have hidden illegal
drug profits.
   David Runkel, a department spokesman, said the legal papers were
filed with the governments of France, Switzerland, Luxembourg and
the United Kingdom, requesting authorities to order banks to block
any transactions in the Noriega accounts.
   ``The request is of money directly tied to his alleged illegal
drug trafficking,'' Runkel said, adding there is ``more than one
account in each country.''
   Authorities in France responded to the U.S. request by freezing
accounts in two banks holding $3.3 million under the names of
Noriega and members of his families. Swiss officials placed a
``precautionary'' freeze on two accounts in banks in Zurich and
Geneva.
   French investigators said the banks in France may have been used
as transit points for funds destined for Luxembourg or Switzerland.
   The Swiss Justice Ministry said the U.S. request charged Noriega
with giving ``logistic support'' to Colombian drug lords' shipments
to the United States.
   Noriega, who is hiding in the Vatican Embassy in Panama City, is
thought to have transferred at least $10 million into numerous
accounts in Europe, Runkel said. State Department officials,
however, say Noriega's personal wealth could total as much as $300
million.
   Deposed as dictator by U.S. troops on Dec. 20, Noriega has been
charged in Florida in two drug trafficking indictments.
   Runkel said department lawyers are confident they can document
that money Noriega sent abroad had been earned illegally in the
drug trade. U.S. troops seized a slew of records in Panama City
after Noriega was ousted.
   The four European countries are expected to cooperate with the
American request, rules of which are spelled out in international
treaties.
   ``We have had a remarkable display of international
cooperation,'' Runkel said. ``These letters were not sprung on
these countries this morning.''
   Once the bank accounts have been frozen _ as Justice expects _
there is still the possibility they will be barren, Runkel said.
It's conceivable, he said, that Noriega, his family or his bankers
moved money out of accounts since the invasion.
   Freezing assets is the first step to seizing them, said Runkel.
``These things are not easy processes.'' Any disposition of the
money, however, would be by international agreements.
   Preliminary discussions were also under way with others
countries where Noriega might has stashed money, Runkel said. But
he is not thought to have assets in the United States.
   State Department estimates put Noriega's worth at between $200
million to $300 million, much of it hidden in secret bank accounts
abroad.
   In a speech last August, Deputy Secretary of State Lawrence
Eagleburger alluded to multimillion-dollar transactions Noriega has
made over the past two years involving accounts in West Germany,
Switzerland and Luxembourg.
   The private gains Noriega has accumulated, Eagleburger said,
belie the image he has projected of a ``poor youth of humble
origins who by virtue of individual effort, merit and talent rose
through the ranks to become head of a small but respectable
military force.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>