<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1009EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Czechoslovakia 1stLd-Writethru   12-19 0605</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Czechoslovakia, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0509,0623</SECOND>
<HEAD>Communist Premier Urges Election of Havel As President</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: LEADS with 15 grafs to UPDATE with additional Calfa comments,
support for Havel, details of meeting. Pickup 14th graf, `Meanwhile, opposition...</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SYDNEY RUBIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Communist premier today urged
the Communist-dominated Parliament to elect opposition leader
Vaclav Havel for president by the end of the year.
   ``It is the government's opinion that there is no alternative
... than to elect Vaclav Havel as president,'' Premier Marian Calfa
told deputies in the Federal Assembly. They applauded the
recommendation.
   Thousands of students gathered early today around the statue of
St. Wenceslas with banners, balloons and red, white and blue
Czechoslovak flags for pro-Havel demonstrations. Some students, who
arrived early on trains and buses from throughout the country,
passed the time before the demonstrations by Christmas shopping
along Wenceslas Square.
   Calfa's recommendation and its reception by the deputies
appeared to signal the final victory of the peaceful revolution,
which in one month has swept away 41 years of Communist domination
of Czechoslovakia's government.
   The pro-democracy opposition has negotiated a new non-Communist
government that includes two former dissidents; ousted hard-line
Communist President Gustav Husak; and introduced reforms in every
political, social and religious sphere.
   Support has been snowballing for Havel, who would be the first
non-Communist to hold the office in 41 years. Husak resigned Dec.
10.
   Havel's only rivals are former Communist Premier Ladislav Adamec
and Alexander Dubcek, who led the reforms of the ``Prague Spring''
in 1968 and was removed by the Kremlin. Dubcek, who enjoys
tremendous support in his native Slovakia, has been waffling on
whether he is in the race.
   Cestmir Cisar, the students' candidate for president in 1968 and
an unofficial contender in the current race, withdrew Monday night
and threw his support behind Havel.
   Czechoslovakia's constitution requires Parliament to elect a new
president within two weeks of a vacancy occurring, but Communist
and opposition leaders agreed to introduce a resolution to extend
the deadline.
   The two-point agenda approved at the start of today's meeting
would give them until late January to choose a president. It was
unclear when a vote on the extension would be taken.
   Calfa said a president should be chosen before the year ends in
12 days.
   ``The government is making efforts to solve the political and
constitutional crisis,'' Calfa said. ``We want to ask the Federal
Assembly to contribute to this effort by electing the president by
the end of this year.''
   Josef Bartoncik, head of the lower house of the bicameral
Parliament and leader of the People's Party, said his party would
support Havel and would recommend that Parliament recovene Dec. 28
or Dec. 29 to elect the president.
   The Socialist Party, one of four small parties in the
Communist-dominated Parliament, also endorsed Havel.
   Deputies also were considering the government's reform program,
which outlines political and economic changes, repudiates the
repression that followed the 1968 anti-reform crackdown, and
supports a democratic socialism.
   Meanwhile, opposition leaders said reports of a planned military
coup were spread to cause uncertainty. Opposition member Sasha
Vondra was quoted as saying in the Svobodne Slovo daily that the
rumor of an impending coup ``is purposefully propagated
disinformation and rumor.''
   Representatives from the Civic Forum met Monday with Defense
Minister Miroslav Vacek who assured them the army supported
democratic reform, he said.
   Col. Stanislav Pohoral, a Defense Ministry spokesman, condemned
the circulation of ``leaflets, mainly in Brno, which say a ...
military coup is being planned,'' calling it ``totally
irresponsible.''
   The army leadership ``distances itself from these actions and
rejects the accusations,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>