<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0097 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1509EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-PublicEnemy     12-28 0626</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Public Enemy,0647</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rap Group Rapped Again</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Note contents.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JERRY SCHWARTZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The rap group Public Enemy has raised hackles
again with a new single that has been denounced as anti-Semitic by
the Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith and others.
   The song, ``Welcome to the Terrordome,'' was released Wednesday.
Its lyrics _ a multitude of statements and images focusing on black
life in 1989 _ include the lines ``Told the rab, get off the rag''
and:
   ``Crucifixion ain't no fiction
   ``So-called chosen, frozen
   ``Apology made to whoever pleases
   ``Still they got me like Jesus.''
   The group's critics argue that Public Enemy is accusing the Jews
of killing Christ and of treating Public Enemy the same way. The
same critics say descriptions of Jews as the ``so-called chosen
people'' are common among Black Muslims who say they and not the
Jews are the chosen people.
   Public Enemy leader Chuck D. said the song refers to last
summer's controversy involving Professor Griff, the group's
non-performing ``minister of information,'' who was quoted as
saying that Jews were responsible for most of the wickedness in the
world.
   Chuck D. fired Professor Griff and disbanded Public Enemy.
Within weeks, the group came together again, with Griff as a
community liaison who was no longer supposed to give interviews.
   Chuck D. insisted that the criticized lyrics of ``Welcome to the
Terrordome'' were not anti-Semitic.
   ``It says I apologized (for Griff's comments) and then the media
crucified me. Griff was wrong and I was the first to admit it. ...
But a lot of wrong things happened after that, too,'' he told the
Daily News.
   He said ``so-called chosen'' referred to both Jews and Muslims _
he does not believe that any people are chosen, he said. And he
suggested that critics were misinterpreting the record because they
were ignorant of rap language.
   Ridiculous, said Rabbi Abraham Cooper, associate dean of the
Simon Wiesenthal Center for Holocaust Studies in Los Angeles.
   ``The people who wrote it, the people who sang it, the people
who produced it, the people who distributed it all know that this
song is anti-Semitic,'' Cooper said.
   Jeffrey Sinenski, head of the ADL's Civil Rights Division, said,
``We've been in the business for 25 years and the Anti-Defamation
League is very familiar with the language of bigotry. We know it
when we see it.''
   In a letter to Tommy Mottola, president of CBS Records, which is
distributing the record, Sinenski said the song revives ``the
repulsive and historically discredited charge'' that the Jews
killed Christ. CBS Records, he said, was helping to distribute
anti-Semitic statements.
   Sinenski said he had received no response from Mottola and there
was ``a wall of silence in the music industry.'' Cooper, who has
met with Chuck D. several times in recent months and has introduced
him to a Holocaust survivor, agreed.
   ``Where is it said in the First Amendment that the mainline
record companies must distribute the rantings of racists and
anti-Semites? We do not reward, in any other area of American life,
bigots,'' he said.
   Officials at CBS Records said Mottola was on vacation and could
not be reached for comment; other company spokesmen also were
unavailable, they said.
   Russell Simmons, president of Def Jam Records, Public Enemy's
recording company, told The New York Times that ``Welcome to the
Terrordome'' is ``a good record,'' but he did not praise the
controversial lyrics.
   ``They're not great lines, and I'm not happy about it,'' Simmons
said. ``But he was frustrated and that's what he wanted to say. I'm
not defending everything he's saying, but chopping people's records
up is not what I do. And in the end, Public Enemy has done a lot
more good than harm.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>