<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0609EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-JudgeExplosion     12-26 0286</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Judge Explosion,0293</SECOND>
<HEAD>Injured Maryland Judge Released from Hospital</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Sheran is cq in 3rd graf</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HAGERSTOWN, Md. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A judge wounded by a mailed pipe bomb was
released from a hospital and was working with investigators draw up
a list of possible suspects.
   Judge John P. Corderman who lost part of a finger and suffered
ruptured eardrums and other injuries, was released Monday afternoon
from Washington County Hospital, said hospital spokeswoman Sheran
White. His hearing has improved, but doctors hadn't decided if he
will need surgery later, she said.
   U.S. Postal Service investigators were running down ``numerous,
significant leads,'' to Friday's bombing at the judge's apartment,
said Inspector Thomas W. McClure.
   Investigators working with the 47-year-old Washington County
Circuit judge began drawing up a list of people ``with an ax to
grind'' against him, said Hagerstown police Cpl. Michael Small.
   Federal investigators have all but ruled out a connection
between the Hagerstown bombing and mailed pipe bombs in the last 10
days that killed a federal judge in Birmingham, Ala., and a
Savannah, Ga., attorney who handled civil-rights cases.
   Two other bombs connected with that series of attacks have been
disarmed, one at the federal appeals court in Atlanta and one at
the offices of the National Association for the Advancement of
Colored People in Jacksonville, Fla.
   Corderman was active in the effort to pass a law restricting
handguns in Maryland and recently joined the board of a national
group opposed to handgun proliferation.
   He also has angered social clubs in Washington County by
prompting a crackdown on gambling. In 1981, the judge and his
family were given police protection when an anonymous threat
followed a decision on gambling in the private clubs.
</TEXT>

</DOC>