<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0652EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Dogvs.Mailman     12-30 0351</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Dog vs. Mailman,0360</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dog Shot by Mailman to get $500 Funeral</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A dog shot by a mailman will be buried in a
silk-lined casket at Post Office expense, but some neighbors are
saving their sympathy for the postman, who faces felony charges.
   Letter carrier Floyd Sterling, described by one resident as a
``sweet, wonderful man'' and ``gentle as a lamb,'' was charged
Friday with one count each of cruelty to animals, carrying a
concealed weapon and negligent discharge of a firearm.
   If convicted on all counts, Sterling, 34, could go to prison for
more than 5 years, said Deputy District Attorney Myron Jenkins.
   Meanwhile, Skippy, the deceased German shepherd mix, is
scheduled for a $500 memorial service and funeral at Los Angeles
Pet Memorial Park. Arrangments for the funeral Wednesday include a
silk-lined casket, large floral displays, a graveside ceremony and
a headstone, said Lara Ortega, spokeswoman for the memorial park.
   Skippy has some enemies in his suburban Arleta neighborhood.
   Neighbor Beth Adams, 30, the one who praised Sterling's
gentleness, said Skippy is notoriously vicious.
   Others feel Skippy's owner, Tammie Brody, 27, is taking
advantage of the Postal Service offer to pay for the dog's burial.
   ``When my son's dog died after he was hit by a car, we put him
in a box and buried him. And they couldn't have loved that dog
more,'' said neighbor Claire DeNunez. ``This is a little
ridiculous. This family is taking things too far and ... the
taxpayers are paying for it.''
   Sterling shot the dog Tuesday as Ms. Brody was opening the front
door to give the mailman a Christmas bottle of vodka. The letter
carrier said Skippy was menacing him and had bitten him in a
previous run-in.
   At the time of the shooting, Sterling was on probation for a
1988 misdemeanor conviction for carrying a loaded .44 magnum
revolver in his car, according to San Fernando Municipal Court
records.
   The postman was put on paid leave pending an internal
investigation of the incident, postal authorities said. Postal
regulations prohibit workers from carrying firearms on duty.
</TEXT>

</DOC>