<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0208 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1203EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--SpecialGift Adv25   12-21 0663</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Special Gift, Adv 25,0680</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv25</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Monday, Dec. 25, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Girl With Cancer Volunteers for Research</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT IMRIE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MARSHFIELD, Wis. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In the spirit of Christmas, 8-year-old
Carly Bores is giving a gift that may mean a longer life for other
children with cancer.
   Carly, a blue-eyed, red-haired second-grader, has cancer of the
lymph system. She volunteered, through Marshfield Clinic, for an
international study to test new treatments for cancers in children
and infants.
   When doctors discussed with Mike and Laura Bores their
daughter's Hodgkin's disease, it convinced them to let Carly take
part in the study.
   ``All they can tell us is she has an 85 percent chance of being
disease-free for two years,'' Mrs. Bores said. ``They can't say 10
years or 20 years or a lifetime because they don't have those kinds
of records.
   ``The more information they can gather from more people, the
easier it will be to tell parents things like that in the future.''
   Carly's ordeal also has changed the meaning of Christmas for the
family.
   ``This Christmas, the kids will be seeing less under the tree
and more of me. I need to give more of myself,'' Mrs. Bores said,
sitting in a special home on the clinic campus where parents and
children can live while a child receives radiation treatment. The
family's medical bills total $30,000, most of wich has been covered
by insurance.
   The Children's Cancer Study Group, headquartered at the
University of Southern California School of Medicine in Pasadena,
enrolls 6,000 patients each year and has 25,000 in long-term
research, said Dr. John Weiner, administrative director. More than
100 hospitals, including 32 major medical centers, take par in
CCSG, which was founded in 1955.
   All treatments are assigned by the national headquarters, which
also monitors patient progess and evaluates the effectiveness of
new treatments, Weiner said, adding that the research has led to
dramatic progress in finding a cure for childhood cancers. In 1972,
30 percent of youths with lymphatic cancers lived more two years;
the survival rate is now 80 percent.
   ``If we had the perfect treatment in hand today, we wouldn't
stop these clinical trials for another 10 years,'' he said.
   The risk to patients is low, Weiner said. They either receive an
established treatment with proven results or they may get a better
treatment with the new drug or therapy being studied.
   Carly found out in May she had Hodgkin's disease. Doctors don't
know what caused it other than a ``cell decided to divide wrong,''
said Mrs. Bores, who with her husband, Mike, owns an outdoors
sports store in Three Lakes.
   The couple have one other child, 10-year-old Aaron.
   After 12 drug treatments, Carly started radiation therapy in
early December. For the next two years, she will undergo monthly
X-rays and blood tests to make sure the cancer is destroyed.
Because her spleen was removed, she also must take penicillin every
day for the rest of her life.
   ``Usually, if a second cancer occurs, it is within the first two
years. The longer you go past that two-year mark the better your
prognosis is,'' said Mrs. Bores, adding that the shock of finding
out her child had cancer has made her more patient, more flexible
and probably kinder this holiday season. ``I feel so fortunate that
I can take Carly and hug her and love her.''
   As for Carly, she says the most difficult part of her ordeal was
the surgery when a catheter was installed for chemotherapy. She
knows how serious the disease is because a friend died of Hodgkin's
disease two years ago.
   But this is Christmastime, and she's been getting ready as
though her life hasn't changed at all. There's been cookies to
bake, shopping to do and the excitement of hoping she may get more
coins for her collection.
   ``It's the same as last year,'' she said. ``Christmas is
Christmas.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Dec. 25</NOTE>

</DOC>