<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0105 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1540EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     12-21 0413</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0426</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SPRAGUE, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   This hard-luck town was destroyed by fire
in 1895, bypassed by the freeway in the late 1960s, flooded in the
'70s and dumped on by Mount St. Helens at the beginning of this
decade.
   But a state centennial project that transformed a vacant lot
into a plaza celebrating the town's heritage has earned some
residents national recognition.
   Eleven members of the Sprague-Lamont Camp Fire group and four
leaders went to Washington, D.C., this month to receive a
second-place award in the national Keep America Beautiful contest.
   The beautification project began last year when Camp Fire group
leader Rae Anna Victor decided Sprague needed something to stir the
community out of its doldrums and shake its downtrodden image. She
decided to start with a vacant lot covered with weeds, broken glass
and litter.
   The 35 boys and girls in the Camp Fire group were joined by
volunteers in raising $20,000 for the project through bake sales,
spaghetti feeds, raffles, turkey bingo and other fund-raisers.
   The lot was cleared and materials were donated to turn it into
the Sprague Centennial Plaza, complete with gazebo, trees and
grass. A 100-foot mural of 270 painted tiles tells the history of
the town, 35 miles southwest of Spokane.
   ``I get weepy when I even talk about it,'' said Gladys Engles,
80. ``There's more spirit and more Christmas lights in Sprague this
year than ever.''
   ``People used to come out of the drugstore and throw stuff into
the lot and it made the town look small and ugly,'' 11-year-old
Heather Wilken said. ``Now the plaza's made a lot of people stop
and see this town of ours.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>HUNTINGTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Richard Beckner won't slide down your
chimney, but for a small fee he'll bring packages to your door
dressed as Old St. Nick.
   Beckner is one of a few Postal Service employees who will
deliver packages this weekend dressed as Santa Claus. The Santa
service, which is not nationwide, costs $12.
   ``I'll take my time, do a little ho-ho with them and ask the
kids what they want for Christmas,'' Beckner said. ``You just don't
put the box down and say goodbye.''
   Joe Stultz, superintendent at the Huntington Post Office, said
two or three employees will be paid overtime on Saturday and Sunday
to deliver packages in Huntington dressed as Santa.
   ``We just decided to do something for the community,'' said
Stultz. ``We're losing money on it.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>