<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0243 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1359EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s f BC-Eastern-ThenandNow Adv24   12-21 0933</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Eastern-Then and Now, Adv 24,0961</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv24</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Sunday, Dec. 24</HEAD>
<HEAD>Reshaped Eastern Airlines Looks to Future</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto, LaserGraphic</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCY GORDON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   On a sultry night last March, Eastern Airlines
workers exploded at the stroke of midnight in a frenzy of anger
against boss Frank Lorenzo.
   The strike against Eastern had begun, like a giant kettle
venting steam built up for years. More than 2,500 red-shirted
strikers defied riot police, lobbed rocks, bottles and cinderblocks
at their employer's fenced Miami headquarters and shredded a ``scab
worker'' effigy.
   Ten months later, the Eastern drama has been played out in
federal bankruptcy court, Congress and smoke-filled union halls.
The most emotional strike in U.S. airline history has been broken
and the strikers are broke.
   It was more than a wage dispute. It was a show of force between
an owner seeking to reshape a moneylosing airline and employees
determined to block what they considered his union-busting.
   Lorenzo, who bought Eastern in early 1986, seems to have left
his mark on industrial history with a key victory. He has
vanquished the unions, hired replacements at lower wages and
restructured Eastern as a smaller carrier.
   ``It's a tragedy of all sorts of dimensions,'' said Mark Kahn,
an independent labor arbitrator in Detroit. ``He (Lorenzo) has
completely undermined the notion of loyalty on the part of
employees.''
   The pilots, who crippled the airline in March by walking out in
sympathy with the Machinists, capitulated just before Thanksgiving.
Striking flight attendants did the same. But both groups face bleak
prospects of returning to their old jobs, filled mainly by
non-union hires.
   Only the Machinists remain on lonely picket lines. Many have
scraped by with part-time work to supplement $100 a week in union
strike pay. Some have left to take jobs elsewhere.
   Still, Lorenzo's victory might prove short-lived. The strikers
may not get their jobs back but they might feel partly vindicated
if the new year brings a serious recession _ which could knock a
fragile Eastern off its feet.
   ``A recession would have a very strong impact,'' said Louis A.
Marckesano, an airline analyst at Janney Montgomery Scott Inc. in
Philadelphia.
   Many experts are expecting the economy to weaken substantially
next year, and the airline industry usually bears the brunt of a
downturn. Analysts single out Eastern, Pan Am Corp. and Trans World
Airlines Inc. as financially shaky and the most vulnerable.
   It would be difficult for Eastern to lure passengers with cheap
fares in a recession, since all the big carriers now price flights
competitively and fare cuts are usually matched by rivals.
   Marckesano said Eastern's recent projection that it will turn a
``modest'' profit in the second half of next year is an optimistic
forecast. The airline told creditors this past week it expects to
lose $250 million in the fourth quarter. That would bring Eastern's
net loss for 1989 to nearly $820 million _ a record high for the
nation's airline industry.
   Can Lorenzo, chairman of Eastern's parent Texas Air Corp. and
the most aggressive practitioner of airline deregulation, pull off
his bold gambit?
   ``Do they (Eastern) have a chance? Sure, but it can be quite a
task,'' said Edward Starkman, who follows the industry for
PaineWebber Inc. in New York. He called the reshaped Eastern
``basically a startup airline ... an Atlanta-hubbed airline with
some Northeast-to-Florida business.''
   In recent months, Eastern has been building up Atlanta as its
hub and ``de-hubbing'' Miami, where it still maintains its
headquarters near the airport.
   Lorenzo's knockout punch came this past week, when rival
American Airlines finally agreed after months of haggling to buy
Eastern's prized Latin American routes and other assets from Texas
Air for $471 million. In one stroke, the deal made American a major
international carrier and shrank Eastern to about two-thirds of its
prestrike size.
   The deal with American capped a series of sales of Eastern jets,
routes and airport gates to several other airlines. The asset
sales, made over several months and approved by U.S. Bankruptcy
Judge Burton R. Lifland, already had totaled about $688 million
before the Latin American routes were transferred.
   The proceeds, put into an escrow account, will be used to pay
Eastern's creditors.
   For the longer term, many observers believe Lorenzo's ultimate
master plan is to merge Eastern with sister carrier Continental
Airlines, the other main subsidiary of Texas Air. The gradual
disappearance of the unions from Eastern would allow a fit with
non-union Continental.
   Lorenzo's handling of Continental seemed to be a dress rehearsal
for what happened at Eastern: he restructured Continental as a
non-union carrier in 1983 after a strike and bankruptcy proceeding.
   Observers believe a merger of the two could come sometime after
Eastern emerges from Chapter 11 protection, anticipated for early
next year.
   ``I think subsequently the two airlines will merge; there'll be
no point in keeping them apart, from Texas Air's point of view,''
said Kahn. ``In effect, you've got one airline operating as two
divisions.''
   The Eastern unions have long suspected Lorenzo intended to merge
the two airlines, charging that his transfers of some Eastern
assets to Continental are part of the plan.
   The issue is so emotionally charged that even flight attendants'
uniforms have been swept up into the dispute. New navy blue outfits
for attendants at Eastern and Continental due early next year have
raised the unions' hackles, since they are almost the same for both
carriers and replace uniforms that were completely different colors.
   But then again, everything about Eastern is emotional _ and
seemingly intractable.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Sunday, Dec. 24</NOTE>

</DOC>