<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0192 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1819EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-MailBombs     12-20 0626</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mail Bombs,0642</SECOND>
<HEAD>Slain Federal Judge Eulogized Under Tight Security</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Mail Bombs-Jacksonville, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto XBM3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HOYT HARWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOUNTAIN BROOK, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bomb-sniffing dogs and squadrons of
police provided tight security Wednesday as a crowd of mourners
paid their respects to a federal appeals judge killed by the first
in a series of mail bombs.
   St. Luke's Episcopal Church was filled to overflowing with more
than 700 people who were asked to put aside their anger over the
slaying long enough to remember the contributions of U.S. Circuit
Judge Robert Vance.
   Dogs searched the church before the service, and dozens of
officers kept watch during the 35-minute program of scripture,
hymns and a eulogy.
   Vance, a member of the 11th U.S. Circuit Court and a former
chairman of the Alabama Democratic Party, was killed instantly last
Saturday when the bomb exploded in his home, propelling nails into
his lower abdomen. His wife, Helen, was injured in the bombing and
remained hospitalized Wednesday.
   A similar bomb two days later killed a civil rights lawyer in
Savannah, Ga., City Alderman Robert Robinson. A package bomb was
found in the Atlanta courthouse including the 11th Circuit on
Monday and a fourth mailed bomb was removed Tuesday from the NAACP
headquarters in Jacksonville, Fla.
   All four targets can be linked to school desegregation efforts
by the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People,
leading investigators to speculate that a white racist group may be
responsible.
   Four anonymous letters mailed in August to declare war on
various federal appeals courts are being examined for clues to the
bombings, FBI spokesman Greg Jones said Wednesday in Washington.
   The bombs and threats has prompted the NAACP to boost security
at its offices, executive director Benjamin Hooks said Wednesday at
the organization's national headquarters in Baltimore.
   Hooks said he's convinced the bombs were the work of white
supremacists who feel threatened by recent victories for blacks in
courtrooms and at the polls.
   ``I think it's the work of white supremacists, without any
question. I think it reveals the derangement, demented, criminally
stupid minds,'' he said.
   Leaders of the Ku Klux Klan are denying any involvement.
   ``There ain't nobody in any white supremacist group got sense
enough to make a bomb,'' said Daniel B. Carver, Georgia grand
dragon of the Invisible Empire Knights of the Ku Klux Klan. ``I'm
hoping if it's one of those big drug dealers, maybe they'll take
credit for it and get the FBI off our backs.''
   Carver was one of several defendants who had appealed a $950,000
jury verdict against two Klan groups for pelting civil rights
marchers with rocks and bottles in Forsyth County. The 11th Circuit
refused in October to rehear the defendants' appeal.
   At Vance's service, U.S. Bankruptcy Judge Clifford Fulford of
Birmingham, a close friend of Vance, delivered the eulogy, asking
the mourners to ``put aside our outrage for awhile'' to honor Vance.
   ``The assassins were cheated if they thought that Bob Vance was
afraid to die,'' Fulford said. He described the 58-year-old Vance
as a strong believer in the law and a man ``who stood up for the
underdog and the oppressed.''
   ``No wonder his assassins could not stand such a man in their
presence.''
   Friends of the Vance family said his remains have been cremated
and his ashes will be placed in the church.
   Because of the rash of bombs, and the attendance of public
officials, the church, south of Birmingham, was surrounded by
police barriers and cordoned off with yellow tape.
   Among those who attended the service were Sessions, Attorney
General Dick Thornburgh, Supreme Court Justice Anthony Kennedy, the
justice who oversees the operations of the 11th Circuit, which
handles appeals from Floria, Georgia and Alabama.
</TEXT>

</DOC>