<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1424EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-Jokes     12-26 0452</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Jokes,0464</SECOND>
<HEAD>Months of Political Turmoil Releases Wave of Dark Humor</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH G. SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lights and decorations brighten the city on
both sides of the Berlin Wall during the Christmas season, but dark
humor holds sway in the streets of the still-divided city.
   For decades, jokes poking fun at the once-mighty Communist
regime remained among family and friends in East Berlin, but biting
humor surfaced openly this fall with the decline of the Communists
and the secret police.
   Most of the jokes floating across the now-porous borders focus
on ousted East German leader Erich Honecker and the corrupt
Communist Party he once headed, as well as the rotten economic
situation he left behind.
   A favorite joke concerns the future of the East German flag with
the familiar compass and sickle emblem embroidered on the
orange-and-black national colors. An unadorned version serves as
the West German flag.
   ``What is the new emblem for the flag?'' goes the question. ``A
suitcase,'' is the answer _ a reference to the more than 320,000
East Germans who have left for West Germany in search of a better
life this year alone.
   Although Honecker, who is reportedly seriously ill, was stripped
of power on Oct. 18 and has been in seclusion ever since,
variations of jokes about him are told over and over in bars,
stores and taxis.
   ``Why has Honecker checked into a hotel on the Hungarian
border?'' asks one East German. ``Because all the best doctors pass
by there,'' replies another.
   Other jokes concern the East German Communist Party, which has
lost some 700,000 members since the political trouble began earlier
this year.
   ``What does a party member who finds one new party member get?''
went a joke that circulated during a recent party congress that
swept away remnants of the old guard. ``He gets to leave the
party.''
   ``What does a party member who enrolls 10 new members get?'' the
joke continues. ``A certificate that he was never a party member,''
goes the reply.
   A few of the jokes are simply unquotable. ``I know a lot of
jokes, But you could never print them and this isn't the right
place to tell them,'' said an East German border guard at the
famous Checkpoint Charlie crossing point.
   Not all of the humor is aimed at East Germany. West German
Chancellor Helmut Kohl, a target of sometimes vicious jokes in his
homeland, has found similar treatment in East Germany.
   Some East Germans have welcomed the West German leader. ``Lieber
Kohl als Sauerkraut,'' or ``Better Kohl than Sauerkraut,'' read one
banner displayed in Dresden during Kohl's trip there earlier this
week. The word Kohl means cabbage in German.
</TEXT>

</DOC>