<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0316EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-WashingtonInBrief     12-19 0523</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Washington In Brief,540</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge Declares Leaflet Regulation Unconstitutional</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 1976 regulation barring people from passing
out leaflets near the White House has been declared
unconstitutional by a federal judge who says such a ban violates
the First Amendment and has ``no conceivable governmental
interest.''
   U.S. District Court Judge John Pratt ruled Monday in the case of
Carol Ann Fennelly, charged with illegally distributing pamphlets
in June on a street between the White House and Treasury Department.
   The material urged passers-by to write members of Congress in
favor of housing for the homeless.
   Regulations approved in 1970 were part of an effort to protect
White House security by restrictions on demonstrations. The
provision at issue in Fennelly's case was added in 1976 to preserve
an atmosphere of calm and tranquility at memorials and buildings
associated with past presidents.
   Pratt noted that Fennelly ``would violate the regulation by
passing out a leaflet,'' but ``could convey the same identical
message by word of mouth without fear of arrest.''
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Ukrainian Dissident Receives Cancer Treatment in U.S.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The wife of a Ukrainian dissident is being
treated in the United States for a possible recurrence of cancer as
105 members of Congress try to get Soviet President Mikhail S.
Gorbachev to give her a temporary exit visa.
   Olha Horyn, who arrived in the United States on Saturday, had
applied for a temporary visa seven months ago. She did not
immediately get it despite a new Soviet law that guarantees a
decision on medical visa requests within three days, said Rep.
Louise Slaughter, D-N.Y. Slaughter and 104 colleagues have sent a
letter to Gorbachev seeking a temporary visa.
   Mrs. Horyn had a radical mastectomy 10 years ago, but is
suffering back pain that may indicate the cancer has returned.
   Her husband is Mikhailo Horyn, a former political prisoner and
general secretary of the Ukrainian national movement, Rukh. He is
also a candidate for a seat in the Ukrainian parliament.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Stamp Ornaments Offered by Postal Service</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tree ornaments featuring the U.S. Postal
Service's annual Christmas stamps are being offered this year.
   The silverplated ornaments, which sell for $12.95 each, are
being offered in about a third of the agency's divisions or may be
ordered from the Postal Service Philatelic Sales Division in
Washington.
   The ornaments feature the annual Christmas stamps, either the
religious or secular design. The stamps are sealed in a clear resin
and surrounded by a silver tracery styled as clusters of holly
leaves and berries.
   Divisions where the ornaments were being offered are:
   Baltimore and Prince Georges, Md.; Brooklyn, N.Y.; Chicago and
South Suburban, Ill.; Columbia, S.C.; Cleveland and Columbus, Ohio;
Dallas and Houston, Texas; Denver; Des Moines; Detroit and Grand
Rapids, Mich.; Greensboro, N.C.; Hartford, Conn.; Indianapolis;
Kansas City, Mo.; Los Angeles, Oakland, San Diego, Santa Ana and
Van Nuys, Calif.; Memphis and Nashville, Tenn.; Minneapolis; New
Brunswick, N.J.; Omaha, Neb.; Philadelphia; Richmond,
Charlottesville, Norfolk, Roanoke and Northern Virginia; St. Louis;
Salt Lake City; Springfield, Mass.; and Tampa, Fla.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Eds: The ornaments may be ordered from: U.S.P.S. Philatelic
Sales Division, Washington, D.C., 20265-9997.
</TEXT>

</DOC>