<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0264 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1050EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-Bloomingdale'sBidders     12-20 0314</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bloomingdale's Bidders,0325</SECOND>
<HEAD>Developer Trump Among Bidders for Bloomingdale's, Report Says</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Property developer and airline owner Donald
Trump is among about half a dozen bidders who are considering a
purchase of Campeau Corp.'s Bloomingdale's department store chain,
according to a report published today.
   Susan Heilbron, a spokeswoman for the Trump Organization,
declined to comment today on the report in The Wall Street Journal.
   The newspaper said Trump and the other bidders have advanced to
the second stage of the bidding process and will be given access to
detailed financial information about the 17-store chain.
   In addition to Trump, the bidders include shopping center owner
JMB Realty Corp. based in Chicago, Japan's Tokyu Department Store
Co. and a group led by Joseph E. Brooks, chairman of the Ann Taylor
stores, the Journal said, citing unidentified sources.
   An investment group headed by Bloomingdale's Chairman Marvin
Traub also is among the bidders although the group doesn't have a
financial partner yet, the newspaper said. Ira Millstein, an
adviser to Traub and a senior partner with the law firm Weil,
Gotshal &amp; Manges, told the Journal the group is engaged in serious
discussions with potential partners.
   A sixth bidder, possibly Japanese, also is believed to be
involved in the bidding, the Journal said.
   Campeau put Bloomingdale's up for sale in September as part of
plan to cope with a cash squeeze.
   The company announced on Dec. 8 that the initial stage of the
sale process had been concluded and that no more than five or six
bidders would advance to the second round. A definitive
announcement on the sale of New York-based Bloomingdale's is
sometime in February, Campeau said.
   Campeau, a Canadian company based in Toronto, has said detailed
information about the bidders would not be disclosed and that all
negotiations would be kept confidential. Spokeswoman Carol Sanger
couldn't be reached early today.
</TEXT>

</DOC>