<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0300EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-TelephoneRates     12-20 0721</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Telephone Rates,670</SECOND>
<HEAD>Many Long Distance Phone Rates to Drop in 1990</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By W. DALE NELSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Many long distance telephone rates to points
in the United States and abroad will be going down after the first
of the year, the three major long distance companies say.
   American Telephone and Telegraph Co. filed reductions with the
Federal Communications Commission Tuesday. MCI Communications Corp.
and U.S. Sprint said they will take action to remain competitive.
   AT&amp;T says it has about 70 percent of the long distance market,
as measured by interstate and intrastate revenues. MCI is No. 2
with more than 10 percent. U.S. Sprint claims 7 to 8 percent.
   The AT&amp;T reductions will take effect Jan. 1, barring an unusual
action by the FCC to block them.
   The company said the reductions were taken in line with an FCC
price cap which has been reduced because local telephone companies
are charging long distance companies less for access to customers'
lines.
   AT&amp;T's submission to the FCC called for $300 million a year in
reductions on interstate and international long distance services
used primarily by residential and small business customers. Other
categories of service used by businesses, such as private lines and
800 and 900 numbers, are not affected.
   MCI spokesman John Hauser said the No. 2 long distance company
also will reduce its rates to pass on the savings in local
telephone company charges. ``We will remain competitive with
them,'' he said. ``I don't know how much our total cost savings
will be.''
   Hauser's counterpart at U.S. Sprint, Robin Pence, said, ``We are
reviewing the filing and we intend to remain competitive.''
   The company said price reductions will apply to its ``Reach Out
America'' and optional long distance plans as well as to basic long
distance service.
   A 10-minute call during daytime hours on a weekday, to anywhere
in the United States, will cost $2.50 or less, a decrease of 1.3
percent on the average, the company said. Some of the increases
would be greater. For example, a 10-minute daytime call from
Washington to New York, which now costs $2.30, would decline to
$2.20. Daytime hours are 8 a.m. to 5 p.m. local time Monday through
Friday.
   In the evening, the rate for a call to anywhere in the United
States will drop by an average of 2 percent, the company said. An
evening call from Washington to San Francisco, Los Angeles or
Dallas, which now costs $1.67 for 10 minutes, would be $1.58. The
evening period is 5 p.m. to 11 p.m. Sunday through Friday.
   Weekend rates are in effect all day Saturday and until 5 p.m. on
Sunday and the same rates apply from 11 p.m. to 8 a.m. Sunday
through Friday. These rates will not change. The maximum for such a
call is $1.32 for 10 minutes within the United States, the company
said.
   Discounts for subscribers to the Reach Out America 24-hour plan
will be increased from 5 percent to 10 percent on weekday calls and
from 20 to 25 percent on evening calls. Under Reach Out America,
the evening period is 5 p.m. to 10 p.m. Sunday through Friday.
   International calls from the U.S. mainland to 25 of the most
frequently called countries and overseas areas will be slashed by
$104 million. The reductions will vary from country to country and
the countries will include Canada, Mexico, Japan, the United
Kingdom, France, Italy, Israel, Brazil, Australia, the Philippines,
Taiwan and Korea.
   A five-minute call from anywhere in the United States to Japan
between 2 and 8 p.m., now $8.72 at the standard rate prevailing in
those hours, will drop to $8.07. A similar call to Britain between
1 and 6 p.m., when discount rates are in effect for such calls,
will decline from $4.21 to $3.99. Calls to Mexico will decline from
2 to 20 percent, depending on the time and the city from which the
call is placed. A five-minute call from New York to Cancun, now
$7.90 at the standard rate, will drop to $5.90. Five minutes from
Los Angeles to Mexico City, now $6.15, will cost $5.55.
   AT&amp;T said the reduction will be the company's 10th since 1984
and would bring total rate decreases to 40 percent in the six years
since the breakup of the Bell System.
</TEXT>

</DOC>