<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0938EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-Fighting     12-21 0518</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Fighting,520</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Spokesman Said Fighting Has Subsided</HEAD>
<UNK>EDITOR'S NOTE: The following report was filed by members of the Pentagon
media pool that accompanied the U.S. invasion force into Panama.    </UNK>
<DATELINE>SOUTHERN COMMAND, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. military officials say they
have concluded that most of the fighting between pro-Noriega forces
and American troops has subsided and that little real threat
remains.
   Col. Ronald Sconyers, director of public affairs for the U.S.
Southern Command, said Wednesday evening that a lot of the sporadic
gunfire still being heard around the country is from roving bands
of Noriega loyalists, known as Dignity Battlations, who are ``just
getting their last licks in.''
   Early Wednesday morning, John Bushnell, the U.S. charge
d'affaires in Panama, briefed the pool after President Bush spoke
to the nation. He said it was the clear desire of the new
government to take contol.
   Bushnell said he had dinner Monday night with three officials
that U.S. authorities say were elected in May 7 balloting:
President Guillermo Endara and Vice Presidents Ricardo Arias
Calderon and Guillermo Ford. Noriega annulled the elections.
   After getting pledges of secrecy from the civilian leaders,
Bushnell said he outlined the scope of the U.S. military plans. He
said they wrote Bush a letter affirming their support for the U.S.
assistance.
   Asked why the Panamanian civilian leaders had changed their
minds about having U.S. rather than Panamanian forces oust Noriega,
Bushnell said there had been no snap conversion.
   ``I don't think it was overnight,'' he said. ``It was a matter
that the Panamanians weren't being very successful in doing it.''
   After the failed coup on Oct. 3, he said, ``there was a feeling
that, well, there weren't many more Panamanians left with guns that
might do it, so it was becoming a hopeless situation.''
   ``They never said it so many words, `we wish you would really
send the 82nd Airborne to do it,' but they clearly indicated their
frustration that if we didn't, the situation was just going to go
on and get worse,'' Bushnell said.
   The new leaders' main concern, he said, was that if Noriega were
shot, another Panamanian Defense Force colonel might take his place.
   Bushnell said he thinks ``it is certainly possible'' that
Noriega might run for the hills to hide out or possibly seek refuge
in Cuba or Nicaragua. But he said it was unlikely he would take to
the hills to form a guerrilla movement inside Panama because he
lacks sufficient popular support.
   Bushnell said calls were made to Panamanan Defense Force
representatives by both the new government leaders and military
officers. In some instances, he said, the military officers would
speak to whomever answered the telephone at PDF headquarters and
say in effect: ``This is suicide _ pack it in.''
   At least two mortar rounds hit the embassy Wednesday, U.S.
officials said. Bushnell said that although Noriega remained at
large, officials had expectations at the outset of the operation
that he could be seized.
   ``If he had been at one of the several places we took down, we
would have gotten him. But he wasn't,'' Bushness said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>