<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0131 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1727EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Bush-China     12-21 0357</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-China,350</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Defends Mission To China</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM RAUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush vigorously defended sending
unannounced high-level missions to Beijing, saying Thursday that if
Americans didn't approve, ``I expect they'd get somebody else to
take my job.''
   Bush compared his sending envoys to China in July and in August,
despite the government's bloody Tiananmen Square crackdown against
protesters in June, to then-President Nixon's decision to dispatch
aide Henry Kissinger to China in 1972.
   ``The whole opening to China would never have happened if
Kissinger hadn't undertaken that mission. It would have fallen
apart. So you have to use your own judgment,'' Bush told a news
conference.
   He denied that sending his national security adviser, Brent
Scowcroft, and a senior State Department official to Beijing on the
two trips represented a violation of sanctions he imposed on China.
   Bush ordered a halt to ``high level exchanges'' which he
insisted Thursday did not apply to government-to-government
contacts between officials.
   The administration claims that Scowcroft's visits were
``contacts'' rather than ``exchanges.''
   Bush said he felt ``no obligation'' to announce the missions.
   ``I feel an obligation to keep you informed, but I have an
obligation as president to conduct the foreign policy of this
country the way I see fit, reporting under the law to the United
States Congress.''
   Asked if similar clandesdine missions were now under way, Bush
said, ``maybe not of that magnitude (but) there's a lot of going on
in the conduct of the foreign policy that ... has to be sorted out
without the spotlight of the news.''
   ``You've got your job and that is to find out absolutely
everything you can,'' Bush told reporters. ``But I have mine, and
that is to conduct the foreign policy of this country the way I
think best. ... If the American people don't like it, I suspect
they'd get somebody else to take my job.''
   Bush also noted that he had been criticized from some quarters
for not announcing sooner his Mediterranean meeting with Soviet
President Mikhail S. earlier this month.
   ``I don't agree with that. And I was elected,'' Bush insisted.
</TEXT>

</DOC>