<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0137 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1414EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     12-20 0616</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0637</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JACKSONVILLE, Ark. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ice-covered roads made the bus ride
after school a harrowing experience, but one man's hospitality made
everything turn out right.
   Six students attending Little Rock schools never reached home
Monday night. Instead, they spent a snug night at the home of their
bus driver.
   ``What else could I have done?'' Carl Wilcox, 58, said Tuesday.
``The bus is family. We're a small group and we're together a lot
during the day, so we're family.''
   ``I'm proud that we have a man who confirmed to the kids that he
would put them up and see to their well-being,'' said David Booth,
an assistant supervisor with the Pulaski County School District's
Transportation Department.
   Wilcox said the slow journey on the bus included a three-hour
traffic jam on highways, waiting in vain for traffic to clear
during an hour-long stay at one student's house, losing traction
between two hills being towed a half-mile backward by Sherwood
firefighters, and narrowly missing a man standing in the road.
   Donna Peterman, 15, said Wilcox told them to keep their seat
belts on and talk to their friends to take their mind off the road.
She and Carl Atkins, 16, said the students sang, played cards and
talked.
   Then the bus got stuck in a ditch. Wilcox and his riders were
taken to the Sherwood Police Department, and the city's fire
department took all seven people to Wilcox's home at about 11 p.m.
in four-wheel-drive vehicles.
   There, Wilcox said, he and his wife Jean fed them hot dogs and
pizzas and put them to bed _ three girls in the couple's own bed
and three boys in beds formerly used by the couple's grown
children. Wilcox said he and his wife slept on a fold-out couch in
their living room.
   ``He's a hero,'' said Atkins. ``He got us out of the mess and
kept everyone calm.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Santa Claus weighs too much, probably has high
cholesterol, eats too many cookies on Christmas Eve and should
exercise more than once a year, but health experts are impressed by
his longevity.
   As far as physicians can determine, Saint Nick is about 1,700
years old.
   ``He must be doing something right to have lived this long,''
Kathy Gonzalez, a dietician at Pittsburgh's St. Margaret Memorial
Hospital, said.
   Health experts worry he inhales too much soot scurrying up and
down chimneys and spends too much time in the cold.
   ``He is clearly overweight and probably has a cardiac problem,''
said Eleanor Streiff, chief of disease control for the Allegheny
County Health Department. ``He probably also has pulmonary problems
from going down chimneys and getting all that dirt in his lungs.''
   Also, driving instructors and physicians wonder how a
17-century-old man has managed to keep a license to operate an
airborne vehicle, even one powered by eight tiny reindeer.
   Santa's unhealthy habits go back at least 180 years, when
Washington Irving described him as fat and was puffing a
long-stemmed pipe.
   ``Santa would certainly be at increased risk of cancer of the
lip or mouth,'' Dr. Ronald Heberman, director of the Pittsburgh
Cancer Institute, said.
   The psychological impact of Santa spending months of unending
darkness at the North Pole worries Dr. Trevor Price, chairman of
Allegheny General Hospital's psychiatry department.
   Price suggested Santa's toy-giving spree is his way of coping
with his generally gloomy winter mood.
   But there is good news about Santa's health.
   ``Children are leaving glasses of low-fat milk and plates of
high-fiber cookies and muffins for him, and that may help fend off
the effects of the other risk factors,'' said Sharon Sclabassi,
director of the American Heart Association's southwest Pennsylvania
office.
</TEXT>

</DOC>