<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0249 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2343EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-EC-GATT     12-19 0345</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EC-GATT,0359</SECOND>
<HEAD>EC To Propose Farm Reform Plan That Retains Farm Subsidies</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRUSSELS, Belgium (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The European Community will unveil on
Wednesday a proposal to reduce, but not eliminate, farm subsidies
over a period of five years.
   The plan, officials said Tuesday, represents the EC position in
crucial talks to reform agricultural trade in the current round of
talks within the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade, the
Geneva-based world trade body.
   The EC position was approved late Monday at a meeting of the 12
EC foreign ministers. It contrasts with that of the United States,
which wants to eventually eliminate all farm subsidies.
   ``With this proposal the EC is taking the initiative in the farm
negotiations,'' an EC Commission source said.
   In it, the EC maintains its opposition to a long-term
elimination of subsidies, calling instead for a ``progressive
reduction in support'' over five years with a review of the
situation at the end of that period.
   Under a U.S. plan presented to GATT, existing agricultural
subsidies would be converted into more visible tariffs that
gradually would be reduced.
   The EC came slightly closer to the U.S. proposal by recommending
a partial conversion of the trade curbs into fixed tariffs. But it
has said cuts in some price supports should be ``rebalanced'' by
raising others.
   The U.S. opposes this, arguing it cannot accept any increases in
trade barriers.
   A controversial element of the EC proposal is the suggestion
that countries receive a ``credit'' for subsidy cuts made since
1986, when the current Uruguay round of GATT talks began.
   The EC says it has built up large credits through changes it has
made in its farm support program over the last three years.
   The EC seeks a ``global'' approach, with all trade-distorting
subsidies _ from export refunds to price guarantees _ covered in
the negotiations. It wants an international agreement on a common
measure of support that would be the basis for subsidy cuts by all
GATT parties.
   For its part, the United States has been looking for commitments
on individual support measures.
</TEXT>

</DOC>