<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0173 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1805EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-PanamaPool-Documents     12-22 0450</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama Pool-Documents,440</SECOND>
<HEAD>Office Search Yields Unusual Items, Few Clues to Noriega's Whereabouts</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   EDITOR'S NOTE: The following is from a pool dispatch filed by
Kevin Marida of The Dallas Morning News, Kathy Lewis of the Houston
Post, Dick Thompson of Time magazine and Bill Clayton of the
Houston Chronicle.
   FORT AMADOR, Panama _ Military intelligence officers were
sifting through papers contained in Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega's
offices Friday, hoping to find clues to his whereabouts.
   ``That's the purpose _ try to evaluate it for intelligence
value,'' said Lt. Tod Furtado of the Army intelligence division.
``If there's something we can use to track the names of people who
might know his whereabouts, that's what we want to do.''
   ``The most important thing now is finding Noriega,'' he added.
   Reporters were given a tour of offices used by Noriega and the
Panamanian Defense Forces in a building on the Panamanian side of
Fort Amador _ a military installation that until Wednesday was
shared by Panama and the United States.
   It appears Noriega was careful not to leave many secrets lying
around, said Furtado. Even his calendars provided few clues about
his activities, he said.
   Military troops seized the building Wednesday morning after the
shelling of PDF barracks on the base.
   Military troops found 500 to 600 weapons inside, including a
variety of machine guns, hand guns and rifles. The tour of
Noriega's quarters revealed an opulent lifestyle and pornography.
   Military officials said they found a number of phallic symbols
and pornographic photos in Noriega's personal office. In another
tour of PDF headquarters Friday, photos of nude women in graphic
poses were lying around in Noriega's office.
   ``I couldn't see President Bush keeping crap like that,''
Furtado said.
   Military officials found one envelope, dated sometime in
September and stamped official, that contained nothing but
pornographic photos. It was sent from a Panamanian consulate in
another country with the note: ``Enjoy the good times. To the
seditious ones _ give them the stick.''
   The two floors of offices contained Noriega's collection of
stuffed bears dressed in military uniforms, two display cases of
frog statues, a video wrist watch and a Sharp Wizard computer
diary. On Noriega's personal desk was a bottle of Krog champagne.
He had an Acer computer and Sony stereo equipment.
   ``He lived a very opulent life,'' said Furtado.
   Col. Mike Snell, the Task Force Bayonet commander, said ``If
you've got to be a petty dictator, you might as well live well, I
guess.''
   Noriega kept a conference room and library at the building,
which was layered inside with plush carpeting.
   There was a decorated Christmas tree upstairs and one downstairs.
   In the courtyard was a parrot in a cage.
</TEXT>

</DOC>