<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0113 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1657EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Reax 1stLd-Writethru a0642 12-19 0666</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Reax, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0642,0685</SECOND>
<HEAD>Other Nations Denounce Romanian Repression</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 2 grafs after 16th `In Prague' with opposition reaction;
picks up 17th pvs `Poland's parliament'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROLAND PRINZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Leaders of East and West were united
Tuesday in denouncing Romania's Stalinist regime for the bloody
repression of protesters.
   Some reports said hundreds of people were killed when Romanian
security forces opened fire over the weekend on demonstrators
protesting the harsh rule of President Nicolae Ceausescu, the last
autocrat in the Soviet bloc.
   Foreign Minister Eduard A. Shevardnadze of the Soviet Union said
that, if the reports of bloodshed were true, ``I can only express
my very profound regret. We are categorically opposed to the use of
force.''
   Shevardnadze was at a meeting of about 200 members of the
European Parliament in Brussels.
   There was no comment in Beijing, where the Chinese government
crushed a peaceful pro-democracy movement with tanks on June 4-5.
   In Washington, White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said:
``The repressive measures undertaken by the Romanian government are
totally unjustified and stand in stark contrast to the positive
changes taking place elsewhere in Eastern Europe.''
   A minister in the British Foreign Office, William Waldegrave,
warned Romanian officials of what may lie ahead.
   ``Those in the security services, those working for the state,
should recognize that a day of reckoning will come for them as it
has come for the East Germans and others,'' he said. ``The right
thing for them to do ... is to represent the true will of the
Romanian people and put an end to this regime.''
   Stan Soare, the Romanian ambassador, was summoned to receive a
protest expressed in ``the strongest possible terms'' a British
government spokesman said, and responded by ``resorting to the
tired old formula of alleging interference in Romania's internal
affairs.''
   In its first protest to another member of the Soviet bloc,
Bulgaria expressed ``serious concern'' to the Romanian Embassy in
Sofia over the closing of the frontier.
   Romania closed its borders Monday allowing passage only to
diplomats and other officials.
   Foreign ministers of the 12 European Community nations denounced
the violence and several governments lodged official protests with
Romanian diplomats.
   A statement by the 12 foreign ministers issued in Brussels said
Ceausescu's regime was ``turning its back on all the commitments
concerning human rights to which it has subscribed'' in the 1975
Helsinki agreements on human rights.
   Ceausescu ``is capable only of repressing by force the
legitimate aspirations of the Romanian people to freedom,'' they
said.
   Thousands of exiled Romanians were said to be planning a rally
Thursday in London.
   In Prague, the Czechoslovak Foreign Ministry said: ``We
resolutely protest the use of army and police against
demonstrators.''
   Vaclav Havel, the opposition leader and presidential candidate,
said to reporters: ``When and if we have greater influence on
Czechoslovakia's foreign policy ... we'll be able to do more for
Romanians and Hungarians in Romania who are being killed by this
terrible, Dracula-like person.''
   A statement from Civic Forum, Havel's opposition group, said
Czechoslovkia was ``learning with horror of the brutal
intervention'' and was ``deeply shaken.''
   Poland's parliament passed a resolution saying Romanian
``authorities used force with exceptional brutality. Even children
were the targets of shooting.''
   Austria's Foreign Ministry said its protest of ``catastrophic
human rights practice in Romania'' was rejected by the Romanian
charge d'affaires, Marian Radu, who also was unwilling ``to give
expedient information verbally on the situation in Romania.''
   In neighboring Hungary, feelings ran high because up to 1.7
million ethnic Hungarians live in Transylvania, the area of western
Romania where the violence occurred.
   Premier Miklos Nemeth said ``anachronistic regimes opposed to
progress cannot remain in place'' if Europe is to be united.
   Nepszabadsag, the official party of the Socialist _ formerly
Communist _ Party, said: ``History has already witnessed the reign
of regimes, not so long ago, that showed off their strength with
tanks before being overthrown by the rage of the people.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>