<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0110 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1552EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Czechoslovakia     12-21 0542</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Czechoslovakia,0565</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former President Suspended from Party Pending Investigation</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SYDNEY RUBIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Communist Party on Thursday
suspended former President Gustav Husak and 31 other former party
leaders pending an investigation into abuse of power.
   In their effort to clean up the party's image and prepare it for
free elections next year, delegates to a party congress also:
   _ Elected a new, steamlined policy-making Central Committee.
   _ Voted to disband a hated paramilitary militia used to crush
dissent.
   _ Adopted a new ``action program'' urging a break with the
Stalinist past.
   _ Expelled the man considered most responsible for the 1968
Warsaw Pact invasion that crushed reforms.
   Husak and the other party leaders were suspended for ``serious
political mistakes'' that will be investigated by a special
commission set up by the new Central Committee.
   Former Communist Premier Lubomir Strougal also was on the list,
which party spokesman Josef Hora said could be expanded.
   Results of the investigation, which could lead to expulsion from
party ranks, are to be delivered at a regular party congress in
May. Altogether, 32 officials will be investigated, Hora told
reporters on the final day of the congress.
   Husak and other hard-liners installed after the 1968 crackdown
have all been driven from power in a popular revolution that ended
the Communist Party's 41-year monopoly on power and led to a
government dominated by non-Communists.
   Former ideology chief Vasil Bilak was expelled Thursday ``as a
representative of forces who initiated the invasion'' of 1968.
   He is viewed by many Czechoslovaks as the man most responsible
for the Soviet-led invasion, which was recently denounced by
Czechoslovakia and by the five Warsaw Pact nations that
participated.
   He stepped down from the ruling Politburo last year and from the
presidium of Czechoslovakia's Parliament Dec. 12.
   The names of the new Central Committee members were not
released. Hora said the new body contains mostly new faces and was
cut to 138 members from its previous 156 members.
   The new ``action program'' calls for the rapid elimination of
the ``Stalinist model of the party and society.''
   ``What we are pursuing is the transformation of the Communist
party into a modern political party which will become party of the
democratic movement of the European left,'' it said.
   The day's session began with delegates voting to disband
immediately the despised paramilitary People's Militia.
   The uniformed militia, which had been under the direct control
of the party, was disarmed Dec. 3 and its weapons stored in army
warehouses.
   The last time it was used was in January, assisting riot polcie
to suppress demonstrations in Prague. Disbanding the militia was
among the earliest demands made by the pro-democracy movement.
   The party began purging undesirable members in late November,
ousting hard-line party leader Milos Jakes and then Prague party
boss Milos Stepan.
   Jakes was replaced by Karel Urbanek, who held the post less than
four weeks before losing it Wednesday.
   Former Premier Ladislav Adamec was elected party chairman and
Politburo member Vasil Mohorita was chosen first secretary. The two
new positions share the powers once wielded by the all-powerful
secretary-general.
   Adamec initiated the first talks in November with the
opposition, and Mohorita played a part in the talks.
</TEXT>

</DOC>