<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0543EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CommuterPlaneCrash     12-29 0401</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Commuter Plane Crash,0411</SECOND>
<HEAD>Light Icing of Wings Reported Before Crash That Killed Six</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PASCO, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   De-icing equipment and other parts of a
commuter plane that will be tested in an effort to find the cause
of a crash that killed all six people aboard the plane.
   The crew of the United Express plane from Seattle reported light
icing about an hour before it crashed at a small airport 180 miles
southeast of Seattle, Barry Trotter of the National Transportation
Safety Board said Thursday.
   De-icing and other equipment was being checked, but it is much
too early to determine the cause of the accident Tuesday, Trotter
said.
   ``We still have not discounted anything and we are still looking
at everything,'' he said at a news conference.
   The British Aerospace Jetstream 31 slammed into a sagebrush
field short of the runway and burst into flames, killing two crew
members and four passengers.
   ``Several other aircraft that had landed (prior to the crash)
reported light icing to insignificant icing,'' Trotter said. ``An
hour and 15 minutes before the accident, this aircraft reported
light icing.''
   But he said the crew didn't report any trouble in its final
communication with the airport control tower or the FAA control
center in Seattle just minutes before the plane went down.
   Icing tends to slow a plane's forward speed or force it downward
by increasing aircraft weight and drag and reducing lift and thrust.
   The plane had made 7,161 flights before to the crash and its
flight history and maintenance records appeared clean, Trotter said.
   United Express _ one of several similarly named commuter
airlines around the country _ is based in Pasco and serves 15
cities in Washington, Oregon, Idaho and Montana.
   It serves as a feeder airline for United Airlines, with which it
has a marketing agreement that permits it to use United's computer
system and logo. United Express, operated by NPA Inc., began
commercial air service in July 1987.
   Killed in the crash were the two crew members, Capt. Barry
``Will'' Roberts, 38, the pilot, and First Officer Doug McInroe,
25, the copilot, both of Kennewick; and passengers Kim Shewmaker,
34, also a United Express pilot who has a home in Kimberly, Idaho,
and an apartment in Richland; Rey Resendez, 46, of Duncanville,
Texas; Wayne Kingry, 42, of Denver; and Elliott Fischer, 56, of
Seal Beach, Calif., who recently moved to Richland.
</TEXT>

</DOC>