<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0302 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2330EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-MobilDismissal     12-20 0347</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Mobil Dismissal,0358</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge Puts Off Hearing on Unsealing Court Documents</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DANIEL J. WAKIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEWARK, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal judge Wednesday put off a hearing
on Mobil Oil Corp.'s request to keep under seal environmental
documents filed in a lawsuit brought by a former executive, who
says he was fired for refusing to ``sanitize'' pollution reports.
   U.S. District Judge Harold A. Ackerman said he wanted to give
Mobil's attorneys a chance to prepare arguments for their
opposition to a request by The Associated Press to enter the case.
   Ackerman was to hear arguments Wednesday on whether or not to
make the documents public. Stephen Wiley, an attorney for the
former employee, said he favors unsealing the documents because
they are ``directly relevant'' to a public proceeding.
   An attorney for the AP, Richard Eittreim, said his arguments
were similar to Wiley's. But Mobil attorney Ron Green said he
wanted to respond to the AP's legal papers, which he received
shortly before the hearing.
   Ackerman set a new date for Friday and told the parties to
submit more papers.
   The former employee, Valcar Bowman Jr., claims he was fired as
Mobil Chemical Co.'s environmental affairs manager for refusing to
``sanitize'' assessments of environmental problems at company
plants nationwide. He claims the company's legal office made
changes to downplay pollution problems.
   Bowman, 47, of Riverdale, Ga., worked at the Princeton offices
of Mobil.
   Mobil denies the charge, saying it had a right to fire Bowman
and did so as part of a legitimate economic cutback. The company
also denies altering the reports other than to make a few minor
editing and typographical changes.
   The parties dispute whether Ackerman should unseal a series of
environmental assessment reports submitted in support of arguments
made in the pre-trial stages.
   Wiley says the whole documents are central to his case. Mobil
says it is willing to release only portions it feels are relevant,
and to release the entire reports _ which are self-critical
evaluations _ would stifle attempts by companies to be candid about
conditions at their plants.
</TEXT>

</DOC>