<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0100 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1849EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel 1stLd-Writethru a0578 12-26 0544</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0578,0556</SECOND>
<HEAD>Arab Protester Fatally Shot, Israeli Bus Set on Fire</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with five grafs to UPDATE with officers' wives claiming
Rabin gave beating orders; picks up 5th pvs: At least ...ADDS three grafs
with details</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALLYN FISHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Israeli officer fatally shot a Palestinian
protester in the West Bank on Tuesday, and an Israeli-owned bus was
reported set ablaze by masked Arab assailants in Israel as
passengers fled the vehicle.
   A group of army officers' wives demanded on Tuesday that Defense
Minister Yitzhak Rabin either resign or accept responsibility for
orders they claimed he issued to soldiers in the occupied
territories.
   On Monday, the army announced plans to court martial Israeli
Col. Yehuda Meir, accused of ordering troops to beat and break the
legs of 20 bound and gagged Palestinian detainees in January 1988.
   Meir's wife, Orna, and other officers' wives claimed Rabin gave
the orders to brutalize the Palestinians.
   Tuesday's violence came a day after a PLO leaflet urged
Palestinians to escalate attacks on Israeli forces between
Christmas and the New Year ``to honor the Palestinian revolution.''
   At least 640 Palestinians have been killed by Israelis during
the two-year uprising against the occupation of the West Bank and
Gaza Strip.
   At least 161 other Arabs have been slain by fellow Palestinians
as accused collaborators with Israel. Forty-three Israelis also
have died.
   The latest fatality, Farraj Daher Abu Fekhaida, 26, was shot in
the chest when an Israeli commander fired on stone-throwers during
an army raid on the village of Jina near Ramallah, the army and
Arab reports said.
   The Israeli-owned bus was set on fire within Israeli territory
near the West Bank town of Jenin, Israeli radio reports said.
   One masked assailant held a hatchet to the driver, while two
others spilled kerosene on the floor and then set the vehicle on
fire, the reports said. The passengers, Palestinians going to jobs
in Israel, reportedly managed to flee unhurt.
   In the Gaza Strip, soldiers shot and wounded three Palestinian
teen-agers in clashes in the Jebaliya and Shati refugee camps, Arab
reports said.
   In Jerusalem, Israeli state prosecutor Dorit Beinisch ordered
further investigation into the death of a 27-year-old Palestinian
who died last week in custody of the Shin Bet security agency in
the Gaza Strip, the Yediot Ahronot daily said.
   The prisoner, Khalid Kamel Sheikh Ali, had been detained three
weeks earlier on suspicion of concealing weapons for a Moslem
fundamentalist group.
   Michael Baden, director of Forensic Sciences for New York State
Police, who was commissioned by the victim's family to conduct an
autopsy, told reporters Monday Ali died from a blow to the abdomen
dealt with ``a large amount of force.''
   The charges against Meir say soldiers under his command left
beaten and bound Palestinians from Beita and Hawara villages in a
field until other Arabs came and took them to a hospital.
   Meir served as military commander of Nablus, the largest town in
the West Bank, and becomes the highest-ranking officer to face
trial during the uprising. He resigned from the army under pressure
in April 1988.
   Orna Meir, who formed the wives' group on Tuesday, said on
Israel radio that Rabin was responsible for the beating orders.
</TEXT>

</DOC>