<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0144 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1609EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-CosmeticPackaging     12-20 0501</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cosmetic Packaging,470</SECOND>
<HEAD>Child-Resistant Containers Backed for Two Cosmetics</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DENISE CABRERA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Consumer Product Safety Commission staff
on Wednesday recommended that the agency require child-resistant
containers for two cosmetic products that pose a risk of poisoning
for young children who might accidentally swallow the preparations.
   ``They can cause severe toxic effects in humans and pose a risk
of serious injury or death to young children,'' said Virginia
White, a project manager in the CPSC's chemical hazards program, in
testimony at a commission hearing.
   White recommended the agency require special packaging for
artificial fingernail glue removers containing acetonitrile and
home permanent hair-wave neutralizers with sodium or potassium
bromate.
   ``Child-resistant packaging is readily available ... and the
costs for complying with a special packaging regulation are
estimated to be low relative to the potential benefits,'' she added.
   The commission deferred voting on the package requirements, but
White said the procedural nature of commissioners' questions
indicated they would follow the staff recommendations and require
the child-proof containers.
   Acetonitrile is used as a solvent in liquids used by manicurists
to remove artificial sculptured fingernails, hobbyists in model
building and as a general household glue remover.
   Material compiled by the agency's staff said a 16-month-old
California boy died in 1987 after swallowing up to two tablespoons
of sculptured nail remover. Three other children under the age of
five also were seriously injured after ingesting similar products
containing acetonitrile, the report said.
   Staff researchers found 17 cases _ one involving the death of a
17-month-old child and one that resulted in permanent hearing loss
and kidney damage to a 16-month-old _ of accidential ingestion of
bromate neutralizers since 1947.
   Neutralizers are used to stop the action of chemicals used in
permanent hair-wave products.
   Preparations with sodium and potassium bromates were commonly
used during the 1940s and 1950s but had virtually disappeared from
the market after being replaced by products with alternative
ingredients, White said. Recently, however, several smaller
manufacturers have again begun adding the bromates to neutralizers,
she said.
   White said it would cost manufacturers of both types of products
2 to 7 cents per package to add the containers child resistant.
   More than $5 million in glue removers are sold for cosmetic and
hobby use annually, the staff materials said. Sales of permanent
wave products, including those containing bromates, were put at
$107.6 million in 1987.
   The staff recommendation would require that any product
containing acetonitrile be in a child-resistant container.
   Both products are sold in supermarkets, drug stores and retail
and wholesale beauty supply outlets.
   The American Association of Poison Control Centers, Inc. had
asked to commission to require the child-resistant packaging. The
petition was supported by the Cosmetic, Toiletry and Fragrance
Association and the California Department of Health Services.
   Wednesday's hearing was the first on product safety since
Jacqueline Jones-Smith became chairman of the panel last month. The
commission has been without a quorum for most of 1989 and could not
meet to conduct official business.
</TEXT>

</DOC>