<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0120 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1457EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Economy Bjt   12-29 0716</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Economy, Bjt,690</SECOND>
<HEAD>Indicator of Economic Activity Shows Tiny Rise for November</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN CRUTSINGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Economics Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government said Friday that its chief
barometer of future economic activity edged up 0.1 percent in
November, a tiny increase seen by many analysts as evidence that
growth in 1990 will be modest at best.
   The Commerce Department said the small rise in its Index of
Leading Economic Indicators followed a 0.3 percent decline in
October, a figure that had originally been reported as a somewhat
larger 0.4 percent drop.
   For most of the year, the leading index has been flashing
signals that the U.S. economy was headed for a rather dramatic
slowdown in growth and analysts said the weak November showing did
not change that picture.
   ``The message is no growth and flirtation with a recession as we
enter the 1990s,'' said Allen Sinai, chief economist of the Boston
Co.
   The economy, as measured by the gross national product, grew at
an annual rate of just over 3 percent through the first nine months
of this year.
   However, a variety of factors including a steep plunge in auto
sales, the San Francisco earthquake and Hurricane Hugo are all
expected to depress economic activity significantly in the current
October-December quarter.
   Sinai is among a minority of economists who believe growth will
be negative in the fourth quarter and the first three months of
1990 as the country suffers through what he believes will be a mild
recession.
   However, less pessimistic forecasters are calling for weak
growth in both quarters and no recession as the current recovery
from the 1981-82 recession chugs into its eighth year, a peacetime
record.
   To bolster their view, they point out that while the leading
index has declined in five of the last 11 months, it has not fallen
for three consecutive months, the traditional, though not
infallible, signal of an impending downturn.
   ``After a weak start, we expect 1990 to pick up some strength
during the course of the year,'' said David Wyss, senior financial
economist for DRI-McGraw Hill, a Lexington, Mass., forecasting firm.
   He predicted GNP growth in the current quarter would register an
anemic 0.5 percent annual rate but would improve modestly in coming
quarters. For all of 1990, he forecast the GNP would expand by 1.6
percent, just about half of the growth this year.
   That would be bad news for the Bush administration, which is
counting on much stronger growth next year to bring in enough
revenues to reduce the deficit without requiring a tax increase.
The administration is expected to unveil its $1.2 trillion budget
proposal on Jan. 22.
   The 0.1 percent rise in the leading index in November was led by
a strong jump in orders for consumer goods.
   The other four indicators providing strength were a drop in
weekly unemployment claims, an increase in plant and equipment
orders, a rise in the money supply and an increase in the backlog
of manufacturers' unfilled orders.
   Six other indicators acted as a drag on the index last month,
with the biggest negative coming from a drop in the price of raw
materials. While such a decrease is considered good news for
inflation prospects, it is counted as a negative in the index
because it also can reflect declining demand.
   Other negative factors were a decline in stock prices, a drop in
consumer confidence, a decline in the average manufacturing work
week, a decline in building permits and a speedup in business
delivery times.
   The various changes left the index at 144.7 percent of its 1982
base of 100.
   One of the main reasons that analysts are looking for an upturn
in activity next year is a belief that credit-easing moves by the
Federal Reserve will provide a boost to interest-rate sensitive
sectors of the economy such as housing.
   But William MacReynolds, forecasting director of the U.S.
Chamber of Commerce, said that the big rise in the money supply in
November, a sign of the Fed's easing efforts, was troubling because
it raised the danger of higher inflation next year.
   ``For the past six months, the money supply has increased much
faster than industrial output. This will lower the purchasing power
of money, causing a new bout of inflation to take hold,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>