<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 2038EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Brazil-Kidnap     12-17 0331</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil-Kidnap,0341</SECOND>
<HEAD>Brazilian Kidnappers Release Businessman Hostage</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAO PAULO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Heavily armed kidnappers claiming
allegiance to a Chilean revolutionary group released a supermarket
tycoon Sunday and turned themselves over to authorities.
   After receiving guarantees of safety, the kidnappers _ a
Canadian woman and six South American men _ left the house in which
they held Abilio Diniz Filho and boarded a bus that took them to
police headquarters for interrogation.
   The 53-year-old Diniz Filho, with a stubble and looking haggard
but otherwise in good condition, emerged from the house smiling and
was greeted by applause after nearly a week in captivity. A police
van drove him to a luxury apartment where his former wife and his
children live.
   More than 200 police, armed with rifles, machine guns and
shotguns, surrounded the house in a lower middle-class neighborhood
of Sao Paulo at dawn Saturday. The kidnappers demanded $200,000, an
armored car and a plane to escape to another country, but police
refused to negotiate on those demands.
   Diniz Filho is vice president of Pao de Acucar supermarket
chain, one of Brazil's largest. He was kidnapped Dec. 11 in front
of his house in Sao Paulo.
   His brother, Alcides Diniz, said the kidnappers never demanded
ransom.
   Police Inspector Nelson Silveira Guimaraes said the seven _ four
Chileans, one Argentine, one Brazilian and the Canadian woman _
``told us they belonged to Chile's Revolutionary Leftist
Movement.'' They were not identified.
   He said police believed they also took part in the abduction of
Brazilian advertising executive Luiz Sales in July. Sales was
released after his family paid $2.5 million in ransom.
   Accompanying the kidnappers in the bus were Roman Catholic
Cardinal Paulo Evaristo Arns, archbishop of Sao Paulo, who took
part in the negotiations; and former Finance Minister Luiz Carlos
Bresser Pereira, a senior executive at Pao de Acucar.
   Bresser Pereira told reporters that part of the agreement with
the kidnappers was that the supermarket chain would pay for their
legal defense.
</TEXT>

</DOC>