<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1144EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-BryantProfileBjt     12-23 0676</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bryant Profile Bjt,680</SECOND>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WX8 of Dec. 15</HEAD>
<HEAD>Director Says She'll Be `Cheerleader' For 1990 Census</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN FLESHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Census Director Barbara E. Bryant views
herself as head cheerleader for the team of statisticians,
interviewers, geographers and demographers who will conduct next
year's massive effort to count and categorize the American
population.
   Mrs. Bryant, who took office last week after President Bush used
a parliamentary tactic to install her without Senate confirmation,
says the groundwork for ``monumental task'' of conducting the 1990
census has been laid.
   ``What I can do now is be a cheerleader. I am really committed
to helping this bureau have a full and accurate count of the
population,'' she said, adding that most of the planning, going
back to 1984, has been done by others.
   The job has been complicated by the flow of immigrants and
illegal aliens into the United States over the past decade. After
heated debate, Congress voted this year to include illegal aliens
and military personnal stationed overseas in the census.
   Officials believe 1.6 percent of the population wasn't counted
in 1980, including a disproportionately high number of blacks and
other racial minorities who often are fearful about taking part in
the census count.
   The Census Bureau, in an attempt to target such
``hard-to-enumerate'' groups, is trying to overcome their fear and
suspicion by working through local grassroots organizations,
especially in urban centers.
   ``Some people don't believe the census is really confidential,''
said Mrs. Bryant. ``Then there are education and language problems
with some segments of the population ... and other people just
distrust the government.''
   She said, ``Every opportunity I have, I'll be getting the word
out. It's confidential. I promise.''
   Mrs. Bryant, 63, is the first woman director of the Census
Bureau, but she's accustomed to blazing trails. In 1947 she became
one of the first women to gain an editorial rank with a McGraw-Hill
Publishing Co. magazine.
   ``I was never the full-time wife and mother type,'' she said.
She married and took an 11-year break to raise three children, but
continued freelance writing and editing.
   She began as a science writer and editor. But while pursuing a
doctorate at Michigan State University, ``I got totally hooked on
communication research'' and later joined Market Opinion Research
of Detroit. In 1977 she became senior vice president of the
company, whose president until recently was Bush campaign adviser
Robert Teeter.
   Mrs. Bryant says she does not consider herself to be a political
appointee and that most of her projects with Market Opinion
Research were non-political. They included studies for
universities, presidential commissions, government agencies and
media organizations.
   For municipal transit authorities, she developed proposals for
making city bus and subway travel more popular. For National
Geographic and Harlequin Books, she crafted strategies for
increasing readership.
   She conducted polls for Detroit news organizations on issues
ranging from casino gambling to putting a dome on Tiger Stadium.
   ``I always felt if I were her age I wouldn't have the energy to
run all over the country the way she does,'' said James Leiman,
another company vice president. ``She's a driven, upbeat, motivated
person.''
   Some critics question the accuracy of polling, but Mrs. Bryant
defends it.
   ``You have to watch for people giving socially acceptable
answers,'' she says. ``But the American public is basically pretty
honest.''
   For relaxation, Mrs. Bryant swims half a mile a day and dabbles
in gardening and cooking. But she'll have little leisure time for
the next year as the census goes forward.
   Bush nominated Mrs. Bryant for the census post in September. But
when Congress recessed for the year last month, the Senate had yet
to take a confirmation vote.
   Bush announced Dec. 7 he was giving her a ``recess
appointment.'' Under the Constitution, an individual appointed by
the president while the Senate is on an extended recess can serve
until the end of the following year without Senate confirmation.
   Mrs. Bryant says she hopes to be confirmed next year and serve
as long as Bush wants her.
</TEXT>

</DOC>