<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0937EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Romania-Ceausescu     12-28 0317</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Ceausescu,0328</SECOND>
<HEAD>Brother of Romanian Dictator Found Dead In Embassy in Vienna</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Marin Ceausescu, the older brother of
executed Romanian leader Nicolae Ceausescu, was found dead at the
Romanian Embassy in Vienna today after apparently committing
suicide, police said.
   A police spokesman who refused to be identified said the
74-year-old diplomat, who reportedly headed Western European
operations of the dreaded Romanian secret police, was found hanged
in the basement of the embassy' trade mission.
   The spokesman said it appeared to be suicide and there were no
indications that anyone else was involved in his death.
   Authorities ordered an autopsy, the Austria Press Agency
reported.
   Little was known about Marin Ceausescu's career until he was
listed as the director of the Romanian presentation at the 14th
International Engineering Fair in Brno, Czechoslovakia, in 1972.
   In April 1974, he moved to Vienna as chief of the Romanian Trade
Agency.
   A man who answered the telephone at the Romanian Embassy said he
was not authorized to answer any questions about Ceausescu and
added that no one else was available for comment.
   The Austria Press Agency said the embassy in the last few days
had repeatedly said Ceausescu was not there.
   In its edition today, the Vienna daily Kurier reported that a
spokesman for the trade mission had claimed Ceausescu had traveled
to Bucharest out of concern for his family, particularly his
daughters, Gabriela and Mihaela.
   Kurier, referring to unspecified sources in the new Romanian
government, alleged Ceausescu ``managed the Romanian secret service
headquarters for Western Europe in Vienna.''
   There was no additional information to corroborate the claim,
and the report could not be independently verified.
   Nicolae Ceausescu was executed with his wife, Elena, on Monday
after he was found guilty of ``grave crimes'' during his harsh
24-year rule. The Communist dictator was toppled Friday after a
popular uprising that began Dec. 15.
</TEXT>

</DOC>