<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0645EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ArtilleryAccident     12-30 0380</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Artillery Accident,0395</SECOND>
<HEAD>Charges Filed Against Soldiers Dismissed</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Nickoles is cq in 2nd graf.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FORT SILL, Okla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two soldiers made ``a tragic mistake''
in causing an artillery accident that killed three soldiers and
wounded 24, but they won't be court-martialed, their commander said.
   Safety violations that caused the Sept. 27 accident were
insufficient reason to prosecute Sgt. Edward C. Tyler of
Washington, D.C., and Spec. Nickoles W. Holly of Canton, Ohio, Maj.
Gen. Raphael J. Hallada said Friday.
   Tyler and Holly were accused of dereliction of duty and
negligent homicide and faced up to 15 months confinement, loss of
wages and bad-conduct discharges if convicted on both charges.
   ``My decision that trial by court-martial is not the appropriate
course was based on the evidence, on the spotless records of Tyler
and Holly, and on my determination that the accident was a tragic
mistake resulting from a momentary violation of safety procedures
rather than a criminal act,'' said Hallada, commander at Fort Sill.
   Officers who investigated the accident at a rifle range in
southwest Oklahoma said one of five rounds fired from a 105mm
howitzer during a training session contained the wrong powder
charge.
   The round overshot its target and exploded behind a group of 80
soldiers lined up in formation to leave the range.
   Two of the injured soldiers remain hospitalized in serious
condition.
   Hallada said he met with Tyler and Holly and their commanding
officers in to review the actions that led to the accident.
   ``The two soldiers know that they caused the accident ... The
officers know that this happened on their watch,'' Hallada said.
``These were very emotional meetings. Every one of them would give
anything to have that round back.''
   Investigators said Holly, a cannoneer in the howitzer crew,
prepared the powder charges before the rounds were fired and was to
remove excess powder bags when a lesser charge was fired. He was to
display the bags to his section chief, Tyler.
   The investigators concluded that Holly failed to do this with
one of the five rounds and that Tyler didn't catch the error.
   But Hallada said, ``I was not convinced a jury would find that
Holly and Tyler blatantly disregarded what a reasonably careful
person would have done under the circumstances.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>