<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0096 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1339EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     12-29 0501</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0519</SECOND>
<HEAD>Brite and Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It's a dirty job, but somebody had to do it.
   Illinois has an official state bird, state flower, state fish,
state insect, even a state fossil. But the Illinois Soil
Classifiers Association insists that what the Land of Lincoln
really needs is a state soil.
   They've formed a State Soil Committee to lobby lawmakers to that
end.
   ``It ties all the symbols of the state together, committee chair
Bob McLeese of Monticello said recently. ``They all rely on soil
for their existence.''
   Illinois' official tree, the White Oak, and state flower, the
violet, grow in the soil. The state bird, the cardinal, gets worms
from it. Monarch butterflies, the state bug, live off nectar from
flowers that grow in the soil. The state fish, the bluegill, swims
in ponds resting on earth.
   Even the state's fossil _ Tullimonstrum gregarium, or,
familiarly, the Tully monster _ lived in Illinois soil, albeit 280
million years ago.
   Members of the association, many of whom work for the U.S.
Agriculture Department's Soil Conservation Service, have selected
Drummer silty clay loam as their nominee.
   That soil beat Cisne silt loam 2-1 in a poll of the group's
approximately 100 members. Drummer silty clay loam covers more than
1.6 million acres of the state, and many of the state's corn stalks
and soybeans call it home.
   State Rep. Gordon Ropp, R-Normal, said he'll sponsor a state
soil bill in the General Assembly, adding, ``I certainly think soil
has as much as priority as the Tully monster.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PEORIA, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mayor Jim Maloof says he has reached detente
with organizers of the Miss Russian-American Pageant by assuring
them that Peoria would still like to be a host city for the event.
   Maloof said Thursday he called the prime organizer, Vera von
Wiren Garczynski, in New York to explain why he didn't plug the
pageant more in a national television appearance after the
Slavic-American Cultural Association announced it would hold the
U.S. portion of the pageant in Peoria.
   Maloof said he explained to Garczynski that he wasn't given
enough time by producers of the ``CBS Morning News'' to talk about
the pageant.
   Garczynski told the Peoria Journal Star that members of the
association and Soviet officials were upset by Maloof's brief
remarks on the show, and that Peoria officials seemed more
interested in short-term publicity than in the event itself.
   ``That explanation is fine,'' Garczynski said. ``I don't want
any fights. One does not need any sensational controversy here.''
   Promoters are hailing the pageant as a symbol of the new harmony
between the United States and the Soviet Union. The pageant will
consist of two contests, one for American women in Peoria and
another for Soviet women in Moscow.
   The Peoria portion is tentatively scheduled to coincide with
Soviet President Mikhail Gorbachev's visit to the United States
this spring. The Soviet contest is scheduled for January.
   Maloof called the questions raised by Garczynski about Peoria's
sincerity a ``misunderstanding.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>