<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0175 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1326EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--Where'stheArt? Adv31-1stLd-Writethru   12-19 0987</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Where's the Art?, Adv 31-1st Ld-Writethru,b0571,1017</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 31</HEAD>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: CORRECTS 6th graf, There are ... plastic flowers., to delete
erroneous reference to `toy cars and doll faces stuck into plastic flowers.'</HEAD>
<HEAD>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 1 b&amp;w photo.)</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   She's a former corporate lawyer from New York
City who confesses she likes to shock people. On the sidewalks of
Portland, Ore., Stephanie Pierce may not be shocking a lot of
people, but she's entertaining them in an unusual way. Welcome to
what she calls the world's first coin-operated art gallery.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By GISELLE PRICE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The 24-Hour Church of Elvis is here,
sharing space with ``the world's cheapest psychic'' and a machine
dispensing an eclectic collection of tacky prizes at a quarter a
pop.
   Put a quarter in the slot and a computer-generated voice greets
you:
   ``Hello, welcome to Where's the Art!!, the world's first 24-hour
coin-operated art gallery. What would you like?''
   Art?
   Stuffed into three storefront windows in downtown Portland,
Where's the Art!! is a repository of spinning, talking and singing
artifacts from American pop culture. Glitter, garland and
fluorescent colors abound.
   There are the Elvis Presley shrine and the ``Amazing New
See-Through Prize-o-Matic Dispenser,'' dispensing little gag prizes
of obscure value.
   ``I like to kind of shock people a little bit,'' says
owner-inventor Stephanie Pierce.
   That helps explain why her certificate of admission to the New
York Bar hangs above her toilet.
   Pierce graduated from Georgetown University Law Center in 1980
and worked as a corporate lawyer for American Telephone &amp; Telegraph
Co. in New York for three years.
   ``People think they can dismiss me as a lunatic, a member of the
far-out fringe, but then they are really so impressed by the fact
that I went to law school,'' Pierce says.
   Working on legal accounting issues just wasn't for her.
   After she handed in her letter of resignation, she says, her
boss, George Finkelstein, said, ``Stephanie, I'll see you ... on
the sidewalk begging for quarters. Good luck.''
   Finkelstein was on target. Pierce often drums up business on the
sidewalk outside her store. She cajoles people who look but don't
drop quarters in the slots.
   When the quarter plinks into one of the coin slots, the computer
talks.
   You can choose psychic counseling from ``Dr. Justin D.
Nikov-Time,'' sacraments in the Church of Elvis, fun with the Kid
Window, or a parody of the game show ``Let's Make a Deal.''
   All sorts of people come by this sidewalk arcade: college
students, tourists, street people, businessmen on lunch breaks.
Some just look. Others stop and put in quarters. They all laugh.
   ``That's one of the things I like the best _ making people
laugh,'' she says.
   Talk about participatory art. The gallery ``marries'' couples in
the Church of Elvis, replete with plastic rings and Elvis singing
``Love Me Tender.'' It conducts question-and-answer sessions with
the ``psychic counselor,'' and pushes people to ``dance with the
stars'' right there on the pavement.
   Doing a past-life regression, the computer psychic might say,
``You were a fish, you were a bird, you were Shirley MacLaine, you
were Shirley MacLaine, you were Shirley MacLaine, you were Shirley
MacLaine.''
   After answering all the questions by pushing colored buttons,
the ``patient'' receives a prize: perhaps a 3-D Psychic Calendar,
or the Handy Horoscope, which might include a prediction of an
impending restaurant deal with Reggie Jackson. Pierce makes most of
the prizes herself.
   Living in one window are a male mannequin with a
paint-by-numbers picture of a raccoon, and a female mannequin
wearing a sign that says ``Don't Hate Me Because I'm Beautiful.''
Attached to her bizarre helmet is a vacuum hose that runs up from a
contraption called the ``Bowling Channel Brain Stimulator.''
   This is art, Pierce says, not what's found in traditional
galleries. ``That's why I call it `Where's the Art!!' It's not a
question, it's a demand,'' she says.
   Pierce, 38, now revels in her place outside the art
establishment. But she did apply, three times, to Cooper Union for
the Advancement of Science and Art in New York. The art samples she
submitted included sketches of a ``Dreaminator,'' a machine that
would allow people to record their dreams and play them back.
   Pierce was rejected, but she says that's all right because not
going to art school kept her on her own track.
   ``I used to hide my strangeness all the time,'' Pierce says.
``It was really a struggle. I was trying so hard to be normal. Now
I feel like I'm myself.''
   Pierce traded in her business suits for leopard-print pants,
shorts, tie-dye shirts, and wild hair.
   She is host of a public access cable television show, also named
``Where's the Art!!'' The program, which she calls a show-and-tell
for artists and musicians, is open to anyone, and just about
anything.
   She has been making unusual pieces since childhood. She and her
brother and sister made little ``machines,'' including one that was
an early version of her current prize dispenser.
   Pierce says she made $42,000 a year as a lawyer, and piled up
the tips as a waitress. Now she struggles to keep her store afloat.
Her financial situation has improved dramatically since she began
selling ``Where's the Art!!'' T-shirts. Until then, she was five
months behind on the rent.
   Business may improve further when Pierce expands to mail-order
delivery of the T-shirts and possibly some of the prizes.
   She says she makes about $600 a month in quarters. She has to
put up with frequent leaks in her store, and duns for her
delinquent student loan payments.
   Pierce works 12 to 15 hours a day. ``But it doesn't feel like
work,'' she says. ``I'm my own boss. I don't make much money but it
doesn't matter. It's a lifestyle.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>

</DOC>