<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0291 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1728EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Dollar-Gold     12-20 0654</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dollar-Gold,0675</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar, Gold Mixed</HEAD>
<HEAD>Precede LONDON BC</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dollar finished mostly lower Wednesday in
foreign exchange trading in the United States after ending mixed
overseas in what dealers called a muted response to the U.S.
military intervention in Panama.
   Gold investors appeared to discard news of the military action,
as prices edged higher in New York after falling in Europe and
Asia. Republic National Bank in New York quoted a bid for a troy
ounce of gold at $413.05 as of 4 p.m. EST, up $1.30 from Tuesday's
late bid.
   The dollar wound up lower against every major currency except
the Japanese yen and Canadian dollar in New York. In Europe, it
rose against the yen, Canadian dollar and Dutch guilder, but fell
against other major currencies.
   Dealers in Europe said the dollar rose early in the trading day
in reaction to news of the U.S. military action in Panama.
   But the dollar reversed course midway through the U.S. trading
day when the Federal Reserve took steps to inject reserves into the
financial system, a move that was viewed as a sign that it may be
encouraging lower interest rates.
   Falling interest rates reduce demand for dollars because the
decline cuts the yields available to foreigners on their
dollar-denominated investments.
   Richard Levine, vice president for foreign exchange and precious
metals at Elders Futures Inc. in New York, said trading was
relatively light all day.
   ``You could tell there was no real conviction,'' he said,
referring to the market's assessment of the impact of both the
military action and the Fed's move to make more money available
within the financial system.
   He said the market viewed the U.S. military action as ``a sign
of strength'' but recognized the move was a ``limited regional
action'' which was not likely to have global ramifications.
   The subsequent decline in the dollar also came on low volume,
Levine said, because traders remember that they misinterpreted a
similar move by the central bank a few weeks ago as an indication
it was easing its credit policy.
   He also noted that as the end of the year approaches, banks that
otherwise would be active in the currency markets are not trading.
``Most of the major banks have squared their banks for the year,''
he said.
   In Tokyo, the dollar rose to 144.23 Japanese yen from 143.80 yen
at Tuesday's close. Later in London, it was quoted at 143.90 yen.
In New York, the dollar edged up to 143.93 yen from 143.65 yen late
Tuesday.
   The dollar fell against the British pound. In London, the pound
rose to $1.6052 from $1.6005 late Tuesday. In New York, the pound
rose to $1.6060 from $1.6010 late Tuesday.
   Other late dollar rates in New York, compared with late rates
Tuesday, included: 1.7320 West German marks, down from 1.7365;
5.9125 French francs, down from 5.9275; 1.5555 Swiss francs, down
from 1.5565; 1,288.50 Italian lire, down from 1,289.25; and 1.16095
Canadian dollars, up from 1.16085.
   Selected late dollar rates in Europe, compared with late
Tuesday's prices, included: 1.7355 West German marks, down from
1.7365; 1.5585 Swiss francs, down from 1.5615; 5.9165 French
francs, down from 5.9300; 1.9720 Dutch guilders, up from 1.9575;
1,288.00 Italian lire, down from 1,291.25; and 1.1625 Canadian
dollars, up from 1.1613.
   On the New York Commodity Exchange, gold for current delivery
rose $1.70 a troy ounce to $413.60.
   But earlier in the day, gold prices fell. Gold dropped to a late
bid of $413.50 a troy ounce in London from $413.75 bid late
Tuesday. In Zurich, the metal fell to a closing bid of $413 an
ounce, down from $414 late Tuesday. In Hong Kong, gold fell 76
cents to close at a bid $412.04.
   On the Comex, silver for current delivery rose 2.1 cents an
ounce to $5.548. Silver bullion fell in London to a late bid of
$5.56 an ounce, down from $5.57 late Tuesday.
</TEXT>

</DOC>