<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0243 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2249EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Panama-OAS 4thLd-Writethru a0919 12-20 0571</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-OAS, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0919,510</SECOND>
<HEAD>OAS Weighs Resolution Condeming US Invasion Into Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 8th graf: ``Among the,'' to include countries condemning
the U.S. action; subs 10th graf, which was 9th graf pvs: ``The OAS,'' to
show they did not consider which government they recognized</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-US-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRYNA BRENNAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. allies in Latin America condemned the use
of force by the United States in speeches Wednesday before the
Organization of American States but bogged down in haggling over
procedures to vote on a resolution.
   Many of the members spoke out against the U.S. attacks in Panama
but they held fast to a rule requiring resolutions be submitted 24
hours before a vote can take place. They agreed to meet again
Thursday.
   The resolution was suggested by Panamanian ambassador Jose Maria
Cabrera, a supporter of Gen. Manuel Antonio Noreiga, and was
introduced by Nicaragua. Cabrera called on the OAS to condemn the
``brutal and criminal aggression'' against his country by the
United States.
   The United States asked members to ``rally around'' the decision
to send American troops into Panama.
   ``We hope you will understand and support our action,'' said
U.S. representative Luigi Einaudi.
   In a separate action, the Mexican government condemned the U.S.
invasion, although it also denounced Noriega.
   ``The fight against international crime is not sufficient reason
to intervene in a sovereign nation,'' the Mexican government said
in a statement issued through its embassy in Washington. ``In
Mexico's opinion, dialogue and negotiation continue to offer the
best alternative in finding a peaceful solution to the situation.''
   Among the usual allies condemning the use of force at the OAS
meeting were Brazil, Chile, Peru, Haiti, Uruguay and Costa Rica.
   Before the meeting began, the members met behind closed doors to
discuss a letter sent by Panama's newly sworn-in president,
Guillermo Endara, asking that the OAS recognize Lawrence Chewning
Fabrega as his designated representative. The letter was telefaxed
from the U.S. Southern Command.
   The OAS members decided to recognize Cabrera. They did not
consider the issue of whether they recognized Endara and his
government.
   ``The forces of the United States continue bombing,'' Cabrera
told the OAS ministers at an emergency session called by Panama to
denounce the U.S. invasion in his country.
   ``Under no circumstances will we accept some supposed leaders
who are puppets imposed by the United States,'' he said, referring
to Endara's government, which is recognized by the Bush
administration.
   The resolution before the OAS asked members to condemn the use
of force and demand a withdrawal of the troops.
   One of the ambassadors, who spoke on condition of anonymity,
said shortly before the meeting began that the OAS ``has to condemn
this act, no matter how bad Noriega is. We can't condone violence.''
   President Bush said Wednesday that he ordered troops into Panama
to save American lives and bring Noriega to the United States to be
tried on drug trafficking charges.
   Bush said the United States would withdraw its invasion force as
soon as possible.
   ``The United States is very pleased that the outlaw regime
manipulated by Manuel Antonio Noriega has given way to a regime
that reflects the democratic will of the people,'' Einaudi told OAS
members. ``Noriega increasingly acted in an unstable, unpredictable
and dangerous manner.''
   The Nicaraguan representative, Victoria Castillo, sided with
Panama.
   ``It is an aberration to speak of democracy and carry out
aggression,'' she said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>