<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0253 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0205EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-AdFoulup     12-20 0437</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Ad Foulup,0452</SECOND>
<HEAD>Some Grand Marnier Mechanical Ads Fail To Operate</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Reader's Digest, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SKIP WOLLENBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Importers of Grand Marnier liqueur say the
failure of about 10 percent of the 200,000 motorized holiday
advertisements they placed in The New Yorker magazine earlier this
month doesn't discourage them.
   Michel Roux, president of Carillon Importers Ltd. of Teaneck,
N.J., called the failure rate ``normal when introducing new
technology'' and said he remained committed to trying new
approaches to magazine ads.
   He estimated there have been about 500 complaints from readers
who were disappointed that the highly-touted ad didn't work as they
thought it should.
   The ad shows two birds with opposite ends of a ribbon in their
beaks. The ribbon is draped around a liqueur bottle and as the
birds alternately appear to fly higher, the bottle beneath them
swings as if it were a bell.
   Roux said Monday in a telephone interview that reader surveys
indicated 10 percent of the ads failed to operate as intended, and
that the company was distributing replacements to those who ask for
them.
   ``It's not a serious problem. We have mailed out 500 or so ads
to people who said their ad didn't work,'' he said.
   He said the technology which made use of a battery and wire
embedded beneath the pieces of cardboard used for the ad was
sensitive and some systems were likely to get crushed in the
binding and mailing processes.
   Some of the ads sent back were in working condition, but the
readers apparently didn't wait long enough for the motorized action
to begin, Roux said. He said a few people complained that the bell
didn't ring _ but the ad was not designed to emit any sound. And
other ads simply didn't work.
   From Roux's perspective, getting a complaint isn't the worst
thing that could happen. ``It shows they were interested by the
ad,'' he said.
   Carillon spent about $750,000 on producing and placing the ad in
200,000 issues of the Dec. 11 edition of The New Yorker that were
sent to subscribers in California and New York state.
   The company has tried to make use of advances in technology for
other magazine ads in the past, including singing and talking
microchips for another of its products, Absolut vodka.
   Steven Florio, president of The New Yorker, said the magazine
got ``about a dozen calls'' about Grand Marnier ads that failed to
move.
   But he said he welcomed the attention that Roux's ads bring to
the magazine. ``We hope he does something as innovative next
year,'' Florio said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>