<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0115 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1250EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-Pentagon-Pool     12-20 0401</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Pentagon-Pool,400</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pentagon Activates Media Pool for Panama Operation</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRYAN BRUMLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Department of Defense activated a news
media pool that arrived in Panama today alongside U.S. troops
dispatched by President Bush. The pool was developed after the
controversy over secrecy surrounding the 1982 American military
operation in Grenada.
   ``The purpose of the pool is to be there at the beginning of the
operation,'' said a Pentagon official, who spoke on condition that
he not be further identified. He said Pentagon pools are usually
disbanded after the first several days as other reporters arrive on
the scene.
   Notifying and assembling the pool takes place under terms of
secrecy that are unusual for the press. The Pentagon requires that
pool members not tell others about their assignment.
   ``We ask them to tell their families that they have been called
to work. That is not that unusual late at night for journalists. We
ask them not to have their spouses drive them to Andrews Air Force
Base, but to drive themselves or find some other way of getting
there,'' said the Pentagon source.
   The Pentagon pool in Panama is made up of journalists from the
following news organizations: The Associated Press; United Press
International; Reuters; Time Magazine; ABC Radio; NBC Television;
Houston Chronicle; Houston Post, and Dallas Morning News.
   The initial writer's report was received at midmorning
Wednesday, but news organizations were still waiting for
photography from the pool well after noon.
   News executives receive short notice when a pool is being
activated and assign the staff members who provide coverage. Their
material is made available to other media organizations that do not
take part. Participation in the pool is rotated several times a
year.
   News executives notified that the pool has been activated are
also sworn to secrecy.
   The first pool was formed in April 1985, and they have been
assembled on average of twice a year since then, officials said.
   One pool accompanied U.S. Navy warships escorting oil tankers
through the Persian Gulf in July 1987, but most times reporters
receiving the midnight summons have watched military maneuvers.
   The most recent previous pool also went to Panama, in May 1989,
a 12-member group that accompanied the first extra detachment of
Marines sent there in Operation Nimrod Dancer. That pool was not
kept secret, because President Bush announced the operation earlier
in the day.
</TEXT>

</DOC>