<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0109 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 2307EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Panama 6thLd-Writethru a0663 12-25 0829</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Panama, 6th Ld-Writethru, a0663,820</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Using `Tough Terms' in Negotiations with Vatican About Noriega</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf with 1 graf to include definition of `Mexican
standoff'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bush administration demanded ``in
extraordinarily tough terms'' Monday that Vatican authorities turn
deposed Panamanian dictator Manuel Antonio Noriega over to U.S.
custody, a State Department source said.
   Negotiations have brought ``a Mexican standoff'' _ a
confrontation that neither side can win _ the official said, with
church authorities rebuffing the request and trying, thus far
unsuccessfully, to find a country to take Noriega from his
sanctuary in the Vatican Embassy in Panama City.
   While the negotiations went on, President Bush summoned National
Security Adviser Brent Scowcroft to his mountain retreat Christmas
Day to discuss diplomatic options for dislodging Noriega to bring
him to trial on drug charges in the United States.
   And speaking in Panama, Defense Secretary Dick Cheney said he
would like to bring U.S. troops home ``as soon as possible'' but
added, ``They will stay as long as they are needed. We don't want
to leave too soon before the task is accomplished.''
   Roughly 26,000 U.S. troops are in Panama, more than double the
12,000 normally based there.
   The State Department source, speaking only on condition he not
be named, said the U.S. demand for custody of Noriega has been
delivered to the Vatican ``in extraordinarily tough terms.''
   But he said the Vatican has been contacting a number of Latin
American and European countries hoping that one will agree to
accept Noriega. The officials didn't mention names but countries
that have surfaced as possible refuges include Spain, Cuba and the
Dominican Republic.
   ``He has no place to go yet,'' the official said. ``Nobody wants
him.''
   The official said most of the discussions have been carried out
between the State Department and church officials at the Vatican.
   Vatican spokesman Joaquin Navarro said in Rome it was too early
to say whether he would be handed over to the United States or the
new U.S.-backed government in Panama or given passage to another
country.
   Scowcroft was asked to come to Camp David in the Catoctin
Mountains of Maryland where the president was spending a holiday
weekend with his wife, five children and 11 grandchildren. The
White House said Secretary of State James A. Baker III was keeping
in touch by telephone from Houston where he spent the holiday.
   Meanwhile, a Panamanian officer and Noriega loyalist who had
been indicted with Noriega on drug-related charges in Florida, was
escorted to Miami on Monday by U.S. drug enforcement agents, the
Justice Department said. Lt. Col. Luis del Cid, surrendered to U.S.
forces in Panama on Saturday.
   Noriega entered the Vatican Embassy on Sunday after eluding
capture by American troops in the four days since their invasion,
despite a $1 million bounty offered by the United States.
   That relieved U.S. forces in Panama from their intensive and
frustrating task of locating him, but it also set in motion a
diplomatic and legal ballet. ``Now it's up to the lawyers and the
diplomats,'' said Defense Secretary Dick Cheney, in Panama for a
brief on-site inspection.
   Sanctuary in embassies usually is granted for people seeking
political asylum, not protection from criminal prosecution.
   ``We want him in the United States to face the indictments,''
said a member of the State Department's Task Force on Panama. ``We
are exploring avenues by which this might be done,'' said the
official, who insisted on anonymity.
   Reports from Panama mentioned the possibility that Noriega wants
to go to Spain or Cuba. When U.S. officials were negotiating with
the Panamanian strongman after his indictment in this country last
year, he reportedly expressed a willingness to go into exile in
either country, but in the end did not.
   Miguel Gil, a spokesman for the Spanish government, said no
official overtures had been made by Noriega. And Foreign Minister
Francisco Fernandez Ordonez said the case was a matter to be
decided between the United States and the Vatican. Spain's national
news agency, EFE, later reported him as saying, ``Spain is not the
ideal country to accept Noriega because of its extradition
agreement with the United States, which includes drug trafficking
(cases).''
   In Vatican City, spokesman Joaquin Navarro said ``the concerned
parties'' would examine the case as soon as possible and that
Noriega's legal status was still being determined.
   Navarro was asked in a television interview if a ``simple''
turnover of Noriega to the United States was foreseeable.
   ``Well, I don't think so,'' said Navarro. ``There isn't an
extradition treaty or anything.''
   The Pentagon issued new casualty figures in Panama. The death
toll of U.S. troops stood at 23, revised downward by one from
Sunday because one victim was counted by two different units.
   There were 303 U.S. wounded, none missing and two dependents
killed, Lundquist said.
   He said Noriega's routed Panamanian Defense Forces suffered 290
dead, 121 wounded, and 3,780 captured or detained.
</TEXT>

</DOC>