<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0850EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-PanamaDiary 1stLd-Writethru a0411 12-23 1301</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama Diary, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0411,1341</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hotel Becomes Hunting Ground for Noriega Supporters</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Subs grafs 31-38, `We went...' to CORRECT to Skinner, sted Stringer;
Pick up 39th graf, `The soldiers...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   AP correspondent Candice Hughes had just arrived
at the Marriott Hotel when the U.S. attack on Panama began at
midnight Tuesday. She was taken hostage by forces loyal to Gen.
Manuel Antonio Noriega, then rescued by U.S. paratroopers.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By CANDICE HUGHES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The invasion of Panama made targets
of U.S. citizens and the Marriott Hotel became a choice hunting
ground for supporters of Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   Minutes after U.S. troops attacked the Panamanian Defense
Forces, a squad of men with ski masks and assault rifles began
prowling the hotel.
   By the time paratroopers of the 82nd Airborne Division arrived
24 hours later, more than a dozen guests had been kidnapped and
others had become hostages to fear.
   I found myself taken hostage, hunted, held incommunicado,
looking down more gun barrels than I care to count, rescued and
evacuated.
   These words began it: ``The United States is invading. We're
looking for American hostages.''
   The speaker was the squad leader, and he had come to the right
place. The Marriott, Panama City's most comfortable hotel, was host
to a corps of journalists and the usual complement of foreign
travelers.
   He and his cohorts settled on a dozen of us. Seven turned out to
be U.S. citizens.
   We tried to persuade them to tell their side of the story _ the
point of view of those being invaded and attacked. We went in
search of a telephone so we could call The Associated Press, but he
and his men had knocked out the phones.
   But we had made a personal contact that might, just might, make
it harder for him to kill us.
   We were taken to a private home in Noriega's neighborhood.
   It was not so bad. We were not blindfolded, beaten, verbally
abused or tied up. Our captors gave us water and returned borrowed
items like pens or cigarette lighters with courtesy.
   Always present, however, was the very real possibility that our
situation would turn suddenly worse.
   At one point, a kidnapper put the barrel of his AK-47 assault
rifle to the head of The New York Times correspondent Lindsey
Gruson.
   ``A lot of Panamanians have died. We can kill you,'' he said.
``Don't think we won't.''
   At another point, when I turned to console a captive who was
weeping, another kidnapper leveled his assault rifle at me, inches
from my nose, and held it there for what seemed like two or three
lifetimes.
   Around 4 a.m., nearly four hours after we were taken hostage,
the sounds of fighting outside diminished. The phone rang.
   ``It's over,'' the squad leader said. ``We don't want to dirty
ourselves. We are going to let you go.''
   He crouched in front of us, tears in his eyes. ``There are
hundreds of dead at the central barracks,'' the Defense Forces
headquarters, he said. ``Hundreds of dead.''
   We were put into two vehicles and freed at different locations.
I, Gruson, Paul Iredale of the Reuters news agency and three
businessmen were dropped on a curbside two blocks from Noriega's
mansion.
   Fighting continued in the streets and we hunkered at a hedge,
trying to devise a strategy for getting back to the hotel, more
than a mile away. Someone shot at us from a gas station across the
street.
   We dashed around the hedge to an apartment building and began
ringing every bell. A frightened doorman appeared and waved us away
with a pistol. We continued ringing buzzers and someone inside
decided to open the door.
   A brave family let me into their apartment. I was in heaven. No
one was pointing a gun at me and the lady of the house made coffee.
There was a view of the main battle area _ the Defense Forces
headquarters several miles away _ and I was able to report by
telephone to our office.
   As we drove back to the hotel I felt terrific: alive, unharmed
and free at last to report Panama's dramatic story.
   The next thing I knew, a gang of civilian Noriega supporters,
from the ``Dignity Battalions,'' raided the hotel. I looked down
from my 10th floor window to see three hostages face down in the
back of a Toyota pickup truck full of armed men.
   There was no way out. Trying to walk away seemed foolhardy while
gangs of thugs were scouting for American hostages. Gruson and I
barricaded ourselves in my room. I called the U.S. Embassy and my
office in New York to explain the situation.
   The hotel was totally unprotected. There were 30 or more U.S.
citizens. The Dignity Battalions had said they would come back.
   They didn't, but that did not mean we were relaxed. At about 4
p.m., 12 hours after I'd been freed the first time, some hotel
workers came to the room.
   ``The Marines will be here in about two minutes,'' they said.
``Hurry.''
   We went down the hall to a room where an Eastern Air Lines
pilot, Jay Skinner, his crew of seven and about 20 other Americans
were waiting. Skinner was on the telephone to an Eastern crisis
center in Miami.
   As it turned out, I was a hostage again, this time of the
terrified Eastern crew.
   Time passed and it was clear no rescue was imminent, but Skinner
and the crew refused to let us use the telephone or leave the room,
saying it would jeopardize their safety to have Americans elsewhere
in the hotel.
   ``If they capture you and torture you, you will tell them where
we are,'' a flight attendant said.
   Fear had overcome them during hours they spent in the hotel
laundry, where some had tried to disguise themselves as bellboys or
chefs.
   A flight instructor screamed at me and shoved me against the
wall when I tried to explain why I wanted to make a telephone call.
Our offices in Mexico City and New York were worried.
   Gruson and I got out after four hours, when food was brought to
an adjoining room. We dashed into the room, grabbed the telephone
and called our offices.
   Skinner's call to his crisis center finally paid off about at 11
p.m. with the arrival of 90 paratroopers from Bravo Company, 2nd
Batallion, 405th Infantry, 82nd Airborne Division.
   The soldiers handed out soft drinks, cookies and fruit from the
hotel kitchen, checked to see if anyone needed medical care, found
blankets and pillows and got everyone settled.
   ``They gotta go through us to get to you and they can't do
that,'' an officer said.
   After more than 24 hours in combat, the men of Battlin' Bravo
exhibited such a degree of courage, kindness and courtesy that I
decided to call on them every time I needed saving.
   Next morning's evacuation was fast and frantic. A sniper had
shot one of the soldiers minutes before. The paratroopers piled 110
guests and hotel workers into two Marriott airport food service
trucks and we barreled down the road to the ruins of an old fort
about three miles away.
   Several hours later, a Chinook troop transport helicopter landed
on the nearby beach in a cloud of green smoke from a marker
grenade. We hustled aboard and flew to Howard Air Force Base, about
eight minutes away.
   Finally I was free. Really free. And I savored it like a
spoonful of caviar.
   My exhilaration faded as I saw what the fighting and looting had
done to the city. I saw gutted stores, shattered glass, smoldering
ruins, streets awash in garbage where armed bands roamed at will.
   The story had just begun.
</TEXT>

</DOC>