<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 1159EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Bush-Home 1stLd-Writethru a0657 12-31 0756</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Home, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0657,690</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush's Home Away From Home May Not Be the Ritz, But It'll Do</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: SUBS 1st graf to restore AP logo and 11th graf pvs, bgng: It's
close, to CORRECT spelling of Otto's Bar-B-Q.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Bush Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER CONNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   HOUSTON _ Home away from home for President Bush is Suite 271 in
the Houstonian Hotel _ two bedrooms and a parlor at the government
discount rate of $88 a room per night, plus access to a world-class
fitness facility on a wooded, 22-acre estate.
   The Houstonian here in Bush's adopted hometown _ not 1600
Pennsylvania Avenue _ is his legal residence. It's the only home he
has left in Texas.
   It is a short jog from his old neighborhood, and not far from
the glittering Galleria shopping center and skyscrapers of this oil
town where Bush's political career got its start.
   Bush and his wife, Barbara, spend five to 10 nights a year at
the Houstonian. The rest of the time, the presidential suite is
open to other wayfarers for $550 a night _ a good deal steeper than
the flat $88 per room the Houstonian charges Bush and other
government workers in his entourage.
   It is not the ritziest hotel in Houston by a long shot, but it
does boast a world-class health club and a mile-long, Astroturf
jogging trail that snakes around the Houstonian's campus, hard by
the Buffalo Bayou and just outside the Loop, the main artery around
Houston.
   The Houstonian actually is more of a retreat center for
corporate conferences than a carriage-trade hotel.
   ``Joe Smith the traveling salesman we don't get,'' said General
Manager Louis R. Lanzino.
   Bush started hanging his hat at the Houstonian after selling his
old home nearby when he moved to Washington in 1981 to become vice
president.
   Why did Bush choose the Houstonian?
   ``It's a great place for him. It's secluded, it's got a
wonderful health club, familiar surroundings,'' said Stephen Hart,
a deputy White House spokesman.
   ``It's close to Otto's Bar-B-Q and friends in the (Houston)
Country Club,'' added Hart, singling out two disparate touchstones
of Bush's existence in Houston.
   Otto's, an unpretentious cafeteria-style eatery, remains a
favorite Bush haunt. And Bush, winding up a year-end vacation, got
in a round of golf Saturday at the Houston Country Club, which
costs $35,000 to join.
   ``He has to be from somewhere,'' said Craig Miller, concierge at
the adjacent Inn on the Park, who still remembers Bush as his local
congressman.
   The Houstonian does not get a lot of guests' requesting to sleep
in the president's bed.
   ``Every now and then the local Democrats rent it and have
something in there. They think that's fairly clever,'' said Miller.
   ``Our presidential suite is a very nice suite, but it's not
overdone,'' said Lanzino, choosing his adjectives carefully. He
described the Bushes as ``very down-to-earth people, and the suite
is reflective of that.''
   The Houstonian is owned by a local developer, Joe Russo, and a
Saudi businessman, Ahmad Mannai. With 300 hotel rooms and 35
conference rooms, it was near capacity when Bush and his entourage
of aides, Secret Service agents and communications specialists
rolled in Friday night.
   Most Houstonian rooms have ``servi-bars'' that offer guests
snacks and drinks _ for a price. But not Bush's suite.
   ``We've been asked to not have `servi-bars' in there,'' said
Lanzino. ``The president likes diet soft drinks and fresh fruit, so
we have that available all the time.''
   If the hotel rooms are modest, the health club is not, from the
full size gym to racquetball and tennis courts, sauna, massage and
a locker room where attendants dispense both fruit juices and
Heineken beer in cans. There is an indoor track with computerized
pacing lights that loops around nearly 80 yards worth of weight
machines, treadmills, stair-walkers and other muscle-building gear.
   ``The president claims that we have the best masseuse in the
world here,'' said Lanzino.
   The compliment is for a 47-year-old onetime South Vietnamese
major called John, who charges $40 for a one-hour massage.
   John _ his real name is Huynh Duy Nguyen _ came to be a masseur
fairly late in life. He was trained in kung fu in Vietnam, but
abandoned the martial art after seriously injuring a friend in the
fight.
   Now he uses his hands on the backs of the president of the
United States and other clients.
   ``My job, I love it,'' he said. ``Mr. President is a very
special customer. He's very good for me.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>