<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0102 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1853EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Panama-Drugs     12-26 0407</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Drugs,0418</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Invasion of Panama Nets Valuable Drug Data</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DORALISA PILARTE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. drug agents have been poring
over thousands of seized documents that are providing valuable
intelligence on international drug trafficking, authorities said
Tuesday.
   They said the information could be used against Panamanians
under U.S. drug indictments, such as Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega
and his associate, Lt. Col. Luis del Cid, who has been arrested and
taken to the United States.
   One windfall was the headquarters of Panama's Anti-Narcotics
Special Force.
   U.S. soldiers stormed the headquarters Monday and detained three
men after being tipped off by an informant, said U.S. Army Lt. Col.
William Leszczynski, commander of the 3rd Battalion, 9th Infantry
Regiment.
   Authorities reported finding rifles, shotguns, handguns and much
ammunition as well as cocaine, marijuana, morphine and drug
paraphernalia.
   Torture apparently was carried out in the same building.
Leszczynski said his troops found ``electronic devices that could
be hooked up to people for electric shocks.''
   They found a room filled with immigration files of foreigners
from more than two dozen countries, including Cuba, Nicaragua and
Colombia. The files, in racks that reached the ceiling, contained
detailed information on foreigners' entries and exits. Each file
had a small photo of the subject.
   One Miami-based agent of the U.S. Drug Enforcement
Administration who visited the white stucco house Tuesday said that
at first glance, it seemed to be a legitimate anti-narcotics
operation.
   ``What I find unusual is that these files were kept in a
house,'' she said. ``I need to find out whose house this is, in
whose name it's registered.'' She spoke on condition of anonymity.
   The files largely were from the 1960s through the 70s.
   ``It's good for us,'' the agent said. ``This tells me who's been
in an out of the country. I already found some files of Colombian
drug traffickers. So now I know they were here. Now I go for the
more recent files.''
   She would not say how many DEA agents came here, although she
said it was far fewer than 20. The U.S. military has provided
transport, communications and other support, she added.
   Three makeshift jails at the back of the house seemed to have
been inhabited recently. A plastic container with urine stood in
the corner of one cell, where the occupant had slept on a dirty mat
and cardboard placed on the cement floor.
</TEXT>

</DOC>