<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0241 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1157EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-BoardofTrade Open   12-21 0378</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Board of Trade, Open,0392</SECOND>
<HEAD>Crop Futures Lower In Early Trading</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Grain and soybean futures prices were mostly
lower in early trading today on the Chicago Board of Trade, largely
reflecting follow-through selling from Wednesday's weaker close.
   Forecasts for more badly needed rain in Brazil, a leading
soybean producer, added to the selling pressure in the soybean
market this morning.
   In the wheat market, there were indications that the Soviet
Union is seeking to buy European, rather than U.S. wheat, which
prompted selling of wheat futures.
   Losses were limited, though by reports of new export sales of
U.S. grains. The Agriculture Department said it had accepted bids
from Iraq for 11,000 metric tons of wheat at subsidized prices and
Mexico was rumored to have bought nearly 205,000 metric tons of
U.S. corn overnight.
   The soybean market had led Wednesday's decline, which analysts
attributed to seasonal factors and to the temporary closing of the
Panama Canal. Shipments of U.S. soybeans to Japan pass through the
canal, which reopened today.
   In early trading, wheat futures were } cent to 1} cents lower
with the contract for delivery in March at $4.12 a bushel; corn was
\ cent to 1 cent lower with March at $2.38 a bushel; oats were
unchanged to { cent higher with March at $1.52} a bushel; soybeans
were } cent to 2 cents lower with January at $5.73 a bushel.
   Cattle futures were mostly lower while pork futures were mostly
higher in early trading on the Chicago Mercantile Exchange.
   The Agriculture Department announced this morning that its
monthly cold-storage report, which was due out this afternoon, will
be delayed until Dec. 27.
   Pork-belly futures had fallen sharply Wednesday on expectations
that the report would show a large net increase in warehoused
supplies of the commodity.
   Live cattle futures were .10 cent to .28 cent higher with
February at 76.50 cents a pound; feeder cattle were .05 cent lower
to .20 cent higher with January at 84.72 cents a pound; live hogs
were .07 cent lower to .23 cent higher with February at 49.07 cents
a pound; frozen pork bellies were .55 cent lower to .23 cent higher
with February at 49.05 cents a pound.
   Livestock and meat futures finished lower on Wednesday.
</TEXT>

</DOC>