<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1259EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PhoneFight     12-19 0655</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Phone Fight,0674</SECOND>
<HEAD>Newly Recognized Tribe Could Face A Battle Over Cellular Phones</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JONATHAN YENKIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two years after the Wampanoag Indians won a battle
to gain official recognition as a tribe, they are willing to pit
themselves against a major telephone company to get into the
cellular phone business.
   The tribe is after a Federal Communications Commission license
estimated to be worth millions of dollars that was to be awarded by
lottery Wednesday.
   The Wampanoags formed a company to operate a cellular telephone
system on Cape Cod and its surrounding islands off the
Massachusetts coast within a year after they won a promise of land
for a reservation on one of the islands, Martha's Vineyard.
Revenues from the company would help them build their community,
the say.
   All they need now is the license. But Nynex Corp. says the tribe
isn't providing telephone service, so is not eligible to compete in
the lottery against the already established company. The Wampanoags
say federal law favors Indian economic development.
   The FCC lottery pits Indian Cellular Telephone Co. against Nynex
Mobile Communications, a subsidiary of Nynex Corp., which provides
phone service throughout New York and New England.
   The issue is complicated by the fact that two licenses will be
awarded.
   One license will go to a ``wire line'' applicant, defined as a
company that provides phone service to the area; the other will go
to a ``non-wire line'' applicant, which can be a company or
individual with demonstrated financial ability to run the system.
   The FCC has hundreds of non-wire line applicants, but only three
on the other side: the Wampanoags, Nynex Mobile and Elizabeth
Islands Telephone Co., which serves a small number of phones on
Naushon Island.
   Nynex and Elizabeth Islands struck a deal before the lottery.
Peter Harrigan, general manager of Nynex Mobile, refused to
disclose the details, except to say, ``We have two of the three
chips.''
   If the third chip, belonging to the Wampanoags, is picked,
Harrigan said his company will appeal the case to the FCC.
   ``We don't believe Indian Cellular is a qualified applicant,''
he said. ``There is a rule that you have to be providing telephone
service.''
   But Tom Tureen, a lawyer for the tribe, said while Indian
Cellular does not currently provide phone service, it should
nonetheless be considered a phone company under FCC rules.
   ``Federal laws must be interpreted to take the special status of
tribes into consideration,'' he said. ``Federal Indian policy
favors Indian economic development and self determination.''
   Myron Peck, deputy chief of mobile services for the FCC, said he
could not discuss whether the agency's rules would be bent for the
Wampanoags.
   ``If they happen to win, depending on the issues that are
raised, we will look at it then,'' he said.
   Peck said the FCC has not yet been forced to decide such an
issue. A similar case occurred in Arizona, where the Gila River
Indians won a lottery, but they reached a settlement recently with
a subsidiary of U.S. West Communications before the case reached
the commission.
   Tureen said he could not predict whether the Wampanoags would
settle the case if they are contested. ``We will vigorously pursue
our application,'' he said. ``We've had tough battles before.''
   The Wampanoags gained federal recognition as a tribe in 1987
culminating a legal battle begun in 1974, when the Wampanoags filed
a lawsuit to recover aboriginal lands.
   About 280 Wampanoag Indians live on Martha's Vineyard, and the
tribe is renting office space in the town of Gay Head. About 250
acres of land have been put into federal trust. Once the land
acquisition is finished, the tribe will have a reservation where
the Indians can build homes.
   Forrest Cuch, a tribal planner, said if the Wampanoags get the
license, the revenue could help with housing, offices and community
buildings.
   ``That would really get us off the ground,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>