<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0607EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     12-23 0566</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0580</SECOND>
<HEAD>Much of Nation in Deep Freeze</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Temperatures were in the single digits throughout the nation
early today, as an arctic cold front extended as far south as
Florida.
   Snow blanketed parts of the Carolinas and Jacksonville, Fla.,
while other parts of the South also shivered under unusually low
temperatures. Temperatures in Tennessee plunged to 0 in Memphis and
6 below in Nashville, and in Georgia a sheet of ice and up to 2
inches of snow covered the state's Golden Isles, normally a holiday
haven of winter golf among the palm trees. Temperatures fell to 6
below in Louisville.
   The deep freeze continued in the Northeast, with temperatures
today dropping to 3 degrees in Portland, Maine, 5 in Boston and 8
in New York. Snow fell amid 0 degree temperatures in Pittsburgh.
   In the Midwest, temperatures dropped to 20 below in Des Moines,
Ill., and Kansas City, Mo. Snow also fell today in Michigan and
Ohio.
   More than 125 cities reported record low temperatures for the
date Friday, with the town of Rochford in the Black Hills of
western South Dakota reporting a low of 60 degrees below 0.
Temperatures dipped to 47 below in Montana at Broadus and Hardin.
   Records lows Friday included Pittsburgh at 12 below; Tulsa 6
below; Oklahoma City at 4 below; Denver at 18 below, and
Scottsbluff, Neb., at 42 below. A low of 23 degrees below zero made
it the coldest day ever in Kansas City, Mo.
   In parts of central Montana, a warm front caused a rapid rise in
Temperatures Friday. Cutbank went from a morning low of 34 below to
an afternoon high of 40.
   Fair skies and seasonable temperatures prevailed in the West
Friday. Temperatures warmed into the 60s and 70s in southern
Arizona and even into the 80s in parts of Southern California.
   The high for the nation today was 81 degrees in California at
Escondido, Fallbrook and Spring Valley.
   Other reports at 3 a.m. EDT:
   _East: Albany -6 fair; Atlanta 10 partly cloudy; Boston 5 fair;
Charleston, S.C. 19 snow; Chattanooga 6 fair; Cincinnati -6 snow;
Cleveland -4 fair; Detroit 0 fair; Hatteras 25 snow; Jacksonville
31 snow; Key West 63 windy; Knoxville 3 fair; Macon 23 partly
cloudy; Miami 57 drizzle; New York 8 fair; Philadelphia 8 fair;
Pittsburgh 0 snow; Portland, Maine 3 fair; Richmond 12 fair; Tampa
40 foggy; Washington, D.C. 9 fair.
   _Central: Birmingham 3 fair; Bismarck -7 partly cloudy; Chicago
-5 fair; Denver 2 fair; Des Moines -20 fair; Fort Worth 3 fair;
Indianapolis -9 cloudy; Kansas City -20 fair; Little Rock 4 fair;
Louisville -6 fair; Memphis 0 fair; Nashville -6 fair; New Orleans
14 fair; North Platte -16 fair; Oklahoma City -5 fair; Omaha -17
foggy; Rapid City -8 fair; St. Louis -12 fair; Minneapolis-St. Paul
-15 fair; Sault Ste. Marie -4 snow; San Antonio 11 fair.
   _West: Albuquerque 22 fair; Anchorage 31 snow; Boise 32 fair;
Casper 27 windy; Fairbanks 4 snow; Great Falls 41 windy; Honolulu
70 fair; Las Vegas 39 fair; Los Angeles 61 fair; Medford 30 foggy;
Pendleton 29 foggy; Phoenix 50 fair; Portland, Ore. 39 rain; Reno
26 fair; Salt Lake City 30 fair; San Diego 51 hazy; San Francisco
44 foggy; Seattle 44 drizzle; Spokane 28 fair.
   _International: Montreal 8 fair; Ottawa 8 fair; Regina 10 partly
cloudy; Toronto 5 fair; Winnipeg 7 windy.
</TEXT>

</DOC>