<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1006EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-BombThreat 3rdLd-Writethru a0482 12-30 0794</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bomb Threat, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0482,0812</SECOND>
<HEAD>Threatened Northwest Flight Takes Off For Detroit With 42 Aboard</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 3 grafs to CORRECT that 14 crew members aboard, UPDATE
that Northwest allowing passengers to switch to other airlines. Pickup
4th graf, `The plane ...'; Flight 51 skedded to arrive in Detroit at 4:41
p.m EST.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhotos</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATRICK McDOWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A nearly empty Northwest Airlines DC-10 took off
for Detroit today, despite a bomb threat that persuaded 105 people
to cancel their bookings, leaving just 42 people on board.
   The Paris to San Francisco flight, with change of planes in
Detroit, carried 14 crew members and 28 passengers, three of whom
were journalists making the trip to report on the threatened flight.
   A steady stream of passengers had changed their travel plans
after hearing news reports of threats against Flight 51 in
retaliation for the bombing convictions of two Palestinians.
Northwest offered to allow passengers to change to other flights or
airlines with no penalty.
   The plane left Charles de Gaulle airport at 2:45 p.m. (8:45 a.m.
EST), more than two hours late because of fog.
   Close scrutiny of every piece of hand luggage being put aboard
caused a brief initial delay, but then the plane was held up by fog
that was disrupting all flights at the airport and caused some
flights to be canceled.
   The Saudi newspaper Asharq Al-Awsat reported today that Spanish
authorities had information that Moslem extremists planned to use
surface-to-air missiles to attack Arab and French passenger planes.
   The newspaper, quoting investigators in Madrid, said the
information was developed following last month's seizure of arms
caches apparently intended for terrorist attacks in Europe.
   Spanish police have refused to comment on similar reports in
Spanish newspapers, saying their inquiry is confidential. There was
no indication of a connection between the Saudi report and the
Northwest flight.
   Many passengers requested transfers to other flights when they
arrived at Northwest's check-in desk at mid-morning today.
   ``I would have been on pins and needles the whole way,'' said
Camille Major, 21, of Madison, Wis., who was headed home after
three weeks in Europe.
   ``Six hundred dollars isn't worth my life,'' she said. ``My
vacation was bad and this just tops it off.''
   The Hsia family of Foster City, Calif., near San Francisco,
arrived at the airport about 10 a.m. unaware of the bomb threat.
   The family of four held discussions about whether to change
airlines.
   ``My mom changed her mind three times, but we're going,'' said
17-year-old Eddie Hsia, baseball cap tipped back on his head. ``My
dad follows what my mom says.''
   Security at the airport was extremely tight, as armed officers
of the air and border police and riot police with leashed dogs
shepherded the passengers through scrupulous check-in procedures.
Each piece of luggage was X-rayed on freeze-frame video machines.
   Even a small souvenir bust of Napoleon was put on the belt and
X-rayed separately.
   The DC-10 can hold 284 passengers. Northwest originally had 130
seats booked, but cancellations started pouring in Friday after
news reports described the bomb threat against the plane.
   Northwest announced the threat Thursday, but said the FBI asked
that no details be disclosed.
   ABC News, quoting sources it did not identify, reported Thursday
night that a man with a ``Middle Eastern accent'' made the threat
to Northwest's Detroit office, saying the bombing would be in
retaliation for life sentences given two Palestinians convicted in
Sweden of charges connected with a string of bombings in Europe.
   One of the two, Abu Mohammed Talb, is a suspect in the December
1988 bombing of Pan Am Flight 103, which exploded over Lockerbie,
Scotland.
   He and co-defendant Marten Imandi were sentenced to life for
their part in the 1985 bombing of a Northwest office in Copenhagen
that killed one person and wounded 20, one of four bombings in
Denmark and the Netherlands for which they were convicted.
   In Washington, Federal Aviation Administration spokesman John
Leyden said officials were ``working with Northwest and with the
French authorities to ensure there is extra security on the
flight.''
   Pierre Quilici, deputy chief of France's Air and Border Police,
said U.S. authorities had passed on word of the threat several days
ago. He said he could not disclose any special security measures
planned to protect the flight.
   Airline spokesman Robert Gibbons said Northwest originally
agreed to a request by security agencies not to make the threat
public. But then a report of the threat came out of Europe.
   The FAA has a policy of not alerting the public to security
threats unless they are very specific and the flight involved is
not being canceled. The Northwest threat appeared to meet
conditions that would allow disclosure.
</TEXT>

</DOC>