<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0216EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-Color     12-21 0502</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Color,0519</SECOND>
<HEAD>City in Chaos: Looting and a Vow to Keep Up the Fight</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RAFAEL CANDANEDO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dodging gunfire and patrols of both
U.S. troops and Panamanian militia, civilians took to the streets
of a city in chaos and enthusiastically looted everything from
jewelry stores to appliance shops.
   A festive atmosphere reigned Wednesday in commercial districts
as civilians walked away with cameras, tires, mattresses, even
refrigerators and stoves carried by four or five people at a time.
   As midday temperatures hovered at 99 degrees, Red Cross teams
scurried to pick up bodies from the pre-dawn fighting before they
decomposed in the heat.
   Men, women and children emerged from the low-income area of
Chorillo and Old Panama, where combat was especially intense, and
walked to churches, hospitals and schools in search of safety.
   Some cursed the U.S. troops, others Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
Still others said they had faith in the strongman's powers of
survival.
   ``They (the Americans) have been very tough with this invasion,
and the poorer people had to suffer most,'' said Juan, about 25
years old, as he and a group of friends fended off the heat with
cold beers a few yards from the Old Panama barracks, destroyed by
American troops.
   ``If you keep standing in the middle of the street, the
`gringos' are going to arrest you,'' Juan warned a reporter. About
half a dozen American soldiers sat on a roadside patch of grass
about 20 yards away.
   The GIs appeared nervous as they took a break to eat lunch.
   A few blocks away, a housewife of about 40 looked happily at the
American troops. ``There was no other way to get this bandit out,''
she said of Noriega.
   A man of about 25, with unkempt hair, spray-painted a nearby
wall: ``Sovereignty Without Noriega!''
   Armed toughs who support Noriega took advantage of the chaos to
commandeer cars, often at gunpoint.
   Attack jets bombed and helicopters strafed a Panamanian Defense
Forces barracks on a hill in the San Miguelito neighborhood to the
northeast, a stronghold of the Dignity Battalions _ the armed
militia loyal to Noriega.
   One man who said he was a government employee stood at a
newsstand near the Foreign Ministry building. About 35, he refused
to give his name but said he had confidence in Noriega.
   ``The MAN,'' he said, referring to the general by his nickname,
``he's going to resist and things are going to get tough for the
Yankees. He knows what he's doing.''
   At dozens of U.S. Army checkpoints, those who wanted to pass had
to get out of their cars and drop to their knees while their
vehicles were thoroughly searched.
   In one house, where four reporters were hiding along with the
residents, the owner said he had nothing to fear until his wife
noticed an 8-by-10 color photo of her husband as a student shaking
hands with Cuban President Fidel Castro.
   She swiftly hid the photo in their bedroom.
</TEXT>

</DOC>