<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0167 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2309EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-MailBombs 3rdLd-Writethru 2Takes 12-19 0930</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mail Bombs, 3rd Ld-Writethru, 2 Takes, a0722,0954</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Disarm Another Mail Bomb at Jacksonville, Fla., NAACP Office</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 29 grafs to UPDATE with Thornburgh comment, further
Sessions comment, NAACP offices nationwide told to tighten security, television
station receiving letter declaring war on 11th Circuit, DELETES outdated
Sessions comment. Picks up 25th graf of a0722: ``He said they ...</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos SAV1,2, AX4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURAN NEERGAARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Police on Tuesday disarmed a parcel bomb at the NAACP office in
Jacksonville, Fla., the fourth in a series of mail bombs that
killed an alderman in Savannah, Ga., and a federal judge in Alabama.
   U.S. Attorney General Dick Thornburgh said in Washington that
investigators were ``concentrating on a possible racial
motivation'' for the rash of mail bombs that began Saturday. FBI
Director William Sessions said an organized group might be involved.
   Savannah officials and the FBI confirmed that the parcel bomb
that killed Alderman Robert Robinson on Monday was similar to those
that killed 11th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals Judge Robert S.
Vance on Saturday and forced the evacuation Monday of the
courthouse in Atlanta that includes the 11th Circuit.
   An FBI agent said the Alabama and Georga bombs all had different
postmarks, phony return addresses and too many postage stamps.
   Elsewhere Tuesday, an anonymous caller threatened to kill a
federal judge in Alabama. A package delivered to a Birmingham,
Ala., city councilman who was a friend of Vance was found to be
harmless.
   The National Association for the Advancement of Colored People
instructed its 1,800 branch offices and seven regional offices to
tighten security because the bombs might be racially motivated,
Executive Director Benjamin Hooks said from the organization's
headquarters in Baltimore.
   The discovery of the parcel bomb at the NAACP's Jacksonville
office prompted police to evacuate and cordon off the building.
   The bomb was disarmed inside the building with a device that
disconnected the battery from the explosive, officials said.
   ``It was designed to kill the individual that opened this
package or anyone else standing in the area,'' said Jacksonville
Sheriff Jim McMillan.
   ``It had a great similarity in the packaging to the other
bombs,'' said Willi Ellison of the U.S. Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco
and Firearms. ``It was addressed to no one specifically, but to the
legal staff of the NAACP.''
   The bomb was to be taken to an FBI laboratory in Washington and
compared with the other devices, Ellison said.
   The package arrived at the NAACP office Monday, but had been
left unopened. A series of bomb threats and scares hit federal
buildings around Florida, but no other explosive devices were found.
   Thornburgh said in a statement that he had contacted civil
rights leaders ``to assure them that we are fully committed to the
vigorous investigations of these crimes and the apprehension of the
person or persons'' who committed them.
   The FBI and Thornburgh warned civil rights leaders, judges and
attorneys that the bombings may be racist attacks, but the attorney
general stressed there was no firm conclusion on motivation.
   A pattern of racist attacks ``has to be one of the factors in
the back of all our minds,'' Sessions told a Justice Department
news conference. He said the incidents have involved ``federal
judges who have heard cases involving racial matters,'' the NAACP
and a black civil rights activist.
   Sessions said it was ``quite possible'' more than one person was
involved, and that the bombs might be the work of an organized
group. He noted that the incidents had occurred in three states in
the 11th Circuit.
   Sessions said no one had claimed responsibility for the bombs.
   Robinson, a civil rights activist and lawyer, was fatally
wounded by a mail bomb in his law office Monday, hours after the
courthouse evacuation in Atlanta.
   Although he was black, a law colleague said there was little
reason to figure him as a target of extremist bombers.
   Funeral services for Vance will be held Wednesday. U.S. Supreme
Court Justice Anthony M. Kennedy, who oversees the 11th Circuit, is
expected to attend, along with Sessions and the attorney general.
   FBI agent Tom Moore in Birmingham said there were ``strong
similarities'' between the three bombs.
   FBI Agent Allen Whitaker in Birmingham said the Georgia and
Alabama bombs came in similar packages but were mailed from
different places.
   ``There was not a common postmark,'' Whitaker said. ``All had
return addresses of different legitimate persons who had no
connection with the packages.''
   He said the packages bore an excessive number of postage stamps,
apparently to protect the senders from ``a face-to-face meeting
with postal employees.''
   Authorities in Alabama said the bomb that killed Vance sprayed
nails and The Atlanta Constitution reported Tuesday that the
Atlanta bomb also contained nails.
   ``We believed nails were part of this bomb also, and that has
been confirmed,'' said Savannah Mayor John Rousakis. He said he
learned from the FBI that the Savannah bomb bore a Georgia return
address, presumed to be fake.
   WAPT-TV in Jackson, Miss., reported Tuesday that it received an
anonymous letter in August declaring war on the 11th Circuit. The
letter was postmarked Aug. 21, one day a mail bomb tear-gas attack
on the NAACP's Atlanta offices.
   ``We turned it right over to the FBI,'' reporter Deanna Lee said
in a telephone interview. FBI spokesman Charles Steinmetz an
investigation into the letter began soon after the television
station had passed it along.
   Joseph Lowery, president of the Southern Christian Leadership
Conference in Atlanta, said he received a call from Thornburgh
expressing concern over the possible racial motive in the bombings.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>