<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0222 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1337EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--CBComeback Adv31   12-18 1085</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--CB Comeback, Adv 31,1113</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 31</HEAD>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<HEAD>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 1 b&amp;w photo.)</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Remember when it seemed everybody was jabbering
away on CB radios out on the highway, including Betty ``First
Mama'' Ford? It was a fad that peaked in the mid-1970s, then hit
the skids. But now sales of citizens band radios are on the upswing
again, industry officials say, but not to people who just want to
chitchat.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By ELLIOTT MINOR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Breaker, breaker, one-nine.
   CB radios, a craze during the gasoline crisis of the 1970s, are
making a comeback, largely because of increased sales to motorists
who want a way to summon help in case of breakdowns or accidents.
   Industry spokesmen say citizens band radios appeal to women,
retirees and young people who do not want to pay hundreds of
dollars for a cellular telephone.
   ``It's not a boom, but it's a nice, steady, gradual increase,''
says John Chass, vice president of marketing for Midland
International Corp., a major supplier of the radios in Kansas City,
Mo. ``The preponderance of customers we've surveyed are using the
CB for emergency use. They don't buy a CB to talk 24 hours a day.
They buy a CB for a perceived problem with their vehicle.''
   Chass says emergency radios account for 37 percent of all CB
sales, 22 percent of all CB buyers are women and 30 percent of the
male CB purchasers say they are buying them for women.
   Emergency CBs are small hand-held units costing $30 to $60 that
have the power of larger radios. They plug into cigarette lighters,
use antennae with magnetic bases and can be stowed in the trunk
with the jack and spare tire when not in use.
   ``The market is coming back,'' says Tony Margoulas, a marketing
information representative for Tandy Corp., a major supplier of CB
radios through its nationwide network of Radio Shack stores.
   CB sales peaked at about 11 million a year in 1975 and 1976 as a
result of the Arab oil embargo. Motorists used them to share
information on dwindling gasoline supplies, high prices and long
lines at service stations.
   In the process, Americans became fascinated with the nation's
long-haul truckers who had been using the radios for years to warn
of ``Smokey Bears'' and maintain human contact during lonely trips
that kept them away from home for weeks.
   Chass says sales plummeted to 800,000 units a year by 1980, but
began picking up about five years ago. An industry publication says
sales jumped from 1.6 million in 1984 to 2.2 million last year.
   Tom Lauterback, spokesman for the Washington-based Electronic
Industries Association, says emergency radios have become popular
with young, fairly affluent motorists who want to be able to get
help on the road.
   ``They provide a tremendous amount of peace of mind at an
affordable price,'' Lauterback says. ``If you have a flat tire or a
mechanical breakdown between towns, you can summon a trucker to
help you, or at least report it when he gets to the next town.''
   Ron Mayes, general manager of React International Inc., a
12,000-member group that uses CBs and other radios to assist
motorists and maintain communications during emergencies, says
studies show that emergency vehicles can reach an accident about 20
minutes faster when the trouble is reported by CB radio. React's
700 teams in the United States and Canada and many police
departments monitor channel 9, the official CB emergency channel.
   ``If there is a serious injury, 20 minutes is a significant
amount of time,'' Mayes noted during a phone interview from React's
headquarters in Wichita, Kan. ``We would like to see more
monitoring of channel 9 by police departments and volunteer groups.
We know that if they did, more people would utilize CB 9 for
emergencies and in general the traveling public would be safer.''
   Most CB radios have 40 channels, but the majority of routine
highway information is relayed on channel 19, a popular frequency
for truckers. The Federal Communications Commission no longer
requires a CB license, but users need to learn the truckers' jargon
to do much talking or listening. CBs have a range of 5 to 15 miles,
depending on terrain, weather conditions and antenna.
   ``Once you learn to understand all that gibberish, you can tune
in to what they're saying,'' Margoulas said in an interview from
Tandy's headquarters in Fort Worth, Texas.
   Rather than names, CBers use ``handles,'' such as
``Roadrunner,'' ``Six Pack,'' ``Double Clutch,'' ``Candy Man,''
``Old Timer,'' ``Night Rider'' and ``Alabama Slim.''
   Before transmitting it's polite to ask for a ``break.''
   A ``bird dog'' is a radar detector. ``My bird dog is barking''
means there's police radar in the area. Police who use radar are
``taking pictures.''
   A ``Smokey Bear'' is a state trooper, a ``county mounty'' is a
deputy sheriff and a ``city kitty'' is a city cop.
   A ``chicken coop'' is a weigh station, a trucking terminal is a
``junkyard'' and ``the big road'' is an interstate highway.
Automobiles and pickups are known as ``four wheelers,'' and car
carriers are known as ``portable parking lots.''
   A ``footwarmer'' or ``kicker'' is an illegal linear amplifier
that boosts the transmission power of a CB beyond 4 watts.
   Besides their communications value, CBs also provide a source of
entertainment and help break the monotony on long drives.
   Keith Urban, a marketing director with Dynascan Corp., a Chicago
company that sells Cobra CBs, says cellular telephones are helping
to fuel the comeback. Young people who don't want to pay $300 for a
cellular phone can buy a CB for less than $100 and talk to friends.
   Urban says CBs are still important to the nation's 1 million
commercial truck drivers, despite the advent of cellular phones and
small computers that allow truckers to communicate with their
companies by satellite.
   ``They spend long hours on the road,'' he said. ``They don't
listen to it all the time, but when they get bored they know they
can flip on their radio and talk to the guy in front of them.''
   Trucker Roy Carden of Albany uses his CB to locate delivery
points in strange towns, to get help if he has a breakdown and to
talk to other drivers.
   ``I think everybody who is on the road a lot ought to have a
CB,'' says Carden, who goes by the handle ``Wild Man.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>

</DOC>