<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0115EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Panama-CoupWidow     12-23 0359</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Coup Widow,0365</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Invasion Viewed with Favor by Widow of Failed Coup Leader</HEAD>
<UNK>With PM-Panama,Bjt</UNK>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For the widow of Maj. Moises Giroldi, who led
October's failed coup attempt against Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega,
the U.S. overthrow of the Panamanian strongman was the welcome
culmination of a sad story.
   But Adela Bonilla de Giroldi said she doesn't think Gen. Manuel
Antonio Noriega, who she believes killed of her husband, will ever
see trial in the United States, despite the $1 million bounty
offered by President Bush.
   ``I have faith that they will find him dead,'' she said. ``They
will never catch him alive. It doesn't matter to me if Bush wants
to put a price on Noriega's head. The important thing is that
Noriega doesn't stay in Panama.''
   Mrs. Giroldi, 36, called U.S. Army officials two days before the
failed Oct. 3 coup attempt by her husband to appeal for help. The
coup failed, and Noriega was reported to have executed Giroldi
himself after regaining control. Mrs. Giroldi is among those who
accuse the United States of dooming the coup by failing to support
it quickly enough.
   ``I was so frustrated because President Bush didn't do anything
for my husband,'' Mrs. Giroldi said Thursday in Miami, where she
fled after the failed coup. ``But now, even though many lives have
been lost (in the U.S. invasion), I am relieved. My husband did not
die in vain. His dream of ridding Panama of Noriega has come true.
He is dead but he died for a great cause.''
   Mrs. Giroldi said her husband, a one-time confidante of Noriega,
planned to deliver the general alive to U.S. authorities to face
drug trafficking charges. But Pentagon officials have said Giroldi
planed to let Noriega retire in Panama. The Bush administration its
inaction during the coup attempt stemmed from disagreement among
the rebels about what to do with Noriega.
   Like many Panamanian exiles, Mrs. Giroldi, a mother of three who
worked at the national bank of Panama, said she would return as
soon as stability was restored.
   ``It is our home and we want to help rebuild it,'' she said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>