<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0193 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0109EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Eastern Bjt   12-19 0761</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Eastern, Bjt,0785</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eastern Expects To Sell Latin American Routes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCY GORDON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eastern Airlines has revived a plan to shrink
its operations by about a third, telling creditors it expects to
sell its valuable Latin American routes.
   At a meeting with major creditors Monday in New York, Eastern
officials also projected a net loss of $250 million for the fourth
quarter. They presented creditors with a revised business plan that
takes into account the sale of the Latin American routes.
   The plan reverts to an April proposal for restructuring Eastern
at about two-thirds its pre-strike size. With the Latin American
routes, the airline would have remained at 80 percent to 90 percent
of its original size.
   The sale of the routes is being negotiated, but no deal has been
struck with the potential buyer, rival American Airlines.
   ``We are in intense negotiations with Eastern but a deal has not
yet been completed,'' said Al Becker, a spokesman for American at
its headquarters in Fort Worth, Texas. He refused to elaborate.
   According to a report Monday in The Wall Street Journal, Eastern
tentatively agreed over the weekend to sell the Latin American
routes and other assets to American for $450 million to $500
million.
   Eastern spokeswoman Karen Ceremsak declined to comment on the
Journal report. Eastern has not named American, the nation's
largest carrier, as the interested party.
   The New York Times reported today that Eastern agreed to sell
the routes to American for almost $350 million.
   In another sign of its ambition to expand, American announced
separately Monday an agreement to buy from Trans World Airlines its
Chicago-to-London route and four gates at Chicago's O'Hare
International Airport for $195 million.
   Miami-based Eastern has been working on a reorganization plan
since filing for bankruptcy court protection March 9, five days
after being crippled by a strike. Sales of other assets totaling
about $688 million already have been approved by U.S. Bankruptcy
Judge Burton R. Lifland.
   Negotiations with American, which has coveted the Latin American
routes for its expansion plans, stalled in August. Eastern
initiated new talks about two months ago, amid concerns about cash
shortfalls in its rebuilding plan.
   Eastern has delayed presenting a new reorganization plan to
creditors while the negotiations have continued. The airline hopes
to emerge from Chapter 11 early next year.
   If Eastern can sell the routes, ``It puts the reorganization
plan back on schedule,'' said Kevin Murphy, an airline analyst at
Morgan Stanley &amp; Co.
   The officials also told creditors that Eastern will be ``an
airline in transition'' between January and June of next year. In
addition to selling the Latin American routes, they said, Eastern
will continue to build up Atlanta as its hub and ``de-hub'' Miami,
to reduce Caribbean operations, and to retire its 14 Lockheed
L-1011s.
   Eastern expects to post a fourth-quarter net loss of $250
million, widened from a loss of $185.2 million in the third
quarter, said the officials, led by President Phil Bakes. Next
year, the carrier expects to turn a ``modest'' net profit in the
second half and a net loss for 1990 of $90 million.
   The improvement in the second half will result from refocusing
on the Atlanta hub, reducing expenses and expanding revenue, the
officials said.
   The sale of the Latin American routes was envisioned in
Eastern's original business plan presented to creditors last April.
The idea was scrapped in a later plan after talks with American
stalled.
   The Journal report Monday, citing unidentified sources, said
American would get Eastern's South American and Caribbean routes,
plus gates and landing sites at various airports. American also
would obtain some other assets of Eastern's parent Texas Air Corp.,
including Continental Airlines' Miami-London route, the report said.
   The Journal reported that the weekend agreement came about after
Continental agreed to settle a long-standing lawsuit against AMR
Corp., American's parent. That suit sought as much as $1 billion in
damages and alleged that American's computer reservations system
gave American an unfair advantage.
   The Times, citing an unidentified source, said Continental would
agree not to bring another suit over its contention that American's
reservation system, which is used by travel agents, favors American
flights over those of other carriers.
   The sale of international routes must receive government
approval, as well as that of the bankruptcy court.
   Also at the meeting Monday, the officials told creditors that
Eastern will ask Lifland for an extension of the Dec. 29 deadline
for submitting its revised reorganization plan. The judge already
has given the airline several such extensions.
</TEXT>

</DOC>