<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0097 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1529EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-RadiationDangers     12-19 0728</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Radiation Dangers,690</SECOND>
<HEAD>Study Says Low-Level Radiation Greater Cancer Risk Than Earlier Thought</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A National Research Council report said
Tuesday that cancer risks from low level X-ray and gamma ray
radiation are three to four times greater than earlier believed, a
finding that may lead to new standards for workers in nuclear
industries.
   However, Arthur C. Upton, chairman of the NRC committee that
made the study, said, ``The average citizen should not view this as
a source of great concern.''
   Upton said he expects that agencies worldwide that set industry
radiation exposure standards will reassess the risks as a result of
the NRC study. Although he said the committee did not recommend
changes, he did say, ``I personally expect that there will be
changes.''
   The committee reassessed the health effects of low-level
radiation using new data developed from studies of survivors from
the World War II atomic bombings in Japan; from other ``irridated
populations,'' such as workers in atomic industries, and from
animals studies.
   Experts on the committee also revised previous mathematical
methods of estimating risks from low-level radiation.
   Using the new information and methods, the committee concluded
that the risk for solid tumor cancer is three times greater than an
earlier NRC estimate, and the risk for leukemia is four times
greater.
   The committee also found a much greater danger for mental
retardation among unborn babies exposed to low-level radiation in
the eighth to 15th weeks after conception.
   The committee found that women are slightly more likely than men
to develop cancer from low levels of radiation, and that in some
types of cancer, children are more susceptible to radiation's
effects than are adults.
   Upton, who is chairman of the Department of Environmental
Medicine at New York University Medical Center, said the study
``merely endorses earlier reports that we really don't know that
there is a safe level'' of radiation exposure.
   He emphasized that the findings should not prevent patients from
receiving appropriate diagnostic X-rays or treatments because the
added risk from such medical radiation is very slight.
   ``A chest X-ray might increase (an individual's) risk by 1 in a
million,'' he said. ``It's essentially negligible. But it's not
negligible to public health authorities'' who analyze risks for the
population as a whole.
   Unneccessary X-rays, however, said Upton, ``should be avoided.''
   Seymour Jablon, a National Cancer Institute scientist who was on
the NRC committee, said ``the bottom line is that you ought to
avoid radiation whenever you can. But there are certain benefits,
such as medical X-rays, that outweigh the risk.''
   Many of the study's conclusions are based partly on the medical
history of 76,000 survivors of the 1945 atomic bombings in Japan, a
factor that powerfully influenced the new cancer risk estimates.
   Previously, the committee said, neutron radiation was
erroneously considered to have a major influence on the health of
the A-bomb survivors. Removing neutrons from the equation, it said,
means that the survivors are experiencing higher rates of cancer
from lower radiation doses.
   This is interpreted by the committee to mean that there is an
increased risk of cancer and other health problems from low-level
radiation.
   Dose and duration of exposure generally determine health
effects, the committee said.
   In the United States, for instance, natural background radiation
gives an exposure of 0.1 to 0.3 REMs a year. REM stands for ``rad
equivalent in man'' and is a unit of measure used to describe a
biological effect from a level of radiation exposure.
   A routine chest X-ray gives an added exposure of 0.06 REM;
occupational standards limit nuclear workers to an annual exposure
of no more than 5 REM.
   The committee estimated that a single burst of 10 REM radiation
exposure will result in 790 excess cancer and leukemia deaths per
100,000 people. For this same exposure, a 1980 National Research
Council report estimated cancer deaths per 100,000 people at 80 to
230..
   For a lifetime radiation exposure of 0.1 REM a year, the new
study estimated 520 male cancer deaths per 100,000 men, and 600
deaths per 100,000 women. The 1980 report estimated cancer deaths
at 25 to 119 for this rate of exposure.
   The NRC, which organized the committee study, is the research
arm of the National Academy of Sciences, a congressionally
chartered private organization that conducts research at the
request of the government.
</TEXT>

</DOC>