<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1522EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Hungary     12-17 0342</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hungary,0354</SECOND>
<HEAD>Old-Time Communists Gather to Revive Party</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Czechoslovakia, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALEX BANDY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUDAPEST, Hungary (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 800 aging, old-time
Communists reaffirmed their loyalty to a hard-line ideology Sunday
at a meeting to reorganize the party, which reformers disbanded two
months ago.
   Communist reformers declared the old party dead on Oct. 8 and
formed the Hungarian Socialist Party.
   Former general secretary Karoly Grosz denounced the move as a
``coup.''
   Grosz and other leading conservatives since have tried to
reassemble like-minded Communists, asserting that the old party _
officially known as the Hungarian Socialist Workers' Party _ still
exists.
   The tone of Sunday's session was set by Gyoergy Marosan, 82, who
told the gathering in a voice choked with emotion: ``I am glad I
don't have to begin by saying `ladies and Gentlemen' because we are
all comrades here.''
   The delegates responded with deafening applause.
   The old Communist Party had more than 750,000 members and they
have not been allowed to join the new party unless they sign a
declaration reflecting support for democratic reforms similar to
those taking place in other Eastern European countries.
   Marosan urged efforts to avoid ``fratricide,'' referring to the
split. ``No one can sweep Marxism off the table of history,'' he
told the cheering audience.
   In his keynote speech, Grosz declared that the Communist Party
``is alive because members want it that way'' and said it had about
100,000 members.
   He attacked the new government's economic plans, which are
similar to his when he was premier 18 months ago, and warned
against ``capitalist restoration.''
   Grosz announced that the committee that organized the
conservatives was resigning and urged the delegates to elect ``new
faces, new personalities into the leadership.''
   That organizing committee had been an uneasy alliance of former
government leaders. It included former Communist ideologist Janos
Berecz, one-time Foreign Minister Frigyes Puja and Robert
Ribanszki, a former personal secretary of the late party chief
Janos Kadar.
   A strong candidate to lead the party is Gyula Thuermer, Grosz's
former foreign policy adviser.
</TEXT>

</DOC>