<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0119EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Flight103     12-22 0559</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Flight 103,0576</SECOND>
<HEAD>A Year After Flight 103 Bombing, Lockerbie Remembers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LESLIE SHEPHERD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOCKERBIE, Scotland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Candles flickered in the bitter cold
of a Scottish winter night, lit by still-grieving American
relatives to remember the 270 people killed one year ago in the
bombing of Pan Am Flight 103.
   The candle lanterns, provided by an Albany, N.Y., couple whose
only daughter died in the terrorist attack, cast a soft
illumination over a granite memorial bearing the names of each
victim.
   ``It's a beautiful memorial,'' said Paul Hudson, an attorney who
heads the American relatives support group Pan Am Flight
103-Lockerbie.
   ``I think most of us will be back here many times.''
   Later Thursday, many of the more than 20 Americans who crossed
the Atlantic attended a memorial service at the small stone
Tundergarth church three miles outside town, near where the plane's
blue-and-white nose cone smashed down.
   The Rev. Cameron Gibson called the bombing ``an act of
indescribable evil and wickedness'' and read the biblical passage,
``Vengeance is mine . . . saith the Lord.''
   The service concluded just about the time the Boeing 747
exploded last year, and some relatives made short pilgrimages to
the surrounding farms and fields where 90 bodies were recovered.
   Flight 103, bound for New York and Detroit, exploded in midair
at approximately 7:03 p.m. on the Wednesday before Christmas last
year, killing all 259 people on board and 11 on the ground.
   Police say a bomb made of plastic explosives was concealed in a
radio-cassette recorder in a suitcase loaded into a forward cargo
hold.
   The dedication of the memorial by local clergymen began poignant
and somber commemorations that culminated in an outdoor ecumenical
service in Lockerbie's town square. No formal invitations were
issued, but U.S. Ambassador Henry Catto was present and Queen
Elizabeth II sent a representative.
   The lanterns, wax-coated paper bags filled with sand containing
a candle and each inscribed with the name of one of the victims and
the silhouette of a dove, were made for Hudson and his wife,
Eleanor, by students at the Albany Academy for Girls. Their
16-year-old daughter, Melina, had attended the school.
   As darkness fell, the lanterns lined both sides of the footpath
leading to and surrounding the Garden of Remembrance, the memorial
site carved from the local cemetery.
   Later outside the town hall, a temporary morgue in the days
following the disaster, more than one-third of the town's 3,500
residents gathered to hear the Rev. Patrick Keegan say, ``From this
disaster there is no complete recovery.''
   ``Quite simply, life cannot be the same again. It has changed.
We have changed,'' he said.
   ``To say that there is no recovery, that things won't get better
... is to say to the terrorists: `Here, you can have our lives as
well.'''
   Many of the American relatives wore simple blue-and-white lapel
buttons bearing the words ``Pan Am 103 _ The truth must be known.''
   Relatives in the United States and Britain have closely
monitored the police investigation in their campaign to bring the
bombers to justice and to improve airport security.
   Police confirm they have investigated the Popular Front for the
Liberation of Palestine-General Command, and are interested in
Mohammed Abu Talb, a member of another radical Palestinian faction
sentenced Thursday to life in prison in Sweden on unrelated bombing
charges.
</TEXT>

</DOC>