<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0510EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Panama-Incidents     12-20 0408</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Incidents,0423</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. and Panamanian Soldiers Have Had Several Confrontations</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Several incidents between U.S. and
Panamanian troops have occurred this year before the U.S. invasion.
   Here is a list of major ones:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>___</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Jan. 6 _ Nine launches and two helicopters from the U.S.
Southern Command went to the southern outlet of the Panama Canal.
The Southern Command said it was a training mission; the Panamanian
Defense Forces called it intimidation.
   March 1 _ One Panamanian was killed and two were wounded when
they stepped on unexploded munitions in a military zone, the
Southern Command said.
   March 3 _ Panamanian soldiers held nine Southern Command school
buses carrying 100 children for three hours on grounds the buses
did not have proper license plates.
   Aug. 8 _ U.S. forces detained 20 Panamanians, including nine
soldiers who had tried to block maneuvers on U.S.-controlled
territory, the Southern Command reported. They were were released a
few hours later.
   Aug. 9 _ Southern Command tanks blocked the entrance to Fort
Amador and helicopters flew over the area at the southern end of
the canal. The Southern Command said it acted because Panama
detained two U.S. soldiers. The Americans were exchanged for two
Panamanians detained by the Americans that day.
   Aug. 17 _ The Southern Command conducted maneuvers at 11
installations along the Panama Canal. U.S. officials said they were
enforcing their rights under the Panama Canal treaties; Panama said
the United States was violating the treaties.
   Oct. 3 _ Panamanian soldiers attempted a coup against Gen.
Manuel Antonio Noriega. American soldiers blocked some routes to
Defense Forces headquarters, but not all, and Noriega loyalists
rescued him.
   Oct. 31 _ U.S. forces blocked highways and held maneuvers along
the canal with tanks and aircraft. Panama called it an attempt at
intimidation.
   Nov. 20-21 _ The Southern Command blocked access to Health
Ministry installations with tanks, accusing Panamanian forces of
doing the same to Gorgas Hospital, a U.S. installation. All forces
withdraw two days later.
   Dec. 16 _ Panamanian soldiers fatally wounded an American
officer. The United States said the officer and his companions were
unarmed; the Panamanians said the Americans provoked the
confrontation.
   Dec. 18 _ An Army officer shot and wounded a Panamanian police
corporal.
   Dec. 20 _ President Bush ordered U.S. troops into combat in
Panama City on a mission to seize Noriega to face federal drug
charges in the United States.
</TEXT>

</DOC>