<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0106 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1533EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-Looters     12-21 0560</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Looters,0579</SECOND>
<HEAD>Panama City Looters Set Up Sidewalk Businesses _ With Stolen Goods</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALINA GUERRERO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In a shantytown named Brooklyn and in
a half- dozen other slums, hundreds of people set up shop on the
sidewalks Thursday with merchandise looted from the rich stores.
   They were hawking everything _ from designer brassieres to
French champagne and Gucci watches _ all at bargain-basement prices.
   The alleys of the slum called Brooklyn were crowded with buyers
and sellers, haggling and bargaining, while the wealthy stores on
Avenida Espana, Panama City's main thoroughfare, were stripped bare.
   All day Wednesday, while fighting raged between U.S. troops and
Defense Forces loyal to strongman Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega, mobs
out of the dirt-poor barrios invaded Calidonia, Avenida Central,
Transistmica, Supercentros, Almanecenes and other stores.
   They carried off everything, from TVs and stereos, to cellular
phones, mattresses and even huge refrigerators and washing
machines, from clothes to desingner shoes and Barbie dolls.
   Some even set up shop in the doorways of their wooden shacks.
   Many people deplored the massive robbery and said they were
ashamed of it, but for a neighborhood such as Brooklyn it appeared
to be a Christmas boon. Virtually all the residents are without
work.
   They lost their jobs when the U.S. imposed a trade embargo last
year, one of a series of Bush administration measures to pressure
Noriega out of power, plunging Panama into a severe economic crisis.
   ``He doesn't have any running shoes for me, but I ordered a pair
for tomorrow,'' a buyer, about 50 years old, explained to a
visiting reporter, pointing to one of the stall vendors.
   ``It'll be only $5,'' another vendor nearby said as he draped a
girl's dress over his arm, trying to convince a prospective client.
   ``Too expensive,'' said the client, a housewife. They started
haggling. She, like almost all Panamanians these days, did not want
to give their names.
   One small house was filled with women buyers. The owner was
selling designer brassieres at $2 apiece. The buyers rummaged
through boxes full of them, looking for their sizes.
   At another ``store,'' men jostled each other, trying to buy some
of the best brand shaving lotions and perfumes, at a fraction of
the regular price.
   ``Look,'' a young man said, proudly showing a visiting reporter
a gold watch. ``I bought it for $20, the salesman didn't even
realize it is a Gucci.''
   A middle-aged matron doing her Christmas shopping was all
smiles. ``I bought it for $8,'' she said, pointing to an imported
turkey that costs at least $40 in regular stores.
   But another woman about her age, looking down at the scene from
a nearby balcony, shook her head in dismany. ``It makes feel like
sitting down and crying,'' she said sadly as a couple of handcarts
were dragged down the street full of looted merchandise.
   One of the carts even had pieces of furniture.
   ``This is horrible. I prefer to continue being poor. I just
don't like this,'' said another woman in Los Libertadores, another
shanty neighborhood.
   A little girl of about eight ran by, carrying three boxes full
of clothes for a Barbie doll her brother had given her as a present.
   ``I'm scared. I'm trembling. I couldn't keep my son from going
out to look,'' said one man.
</TEXT>

</DOC>