<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1621EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Christmas-Israel     12-25 0543</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Christmas-Israel,0559</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tutu Condemns Israeli Treatment of Palestinians</HEAD>
<HEAD>With-AM-World Christmas, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LOUIS MEIXLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Archbishop Desmond Tutu of South Africa on
Monday compared his country's suppression of blacks to Israel's
treatment of Palestinians in the occupied lands, where Christmas
celebrations were subdued because of the Arab uprising.
   The Nobel Peace Prize laureate came under increased criticism
from Jews and also Christians sympathetic to Israel, who accused
him of taking a one-sided approach to the Middle East conflict
during his five-day trip.
   ``Members of our team have remarked on the similarities between
the situation in the occupied territories and that in South
Africa,'' Tutu told reporters.
   ``In the methods of resistance used by Palestinians, and in the
ways the Israeli government deals with the resistance, we
experienced an extraordinary sense of being at home,'' he said.
   In the West Bank city of Bethlehem, hundreds of Christian
pilgrims marked Christmas with a visit to St. Catherine's basilica
in Manger Square, the legendary site of Jesus' birth.
   Israeli soldiers removed barricades and metal detectors from
Manger Square after Christmas Eve passed without incident. But the
military presence was heavy, and at least 50 paratroopers and
soldiers from the elite Givati brigade patrolled the square.
   ``I don't like it, but I guess it's for security,'' said Sara
Paredes, 20, of Fort Leavenworth, Kan. as she stood outside the
Church of the Nativity.
   Paredes said making a pilgrimage to Bethlehem was a ``dream''
for her, but added that she would like to return in the future when
tensions and security are lessened and ``when I can find a better
Christmas.''
   Twenty Palestinians were wounded after troops opened fire on
stone-throwing demonstrators in the Gaza Strip, Arab reports said.
   The army said it was investigating the reports.
   Tutu drew harsh criticism after he refused to meet with a
delegation of Ethiopian Jews, saying their visit to the St. George
Anglican Church in East Jerusalem was not on his schedule.
   ``He did not have time to sit with us, even for two or three
minutes,'' Yitzhak Rahamim, a spokesman for the Ethiopian
Immigrants Association told a reporter outside the church. ``I
heard he had time to meet with Palestinians, but not with Jews,
even with us from Africa.''
   Tutu met Monday with a group of prominent Palestinian leaders to
discuss the situation in the occupied territories, where
Palestinians began their revolt against Israeli rule in December
1987.
   The Jerusalem-based International Christian Embassy, headed by
Willem van der Hoeven, a Dutch Evangelist cleric, published a
statement denouncing Tutu's repeated expressions of support for
Palestinians.
   In the statement that was also sent to Israeli leaders, Van der
Hoeven wrote: ``we specifically apologize for the remarks made by
the visiting Anglican Archbishop Desmond Tutu...we bow our heads in
shame.''
   Tutu's endorsement of a Palestinian state has alienated many
Israelis, and Israel's two chief rabbis refused to meet with the
Anglican human rights leader.
   When asked to comment on criticisms of his visit, Tutu replied:
``The bible...speaks about Israel as being an agent of God for
establishing justice and peace, and there is no way I am going to
say the way Israel is treating Palestinians is just. And if they
revile me for that, tough luck.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>