<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0176 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1400EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-PRI--FreefromRestraint Adv28   12-26 0406</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-PRI--Free from Restraint, Adv 28,0413</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv28</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Thursday, Dec. 28, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Family Sees Calmer, Happier Alzheimer's Victim With Restraints Gone</HEAD>
<HEAD>With BC-PRI--Untie The Elderly</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NANCY BENAC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Keith Grant never considered he'd ever have to
choose a nursing home for his wife, an active, intelligent
52-year-old mother of five.
   Then Virginia Grant's personality began to change, and months of
tests pointed to Alzheimer's disease. After three years of home
care, Mrs. Grant's behavior became so erratic her family made the
painful decision in 1985 to place her in Tel Hai Retirement
Community in Honey Brook, Pa.
   ``She would wander off, pick up things to eat anywhere, out on
the road, hitchhike, stop cars,'' Grant recalled. When family
members visited, however, they were troubled to find that more
often than not, Mrs. Grant was strapped down to keep her from
wandering and eating foreign objects.
   ``She seemed very upset and so were we,'' said her daughter,
Susan McTyier. ``Mom no longer was able to speak but she would
often look very angry or grumpy whenever we visted. Dad often made
the comment, `It looks as if she's saying, Why are you doing this
to me?'''
   Last January, Tel Hai launched a program to reduce its use of
restraints, cutting the rate from 43 percent of patients to less
than 10 percent. Confused residents who once were tied down now are
free to stroll an outdoor ``wandering garden''; those who were
restrained because they were unsteady on their feet have been
fitted with sturdy walking shoes.
   ``I remember from my nursing school days, it was considered a
standard of good care to restrain residents who might fall and
injure themselves,'' said assistant administrator Betty Petersheim.
``But now there's been a bubbling up from within the health-care
providers saying there's a better way.''
   The resulting new freedom has improved Mrs. Grant's demeanor and
that of other residents, Ms. McTyier said at a recent symposium on
restraints.
   ``She's calmed down visibly and we've also noticed an overall
happier attitude in the whole facility. It used to disturb us when
we would walk in and hear the residents moaning and crying for
help. Since the change, the noise level has dropped considerably.
...
   ``The nursing home doesn't seem like such a prison anymore when
you walk through and don't find people strapped down all the time.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Dec. 28</NOTE>

</DOC>