<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0702EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CommuterPlaneCrash     12-28 0388</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Commuter Plane Crash,0401</SECOND>
<HEAD>Crew Gave No Sign Of Trouble Before Fatal Plane Crash</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES L. ENG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASCO, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The crew of a commuter plane didn't indicate
any trouble in communications with the airport control tower just
minutes before the plane crashed, killing all six people aboard, a
federal investigator said.
   United Express Flight 2415 made a normal request to land, and
the tower operator at the Tri-Cities Airport acknowledged, said
Barry Trotter, the National Transportation Safety Board official
leading the investigation.
   ``There were no distress signals. All conversations were normal
two to three minutes before final impact,'' Trotter said of late
Tuesday night's crash.
   The British Aerospace Jetstream 31 slammed into a sagebrush
field short of a runway and burst into flames. The two crew members
and four passengers were killed.
   Trotter said investigators would try to determine whether ice
found at the wreckage site came from a wing of the airplane, a
19-passenger turboprop.
   Craig Belmondo, president of the United Express regional
airline, said it was too early to speculate on the cause of the
crash.
   The flight was en route from Seattle to Pasco via Yakima.
   United Express _ one of several similarly named commuter
airlines around the country _ serves as a feeder to United Airlines
and uses the United logo, but is separately owned.
   Federal investigators arrived in Pasco Wednesday and began
sifting through the wreckage. They planned to interview a tower
official who may have seen the crash, and appealed for any other
witnesses to come forward.
   The plane was built in Prestwick, Scotland in October 1987 and
delivered to United Express in December of that year, Belmondo
said. It had 5,000 hours of flight time when the crash occurred and
was in for its last maintenance inspection on Dec. 20, he said.
   The pilot, Capt. Barry Roberts, 38, had more than 11 years of
regional flying experience, including more than 660 hours in
Jetstream aircraft, Belmondo said.
   Co-pilot Doug McInroe, 25, joined United Express in August with
more than two years flying experience, Belmondo said.
   The plane wasn't equipped with the voice and flight-data
recorders that larger commercial airlines use to tape cockpit
conversations.
   United Express, owned by NPA Inc., is based in Pasco and serves
15 cities in Washington, Oregon, Idaho and Montana.
</TEXT>

</DOC>