<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0219 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0213EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-FederalReserve-Senate     12-21 0339</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Federal Reserve-Senate,0351</SECOND>
<HEAD>Panel Praises Fed's Independence</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVE SKIDMORE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Senate Banking Committee has defended the
independence of the Federal Reserve Board and praised the central
bank's inflation-fighting program.
   ``A suitable degree of independence for the Federal Reserve is
essential,'' the committee said Wednesday in a report to Vice
President Dan Quayle, adding, ``the Fed's current structure
appropriately provides some insulation from (political) pressures.''
   Reviewing the Fed's attempt to curtail inflation by slowing
economic growth just short of a recession, the committee said,
``This policy has been reasonably successful.''
   It also said the Fed's plan to depress growth slightly next year
in order to achieve modest reductions in inflation ``does not
appear unreasonable.''
   The report comes after several attack's on the Fed's
independence from Bush administration officials and members of the
House.
   President Bush and members of his Cabinet have criticized the
central bank for what they call its excessive concern with
inflation and dampening growth too much. Housing Secretary Jack
Kemp has said the administration and Congress should have more
influence over the Fed.
   He is backed by the chairman of the Joint Economic Committee,
Rep. Lee Hamilton, D-Ind., who introduced legislation earlier this
year which would force the Fed to operate more openly and consult
more closely with the administration.
   Earlier this month, House Banking Committee Chairman Henry B.
Gonzalez, D-Texas, said he would launch a major review of the Fed
next year.
   The Senate panel's report was signed by its chairman, Sen.
Donald W. Riegle Jr., D-Mich. Only one of the panel's 20 members
dissented, Sen. James Sasser, D-Tenn., who is chairman of the
Budget Committee.
   Sasser, in a written addition to the report, said the Fed, which
has eased its tight money policy since June, has been ``not nearly
aggressive enough'' in allowing interest rates to decline.
   ``I think that there is increasing evidence that we may be
sliding into a recession. If this is so, it will be the result of
the Fed's tightening,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>