<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0109 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1306EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-Iraq 550   12-22 0542</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Iraq, 550</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Planning to Resume Loans to Iraq</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RUTH SINAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bush administration plans to lift a
congressional ban of government loans to Iraq, a move likely to
antagonize lawmakers who are critical of Iraq's human rights abuses
and credit problems.
   Officials say President Bush will exercise his right to lift the
ban, imposed by Congress several months ago, on grounds of U.S.
national interests. The officials, who spoke on condition of
anonymity, said the move is expected within several weeks.
   U.S. oil companies and other businesses have exerted heavy
pressure on the administration to broaden trade ties with Iraq
since the 1988 end of its ruinous eight-year war with Iran. The
administration wants to increase its influence over the government
of Iraqi strongman Sadam Hussein, who commands one of the Middle
East's strongest and most proven armies, as well as the world's
second-largest proven oil reserves.
   However, the move may anger lawmakers who are expected to take
up debate over reports of recent Iraqi testing of two long-range
missiles when Congress returns of the holiday recess next month.
   Iraq announced the testing earlier this month, saying it had
also test-fired a rocket able to carry satellites into space. The
Pentagon confirmed the test-firings, but has declined to discuss it
further.
   U.S. officials say they are concerned by the implications of
such a missile program for the arms race in the Middle East, and
have raised their concerns with the Iraqis.
   Critics also say the administration failed to act against Iraq
for attacking its Kurdish minority with nerve and mustard gas last
year.
   Congress voted to suspend $200 million in annual short-term
credits to Iraq by the Export-Import Bank, a U.S. government
institution that promotes the export of American goods. To head off
a presidential veto and respond to pressure from U.S. businesses,
Congress agreed to incorporate the executive branch's right to a
waiver.
   ``But there were many up here who didn't like it and wanted a
flat-out prohibition on Iraq,'' said a congressional source who
spoke on condition he not be named.
   ``We couldn't do that. Iraq is a major untapped market for the
U.S. in the Middle East,'' said one official, also speaking on
condition of anonymity.
   Even with the credit problems, U.S. exports to Iraq nearly
doubled from 1987 to 1988, reaching $1.2 billion. For the first
nine months of 1989 exports totaled $909 million, mostly
agricultural commodities, according to Commerce Department
statistics.
   American oil imports from Iraq have risen sharply, from a daily
average of 83,000 barrels in 1987 to 345,000 barrels in 1988,
according to Energy Department figures. The year-end figures for
1989 are expected to show about a 40 percent increase over 1988.
   Iraq has run up a debt to foreign governments and banks
estimated at between $30 billion and $70 billion.
   In the long-run, Iraq's past performance and future oil capacity
make it a worthy credit risk. The government plans to increase its
daily oil output from 2.5 million barrels to 4 million once its oil
terminals, damaged in the war, are repaired.
   The Baghdad government is eager to attract U.S. business so it
can profit from American technology and build up its
export-oriented industries.
</TEXT>

</DOC>