<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0132 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1545EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Czechoslovakia-Parties 1stLd-Writethru   12-29 0597</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Czechoslovakia-Parties, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0591,0623</SECOND>
<HEAD>A Look at Czechoslovakia's Political Parties</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 9th graf, `The Socialist ...' to CORRECT name of previous
party to Czech Socialist, sted National Socialist; SUBS last graf to CORRECT
name of author to Hasek, sted Schweik.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Czechoslovakia, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ONDREJ HEJMA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As Czechoslovakia looks toward
free elections next year for the first time in four decades, 11 new
political parties have emerged.
   Those already established are expected to attract large numbers
of new members as people take advantage of the right to join
political parties denied by Communists for 41 years.
   The parties:
   _ Communist Party. After four decades of a virtual monopoly on
power, enshrined in Czechoslovakia's Constitution, the Communists
are by far the best organized. However, the party is on the verge
of bankruptcy and has lost more than 66,000 of its 1.7 million
members since the peaceful revolution began in mid-November.
   During the decades of Communist control, only four small
political parties survived, the Socialist Party, the People's Party
and two parties in Slovakia considered relics of Czechoslovakia's
prewar democracy.
   All of them recognized Communist rule in their statutes and
cooperated with the Party.
   Within the party is a potential splinter group, the Democratic
Forum of Communists. This group of reform-minded party members is
organizing nationally and has threatened to leave the party at its
forthcoming congress in May 199O.
   Such a break would further reduce the Communist Party's already
greatly diminished political influence.
   _ The Socialist Party evolved from the Czech Socialist Party
after the Communist takeover in 1948. It has 18 deputies in the
350-member parliament, and publishes the widely read daily Svobodne
Slovo.
   Two of the new government ministers are Socialists.
   Membership in the Socialist Party has stagnated at about 16,000
but in the current political landscape the party is expected to
attract new members.
   _ The People's Party traditionally attracts Catholics and other
religious Czechoslovaks. It has 47,000 members and holds 19 seats
in parliament.
   Two members of the new cabinet are members of the People's Party.
   Before the revolution, both the Socialists and the People's
Party were docile partners of the Communists with membership quotas
keeping them out of real competition.
   But they are emerging as viable contenders for the upcoming
elections, distancing themselves from the Communists and siding
with the democratic opposition. The People's Party was the party to
propose Havel for president in parliament.
   It is difficult to estimate membership in the smaller political
parties and groups, as the political terrain shifts with new
parties emerging daily. It is unlikely that any will be able to
organize and attract a large number of members before the first
elections.
   Among the smaller parties are:
   _ The Czechoslovak Social-Democratic Party.
   _ Czechoslovak Democratic Initiative.
   _ The Green Party.
   _ The Czechoslovak Agricultural Party.
   _ The Christian Democratic Party.
   _ The Trend for the Third Millenium.
   _ The Permanent Opposition for Democracy.
   _ The Party of Free Democrats, created Friday.
   The strongest political force in the country, however, is not a
political party.
   Civic Forum, founded by former dissident and new President
Vaclav Havel, is an association of former dissidents, intellectuals
and democratic reformers.
   Havel has said that anyone who feels like a member of Civic
Forum is one and that after free elections are held there will be
no more need for the group.
   Finally, illustrating that these days anyone can form a party,
The Party of Mild Progress Within the Constraints of the Law was
revived by Jaroslav Hasek, author of ``Good Soldier Schweik''.
</TEXT>

</DOC>