<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0215 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0634EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DigestBriefs     12-22 0896</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Digest Briefs,0928</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush says the United States will
hunt for deposed dictator Manuel Antonio Noriega for ``as long as
it takes'' to bring him to justice, at the same time thousands of
U.S. troops settle in on Panamanian soil to help restore order in a
chaotic country.
   ``This operation is not over, but it's pretty well wrapped up,''
Bush said Thursday at a news conference that coincided with return
of the first bodies of U.S. soldiers killed in the massive strike
in Panama.
   ``General Noriega is no longer in power. He no longer commands
the instruments of government or the forces of repression that he's
used for so long to brutalize the Panamanian people,'' Bush said.
   At the same time, the president said the U.S. military operation
was ``open-ended as far as going after Noriega, open-ended as far
as restoration of order in Panama,'' where looters were hauling
away goods from virtually every shop in Panama City. Defense
Secretary Dick Cheney said a sizeable troop presence would remain
until a ``condition of normalcy'' had returned.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S.-backed President Guillermo
Endara, promising ``peace and justice in Panama,'' is moving to
establish his government by organizing a new national police force
and making his first handful of appointments.
   Under heavy U.S. guard, Endara and his two vice presidents met
Thursday with members of the national legislative assembly. Later,
he said he hoped to organize a new police force to take over within
a month from U.S. military forces now seeking to impose order and
searching for ousted dictator Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   ``I think we can lift up the country and ... do our duty in
making peace and quiet in Panama, peace and justice in Panama with
Noriega in hiding,'' Endara said in a telephone interview with
ABC's ``Nightline'' program Thursday night.
   ``I hope in a month we can put up a police force, a public force
good enough to keep peace and order in all Panama. And then the
U.S. forces would leave according to what Mr. Bush promised us,''
Endara said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush is preparing to lift a ban on
federal government loans to Iraq, a move expected to rile lawmakers
opposed to the country's human rights abuses, heavy indebtedness
and ballistic missile program, administration officials say.
   Bush is expected to invoke a provision allowing him to lift the
ban _ imposed by Congress several months ago _ on grounds of U.S.
national interests, according to the officials who spoke Thursday
on condition of anonymity.
   The United States, which reestablished ties with Iraq in 1984,
has been seeking to increase its influence over the government of
strongman Sadam Hussein.
   The administration is especially eager to expand trade with
Hussein, who commands a powerful military force and the world's
second largest proven oil reserves.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   UNDATED _ A record-breaking cold snap was beginning to sap
energy supplies and posed perils for the citrus industry, even as
it threatened the lives of the homeless and impoverished elderly
from the Rockies to the East Coast.
   Thursday night, the longest of the year, was ``one not fit for
man or beast,'' said Hugh Crowther of the National Weather Service
in Kansas City.
   Temperatures sank even lower today _ the first full day of
winter _ following a day that saw wind chill readings of 89 degrees
below zero at Dickinson, N.D., the mercury steady at 40 below at
noon in Havre, Mont., and temperatures about zero as far south as
Tennessee and Alabama.
   The weather service was predicting bone-chilling weather at
least until Sunday.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Successes and failures in the war against AIDS
show that concern for patients' rights is essential if health
authorities hope to stem the epidemic, the director of the World
Health Organization's AIDS program says.
   In an interview Thursday, Dr. Jonathan Mann said many of the
discriminatory laws put in place during the initial panic earlier
in the '80s have been repealed as governments discovered the laws
were impeding efforts to fight the disease's spread.
   ``We made a big discovery during the 1980s that ranks right up
there with the discovery of the virus and the modes of spread,''
Mann said by telephone from Geneva. ``And that discovery is that to
fight this global epidemic of infectious disease, you must also
fight against prejudice and discrimination.''
   Health officials have been successful in curbing risky sexual
behavior among homosexual men in San Francisco and among female
prostitutes in Nairobi, Kenya and Peru, among other places, Mann
said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Women with furs are facing a new threat on the
streets _ not muggers, but animal-rights activists who have adopted
confrontational tactics in their fight to mothball the fur industry.
   Women strolling down the street in fur coats report they've been
jeered at, sprayed with ketchup or red paint, even had their coats
slashed.
   ``We're encouraging people to go up to fur wearers and to say
something to them,'' said Dana Stuchell, national director of
Trans-Species Unlimited, one of the country's leading animal-rights
groups.
   ``Some people are extremely mild, some people are more abrasive,
but the point is to let them know how you feel about their fur coat
and to explain that animals had to suffer and die for it.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>