<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0182 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1334EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-YE--Quotes'89 1stLd-Writethru b0589 12-19 0870</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-YE--Quotes '89, 1st Ld-Writethru, b0589,0929</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv00</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release in Year-End Editions</HEAD>
<HEAD>The Voices of a Year to Remember</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Previous version was partly unedited; RESTORES editing throughout.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   It was a year packed with news, news that came to life in the
voices of those who made it. Here is a sampling of 1989, in its own
words:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``I've waited for this day all my life. Coming here, it's like
learning to walk again.''
   Stefan Needack, 27-year-old carpenter from East Berlin, on his
first visit to West Berlin.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``I am an example of the small person who can do great things. I
am proof of the adage that faith can move mountains. I believe in
freedom and liberty and in democracy and I didn't have an army.''
   Solidarity leader Lech Walesa during his visit to the United
States.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``I think we have a little problem here.''
   Exxon Valdez captain Joseph Hazelwood alerting the Coast Guard
his tanker had struck a reef.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``The banishment for life of Pete Rose from baseball is the sad
end of a sorry episode. One of the game's greatest players has
engaged in a variety of acts which have stained the game, and he
must now live with the consequences of those acts.''
   Baseball Commissioner A. Bartlett Giamatti.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``If you strike a cop, you go to jail.''
   Beverly Hills Municipal Judge Charles Rubin, sentencing Zsa Zsa
Gabor to a three-day jail term for slapping a policeman.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``The gringo piranhas want to do away with me.''
   Panamanian Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega, blaming the United
States for a failed coup attempt.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``Instead of doing something about it, we were like a bunch of
Keystone Kops running around bumping into each other.''
   Sen. Jesse Helms after U.S. forces stood aside in Panama as the
anti-Noriega coup failed.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``It didn't sound like a train like everybody says it does. I
lived near a train track. It did not sound like a train. It sounded
more like a jet aircraft at very close range.''
   Jeff Bryant describing a tornado that passed near his home south
of Atlanta.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``I've never been in one. I hope I'm never in one again. It's
scarcely a light summer breeze.''
   Charleston, S.C., Mayor Joseph P. Riley Jr., speaking from a
flooded City Hall command post as Hurricane Hugo pounded the
Atlantic coast.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``It kills you. It just kills you. We all have families, you
know. ...The adults are no problem. But the kids... ''
   Firefighter Lee Kraft, fighting tears after pulling the bodies
of a 6-year-old girl and her mother out of the collapsed Nimitz
Freeway in Oakland, Calif., after the earthquake.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``Those of us who do have a religion are sick of being saps for
money-grubbing preachers and priests.''
   U.S. District Judge Robert Potter, sentencing evangelist Jim
Bakker to 45 years in prison for defrauding followers.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``Even if Salman Rushdie repents and becomes the most pious man
of all time, it is incumbent on every Moslem to employ everything
he's got, his life and wealth, to send him to hell.''
   Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini on the death sentence imposed
against Salman Rushdie, author of ``The Satanic Verses.''
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``Don't forget the baby. That's all the Catholic Church is
saying to America.''
   Archbishop John May of St. Louis, issuing a rallying cry against
abortion in an address to the National Conference of Catholic
Bishops.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``They don't get it. For the men, it's all hypothetical.''
   Rep. Patricia Schroeder after the House sustained President
Bush's veto of a bill allowing federal funds for abortions for
women who have been raped or are the victims of incest.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``I figured that as long as I was going to go to jail anyway, I
would help a few people with the time I had left.''
   Marilyn Harrell, ``Robin HUD,'' private escrow agent indicted on
charges of diverting $5.5 million of government funds in HUD
scandal. Harrell said she used the money to help feed, clothe and
house the poor.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``Those of you who depend on cocaine have created the largest,
most vicious criminal enterprise the world has known.''
   President Virgilio Barco of Colombia in an English-language
address delivered to U.S. television networks.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``I've been on this job for 25 years, and I've never seen so
much dope in one place. I couldn't believe it.''
   John M. Zienter, U.S. drug agent in Los Angeles, after 20 tons
of cocaine was seized in the world's biggest cocaine bust.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``Do you think this is a bouquet of roses hanging under the
wing?''
   American U.N. Ambassador Vernon A. Walters, presenting blurred
photographs showing what he said were heavily armed Libyan MiGs
that U.S. warplanes shot down, reportedly in self-defense.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``It means that somehow the universe is comprehensible, that
it's not a total mystery, that it can be grasped by the human
mind.''
   Physicist Michael Riordan on findings by scientists that the
universe contains no more than three fundamental types of matter.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``The world is quiet today, Mr. President.''
   Lt. Gen. Colin Powell, offering departing President Reagan his
last assessment of the world's trouble spots.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Release in Year-End Editions</NOTE>

</DOC>