<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0947EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-PentagonText 1stAdd   12-20 1076</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Pentagon Text, 1st Add,1,000</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON: assigned missions.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Let me turn now to Task Force Semper Fidelis, which is
essentially a Marine rifle company and a light armored Infantry
company, Marine as well as some additional MPs assigned to Task
Force Semper Fidelis.
   Their principal mission was to secure the Bridge of the
Americas, insure the security of Howard Air Force Base and environs
around Howard Air Force Base. Task Force Semper Fi has completed
their mission successfully.
   Let me turn now to Task Force Red, which is off to the west down
by Rio Hato. For those of you who were here on the third of
October, you'll recall that that was the location from which the
7th Company launched their operation to come to the assistance of
Gen. Noriega during the coup attempt in October.
   Because of the criticality of that facility as well as two
companies located there, a Ranger battalion parachute assaulted
onto that location at H-hour, just about 1 a.m.
   All the things I'm describing so far all took place
simultaneously about H-hour, 1 a.m. In the course of their
activities there, they succeeded in neutralizing Rio Hato. It is
under our control. Some of the members of the 6th and 7th Company
have dispersed away from Rio Hato, but we also took a number of
prisoners. So it is neutralized and Task Force Red has accomplished
its mission and is sweeping up in the area.
   If I could now turn into the Task Force Bayonet area in the
central section, the narrowest zone there. Task Force Bayonet
consisted of a Mechanized battalion, the force of the 6th
Mechanized. It also was supported by a platoon of light tanks as
well as the 5th battalion of the 87th Infantry.
   And the mission of Task Force Bayonet was two-fold really: to
provide security for our major facilities in the Task Force Bayonet
area of operations and the principal combat mission performed by
the Mechanized battalion was to seize the Comandancia, the
headquarters of the PDF, Gen. Noriega's headquarters, and that was
also done beginning at about one in the morning.
   They have accomplished that mission. The headquarters has been
reduced. There has been considerable burning. I'm not quite sure
how much of it has been burned out, but there has been quite a bit
of fire down there. But they, for the most part _ most part have
accomplished their mission.
   There is sporadic firing that continues in the area, and some of
the PDF members who were in the Comandancia have now slipped out
and are mixing in with the general population. And so there will
still be a need for mopping up and stability operations in support
of the new government.
   The forces that were opposing them in the vicinity of the
Comandancia are shown under the Comandancia listing, First Public
Order Company, Second Public Order Company, and elements of the
Sixth and Seventh Infantry, which I mentioned were out at Rio Hato.
   Then we also mentioned that as part of Task Force Bayonet,
another unit was flown across the entrance of the canal in order to
block the Fifth Infantry Company which is at Fort Amador, and at
the moment there is continuing work down there to completely
neutralize the Fifth Infantry Company.
   But for the most part, Task Force Bayonet has accomplished its
mission and is undertaking stability and sweep-up operations.
   Let me turn now to the East to Task Force Red. Task Force Red
consisted of another Ranger battalion which parachutists assaulted
in at H-hour. Their mission was to take over the international
airfield, get it ready for follow-on forces coming from the 82nd
Airborne, and begin to block access for Battalion 2000, which as
you know, also played an instrumental role in the events of Oct. 3.
   The Rangers landed on the ground, quickly seized the airport,
began to put out patrols to the East. They were assisted, and I
might add that throughout the area of operations, the special
forces group elements belonging to Southern Command have been
performing reconnaissance and surveillance, and some of those
reconnaissance and surveillance efforts cut out to the Pacora River
Bridge early and blocked that.
   here was some fighting out there but no main elements of PDF
units came down the road in the direction of the city, and the
Rangers are now out in that location as well.
   Beginning 55 minutes after H-hour, or about 1:55 this morning,
the first element of the 82 Airborne Division Ready Brigade
arrived, 10 C-141s, and they conducted a parachute assault onto the
international airfield in that vicinity.
   Ten C-141s arrived several hours later and at 0515 the second
half of the 82 Airborne Division parachuted in. And their mission
is sort of depicted by the arrows. They will move, one arrow going
out to make sure battalion 2000 stays where it is. Two other arrows
coming back into the direction of the city to assist with stability
operations and make sure the First Infantry Company and the Cavalry
Squadron you see depicted, remain neutralized.
   In order to continue our stability operations and to make sure
we really accomplish our mission of protecting Americans and
assisting the newly inaugurated government, additional forces are
being brought down from Fort Ord, Calif., the 7th Infantry
division, a brigade, and as I mentioned earlier, the 16th MP
brigade will be sending additional elements down.
   In the process of these operations we also took special actions
to immobilize the PDF navy. They have a small fleet of boats which
were immobilized. And we also took actions to immobilize aircraft
that could have been used for escape purposes.
   All of these actions that I have mentioned were marvelously
supported by Air Force and Army gunships; magnificent support from
the military airlift command, Tactical Air Command, and refueling
tankers from the Strategic Air Command, Special Operations units as
well as Special Forces reconnaissance and surveillance units.
   Let me mention a few specific events that I know are of interest
to you. There are reports of hostages. We are chasing these
reports. In some cases hostages were taken and then released.
   And I don't want to go into any numbers or details because this
is an ongoing operation, except to let you know that we are looking
into every one of these and we believe we have adequate resources
in the area to deal with that situation.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>MORE</BYLINE>

</DOC>