<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0307EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-US-PanamaStatement 1stAdd   12-20 0509</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-US-Panama Statement, 1st Add,a0474,440</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHN: prosperous Panama.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Q. Has Noriega been captured yet?
   A. This operation began at 1 o'clock. The situation on the
ground is such that we are not at liberty a this point to comment
on the military undertaking.
   The operation is ongoing. We don't know how long it will take.
But that is our ultimate objective. It has not happened at this
time.
   Q. On what legal basis was this operation undertaken?
   A. The legal basis was: First of all, the president's
responsibility and duty to protect the lives of American citizens.
We have laid out in the past the number of threats to American
citizens and to U.S. servicemen. There have been literally hundreds
of cases of harassment, of abuse and of situations that have caused
us to believe very greatly that there is a threat to American
citizens, there is a threat to our rights under the canal treaty,
and the president has acted on that basis.
   Q. Was the president acting under intelligence reports that this
operation has a guarantee or a certainty of success?
   A. The certainty of an undertaking like this is something that
we obviously have confidence in. We would not undertake a military
action that we did not believe was well planned and had a high
degree and high chance of success.
   Q. Is this being done in conjunction with any of the Panamanian
Defense Forces? Are any of the Noriega forces joining in the U.S.
effort to oust Noriega?
   A. As I indicated, this operation began just less than a half an
hour ago. There are no indications of those kinds of changes in the
conflict that I can report at this time.
   Q. Was there any planning in conjunction with the Panamanian
Defense Forces or is this solely a U.S. operation?
   A. I can't comment on those kind of planning operations.
   Q. The Organization of American States is urging the president
not to do this. He has gone ahead and done it. Have you talked to
the OAS(Organization of American States)? Have you had any change
of heart from the OAS, any indications of how they're going to feel
about this?
   A. The OAS, as you will recall, considered this matter
considerably following the May elections in Panama. Those
elections, as you also know, were thwarted by Gen. Noriega. All of
America saw the bloody shirt and body of Billy Ford and the others
who were beaten by Gen. Noriega in the aftermath of that election.
And the OAS was very forceful in their consideration of this issue.
And they sent a mission to Panama to try to urge the termination of
the Noriega regime. And they passed a resolution urging that it be
ended by Sept. 1. This evening, President Bush, Vice President
Quayle and Secretary of State Baker are calling various leaders of
Latin American countries, members of the OAS as well as allied
leaders and others. We believe we do have support of the OAS and
the Latin American countries.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>