<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0123 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1754EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-Switzerland 1stLd-Writethru a0619righttofreespeech.
12-27 0382</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Switzerland, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0619,0391</SECOND>
<HEAD>PRECEDE BERN</HEAD>
<HEAD>France, Switzerland Freeze Noriega Bank Accounts</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with France freezing about $3.3 million
of Noriega money. No pickup</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Authorities froze French bank accounts Wednesday
holding about $3.3 million under the names of Panama's Gen. Manuel
Antonio Noriega and members of his family. Switzerland
provisionally froze two bank accounts there.
   U.S. troops invaded Panama last week and deposed Noriega as
leader. Noriega, who is wanted on U.S. drug-trafficking and
money-laundering charges, is penned up in the Vatican Embassy in
Panama City.
   Justice Department chief spokesman David Runkel said in
Washington that U.S. officials believe Noriega hid at least $10
million in bank accounts in Switzerland, France, Luxembourg and
Britain.
   Judge Patrick Fievet of the Paris Tribunal blocked the Noriegas
from having access to accounts at the Banque Nationale de Paris and
the Credit Industriel et Commerciale.
   He acted under a warrant issued Friday charging unidentified
people with drug-trafficking and taking part in international
financial operations related to illegal drugs.
   Investigators said the banks may have been used as transit
points for funds destined for Luxembourg or Switzerland.
   The French customs and anti-drug investigation appears to have
been based on a tip from the United States.
   In Bern, a statement issued by the Swiss Justice Ministry said a
U.S. request to Switzerland charged Noriega with illegal drug
trafficking by giving ``logistic support'' to Colombian drug lords'
shipments to the United States.
   It said that according to U.S. authorities, some of the money
Noriega received from the Colombians was paid into accounts in
Switzerland.
   Ministry spokesman Joerg Kistler said the U.S.request included
``precise information'' on two accounts in banks in Zurich and
Geneva. Authorities ordered a ``precautionary'' freeze on the
accounts. Kistler refused to elaborate.
   Runkel said that based on records seized in Panama, U.S.
officials think they can document that the money in the overseas
accounts stemmed from Noriega drug dealing.
   Leaders of the so-called Group of Seven industrialized nations
agreed at a Paris summit in July to cooperate more closely against
the illegal drug trade and money-laundering.
   Noriega would be the biggest target of a joint investigation
since the agreement.
   The G-7 countries include the United States, Britain, Canada,
France, Japan, Italy, and West Germany.
</TEXT>

</DOC>