<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1354EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Storms-ColdRdp 3rdLd-Writethru a0527 12-19 0796</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Storms-Cold Rdp, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0527,0813</SECOND>
<HEAD>Snow Hits Midwest; Ice Clogs Mississippi River</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 14 grafs to UPDATE with two more weather-related
deaths; snow in Midwest, more records broken. PICKS UP 13th graf, `With
even ...' </HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto AX1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GARTIES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Snow whitened the Midwest today, sleet put the Deep South on the
skids and ice clogged the Mississippi and Missouri rivers as much
of the nation remained in the grip of an cold wave blamed for 40
deaths.
   ``Icky, icky, icky,'' was how Duplin County, N.C., sheriff's
dispatcher Jennie Myrick described it this morning. ``We have
sleet, lovely sleet. We have accumulation of about an inch on most
of the roads.''
   A wintry storm bedeviled the Deep South on Monday with sleet and
freezing rain, and another onslaught of cold air from Canada
advanced through the Plains today. In Illinois this morning, Peoria
and Springfield received about 4 inches of snow, with an inch
reported in the Chicago area.
   In Colorado, motorists slipping and sliding along icy,
snow-packed roads deluged the Rocky Mountain AAA Auto Club with 100
to 150 calls an hour for tow trucks.
   Ski resort operators, meanwhile, were a very happy lot.
   ``We're set up for the rest of the season,'' said Barb Jennings,
spokeswoman at a Steamboat Springs ski lodge, where storms have
dumped 110 inches of powder in the last nine days. ``We're ready to
do some powder skiing.''
   On Monday, the storm iced roads from Mississippi to the
Carolinas. There were scores of minor accidents, and traffic came
to a standstill in many areas. ``If you had a cardiac now it could
be a matter of living or dying because of the roads,'' said police
dispatcher Ronnie Toliver in Little Rock, Ark.
   The cold has been blamed for nine traffic deaths and 31 other
fatalities since Friday, among them Atlanta Falcons player Brad
Beckman, who was killed Monday in a crash on icy Interstate 85
outside Atlanta.
   The fatalities also included a homeless man who set himself on
fire in a New York City subway station while using a hotplate to
keep warm, and an 86-year-old found dead, apparently of exposure,
in the driveway of her Birmingham, Mich., home.
   In Chicago, a man got stuck in the ventilator shaft at a
restaurant, apparently during a burglary attempt, and died of
exposure, police said.
   In Apalachin, N.Y., a woman accused of pouring water on her
7-year-old foster daughter and leaving her outside as the
temperature dipped to 5 degrees was charged Monday with murder.
Police said Lisa Braden, 36, put the girl outside as punishment.
   Dickinson, N.D., reported a record 23-below zero this morning.
Bismarck reached minus 34, two degrees above the record. Denver's
Stapleton International Airport reported a record 10 below-zero
reading, one degree below the previous record set in 1924.
   In Youngstown, Ohio, the temperature dipped to minus 3 this
morning, breaking a record of 2 below set in 1963. Monday's reading
of 12 below also set a record.
   Record-breaking cold gripped at least 11 cities Monday,
including Pittsburgh, minus 7, and Lexington, Ky., 1 below. The
outlook for most of the country is for below-average temperatures
for the next month or so, according to the National Weather Service.
   With even the desert Southwest expecting relatively chilly
60-degree temperatures, South Florida is the only hot spot. Miami's
forecast called for highs in the 80s today.
   Though winter doesn't officially begin until Thursday, ice
forced closure of a 200-mile stretch of the Mississippi River to
barge traffic from Cairo, Ill., to St. Louis. The ice compounded
navigation problems posed by low water that has plagued barge
operators because of the summer's drought, the Coast Guard said in
announcing the closure Monday night.
   This is the slowest time of year for shipping on the Mississippi.
   The Missouri River turned to ice for the 75 miles between Blair,
Neb., just north of Omaha, and Sioux City, Iowa, the weather
service reported.
   The ice jam began late Friday and has continued to grow.
Officials feared that the freeze could cause problems for
communities that pump their water from the river, and Weather
Service hydrologist Roy Osugi didn't hold out hope for an early
thaw.
   ``Nothing is going to bust it up except warmer weather,'' Osugi
said. ``We think it's going to stay in place at least this week
because it's going to stay very cold.''
   In St. Joseph, Mo., officials activated a new emergency pump as
a precaution to keep water flowing to the city.
   Some merchants welcomed the chill, saying it drove people to
warm indoor malls and shops.
   ``Were selling lots of mufflers, outerwear, coats and gloves,''
said Robert Spevak, senior vice president at the Alexander's
department store in New York.
</TEXT>

</DOC>