<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0224 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1341EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s e BC-APN--TheaterWeek Adv31   12-18 0906</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Theater Week, Adv 31,0946</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 31</HEAD>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<HEAD>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 1 b&amp;w photo.
ColorFoto subscribers get 1 35mm slide.)</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY CAMPBELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Newsfeatures Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   What's that sweet Karate Kid doing now? He's
changing his image in a big way.
   Actor Ralph Macchio, who played the title role in three ``Karate
Kid'' movies, is on stage playing a character so nasty that when
another character knocks him out with a bucket of ice, the audience
cheers. The play, at off-Broadway's Westside Arts Theater, is
``Only Kidding!'', set in the world of stand-up comedy.
   Macchio did New York theater once before, in 1986, in ``Cuba and
his Teddy Bear,'' which he calls ``probably the most exciting
moment of my career.'' It opened off-Broadway and moved to
Broadway. One big attraction for him was playing Robert DeNiro's
son.
   This time the big attraction is a chance to change his image.
The Karate Kid brought Macchio to the public's attention. ``But it
has made it difficult in trying to prove myself as something other
than that character,'' he says. ``I've got my work cut out.'' He
says that casting directors are apt to think ``angelic guys'' when
they think of Ralph Macchio.
   ``This is a step to chopping through that wall.''
   Sitting on the set of ``Only Kidding!'', looking younger than
his 28 years and wearing the wedding ring he takes off before
playing an unmarried young comedian, Macchio says: ``I do not
complain. Things could be a heck of a lot worse. Sometimes I think
there isn't a better thing that could have happened (getting the
Karate Kid part) and at times I feel there isn't a tougher thing
that could have happened.''
   In ``Only Kidding!'' Macchio is half of a young, struggling
comedy team. Then he breaks with his partner, and ties up with a
mob-connected manager for whom sleazy would be a compliment. In Act
2, he arrives, famous and stoned, for a television talk show. He
demands that an older, making-a-comeback comedian be bumped from
the program. But righteousness prevails, and Macchio's character
gets chilled out with a bucket of ice. And the older comic gets his
chance. Curtain.
   Paul Provenza, who played the part when ``Only Kidding!'' opened
in April, had been a stand-up comedian. Macchio's career began in
movies, in ``Up the Academy'' in 1980. ``I've never done stand-up
comedy, not outside of my own house. I always expressed a sense of
humor. Or attempted to.
   ``I'm learning it as I go. Being with this cast is like doing
stand-up comedy, even backstage. You've got to keep up with them,
especially being the new kid on the block.''
   The role came up, Macchio says, after he told his agent he was
interested in doing a play. ``I said I didn't want to be 17 again.
I didn't want to be a student of a mentor, or such a nice guy.
   ``He said Paul was leaving this show. My wife and I came to see
it. I had a great time. Initially I was going to say I couldn't do
it. Paul was so perfect. We're different types. Did I want to fill
in for somebody else?''
   He saw it again and decided the play was timely, as comedy clubs
more than rock clubs are ``an '80s thing.'' He figured it would be
a challenge. He started in mid-November.
   ``I've seen characters like the one I play, sad to say,'' he
says. ``They'll do anything, step over their mother, to have a
chance at `The Johnny Carson Show.' They have the fear that the
laughs won't be there. Or when the laughs are there, it's all in
life that matters.
   ``That's the gist of the guy I play. Desperate is the key word.
Tragic also.
   ``When you first meet him, he is offensive in certain things.
But he seems like a likable guy. He is so desperate and so afraid,
he does so many offensive things, he becomes quite loathsome.
   ``When I'm playing the scenes, as nasty as he gets, as hurtful
and angry, there is something about him I like. I feel bad for him.
When he is out there, when I say those lines, I'm believing him.
   ``It is exciting to play a role like that, to be cheered against
as opposed to always being cheered for.''
   Macchio grew up on Long Island, learning to tap-dance, enjoying
school plays and talent contests. ``My mouth was always going.''
   Macchio's wife of 2{ years is a nurse. They make their home on
Long Island. He lived in Los Angeles for 18 months while shooting
the ``Eight Is Enough'' TV series.
   His first noteworthy movie part was as an abused kid in ``The
Outsiders,'' directed by Francis Ford Coppola in 1983. Patrick
Swayze, Emilio Estevez, Matt Dillon, Rob Lowe and Tom Cruise also
were in the cast.
   Macchio didn't expect the following year's ``The Karate Kid'' to
be a hit. ``I thought it was too corny,'' he says. ``Some of the
scenes were just so sweet. That's why I'm not a studio head.''
   After his current stint among the stand-up comedians of ``Only
Kidding!'' he'd like to make another film. ``I think that would be
the right move,'' he says. ``I'm rummaging, trying to find one that
would be best to do.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>

</DOC>