<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0110 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1300EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-BusCrashTrial 4thLd-Writethru a0617 12-22 0872</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bus Crash Trial, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0617,0893</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Jury Recommends 16-Year Prison Sentence in Church Bus Crash</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 2 grafs after 6th graf, `The jury...' to UPDATE with
reaction from victim's father.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto XCRL1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHARLES WOLFE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CARROLLTON, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A jury today recommended a 16-year prison
sentence for the man convicted of causing a fiery crash that killed
27 people on a church bus in the nation's worst drunken-driving
accident.
   Under Kentucky law, Larry Mahoney would have to spend eight
years in prison before he could be considered for parole. He was
tried on 27 counts of murder, which carried a life sentence, but
the jury convicted him Thursday of 27 counts of second-degree
manslaughter, lesser charge.
   Mahoney, 36, was composed as he stood to hear Judge Charles
Satterwhite read each of the sentence recommendations, but he
appeared to have tears welling in his eyes by the time the judge
concluded.
   Satterwhite must schedule a formal sentencing. He could give
Mahoney a lighter sentence than the jury recommended but cannot
exceed the jury's recommendation.
   The jury recommended 16 years of a possible 20-year sentence on
each of 12 counts of first-degree assault. It recommended maximum
prison terms of 10 years on each of 27 counts of second-degree
manslaughter, five years on each of 27 counts of first-degree
wanton endangerment and one year on each of 14 counts of
second-degree wanton endangerment, a misdemeanor.
   The jury then exercised its option of recommending that the
sentences run concurrently. The jury could have recommended
consecutive sentences in any possible combination.
   The recommendation was ``a big letdown'' for families of the
victims, said Bill Nichols, whose only child, 17-year-old William
Joseph Nichols Jr., was killed.
   ``Those people don't know what we're going through and I hope to
God they never have to,'' Nichols said. ``I've forgiven Larry
Mahoney, but he's got to pay for his crime and eight years is not
enough.''
   At a sentencing hearing Thursday, Mahoney had pleaded for a
chance to atone, saying he could warn schoolchildren of the dangers
of drinking and driving.
   The prosecutor, during the sentencing hearing, said Mahoney
should draw a long prison sentence because his victims, 24 of them
children, ``will never get the opportunity to ... talk to other
children.''
   Mahoney, a chemical plant worker, was driving on the wrong side
of Interstate 71 near Carrollton on May 14, 1988, when his pickup
collided with the bus. Autopsies showed the resulting fire, not the
crash, killed the victims.
   Mahoney also was convicted on 12 counts of first-degree assault,
for the children who were badly burned in the fire; on 27 counts of
first-degree wanton endangerment, representing others who escaped
the bus; and 14 counts of second-degree wanton endangerment, for
motorists who had to dodge his truck.
   He was acquitted of a 42nd wanton-endangerment charge.
   The penalty for first-degree assault is 10 to 20 years in
prison. Wanton endangerment in the first degree is a felony,
punishable by one to five years in prison, and a misdemeanor in the
second degree, punishable by up to a year in jail and a $500 fine.
   The final conviction was for drunken driving and the jury set
Mahoney's punishment at 30 days in jail and a $500 fine.
   Defense attorneys had acknowledged that Mahoney was drinking on
the day of the accident, but they argued that a defective bus
design was the primary cause of the deaths, and that he had been
tricked into drunkenness.
   The bus was a 1977 model former school bus bought by the
Radcliff First Assembly of God church in Radcliff, Ky.
   In the sentencing hearing after the verdict, Mahoney took the
witness stand and told the jury he intended, after prison, to visit
schools to tell students ``never to drink and drive.''
   ``I know God kept me alive for a reason,'' he said.
   ``If I just save one life,'' Mahoney said, beginning to lose his
composure, ``at least that will be one life saved.''
   Mahoney later sobbed, as did his parents, sisters and other
relatives and some on the jury as Russell Baldani, one of Mahoney's
lawyers, pleaded for leniency.
   Baldani asked the jury to recommend 10-year sentences on the
assault charges and to exercise its option of ordering all
sentences to run concurrently. Mahoney would be eligible for parole
consideration after five years.
   Special prosecutor Paul Richwalsky, visibly disappointed by the
jury's refusal to convict Mahoney of murder, scoffed at the plea.
   ``For crime, there must be punishment,'' Richwalsky said. ``I am
sorry, (Mahoney) is sorry. But there are 27 people dead, 24 of them
children. They will never get the opportunity to go around and talk
to other children. ... They will never get the opportunity to
repent and atone.''
   The victims' lives were worth more than five to 10 years in
prison, Richwalsky said.
   Neither time nor Mahoney's conviction has healed the victims'
families' wounds, said one parent who attended a Radcliff First
Assembly of God board meeting Thursday night.
   ``I think some of us have put our lives together and can cope
with it now, but it's never over,'' said Jacob Pearman, whose
brother, John, drove the bus struck by Mahoney's pickup and was
killed.
</TEXT>

</DOC>