<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0002EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HousingPlan     12-28 0411</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Housing Plan,0423</SECOND>
<HEAD>State Proposes `Instant Housing' Plan</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARTFORD, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A glut of unsold condominiums around
Connecticut could provide ``instant housing'' for families with low
or moderate incomes, state Housing Commissioner John F. Papandrea
said Wednesday.
   He proposed that his agency help non-profit corporations and
housing authorities acquire the units using grants or loans from
his department. He said entire developments, parts of developments
and even individual condos would be considered for inclusion in the
program.
   The non-profit sponsors then would sell or rent the units to
families with incomes at or below 100 percent of the area median
for rental housing and at or below 135 percent of the area median
for ownership.
   Papandrea said the goal is to get as many as 500 condos sold
under the program.
   He called it ``a unique opportunity'' for his department to help
low- and moderate-income residents.
   ``It's not a bailout of developers, or of banks holding
construction mortgages in default. We will openly consider prices
that are below market rate,'' he said.
   ``We're looking for the most favorable deals to benefit the
greatest number of people (while using) the least amount of state
funds,'' the commissioner said at a news conference. ``Connecticut
is faced with a severe shortage of affordable housing. There are
thousands of ill-housed families throughout the state.''
   Jude D. Brennan, president of the 17,000-member Connecticut
Association of Realtors, said he hoped the program would not
compete with other state housing programs that have proven
beneficial to Connecticut families.
   But, he said, ``we simply do not know enough of the details of
the new program to make an informed judgment.''
   Department officials said the program is intended to help meet a
goal of providing 3,000 new units by the end of next year for
families now unable to afford the rental or home-buying markets.
The officials said there are thousands of vacant condominiums for
sale in the state.
   The criteria for selecting the condominiums, in addition to
price and local housing needs, would be to provide affordable units
in suburbs and small towns.
   The Connecticut Housing Finance Authority would provide
low-interest mortgages to some of the families who buy the units
from the housing authorities or non-profit agencies.
   The state treasurer's office is expected to coordinate the
involvemet of banks or other lenders in providing either mortgage
or down-payment assistance. The lenders also would provide loans to
non-profit agencies to finance the purchase of the vacant
condominiums.
</TEXT>

</DOC>