<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0133 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1404EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-GNP     12-20 0784</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-GNP,800</SECOND>
<HEAD>Economy Continues Growth Amid Fears It's Running Out of Steam</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN D. McCLAIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.S. economy grew at a faster rate in the
third quarter than previously estimated, the government said
Wednesday, but analysts say it is fast running out of steam and
some suggest it is flirting with a recession.
   The Commerce Department said the gross national product, the
broadest measure of economic health, grew at an annual rate of 3
percent in the July-September period, up from a 2.5 percent rate
reported in October and the subsequent revision to 2.7 percent last
month.
   However, analysts said the economic growth in the third quarter
borrowed its strength from the current quarter, when many see a
growth rate of less than 1 percent and possibly an end to the
unprecedented seven years of peacetime expansion.
   The administration is forecasting a 2.7 percent growth rate for
all of 1989, and the fourth-quarter GNP would have to advance 1.6
percent to meet that goal. The GNP grew by 3.7 percent in the first
quarter and 2.5 percent in the second.
   ``The bottom line is that we borrowed from the future to produce
3 percent growth and that source of strength is gone now,'' said
Allen Sinai, chief economist for The Boston Co.
   Sinai and others said much of the third-quarter growth resulted
from robust earlier-than-normal sales of automobiles and light
trucks in the third quarter that were driven by incentives.
   But the incentives were dropped with the introduction of
higher-priced 1990 models in October and sales immediately slumped.
Only this month have automakers begun to restore rebates and lower
interest rates that chief economist David Berson of the Federal
National Mortgage Association said could boost sales early next
year.
   Many analysts had suggested the Federal Reserve would have to
ease credit further to stimulate the economy and the central bank
late Tuesday added money to the banking system in a signal that it
might lower interest rates.
   As a result, the key federal funds rate, the interest banks
charge each other for overnight loans, dropped to 8 7-16 percent
from about 8{ percent late Tuesday. Analysts said they expected a
target of 8\ percent for the rate, the first drop since late
November.
   Samuel D. Kahan, chief financial economist at Kleinwort Benson
Government Securities Inc. in Chicago, forecast fourth-quarter
growth of 1 percent with continued weakness in the first quarter of
1990.
   ``I think a lot will depend on monetary policy,'' Kahan said.
``If the Fed continues to drag its heels, it could continue to get
weakness and could turn this into a recession.''
   But even with further easing by the central bank, Kahan said he
expects a ``somewhat lackluster first quarter'' returning to 2
percent to 2.5 percent growth later in the year.
   Sinai, on the other hands, says that while economic data does
not support his view, ``I think we're in some sort of recession''
now.
   The sluggish fourth-quarter growth is a result of Fed efforts to
contain inflation by keeping a tight rein on credit. Inflation
appeared to begin moderating earlier this year and since June the
central bank has eased some short-term interest rates.
   Its policy-making arm, the Federal Open Market Committee, met
secretly Monday and Tuesday, but as usual, gave no indication of
any decisions.
   The GNP report contained favorable inflation news, however. A
price index tied to the GNP rose at an annual rate of 2.9 percent,
unchanged from earlier estimates but down from the 5 percent jump
in the April-June quarter.
   The revision in the latest report was due in large part to new
data that showed exports rose 3.9 percent, rather than 1.6 percent
as reported earlier. At the same time, imports fell from a 9.5
percent gain first reported to 7.4 percent in the latest report.
   Consumer spending, however, dropped to a 5.6 percent increase
rather than the 6.2 percent advance reported last month. Consumer
spending represents two-thirds of the nation's economic activity.
   Business capital spending posted a 5.2 percent gain, compared
with 4.6 percent in last month's report, possibly reflecting an
improvement in the decline of corporate profits.
   In that report, the Commerce Department said after-tax profits
of U.S. corporations fell 5.4 percent rather than the 7.2 percent
decline reported in November.
   Housing construction, hit by high mortgage interest rates during
much of the year, fell 9.2 percent in the third quarter. It was
reported to be off 8.4 percent a month ago.
   Government purchases were down 2.4 percent, 0.3 percentage point
below the November estimate.
   The various changes left the GNP expanding in the third quarter
at a seasonally adjusted annual rate of $4.16 trillion.
</TEXT>

</DOC>