<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0312EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Japan-Markets     12-21 0388</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Japan-Markets,0399</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar Down In Tokyo, Stucks Plunge</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Tokyo Stock Exchange's key index plunged today,
while the dollar inched down against the Japanese yen.
   The dollar finished at 143.77 yen, down 0.43 yen from
Wednesday's 144.23-yen close. The U.S. currency opened at 143.80
yen and ranged between 143.70 yen and 143.90 yen.
   The 225-issue Nikkei Stock Average shed 296.52 points, or 0.77
percent, ending the day at 38,215.48. It had gained 72.90 points
Wednesday.
   Dealers said the index fell as many market players remained on
the sidelines, discouraged by the continuing speculation over the
discount rate hike by the Bank of Japan.
   Kazuhiro Nomura, a dealer with New Japan Securities Co., said
the index fell further in the afternoon, when major securities
firms, including Yamaichi and Nikko, sold issues for profit-taking.
   ``Investors were not in the buying mood simply because of the
discount rate rumor,'' Nomura added.
   Earlier this week, news reports said the Bank of Japan might
raise its key lending rate by 0.5 percentage points to 4.25 percent
by this weekend, which was denied by both the Finance Ministry and
central bank officials. But Kyodo News Service, quoting what it
described as a reliable source in the Bank of Japan, reported
Wednesday that the two sides would negotiate on a hike.
   Trading was moderate with first section volume estimated at 650
million shares, down from Wednesday's 1 billion.
   In currency dealings, the dollar moved narrowly after its lower
start in Tokyo in the wake of credit-easing overnight by the U.S.
Federal Reserve Board, but the action had little long-term impact
on Tokyo trading, which was inactive prior to the year-end
holidays, traders said.
   The U.S. unit ended only slightly lower than the opening rate as
participants traded the currency for position adjustments, said a
Daiwa Bank trader, speaking anonymously.
   ``Market players waited to check how the New York market
performs tonight,'' he said.
   The Fed was seen adding reserves to the U.S. banking system when
the key Federal Funds rate was at 8.4375 percent, below the 8.5
percent equilibrium rate perceived as the Fed's target. Late
Wednesday in New York, the Federal Funds rate, a short-term lending
rate between commercial banks, stood at 8.25 percent.
   An estimated $3.73 billion changed hands in spot trading, down
from $6.3 billion the previous day.
</TEXT>

</DOC>