<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0348EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Judge-Explosion     12-23 0663</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Judge-Explosion,Bjt,0689</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge Injured by Pipe Bomb Delivered to Home</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WX6</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEB RIECHMANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HAGERSTOWN, Md. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A county judge described as tough-minded
and outspoken was injured by a pipe bomb delivered to his home, but
authorities said the case appeared to be unrelated to four other
recent bomb attacks.
   Washington County Circuit Judge John P. Corderman, listed in
stable condition today, isn't known to have handled civil rights
cases _ the presumed motive in the earlier attacks, one of which
killed a federal judge.
   Corderman, 47, suffered shrapnel injuries to his abdomen and
right hand, and both eardrums were ruptured in the blast in his
third-floor apartment about 2:30 p.m. Friday, said Chuck Jackson,
Maryland State Police spokesman.
   ``Apparently, the device was situated outside when he arrived
home,'' Jackson said. ``He retrieved it, entered the apartment and
a short time later it exploded. We don't know whether it was opened
or not.''
   Despite his injuries, Corderman left the apartment and activated
a fire alarm about 10 feet outside his front door before collapsing
inside the apartment, Jackson said.
   A second bomb that apparently was in the package was taken to a
nearby city park and detonated.
   George Hopgood, an assistant FBI special agent in charge, said
the latest bomb was dissimilar to the ones that have been found in
the South.
   ``At this time there doesn't appear to be any connection,''
Hopgood said.
   Investigators are checking the possibility the earlier bombings
could have suggested such an attack to some with a grudge against
Corderman, Jackson said.
   In the earlier cases, a nail-packed mail bomb killed Judge
Robert S. Vance of the 11th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals Dec. 16
at his home outside Birmingham, Ala., and a similar bomb killed
black civil rights attorney Robert E. Robinson two days later at
his Savannah, Ga., office.
   Parcel bombs were found during the week at the Jacksonville,
Fla., chapter of the National Association for the Advancment of
Colored People and the 11th Circuit courthouse in Atlanta, where
Vance sat. Both were defused.
   Federal investigators believe the attacks were motivated by the
victims' or groups' role in civil rights cases.
   Vance's colleagues also have received threatening letters,
sources told The Associated Press on Friday. Investigators
disclosed Thursday there had been four follow-up threatening
letters, but refused to divulge who received them.
   In Washington, Justice Department spokesman David Runkel said he
was unaware that letters had been delivered to judges on the 11th
Circuit. But he said ``solid evidence'' linked the letters to the
bombers.
   The threatening letters had references to a group called
``Americans for a Competent Judiciary,'' the Atlanta Journal and
Constitution reported today, citing anonymous sources familiar with
the investigation.
   The group isn't known to authorities, said William Hinshaw,
special agent in charge of the FBI's Atlanta office.
   Washington County lawyers said they didn't recall Corderman
dealing with civil rights cases.
   ``He's the kind of gentleman who you like him or don't like
him,'' Baltimore attorney Chris Brown said. ``He has rubbed people
the wrong way.''
   Brown said the judge ``takes unusual stances and gives lawyers a
hard time. He's a very colorful, outspoken, controversial judge.''
   Said to be tough with criminal defendants, Corderman is a board
member of the Center to Prevent Handgun Violence, a gun control
group.
   Washington County State's Attorney M. Kenneth Long described the
judge as ``no-nonsense ... tough-minded, fair, bright and
articulate.''
   Long, who had lunch with Corderman shortly before the blast,
said the judge was in good spirits when he visited him later at
Washington County Hospital, where he was under 24-hour guard.
   ``He was trying to smile and trying to chuckle, but it was
difficult,'' Long said. ``He's grateful to be alive.''
   A neighbor of Corderman's, Steven Keyes, 30, said he saw a
delivery man bring a package to the building about 20 minutes
before the explosion.
   ``It looked like a normal person to me, a normal delivery,''
Keyes said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>