<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0179 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1412EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-PRI--KeepingFit Adv28   12-26 0633</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-PRI--Keeping Fit, Adv 28,0649</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv28</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Thursday, Dec. 28, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Age No Bar to Physical Fitness</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARILYN HAUK ESSEX</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Frieda Anderson strides into her
exercise class, warmed from a brisk bicycle ride, and puts away her
helmet.
   She's ready for her three-times-a-week class of stretching,
floor exercises, and physical activity to music ranging from 1950s
doo-wop to classical to the Grateful Dead's ``Touch of Gray.''
   Most in the class have their own touches of gray.
   This is the Walnut Creek YMCA's older adults fitness program,
some of the older Americans walking, biking and swimming their way
to better health.
   Mrs. Anderson, 73, logged 1,886 miles last year, just completed
her ninth RAGBRAI _ an annual bicycle ride across Iowa _ and rode
her bicycle at least 10 miles a day this summer. She posted the
most miles last year in a walking-jogging program, which credits
three miles of bicycling as one mile of walking.
   ``In cold weather, I walk at Valley West Mall,'' she said. ``The
rest of the time I ride my bike alone.''
   Others in the program are just discovering the rewards of
fitness.
   ``By age ... alone, there is no limit'' to when a person can
begin an exercise program, said Dr. John Rachow, of the University
of Iowa's College of Medicine. ``It's as fine if they're 89 as if
they're 63 and about to retire.''
   Norma Casserly, 62, of Des Moines, joined the senior fitness
class in February. ``The first time I went, I didn't think I would
be able to get off the floor.'' Seven months later, she weighed 10
pounds less, had cut her blood-pressure medication by a third and
felt better ``physically and emotionally.''
   Becky Harkema, director of the Walnut Creek older adults fitness
program, said it has grown from seven members in 1981 to about 100.
It is one of 34 Y's in Iowa with such programs, which generally
include 25 to 50 participants.
   Most people walk or bike in addition to the organized class and
keep logs of ground covered. They also meet monthly for lunch and
get together frequently to tour Iowa, talk about trips or discuss
the restoration of the Statehouse.
   The activity leaves participants with more energy to do more,
both physically and mentally, Harkema said. ``They can go to the
grocery store and not be short of breath. They can stay up an hour
later. The seniors who may have lost a spouse will regain new
friendships. They realize they have strengths they never knew they
had.''
   Arlene Lapscheske, 70, attends the program with her best friend
of 47 years, 72-year-old Maxine Dolan, and describes it as ``our
own special time.'' Both have been in the senior fitness program
for six years. ``I'm able to get up the stairs when other people my
age are out of breath,'' she said.
   Rachow advises patients to start an exercise program slowly, by
walking, riding a stationary bicycle or swimming. Someone who wants
to gain strength can ``start by lifting the weight of your own
limb,'' he said. ``It doesn't have to be a fancy Nautilus machine.''
   Regular exercise tends to decrease anxiety and depression and
the severity of muscle shrinkage, brittle bones and high blood
pressure, he said. ``There's already a tendency as you age to lose
muscle mass. Once you get weak, you end up going down into a chair
and not being able to get back up again.''
   Exercise also burns calories, and avoiding obesity can help
prevent high blood pressure, high blood cholesterol and diabetes.
   One reason 75-year-old Nate Bernstein attends the class is so he
``can eat a little more,'' but the main reason, he said, is ``for
the girls.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Dec. 28</NOTE>

</DOC>