<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0173 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1938EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-AlaskaVolcano     12-18 0598</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Alaska Volcano,0618</SECOND>
<HEAD>Volcano Snarls Mail, Air Travel</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL JENKINS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Redoubt Volcano continued to fire
clouds of steam and gritty volcanic ash high into the sky Monday,
forcing airlines to ground flights or route them around the
abrasive powder for fear of engine damage.
   Also grounded were 240 Korean Air Lines passengers who have
refused since Saturday to reboard their flight since it made its
scheduled stop here..
   Ash clouds rose to 31,000 feet from Redoubt's 10,197-foot summit
Monday.
   ``The volcano is still very active,'' said Steve Brantley, a
geologist with the Alaska Volcano Observatory. ``We are continuing
to observe a high level of earthquake activity on the mountain, and
we received a number of reports of confirmed ash plumes rising
above the volcano this morning.''
   Anchorage International Airport was open Monday, but service was
irregular, with some airlines grounding aircraft and others
offering limited service. Some domestic airlines canceled flights
and international carriers routed their aircraft around Anchorage.
   Projections showed that the ash, carried by high-altitude wind,
could reach the Kenai Peninsula, and perhaps the outskirts of
Anchorage, sometime late Monday.
   While some tried to get on planes, a group of Korean Air Line
passengers refused to reboard their flight Monday, saying they were
concerned whether it was safe to fly.
   ``We are debating that right now,'' said Christine Lee, 23, a
spokeswoman for the balky passengers. ``There are 240 of us total,
and the factions to leave and stay are about the same. If some go,
we all have to go.''
   KAL Flight 25 was en route from New York to Seoul on Saturday
when it landed in Anchorage.
   Lee, a Korean national with a home in the United State, said the
plane arrived late, then was delayed and passengers were taken to
hotels. ``Then all these rumors started about the safety of the
plane; the volcanic ash,'' she said. ``It's hard to tell what's
really true.''
   Elected passenger representatives met Monday with KAL officials,
Lee said. KAL representative Lee Steiner in Los Angeles said he
unsure what the problem was, and airline officials in Anchorage had
no comment.
   Federal Aviation Administration spokesman Paul Steucke said his
agency was not involved because Flight 25 was an international
flight. International airline companies are responsible for the
safety of their planes, he said.
   The volcanic ash's threat to aircraft, especially jets, also
hampered holiday mail delivery.
   About 22,000 pounds of mail was stacked in Anchorage on Monday
for shipment out of Alaska. An additional 130,000 pounds waited in
Seattle for shipment to Alaska, said spokeswoman Nancy Schmitt.
   ``It's playing havoc with us,'' she said. ``This is the largest
backup we've ever had.''
   The postal service depends on commercial jets to move the mail,
but has resorted to chartering propeller-driven aircraft, she said.
``The mail's moving, but slowly,'' she said.
   The Alaska Railroad added a train Monday between Anchorage and
Fairbanks for travelers trying to reach that interior city, said
spokeswoman Vivian Hamilton.
   Redoubt began erupting Thursday after two decades of silence and
has sent ash and steam skyward intermittently since. It is in a
sparsely populated area 115 miles southwest of Anchorage in the
Lake Clark National Park and Preserve.
   No injuries have been reported but one family was removed Sunday
from a lodge in the shadow of the volcano although they were in no
immediate danger.
   Another couple remains at a lodge north of the peak. Workers
were removed from an oil storage depot along a river which has
flooded in the past when Redoubt's eruptions melted snow.
</TEXT>

</DOC>