<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0102 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1144EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-Panama-Pentagon 4thLd-Writethru a0618 12-20 0891</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Pentagon, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0618,850</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pentagon Chiefs Dispatch Soldiers, Paratroopers</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Top 9 grafs with Cheney saying plans long in works and correcting
that 7,000 sted 9,500 troops in initial invasion; picks up at pvs 6th graf,
Powell, the</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSANNE M. SCHAFER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Military Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Defense Secretary Dick Cheney said today that
plans for a U.S. military invasion of Panama, carried out today in
the predawn ``Operation Just Cause,'' had been in the works since
before he took office last spring.
   Cheney and other administration officials called the 1 a.m. EST
invasion a success even though its initial attempts to capture
Panamanian leader Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega had failed.
   The Pentagon, on President Bush's orders, sent 7,000
paratroopers and other soldiers from U.S. bases to Panama in a bid
to oust Noriega and bring him to this country to face
drug-trafficking charges.
   Nine American servicemen were killed, 39 injured and one
reported missing in the operation, which pulled together more than
20,000 U.S. infantrymen, paratroopers, Marines, airmen and sailors.
   ``I think this operation was a success already because we cut
off the head of that government and there is a new government that
was elected by the Panamanian people, waiting, willing and ready to
take over,'' said Gen. Colin Powell, chairman of the Joint Chiefs
of Staff.
   He added that he believed the people of Panama will rally to
support the new leaders installed under U.S. auspices.
   ``We have not located the general. But as a practical matter, he
is a fugitive and will be treated as such,'' Powell told reporters
at the Pentagon. ``This reign of terror is over.''
   Cheney said, ``The order went out late on Sunday to implement a
plan that had been in existence for some time. It was one of the
first items I was briefed on when I became secretary of defense
last spring.''
   ``We hope to be wrapping up General Noreiga in the future,''
Cheney said. ``As the president has said, we have achieved the bulk
of our objective.''
   Powell, the nation's top military officer, said sporadic sniping
continued from Noriega's former headquarters and that there was ``a
slight problem'' near Fort Amador where the Panamanian 5th Infantry
was located. Most of the remaining action consisted of putting down
the remaining forces loyal to Noriega.
   ``We're into mopping up and chasing down those ... who have not
yet decided to give it up,'' the general said.
   Powell said the U.S. forces were determining whether the firing
was coming from ``an armed resistance force, or just individuals,
who are now just criminals and thugs running around the
countryside.''
   In a nationally broadcast address from the White House shortly
before the Pentagon briefing, President Bush said he had ordered
the invasion to protect American lives and install an elected
government in place of Noriega, who faces drug-trafficking
indictments in the United States.
   Powell said 7,000 troops had been sent from the United States
overnight to augment the 13,000 U.S. troops based near the Panama
Canal and that 2,500 more were arriving later in the day. Some
forces parachuted into action.
   The general said the invasion, dubbed ``Operation Just Cause,''
simultaneously used airborne Rangers, paratroopers, infantrymen,
Marines and light tank units to attack the central headquarters of
the Panamanian Defense Forces, as well as several other military
bases and airports.
   The bulk of the forces came from the 82nd Airborne Division from
Fort Bragg, N.C., and the 7th Light Infantry Division from Fort
Ord, Calif.
   They were transported in south by huge Air Force C-141 transport
planes, which had been landing in Panama throughout the night.
   Powell said the U.S. forces encountered opposition from local
forces ``throughout the area of operations,'' but that the invasion
went smoothly.
   ``I hope you recognize how complicated an operation this was and
how competently it was carried out,'' he told reporters.
   Asked whether Noriega would become a fugitive leader of
rebellious troops that would harass U.S. forces, Powell said:
   ``He can do that, and we will chase him and we will find him. He
is a very canny individual. He's demonstrated incredible ability to
survive catastrophe, and we'll see over time whether he survives
this catastrophe.
   ``It's been some years since General _ Mister _ Noriega, the
fugitive, has been seen in the jungle. He's used to a different
kind of lifestyle. I'm not quite sure he would be up to being
chased around the countryside by Army Rangers, Special Forces and
light infantry units,'' Powell said.
   The general said the American deaths came ``as a result of
firefighting,'' but could offer no further detail. He said U.S.
officials ``deeply regret the loss of American life.''
   Powell said he did not have a reliable number for the number of
Panamanian troops killed in the overnight invasion. He said that in
addition to the American casualties, some U.S. cargo planes and
helicopters were damaged.
   The general said there had been reports that some American
civilians had been taken hostage and that U.S. forces were looking
into each incident, but that he had ``no numbers or details to
provide'' about them.
   Powell detailed the parachute drops and assaults that resulted
in American forces occupying ``all the bases'' that had been manned
by the Panamanian military.
   Cheney and Powell met with reporters after a night-long vigil in
the Pentagon.
</TEXT>

</DOC>