<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0144EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Romania-Glance     12-19 0320</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Glance,0330</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romania At A Glance</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Facts and figures on Romania:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   GEOGRAPHY _ Romania covers 91,700 square miles and shares
borders with Hungary, Yugoslavia, the Soviet Union and Bulgaria.
The Danube River empties into the Black Sea on Romania's eastern
coast. The north of the country is dominated by the Carpathian
mountains and the center by the Transylvanian alps.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   THE PEOPLE _ Romania's population of 23 million includes about
1.7 million ethnic Hungarians _ the largest minority _ and 220,000
ethnic Germans. Romanian is the main language, but Hungarian,
Serbian, German and Turkish are also spoken. Eighty percent of the
population is Romanian Orthodox and 10 percent are Catholics. There
also are 21,000 Jews.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ECONOMY _ Romania, whose industry accounts for around 60 percent
of the gross national product, exports machinery, metals, lumber,
refined fuels and textiles. Agricultural products include corn,
wheat, potatoes and beets. Natural resources include oil, natural
gas and coal.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   HISTORY _ Romania gained independence in 1877 after some five
centuries of Ottoman rule. A monarchy before World War II, the
country was reorganized along Fascist lines from 1940 until August
23, 1944, when Romania switched to the Allied side. With the
support of Soviet troops, a Communist-dominated government bloc won
elections in 1946, and in 1955 Romania joined the Warsaw Pact.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   LEADERSHIP _ The present leader, Nicolae Ceausescu, came to
power in 1965. Noted for his moderately independent foreign policy
in the 1960s and 1970s, he is under increasing fire for his home
policy, including suppression of dissent and alleged discrimination
against the Hungarian minority. Efforts to repay the foreign debt
quickly have led to growing domestic food and energy shortages in
recent years. Ceausescu's ringing rejection of reform is leaving
him with fewer friends, as Warsaw Pact allies move toward democracy
and Western countries step up criticism of Romania's human rights
records.
</TEXT>

</DOC>