<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0160 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1850EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Romania-Americans     12-22 0591</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Americans,0606</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romanian-Americans React With Delight At Ouster of `Butcher' Ceausescu</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Will be updated with Los Angeles rally, scheduled for 10 p.m.
EST.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Romanian-Americans reacted with joy and surprise Friday to the
triumphant revolt against the man one woman called ``an absolutely
pathological character.''
   ``We are free, we are free, finally we are free!'' said Lucian
Cruceanu, a spokesman for Romanian Faith and Freedom Coalition in
Los Angeles. ``That is the first words they told me on the phone
(from Romania) this morning.''
   President Nicolae Ceausescu was ousted from power by an outraged
public after a week of protests in which thousands reportedly died.
The revolt ended 24 years of oppression and brought down the last
hard-line rule in the Soviet bloc.
   The Rev. Constantine Alesce of the Holy Trinity Romanian
Orthodox Church in Los Angeles called Ceausescu ``the worst
dictator that ever existed on the face of the Earth. We just prayed
that Christmas would bring the greatest gift to Romania, the
freedom ... of the country.''
   Dr. Virginia Sulica, a Washington, D.C., physician with family
and friends in Romania, said she had visited the country recently
and ``people did not have electricity, did not have food. I came
out very upset, but I'm very happy now. I think this is wonderful
news for everybody.''
   ``We all expected it to happen. Unfortunately, it happened with
bloodshed. We hope now that's over with. It was the last country to
go, but that man, that Ceausescu, was an absolutely pathological
character. It's the only way I can explain it.''
   The most famous Romanian exile in the United States, Olympic
gymnast Nadia Comaneci, had no public comment. She has been
incognito for the past 1{ weeks, after criticism arose over her
purported romance with a married Romanian immigrant.
   Ms. Comaneci, 28, who became world famous as a teen-ager with
her unprecedented perfect scores in the 1976 Olympics, escaped her
country last month. She was last seen in public at a Pompano Beach,
Fla., hotel on Dec. 12.
   Viorel Catarama, 33, of Hinsdale, Ill., who came to this country
in 1982 and is now an American citizen, said ``happy is not enough
to say. I'm just trying to find the proper words to say.''
   Referring to the victims of the uprising, he added, ``My heart
is with the people who died. ... They paid the price but it's worth
it in a way.''
   He said Romanian-Americans planned a weekend rally at Chicago's
City Hall to celebrate the revolt. In Los Angeles, a Friday evening
rally was planned.
   Catarama, now a U.S. citizen and owner of a construction
company, said, ``I hope for the best, I hope for democracy, I hope
for freedom of speech, freedom of religion, freedom to express
yourself, and most of all now I'd like to see the president being
brought to justice.''
   The Rev. George Gage, parish priest at St. Mary's Romanian
Orthodox Church in Chicago, who fled Romania in 1981, called
Ceacescu a ``butcher'' and said many priests were killed by the
regime.
   Dana Mester, 25, of New York City, who left Romania five years
ago, was at a party, celebrating with other Romanian friends.
   ``My radio came on to wake me up and when I heard, I jumped out
of bed. ... People had been saying Romania was the only country
that didn't do anything. I'm just so happy. ... After they shot
people, I was sure the dissent would end and nothing would happen.
But then this morning, Oh my God!''
</TEXT>

</DOC>