<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 2309EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-AtlanticStorm     12-17 0459</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Atlantic Storm,0471</SECOND>
<HEAD>Storm Toll Put at 14 in Britain, France</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gales and torrential rain from an Atlantic storm
lashed Britain and France over the weekend, killing at least three
people and leaving 11 missing.
   The storm, raging along the English Channel and Atlantic coast,
briefly pushed into Paris on Sunday with 50 mph gusts accompanied
by thunder, lightning and a sudden downpour.
   The 35-foot fishing boat Destiny sank Saturday in Scotland's
Firth of Clyde, 750 feet from safe harbor, and all six fishermen
were believed lost in heavy seas and driving snow, authorities said.
   David Rowan, captain of the Irish coastal steamer Arklow Victor,
was washed overboard early Sunday in the Bay of Biscay off France
as his ship went down. A French helicopter rescued his five
crewmembers.
   Waves swept two teen-age boys out to sea late Sunday. One, 16,
was hit by a huge wave near Folkstone on England's south coast. The
other, 14, was swept to his death as he and a group of youths
watched the waves from rocks at Castletown on the Isle of Man in
the Irish Sea.
   Rain sent golfers at a course in the Paris suburb of
Villennes-sur-Seine scampering for cover under a covered brick
platform which serves as a driving range, firefighters said. A
sudden gust knocked the structure over, killing Bernard Ecarlat,
58, a doctor, and injuring nine people, three seriously.
   Wind toppled a 6{-foot-high outdoor wall in Aubervilliers,
another Paris suburb, crushing to death two men passing by, police
said.
   On the Normandy coast at St. Pierre-en-Port, a French coast
guard helicopter searched in vain for Stratos Smyranos, 32, a
Parisian taking a seaside holiday who was walking his dog along the
shore Sunday when caught by a high wave.
   No trace was reported of TV cameraman-journalist Joseph Delage,
37, carried out to sea by a huge wave Saturday night as he
struggled to repair his car at Conquet, about 385 miles west of
Paris. Delage had just finished shooting footage of the storm for
the French television network FR3.
   Storms battered the southwest coast of England and Wales all day
Sunday and boats stood by to rescue hundreds of people from
Lymington, on the south coast, as a high tide approached.
   Parts of the town were under five feet of water but the high
tide passed without further flooding.
   Homes were evacuated in Porthleven and Newlyn in Cornwall in
southwesternmost England on Sunday, and there was extensive
flooding in east Devon and Dorset in the south.
   In France, waves broke a protective dike Saturday on the Ile de
Sein, west of Brest, flooding about 13 summer homes, said residents
reached by telephone. No injuries were reported on the island, home
to 600 people.
</TEXT>

</DOC>