<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0522EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-Panama-Decision     12-20 0629</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Decision,620</SECOND>
<HEAD>Decision to Strike Against Noriega Made on Sunday, White House Says</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-US-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER CONNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush made up his mind Sunday to
launch the U.S. military strike against Panama's Manuel Antonio
Noriega, barely 24 hours after the slaying of an American Marine
officer outside Noriega's military headquarters in Panama City, the
White House said.
   Bush administration officials kept their plans secret until
Tuesday evening when news organizations began reporting heavy U.S.
military flights into Panama, where the United States has 12,000
troops based to protect the Panama Canal.
   Even as the Pentagon was preparing the effort to capture Noriega
and allow Panamanian opposition leaders to take over the
government, Bush went as planned Tuesday evening to a White House
Christmas party for 300 friends, administration officials, White
House staff and reporters.
   The president maintained silence Sunday when asked for his
reaction to the killing of the unarmed Marine lieutenant, who was
trying to escape a Panamanian Defense Force checkpoint after a
wrong turn brought him and three other U.S. soldiers close to
Noriega's headquarters.
   White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater, in an early morning
briefing today announcing the move against Noriega, said Bush ``has
been considering this matter for several days.'' He said the
president ``was quite disturbed'' by the killing of the Marine
officer and harassment of a naval officer and his wife by
Panamanian soldiers at the same checkpoint.
   ``The president reviewed this issue with his national security
advisers on Sunday afternoon. They considered options, developed a
plan and the president made the basic decision to proceed with this
action,'' Fitzwater said.
   He added that there had been ``any number of meetings'' since
Sunday, but emphasized, ``there really has not been any question
about our willingness or our readiness to proceed since that time.''
   The White House on Sunday deplored the killing of the Marine and
said the incident was a ``consequence'' of the outlaw Noriega
regime, imposed on Panama against ``the will of the Panamanian
people'' who voted in May to elect opposition leader Guillermo
Endara to the presidency.
   Noriega, Panama's military commander and de facto ruler,
nullified those elections. On Friday a legislature of Noriega
cronies declared the country in a state of war against the United
States and named Noriega its ``maximum'' leader.
   Bush, in an interview Monday with The Associated Press and other
wire services, expressed ``enormous frustration ... that the
democratic system that was voted on in Panama was totally put down
by force.''
   He called the killing of the Marine ``an enormous outrage,'' and
pointedly refused to rule out a military response.
   Bush had no public events on his schedule Tuesday except the
Christmas party, where he and wife Barbara gaily posed with each
guest for pictures in front of an enormous tree, decorated with
dolls from children's stories and fables.
   Bush stayed to hear an Army chorus sing carols in the East Room,
hoisting up 3-year-old granddaughter Nancy Ellis LeBlond in his
arms for a better view and extending a hearty handshake to former
White House press secretary Jim Brady, wounded in the 1981
assassination attempt against former President Reagan.
   At the Pentagon, military public information officers also
sought not to tip their hand. Most left their offices at the
regular quitting time Tuesday evening.
   National Security Adviser Brent Scowcroft, his deputy Robert
Gates and White House Chief of Staff John Sununu all put in brief
appearances at the Christmas party Tuesday night before shuttling
back to their offices to wait for the U.S. military strike.
   Bush stayed in the Oval Office until 4:05 a.m. EST, when he
retired to his personal residence for a brief sleep before a 7 a.m.
address to the nation from the Oval Office.
</TEXT>

</DOC>