<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0937EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-EC-Turkey     12-18 0495</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-EC-Turkey,0512</SECOND>
<HEAD>EC Says No to Turkish Membership</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTINA MACKENZIE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRUSSELS, Belgium (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The European Community's executive body
today said Turkey should not be allowed to join the trading bloc in
the near future, saying it must improve its economy and human
rights record.
   ``It is impossible to begin immediate (membership)
negotiations,'' with Turkey, said Abel Matutes, the EC's
commissioner for Mediterranean policy. Negotiations could not begin
before 1993, he added.
   But the Commission recommended strengthening cooperation between
the 12-nation trade bloc and Turkey in the next few years to pave
the way for eventual membership.
   The EC's executive body has been considering the economic and
political implications of Turkish membership since Ankara
officially applied to join the Community on April 14, 1987.
   Under EC rules, the commission must give its opinion on
membership applications, but a final decision is up to the 12
member states' governments and the European Parliament. At any
rate, no new members can join until 1993 when the EC should have a
Single Market.
   Austria is the only other country to have made an official
membership request.
   Matutes said today's decision did not question ``the principle
of Turkey's eligibility for membership of the Community,'' sometime
in the future.
   He said the Commission reached its decision after an exhaustive
survey of Turkey's economic and political situation, undertaken
with the help of the Turkish government.
   He said the Commission had also looked at the effects of Turkish
membership in the context of developments within the EC, which is
working to abolish its internal barriers to the free movement of
trade, services, capital and people by the end of 1992 _ the
so-called Single Market.
   ``Between now and 1993 we must concentrate all our efforts on
achieving the Single Market,'' Matutes said.
   Although the Turkish economy had made ``really remarkable and
encouraging progress ... there are still disparities and problems
which we cannot ignore,'' he said.
   The commissioner said that on average Turkish economic
development was only one-third of the EC average.
   ``Unemployment is high, ... social security is low and is far
from the norms current in the Community. Inflation remains a sharp
problem,'' he said.
   Although Turkey is a parliamentary democracy, Matutes said,
there are still areas ``notably in the trade unions sector, human
rights and respect for minorities,'' where ``progress is
necessary.''
   Turkey was under military rule from 1980 to 1983.
   In addition to the human rights and trade unions problems,
Matutes said the Commission was concerned about Turkey's
relationship with Greece.
   The two Mediterranean neighbors have long been at odds over
Cyprus and mineral rights in the Aegean Sea. They almost went to
war over the latter issue in early 1987.
   Greece said it would oppose Turkish membership in the trading
bloc for as long as Turkey maintained 30,000 troops on Cyprus.
Turkey invaded Cyprus in 1974, saying it had to protect the
island's Turkish Cypriot minority after a coup by pro-Greek
elements.
</TEXT>

</DOC>