<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0172 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1943EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-Panama-Americans-Thumbnails 1stAdd   12-22 0807</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Panama-Americans-Thumbnails, 1st Add,0853</SECOND>
<HEAD>UNDATED: ... a sister</HEAD>
<BYLINE>Spec. Alejandro I. Manrique Lozano</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Alejandro Manrique Lozano, 30, of Lauderdale Lakes, Fla., called
his wife from Fort Bragg, N.C., before leaving for Panama and said,
``Watch the news. I love you.'' He was an anti-armor weapons expert
with the 82nd Airborne division.
   Manrique was a naturalized citizen born in Callao, Peru, a Lima
suburb where his parents still live. He had lived in the United
States for five years and enlisted for a four-year stint in the
Army's elite Special Forces in January 1988. He and his wife,
Sheree Nelson-Manrique, 47, met four years ago when they both were
working for singer Julio Iglesias. They had no children during
their 2{ years of marriage.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Pfc. James William Markwell</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Markwell, 21, an Army Ranger medic from Cincinnati, died soon
after U.S. forces began their assault on Panamanian military
headquarters.
   Markwell had been stationed at Hunter Army Airfield in Savannah,
Ga.,
   ``His leave was supposed to start today (Thursday) and he was
planning to come home for Christmas,'' said his stepfather, Bill
Rouse, of Shannon, Ohio. ``He knew what the dangers were, but he
was willing to take the chance.''
   Markwell played football at Cincinnati's Princeton High,
graduating in 1986, then spent two years in college studying
medicine.
   ``He just loved people and that was the basis for his decision
to become a Ranger,'' Rouse said. ``He was committed to it and
planned to make a career of the military.''
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Chief Engineman Donald Lewis McFaul</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   McFaul, 32, died three days after his first wedding anniversary.
His wife, Patricia, in Norfolk, Va., is expecting their first child.
   McFaul, of San Diego, Calif., was a 14-year Navy veteran and a
member of the SEAL operation based at Little Creek, Va. He had been
sent to Spanish language school and had assignments in the
Philippines and may have gone to Central America and El Salvador.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Cpl. Ivan D. Perez</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Perez, 22, an infantryman, had been offered an honorable
discharge last year when an accident caused him to loose sight in
one eye, but refused because ``he wanted to be a soldier,'' said
his sister, Adriana, of Pawtucket, R.I.
   Perez, who was born in Colombia, graduated from Central Falls
High School and most of his family lives in nearby Pawtucket.
   He entered the Army in 1985 and had been stationed at Fort Polk,
La., until being transferred to Panama on Oct. 14.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Pfc. John Mark Price</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Price, sumoned to Panama eight days ago, would have turned 23 on
Christmas Eve. He was a paratrooper in the Army's 75th Rangers.
   Price, of Conover, Wis., joined the Army in July 1988 for its
college fund when he could not continue his education at Olivet
Nazarene College in Illinois. His two younger brothers also joined
the Army to earn college money after their father died of a heart
attack three years ago.
   He is also survived by his mother, Ruth Ann, and a sister.
Friends remembered him as polite, outgoing, jovial and
hard-working. He loved the outdoors and fishing.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Torpedoman 2nd Class Issac George Rodriguez</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Rodriguez, 24, of Missouri City, Texas, near Houston, was a
six-year Navy veteran. He is originally from Los Angeles.
   He joined the SEAL Delivery Vehicle Team II in Little Creek,
Va., in March 1985, and went to basic underwater demolition school
in Coronado, Calif., last year. Rodriguez returned to Little Creek
in January and was assigned to the Naval Special Warfare Group II.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Pfc. Scott Lee Roth</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Roth, 19, of Killeen, Texas, was a military policeman stationed
at Fort Hood, Texas. He was married to another soldier, Spec. Mary
Roth, also stationed at Fort Hood.
   The couple wed shortly after Roth graduated from Rockridge High
School in Illinois in 1988, said his father-in-law, Donald
Ziegenhorn, of Illinois City, Ill.Roth entered the Army in
September 1988.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Pvt. 2 Kenneth Douglas Scott</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   _Pvt. 2 Kenneth Douglas Scott, 20, of Princeton, W.Va., joined
the Army six months ago and was stationed out of Fort Polk, La.
   He was to marry his high school sweetheart, Yvette Howard, when
he came home on leave in January. She had Christmas presents ready
to mail to him.
   Scott was the fourth of five children. His legal guardian, Ruth
Palmer, did not know he was in Panama.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Boatswain's Mate 1st Class Christopher Tilghman</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Tilghman, like Connors, McFaul and Rodriguez, was a member of
the Navy SEAL team who died in an assault on a Panamanian airfield.
   Tilghman, 30, was a native of Kailua, Hawaii, and entered the
Navy in 1979.
   ``He was following in my footsteps. He joined right after high
school,'' his father said in a telephone interview from his home in
Kailua. Taylor Tilghman was in the Navy for 15 years and the Coast
Guard for 15 years.
</TEXT>

</DOC>