<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0275 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 2137EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f BC-WeeklyWallStreet Adv23-24   12-22 0655</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Weekly Wall Street, Adv 23-24,0678</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv23</HEAD>
<HEAD>$adv24</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Weekend Editions Dec 23-24</HEAD>
<HEAD>A Tale of Two Blue Chips</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHET CURRIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   One blue-chip stock multiplied your money to
nearly 10 times its former value. Another turned your dollar into
less than a dime.
   That, in microcosm, was the story of the 1980s on Wall Street _
a decade in which many fortunes were made, and more than a few were
lost, in a roaring bull market.
   To pick the biggest winner among the 30 stocks that now make up
the Dow Jones industrial average, you had to ignore a gathering
storm over the tobacco industry.
   The company in question was Philip Morris, whose shares
increased almost 850 percent in value from the beginning of the
'80s through mid-December, according to calculations by William
LeFevre at the investment firm of Advest Inc. Adjusted for splits,
Philip Morris stock soared from $4.50 to $40-plus.
   Philip Morris, widely known as the producer of Marlboro and
several other cigarette brands, began a diversification program
many years ago with Miller Brewing Co.
   In the '80s it claimed the status of world's largest
manufacturer of consumer products with the acquisitions of General
Foods and Kraft Inc., gaining such familiar product lines as
Maxwell House coffee and Post cereals.
   Meanwhile, it strengthened its hold as the dominant force in the
tobacco industry.
   At the other end of the standings, Navistar International was
the biggest loser among the Dow 30, falling from $39.12 at the
start of the '80s to less than $4 recently.
   Navistar, known a decade ago as International Harvester, left
the farm- and construction-machinery businesses to concentrate on
making trucks and diesel-powered equipment. It suffered through a
seven-year spell of losses before recently returning to
profitability.
   Among the winners, Philip Morris wasn't alone in benefiting from
the ravenous consumer appetites of the '80s.
   Close behind it in the Dow performance ranking stood McDonald's
Corp., up nearly 700 percent; Coca-Cola, up nearly 600 percent, and
Merck, the health care giant, up more than 500 percent.
   Like Navistar, Bethlehem Steel, which was down more than 20
percent, and International Business Machines, up less than 50
percent, reflected the many problems of the economy's industrial
sector.
   What did all this mean for a diversified portfolio of stocks?
Once the big winners and losers are balanced out, the Dow Jones
industrial average has more than tripled. ``All in all, not a bad
10 years,'' LeFevre observed.
   In the past week, the average suffered something of a setback,
beset by fears that softening real estate markets might increase
the odds of a recession in 1990. It closed Friday at 2,711.39, down
28.16 from the week before.
   The New York Stock Exchange composite index dropped 1.50 to
191.95; the NASDAQ composite index for the over-the-counter market
rose .73 to 444.57, and the American Stock Exchange market value
index was down 1.50 at 191.95.
   Volume on the Big Board averaged 168.70 million shares a day,
against 185.54 million the week before.
   Just how the experience of the '80s might translate into good
decisions for the '90s remains to be seen.
   Some say the new decade, like the old one, may begin with a
recession, especially since the great prosperity of the past
several years has left a lot of debts to be paid.
   Others contend that the pessimists and the skeptics, who missed
many an opportunity in the '80s, may just wind up repeating the
same mistake.
   Whatever happens, however, people in the stocks and bonds
business say the story of the '80s' big winners and losers provides
a dramatic demonstration of the virtues of a diversified investment
program.
   Anyone who owned $10,000 each of the best and worst blue chips
through the '80s would have an $80,000-plus Philip Morris profit as
consolation, and then some, for a $9,000 Navistar loss.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Weekend Editions Dec. 23-24</NOTE>

</DOC>