<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1511EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-China     12-17 0473</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-China,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>US, China Discuss Release of 2 Dissidents</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GREENE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United States and China are discussing the
release of Chinese dissident Fang Lizhi and his wife, Li Shuxian,
to a third country, a published report said Sunday.
   The discussions about a possible release of Fang occurred as a
result of private talks that former Secretary of State Henry
Kissinger held in Beijing last month, The Washington Post said,
quoting an anonymous Bush administration source.
   National Security Adviser Brent Scowcroft followed up on those
talks last weekend when he and Deputy Secretary of State Lawrence
Eagleburger met with officials in Beijing on a much-criticized
surprise mission, the newspaper said.
   Scowcroft and Eagleburger are former business partners of
Kissinger's in a consulting firm that has clients in China.
Kissinger has been involved with China since the Nixon
administration, which paved the way for a reopening of relations
between the two countries. Former President Nixon visited China in
late October.
   Fang and Li have taken refuge in the U.S. Embassy in Beijing
since the Chinese government's bloody crackdown in June on the
democracy movement. The suppression culminated in the killing of
hundreds, perhaps thousands, of people at Tiananmen Square.
   The recent U.S. overture, including a toast by Scowcroft to the
Chinese leaders who led the crackdown, has been criticized in the
United States. Some lawmakers have threatened to seek sanctions
against China when Congress returns in January.
   President Bush, however, said Saturday in St. Martin that he had
seen ``a couple of indications'' that the visit would have
``positive results.'' He did not elaborate.
   Bush made the remarks after a meeting with French President
Francois Mitterrand.
   According to the official quoted in the Post, China's leaders
have said they would not release Fang to the United States or
France. Both countries host numbers of Chinese student dissidents.
   The official said the United States ``wants to get him out of
there'' and the search is continuing for a compromise, the Post
reported.
   Kissinger, appearing Sunday on CBS-TV's ``Face the Nation,''
declined to comment on his discussions.
   But he did say: ``I would expect that over the next four to six
weeks it will be obvious that the human rights issue was not put on
the back burner and that important considerations with respect to
human rights were raised.''
   Asked if there were a conflict of interest between his business
interests and his private diplomacy, Kissinger said: ``Well, the
funny thing is that I'm trying to keep the list of my clients
confidential for that very reason, that I don't want to raise
conflict-of-interest questions, and others are trying to make me _
get me to make them public, because our client list is not revealed
to the governments concerned.''
   He added, ``My opinions are not for sale.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>