<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0291 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 2002EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-ResortsReorganization     12-22 0638</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Resorts Reorganization,0662</SECOND>
<HEAD>Resorts International Files Reorganization Plan</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HENRY STERN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTIC CITY, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Resorts International filed a
reorganization plan in bankruptcy court Friday that seeks to shed
about two-thirds of its $912 million in debt.
   Analysts said the plan, which formalizes a bankruptcy petition
filed Nov. 13 in U.S. Bankruptcy Court in Camden, N.J., will buy
the company badly needed time to get its finances in order.
   The plan seeks the court's approval of company owner Merv
Griffin's proposal to swap 78 percent of his Resorts stock for
about $600 million of the outstanding debt, said company spokesman
Rob Shepardson.
   In addition to the approval of the bankruptcy court, the plan
requires the approval of half the Resorts bondholders, New Jersey's
Casino Contol Commission and the government of the Bahamas, where
Resorts owns a casino.
   Shephardson said the companies would likely mail proxies in late
January to bondholders.
   Resorts' casinos in Atlantic City and the Bahamas will not be
affected by the plan, Shepardson said.
   In August, Resorts suspended interest payments on its
outstanding bonds, which Shepardson estimated at $912 million. In
September, the company announced a restructuring plan aimed at
preventing a bankruptcy filing.
   Bondholders attacked the plan and split into two groups, one
holding subordinated unsecured debt and the other with senior
secured debt.
   The plan filed Friday would give senior secured bondholders
$187.5 million in new notes with a 4-year term, bearing interest of
6 percent in the first year, 9 percent in the second, 12 percent in
the third and 15 percent in the fourth. Those bondholders also
would receive 2.5 percent of Griffin's shares.
   Holders of Resorts' highest paying bonds, 16| percent, would
receive 32.4 percent of the shares. The remaining bondholders would
get 43.1 percent of the company stock.
   The deal would leave Griffin as chairman of a newly constituted
six-person board of directors.
   The plan also would require Griffin to invest a total of $30
million in the company and fund a $5 million kitty for any legal
action against billionaire developer Donald J. Trump.
   Trump had been Resorts chairman and controlling shareholder
before Griffin bought the company in November 1988. As part of the
deal between the two, Trump received the unfinished Taj Mahal
casino in Atlantic City for $230 million, less than half the $500
million Resorts poured into construction.
   Attorneys for some bondholder groups say they may sue Trump for
``fraudulent conveyance.'' Trump has said Griffin bears
responsibility for the deal.
   Analysts have said Griffin paid too much for the casino and
weighed down his purchase with too much debt, which Shepardson
estimated at $912 million.
   But analysts said Friday that Griffin's plan may yet save the
company.
   ``I think it's the only alternative,'' said John Uphoff, a
casino analyst for Raymond James &amp; Associates in St. Petersburg,
Fla.
   He said the scheduled spring opening of the massive Taj Mahal
next door may bring in new customers for Resorts.
   ``The opening of the Taj will give them some extra business that
they desperately need,'' Uphoff said.
   Daniel R. Lee, an analyst for Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc., which
issued $325 million in bonds for the transaction, said the Taj
Mahal is a ``plus and a minus.''
   ``It will be a big competitor sitting on Resorts' doorstep,'' he
said. ``But it's also going to bring in a lot of business.''
   The casino's most recent financial results showed a $34.9
million net loss for the third quarter.
   Resorts, which was the first casino to open on Atlantic City's
Boardwalk in May 1978, posted a ``win'' total for November of $17.1
million, an 8.1 percent decrease from the $18.4 million of November
1988.
   Yearly figures show a win of $214.9 million, 9.4 percent lower
than the $228.5 million for the first 11 months of 1988.
</TEXT>

</DOC>