<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0117 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1700EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Ceausescus 1stLd-Writethru a0587 12-28 0501</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Ceausescus, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0587,0512</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ceausescu Brother Apparently Kills Himself, Sister Arrested</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 1st graf to CORRECT typo in ``rule.''</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The family that helped Nicolae Ceausescu
rule Romania for 24 years was in ruins Thursday, its leading
members dead by firing squad, a brother hanged by his own hand and
eight other relatives under arrest.
   Marin Ceausescu, 74, the eldest brother of the deposed dictator,
was found hanging in the trade section of the Romanian Embassy in
Vienna on Thursday, an apparent suicide, Vienna police said.
   A sister and her son also were reported arrested Thursday in
Romania, bringing to at least eight the number of family members
known to be under arrest and awaiting trial.
   Nicolae Ceausescu and his wife, Elena, were killed by a firing
squad on Monday after a trial by the revolutionary government found
them guilty of grave crimes against Romania.
   Marin Ceausescu had been active as a trade counselor here since
1973. The Vienna daily Kurier, citing unspecified sources in the
new Romanian government, alleged Thursday that Marin ``managed the
Romanian secret service headquarters for Western Europe in Vienna.''
   The claim could not be confirmed.
   Nicolae Ceausescu was overthrown on Dec. 22 by a mass uprising
backed by the army. He mistrusted many, and he was believed to have
put at least 40 of his relatives in power to help him maintain his
oppressive rule.
   Elena Ceausescu was a member of the now-disbanded Politburo and
the first deputy premier, the second-most powerful person in the
nation.
   Ceausescu's two other brother's, Ilie, an army general and
deputy defense minister, and Nicolae Andruta, a police general and
deputy interior minister, were captured the day their brother was
deposed and have since been in detention.
   Romanian soldiers and police on Thursday arrested Ceausescu's
sister, Elena Barbulescu, and her son, Emil, as they were hiding
out in Ceausescu's hometown of Scornicesti, the official Romanian
news agency Agerpres reported.
   Also arrested with them was Ilie's wife. The news agency did not
give her first name.
   Checks worth about $50,000 and about $3,600 worth of Romanian
currency were found in Mrs. Barbulescu's possession, said Agerpres.
   Mrs. Barbulescu is the wife of Vasile Barbulescu, who was
Ceausescu's agricuture chief and is currently under arrest.
   Ceausescu's youngest son, Nicu, and daughter, Zoia-Elena, have
been in custody since last week.
   Nicu Ceausescu was party secretary in Sibiu in southern
Transylvania, home to a powerful military and security garrison. He
was reportedly a heavy drinker and womanizer who killed two people
while running red lights.
   Among the items police found in Zoia Elena's apartment were
seven expensive watches, jewelry, $95,000 in cash and valuable
paintings. Also found was a golden scale used to weigh the imported
meat fed to her two lapdogs. She reportedly was head of the
Bucharest Institute of Mathematics.
   Scores of other more distant members of the clan occupied
positions in the security, trade and agriculture, but their fate
was not known.
</TEXT>

</DOC>