<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0110 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1622EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SriLanka     12-27 0301</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sri Lanka,0311</SECOND>
<HEAD>36 Die in Ethnic Violence</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATRICK CRUEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>COLOMBO, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sinhalese radicals stormed a wedding
party in southern Sri Lanka and stabbed to death four guests whom
they accused of being government spies, military officials said
Wednesday.
   Thirty-two other people, including some Sinhalese extremists,
were reported killed since Tuesday in violence inspired by
Sinhalese militants of the People's Liberation Front.
   The wedding party attack occurred Tuesday night in Urubokke, 85
miles south of Colombo, the officials said. All the victims were
Sinhalese men, and all the killers escaped.
   In the nearby city of Tangalle, extremists blew up a truck
Wednesday, killing three policemen and a soldier, the officials
said without elaboration.
   Also Wednesday, extremists shot to death two supporters of the
governing United National Party.
   The truck explosion occurred hours after police found the burned
bodies of 13 young Sinhalese men who had been shot.
   It was not known who killed the men, but the method was similar
to that used by vigilante groups who allegedly kill civilians
suspected of associating with the radical People's Liberation Front.
   Government troops killed 12 front members in three separate
incidents since Tuesday in central and southern Sri Lanka,
officials said.
   Sinhalese extremists began a violent campaign in 1987 to protest
an accord the government approved in an effort to end a war by
minority Tamils demanding more autonomy.
   Ultranationalist Sinhalese claimed the Sinhalese-controlled
government made too many concessions to the Tamils, who comprise 18
percent of Sri Lanka's 16 million people.
   At least 11,000 people have died in the Tamil insurrection,
while another 6,000 have been killed in the Sinhalese backlash.
   Sinhalese make up 75 percent of the population. Tamils say the
Sinhalese discriminate against them in jobs, education and use of
the language.
</TEXT>

</DOC>