<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0153 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1755EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-Espionage     12-22 0285</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Espionage,0293</SECOND>
<HEAD>West Steps Up Espionage To Get Grip on New East Germany</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-East Germany, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Western governments have stepped up
intelligence gathering in East Germany to get a grip on the new
political situation, the official ADN news agency said Friday.
   The United States and West Germany are interested especially in
acquiring information from political, economic and military
sources, the agency said, citing the Agency for Protection of the
Constitution, as the country's counterintelligence service is known.
   The new service, which bears the same name as its West German
equivalent, was created when the Stasi _ the hated secret police _
was dissolved and reorganized.
   Western intelligence agencies are seeking to get a fix on the
new leaders who have emerged since the collapse of the Communist
Party to be able formulate a new German policy, the agency said.
   The agencies have concluded that German reunification is on the
poltical agenda, but have yet to decide whether German unity is a
military danger to European stability or if Western governments
should support the rapprochement, ADN said.
   The ouster of former Communist Party leader Erich Honecker on
Oct. 18 as well as his successor Egon Krenz on Dec. 3 has pushed
little-known groups into the political limelight.
   The future role of the newly renamed Communist Party remains
unclear to the Western agencies, ADN reported.
   As a result of political fragmentation and the emergence of new
political groups, Western intelligence services are trying to
recruit new sources on a wider political basis.
   The creation of a new pool of agents in strategic positions in
the government, economy military and security service is of key
importance to the West, ADN reported.
</TEXT>

</DOC>