<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1234EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People-CasinoNewYear's     12-30 0408</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People-Casino New Year's,0417</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sellout Crowds Expected to Jam Casino Showrooms for New Year's</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURA MYERS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RENO, Nev. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Comics Jay Leno and George Carlin and singers
Wayne Newton and Dolly Parton are among the headliners who will do
their numbers New Year's Eve for both high rollers and tourists at
Nevada casinos.
   Even Tony Bennett will leave his heart and long-running singing
engagement at the Fairmont Hotel in San Francisco for a one-night
show Sunday in Las Vegas at the Riviera hotel-casino.
   ``We book way in advance to get the top headliners for the New
Year's Eve show because people expect the biggest names,'' Dave
Verbon, vice president of public relations at the Riviera, said
Friday. ``All the casinos do it.''
   Hotel-casinos also usually hold expensive parties for high
rollers, which they refer to as VIPs, MVPs (most valuable players)
or just ``good customers,'' who sometimes drop large amounts of
cash and chips on gaming tables, said Brian Lawson, publicist for
Bally's Reno.
   ``We put on a special New Year's Eve banquet that's a black-tie
affair for our MVPs and they have their choice of shows
afterwards,'' Lawson said.
   The special one-night show in Bally's Reno Grand Ballroom on
Sunday night is called ``Into the '90s Laughing with George Carlin
and Special Guests.'' The room's 2,600 seats are sold out, Lawson
said.
   Country singer Randy Travis is playing to a capacity crowd of
2,000 in Bally's Ziegfeld Theatre and there's a rock 'n' roll show
for people who want to see the new year in with a blast from the
past.
   Some 150,000 tourists are expected at Las Vegas during the
three-day holiday weekend and more than 50,000 in the Reno-Sparks
area in northern Nevada, according to tourism officials.
   Rock 'n' roll hall of famers Chuck Berry and Jerry Lee Lewis
will play Bally's Celebrity Room in Las Vegas, while the casino's
other rooms will feature nostalgic appearances by '60s
chart-toppers the Four Tops and Frankie Valli and the Four Seasons.
   Newton, a Las Vegas fixture, is playing the Hilton, the Smothers
Brothers will be bickering at the Desert Inn and the Pointer
Sisters will be singing in the new year at Caesars in Las Vegas.
   Miss Parton will play New Year's Eve and New Year's Day shows at
Caesars Tahoe on the south shore at Stateline, Louise Mandrell
headlines at Harrah's Reno and Leno cracks jokes at Harrah's Tahoe
hotel-casino.
</TEXT>

</DOC>