<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1208EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-1989Earthquakes     12-28 0355</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-1989 Earthquakes,0367</SECOND>
<HEAD>List of Fatal Earthquakes This Year</HEAD>
<HEAD>With Australia-Quake</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here is a list of other earthquakes in 1989:
   
   JAN. 23 _ Earthquake measuring 5.4 on Richter scale triggers
huge mudslide that buries three villages in Soviet republic of
Tadzhikistan, killing 274.
   APR. 16-18 _ Quake measuring 6.7 and aftershocks kill at least
11 people in remote region of Sichuan province in China near
western border with Tibet.
   APR. 25 _ Earthquake east of Acapulco and south of Mexico City
measuring 6.8 kills one man who is electrocuted by falling power
line.
   JUNE-JULY _ Series of five earthquakes, with the strongest
measuring 6.7, strikes western Sichuan province in China in
three-week period killing 11 people.
   JULY 15 _ One person dies when quake measuring 6.0 strikes Alor
Island in Indonesia.
   AUG. 1 _ Strong quake measuring 6.0 in remote province of Irian
Jaya of Indonesia kills at least 90 and injures 125.
   AUG. 8 _ Quake measuring 5.2 on scale jolts San Francisco and
kills one man who fell from his fifth floor apartment window.
   OCT. 17 _ Earthquake measuring 7.1 rattles San Francisco Bay
area; 67 die.
   OCT. 18 _ Series of six quakes in 24 hours kills 29 in northern
Shanxi and Hebei provinces in China, about 135 miles west of
Beijing. The quakes destroyed over 11,000 homes in 40 villages over
a 320 square-mile area, leaving 50,000 people homeless. Authorities
said casualties were relatively low since most people fled their
homes after the first tremor measuring 5.7 hit, and were outside
when one measuring 6.1 struck and destroyed their homes.
   OCT. 29 _ Severe quake measuring 6.0 and second 4.8 quake 12
minutes later shake Algeria, causing heavy damage to towns and
villages east of Algiers along Mediterranean coast. At least 24
people died and 456 were injured. Many older structures in famed
Casbah of Algiers suffered heavy damage.
   DEC. 12 _ Moderate quake registering 4.4 triggers landslide in
southern Iran that kills one person.
   DEC. 16 _ Earthquake measuring 7.3 in a sparsely populated area
of Mindanao in southern Philippines collapses a concrete wall,
killing a 7-year-old boy.
</TEXT>

</DOC>