<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0149 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2052EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Opposition     12-21 0292</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Opposition,0300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Group Declares Opposition in Soviet Congress</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A leading reformer said Thursday that scores of
members of the Congress of People's Deputies have been forced into
opposition by the majority's unwillingness to press reforms.
   The declaration by historian Yuri N. Afanasyev was a
watered-down version of a statement first debated a week ago by the
Inter-Regional Deputies Group, proclaiming a ``political
opposition'' to the Communist Party and government. Still, it set
the 2,250-member Congress on a stormy debate.
   Afanasyev called for an end to the Communist Party's monopoly on
power, and criticized the congress for failing to take up key
questions of economic reform.
   ``We are in the opposition to the decisions of the Congress,''
Afanasyev said. ``We can't agree with indefinite postponement of
the passage of the most important laws.''
   The Inter-Regional Group failed on the opening day of the
Congress Dec. 12 to place on the agenda the party's constitutional
role as the ``leading and guiding force'' of Soviet society.
   It also failed to put on the agenda a discussion of laws on
land, property, and economic organization.
   Afanasyev said he spoke for at least 130 members of the
Inter-Regional Deputies Group, which includes about 400 Congress
members. The group had included human rights activist Andrei D.
Sakharov, who died last Thursday after attending a meeting in which
the group discussed declaring a formal opposition.
   Svyatoslav Medvedev, a deputy from northern Kazakhstan, charged
in a congress debate that Afanasyev's group ``has started an open
struggle for political power in the country.''
   Afanasyev has said formation of a formal opposition to the
Communist Party and government could be a step toward formation of
an opposition political party.
   He has declared his support for a multiparty system.
</TEXT>

</DOC>