<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0186 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1724EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Czech-Soviet     12-20 0530</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Czech-Soviet,0549</SECOND>
<HEAD>Moscow, Prague to Examine Soviet Troop Presence</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Czechoslovakia, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GIRARD C. STEICHEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Czechoslovakia and the Soviet
Union agreed Wednesday to begin reviewing the presence of 80,000
Soviet troops stationed here since the ``Prague Spring'' reforms
were crushed in 1968.
   Foreign Minister Jiri Dienstbier and Premier Marian Calfa told
reporters after returning from a one-day visit to Moscow that a
joint commission will be set up in the first half of January.
   The commission, composed of civilian and military experts, also
will re-examine the political and historical events that led up to
the Soviet invasion and its consequences, Dienstbier said at an
airport news conference.
   Dienstbier, who has said he hopes an agreement can be reached
soon on the withdrawal of Soviet troops, told reporters the
commission would ``deal with all aspects of the Soviet military
presence'' in Czechoslovakia.
   Calfa was asked if there would soon be a timetable for a pullout
of the troops, which have been stationed in Czechoslovakia on a
``temporary'' basis for 21 years.
   ``I don't know, but I think we will have results in this area
that will satisfy the nation,'' Calfa replied without elaboration.
   In Moscow, the official news agency Tass announced that the
Soviet Union had agreed to negotiate its troop presence in
Czechoslovakia. Tass said Dienstbier and his Soviet counterpart,
Eduard A. Shevardnadze, agreed to begin the talks in the first two
weeks of next month.
   The dispatch did not say the Soviet Union would be negotiating
withdrawal of its troops, but the Czechoslovak state news agency
CTK has said the East bloc country would begin preliminary
negotiations for the pullout of Soviet troops.
   Dienstbier said he met with Shevardnadze for more than an hour
Wednesday. Calfa met with Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev and
Premier Nikolai I. Ryzhkov.
   Calfa said he left Moscow with the feeling that there was
``great understanding for this question.''
   Alexander Dubcek, who led the Prague Spring movement crushed by
the Soviet-led Warsaw Pact invasion in August 1968, signed the
initial document allowing the troops' presence after tense
negotiations in the Kremlin, where he was flown right after the
invasion.
   Since the ouster of hard-line communist leaders the last month,
the new Czechoslovak leadership has said the agreement was invalid
because it was signed under duress.
   On Wednesday, the Communist Party apologized for its hard-line
policies of the past and for abusing its opponents after the 1968
crackdown.
   Earlier this month, the Soviet Union condemned the invasion as a
mistake. Under Gorbachev, the Kremlin has vowed not to interfere in
the affairs of its Warsaw Pact allies.
   Poland, East Germany, Hungary and Bulgaria also have apologized
for their roles in the invasion.
   Dienstbier sai before the visit that any troop withdrawals must
run parallel with East-West talks on conventional weapons
reductions under way in Vienna, where a preliminary accord is
expected next year.
   Faced with a peaceful revolution, Czechoslovakia's hard-line
President Gustav Husak resigned Dec. 10 after swearing in the new
government dominated by non-communists. Other hard-line leaders
associated with the crackdown that followed the invasion have been
ousted from power and purged from the party.
</TEXT>

</DOC>