<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0125 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0633EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DigestBriefs     12-30 0565</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Digest Briefs,0585</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Navy is ``seriously considering'' limiting
purchases of its prized $1.2 billion Trident submarine to every
other year in reaction to intense budget pressures for the new
fiscal year, a senior Pentagon official says.
   The service also is proposing to put two of its four battleships
in mothballs as it fights to retain at least 14 aircraft carriers.
   President Bush is scheduled to deliver his 1991 budget to
Congress on Jan. 22, and he may be called upon to make the final
calls on the controversial suggestions.
   ``We're robbing Peter to pay Paul,'' the Pentagon official said
of the current budget-juggling exercise. He spoke on condition of
anonymity.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Drug Enforcement Administration, rejecting
a recommendation of its own chief judge, has refused to relax
restrictions on marijuana.
   The order by Administrator John C. Lawn, published Friday in the
Federal Register, means that marijuana will continue to be listed
under Schedule I of the Controlled Substances Act, for substances
with a high potential for abuse and no accepted medical
application, where it has been classified since the act was passed
in 1970.
   NORML, the National Organization for Marijuana Law Reform,
petitioned three years ago to have the substance reclassified to
Schedule II, meaning it would remain unavailable to the general
public but could be prescribed by doctors for limited purposes.
   The DEA's chief administrative law judge, Francis L. Young,
recommended Sept. 6, 1988, that marijuana be placed on the less
restrictive schedule, calling it ``one of the safest
therapeutically active substances known to man.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Attorney General Dick Thornburgh's decision to
close an internal investigation into a news leak about an FBI probe
of Rep. William H. Gray III's office got a sharp rebuke from Gray
and from Sen. Joseph R. Biden Jr., who says the leak investigation
should continue.
   Thornburgh wrote Biden, the Senate Judiciary Committee chairman,
that investigators had been ``unable to identify with certainty the
original source'' of disclosures to CBS reporter Rita Braver about
Gray's office financial affairs and therefore will not prosecute or
fire anyone.
   The leak occurred at the end of May while Gray, D-Pa., was
seeking election in the House as majority whip, and it prompted
accusations from Democratic lawmakers that Thornburgh's aides were
the source of a political leak.
   Thornburgh said in Friday's letter to Biden, D-Del., that
investigators also told him ``the nature of the confirmations
alleged to have been forthcoming to Ms. Braver'' were ``uncertain.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Federal Communications Commission is
investigating claims that some companies are charging backyard
satellite dish owners as much as 20 times more than cable systems
for the same TV programs.
   The FCC said Friday it had ``disturbing evidence'' that cable
operators were receiving preferential treatment from satellite
carriers for the programs cable operators provide by coaxial cable
to their subscribers.
   ``Because this evidence raises serious concerns about the
competitive nature of this market and the impact on consumers,''
the commission said it would conduct an inquiry into the matter to
determine if remedies were needed to protect the nation's 2.5
million dish owners.
   ``This is a great victory,'' said Larry Helland, attorney for
the Valhalla, N.Y.-based American Home Satellite Association.
Helland said the new FCC inquiry finally would force satellite
companies to justify their rates to backyard dish owners.
</TEXT>

</DOC>