<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0000EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-EastBloc-Christmas Bjt   12-25 0793</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-East Bloc-Christmas, Bjt,0813</SECOND>
<HEAD>Christians Jam Churches Around East Europe, Remember Romania</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NESHA STARCEVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Millions of Christians jammed churches in
Eastern Europe to celebrate their first Christmas in freedom after
four decades of Communist rule, but their thoughts also went to the
brave Romanian people.
   In Prague, Leipzig, East Berlin and even in battle-ravaged
Bucharest, the spirit of defiance that had guided Eastern Europeans
to their remarkable revolutions turned into hope for a brighter
future.
   The change was striking in Berlin as people from both sides of
the technically still divided city mingled freely, attending joint
church services for the first time since the Berlin Wall was built
28 years ago.
   East Germany on Sunday began allowing visa-free travel by West
Germans and thousands used the opportunity to cross to East Berlin
to join relatives for a Christmas service.
   ``We had very good attendance this year. Many people from West
Berlin came. Now we really have a feeling of freedom,'' said
Christiana Winter, an East Berliner who was showing West Berliners
around the Lutheran St. Mary's Church.
   ``The church gave hope during all those years when there was no
hope and now we are full of hope.
   ``This year it was important to speak of God's message of love
so that there are no acts of revenge. The church was on the side of
the weak for years and now its is important not to hate those who
treated us unjustly,'' she said.
   The pope's midnight Mass was broadcast live for the first time
by East German television.
   In Leipzig, the cradle of East Germany's pro-democracy movement,
pastor Friedrich Magerius began the service in St. Nicholas Church
by commemorating the thousands of Romanians killed and wounded in
their struggle to overthrow Communist dictator Nicolae Ceausescu.
   In Leipzig, like in many other towns in East Europe, the church
had sheltered dissidents during the years of oppressive Communist
rule.
   In Bucharest, hundreds of faithful came to the Mitropolia
Cathedral to hear the Patriarch of the Romanian Orthodox Church,
Teocitist Arapas, and Christmas carols played on radio for the
first time in more than 40 years.
   The patriarch thanked about 500 believers for coming to the
service despite battles raging in the city between popular forces
and die-hard Ceausescu loyalists.
   ``We must thank God, who gave us freedom after 25 years of
terror,'' the patriarch said, referring to the length of
Ceausescu's dictatorship.
   ``I have been waiting 40 years for this. Now I can openly go to
church,'' said Ion Ganescu, a dissident who spent 10 years in
prison for his opposition to Ceausescu.
   In Poland, where the Roman Catholic Church had enjoyed much more
freedom than churches in other Communist countries, many people
stayed by television sets Sunday night to watch Polish-born Pope
John Paul II celebrate Midnight Mass at the Vatican.
   Thousands attended the midnight service at their local parishes
and crowds filled churches to capacity on Christmas Day to pray and
see traditional nativity scenes, which at some churches comment on
the changes in Eastern Europe. One, at Warsaw's St. Ann's church,
showed the Holy Infant resting upon the fallen Berlin Wall.
   In most of the vast Soviet Union, Christmas will be celebrated
Jan. 7 according to the Russian Orthodox calendar. But in the three
Baltic republics, where there are large populations of Roman
Catholics and Protestants, Christmas was a holiday for the first
time under Soviet rule.
   In Vilnius, the capital of Lithuania, Roman Catholic activist
Antanas Terleskas said many people attended church as usual. But he
said people were not especially happy, because ``the freedom of
expressing religious beliefs is just an illusion we are permitted
to toy with,'' he said.
   In Riga, Latvia, radio and television broadcast the pope's mass
and activists said church attendance was up.
   In Tallinn, Estonia, people were able to watch the pope's mass
on Finnish television, which they receive easily, and for 12 hours
Estonian television broadcast Christmas carols.
   On Christmas Eve, millions of Czechoslovaks watched Christmas
Mass on an unprecedented live television broadcast. The Mass from
Prague's 13th century Strahov Monastery was said by the Rev. Vaclav
Maly, who the government had banned from the priesthood for 11
years because of his human rights activities.
   Millions of believers jammed into churches and Cathedrals
throughout the country for midnight Mass. On Christmas Day,
90-year-old Cardinal Frantisek Tomasek said Mass at the gothic St.
Vitus Cathedral overlooking the city, delivering a sermon on the
responsibility that freedom brings.
   In central Prague, on the site where mass pro-democracy rallies
turned the tide of Czechoslovak history last month, crowds of
students gathered to sing and share the holiday at the statue of
Bohemia's patron saint _ good King Wenceslas.
</TEXT>

</DOC>