<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0091 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1424EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ProsecutorIndicted     12-21 0426</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Prosecutor Indicted,0436</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Orleans D.A., Actor Plead Innocent in Gambling Case</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JANET McCONNAUGHEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   District Attorney Harry Connick and actor
Paul Burke pleaded innocent Thursday to charges that they schemed
to help an arrested bookie continue a gambling operation.
   The two were among nine people indicted Dec. 15. Magistrate
Louis Moore Jr. set bond at $10,000 apiece for Connick, Burke and
four others, and at $20,000 apiece for convicted bookmaker Walton
Aucoin, 49, and Steven Bertolino, 57, accused of taking part in the
bookmaking operation. All were allowed to sign for their bonds
without putting up cash.
   ``I did nothing wrong. ... The allegations are pure D baloney,''
said Connick, who gained notoriety this year with a continuing
attempt to revive Louisiana's anti-abortion laws. He could get up
to 25 years in prison and a $250,000 fine if convicted on the
charges against him.
   The indictment accuses Connick of giving Aucoin gambling records
seized when Aucoin was arrested in December 1988. Connick has said
it was proper to give Aucoin records needed for his defense.
   A grand jury said the records were provided to help Aucoin
continue collecting and paying gambling debts.
   Connick has repeatedly said the indictment is the result of a
personal vendetta by U.S. Attorney John Volz, who began the federal
investigation but later turned it over to the U.S. Justice
Department in Washington.
   Also charged in the case are Wilson P. Abraham, 70, a New
Orleans real estate developer who pleaded innocent Wednesday,
William G. Condon, 34; Iris Ethridge, 30; Aucoin's daughter,
Darleen Aucoin Toca, 27; and Patrick Fanning, a defense lawyer who
was once an assistant district attorney and an assistant U.S.
attorney.
   Aucoin, Bertolino, Condon, Ms. Ethridge and Ms. Toca were
charged with owning and conducting a New Orleans-based illegal
interstate gambling operation that allegedly netted as much as
$2,000 a day. Fanning, Abraham and Burke were charged with aiding
the operation by helping Connick cook up an excuse for returning
the records Aucoin needed to keep it going.
   The excuse was, according to the indictment, that Aucoin needed
the records to pay his federal gambling stamp taxes.
   Burke was once a star of television's ``The Naked City'' and
appeared in ``The Valley of the Dolls'' and other movies. He is a
New Orleans native now living in Palm Springs, Calif., according to
the indictment.
   Connick wants to act as his own co-counsel along with defense
lawyer Bill Wessels, Wessels told the court.
   The trial was tenatively set for March 1.
</TEXT>

</DOC>