<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0247 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2216EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Chevron-Pennzoil     12-19 0531</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Chevron-Pennzoil,0550</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pennzoil Says It Won't Sue Chevron But Wants the Right To Do So</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BOB EGELKO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The battle over Pennzoil Co.'s purchase of
$2.1 billion worth of Chevron Corp. stock moved into murky legal
waters Tuesday, with a Pennzoil lawyer asking a federal judge to
lift restrictions on suing the rival oil giant but denying any
intention to sue.
   ``People have a right to be in court,'' Stephen Bomse, a lawyer
for Houston-based Pennzoil, said at a hearing on Chevron's request
for a long-lasting order protecting it from suits by Pennzoil
without court permission. He said the order ``would tie our hands.''
   While Bomse insisted Pennzoil had no plans to sue Chevron over
its anti-takeover maneuvers, Chevron lawyer William Edlund said
Pennzoil has a history of ``hostile, non-passive investments,'' and
added, ``Chevron suspects the motives of Pennzoil.''
   U.S. District Judge Thelton Henderson said he would rule within
a few days, and meanwhile left another judge's order in place that
requires Pennzoil to obtain the court's permission before suing San
Francisco-based Chevron in any court over issues related to the
case.
   Chevron, the nation's fourth-largest oil company, sued Pennzoil,
the 14th-largest, on Dec. 7 after learning that Pennzoil bought 8.8
percent of Chevron's common stock.
   Pennzoil said it was making a long-term investment for tax
purposes, to shelter the bulk of a $3 billion settlement it
received from Texaco, and had no intention of acquiring control.
   Chevron challenged those statements, citing Pennzoil's past
attempts at oil company acquisitions, and accused Pennzoil of
concealing its purpose of a takeover or forced restructuring, in
violation of federal securities law.
   The suit seeks to force Pennzoil to sell the stock and prohibit
more purchases without court approval.
   At the same time, Chevron beefed up its defenses against
takeovers, giving its directors a veto over purchases of stock
purchases of more than 10 percent and arranging a $5 billion line
of credit. Five groups of stockholders, none affiliated with
Pennzoil, have sued Chevron management over those moves.
   Pennzoil says the suit is based on unfounded speculation and has
moved to dismiss the case. Henderson, who will hear that motion
Friday, has already ruled that the allegations in the suit are
serious enough to give Chevron access to Pennzoil documents and
executives _ orders Chevron says Pennzoil has largely resisted so
far.
   When it filed the suit, Chevron obtained a temporary restraining
order from Chief U.S. District Judge William Ingram prohibiting any
related suits by Pennzoil without approval of the local court.
Chevron sought an injunction Tuesday that would leave the
prohibition in place until the court disposed of the case.
   ``Chevron believes that Pennzoil will be litigating,'' Edlund,
Chevron's lawyer, told Henderson, saying such suits were common in
takeover attempts.
   He said extending the restrictions would avoid multiple suits
and should not harm Pennzoil, if it is telling the truth about its
intentions.
   But Bomse said Chevron had failed to show any threat of harm
that would entitle it to an injunction.
   ``You can't grant an injunction based on speculation, merely
because Chevron ... may believe that Pennzoil is going to commence
litigation,'' Pennzoil's lawyer said.

</TEXT>

</DOC>