<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1206EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Israel-Lebanon 4thLd-Writethru   12-26 0630</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Israel-Lebanon, 4th Ld-Writethru,a0513,0647</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israeli Military Wipes Out Two Guerrilla Posts</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 16 grafs to UPDATE with second raid, background,
troops out of southern Lebanon; picks up 16th pvs, `Israel carved...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SHIBLI ABI ASSI</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RASHAYA, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israeli warplanes today raided a major
Communist Party command post south of Beirut, and police said at
least three people were killed. Israel said it destroyed the base.
   The air strike came just hours after Israeli paratroopers backed
by tanks and air cover swept deep into southern Lebanon, killing
guerrillas and wiping out another Lebanese Communist base.
   In Jerusalem, the Israeli military command said the Communist
command post at Rmeile, 20 miles south of Beirut, was destroyed in
the air raid.
   ``At the terrorist target ... there are dead and wounded,'' the
army said, adding that the Israeli fighter jets returned safely to
their bases. No further details were released.
   Lebanese police said at least three people were killed and seven
wounded in the five-minute air raid. Israeli authorities said there
were no Israeli casualties in either attack.
   Six Phantom F-4 fighter bombers attacked Rmeile, and guerrillas
fired several heat-seeking SAM-7 anti-aircraft missiles that were
deflected by balloons released by the Israeli pilots, police
reported.
   Earlier today, paratroopers attacked a Communist base which the
army described as a terrorist target used as a launching pad for
anti-Israeli attacks.
   That attack was the Israeli army's biggest ground operation in
Lebanon in more than a year. The later air raid was Israel's 17th
such strike in Lebanon this year. At least 18 people were killed
and 109 wounded in the previous 16 air raids.
   In Beirut, police said army sappers defused a car packed with
165 pounds of explosives near Prime Minister Salim Hoss' office.
Hoss, a Sunni Moslem, was at home five blocks away when the bomb
was discovered, and police said it appeared he was not the target.
   A police spokesman said it was defused a half-hour before it was
set to go off. ``A bloodbath has been averted,'' said the
spokesman, who cannot be named under standing regulations.
   The guerrilla base at Nabi Safa, in the foothills of Mount
Hermon 7{ miles north of Israel's self-proclaimed ``security zone''
in Lebanon, was manned by the Moscow-oriented Lebanese Communist
Party.
   The Israeli army's attack was its biggest ground operation in
Lebanon since an assault against the Syrian-backed Popular Front
for the Liberation of Palestine-General Command Dec. 9, 1988.
   The attack force of about 100 commandos pushed out from the
border enclave, occupied by the Israelis since 1985, in four tanks
and eight armored personnel carriers at 2 a.m. behind a massive
artillery barrage, police reported.
   The attackers stormed through the villages of Kfar Meshki and
Lebbaya in the eastern Bekaa Valley after two helicopter gunships
blasted them with eight rockets, destroying many houses, the
spokesman said. He cannot be named under standing regulations.
   Forty other commandos were then dropped by helicopters in Nabi
Safa, where they blew up the Communists' two-story command post
after raking the base with machine-gun fire, the spokesman added.
   He said the attackers pulled back into the security zone two
hours after the attack began.
   Israel carved out the two- to 15-mile wide border enclave to
curb guerrilla raids following its army's withdrawal from Lebanon
three years after it invaded in 1982.
   The 2,500-man South Lebanese Army holds the enclave along with
an estimated 1,500 Israeli troops.
   The Israeli assault came amid heavy fighting in south Lebanon
between two rival Shiite Moslem factions, the Iranian-backed
Hezbollah, or Party of God, and the Syrian-allied Amal.
   Police have reported at least 38 people killed and 150 wounded
in four days of battles in a power struggle for control of
Lebanon's 1.2 million Shiites, the country's largest sect.
</TEXT>

</DOC>