<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0241 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0801EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-ExcelInjuries     12-22 0309</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Excel Injuries,0318</SECOND>
<HEAD>Excel, Union Reach Agreement on Meatpacking Injuries</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WICHITA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Excel Corp. and the union that represents
many of the company's workers have reached an agreement aimed at
reducing injury rates at Excel's meatpacking plants.
   Both parties said the agreement is unique because Excel, based
in Wichita, acted voluntarily.
   ``Obviously we hope that the rest of the industry will respond
as responsibly as Excel has,'' said Al Zack, spokesman for the
United Food and Commercial Workers in Washington. ``We've gone
through a lot of battles with other companies just to prove that
problems existed.''
   Battles with other packers, notably IBP and John Morrell &amp; Co.,
have resulted in the Occupational Safety and Health Administration
levying more than $10 million in fines. The union's complaints have
centered on injuries caused by repetitive-motion stress.
   Zack said provisions of the agreement were similar to those
ordered by OSHA in the IBP and Morrell cases.
   The agreement will first be implemented at Excel's Plainview,
Texas, plant and later expanded to beef-processing plants in Dodge
City; Friona, Texas; Nebraska City, Neb.; Schuyler, Neb.; Sterling,
Colo.; Marysville, Calif.; a beef-distribution center in
Philadelphia; and pork-processing operations in Beardstown, Ill.,
and Ottumwa, Iowa. The union represents about 8,600 workers at
those plants.
   Zack said the union had brought safety issues to Excel's
attention at the Plainview and Ottumwa plants. The company
responded with a proposal, rather than denying that injury problems
existed, he said.
   Under the terms of the agreement, Excel will hire an ergonomic
consultant and other medical personnel, and union members will be
trained as monitors to survey work areas, spot symptoms of
repetitive-motion stress and recommend solutions. The program will
involve testing of production flows and equipment, experimental
work stations, worker training on the causes and prevention of
injuries and revised procedures to treat and rehabilitate injured
workers.
</TEXT>

</DOC>