<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0101 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1853EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RefineryExplosion 1stLd-Writethru a0623 12-26 0413</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Refinery Explosion, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0623,0423</SECOND>
<HEAD>Search Continues For Man Missing Since Sunday Explosion</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS throughout to UPDATE with second body found, heating oil
prices close sharply higher, spokesman saying Exxon expects to meet its
long-term commitments for heating oil. No pickup.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Oil Prices</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BATON ROUGE, La. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Searchers on Tuesday found the body of a
second victim of a Christmas Eve explosion at Exxon's giant
refinery here that damaged buildings six miles away.
   Property owners, meanwhile, flooded the plant's office with
calls about damage caused by the storage tank blast.
   Elsewhere, heating oil futures prices surged on speculation that
the damage to the nation's second-largest refinery, combined with a
recent record-setting cold wave, would tighten home fuel supplies.
Heating oil for January delivery jumped 10.74 cents to 92.48 cents
a gallon on the New York Mercantile Exchange.
   Officials said they were trying to determine whether the second
body was that of an Exxon worker missing since the blast.
   The missing worker's name has not been made public. Some workers
reported seeing him Sunday after the explosion, but he has not been
seen since.
   ``The family of the missing employee has been notified and is
being updated on the status of the identification effort,'' Exxon
spokesman Dave Gardner said.
   Previously, the company said mechanic Harold Guillory, 31, of
Erwinville, an employee of a contractor, died when his pickup truck
caught fire near the explosion.
   Exxon spokesman Jim Davis said the company didn't anticipate any
immediate effect from the blast on its ability to supply heating
oil. Davis said there was some flexibility in the Exxon refinery
network, which includes refineries in Baytown, Texas, and Linden,
N.J.
   Asked about long-term supplies, company spokesman Walter
Eldredge said, ``We think we will be able to meet all our
commitments.''
   Investigators from Exxon were still working to determine the
cause of the explosion.
   More than 1,000 Baton Rouge area residents have called Exxon
with complaints that their houses were damaged by the explosion.
   Eldredge said Exxon officials will begin Wednesday to inspect
the claimed damages.
   The Christmas Eve fire engulfed two large storage tanks, holding
a combined 3.6 million gallons of heating oil, and three smaller
tanks with about 882,000 gallons of lubricating oil, officials said.
   The refinery has a capacity of 455,000 barrels _ more than 19
million gallons _ of crude oil a day.
   The Occupational Safety and Health Administration and the
Environmental Protection Agency were investigating the accident.
</TEXT>

</DOC>