<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0107 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1852EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CitrusFreeze 1stLd-Writethru a0610 12-26 0794</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Citrus Freeze, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0610,0814</SECOND>
<HEAD>Growers Start Salvage Operations After Christmas Freeze</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto staffing</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS new 18th graf, `Nevertheless, commodities ...' to UPDATE
with orange juice futures prices soaring. SUBS last graf to UPDATE with
Citrus Commission saying it will not limit fruit shipments.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By IKE FLORES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ORLANDO, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A numbing Christmas freeze caused
widespread damage to Florida crops, but citrus growers were
optimistic Tuesday that trees suffered little damage and much of
the iced fruit can be turned into juice.
   Florida's third major killer freeze in six years was not
believed as disastrous to citrus as those in December 1983 and
January 1985.
   But near-total losses were reported in winter vegetables _ much
of it destined for Northeastern markets _ in large areas of the
state.
   Agriculture officials said it was too early to estimate the
financial losses. In some cases, the full extent of damage will not
be known for weeks or months.
   Elsewhere, Texas officials estimate 70 percent of that state's
citrus crop and 80 percent of the winter vegetable crop were
destroyed by the cold weather.
   Sleet, snow, rain and wind combined with temperatures ranging
from the teens to the high 20s throughout the Florida peninsula
during the weekend. The cold contributed to at least seven deaths
and caused burst water pipes and other problems for residents used
to sub-tropical December weather.
   The multibillion-dollar citrus industry was still recovering
from the earlier freezes that wiped out some 250,000 acres of trees.
   But many growers believed the major damage this time was
confined to the fruit.
   ``I don't think it was a tree-killing freeze,'' said Dan Gunter,
executive director of the Florida Department of Citrus.
   More than 80 percent of the citrus crop was still on the trees
when the cold arrived, and few groves escaped damage in the
700,000-acre citrus belt.
   Vegetables, strawberries, ornamental plants and other crops were
also hard hit.
   Florida Agriculture Commissioner Doyle Conner said there were
heavy losses of beans, squash, corn, tomatoes and watermelons. He
said he hoped enough citrus and vegetables could be salvaged to
maintain market supplies.
   ``With shortages, naturally prices will go up. I just hope that
we have enough fruit to keep a rather stable market because
everyone prefers to have product in the marketplace rather than
heavy limitations on supply and unreasonable prices,'' the
commissioner said.
   Central Florida growers said thousands of acres of carrots,
radishes, cauliflower and broccoli were destroyed and little would
be salvageable.
   The $1 billion foliage industry, one of the state's
fastest-growing agriculture commodities, suffered a minimum of 20
percent losses statewide, said Earl Wells, executive vice president
of the Florida Nurserymen and Growers Association.
   Almost 90 percent of the Florida orange crop goes into juice.
Gunter said the citrus industry had large stocks of juice
concentrate. That stock and the larger-than-normal Brazilian citrus
crop should stabilize juice prices somewhat, he said.
   ``Because of that, there might be a more moderate impact than we
might expect for a freeze year,'' Gunter said.
   Nevertheless, commodities traders sharply bid up the price of
orange juice futures Tuesday, speculating that the freeze would
cause a scramble for supplies. The January contract for frozen
concentrated orange juice rose 16.1 cents to $1.531 a pound on the
New York Cotton Exchange.
   Harvesting crews were out in force in bright, sunny weather
Tuesday. Citrus growers rushed to pick early and midseason oranges
and grapefruit and get them to processing plants to be turned into
juice before spoilage.
   Ironically, growers now hope the cool weather will stick around
for a week or so during the citrus harvesting and round-the-clock
processing. Temperatures forecast in the 60s and 70s later in the
week would hasten juice loss in the damaged fruit.
   Rapidly rising temperatures in Texas blocked efforts to salvage
frozen fruit for juice. Growers said they were dealt the fatal blow
Monday when temperatures shot into the mid-50s, reducing the frozen
fruit to mush.
   ``It appears to me even the canneries wouldn't accept it because
the fruit has been frozen so bad,'' said Joe Kutzenberger,
president of KY Farms in Harlingen, Texas. ``It's turning soft and
even bleeding through the skin of the fruit. I would say it's a
total loss.''
   Losses to Texas citrus industry are estimated at $200 million so
far and could top $500 million as trees begin to show effects from
the freeze, said David Galvan of the Texas Department of
Agriculture.
   The Florida Citrus Commission said Tuesday it would not invoke
emergency rules limiting shipments of fresh fruit that suffered
icing. Commission Chairman Bill Becker said the industry was
relying on the Florida Fruit and Vegetable Inspection Service,
affiliated with U.S. Department of Agriculture, to ensure the
quality of fresh-fruit shipments.
</TEXT>

</DOC>