<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1138EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Romania-Reaction     12-19 0421</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Reaction,0435</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Leaders, Newspapers Unite To Condemn Bloody Repression
^With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROLAND PRINZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Government leaders and newspapers
throughout Europe, displaying rare unison across East-West borders,
today denounced the Romanian government for its bloody repression
of weekend protests.
   Scores, perhaps hundreds, of people were reported killed when
Romanian security forces crushed anti-government demonstrations on
Saturday and Sunday, according to unconfirmed reports. Gunfire was
said to have also been heard today in Timisoara, 30 miles from the
Yugoslav border.
   Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard Shevardnadze, at a session with
some 200 members of the European Parliament in Brussels, said that
if reports of bloodshed are true, ``I can only express my very
profound regret.
   ``We are categorically opposed to the use of force,''
Shevardnadze said.
   There was no comment in Beijing, where the Chinese government
crushed a peaceful pro-democracy movement with tanks on June 4-5.
   In its first protest to another Soviet bloc country, the
Bulgarian government today expressed ``serious concern'' to the
Romanian Embassy in Sofia over the unilateral closure of the border.
   Romania closed its borders to all visitors, allowing in only
diplomats and others with official papers.
   Foreign ministers of the 12 European Community nations denounced
the violence to suppress the demonstrations. Several governments
summoned Romanian diplomats to protest.
   In Brussels, the 12 foreign ministers said in a statement the
regime of President Nicolae Ceausescu was ``turning its back on all
the commitments concerning human rights to which it has
subscribed.''
   In Poland, both Parliament and Nobel Prize winner Lech Walesa
unanimously denounced the human rights abuses and demanded Romania
stop the violence.
   The British government summoned Romanian Ambassador Stan Soare
to protest ``in the strongest possible terms'' about the violent
crackdown.
   A spokesman said Soare responded to the British protest by
``resorting to the tired old formula of alleging interference in
Romania's internal affairs.''
   ``We urgently called upon the Romanian government to end
policies of repression and allow their citizens to exercise their
fundamental human rights,'' the Foreign Office said.
   In neighboring Hungary, feelings ran high because as many as 1.7
million ethnic Hungarians live in Transylvania in the western part
of Romania.
   ``Anachronistic regimes opposed to progress cannot remain in
place'' if Europe is to be united, liberal Hungarian Premier Miklos
Nemeth said.
   ``History has already witnessed the reign of regimes, not so
long ago, that showed off their strength with tanks before being
overthrown by the rage of the people,'' the Hungarian Socialist
Party newspaper Nepszabadsag said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>