<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0191 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1930EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Panama 3rdLd-Writethru   12-22 0832</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Panama, 3rd Ld-Writethru,a0808,880</SECOND>
<HEAD>New troops on the way to Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Combines pvs material in a0808 and a0761</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM RAUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Pentagon ordered 2,000 additional Army
soldiers airlifted to still-chaotic Panama late Friday, a source
said, as President Bush shrugged off a Latin American appeal to end
the U.S. intervention and declared the troops would stay ``to do
what is necessary.''
   ``The decision has been made'' to bolster roughly 24,000 U.S.
troops already on the ground trying to quell the resistance being
offered by forces loyal to deposed dictator Manuel Antonio Noriega,
said the Pentagon source, speaking on condition of anonymity.
   ``The movement will be taking place in the near future,'' he
added.
   Renewed resistance in Panama City also prompted the Pentagon to
give a new estimate of up to 10 more days for American forces to
seize complete control of Panama's capital city.
   Earlier, Lt. Gen. Tom Kelly, director of operations for the
Joint Chiefs of Staff, said, ``We are looking to bring more troops
in. We are also looking at re-establishing the police force.''
   Meanwhile, in an indication the Army was settling in, military
officials also convened their first press briefing at the Southern
Command in Panama.
   In Washington, Bush told Congress in a formal notification
abiding by the War Powers Act that it was impossible to predict the
``scope and duration'' of the U.S. intervention.
   He underscored his support for the new government of Guillermo
Endara by welcoming Endara's ambassador, Carlos Rodriguez, in the
Oval Office.
   The administration also offered what it said was new evidence of
drug dealings by _ including a 110 pound stash of cocaine found
near Noriega's private office at a military barracks.
   Also uncovered at other locations were an arsenal of more than
5,000 weapons, a picture of Adolf Hitler and a bizarre assortment
of occult and witchcraft paraphernalia, according to U.S. officials.
   Noriega himself continued to elude U.S. forces.
   ``We continue to receive reports ... and the search continues,''
presidential press secretary Marlin Fitzwater said of the deposed
general who faces drug-trafficking charges in the United States.
   The administration dismissed a vote by the Organization of
American States deploring the U.S. invasion and calling for an
immediate withdrawal. The OAS vote was 20-1, with the United States
casting the lone ``no'' vote. Six nations abstained.
   ``I don't think we're surprised that the OAS would take this
position,'' Fitzwater said, adding that the administration thinks
``that eventually the countries of Latin America will recognize and
support the new government.''
   Privately, he suggested, some Latin American leaders have been
more supportive.
   Bush mentioned the continuing chaos in Panama during a speech on
AIDS at the National Institutes of Health, saying: ``We sorrow at
the casualties in Panama, but we know nothing is more crucial to
peace on earth than freedom and democracy.''
   With American troops under fire at Christmastime, Bush told his
audience, ``I assure you that through these holidays we will not
forget our brave soldiers down there and their families.''
   ``We will continue to do what is necessary to help the people of
Panama achieve the democratic society that they voted for and that
they so rightfully deserve,'' Bush said.
   After the midday speech, Bush flew by helicopter to the
presidential retreat at Camp David, Md., where he will remain
through Christmas.
   Aides said that Bush would keep in touch on developments in
Panama by phone.
   On Sunday, Bush will deliver a holiday message to U.S. Armed
Forces worldwide over the Armed Forces Radio Network. A week later,
on Sunday Dec. 31, he will visit wounded soldiers who have been
flown from Panama to Lackland Air Force Base and at Fort Sam
Houston, both near San Antonio.
   Early Friday, Bush formally notified Congress of his reasons for
ordering the military assault.
   While asserting that the worst fighting had ended, Bush told
Congress, ``It is not possible at this time to predict the precise
scope and duration of the military operations or how long the
temporary increase of U.S. forces in Panama will be required.''
   Bush's notice to Congress complied with the War Powers Act,
which requires formal notification any time U.S. military forces
are sent into action. The administration contends the act is
unconstitutional, but follows it anyway.
   In his written message, Bush accused Noriega of directing
``vicious and brutal acts'' against Americans and asserted that the
lives and welfare of U.S. citizens had been ``increasingly at
risk.''
   He also said that Noriega's action had threatened the operation
of the Panama Canal, which the United States is under treaty
obligation to turn over to Panama in the year 2000.
   At the Southern Command headquarters in Panama City, Gen.
Maxwell Thurman delivered a lengthy denunciation of Noriega,
depicting him as a drug trafficker who had a picture Hitler in his
closet and pornography in his desk.
   Thurman said Noriega had been organizing a terrorist force with
the possible goal of taking over the Panama Canal.
</TEXT>

</DOC>