<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0130EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AIDS-Discrimination Bjt   12-22 0537</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AIDS-Discrimination, Bjt,0551</SECOND>
<HEAD>Concern for Patients' Rights Called Critical in AIDS Fight</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RAEBURN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Editor</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Successes and failures in the war against AIDS
show that concern for patients' rights is essential if health
authorities hope to stem the epidemic, the director of the World
Health Organization's AIDS program says.
   In an interview Thursday, Dr. Jonathan Mann said many of the
discriminatory laws put in place during the initial panic earlier
in the '80s have been repealed as governments discovered the laws
were impeding efforts to fight the disease's spread.
   ``We made a big discovery during the 1980s that ranks right up
there with the discovery of the virus and the modes of spread,''
Mann said by telephone from Geneva. ``And that discovery is that to
fight this global epidemic of infectious disease, you must also
fight against prejudice and discrimination.''
   Health officials have been successful in curbing risky sexual
behavior among homosexual men in San Francisco and among female
prostitutes in Nairobi, Kenya and Peru, among other places, Mann
said.
   ``All of those programs have in common ... the careful attention
to developing a supportive social environment that refuses
discrimination against infected people,'' he said. ``We've realized
that in order to fight successfully against AIDS, it is vital to
protect the rights and dignity of people.''
   Mann said that more than 35 countries, including the United
States, passed laws in the 1980s restricting immigration by people
infected with the human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) that causes
acquired immune deficiency syndrome.
   Other countries, including the Soviet Union, South Korea and
Iraq established mandatory screening for HIV infection. Some,
including China, South Africa and Chile, passed laws that require
the isolation of people infected with HIV, Mann said.
   ``In Cuba, when people were found to be infected, they were
asked to leave their home and their job and go to a renovated
hospital on the outskirts of Havana where they were given a salary
but were basically `kept,''' Mann said.
   Such laws have crippled efforts to block the spread of AIDS, he
said.
   ``If you knew that being tested for HIV infection could result
in your having to leave your family, lose your job, and in every
other way be separated from society, would you be tested?''
   Mann noted that Illinois and Louisiana recently repealed laws
requiring AIDS tests for couples seeking marriage licenses,
concluding that the laws were ineffective and wasteful.
   Costa Rica repealed a law requiring that foreign sailors display
a certificate showing they were free of AIDS before they could come
ashore.
   ``It sounds like good sense, superficially, to `build a wall'
around a country and say everybody who comes into this country has
to be tested for HIV infection,'' Mann said. ``Then you get into
the realities.''
   In 1987, a group of experts convened by the World Health
Organization concluded that HIV screening for international
travelers ``would at best _ and at great cost _ retard only briefly
the dissemination of HIV both globally and with respect to any
particular country.''
   ``A virus, a disease, doesn't respect walls,'' Mann said. ``As
the Berlin Wall has shown, walls don't protect people; they
actually endanger the people within the walls.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>