<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0091 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1416EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-CommuterPlaneCrash 2ndLd-Writethru a0483 12-27 0419</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Commuter Plane Crash, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0483,0426</SECOND>
<HEAD>Six Reported Killed in Plane Crash</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS grafs 6-8 bgng `The year-old...' with 4 grafs to UPDATE
with identities of five of six dead and comments from United Express president's
news conference. Picks up 9th graf, `Belmondo said...' SUBS penultimate
graf, `The commuter...' to CORRECT to 25 sted 23 planes in fleet.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES L. ENG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASCO, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A twin-engine commuter plane crashed and
burst into flames after trying to land at an airport, killing the
six people aboard, authorities said.
   The United Express plane went down 100 feet short of a runway at
the Tri-Cities Airport, said Dave Duff, a Federal Aviation
Administration spokesman in Seattle.
   Visibility was seven miles and winds were calm when the
Jetstream turbo prop went down at 10:30 p.m. Tuesday, Duff said.
   The plane apparently split in half on impact and fire broke out
in the forward section about one minute later, Duff said.
   One of the first to reach the scene was firefighter Dave Bickle,
who said he ``didn't know how anybody could have survived. It was a
ball of flame.''
   The year-old aircraft had a two-man crew, Capt. Barry ``Will''
Roberts, 38, and First Officer Doug McInroe, 25, both of Kennewick,
said Craig Belmondo, president of the airline.
   Belmondo said the passengers included Kim Shewmaker of Richland,
a United Express pilot; Rey Resendez of Duncanville, Texas; and W.
Kingry of Denver. Kingry's first name was not available and the
identity of the sixth victim was being withheld pending
notification of relatives. All passengers were male, Belmondo said,
correcting a report that a woman was on board.
   Belmondo estimated the plane crashed 500 to 700 feet short of
the runway and said it plowed into a sagebrush field where it burst
into flames.
   He said he could not speculate on the cause of the crash.
   Belmondo said there had been no reports of problems during the
flight from Seattle to Pasco via Yakima.
   United Express is one of five commuter airlines of the same name
around the country operating under a marketing agreement with
United Airlines. It uses the United logo and acts as a feeder
service to the larger airline.
   The commuter airline is based in this town 180 miles southeast
of Seattle. It serves Washington state, Oregon, Idaho and Montana
and had a fleet of 25 planes.
   The Jetstream is built by British Aerospace and can hold 21
people, said Randy Lanfell, a United Express pilot.
</TEXT>

</DOC>