<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0210 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1206EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--Briefs Adv25   12-21 0567</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Briefs, Adv 25,0582</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv25</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Monday, Dec. 25, and thereafter</HEAD>
<UNK>Franklin Institute To Offer $250,000 Annual Science Award</UNK>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Franklin Institute is looking for a few
good scientists _ to nominate an even better one to be the first
recipient of a new $250,000 annual prize for research benefitting
humanity.
   ``We will be searching for a scientist who, in the spirit of
Benjamin Franklin, has made a discovery that is beneficial to
mankind,'' said Benjamin Franklin National Memorial Executive
Director Larry Tise. ``We will be conducting a worldwide search to
find the right person.''
   The Bower Award for Science will begin next year through a $7.4
million bequest from Henry Bower, a Philadelphia chemical
manufacturer who died last year. A second award will go for
excellence in business leadership.
   ``We hope that the Bower Awards will be recognized as American
prizes comparable to the Nobel Prizes in international prestige,''
said Charles L. Andes, chairman of the institute's board of
trustees.
   Among those who have agreed to help find science candidates are
Erich Bloch, head of the National Science Foundation; Peter
Goldmark Jr., president of the Rockefeller Foundation; Zhou
Guangzhao, president of the Chinese Academy of Sciences; M.G.K.
Menon, science adviser to India's prime minister; and University of
Pennsylvania engineering school dean Barry Dean.
   Tise said a special effort would be made to find a Third World
scientist.
   Deadlines for nominations for the 1990 prizes is April 17, the
bicentennial of Franklin's death. The winners will be announced in
September and honored in November in three days of ceremonies in
Philadelphia.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Study Concludes Depression Interferes With Parenting</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SALT LAKE CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Babies of depressed women cry more and are
less responsive to their mothers, who in turn are less
affectionate, less sensitive and less attached to their babies, a
psychological researcher says.
   About 26 percent of American women experience a major depression
some time during their lives, and depression seems to be hitting
earlier, when the likely have small children, said University of
Utah psychologist Donna M. Gelfand.
   Gelfand's findings compared 41 depressed mothers who had 3- to
12-month-old babies with 40 non-depressed mothers. The depressed
women were referred by area clinics and therapists; non-depressed
women were chosen from a birth registry.
   Researchers who weren't informed which women were depressed made
three home visits to each, asking questions and observing
interactions with their babies.
   The depressed women were less attached to their babies, less
affectionate and less sensitive to babies' needs, Gelfand said.
They also gave conflicting emotional messages more and gave their
babies lower ratings than did the non-depressed group for being
lively and alert. In one extreme case, a mother was so inattentive
she didn't notice her baby had fallen off her lap. Depressed
mothers lacked confidence in their own effectiveness as parents.
   Depressed mothers tended to issue strict prohibitions instead of
showing or telling the child what to do, she said. This baffles
children, who can't make sense of it, and makes their environment
seem capricious. The child may respond by being fussy and resisting
parents' directives. The child's responses add to the woman's
feeling that she's not a good mother.
   In the second phase of the research, public health nurses are
visiting the mothers weekly for six months to demonstrate methods
of care and discipline, answer questions and provide social support.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Dec. 25</NOTE>

</DOC>