<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1000EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Panama 3rdLd-Writethru   12-25 0958</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama, 3rd Ld-Writethru,a0494,0992</SECOND>
<HEAD>Noriega Takes Asylum at Vatican Embassy</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: New thruout to ADD Vatican comment, seizure of town, new casualty
count. No pickup.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY9,10,11</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOSEPH B. FRAZIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. troops and armored vehicles
ringed the Vatican Embassy early today after deposed strongman Gen.
Manuel Antonio Noriega took refuge there and asked for political
asylum.
   American troops captured the town of Santiago southwest of
Panama City, but otherwise fighting died down as Christmas came to
Panama.
   About 40 soldiers kept watch in the pre-dawn darkness as a
helicopter, its running lights turned off, landed several times
across the street from the Vatican Embassy, then took off. The
chopper was not seen picking up or dropping off anyone.
   The Vatican, in its first official statement on the situation,
said today that Noriega took refuge in the embassy Sunday after
expressing ``the will to end the conflict'' between his supporters
and the United States.
   Vatican spokesman Joaquin Navarro said it was too early to say
if Noriega would be handed over to the United States, where he
faces drug charges, or given passage to another country.
   Under international law, embassies are sacrosanct ground and
U.S. troops cannot legally enter the papal embassy to arrest
Noriega.
   Earlier, an official at the Vatican said he doubted the embassy
would immediately turn Noriega over to the United States.
   Panamanians banged pots and pans and cheered when word of
Noriega's surrender spread through the capital, littered with glass
and looted bare after five days of fighting.
   The American invasion, which began at midnight Tuesday, has
killed at least 23 American soldiers and two American civilians,
and nearly 300 Panamanians, according to U.S. figures announced
today. Many Panamanian victims are believed to be civilians.
   Lt. Col. Jerry Murguia told reporters at a Southern Command
briefing today that American troops had captured Santiago, 120
miles southwest of Panama City, taking 188 prisoners and seizing
several hundred small arms.
   ``It was a quiet night. That's the good news,'' he said.
   There was little else to celebrate in this mainly Roman Catholic
country.
   ``What am I going to tell my 6-year-old daughter? I cannot tell
her Santa Claus was killed by a bomb,'' said one woman in a
middle-class neighborhood Christmas Eve.
   Residents roamed their neighborhoods, cleaned glass and trash
off streets and put up Christmas lights.
   Noriega drove himself or was driven to the embassy in a car at
about 3 p.m. Sunday, an informed military source said. None of the
26,000 American troops searching for Noriega in this Central
American country was at the embassy at the time.
   American soldiers had surrounded the Nicaraguan and Cuban
embassies after rumors Noriega might seek refuge there.
   Navarro rejected the idea the Vatican was ``embarrassed'' by
Noriega's decision to seek refuge at its embassy and depicted it as
an opportunity to bring peace to the country.
   ``I can announce with satisfaction that the conflict in Panama
seems to be nearing a solution without further shedding of blood,''
he said in a four-paragraph statement. ``And this is good news for
Christmas Day.''
   White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said the United States
would continue to seek ways to bring Noriega to the United States.
Asked if anyone would get the $1 million reward the Bush
administration offered for Noriega's capture, Fitzwater said, ``No,
I don't think so.''
   Gen. Maxwell Thurman, chief of the U.S. Southern Command, said
he ordered the Vatican Embassy surrounded after Noriega's surrender
to prevent Noriega supporters from ``blowing into the place. I
would not want them to come with an armored car and blow their way
into the embassy.''
   Noriega surfaced a few hours after three high-ranking members of
his Defense Forces surrendered and another pledged loyalty to the
U.S.-backed government.
   Witnesses said they saw several Noriega officials, including
former acting president Manuel Solis Palma, entering the embassy.
   The Italian news agency ANSA reported from Panama City that 32
people had sought asylum from the Vatican, including high officials
of the Panamanian Defense Forces and political parties of the
Noriega regime.
   Panamanians cheered as word spread that Noriega had turned
himself in. Hundreds congregated at the embassy.
   ``The man has fallen! He is gone!'' some shouted.
   A radio station went on the air with a nationalistic song called
``Patria'' (Fatherland), written and sung by Panamanian Ruben
Blades.
   ``Now we can have Christmas!' said one man in Panama City as he
grabbed a friend and hugged him. ``I don't have a turkey in the
house, we don't even have any hamburger. All we have is a can of
sardines, but what the hell!''
   Food and medical supplies were in short supply, and stores were
ransacked by looters.
   Combat from Noriega loyalists dwindled Sunday, but there was
fighting in the working-class San Miguelito district, one of those
where the pro-Noriega paramilitary Dignity Battalions are strongest.
   Thurman estimated the battalions number about 1,800. They have
been joined by an unknown number of Noriega's original
15,000-member Defense Forces.
   Murguia said today that 23 U.S. soldiers had been killed and 285
wounded since the invasion began. The Pentagon on Sunday said 25
U.S. soldiers were killed. It then changed that figure to 24,
saying one death had been counted twice.
   Murguia, in announcing his figures, said two deaths were counted
twice.
   The latest figures no longer listed a soldier as missing.
   Pentagon officials also said two American civilians had been
killed.
   Murguia said 290 ``enemy'' troops had been killed, 121 wounded
and 3,780 captured. It was not clear whether the figures included
both Defense Forces and Dignity Brigade personnel.
   Dr. Elmer Miranda, director of Santo Tomas Hospital, put the
Panamanian death toll at 260 and said many victims were civilians.
</TEXT>

</DOC>