<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0259EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     12-21 0337</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0352</SECOND>
<HEAD>On the Light Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATLANTIC CITY, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Rolling Stones got
short-circuited for more than three minutes during their
pay-per-view concert, depriving their TV fans of a little bit of
``Satisfaction.''
   A technical difficulty in the time delay transmission of
Tuesday's pay-per-view audio signal produced a network outage of
three minutes and nine seconds just after 10:59 p.m. EST, said
Brian Lewis, a spokesman for Set Pay Per View, the distributors of
the show.
   ``It affected the last minute and a half of `Satisfaction' and
some crowd scenes,'' Lewis said.
   ``Satisfaction'' is the next-to-last song of the Stones'
concerts on the ``Steel Wheels'' tour, which ended its 32-city run
Wednesday in Atlantic City.
   Lewis said the outage would not affect the replay of the repeat
pay-per-view telecasts scheduled for Saturday.
   Suzan Couch, another spokeswoman for the distributor, said each
of the 815 cable companies receiving the program would have to
decide whether to refund any of their customers' money.
   Pay-per-view prices ranged from $19.95 to $24.95.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>MIAMI BEACH, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rembrandt she's not, but 43-year-old
Calixto War is good enough with crayons to fool the U.S. Postal
Service.
   Using yellow, brown, and magenta crayons, Ms. War recently drew
her rendition of the Postal Service's tyrannosaurus dinosaur stamp
in the upper right-hand corner of an envelope.
   Then, she mailed it to a columnist for The Miami Herald.
   ``It's a simple idea. No big deal,'' said Ms. War, who works
part time in a plant nursery. ``I do these; they never notice.''
   Counterfeiting stamps is a crime, but prosecuting someone like
Ms. War is unlikely, said Postal Service spokesman Lou Eberhardt in
Washington.
   The post office has won felony convictions against larger rings
that wash and recycle used stamps ``to the tune of millions of
dollars,'' but it can't do much to stop an occasional counterfeiter
like Ms. War from slipping past scanning machines, Eberhardt said.
   ``We'd be hard pressed to get a U.S. attorney to take it to
court,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>