<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0155 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0740EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WKD--TurntableTips 1stADD   12-28 0310</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--Turntable Tips, 1st ADD,0356</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv29</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Friday, Dec. 29, and thereafter</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   COUNTRY SINGLES
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   1.``Who's Lonely Now'' Highway 101 (Warner Bros.)
   2.``Out of Your Shoes'' Lorrie Morgan (RCA)
   3.``Til I Can't Take It Anymore'' Billy Joe Royal (Atlantic)
   4.``It Ain't Nothin''' Keith Whitley (RCA)
   5.``Many a Long and Lonesome Highway'' Rodney Crowell (Columbia)
   6.``She's Gone, Gone, Gone'' Glen Campbell (Universal)
   7.``That Just About Does It'' Vern Gosdin (Columbia)
   8.``It's You Again'' Skip Ewing (MCA)
   9.``My Arms Stay Open All Night'' Tanya Tucker (Capitol)
   10.``There You Are'' Willie Nelson (Columbia)
   11.``Nobody's Home'' Clint Black (RCA)
   12.``Simple Man'' The Charlie Daniels Band (Epic)
   13.``When It's Gone'' Nitty Gritty Dirt Band (Universal)
   14.``When I Could Come Home To You'' Steve Wariner (MCA)
   15.``A Woman in Love'' Ronnie Milsap (RCA)
   16.``In My Eyes'' Lionel Cartwright (MCA)
   17.``Start All Over Again'' The Desert Rose Band (MCA-Curb)
   18.``Statue of a Fool'' Ricky Van Shelton (Columbia)
   19.``One Man Woman'' The Judds (Curb-RCA)
   20.``I Can't Turn the Tide'' Baillie and the Boys (RCA)
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ADULT CONTEMPORARY SINGLES
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   1.``How Am I Supposed to Live Without You'' M. Bolton (Columbia)
   2.``Another Day in Paradise'' Phil Collins (Atlantic)
   3.``Sacrifice'' Elton John (MCA)
   4.``Downtown Train'' Rod Stewart (Warner Bros.)
   5.``The Last Worthless Evening'' Don Henley (Geffen)
   6.``Walk On By'' Melissa Manchester (MCA)
   7.``Don't Know Much'' Linda Ronstadt &amp; Aaron Neville (Elektra)
   8.``Leave a Light On'' Belinda Carlisle (MCA)
   9.``Here We Are'' Gloria Estefan (Epic)
   10.``Angelia'' Richard Marx (EMI)
   11.``The Way to Your Heart'' Soulsister (EMI)
   12.``Everything'' Jody Watley (MCA)
   13.``Just Like Jesse James'' Cher (Geffen)
   14.``Bring It All Back'' Grayson Hugh (RCA)
   15.``When I See You Smile'' Bad English (Epic)
   16.``What Kind of Man Would I Be?'' Chicago (Reprise)
   17.``We Didn't Start the Fire'' Billy Joel (Columbia)
   18.``Just Between You and Me'' Lou Gramm (Atlantic)
   19.``The Same Love'' The Jets (MCA)
   20.``Listen to Your Heart'' Roxette (EMI)
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   MORE
</TEXT>

</DOC>