<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0176 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0743EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Baxter-HCA     12-28 0475</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Baxter-HCA,0496</SECOND>
<HEAD>Baxter Signs $2.5 Billion Supply Pact With HCA Hospital Companies</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID DISHNEAU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Baxter Healthcare Corp. is continuing its
medical-supply relationship with the Hospital Corp. of America _
but there's a twist.
   The company that was HCA is now three companies, and Baxter has
signed contracts with them all. The $2.5 billion deal covers more
than 450 hospitals nationwide.
   Under separate contracts that become effective Jan. 1, Baxter
will provide products and services for six years to HCA,
HealthTrust Inc. and HCA Management Co. Together, they own or
manage 452 hospitals nationwide.
   HealthTrust and HCA Management are former HCA units that became
independent companies through a reorganization completed in the
four years since HCA's original contract with Baxter.
   That contract, a five-year pact worth $1.25 billion, was due to
expire at the end of 1990, Baxter spokesman Geoffrey Fenton said.
   The new contracts replace and expand upon the old one, providing
products and services that meet the different needs of the new
companies, Fenton said.
   HCA owns and operates 78 U.S. medical-surgical hospitals and 53
psychiatric facilities.
   HealthTrust, a network of 93 former HCA hospitals, was formed in
1987 through an employee stock ownership plan.
   HCA Management became independent this year when HCA sold the
unit to a holding company formed by a group led by senior managment
and the New York-based investment firm Welsh, Carson, Anderson and
Stowe.
   Fenton said the company manages 228 hospitals.
   Baxter, based in Deerfield, Ill., outside Chicago, manufactures
a wide range of healthcare products including medical and surgical
supplies, intravenous fluids and diagnostic equipment.
   Baxter also offers inventory management and strategic planning
services.
   HCA's initial contract with Baxter was an outgrowth of their
1985 battle for American Hospital Supply Corp. American Hospital
Supply had agreed to merge with HCA but Baxter offered more money
and bought the company for $3.7 billion.
   Baxter paid HCA $150 million to terminate the merger agreement
and HCA agreed to buy $250 million worth of Baxter products
annually for five years.
   ``We've been very satisfied with the products and services we've
received during this term so once we went through the divestiture,
we asked to renegotiate,'' said David McFadden, an HCA spokesman.
   In 1988 Baxter signed its largest supply agreement, a 5{-year
pact worth up to $6.4 billion with American Healthcare Systems, a
group of more than 1,000 healthcare facilities.
   Baxter also has multi-year supply agreements with the Daughters
of Charity National Health System and Massachusetts General
Hospital.
   Baxter Healthcare is the principle U.S. operating company of
Baxter International Inc., the world's leading manufacturer and
marketer of healthcare products and services.
   Baxter International reported 1988 net income of $388 million on
sales of $6.9 billion. Through the first three quarters of 1989,
Baxter had net income of $307 million on sales of $5.4 billion.
</TEXT>

</DOC>