<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0229 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1541EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WKD--VideoView Adv00   12-18 0566</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--Video View, Adv 00,0589</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv00</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Anytime</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WEEKEND ENTERTAINMENT AND ARTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Video View: Home Video News and Reviews</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETE BROWN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   ``License to Kill'' (CBS-Fox Video. VHS-Beta, $89.98. Rated
PG-13)
   
   Bond _ James Bond _ is a grim figure in ``Licence to Kill,'' in
which the secret agent takes on a murderous Latin drug lord in
Florida and Latin America. While earlier 007 films offered a sly,
roguish charmer given to jaunty double entrendres, ``Licence to
Kill'' serves up a moody, humorless Bond.
   Which is to say, no Bond at all. Bond, played by Timothy Dalton
in his second 007 film, is upstaged this time by the gadgetry and
special effects.
   Worse, not even the villain lives up to the usual standards.
While previous villains were often megalomaniacs who wanted nothing
less than the entire world, Sanchez _ played with reptilian charm
by pockmarked Robert Davi _ is a bad guy of almost real-life
proportions. He's not much worse than some of the drug lords making
headlines these days.
   In place of Bond, ``Licence to Kill'' offers lots of violence,
including a few gruesomely creative ways to die, and the usual
fiendish weapons, as unveiled by gadget scientist Q.
   Davi is so believable that his character comes off as
conventional. Talisa Soto is perfectly wooden as Sanchez's _ and
later Bond's _ love interest, and Carey Lowell plays an agent whose
most alluring quality is the way she keeps her gun in a thigh
garter.
   But without a compelling Bond, ``License to Kill'' rarely rises
above the level of a good episode of ``Miami Vice.''
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   
   ``Road House'' (MGM-UA Home Video. VHS-Beta, $89.95. Rated R)
   
   The Double Deuce is a down and dirty bar where the low-rent
patrons mix it up at the slightest provocation, a toilet of a place
so mean that someone hits a blind guitarist in the face with a
bottle. Then comes Dalton (Patrick Swayze).
   Dalton _ a bouncer with fists of steel, Zen-like calm and a
philosophy degree from New York University _ weeds out the
undesirables among his bouncers, schools them in self-restraint and
has the place looking like a yuppie nightspot in no time.
   But in doing so he runs afoul of Brad Wesley, a high-class thug
who bleeds local merchants for protection money and at one point
flips a coin to decide who will live and who will die.
   This is a violent tale as simple-minded as a comic book, and
this bouncer-with-a-brain stuff is a little much.
   But ``Road House'' is packed with action and rollicks along to a
rip-roaring ending.
   Swayze (``Dirty Dancing'') gets the job done as a sort of
next-generation, shirtless Clint Eastwood, playing a squinty-eyed
loner from out of town who takes on the local bully. Ben Gazzara is
a stylishly evil Wesley.
   ``Road House.'' See it in the safety of your own home.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Motion Picture Association of America rating definitions:
   G _ General audiences. All ages admitted.
   PG _ Parental guidance suggested. Some material may not be
suitable for children.
   PG-13 _ Special parental guidance strongly suggested for
children under 13. Some material may be inappropriate for young
children.
   R _ Restricted. Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult
guardian.
   X _ No one under 17 admitted. Some states may have higher age
restrictions.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Release Anytime</NOTE>

</DOC>