<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0156 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2106EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Germany-SummitHighlights     12-19 0294</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Germany-Summit Highlights,0301</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kohl-Modrow Summit Produces Sheaf of Agreements</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-East Germany</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DRESDEN, East Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Following are the agreements
announced after Tuesday's summit between East German Premier Hans
Modrow and West German Chancellor Helmut Kohl:
   _ The two German states will negotiate a ``Treaty Community''
relationship, which would recognize the sovereignty of both nations
and facilitate closer political and economic ties.
   _ An economic cooperation agreement has been signed and a joint
committee established to determine how West German aid should be
used to help East Germany recover and boost production.
   _ The East German government will open a pedestrian crossing
through the Berlin Wall at the historic Brandenburg Gate before
Christmas.
   _ Visa-free travel for West Germans and an end to the forced
exchange of at least 25 marks ($14.50) per day will take effect on
Dec. 24, instead of Jan. 1 as announced earlier.
   _ West Germans will be allowed to change their convertible West
German marks at a rate of 1:3 for the non-convertible East marks
after Jan. 1. All official exchanges had been fixed at 1:1 to date.
   _ East Germany will work to change regulations to allow all
interested airlines to fly to West Berlin outside the Allied
prescribed corridors. Only British, French and American airlines
have been allowed to use the corridors to West Berlin's Tegel
Airport.
   _ West German credit guarantees for exports to East Germany will
be raised from 4.5 billion to 6 billion marks ($2.6 billion to $3.5
billion), to ensure delivery of goods to the economically strapped
socialist state.
   _ West Germany's contribution to the East German communications
network will be raised from 200 million to 300 million marks ($116
million to $173 million) annually, to rebuild the nation's
telephone system.
</TEXT>

</DOC>