<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0086 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1246EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Jews     12-18 0615</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Jews,0634</SECOND>
<HEAD>Conference of Soviet Jews Opens in Moscow</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN IAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jewish leaders from across the Soviet Union
gathered Monday for the first major conference since Lenin's time
to create a national council and formally renew ties with the
global Jewish community.
   As the conference opened, about 60 jeering members of the
Russian nationalist Pamyat Society demonstrated across the street
from the Cinema Center and jostled delegates as they attempted to
enter the hall. They waved signs saying, ``Zionists Out of the
U.S.S.R.'' and ``Jews, Get Out of the Union.'' Police stood by, but
did nothing to break up the demonstrators who dispersed after about
an hour, witnesses said.
   The three-day meeting, organized by more than 160 Jewish
organizations in 75 cities, marked the first time since 1920 that
Jewish leaders were allowed to congregate openly to establish a
national organization.
   The country's biggest Jewish group, the Jewish Bund, was founded
by Jewish socialists in 1897 but disbanded in 1920.
   Jewish emigres, deputies from the Soviet parliament and about
150 Jewish leaders from the West were among the 650 people at the
conference in the state-owned Cinema Center in central Moscow.
   ``I never thought I would be back in the Soviet Union or see
Jews meeting in the center of Moscow in an official hall to create
the first national Jewish body,'' said Shmuel Azarkh, who emigrated
in 1981 and lives in Israel.
   Azarkh, an aide to former dissident Natan Sharansky who was
denied a Soviet visa in Israel to attend the conference, said
President Mikhail S. Gorbachev's reforms have helped improve life
for Soviet Jews, but have not gone far enough.
   ``When the leader of perestroika does not permit the visa, it
means the country is still far from real democracy,'' he said.
   But, he added: ``This kind of conference will lead the way for
the beginning of a new Jewish community which was destroyed 70
years ago.''
   Leonid Shkolnik, a member of the Congress of People's Deputies
and a former editor in chief of the Jewish newspaper Birobidzhan
Stern, said the conference was an important milestone for the
country's estimated 2 million Jews.
   He said the conference, with one stated goal of ``uniting Soviet
Jews and firmly establishing their roots,'' was long overdue.
   Shkolnik was one of 200 deputies who at the first Congress of
People's Deputies session last summer signed a letter to Gorbachev
demanding that anti-Semitism be put on the agenda of the Congress.
So far, he said, there has been no reply.
   Grigory Kanovich, another national Congress deputy, said the
demonstration outside the hall was deplorable, but that hidden
anti-Semitism was worse.
   ``Pamyat is not dangerous; anonymous anti-Semitism is
dangerous,'' he said. ``Those who don't declare they are
anti-Semites cannot be counted and cannot be controlled.''
   Conference officials said they expect to adopt a resolution
naming representatives to international Jewish groups such as the
World Jewish Congress.
   Anti-Semitism, emigration and the development of Jewish culture
are on the agenda.
   ``This conference will give a new push to Jewish life in the
U.S.S.R., Kanovich said. ``It will let them realize their Jewish
roots.''
   Among the delegates were two members of a group of 15 who have
begun a week-long hunger strike to press demands that Israel issue
them invitations so they can emigrate.
   Igor Torick said he had been waiting more than a year for an
invitation, necessary before Soviets can apply for an exit visa.
   He said it was the right of every Jew ``to return to his
motherland anytime.'' For his group, he said, no invitations were
being issued. ``They are refusing us our rights of life and
return,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>