<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0174 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1347EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a AM-ReligionRdp Adv22   12-19 0642</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Religion Rdp, Adv 22,0666</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv22</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Friday AMs, Dec. 22, and thereafter</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first Roman Catholic Mass from the Soviet
Union to be telecast in the United States will be carried Christmas
Eve by the Vision Interfaith Satellite Network.
   Jeff Weber, program vice president for the cable system, said
the service from Vilnius Cathedral in Lithuania would be presented
at 9 p.m. EST on Sunday, and repeated Christmas Day at 5 p.m.
   The Mass is to be celebrated by Archbishop Julionas
Steponovicius of Vilnius, believed to have been secretly made a
cardinal by Pope John Paul II in 1979. He was allowed to resume his
church duties only a year ago.
   The 14th century Vilnius Cathedral, known as the ``cradle of
Lithuanian Christianity,'' was seized by Soviet authorities in the
1950s and converted into a secular gallery, but was returned to the
church early this year.
   VISN is operated by a consortium of 22 faith groups in the
Eastern Orthodox, Jewish, Roman Catholic and Protestant religions.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The policy-making general board of the
American Baptist Churches has urged the federal government to
re-establish full diplomatic relations with Cuba and to lift the
trade embargo on the country.
   The board also urged a halt to U.S. military aid to El Salvador.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>GENEVA, Switzerland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Amid the injustices in the world and
wasteful exploitation of nature, the World Council of Churches
general secretary says Christmas raises a beacon of hope.
   The Rev. Emilio Castro said in a holiday message:
   ``God in Christ has established forever a token of encouragement
to which all can turn who hunger and thirst for justice, a promise
of peace for all those who are peacemakers, and ... an objective
vision of all who struggle for justice, peace and the integrity of
creation.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CHAPPAQUA, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Randall A. Terry of Binghamton, N.Y., who
founded the ``Operation Rescue'' anti-abortion movement, has been
honored by Christian Herald magazine with its annual ``James 1:22
Award'' as a leading ``doer of the Word'' in 1989.
   His ``controversial and dramatic tactics have forced Christians
to either join the fight over abortion or turn their backs on the
babies and mothers,'' said Bob Cuivala, editor of the 113-year-old
evangelical magazine.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Soviet Union is sponsoring its first
conference on Jewish history in more than 40 years, says one of the
participants, Rabbi Ishmar Schorsch, chancellor of the Jewish
Theological Seminary of America.
   ``We are afforded a unique opportunity to facilitate a Jewish
renaissance in the Soviet Union,'' he said of the conference, which
will be Dec. 25-27 in Moscow.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>MILWAUKEE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Roman Catholic Archbishop Rembert Weakland said
he will hold hearings to gather women's views on abortion.
   He wrote in the Milwaukee archdiocese's newspaper, Catholic
Herald, that he hoped ``a more systematic hearing and listening
process ... will help me understand and articulate better my own
moral insights'' on abortion.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   People have an extra reason for celebrating
Christmas this year _ the end of the Cold War between West and
East, says the president of the United Methodist Council of Bishops.
   Declaring the year has seen the ``unfolding of events in the
family of nations which hold the promise of a truly better day for
humankind,'' Bishop Jack Tuell of Los Angeles said in a Christmas
message:
   ``Long-standing repressive regimes have yielded to the cries of
the people for a fuller measure of the freedom and dignity with
which God has endowed all of humanity.
   ``Groups long separated by artificail political barriers now are
coming together to form new relationships of community and
cooperation. The God who is the God of peace and justice and
freedom is surely at work in all this.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Fri AMs, Dec. 22</NOTE>

</DOC>