<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0419EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-WashingtoninBrief     12-22 0484</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Washington in Brief,420</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush to Attend Drug Summit Despite Peru's Panama Protest</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush still plans to attend a
February drug summit in Colombia even though Peru, the world's
largest cocaine producer, canceled its participation to protest the
U.S. assault on Panama.
   Presidential spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said Thursday that Bush
will still go to Cartagena, Colombia as a show of support for
President Virgilio Barco, whose nation has been at war with drug
lords.
   Peru issued a strongly worded statement Wednesday condemning the
use of force in Panama, recalling its ambassador from Washington
and calling for a postponement of the scheduled Feb. 15 summit. It
did not offer an alternative date.
   The other two nations scheduled to attend the summit, Colombia
and Bolivia, issued statements condemning the U.S. actions in
Panama but did not mention the drug summit.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Juror Says Well-Publicized Drug Buy Viewed as ``Setup''</NOTE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prosecutors say they will try again to convict
the teenager who is accused of selling undercover agents the crack
cocaine that President Bush used as a prop in a television address
on drugs.
   A federal judge declared a mistrial Thursday after jurors failed
to reach a verdict in the criminal case against Keith Jackson, who
is charged with selling the cocaine in Lafayette Park across the
street from the White House. Jackson, 18, also is accused of
distributing crack at a mall and twice near a high school.
   Federal drug agents who said they had bought drugs from Jackson
were ordered to buy cocaine in Lafayette Park for the president's
anti-drug address. Bush displayed a bag of crack cocaine in his
national address Sept. 5, saying that it showed the extent of the
drug problem.
   But jury forewoman Cheryl Adams-Huff told The Washington Post in
an interview published today, ``The majority of the jurors felt it
was a setup.''
   U.S. District Court Judge Stanley Sporkin scheduled a new trial
to begin Jan. 8.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>President Vows Further Emigration Efforts</NOTE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush says he will press Mikhail S.
Gorbachev for freedom for Jews denied the right to emigrate from
the Soviet Union to join their families elsewhere.
   ``We'll get the job done,'' Bush promised an audience Thursday
at a ceremony in the Old Executive Office Building commemorating
the Jewish holiday of Hanukkah, which begins Friday.
   Bush said that during the Dec. 2-3 summit with Gorbachev in
Malta, he presented the Soviet president with a list of 20
``refuseniks.''
   Gesturing toward the audience, which was sprinkled with newly
emigrated youngsters, Bush said, ``For sake of the children who are
with us today, from countries that still deny freedom of faith, we
will strive for the religious freedom their parents have never
known.''
   The Soviet Union has greatly loosened emigration restrictions in
recent years, and as a result Bush may grant that country trade
concessions denied in previous years.
</TEXT>

</DOC>