<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1309EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-RomaniaAid     12-30 0530</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Romania Aid,540</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romania To Need Loans From West; Prospects Uncertain</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CARL HARTMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   If a country like Romania were just an
ordinary person applying for a mortgage or a loan, bankers would
consider him or her an excellent risk.
   But Romania's prospects are uncertain.
   The country has a well-educated work force, good land and
mineral resources, almost no foreign debt and a surplus in world
trade. But it will need massive credit to switch from a controlled
communist economy to something more like a free market system.
   The problem for world lenders is that Romania's past behavior
under communist dictator Nicolae Ceausescu gives little clue to
what it will do in the future under a government whose shape cannot
yet be foreseen.
   ``With a person you can look at past behavior,'' said Pietra
Rivoli, an assistant professor of business administration at
Georgetown University. ``With a country you look at ability to pay.
...
   ``The United States has an enormous debt, but it's able and
willing to meet its payments,'' she said.
   Rep. Lee Hamilton, D-Ind., chairman of the congressional Joint
Economic Committee, predicted that a large flow of goods and money
will be needed in Eastern Europe if market prices are to be set
free from the control of communist governments.
   Goods also are needed to keep inflation down.
   ``Those countries have a goods shortage,'' he told reporters
last week. ``When you free prices you'll have a terrible inflation
unless they have goods from the West.''
   Vladimir Tismaneanu, who came to this country from Romania, told
a television interviewer that Ceausescu paid off his country's
foreign debt because he did not want anyone to be in the position
of a creditor objecting to human rights abuses in Romania.
   When Tismaneanu left in 1981, Romania owed foreigners more than
$10 billion. By last year, the debt was less than $2.8 billion.
   To get that reduction, Ceausescu imposed a severe austerity
program, exporting as much as possible _ including Romania's
normally abundant food supply _ to get the necessary cash.
   The Central Intelligence Agency calculated that Romania was the
only major country in Eastern Europe where per capita income
declined in 1988. Its figure was the lowest in the region: $5,490.
   Tismaneanu said this situation opens the possibility for loans.
   John Steinbruner, who directs foreign policy studies at the
Brookings Institution, was sceptical,
   ``Romania has been very, very isolated,'' he said in an
interview.
   ``Its internal development is primitive. There will be a
response to appeals for help, but it will be aid rather than
investment. They'll have to show a fair amount of political
stability and responsible policy before there's any investment.''
   The Soviet Union, Hungary, Poland and Yugoslavia all are
installing new policies meant to attract foreigners into joint
ventures and other projects that will bring new capital and
know-how.
   Romania lags far behind them, according to Kate Holder, research
associate at the Center for Strategic and International Studies.
   ``The provisional government has no idea what to do,'' she said.
   ``There won't be any economic reform until after the election in
April. ... I can't imagine anyone considering investment in Romania
yet.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>