<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0100 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1131EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-US-Panama 8thLd-Writethru a0632 12-20 1273</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-Panama, 8th Ld-Writethru, a0632,1,200</SECOND>
<HEAD>Noriega Remains At Large Despite U.S. Offensive; Nine Americans Dead</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Inserts graf 5, ``The Pentagon xxx'' with operation given a
codename; subs graf 25 with 3 grafs byplay at OAS meeting, ``At a xxx''</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID ESPO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush told the American people today
that he sent American forces into a surprise overnight assault in
Panama to end a ``dark chapter of dictatorship'' by Manuel Antonio
Noriega and forestall a ``grave danger'' to the 35,000 Americans
living there.
   Bush ordered American forces to apprehend Noriega so he could be
put on trial in the United States on charges of drug trafficking,
but he acknowledged that Noreiga remained at large.
   ``We will chase him and we will find him,'' vowed the nation's
top military officer, Gen. Colin Powell. He said reinforcements
flown to Panama and those on the way would bring the U.S. force
there to 24,000.
   Powell, chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, said nine
Americans were killed in action, 39 were wounded and one was
missing. He said he did not know how many Panamanians had died.
   The Pentagon codenamed the mission ``Operation Just Cause.''
   In a nationally televised Oval Office speech at 7:20 a.m. EST, a
somber Bush said, ``I took this action only after reaching the
conclusion that every other avenue was closed and the lives of
American citizens were in grave danger,'' Bush said.
   The White House said the decision had been reached Sunday, after
an American Marine officer was shot and killed outside Noriega's
military headquarters.
   Bush offered this explanation:
   ``General Noriega's reckless threats and attacks upon Americans
in Panama created an imminent danger to the 35,000 American
citizens in Panama. As president, I have no higher obligation than
to safeguard the lives of American citizens. And that is why I
directed our armed forces to protect the lives of American citizens
in Panama, and to bring General Noriega to justice in the United
States.''
   But while key military objectives had been achieved and most
organized resistance eliminated, Bush said, ``the operation is not
over yet. Gen. Noriega is in hiding.''
   ``Nevertheless, yesterday a dictator ruled Panama and today
constitutionally elected leaders govern,'' the president said.
   One intelligence source on Capitol Hill said there had been
reports in recent months of a deterioration in Noriega's mental
state, including increased paranoia and constant drinking. But the
source cautioned that the reports were not based on hard evidence
and he discounted their importance as a factor in the launching of
today's military action.
   U.S. officials noted that leaders of a failed coup attempt last
October had said Noriega had been drinking heavily and Powell said
he had heard reports that Noriega had been threatening operations
of the canal.
   After his speech, Bush signed an order lifting U.S. economic
sanctions against Panama and directing ``an orderly unblocking of
Panamanian government assets in the United States.''
   Separately, Bush issued a memo to the Pentagon specifically
authorizing U.S. forces to apprehend Noriega ``and any other
persons in Panama currently under indictment in the United States
for drug-related offenses'' and to turn them over to U.S. law
enforcement officials.
   However, his declaration that Noriega had so far eludd the grasp
of American forces left the overall success of the military mission
in question.
   Bush said Guillermo Endara, who won last May's election in
results that Noriega refused to accept, was hastily sworn in as
president of Panama. And he said he was committed to implement the
Panama Canal Treaties and surrender control of the canal to Panama
in the year 2000.
   Bush's swift action stood in contrast to his inaction last
October, when he kept U.S. forces on the sidelines while some
Panamanian generals sought to oust Noriega in a coup. Bush drew
heavy congressional criticism at that time.
   As evidence, Bush noted that Noriega last week declared his
``military dictatorship to be in a state of war with the United
States.'' He also recited a series of events in Panama over the
past few days, including the fatal shooting of an American military
officer.
   ``Tragically some Americans have lost their lives in defense of
their fellow citizens, in defense of democracy,'' the president
said. He expressed his condolences to their families and said he
regretted that some innocent Panamanians also had been killed.
   Bush said the forces flown overnight to Panama would be
withdrawn ``as quickly as possible.'' Powell said nearly 7,000
additional soliders and paratroopers had arrived from stateside
bases and 2,500 were en route this morning to supplement those
troops based in Panama.
   Bush said he informed congressional leaders and U.S. allies
about his decision.
   Sen. Jesse Helm, R-N.C., predicted, ``The majority of the Senate
will feel good by this turn of events.'' Senate Majority Leader
George Mitchell, D-Maine, said Bush's action ``was made necessary
by the reckless actions of Gen. Noriega.''
   But Sen. Claiborne Pell, chairman of the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee, said, ``I would not have engaged in such
unilateral or such go-it-alone action'' without the support of
other Central American nations.
   At an emergency meeting of the Organization of American States,
called at the request of Noriega's envoy, Endara issued a statement
asking the organization to recognize Lawrence Chewning Fabrega as
its ambassador to the OAS. The statement was faxed to the OAS from
the U.S. Army South headquarters in Panama, according to the
sign-off.
   Noriega's representative, Jose Maria Cabrera, stayed in the
chair designated for his country. ``I am the representative of the
Republic of Panama, and I denounce this criminal aggression,'' he
told a reporter.
   White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said the administration
sent a cable to Soviet officials informing them of the action. The
Soviets swiftly condemned the move as a violation of the United
Nations charter.
   Bush said the United States had tried repeatedly _ but
unsuccessfully _ to use diplomacy and negotiation to remove Noriega
and that it was now recognizing the ``democratically elected
government.''
   The president spoke after only a few hours of sleep. He had
stayed in the Oval Office until a few minutes after 4 a.m. to
monitor developments in Panama, and was in time for his speech that
began shortly after 7 a.m.
   Vice President Dan Quayle, Secretary of State James A. Baker III
and other top aides also were at the White House for much of the
night.
   Defense Secretary Dick Cheney and Powell were in the Pentagon's
military command center.
   Beginning with Bush, the administration did what it could to
preserve secrecy of the operation before Fitzwater's dramatic
announcement about the military action. The president hosted a
White House Christmas party attended by reporters, but gave no hint
of the impending action.
   U.S. military intervention in Central America is a tradition of
long standing _ including President Reagan's decision to invade
Grenada in 1983 and overthrow a leftist government.
   Bush had hinted at military action earlier in the week, when he
told interviewers, ``I think a president, all presidents, have
options, but they don't discuss what they might be.''
   First Reagan and then Bush have been trying to force Noriega's
ouster since 1988, when the Panamanian leader was indicted in this
country on federal drug trafficking charges. The United States
imposed stiff economic sanctions against Panama in hopes of
dislodging him from power.
   The situation in Panama had been jumpy for days. Tuesday
afternoon, the Pentagon spokesman said a U.S. soldier used an
unauthorized weapon when he shot a Panamanian police officer
Monday. He called the incident ``very regrettable'' but said it had
to be considered in the context of a deteriorating situation.
</TEXT>

</DOC>