<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1056EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ExxonExplosion 1stLd-Writethru a0459 12-26 0451</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Exxon Explosion, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0459,0458</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Still Missing in Refinery Blast that Killed One</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: New throughout with heating oil prices higher, details, restores
dropped first reference to Exxon spokesman in penultimate graf.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BATON ROUGE, La. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rescuers today searched through charred
wreckage at the nation's second-largest petrochemical refinery for
a worker missing in the aftermath of an explosion and fire that
killed another man.
   Separately, heating oil futures prices shot higher in early
trading today in New York on speculation that the damage combined
with the nation's recent record-setting cold wave would tighten
already short home heating oil supplies.
   ``They are searching now and they'll search through the night in
the units where we've gotten clearance to go through,'' Exxon
spokesman Travis Joslin said Monday night. ``We've got to get
assurance before we send people back into the dangerous areas.''
   Seven people were injured and one contract worker was killed
when his pickup truck caught fire 100 to 200 feet from the
Christmas Eve explosion. The blast at the plant on the Mississippi
River in North Baton Rouge shattered windows up to six miles away
and ignited a fire that raged 15 hours.
   The name of the missing worker was withheld.
   Co-workers reported seeing the missing man after the explosion,
and officials wouldn't ruled out the possibility he wasn't at the
plant.
   The fire, which burned into Monday morning, engulfed eight
storage tanks holding more than 4 million gallons of oil and
lubricants, and two separator units, which remove water from oil,
the company said.
   It was believed to have begun in gas that was somehow released,
but the cause remained under investigation, said plant Manager Ed
Galante.
   Production was halted at the refinery, but Exxon officials said
they did not know whether heating oil shortages would worsen as a
result.
   ``Generally, the limit to fuel oil seems to be due to
transportation problems in bad weather, and not supplies,'' said
spokesman Ron Embry. The refinery has a capacity of more than 19
million gallons of crude oil a day.
   On the New York Mercantile Exchange, the January contract for
No. 2 heating oil jumped 4.01 cents a gallon to 85.75 cents in
early trading today.
   Gov. Buddy Roemer called out 50 National Guardsmen overnight to
prevent looting of stores where plate-glass windows were blown out.
Initial reports said looters hit some stores, but police Lt. Willie
Stevens said Monday that there had been no arrests.
   The dead man was identified as mechanic Harold Guillory, 31, of
Irwinville, an employee for contractor Vernon McKenny Enterprise,
said Exxon spokesman Dave Gardner.
   Three Exxon employees and four contract workers were treated at
hospitals and released, Gardner said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>