<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1105EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania-Albania     12-23 0316</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Albania,0326</SECOND>
<HEAD>Albanian News Agency Reports on Romanian Uprising</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Albania's state news agency on Saturday
issued an unusually frank report on the Romanian revolt against
dictator Nicolae Ceausescu, whose regime had much in common with
the Albanian leadership.
   With the ouster of Ceausescu, Albania remains the last stalwart
of Stalinism in Eastern Europe.
   But ATA's reporting indicated the present Tirana leadership was
at least not opposed to Ceausescu's reported ouster.
   Romania was the last member of the Soviet alliance to be hit
with the wave of reform. Earlier this year, Poland, Hungary,
Bulgaria, East Germany and Czechoslovakia each embraced liberal
change.
   The other two Eastern European nations, Albania and Yugoslavia,
are non-aligned nations.
   Yugoslavia broke with Moscow in 1948 because its founder, the
late Jozip Broz Tito, espoused a less harsh brand of Communism than
Stalin. Albania broke with the Kremlin in 1961 to continue its
orthodox Stalinist course.
   Long-time leader Enver Hoxha led his country into increasing
isolation, and the nation of 3 million became one of the most
closed societies in the world.
   Under Ramiz Alia, who took over after Hoxha's death in 1985, the
country renewed diplomatic relations with dozens of countries and
opened up somewhat to tourism, but Alia has continued to abhor the
reforms in the Soviet Union and other Eastern European countries.
   The ATA report quoted Western and Soviet bloc news agencies in
its dispatch and noted that the Soviet news agency Tass had been
unusually vivid in its reporting of the Romanian situation.
   The dispatch could indicate a further opening in the poorest
nation in Europe.
   The news agency has not issued any editorial comment on the
situation in Romania.
   ATA has on previous occasions quoted Western and other foreign
news agencies but usually only in connection with the situation in
neighboring Yugoslavia, where there is a large ethnic Albanian
population.
</TEXT>

</DOC>