<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0122 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1801EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Census-States     12-28 0446</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Census-States,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>For release 12:01 a.m. EST Friday; time set by sources</HEAD>
<HEAD>New Census Figures Could Affect Reapportionment</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The populations of five states grew at rates
faster than 10 percent in the last half of the 1980s, the Census
Bureau said Thursday in a report that is causing revised estimates
for congressional reapportionment.
   The Census figures on state population, issued for release
Friday, showed Nevadawith the biggest population gain at 18 percent
from 1985 to the middle of 1989. Arizona had the second highest
growth rate, at 12 percent, followed by Florida and New Hampshire
at 11 percent and California at 10 percent.
   Seven states lost population during the same period, the bureau
said: Iowa, North Dakota, Montana, West Virginia, Wyoming,
Louisiana and Oklahoma.
   The population figures are closely watched at the end of each
decade because they determine how many seats in the U.S. House of
Representatives each state will have. The next reapportionment will
be based on the final 1990 Census figures, which will be collected
in the 10-year census next year.
   The report issued Thursday represents one last checkpoint before
that final, official count, and two forecasting groups on Thursday
issued revised reapportionment predictions based on the trends.
   While the two reports varied on some specifics, they agreed on
the overall trend: states in the Sunbelt will generally pick up
seats lost by states in the Northeast and Midwest.
   The non-profit Population Reference Bureau said that if the
trends in Thursday's report hold true through the final 1990
figures, 11 states are likely to lose one or more seats in Congress
while seven will gain.
   It said New York will lose three seats, Pennsylvania two, Ohio
two, Michigan two, Illinois two, New Jersey one, Massachusetts one,
Iowa one, Kansas one, West Virginia one and Montana one.
   The Population Reference Bureau said California will gain seven
seats, Texas will gain three, Florida three, Virginia one, North
Carolina one, Georgia one and Arizona one.
   The comparable prediction by Election Data Services Inc., a
Washington-based political consulting firm, differed only for a few
states. It said Florida is likely to pick up four seats, rather
than three, and it added Kentucky to the list of those losing
seats, dropping one.
   There is still a wild card in the deck which cannot, at this
point, be predicted with certainty. The Census Bureau figures on
which the projections are based do not include members of the
military and their dependents living overseas.
   The government recently announced that they will be counted in
the 1990 reapportionment. This change could tip the balance in some
states that now appear close to winning or losing a seat.
</TEXT>

</DOC>