<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0224 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2208EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania-Reax     12-20 0474</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Reax,0490</SECOND>
<HEAD>European Community, East Germany Condemn Romania Crackdown</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The European Community said Wednesday it was cutting back
economic relations with Romania to protest that country's crackdown
on demonstrators, and East Germany and the World Council of
Churches also issued condemnations.
   Here are some of the statements released:
   _ In Brussels, the EC Commission criticized the repression of
anti-government protests as a ``most heartless demonstration of the
abuse of human rights.''
   EC Commissioner for External Relations Frans Andriessen said a
1980 agreement covering industrial goods ``should be frozen'' and
planned visits and meetings will not be held. No new trade
concession will be made ``pending any significant improvement in
the situation.''
   The Commission also offered to help some 25,000 Romanian
refugees currently in Hungary.
   _ In East Germany, the Communist Party called on Romania's
leadership to ``stop immediately all acts of violence against its
own population'' and respect human rights.
   Another East German party leader, Lothar de Maiziere, chairman
of the Christian Democratic Union, said he feared ``genocide'' in
Romania and called for an emergency meeting of the U.N. Security
Council on the situation, the state news agency ADN said.
   Young East Germans, meanwhile, staged a silent candlelight vigil
in front of the Romanian embassy in East Berlin, and an unspecified
number of students in Leipzig also protested publicly against the
crackdown, ADN said.
   _ In Geneva, leaders of the World Council of Churches and
affiliated organizations on Wednesday expressed shock at the
crackdown and said it revealed the ``ruthlessness'' of Romania's
leadership.
   ``We strongly condemn the use of violence in response to
peoples' expression of their aspirations and of their longing for
justice,'' said the statement issued at the Geneva WCC headquarters.
   The World Council comprises about 300 churches representing some
400 million Anglican, Protestant, Orthodox and other non-Roman
Catholic Christians in more than 100 countries.
   _ The U.N.'s Special Rapporteur on Summary or Arbitrary
Executions, Amos Wacko, sent an urgent cable from his Geneva office
to Romania's Foreign Ministry about the reports that hundreds of
people were killed at Timisoara last Sunday.
   Wacko ``appealed to the government of Romania to respect the
right to life of the Romanian people in accordance in particular
with the Convention on Civil and Political Rights,'' said an
official at U.N. headquarters in New York.
   _ About 150 people outraged by the reported massacres protested
outside Romania's embassy in Warsaw, Poland, on Wednesday, with
some hurling stones and bottles of ink before being stopped by
police.
   _ In Moscow, Moldavian delegates asked the Soviet Congress to
appeal for ``reason and order'' in Romania to help their ethnic
brethren there.
   _ In Israel, a firebomb was thrown at the Romanian Embassy in
Tel Aviv, causing a small fire at a nearby construction site,
Israel Television said. No injuries were reported.
</TEXT>

</DOC>