<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0352EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BusCrash-Impacts     12-22 0512</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bus Crash-Impacts,0528</SECOND>
<HEAD>Carrollton Bus Crash Prompts Tougher Bus-Safety Regulations</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Bus Crash Trial, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOUISVILLE, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation's worst drunken-driving
disaster has prompted federal and state officials nationwide to
work to make school buses safer.
   Kentucky, in particular, has approved new safety standards for
future school buses and is poised to toughen its drunken driving
laws after the fiery bus crash that killed 27 people, including 24
children.
   The crash happened when a church bus collided with a pickup
traveling the wrong way on Interstate 71 near Carrollton, Ky. A
jury on Thursday convicted the pickup's driver, Larry Mahoney, of
27 counts of second-degree manslaughter.
   The former school bus, owned by the First of Assembly of God
Church in Radcliff, Ky., burst into flames upon impact. Defense
lawyers contended that safety defects in the 1977 bus caused the
loss of more lives.
   Investigators said the victims were trapped inside the bus with
only one working exit and were overcome by smoke from a fire that
spread among highly flammable seats.
   The magnitude of the tragedy, exacerbated by its young victims'
ages, has drawn attention from all parts of the United States.
   ``There's been a lot of changes as a result of the Carrollton
accident than anything else we've seen,'' said Don Carnahan,
director of pupils' transportation in Washington state.
   Since the May 14, 1988, crash, officials at all levels of
government have taken steps to add emergency exits, install less
flammable materials, reconsider the location of the gas tank on
buses and restrict the use of older buses.
   Across the country, school officials, government regulators and
bus manufacturers say the crash has torpedoed a decade of
confidence in the safety of school buses _ confidence dating back
to the last extensive changes in federal regulations in 1977.
   The crash ``has caused more dialogue within the industry than
any other accident in recent history,'' said Ray Kroll, director of
transportation for Minneapolis schools and president of the
National Association for Pupil Transportation.
   In Kentucky, the state school board approved new safety
regulations in July for new school buses that will require them to
have roof-escape hatches, fire resistant interiors and a wider
space by the emergency exit.
   Those were among some of the recommendations made by the
National Transportation Safety Board after it concluded an
investigation of the bus crash.
   The board also urged the state to enact stricter laws for
driving under the influence.
   In its final report, the board praised the work of a task force
on drunken driving appointed by Gov. Wallace Wilkinson.
   Among the task force recommendations was proposed legislation
that would make it an offense for any driver to test above a 0.10
level on a blood alcohol level. Current law presumes that a driver
is intoxicated if they have a test at that level.
   A state attorney general's task force later recommended the
state lower the blood-alcohol level at which a person would be
considered legally drunk.
   Both proposals, among numerous others, will be dealt with when
the state Legislature convenes in January.
</TEXT>

</DOC>