<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0225 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1321EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-Peru-StrikeChaos Adv24   12-18 0850</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Peru-Strike Chaos, Adv 24,0875</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv24</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 24, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Plague of Strikes Brings Chaos to Daily Life in Lima</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOSE GONZALES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LIMA, Peru (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A string of strikes by public workers has
disrupted Peru's already battered economy and brought chaos to the
daily lives of thousands of people.
   Prisoners who complete terms can't get out of jail. Bodies stack
up in the morgue waiting for autopsies. Mail piles up undelivered
in post offices. Taxes are uncollected. Hospital patients must wait
for treatment.
   ``The crisis in the public sector is an expression of the
economic chaos that exists in the country,'' said Carlos Morales,
an independent labor analyst.
   Hundreds of thousands of government workers have walked off
their jobs to demand gargantuan pay raises to offset the loss in
the purchasing power of their salaries caused by Peru's
hyperinflation, running at nearly 3,000 percent annually.
   Not wanting to fuel inflation, the government has resisted the
workers' demands, approving wage increases that fall short of the
inflation rate.
   A mountain of 5 million letters sits in Lima's central post
office waiting to be sorted and delivered as postal workers walk
the picket lines.
   A walkout by workers at the National Tax Administration office
has reduced tax collections by 70 percent.
   A strike by prison workers has delayed paperwork authorizing the
release of prisoners who have served out their terms. The director
of Peru's department of prisons, Wilder Vidal, said recently that
more than 900 convicts whose sentences have lapsed remain behind
bars.
   Teachers, bus drivers, water and sewer workers and gravediggers
are all on strike.
   Even prostitutes from the nearby port of Callao took to the
streets recently to demand a reduction in the 50 percent tax they
are required to pay to a city government starved for revenue to
meet escalating costs.
   A sign in the emergency room at Casimiro Ulloa hospital asks the
``understanding of patients and injured'' who cannot be attended
because of a strike by hospital workers, including doctors.
   The strike in public hospitals has had grave consequences for
the poor, who cannot afford private clinics.
   Josefina Quispe said she tried to take her father, a street
vendor, to a state hospital when he complained of kidney pains,
apparently caused by complications from a kidney operation months
earlier.
   ``A doctor told me to take him home to die,'' Ms. Quispe said.
   Her father died at home, without medical attention.
   The common denominator in all the strikes, some of which have
resulted in bloody street clashes with riot police, is a demand for
higher pay to help workers deal with the inflation.
   ``On average, government salaries have 15 percent of the
purchasing power they had in 1973, and 35 percent of what they had
before September 1988,'' the magazine Analisis Laboral said
recently.
   The average monthly salary for public employees is 753,012 intis
_ $50. Government studies say the minimum income a family of five
needs to buy basic necessities is the equivalent of $213, or 10
times the minimum wage of $21.
   The economic crisis also has provoked the most dramatic fall in
the gross national product in Peru's history. The economy has
shrunk by 14 percent so far this year, following a 9 percent drop
in 1988.
   With public services paralyzed, some entrepreneurs have been
quick to see an opportunity in the chaos. They have created private
ventures to offer alternatives to public services.
   At least six private mail services have started up, some
offering guaranteed, four-day delivery to the United States at
prices ranging from $1.50 to $7 a letter.
   ``It's very simple,'' said a worker at Giant Express, one of the
new mail services. ``So we don't have to charge as much as
door-to-door courier services, we take the letters and send them to
Miami with an airline, and from there we send them on by regular
mail.''
   The company also brings mail into the country, a service many
have used since the U.S. postal service stopped delivering to Peru
in October because of the strike, which began Sept. 14.
   ``Business is booming, and we have increased our deliveries
tenfold,'' said the Giant Express worker.
   Morales, the labor analyst, predicted the strikes will continue
as long as the country's economic slide goes unchecked. He and
others blame a bloated bureaucracy for much of the economic
troubles.
   They say the excessive number of bureaucrats, numbering more
than 1 million in a nation of 21 million people, are an
unproductive drain on the government.
   One who shares that view is the novelist Mario Vargas Llosa, the
front-running candidate for the presidency in April's election.
Vargas Llosa is running on a platform of free-work economic
policies. He is pledging to reduce the government bureaucracy and
``shift'' thousands of state workers to the private sector.
   President Alan Garcia, a populist ineligible for re-election,
has tried to maintain the little political support he still enjoys
by accusing Vargas Llosa of planning to fire half a million
workers, a charge the candidate denies.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, Dec. 24</NOTE>

</DOC>