<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0102 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1542EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-MorialFuneral     12-28 0588</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Morial Funeral,0605</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Orleans Says Goodbye to First Black Mayor</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY FOSTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   They gave Dutch Morial a New Orleans sendoff
Thursday _ a sometimes mournful, sometimes jubilant jazz funeral
procession to and from St. Louis Cathedral, where a Mass was held
for the city's first black mayor.
   ``He had a vision and the lives of black people in Louisiana
were changed forever,'' retired Archbishop Phillip Hannan said at
the Mass. ``He saw that equal rights for all would bring in a new
era for Louisiana.''
   Morial, who also broke ground as the first black to graduate
from the Louisiana State University law school, the first black
judge in New Orleans and first black Louisiana state representative
since Reconstruction, died of a heart attack Saturday. He was 60.
   Morial's son Marc received a standing ovation during the Mass
when he ended a eulogy with the words that were a campaign theme
for his father:
   ``Daddy,'' he said, ``we're going to keep the drive alive.''
   City and state officials and civil rights leader Jesse Jackson
were among the approximately 1,000 people at the service.
   Thursday's jazz funeral procession was led to the church, and
afterwards to St. Louis Cemetery No. 1, by the Olympia Brass Band
and members of the Zulu Social Aid and Pleasure Club, the city's
original all-black Mardi Gras club.
   Thousands who lined the route of the procession moved with it in
parade fashion to Jackson Square and waited outside the cathedral.
Many along the route cried. Some wore small pictures of Morial
pinned to their clothes.
   The Olympia musicians, regulars at the jazz funerals that
traditionally mark the passing of New Orleans musicians, played
mournful renditions of ``Nearer My God to Thee'' and ``The Battle
Hymn of the Republic,'' then a spirited ``Gloryland'' that sparked
dancing and clapping among the mourners who fell in behind the
five-block motorcade.
   ``I've played for a million of these,'' bandleader Harold Dejan
said before the procession moved into the French Quarter. ``It's an
honor to play for someone like Dutch. He was a great man. He
deserves a great sendoff.''
   Men and women wept in the church and Wynton Marsalis played
``Just A Closer Walk'' as the coffin was moved to the hearse at the
end of the ceremony.
   Outside, the band _ including tuba, trumpet, bass drum, trombone
and wailing clarinet _ picked up the mournful tune, but quickly
switched to ``Down By the Riverside'' as people held aloft gaily
decorated umbrellas and pictures of Morial and danced.
   ``Time to cut loose and think about him in happier days,'' said
one woman as she moved toward the cemetery.
   Morial participated in numerous successful integration lawsuits
aimed at education, transportation and public institutions. He
chaired Jackson's presidential campaign in Louisiana in 1984. In
1988, he was an adviser to Democratic presidential candidate
Michael Dukakis.
   During his two terms as mayor from 1978 to 1986, Morial was
recognized for his pioneering policies in fields such as minority
business development. He was a president of the National Conference
of Mayors.
   Morial failed to get a change in the city charter so he could
run for a third consecutive term and spent the last three years out
of office.
   But Morial remained in the thick of local politics.
   Eleven days before he died, he announced that he would not run
for mayor again but held out the possibility he might someday seek
another office _ possibly a congressional seat or the governor's
office.
</TEXT>

</DOC>