<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0718EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ColdRdp     12-20 0592</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Cold Rdp,0607</SECOND>
<HEAD>Record Cold Continues, Snow Across Northern States</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Ice clogged more than 200 miles of the Mississippi River and
people across the country bundled up today against an arctic blast
that dropped temperatures to record lows from the Plains to the
East Coast.
   ``You'd have to take extra care if you're going to be out for
any length of time,'' said Paul Merzlock, a weather service
forecaster in Chicago. ``It's certainly a danger.''
   Since Friday, at least 40 deaths have been blamed on the
weather, including traffic deaths on slippery roads and hypothermia.
   In North Dakota, high temperatures today were expected to be no
more than 15 below to 25 below, with winds of 15 to 25 mph
producing wind chills of 55 below to 80 below, according to the
National Weather Service.
   ``This is way below normal for December,'' said Richard May, a
weather service meteorologist at Bismarck, which recorded Tuesday's
coldest reading for the Lower 48 at 35 below. ``It will be the
worst cold we've had this season.''
   A 203-mile stretch of the Mississippi River, from St. Louis to
Cairo, Ill., was closed to barge traffic by ice and low water, the
U.S. Coast Guard said.
   About 60 percent of the 195 miles of Missouri River north of
Omaha, Neb., to the Gavins Point Dam was frozen Tuesday, forming
ice jams that reduced the amount of water flowing downstream to
towns and power plants.
   The river level was within one foot of the level at which some
power plants would be unable to operate because their water intake
systems would no longer work, said Chet Worm, chief of the
reservoir regulation section of the Corps Missouri River District.
   About 300,000 Illinois-American Water Co. customers in
Belleville, East St. Louis and Granite City soon may have to ration
water if the cold weather keeps freezing the river and causing ice
to form on water intake valves, officials said.
   In such brutal weather conditions, officials advised people
going outside to dress with extra layers of clothing and to carry
emergency survival kits when traveling. Farmers and ranchers also
were warned to take precautions to protect their animals from the
bitter cold.
   In Grand Forks, N.D., the local humane society put to sleep 40
animals on Monday to make room for a high number of animals brought
in because of the bitter cold, said the society's executive
director, Terri Toay.
   Michigan outreach centers pleaded for donations of warm clothes
to help the needy stave off the unusual cold. The average mean
temperature in Michigan for the first 18 days of December was 14.1
degrees, compared to the month's norm of 23.5 degrees.
   ``There are people coming in here with just tennis shoes on
their feet. It's cold, so cold out,'' said Floria Ellison at St.
Patrick's Outreach in Detroit on Tuesday.
   Ice on roads was blamed for accidents around metropolitan
Atlanta and Athens, Ga., and police blocked off several interstate
highway ramps that were littered with cars and trucks unable to
cross slick spots.
   Record low temperatures for the date Tuesday included 8 at
Atlantic City, N.J.; 6 at Baltimore; 10 at Bridgeport, Conn.; 26
below zero at Dickinson, N.D.; 6 below at Elkins, W.Va.; 19 below
at Grand Island, Neb.; 5 at Harrisburg, Pa.; 20 below at Lincoln,
Neb.; 24 below at Norfolk, Neb.; 7 below at Wheat Ridge, Colo.; and
3 below at Youngstown, Ohio.
   But Florida baked. Miami hit a record high of 85 and West Palm
Beach reached a record 88.
</TEXT>

</DOC>