<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0225 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0746EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Hunts-Commodities     12-21 0346</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hunts-Commodities,0359</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hunts Agreed To Lifetime Ban From Futures Trading</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nelson Bunker Hunt and William Herbert Hunt have
accepted lifetime bans from trading commodities futures and will
pay a $10 million penalty after they emerge from bankruptcy.
   But the Hunts, who officials say came within weeks of cornering
the world's silver market, have neither admitted guilt nor claimed
innocence under terms of the agreement.
   The move will help the brothers speed the settlement of their
personal bankruptcy cases, filed after they lost a court case
stemming from their silver speculation.
   In 1985, the federal Commodity Futures Trading Commission filed
a complaint that sought more than $50 million in fines from the
Hunts.
   ``It could have been a very extensive fight and they wouldn't
have had the money to hire attorneys and continue to litigate after
settlement of their bankruptcy cases,'' CFTC attorney Linda Groves
told the Dallas Morning News.
   Bunker Hunt's bankruptcy neared end last week with U.S.
Bankruptcy Judge Harold Abramson's approval of a reorganization
plan. Herbert Hunt's case may end this week.
   ``We were happy to get the CFTC decision behind us,'' said
Russell Munsch, Bunker Hunt's lead bankruptcy attorney. ``It is one
of those things that Bunker would have liked to have gone and
litigated.''
   Under the agreement, on file in Dallas bankruptcy court, the
Hunts agreed to pay the $10 million penalty out of future income,
gifts and inheritances once they emerge from bankruptcy.
   The terms of the CFTC agreement say the Hunts consent to
findings the brothers violated the Commodity Exchange Act by
manipulating the price of silver.
   CFTC documents on file in Washington claim that ``by the end of
May 1980, (the Hunts) could have owned virtually the entire
available world supply of deliverable .999 silver bullion.''
   The effort collapsed on March 27, 1980, the agency said, when
prices fell from about $50 an ounce to about $10 an ounce.
   The Hunts lost an estimated $1.3 billion in the collapse and
then a series of lawsuits and claims were initiated against them
that toppled their empire.
</TEXT>

</DOC>