<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0258 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0923EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-MarriottRestructuring     12-18 0496</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Marriott Restructuring,0513</SECOND>
<HEAD>Marriott Plans Sweeping Restructuring</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Marriott Corp. today announced a major
restructuring, including the sale of its fast food and family
restaurant businesses, in an effort to reposition the company for
the next decade.
   The company also said that it has completed the sale of its
airline catering division to a group of senior managers for $570
million. That sale was expected to yield more than $200 million for
Marriott.
   ``As we move into the 1990s, we want to sharpen Marriott's focus
on mega-markets in lodging and contract services which together
have an estimated aggregate potential of more than $400 billion in
industry annual sales,'' said J.W. Marriott Jr., chairman and
president, in a news release.
   ``We believe the restructuring will help the company to grow at
15 to 20 percent per year from our 1989 profit base for continuing
operations,'' Marriott said.
   The plan calls for the sale of 358 company-operated Roy Rogers
fast food restaurants in the Middle Atlantic states in the first
quarter of 1990. Those stores were expected to register about $400
million in sales this year.
   Marriott also said it intends to sell the 434 units operated by
its family restaurants division, including 235 Bob's Big Boy, 79
Wag's, 31 Bickford's, 57 Howard Johnson's and 32 Allie's
restaurants. In total, these restaurants had 1989 anticipated sales
of about $440 million.
   The company also announced it has repurchased 32 million shares,
or 24 percent, of its common stock over the past three years,
leaving 104 million outstanding.
   Marriott said one of the company's key objectives is to be a
leader in each of its segments.
   ``We have concluded that it is unrealistic for us to continue to
pursue this goal in `stand-alone' restaurants,'' Marriott said.
   ``In fast food, we have a strong regional concept in a highly
competitive segment dominated by a handful of national chains. In
the family restaurant segment, competitive conditions have changed
significantly within the past year, and we believe it now is too
difficult for a new grand to become number one,'' he said.
   The company, headquartered in suburban Bethesda, Md., expects to
record pretax restructuring charges and writeoffs of between $225
million and $250 million on continuing operations in the fourth
quarter of this year. Pretax writeoffs and reserves of $50 million
to $75 million also will be incurred in the sale of the restaurant
operations, the company said.
   Despite the additional costs, William J. Shaw, executive vice
president and chief financial officer, said he expected per share
income from continuing operations in fiscal 1989 to be up slightly
from 1988.
   Marriott, the nation's largest hotel company, has projected 1990
sales of $7.5 billion.
   ``Our airline catering and `stand-alone' restaurant operations
are sound, profitable businesses,'' Marriott said. ``But they do
not offer the same scale of long-term market growth potential as
our other major businesses.''
   The company has recently launched a new division _ senior living
services _ for older Americans.
</TEXT>

</DOC>