<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0240 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1844EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Eastern 1stLd-Writethru   12-19 0514</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Eastern, 1st Ld-Writethru,0529</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rebuilding Carrier To Shift Focus To Atlanta</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 6 new grafs to reflect American announcement of purchase
of Eastern's Latin American routes. Picks up 7th graf pvs ``Eastern officials
...''</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAN SEWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eastern Airlines' sale of its Latin American routes
highlights a declining role for its traditional Miami base, while
the rebuilding carrier puts its emphasis on Atlanta.
   Pan American World Airways and American Airlines, the buyer of
the Latin routes, expect their Miami expansion plans to be
bolstered by Eastern's cutbacks in Miami, where it is the No. 1
carrier.
   In its presentation to creditors in New York on Monday, Eastern
disclosed the planned ``de-hubbing'' of Miami because it ``has been
a source of heavy losses.'' Creditors were told Eastern's planned
sale of Latin American routes, to American, would enable Eastern to
``re-focus on Atlanta as the airline's major hub.''
   The sale of the routes and certain other assets to American for
$471 million was confirmed late Tuesday in an announcement from
American.
   Eastern's revised business plan is ``quite similar'' to its
original rebuilding plan devised last April, as the carrier tried
to recover from a crippling strike. Eastern in August decided to
keep its Latin routes, but recently resumed negotiations with
American because of concerns about a cash shortfall.
   Company spokesman Robin Matell declined to elaborate on the
future of the Miami and Atlanta operations.
   Eastern officials in the past said there were no plans to move
Eastern's corporate headquarters from Miami to Atlanta, but
wouldn't speculate on whether that was a possibility later.
   Eastern has 260 departures from Atlanta, where it is second to
Delta Airlines. It had 285 departures from Atlanta before the
strike. Eastern spokespeople said no projections were available
Tuesday on the total flights planned for Atlanta.
   Before the March 4 strike, Eastern operated about 10 percent of
its daily schedule of 1,040 flights out of Miami. Eastern officials
had said recently that sale of the Latin routes could leave as few
as 24 Miami departures daily.
   Eastern, building back while in Chapter 11 bankruptcy
reorganization, is back to 76 daily departures from Miami.
   Peter Reavely, chief of aviation development at Miami
International Airport, said he expects New York-based Pan Am to
become the airport's major carrier between Miami and the Northeast,
and Texas-based American would dominate between Miami and Sun Belt
destinations.
   ``The effect is positive for us,'' Pan Am spokeswoman Pamela
Hanlon said of Eastern's plans. ``One of the primary reasons (for)
building up Miami was to fill the void left by Eastern's diminished
operations. What they are saying regarding the `de-hubbing'
supports the decision we made earlier.''
   Pan Am has boosted its daily Miami departures to 70, from 48 one
year ago.
   American has 36 departures from Miami, is expanding its American
Eagle commuter service there, and has made Miami the headquarters
for its new Florida-Caribbean-Latin Services Division.
   ``We see Miami as a very important part of the American system,
particularly feeding traffic from the Caribbean,'' American
spokesman Ed Stewart said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>