<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0135 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1406EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Sears-RocketBooster     12-20 0419</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sears-Rocket Booster,0434</SECOND>
<HEAD>Boys Protest Exploding Rocket Booster Toy as `Sick Humor'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOISE, Idaho (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four young brothers, upset by a Sears,
Roebuck and Co. Christmas catalog toy that features an exploding
rocket booster, have taken on the giant retailer and apparently won.
   ``Sabotage the rocket booster'' is how the holiday Wishbook
promotes an exploding toy rocket, part of a series called Building
Blasters.
   Angry over the association with the fatal January 1986 explosion
of the space shuttle Challenger, the Sanders boys fired off letters
in September to Sears executives and President Bush.
   ``We feel this is very sick humor,'' wrote Jared, 13, and Seth,
9. ``We don't want children learning to blow up space shuttles!
There are plenty of terrorists in the world already.''
   Younger brothers Spencer, 5, and Cody, 3, also signed the
letters.
   Rita Guttke, a Sears customer relations official in Chicago,
recently wrote the boys: ``Your concern is valid. I doubt that this
product will be offered in future catalogs.''
   The catalog, distributed over the summer, invited customers to
build a rocket pad and ``detonate'' the accompanying rocket upon
launch.
   ``It's pretty disgusting, from both a parent and a schoolteacher
point of view,'' Barbara Morgan, who was NASA's backup teacher in
space, said Tuesday.
   Mrs. Morgan, of McCall, witnessed the Challenger explosion that
killed all seven astronauts aboard, including New Hampshire teacher
Christa McAuliffe.
   NASA's James Funkhouser, a public services division director in
the Office of Communications, said he wrote a letter of complaint
to Sears a week ago after learning of the Sanders' protest but has
not received a response.
   The boys' mother said Sears' reply to her sons was not enough.
``There's no guarantee the toys are going to be off their
shelves,'' Christa Sanders said Tuesday.
   However, the manufacturer, Kenner Products Inc., said
manufacturing and shipping of the toy have been discontinued due to
poor sales.
   John Bohach, vice president of advertising and marketing
services at Kenner's Cincinnati headquarters, said the company had
no intention of equating the toy with the Challenger. He said the
company found that ``kids like to build things and like to knock
them down.''
   The Building Blasters series includes an oil rig, a fuel depot,
a suspension bridge and a communications tower.
   In her letter to the Sanders boys, Ms. Guttke said the
possibility of encouraging terrorism never surfaced while the toy
was being child-tested.
   Sears spokesman Gordon Jones and Kenner's Bohach both said the
Sanders children's complaint was the only one they had heard.
</TEXT>

</DOC>