<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1730EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-DrugExecutions 1stLd-Writethru a0702 12-24 0295</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Drug Executions, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0702,0300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jury Splits on Convictions in Drug-Slaying Case</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS penultimate graf to CORRECT that jury acquitted Garrett,
sted convicted him, and that jury deadlocked in case of Cornell Williams,
sted Anthony Williams.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jurors have convicted two men, acquitted
another and split on a fourth accused of killing two teen-age
brothers who failed to deliver the proceeds from $500 worth of
crack.
   Miguel Martinez Jr., 17, and Mark Christian, 26, both of New
York City, were convicted Saturday of first-degree murder,
kidnapping, conspiracy and related offenses in the deaths of
Cornell Williams, 15, and Anthony Williams, 13.
   Martinez, because of his age, was automatically sentenced to
life in prison. A hearing to determine if Christian will receive
the death penalty will begin Tuesday.
   Thirteen-year-old Joseph Jones testified that he and the
Williams brothers received $500 worth of crack to sell for a gang.
   However, the Williams' mother took $100 worth and $80 worth was
stolen by neighborhood kids, Jones said. He did not know what
happened to the rest.
   When the youths failed to deliver the money, they were kidnapped
March 12, 1988, and ordered to work off the debt in a drug house,
Jones said.
   Police said Anthony Williams was shot March 15 and died the
following day.
   Jones said he and Cornell Williams were taken to a desolate area
to be killed March 18, but he escaped. Martinez then shot Cornell
Williams twice in the head, police said.
   The jury split in the case of John Garrett, 26, of Philadelphia,
acquitting him in the murder of Anthony Williams and deadlocking in
the case of Cornell. He faces a retrial, Assistant District
Attorney Joseph McGettigan said.
   Kelly Robinson, 17, of New York City, was acquitted.
</TEXT>

</DOC>