<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0211 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1209EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--What'sNew-Sewage-Plants Adv25   12-21 0383</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--What's New-Sewage-Plants, Adv 25,0393</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv25</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Monday, Dec. 25, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Retired Scientist Uses Plants In Organic Home Waste Treatment System</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PICAYUNE, Miss. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The grass isn't greener over Bill
Wolverton's septic tank _ he doesn't have one. Nor is his home
hooked to a seage treatment system.
   Wolverton's household sewage flows through 50 feet of pipes,
reservoirs and plants along the outside wall of a 1,500-square-foot
addition. The plants grown along large windows eat the organic
wastes, leaving pure, clean water.
   ``I wanted to put it in just to show that it can be done and
this is what will be done on the moon base, if NASA ever builds a
moon base,'' the retired National Aeronautics and Space
Administration scientist said.
   Wolverton's system uses a variation of the ``artificial marsh''
he developed a decade ago. Plants are supported on clay rocks
imported from Germany above reservoirs of wastewater. The end roots
of the plants reach into the wastewater for nutrients and thrive
without fertilizer or watering. The bug problem was corrected by
introducing a few chameleons to the indoor system.
   Wolverton's artificial marsh, in large outdoor versions, is used
by several small towns in Mississippi and Louisiana. The system is
relatively simple to install and, once operating, presents little
or no maintenance costs.
   ``I think, philosophically, that this sort of system would come
closer to meeting the goals of the Clean Water Act than some of the
mechanical systems,'' said Barry Royals, of the state Bureau of
Pollution Control. ``The problem is that a wetlands system is not
the answer to everybody's problem.
   ``An example of that would be if you tried to build a wetlands
system for the city of Jackson. You would take up a good portion of
Hinds County and we know that's not practical.''
   Interest is growing; Japanese officials visited in October and
Wolverton was invited to Holland last month to speak. Things were
different 15 years ago, however, when he told the director of
Mississippi's Bureau of Pollution Control that sewage could be
treated with water hyacinths instead of chemicals.
   ``He said, `If I stopped to listen to every kook who came in
here, I'd never get anything done' and he threw me out of the
office.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Dec. 25</NOTE>

</DOC>