<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0708EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Israel     12-25 0404</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Israel,0416</SECOND>
<HEAD>Subdued Christmas Celebrations in Bethlehem, Violence in Gaza Strip</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By G.G. LaBELLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BETHLEHEM, Occupied West Bank (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Christians from around the
world today prayed where tradition holds that Jesus was born, but
the subdued Christmas was overshadowed by more violence in the
2-year-old Palestinian uprising.
   Israeli soldiers removed barricades and metal detectors from
Manger Square after Christmas Eve passed quietly in this town in
the occupied West Bank. Many troops also left the plaza during
morning Mass.
   Violent clashes were reported in the Gaza Strip, where soldiers
shot and wounded four Palestinians during stone-throwing protests
in Jebalya refugee camp, Arab reports said.
   In Jerusalem, a firebomb was thrown at parked Israeli cars on a
busy shopping street, causing no injury, and one Arab suspect was
detained near the scene, police said.
   Desmond Tutu, the South African Anglican archbishop, worshiped
at the Anglican St. George's church in Jerusalem's Arab sector. The
1984 Nobel Peace Prize winner has been criticized for repeatedly
voicing sympathy with the Palestinians since his arrival in Israel
Friday.
   Tutu's latest pro-Palestinian remarks came Sunday in a Christmas
Eve sermon at Shepherd's Field near Bethlehem, the site where
Jesus' birth was announced.
   ``We pray that Arabs and Jews will know that they are brother
and sister, that they belong in one family, that they belong in
God's family, that they belong in the human family. We support the
struggle of the Palestinian people for nationhood,'' Tutu said.
   ``But we say also, dear brothers and sisters, the Jews have a
right to their independent state as well,'' he said.
   Tutu's endorsement of a Palestinian state has alienated many
Israelis, and the nation's two chief rabbis refused to meet with
the Anglican human rights activist. Israeli media gave only sparse
coverage to Tutu's visit.
   The Palestinian uprising was also the theme of a Christmas
sermon given by Jerusalem's Roman Catholic patriarch, Michel
Sabbah, at midnight mass in St. Catherine's basilica on Manger
Square.
   ``How can we celebrate Christmas with what we are going through,
with our sons killed or in prison?'' asked Sabbah, the first Arab
appointed to his post. ``Despite all that is happening to you, you
will win, in the end you will win.
   ``To the Jewish people, we say the same thing: love and
forgiveness.''
   Since the uprising began Dec. 8, 1987, at least 639 Palestinians
have been killed and 43 Israelis have died.
</TEXT>

</DOC>