<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0151 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1947EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Women'sYear     12-18 0488</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Women's Year,530</SECOND>
<HEAD>NOW Fund Lists Advances, Setbacks</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HARRY F. ROSENTHAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The swearing in of a congresswoman, a pair of
marches and the election of two pro-choice candidates for governor
were among the top advances for women's rights in 1989, according
to a survey released Monday by an advocacy group.
   A report of increasing risks to women's health because of
cigarette smoking and breast cancer, a series of Supreme Court
decisions on job discrimination and a presidential veto of a bill
to permit use of Medicaid funds for abortions were among the most
important setbacks, according to the Legal Defense and Education
Fund of the National Organization for Women.
   Another setback was the Webster decision in the Supreme Court
that, the defense fund said, ``provided states with new authority
and encouragement to limit a woman's right to abortion, although
technically not overturning its 1973 decision in Roe v. Wade.''
   Listed under ``Terrific Trends,'' was a congressional move to
provide more child care options for America's families and the
expansion of the rights of gay and lesbian people living together.
   ``We'll look back on 1989 as a watershed year,'' said Helen
Neuborne, executive director of the fund.
   ``Setbacks for women's reproductive and employment rights
renewed the challenges to the women's movement and revitalized
women's activism,'' Ms. Neuborne said. ``Public opinion polls show
that the overwhelming majority of women recognize and appreciate
feminism's achievements and realize that a strong movement is still
needed.''
   The survey listed 150 events of 1989 and singled out eight as
top advances.
   They were:
   _The 27th woman, an all-time high, sworn in as a member of the
House of Representatives.
   _A record settlement of $14 million in back pay in a case
charging race and sex discrimination against employees of the
Harris Trust and Savings Bank in Chicago.
   _The turnout for women's rights marches in April and November.
   _An injunction upheld by a federal appeals court barring
protesters from blocking access to abortion clinics.
   _The rejection by the Florida State Legislature of anti-choice
proposals and a state Supreme Court ruling striking down a parent's
consent requirement for girls under 18 seeking an abortion.
   _The election of pro-choice gubernatorial candidates in New
Jersey and Virginia.
   _New protections in the federal Fair Housing Act for families
with children.
   _Rejection by the Canadian Supreme Court of an injuction won by
a woman's former boyfriend that barred her from having an abortion.
   Setbacks listed by the fund:
   _A series of decisions by the Supreme Court cutting back the
rights of workers to be protected from sex and race discrimination
in employment
   _Statistics showing nearly 10 percent of AIDS cases were women
and nearly two percent were children under 13.
   _An article in the Harvard Business Review advocating a ``mommy
track'' in business.
   _The Webster decision.
   _President Bush's veto of the Medicaid bill.
   _The new findings on cigarette smoking and breast cancer.
</TEXT>

</DOC>