<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0205 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0944EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Japan-Nissan     12-19 0483</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Japan-Nissan,0499</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nissan's Exports Expected to Rise 0.2 Percent Next Year</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERRIL JONES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nissan Motor Co. expects exports to rise 0.2
percent next year but overseas production to increase by 7 percent,
officials of Japan's second biggest automaker said Tuesday.
   Exports are expected to reach 1.07 million vehicles with
overseas production totaling 683,000 vehicles, Nissan Managing
Director Kiyofumi Morimoto told a news conference.
   Domestic production is likely to rise 3 percent to 2.44 million
vehicles, while domestic sales will increase 4 percent to 1.37
million, Morimoto said.
   He said Nissan's increased output will not contribute to trade
friction with the United States or other trading partners ``because
there will be a gradual shift to production overseas at the expense
of domestic production.''
   By 1992, he said, Nissan expects overseas production to rise to
1 million cars and trucks, and domestic production to stand at some
2.5 million vehicles, including 1 million exports, making half of
all Nissans sold overseas manufactured in Japan.
   Projected domestic sales by 1992 of 1.5 million vehicles are in
line with Nissan's effort to capture 30 percent of Japan's domestic
market, Morimoto said.
   Currently Nissan's market share is 23.8 percent, but the
automaker hopes to gain 1 percentage point a year for the next
several years, he said.
   Nissan also will consolidate its operations in North America
from next year under a new umbrella company, Morimoto said.
   Nissan North America Inc. will oversee research and development,
sales, finance and other operations in the U.S. market, and
coordinate the activities of Nissan's 10 U.S. subsidiaries.
   ``The establishment of NNA in the United States will give Nissan
a tripolar corporate management structure, with integrated
operations headquarters in Japan, North America and Europe,''
Nissan President Yutaka Kume said in a statement. ``We decided to
establish NNA in order to promote the growth of our U.S. operations
as truly American firms.''
   ``The authority to make decisions will be gradually transferred
from Tokyo to this company,'' Morimoto said. ``They will have more
and more responsibility for making decisions for our business
activities in the United States such as model lineups and
marketing.''
   Capitalized at $2 million and based in Los Angeles, Nissan North
America will be established Jan. 1 with 30 staff members, and grow
to some 100 in a few years, Morimoto said.
   The firm's president will be Yoshikazu Hanawa, currently a
Nissan managing director and chairman of Nissan Motor Corp. USA,
Morimoto said.
   The automaker considered naming an American to head its U.S.
operations but decided on Hanawa because ``the main job is
coordinating Nissan subsidiaries, the central player is obviously
going to be Nissan Tokyo,'' Morimoto said. ``One who is most versed
in this is a Japanese (who) is the best choice for this company.''
   He said he expected an American would eventually take over the
job, although he did not say when.
</TEXT>

</DOC>