<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0182 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1459EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-YE--Chronology'89 3rdLd-Writethru b0623-b0624 12-29
0800</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-YE--Chronology '89, 3rd Ld-Writethru, b0623-b0624,0845</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv00</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release in Year-End Editions</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: UPDATES Romania and Panama entries at end of second take with
recent events. Leads b0623-b0624 of Dec. 22.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Twelve Months of Historic Change</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a chronology of news events in 1989:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   JAN. 4 _ U.S. Navy F-14s shoot down two Libyan MiGs over
Mediterranean.
   JAN. 7 _ Emperor Hirohito of Japan dies after 62 years on throne
and is succeeded by his son, Crown Prince Akihito.
   JAN. 10 _ Cubans begin troop pullout from Angola.
   JAN. 16 _ Motorcyclist shot by policeman in Miami, sparking
rioting by blacks. Policeman later convicted on manslaughter
charges.
   JAN. 17 _ Disturbed gunman opens fire on Stockton, Calif.,
schoolyard, killing five children and wounding 30 other students
and teachers.
   JAN. 20 _ George Bush inaugurated 41st president of United
States.
   JAN. 22 _ San Francisco 49ers defeat Cincinnati Bengals 20-16 in
final minute of Super Bowl XXIII.
   JAN. 24 _ Serial killer Ted Bundy executed in Florida.
   JAN. 27 _ Political extremist Lyndon LaRouche sentenced to 15
years in prison for conspiracy and mail fraud.
   FEB. 3 _ Strongman Alfredo Stroessner ousted as Paraguayan
leader.
   FEB. 11 _ Barbara Harris consecrated first female bishop of
Episcopal Church.
   FEB. 14 _ Union Carbide agrees to pay $470 million settlement in
deadly gas leak at Bhopal, India. Ayatollah Khomeini orders
assassination of author Salman Rushdie as riots in India and
Pakistan over Rushdie's ``Satanic Verses'' kill 19.
   FEB. 15 _ Soviets complete withdrawal from Afghanistan.
   FEB. 24 _ Nine passengers aboard United Flight 811 killed when
large hole opens in Boeing 747 after takeoff from Honolulu.
   FEB. 27 _ Four days of rioting begins in Venezuela, touched off
by price increases. More than 300 die.
   MARCH 4 _ Machinists strike Eastern Airlines. Pilots and flight
attendents honor picket lines.
   MARCH 8 _ Daily artillery barrages between Christian and Syrian
forces and their militia allies begin in Beirut. At least 930 die
before cease-fire takes hold Sept. 22.
   MARCH 9 _ President Bush's nominee for defense secretary, John
Tower, loses Senate ratification vote.
   MARCH 14 _ Lebanese hijacker Fawaz Younis, brought to United
States to stand trial, found guilty of air piracy in 1985 hijacking.
   MARCH 24 _ Tanker Exxon Valdez spills more than 10 million
gallons of oil in Alaska's Prince William Sound.
   MARCH 26 _ Soviet Union holds first nationwide multicandidate
elections in 70 years.
   APRIL 4 _ Richard M. Daley, son of former mayor, elected mayor
of Chicago.
   APRIL 5 _ Solidarity legalized in Poland.
   APRIL 7 _ Soviet nuclear sub sinks in Norwegian Sea, killing 42
sailors.
   APRIL 11 _ Bodies found near Mexico-Texas border, in ritualistic
sacrifice-drug slayings. Fifteen bodies eventually found and
several suspects captured.
   APRIL 14 _ Seven people killed in California winery rampage;
suspect Ramon Salcido captured five days later.
   APRIL 15 _ Crowd crush at soccer match in Sheffield, England,
kills 95.
   APRIL 19 _ Gun turret explodes on USS Iowa, killing 47 sailors.
   APRIL 25 _ Japan's Prime Minister Takeshita announces he will
resign in ongoing Recruit political bribery scandal.
   APRIL 26 _ Pennsylvania lottery jackpot of $100 million divided
among 14 winning tickets.
   MAY 3 _ Yasser Arafat says call for destruction of Israel in PLO
charter ``null and void.''
   MAY 4 _ Oliver North convicted on three counts in Iran-Contra
affair, acquitted on nine.
   MAY 10 _ Panamanian leader Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega annuls
elections after opposition wins by 3-1 margin.
   MAY 17 _ More than 1 million Chinese pro-democracy demonstrators
take to Beijing's streets. Hijacker Mohammed Ali Hamadi convicted
and sentenced to life for TWA hijacking and killing of U.S. Navy
diver.
   MAY 31 _ Speaker of the House Jim Wright announces resignation
in face of ethics problems. Thomas Foley later succeeds him.
   JUNE 3 _ Chinese troops firing indiscriminately march on crowds
in Beijing, killing hundreds, possibly thousands. Revolutionary
leader Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini dies in Iran.
   JUNE 4 _ Gas explosion in Soviet Union engulfs two passing
trains, killing 645. Solidarity overwhelmingly defeats Communist
Party in Polish parliamentary elections.
   JUNE 24-25 _ Oil spills in Texas, Delaware, and Rhode Island.
   JULY 3 _ Supreme Court grants broad authority to states to
restrict women's rights to terminate pregnancies but leaves intact
its 1973 decision legalizing abortion.
   JULY 6 _ Palestinian steers Israeli bus into ravine, killing 16.
Last Pershing 1A missiles scrapped.
   JULY 12 _ French farmer on shooting spree kills 14, injures 11.
   JULY 17 _ Maiden flight of B-2 stealth bomber.
   JULY 18 _ Actress Rebecca Schaeffer, co-star of television's
``My Sister Sam,'' age 21, shot to death by obsessive fan.
   JULY 19 _ United DC-10 crashes while attempting emergency
landing in Sioux City, Iowa _ 112 dead, 184 survivors.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>