<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0226EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Panama-CrisisPopularity     12-21 0712</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Crisis Popularity,700</SECOND>
<HEAD>Military Moves Boost Presidential Popularity _ For a While</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HARRY F. ROSENTHAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When American blood is shed, Americans rally
around the flag. Remember the Maine. Pearl Harbor. Mayaguez,
Grenada and the unsuccessful Iran hostage rescue.
   The doubts come later.
   When the casualties are tolled and the troops have returned,
there may be rethinking. But the immediate reaction of the American
people is to be on the president's side.
   Sure enough, the first of the surveys, a tally of viewers by
Cable News Network on Wednesday afternoon, showed 91 percent
supporting the American action in Panama.
   It's the Roman candle effect, says Stephen Hess, a Brookings
Institution scholar.
   ``It goes pop,'' he says. ``It's an immediate burst into the
air, but like a Roman candle, it also tends to fall quickly. In
short, it's like a shot of adrenalin in the body politic.''
   If the Panama operation had come close to an election, Hess
says, ``that Roman candle burst of color in the air would have been
very valuable.''
   Military actions like the one in Panama tend to wipe other
troublesome issues off the front page.
   ``It's hard to keep two balls bouncing and it's impossible with
three balls,'' says Hess. ``It's the crisis of the moment, like the
children's game where paper covers rock and rock breaks scissors.
This is the newest one in and will immediately take precedent.''
   Bush, for instance, had been under fire for sending a delegation
to China while the memories of Tiananmen Square were still fresh.
The latest development in that story came Monday when the White
House conceded it had made an earlier, high-level visit only a
month after the Chinese massacre of student demonstrators.
   On Wednesday, with gunfire in Panama City and smoke in the San
Miguelito neighborhood, the troublesome subject of China had faded,
at least for a while.
   In 1983, President Reagan faced sharp questions when more than
200 U.S. Marines and sailors were killed by a suicide terrorist
bomb in Beirut. Just two days later, Reagan sent troops to the
Caribbean island of Grenada and elicited an outpouring of patriotic
support.
   A New York Times-CBS News poll taken after the bombing in Beirut
found ``substantially'' more Americans approved of the U.S.
military presence there than a month earlier. It also found that a
slight majority approved of the Grenada invasion.
   Reagan's approval rating improved three points, to 49 percent,
after those two events. But the Times noted that Reagan ``thus far
has not become the beneficiary of the sharp upturn of approval that
presidents often enjoy after a foreign crisis.''
   Jimmy Carter, not the most popular of recent presidents, got a
46 percent approval for his handling of the Iran hostage crisis of
1979-1980 in a Newsweek poll taken after the aborted plan to rescue
the Americans. Seventy-one percent said Carter was right in the
attempt; only 18 percent disagreed.
   When Reagan sent American planes to bomb Libya in 1986, a USA
Today poll found 84 percent of the American people would support
another attack on that country if it were linked to another act of
terrorism. And more than two-thirds of 534 adults surveyed in an
NBC News-Wall Street Journal poll an hour after the attacks
supported the strike.
   Gerald Ford sent American sea, air and ground forces to rescue
39 U.S. crewmen when their container ship Mayaguez was captured by
Cambodians in 1975. The operation cost more lives than it saved,
but the president's approval rating in a Gallup Poll rose by 11
percent _ one of the sharpest gains ever recorded. The previous
high was Richard Nixon's 17-point rise in approval after the
Vietnam peace settlement in January 1973.
   While the national adrenalin is flowing, policymakers can
announce news that otherwise might be controversial. As proof,
Secretary of State James A. Baker III on Wednesday notified
Congress that the U.S. embassy in Moscow will be torn down because
it is riddled with listening devices put there by the Soviets. A
new facility will cost an estimated $500 million.
   At any other time that might have received critical reviews and
widespread attention, especially during a Christmas-time news
drought. With troops in Panama, it's possible that hardly anyone
will notice.
</TEXT>

</DOC>