<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1810EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-ColtBuyout     12-24 0419</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colt Buyout,0433</SECOND>
<HEAD>Connecticut: Uncertain Gun Market Makes State Wary of Colt Buyout
Role</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARTFORD, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Connecticut officials are reconsidering a
possible investment in the buyout of Colt Industries Inc.'s
firearms division because of uncertainty in the market for guns,
state Treasurer Francisco L. Borges said.
   The state's hesitation is causing concern among the investor
group seeking to buy the firearms division. The group, CF Holdings
Corp., sees Connecticut's investment as the last hurdle before new
owners can take over the troubled gunmaker.
   Borges said state officials have several concerns about joining
the buyout, including a declining world market for handguns and the
possibility of new gun control legislation that could hamper the
new company.
   However, Borges said, ``This does not mean we won't get to a
point where we have something acceptable,'' and he added that talks
were continuing.
   Colt Industries put the Firearms Division on the market last
spring and agreed in late November to sell the division to CF
Holdings in a deal that was to include the state as a shareholder.
   CF Holdings includes Anthony Autorino, former president of
United Technologies' Hamilton Standard division and now president
of Shared Technologies in Wethersfield, Conn.; Richard F. Gamble,
another former Hamilton Standard president; and Ronald F. Stilwell,
Colt Firearm's vice president for military sales.
   The price of the deal was never disclosed but analysts estimated
it could range from $50 million to $200 million. The state has
refused to disclose the size of its possible investment in the
project.
   Autorino said the investor group was becoming anxious about the
state's hesitation.
   ``We have a firm price and an agreement, and time's getting
short,'' he said.
   One obstacle to completing the sale was removed earlier this
week when the United Auto Workers and the investors who would run
the plant agreed to a full settlement of the 3-year-old UAW-Colt
strike and endorsed a contract to return to work.
   ``The union was supposed to be the last hurdle in the deal,''
said Philip Wheeler, chief negotiator fo UAW Local 376. ``That was
the agreement and everybody was happy the union settled. This deal
should be done now.''
   Wheeler would not disclose the details of the strike settlement
and the new union contract Friday ``because financing for the deal
is still pending.''
   ``This is a difficult situation, but as far as we are concerned,
we had an agreement with the state,'' Wheeler said. ``We are still
confident (Borges) will finalize the deal. The deal is still
sound.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>