<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0012EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Romania-Mood     12-28 0765</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Mood,0792</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romanians Jubilant, Yet Wonder At What Life Will Now Bring</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERRY LEONARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A librarian stood in the ashes of a
half million books inside the scorched, shell-pocked walls of the
once prestigious University Library and wondered aloud if Romania
can ever return to normal.
   ``Things are not returning to normal because we don't know what
normality is,'' said librarian Ion Visoiu.
   ``We have to learn how to live as decent, normal beings. We know
about civilized life only from books, from our traditions and from
our parents. Nobody here knows it personally.''
   The burned-out library near the center of Palace Square was
destroyed by the fierce weekend fighting that followed the ouster
of Nicolae Ceausescu, the Communist dictator whose 24-year reign of
terror still frightens and mystifies.
   ``Probably in each of us there is a little of Ceausescu,'' said
Visoiu. ``He wasn't so special. He was rather common. But he was
shrewd enough to get enough power to become a monster.''
   Tanks and armored cars still filled the square on Wednesday
afternoon, but the mood was light and jubilant. Old men embraced
young soldiers. Groups of women handed up pastries and hot coffee
to tank crewmen lounging beside their machine guns, some of which
have bouquets of flowers taped to the barrels.
   Smiling children posed in front of massive tanks for their
parents' cameras. Thousands of people strolled through the square,
gawking at the Royal Palace battered by machine guns, at the ruins
of the library and at other buildings shattered and burned by the
fighting.
   There was still some scattered shooting. After dark, isolated
bursts of automatic weapons fire crackled in the distance.
   ``But there is no fighting here,'' shrugged a smiling soldier in
Palace Square. Ceausescu's dreaded security police had put up a
fierce fight but were reported surrendering by the hundreds after
learning of his execution.
   Glazers were already at work Wednesday replacing some of the
windows shot out along Victoria Street, which leads into the square.
   Apartment dwellers cleared the debris from their balconies
overhead and boarded up bullet-shattered windows.
   Romanians are digging out, preparing to go on with their lives.
   A few blocks south of Palace Square three barbers calmly clipped
hair in their small shop. A line of about 35 people stretched out
in front of a store where cheese and sausage could be bought.
   ``This is just the beginning,'' said Sorin Serb. ``Maybe after a
year we can talk about our political destiny.''
   He looked at the ruins and shell-scarred buildings and shook his
head as he thought about what had happend.
   ``All this in just one day,'' he said. ``There was this
wonderful eruption of the people'' in Bucharest exactly one week
ago.
   A few blocks north of Palace Square scores of people lined up to
buy canned vegetables, bottled juice, cheese and some bags of dry
pasta.
   ``It is the kind of food we had before the revolution but now
you don't need a ration card. The goverment has stopped the exports
of food,'' said one student who asked not to be identified.
   It is a commonly heard complaint in Romania that Ceausescu
exported food for profit while his people went hungry.
   Across the street from the food store about 200 people stood in
line in temperatures just above freezing outside a shop where an
18-wheel truck had just unloaded a huge shipment of frozen beef.
   ``There was nothing like this before. This was for export,''
said the student, suggesting the new government has redirected food
formerly for export to the state stores.
   ``It is a good idea. The first step is to build confidence in
the government,'' he said.
   Others agreed, saying their lives had already changed
dramatically.
   ``I feel completely transformed. Things that did not happen in
30 years happened in a few days. We are not the same men we were on
Dec. 21,'' said Marin Ghezu, a furniture maker in line outside the
meat store.
   That was the day before Ceausescu was overthrown in the revolt.
On Monday, both he and his wife and second-in-command, Elena, were
summarily tried and executed.
   ``Life will be more beautiful than it was before. These changes
will last. They will last for eternity.'' said Ghezu.
   ``We cannot speak any more about the Comunist Party. We cannot
say those words. We must wipe them from our mind,'' said Ghezu.
   ``About what party are you talking?'' a middle-aged woman asked
Ghezu. ``There is no party any more,'' she scolded. ``Do not talk
nonsense. ''
</TEXT>

</DOC>