<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0127 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 2238EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Poll-GuardSuit     12-23 0351</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poll-Guard Suit,0363</SECOND>
<HEAD>Settlement Reported in Ethnic Intimidation Lawsuit</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SANTA ANA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A county Republican Party, two GOP
assemblymen and their campaign workers have agreed to pay $400,000
to settle a lawsuit accusing them of hiring uniformed guards to
intimidate Hispanic voters, a lawyer said.
   Under the proposed settlement, none of the defendants would
admit any wrongdoing, said Darryl Wold, attorney for the Orange
County Republican Party.
   But he said Friday their four insurance companies each would pay
$100,000 to the plaintiffs, five Hispanic voters and the Orange
County Democratic Party.
   A federal judge must approve the settlement. The lawsuit had
been scheduled for trial Jan. 16 in U.S. District Court.
   State and federal agencies are still investigating the posting
of guards at 20 polling places in predominantly Hispanic voter
areas of Santa Ana on Nov. 8, 1988, when Assemblyman Curt Pringle
of Garden Grove defeated Democrat Christian ``Rick'' Thierbach by
843 votes for an Assembly seat.
   The guards carried signs in English and Spanish warning that
non-citizens cannot legally vote.
   Hispanic community leaders complained it was racially motivated
intimidation. County GOP officials responded that the guards were
there only to monitor and report election fraud.
   Pringle and another defendant, Assemblyman John R. Lewis of
Orange, could not be reached for comment Saturday. Calls placed to
their offices rang unanswered, and directory assistance had no home
numbers listed for them.
   Michael G. Balmages, chairman of the county Democratic Party,
praised the settlement but said he was sorry the case would not be
going to trial.
   ``The plaintiffs will not get their day in court and the public
will be deprived of learning more about the illegal,
unconstitutional and highly unethical acts that were committed by
the Orange County Republican Party and the campaign of Mr.
Pringle,'' he said.
   ``A million dollars would not compensate for this infringement
on our civil rights,'' said Reuben Martinez, treasurer of the
county Democratic Party.
   Joseph Remcho, the plaintiffs' chief attorney, expects the
settlement will be approved. He said a court order prevented him
from discussing it further before all parties sign it.
</TEXT>

</DOC>