<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0155 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1929EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-EastGermany 1stLd-Writethru a0657 12-21 0602</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0657,0620</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mitterrand Urges Closer German Ties</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs to include work on opening Brandenburg Gate;
picks up 6th `German unity'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH G. SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   French President Francois Mitterrand urged
closer links between East Germany and Western Europe, but said
Thursday that rash moves toward German unity should be avoided
   Mitterrand met Communist premier Hans Modrow and other political
leaders to express the West's concerns about the possibility of
German unification.
   The two countries signed six agreements, including an economic
and industrial cooperation accord for 1990-94 as well as one on
youth exchanges.
   The French president also discussed cooperation between his
Socialist Party and the East German Communist Party.
   At the Brandenburg Gate, work on creating two pedestrian
crossings immediately north and south of the gate began at 10 p.m.
East German workers used a crane to lift a section of the rounded
top of the wall, then began working on opening the two crossing
points.
   More than 1,000 people on the Western side cheered and set off
firecrackers as work began under floodlights.
   Mitterrand drove by the gate on the eastern side and briefly got
out of his car to look at it shortly before the work began.
   He told the students in Leipzig, the birthplace of the
pro-democracy movement, that ``France set conditions but not a
veto'' on German unification.
   ``German unity is first and foremost an affair for Germans.
France will not stand in the way,'' he said.
   ``Only free, open, democratic elections will permit us to know
exactly what the Germans on the two sides want,'' Mitterrand said
in replies to questions posed by some of the 600 students of
Leipzig's Karl Marx University.
   ``But the German people must take the European balance into
account in its decision,'' he added.
   Since a peaceful people's revolution forced the ouster of the
former hard-line Communist leadership, a growing number of East
Germans have called for quick German reunification.
   In recent weeks, demonstrators at traditional Monday rallies in
Leipzig have carried West German flags and shouted for German unity.
   With World War II memories still fresh in many minds, European
leaders have cautioned against quick unification and its
consequences for postwar stability in Europe.
   Mitterrand said a written treaty could not wipe out ``European
realities created after World War II.''
   Mitterrand arrived in East Berlin on Wednesday a few hours after
West German Chancellor Helmut Kohl departed.
   Kohl and Modrow announced the two countries expected to conclude
a treaty broadly expanding bilateral cooperation in the spring.
   The treaty will provide for practical steps to establish close
links between West Germany and East Germany in many areas.
   Kohl also urged East Germans to be patient about unification,
saying the process could not come overnight and that Germans had to
consider security implications of such a move.
   Meanwhile, a leader of the New Forum opposition group warned
that the 200,000-strong movement faced a growing rift.
   Rolf Henrich, a co-founder of New Forum, said the group's
members were divided on whether to constitute the movement as a
political party or leave it as a loose organization.
   Mitterrand also urged the ouster of Nicolae Ceausescu's
hard-line Communist leadership in Romania, where security forces
have reportedly shot and killed hundreds and possibly thousands of
anti-government demonstrators.
   ``It is a regime of personal, family power that has no honest
reason to remain,'' Mitterrand said during a meeting with East
German students in Leipzig. ``I think that the days of this regime,
in a Europe in full movement, are numbered.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>