<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1339EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Czech-Police     12-19 0377</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Czech-Police,0388</SECOND>
<HEAD>Premier Announces Reforms in Security Forces</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Czechoslovakia, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ONDREJ HEJMA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Premier Marian Calfa said Tuesday
all domestic operations of the dreaded secret police have been
halted.
   ``It is one of our priorities to adjust the work of the Interior
Ministry to the new social conditions and turn this ministry into a
component of state administration based on democratic principles,''
Calfa told Parliament, outlining his domestic and foreign policies.
   ``I can tell you that as of today the operations of the police
force in the field of internal intelligence have been stopped,''
Calfa said.
   In 41 years of Communist rule, secret police agents were
involved in continuous surveillance operations against citizens and
were responsible for the interrogation and harassment of dissidents
and independent thinkers.
   Opposition leader Vaclav Havel, once a dissident playwright and
now the leading contender for president, has spoken about the
constant threat of a house search; that every visitor to his home
was photographed; and every conversation bugged by the Communist
regime.
   Havel's house in downtown Prague was continuously monitored from
a nearby tower, and cameras were installed by the secret police in
other streets where dissidents lived.
   Police have been the target of public anger since they broke up
a peaceful student rally Nov. 17, igniting the pro-democracy
revolution that ended Communist domination.
   ``The police action in the streets of Prague has shaken the
faith of citizens in the police force ... the government is taking
steps to prevent the abuse of security forces against the people of
this country,'' Calfa said.
   A parliamentary commission is investigating the crackdown.
   The new government, the country's first non-Communist-dominated
Cabinet in 41 years, does not include an interior minister,
responsible for all branches of the police including the secret
force. Instead, those functions have been assumed by a three-man
committee consisting of Calfa and two deputy premiers.
   Despite the move to control the secret police, opposition
members and students, fearing a coverup of past misdeeds, have been
patrolling police offices and police archives to prevent the
destruction of incriminating documents.
   Activists in Brno reported last week that police documents were
being burned, including documents from the 1950s and others bearing
the names of well-known dissidents.
</TEXT>

</DOC>