<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0120EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-NorthAppeal     12-23 0356</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-North Appeal,360</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prosecutors Call Oliver North's Appeal Arguments Unsound</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETE YOST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government protected its case against
Oliver L. North from the possible taint of his immunized testimony,
Iran-Contra prosecutors assert in opposing North's bid to get his
convictions reversed.
   In a 70-page federal appeals court brief Friday, prosecutors
characterized as ``legally and factually unsound'' North's argument
that the government won three felony convictions against him
without properly guarding against all use of immunized testimony he
gave on Capitol Hill.
   ``The extraordinary protective procedures undertaken'' by
prosecutors and the court ``assured that North's immunized
testimony did not contribute to his conviction,'' said associate
independent counsel Gerald Lynch.
   Prosecutors in the office of independent counsel Lawrence Walsh
were instructed to avoid learning the ontents of immunized
testimony from any source in the Iran-Contra affair.
   U.S. District Judge Gerhard Gesell, who presided at North's
trial, ``undertook extraordinary efforts to protect North's
rights,'' Lynch said.
   North told the appeals court last month he was convicted with
``a stunning disregard'' for his 5th Amendment rights against
self-incrimination.
   ``North does not contend ... that any of the government's trial
witnesses were discovered as a result of his congressional
testimony, or that a single specific piece of grand jury or trial
evidence was derived from that testimony,'' responded the
prosecution.
   Walsh's office said North ``objects only to the trial court's
alleged failure `to follow the procedures established to protect
core Fifth Amendment rights.'''
   North's appeal is scheduled for argument Feb. 6.
   The prosecution also said Gesell made the correct decision in
quashing North's subpoena seeking to compel former President Reagan
to testify at his trial. North said his activities were authorized
by the president and is raising Reagan's absence at the trial as an
issue on appeal.
   ``North could not identify a single instance where President
Reagan directly told him to formulate a false chronology or to
commit other obstructions,'' said the court filing.
   ``North's almost total lack of direct contact with the president
is apparent'' from evidence collected by Walsh's office and from
North's own testimony at his trial, said the prosecution.
</TEXT>

</DOC>