<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0257 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0845EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-NintendoWorkshop 1stLd-Writethru f0021 12-18 0589</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Nintendo Workshop, 1st Ld - Writethru, f0021,0605</SECOND>
<HEAD>They're Not Santa's Elves _ Elves Have Until Sunday</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 4th graf pvs, `At present ...' to DELETE extraneous `across.'
This also moved on general news wires.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE TIBBITS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>REDMOND, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It's crunch time at Nintendo's only U.S.
repair shop.
   With 800 broken electronic game machines to fix each day, scores
of technicians are working feverishly to get them finished and back
home in time to play the new games placed under Christmas trees.
   When Super Mario won't jump, when the screen goes blank, when
the whole gadget chooses to be a lump of uncooperative plastic, the
place to send the misbehaving merchandise is Nintendo of America's
headquarters in this Seattle suburb.
   In a workroom crammed with testing equipment, TV monitors, spare
computer boards and electronic parts from wounded toys, the 160
technicians try to make things right.
   The home office is the only place in the United States to go
with broken Nintendo Entertainment Systems, game packs and other
products for the popular electronic toy. That will change next
year, says Jon Pedersen, Nintendo director of technical services,
as the company starts opening dozens of service centers around the
country.
   At the moment, however, Pedersen is worried about this week.
   ``Right now we're looking at quite a big load for the Christmas
rush,'' Pedersen said. ``We're trying to do the best we can now to
get everything back to the consumer, which means we have to ship by
Wednesday.''
   They've been making about 800 repairs a day, up from 400 to 500
before the holiday season. On the other hand, with Nintendo selling
9 million more game systems this year, ``there's never really been
a normal load,'' Pedersen said.
   ``It grows with the hardware sales. It never really levels off.''
   Nintendo's Entertainment System, a small computer that lets
owners play games on a TV screen, has been the nation's top-selling
toy the past three years. So far, nearly 20 million systems have
been sold in this country, plus about 101 million game cartridges.
   The company expects the game system will be in 22 percent of all
U.S. households by the end of 1989, said spokesman Bill White.
   Pedersen says the machines and games are pretty reliable, with a
problem rate of about one-tenth of 1 percent. But with about 120
million control decks and game cartridges sold, that works out to
something like 120,000 repair jobs.
   The No. 1 troublemaker for Nintendo ``is simply dirty contacts
between the game pack and the control deck,'' Pedersen said.
   ``Basically, because of the age group of the individual who uses
this product, there tends to be a lot of sugar.''
   The machines don't like carpet fuzz either, so when you play on
the living room rug, put something under deck, Pedersen says.
   Nintendo devices carry a 90-day warranty. After that, it's a
flat $30 to fix control decks and $10 for each cartridge, no matter
the problem.
   ``Well, we will call them to ask why we got a sack of parts,''
Pedersen said. ``But I don't think to date we've refused a repair.''
   Starting early next year, Nintendo will open repair centers at
some of its ``World of Nintendo'' retail outlets. By the end of
1990, there should be about 200 service outlets, each capable of
doing any repair the main workshop can.
   That won't mean Pedersen will be cutting back.
   ``The way the workload increases around here, I don't see it,''
he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>