<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0218 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1949EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Panama 5thLd-Writethru 1stAdd 12-20 0598</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Panama, 5th Ld-Writethru, 1st Add,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHN: that's good.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The Organization of American States met in emergency session at
the request of Panamanian ambassador Jose Maria Cabrera, a holdover
from Noriega's regime.
   He told the gathering, ``Under no circumstances will we accept
some supposed leaders who are puppets imposed by the United
States,'' referring to the provisional government headed by
Guillermo Endara and recognized by the Bush administration.
   Endara asked the OAS in a letter to recognize Lawrence Chewning
Fabrega as his designated representative but the members decided to
recognize Cabrera, instead.
   Peru withdrew its ambassador to the United States in protest
``until the invading troops withdraw,'' according to a statement
from the Peruvian embassy.
   Bush, laying out the reasons for the military action, cited
Noriega's declaration last Friday of a state of war, the slaying of
an American officer last Saturday and the manhandling of an
American serviceman and his wife.
   ``Gen. Noriega's reckless threats and attacks upon Americans in
Panama created an imminent danger to the 35,000 American citizens
in Panama,'' Bush said. ``As president, I have no higher obligation
than to safeguard the lives of American citizens.
   ``And that is why I directed our armed forces to protect the
lives of American citizens in Panama and bring Gen. Noriega to
justice in the United States.''
   With Noriega on the run, Bush said the United States was lifting
economic sanctions against Panama and freeing Panamanian assets
frozen in U.S. banks.
   Baker said Bush decided Sunday to use force against Noriega.
   After that decision was made, Baker said, the United States
received intelligence reports that Noriega might launch a commando
attack against Americans in an urban residential neighborhood.
   While saying it was unclear whether the report was reliable,
Baker told reporters that if Americans had been killed or
terrorized, ``you would be asking us today, `Why didn't you act to
prevent this kind of violence against our citizens.'''
   The secretary added, ``I'm not going to tell you that the crisis
in Panama has been totally resolved. ... But Manuel Noriega, who
was yesterday's `maximum leader' is today's hunted fugitive.''
   Ever since Noriega was indicted in Florida on drug-trafficking
charges in February 1988, the United States has been trying to
force him from power through economic sanctions and diplomatic
pressure.
   The Soviet Union condemned the action, saying the United States
``must immediately stop its armed intervention.'' British Prime
Minister Margaret Thatcher praised it as ``a courageous decision''
and said, ``Someone has to uphold democracy.''
   Former President Ronald Reagan, who had unsuccessfully tried to
force Noriega from power, said in Los Angeles, ``There comes a time
when a president must take action. That time has come.''
   Defense Secretary Dick Cheney said the planning for a military
strike ``had been in existence for some time. It was one of the
first items I was briefed on'' when he took office last spring.
   Gen. Colin Powell, chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, said
of Noriega, ``As a practical matter, we have decapitated him from
the dictatorship of this country and he is now a fugitive and will
be treated as such. ... We will chase him and we will find him.''
   At Bush's suggestion, Vice President Dan Quayle called the two
newly installed Panamanian vice presidents, Billy Ford and Ricardo
Arias Calderon, to congratulate them and say he looked forward to
visiting them in a free and independent Panama, said a spokesman,
David Beckwith.
   Quayle is considered likely to attend a presidential
inauguration in Honduras on Jan. 27, and sources said a visit to
Panama then is under consideration.
</TEXT>

</DOC>