<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0098 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1338EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Czech-Apology     12-18 0506</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Czech-Apology,0521</SECOND>
<HEAD>Communist Newspaper Apologizes For Past Attacks</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Czechoslovakia, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ONDREJ HEJMA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After two decades of virulent
attacks on dissidents and reformers, the Communist Party's daily
newspaper apologized Monday to ``all those who were hurt'' on its
pages.
   ``Over the past years our paper printed a number of stories
which our editors cannot be proud of,'' Rude Pravo's new editor,
Zdenek Porybny, wrote in a commentary.
   He admitted that ``serious political debate was abandoned in
favor of personal attacks and the scandalization of people whose
opinions differed from those of the Communist leadership.''
   The newspaper tried to discredit Alexander Dubcek, the leader of
the failed ``Prague Spring'' reforms of 1968, and former dissident
Vaclav Havel, now a leading presidential candidate.
   ``Stories like `Stool Pigeon', `Who is Vaclav Havel,' `Dubcek's
Journey From Tragedy to Farce' and others did not express ... the
(true) attitudes of most of the paper's editors,'' according to the
commentary.
   In July, Rude Pravo accused Dubcek of ``naive blindness,'' and
of being a figure whose words were ``full of megalomania.''
   One frequent tactic by the newspaper was to imply that its
targets had fascist links.
   In one of its articles, Rude Pravo recounted that a ballroom in
central Prague built by Havel's family was used by the Nazis during
the occupation in World War II.
   ``An apology to all those who were hurt on the pages of Rude
Pravo is appropriate and on the behalf of the paper's editors and
myself ... I am doing just that,'' Porybny said.
   Porybny replaced Zdenek Horeni as editor-in-chief of the paper
in a leadership reshuffle that followed a month of sweeping
political change.
   It is just one of several changes in Czechoslovakia's
state-controlled media. A new editor has taken charge of the state
news agency CTK, former government spokesman Miroslav Pavel has
moved to head state TV, and a new editor-in-chief also has been
appointed at state radio.
   Czechoslovakia's opposition has forced an end to Communist
domination in the government and the reforms have swept through the
media, which now criticize the mistakes of the previous hard-line
Communist leadership.
   But a statement issued Monday by Rude Pravo editors fired after
the 1968 ``Prague Spring'' reforms said the changes are not enough.
   ``As long as the paper does not say goodbye to people whose
names have become symbols of an ignorant policy of force, stupidity
and total professional failure, and as long as the paper is not
credible, it will do more harm than good to progressive forces in
the (Communist) party,'' the statement concluded.
   Pavel, who has overseen drastic changes at that have brought
long-banned artists and exiled politicians and others back onto the
TV screen after 20 years, said last week he is also fighting
demands for even more change, particularly in the news department.
   Sources at state TV say its reporters are seeking the
resignation of at least eight editors deemed to have been too
active in pushing the old policies in the past.
</TEXT>

</DOC>