<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0144 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0753EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv06   12-26 0400</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv06,0418</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv06</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Saturday, Jan. 6</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is Saturday, Jan. 6, the sixth day of 1990. There are 359
days left in the year.
   Today's highlight in history:
   On Jan. 6, 1838, Samuel Morse publicly demonstrated his
telegraph for the first time, in Morristown, N.J.
   On this date:
   In 1412, according to tradition, Joan of Arc was born in
Domremy, France.
   In 1540, King Henry VIII of England married his fourth wife,
Anne of Cleves. (The marriage lasted about six months.)
   In 1759, George Washington and Martha Dandridge Custis were
married.
   In 1912, New Mexico became the 47th state.
   In 1919, the 26th president of the United States, Theodore
Roosevelt, died at his home in Oyster Bay, N.Y. at age 60.
   In 1941, President Franklin D. Roosevelt delivered his ``Four
Freedoms'' speech in which he outlined his goals of freedom of
speech and worship, and freedom from want and fear.
   In 1942, the Pan American Airways ``Pacific Clipper'' arrived in
New York after making the first round-the-world trip by a
commercial airplane. (The trip, which required more than 200 hours'
flying time, began Dec. 2, 1941.)
   In 1950, Britain recognized the Communist government of China.
   In 1982, truck driver William G. Bonin was convicted in Los
Angeles as the ``freeway killer'' who tortured and murdered ten
young men and boys in southern California.
   Ten years ago: India held a second round of voting in
parliamentary elections that resulted in a major victory for the
party of former Prime Minister Indira Gandhi.
   Five years ago: U.S. Secretary of State George P. Shultz and
Soviet Foreign Minister Andrei A. Gromyko arrived in Geneva for
superpower arms talks.
   One year ago: The United States presented photographic evidence
to the U.N. Security Council to justify its shootdown of two Libyan
jet fighters as self-defense, evidence that the Libyan ambassador
said was faked.
   Today's birthdays: Comedian Joey Adams is 79. Actress Loretta
Young is 77. Actor-comedian Danny Thomas is 76. Pollster Louis
Harris is 69. Singer Earl Scruggs is 66. Former automaker John Z.
DeLorean is 65. Singer Sylvia Syms is 56. Actress Bonnie Franklin
is 46. Golfer Nancy Lopez is 33.
   Thought for today: ``All ages of belief have been great; all of
unbelief have been mean.'' _ Ralph Waldo Emerson, American
essayist, poet and philosopher (1803-1882).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sat Jan 6</NOTE>

</DOC>