<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1329EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Panama-FutureArmy Bjt   12-21 0779</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Future Army, Bjt,780</SECOND>
<HEAD>Panama Strike Example of Army's Hoped-For Future Role</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSANNE M. SCHAFER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Military Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush's nighttime airlift of
thousands of soldiers to a battle zone in Panama was a
here-and-now, guns and planes example of what some Pentagon
planners see as ``the Army of the future.''
   With the Pentagon facing likely budget restraints in the coming
years _ and with a declining Soviet threat suggesting deep troop
reductions in Europe _ senior Army planners have proposed that
their service be molded into a lighter, more flexible fighting
force that can be ordered to hot spots within hours.
   Since the Panamanian strike came as Defense Secretary Dick
Cheney was hammering out the Pentagon's five-year budget
projections, some senior Army officials indicated that the timing
couldn't hurt their cause.
   ``We made a decision, and in almost no time at all we were
putting our paratroopers and our Rangers on airplanes and sending
them down there,'' Army Gen. Tom W. Kelly, the director of
operations for the Pentagon's Joint Staff, told reporters on
Wednesday.
   ``I don't know that there's another country in the world that
can do that,'' Kelly said.
   There were some advantages in the Panama situation that wouldn't
necessarily be present in many foreign battle scenes. The Army was
able to do months of on-the-scene planning in Panama and link up
with an established fighting force of some 13,000 soldiers, sailors
and helicopter gunship pilots already based there.
   As well, commanders could count on cooperation from the Air
Force, Navy and Marines. The Army would like to plan on that in the
future, but the past has shown that service rivalries can make for
messy military operations.
   Some of the ideas for revamping the Army were first put forward
this year by the Army chief of staff, Gen. Carl Vuono. That was in
a ``white paper'' that envisioned a pared-down force that would
rely more on air assault, light infantry and mechanized units _ the
very mix that was used in the Panamanian operation.
   ``The Army of the future is one that is versatile ... an Army
that can be forward deployed ... albeit at smaller numbers, an Army
that has a contingency package that can go worldwide, an Army that
has a mix of heavy, light and special operations forces,'' Vuono
told reporters in October.
   Army plans envision slashing the current 764,000-strong force to
630,000 by 1994, Army sources have said.
   Gen. Gordon R. Sullivan, the Army's deputy chief of staff for
operations and plans, predicted in an interview last week that by
1995-96, ``you'll see more (of the nation's forces) in the
continental U.S.,'' but that those soldiers will be ``capable of
responding to any contingency.''
   Sullivan added that while the Army is preparing for the future,
its leaders are determined not to repeat what they consider the
mistakes of the past _ such as the post-World War II draw-downs
that caught the military off guard at the break out of the Korean
War.
   While America's new military will be a smaller fighting force,
he said it should be trained to take on new roles and be prepared
to fight in Third World arenas, battle the nation's drug scourge or
help deal with such disasters as Hurricane Hugo and the San
Francisco-area earthquake.
   ``The Army must maintain its relevance to respond to various
requirements,'' Sullivan said.
   The planning officer said he is confident that the Army ``has
the structure to be able to respond to change,'' even though the
challenges of the future ``may be difficult to see'' at this time.
   ``We know where we're going and we know what we should look like
when we get there,'' he said.
   Army officers familiar with Vuono's plans walked the Pentagon's
halls with smiles on their faces after the Panama intervention,
touting the strike as an example of their future fighting force,
even if it is a smaller one.
   ``Versatile, deployable, lethal,'' chanted one Army colonel _
using the three catchwords that define the force's new proposals.
   ``Eighteen hours from stand to start _ it's the Army of the
future,'' said an Army general of the time required for the
Panamanian deployment.
   Another colonel pointed to the complex effort involved in
ferrying troops from both East and West U.S. coasts and dropping
some 3,000 paratroopers from 1,200 feet in the air, so that they
could team up with mechanized units and helicopters that had been
moved into Panama in advance.
   ``There wasn't one life lost in that nighttime parachute drop _
in World War II, they expected to lose between 10 to 15 percent of
their men,'' one officer said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>