<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0658EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-Journalists     12-22 0614</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Journalists,0637</SECOND>
<HEAD>Spanish Photographer Killed, Two Others Wounded in Crossfire</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RAFAEL CANDANEDO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first foreign journalist known to
die in the U.S. invasion was a photographer for a Spanish newspaper
killed in ``friendly'' crossfire between American troops in the
capital.
   Two other photojournalists were wounded Thursday in the same
exchange.
   A CBS news producer seized by Panamanian gunmen on Wednesday was
still missing today. He had been grabbed the Marriott Hotel before
it was secured by U.S. troops in the force that invaded to depose
Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   In the action, a Mexican television crew was briefly detained by
Panamanian gunmen.
   Juan Antonio Rodriguez, a photographer for Spain's largest
newspaper, El Pais, was killed Thursday outside the Marriott Hotel,
said Tomas Lozano, the Spanish ambassador.
   Rodriguez died when American troops mistakenly fired upon each
other in the hotel parking lot, said Maruja Torres, a correspondent
for El Pais.
   Patrick Chauvel, a French photographer for the Sygma photo
agency, was shot in the stomach, said Jacques Rummelhardt, France's
ambassador to Panama.
   Chauvel was listed in serious condition at the U.S. military's
Gorgas Hospital, Rummelhardt said. He was on assignment for
Newsweek magazine.
   Malcolm Linton, an English photographer for the Reuters news
agency, was shot in the leg, said Tom Brown, a Reuter editor.
Linton was listed in good condition at Gorgas Hospital, Brown said.
   U.S. troops had occupied the hotel Wednesday night to rescue
trapped guests and were evacuating them Thursday when the incident
occurred.
   Six journalists were standing outside in the parking lot when a
U.S. armored personnel carrier began approaching, Torres said.
   Apparently thinking the personnel carrier belonged to Panamanian
forces, U.S. troops inside the hotel yelled at the journalists to
get out of the way, then opened fire as they scattered, said Torres.
   ``They fired on us savagely, they don't have any respect for
journalists,'' said Torres.
   The personnel carrier, which turned out to be American, returned
fire briefly, said Torres.
   The journalists took refuge in a nearby house and were trapped
for a time by gunfire in the area.
   In New York, CBS asked U.S. and Central American officials for
help in finding missing news producer Jon Meyersohn, according to
CBS News President David Burke.
   Gunmen abducted Meyersohn and ABC News producer Robert Campos on
Wednesday morning in the lobby of the Marriott. Campos was freed
unharmed that afternoon.
   A television crew for Mexico's private Televisa network was
detained for 2{ hours Thursday by members of the civilian Dignity
Battalions that support Noriega.
   Televisa correspondent Rita Ganem said she and three cameramen
were confronted by the militiamen in the city of Concepcion, about
15 miles east of Panama's border with Costa Rica.
   The paramilitaries took their passports and other
identification, money and jewelry before releasing them, Ms. Ganem
said. The journalists made their way back to Costa Rica. Also
detained were cameramen Alfredo Acosta, Antonio Jasso and Anastasio
Valle.
   Meanwhile, a London-based television news agency charged
Thursday that a U.S. Army soldier confiscated the tape of a TV
cameraman who shot pictures of American troops surrounding the
Nicaraguan and Cuban embassies in Panama City.
   Robert Sullivan, New York bureau chief of Worldwide Television
News, said the agency planned to file a complaint with the
Pentagon. WTN is co-owned by ABC and includes ABC and CNN among its
clients.
   Sullivan said cameraman Alejandro Carbonnel was shooting
pictures when an army sergeant approached him and confiscated the
videotape. The unidentified soldier said Carbonnel ``had to have
permission from the Southern Command to shoot here,'' Sullivan said.
   The Southern Command is responsible for all U.S. military
operations in Latin America.
</TEXT>

</DOC>