<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0088 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1228EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Ryan'sDonation     12-29 0375</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ryan's Donation,0385</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lottery Winner Donates Money To Troubled Family</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ORLANDO, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winner of Florida's record $55 million
lottery prize has gone to the aid of a beleaguered family by making
a $10,000 donation for a 13-year-old girl who needs a kidney
transplant.
   Lottery winner Sheelah Ryan, who established a foundation to
help the needy, said Thursday she hoped the money would prompt
others to help the family of Bob and Donna Armstrong, whose other
daughter was kidnapped and killed in a still-unsolved case.
   Christina Armstrong, 13, suffers from Alport's Syndrome, an
incurable hereditary disease, and is undergoing kidney dialysis
while awaiting a suitable transplant. The Armstrongs expect to
incur bills totaling $100,000.
   Their 6-year-old daughter Regina Mae disappeared from in front
of the family home more than four years ago. The girl's skull was
discovered in a rural area, but police have never found her killer.
   ``I feel very strong that this family has suffered enough,'' Ms.
Ryan said. ``And the foundation cares very deeply about helping
children.''
   The foundation has pledged money to a number of causes,
including $1,000 to college students trying to find homes for stray
cats and $500 to a high school student who found and returned a
$100,000 check.
   The girls' father, Bob Armstrong, recalled Wednesday that he
used to deliver salt for Ms. Ryan's water softener about five years
ago, when she was a real estate saleswoman living in a mobile home.
   Ms. Ryan won the big prize in 1988, but continues to work in
real estate and lives quietly.
   ``I'm sure she wouldn't remember me,'' Armstrong said after
hearing of the donation. ``I was just a long-haired, bearded thing
who was always sweating from hauling around heavy equipment. This
is one heck of a coincidence.''
   Ms. Ryan did not remember him, but she remembered the story of
Regina Mae's disappearance.
   She got approval from a majority of the Ryan Foundation's board
of directors to donate $5,000, then decided to give $5,000 of her
own money.
   ``The people of central Florida have been very good about
contributing to the poor and the homeless, but maybe we can start
something off to get them to contribute here,'' Ms. Ryan said.
``This family has had enough.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>