<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0168 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1558EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Homeless-Mayors     12-20 0709</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Homeless-Mayors,670</SECOND>
<BYLINE>`The Face of Hunger Is The Face of the Young Child' ^By WILLIAM
M. WELCH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Urban hunger and homelessness rose most
rapidly this year among families with children, the nation's mayors
said Wednesday, with Boston Mayor Ray Flynn telling reporters that,
``increasingly, the face of hunger is the face of the young child.''
   He released a survey of 27 cities by the U.S. Conference of
Mayors that said many cities had so many requests for help that
they had to turn away families and others seeking shelter.
   Requests for emergency shelter were up 25 percent. Requests for
food were up 19 percent.
   One in four homeless people was a child; almost two-thirds of
those seeking food were children or their parents.
   The organization of big-city mayors based its report on a survey
of officials in 27 cities, who reported on public and private
relief efforts. The cities ranged from the nation's largest, New
York and Los Angeles, to Charleston, S.C., with a population of
81,000.
   The report found a shifting composition of the nation's urban
homeless, toward families with children.
   Families made up 36 percent of the survey cities' homeless in
1989, up from 34 percent a year ago and 27 percent in 1985. The
percentage of homeless who are single men continued to fall, from
60 percent in 1985 to 46 percent in 1989.
   Democrats cited the report, released annually by the
organization of big-city mayors, as evidence of neglect of the poor
by the Republican White House.
   Rep. Tony Hall, D-Ohio, chairman of the House Select Committee
on Hunger, said the repoort demonstrated ``a tragic ending for the
decade'' and ``an embarrassing legacy for the present and previous
administrations.''
   Flynn, a Democrat, said increased urban misery was a consequence
of congressional inattention as well as Reagan and Bush
administration policies.
   ``It has not been the politically fashionable thing up on
Capitol Hill to help poor people,'' said Flynn, who heads the
mayors' task force on hunger and homelessness. ``I don't see how
they can turn their backs and walk away any longer.''
   The conference, which has reported rising hunger and
homelessness annually for five years, said there was a sharp
increase in the percentage of the homeless population that abused
drugs and alcohol. These accounted from 44 percent of the homeless
population, up from 34 percent last year.
   The increased requests for help were found in nearly all the
cities surveyed.
   The number of families with children requesting emergency food
assistance increased an average 14 percent, and was up in nine of
10 cities. Nearly two-thirds of the requests for food were from
children or their parents.
   The lack of affordable housing was cited as a leading cause of
both hunger and homelessness.
   Flynn said that the poor who have homes, paying increasingly
large portions of their incomes for housing, often have less money
left for food and other necessities.
   The survey said that three-fourths of the cities could not meet
all the demands for food and had to turn people away _ an average
of 17 percent of their requests.
   ``While there's a lot of things going on at the local level _
shelters, soup kitchens ... _ the problem continues to grow and
grow and grow,'' Flynn said.
   One-quarter of the requests for shelter by homeless families go
unmet, the survey found. Three out of four of the cities said
shelters must turn away homeless families because of the lack of
resources.
   On average, the study said, the composition of the cities'
homeless population is 46 percent single men, 36 percent families
with children, 14 percent single women and 4 percent young people
on their own. Blacks made up 51 percent, whites 35 percent.
   A quarter of the homeless were veterans and a quarter were
severely mentally ill.
   The Cities surveyed were Alexandria, Va.; Boston; Charleston,
S.C.; Charlotte, N.C.; Chicago; Cleveland; Denver; Kansas City,
Mo.; Los Angeles; Louisville, Ky.; Minneapolis; Nashville, Tenn.;
New Orleans; New York; Norfolk, Va.; Philadelphia; Phoenix, Ariz.;
Portland, Ore.; Providence, R.I.; St. Paul, Minn.; San Antonio,
Texas; San Diego; San Francisco; Santa Monica, Calif.; Seattle;
Trenton, N.J., and Washington.
   The cities surveyed were those whose mayors serve on the
conference's task force.
</TEXT>

</DOC>