<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0245 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2055EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-American-Eastern 3rdLd-Writethru f0306 12-19 0562</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-American-Eastern, 3rd Ld-Writethru, f0306,0576</SECOND>
<HEAD>Anticipated Deal Between American, Eastern Announced</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-American Expansion</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf, `In addition ...,' to ADD American also gets
Miami-Madrid route authority.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN A. BOLT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   American Airlines announced its anticipated deal
with Eastern Airlines Tuesday, saying it would buy Latin American
routes and certain other assets from Eastern's parent company for
$471 million.
   The deal with Texas Air Corp. in one stroke makes American a
major international carrier, giving it 20 destinations in 15
Central and South American countries.
   In addition to the Latin American routes, American also gets a
Miami-to-London route from Eastern's sister carrier Continental
Airlines and Eastern's routes to Toronto from Miami and Tampa,
Fla., and its unused route authority from Miami to Madrid, Spain.
   Plus, American gets Continental and Eastern slots at John F.
Kennedy International Airport in New York and Eastern slots at New
York's LaGuardia Airport, Miami International Airport, Washington
National Airport, O'Hare International Airport in Chicago and San
Juan, Puerto Rico.
   American and Continental also agreed to a gate exchange at
Dallas-Fort Worth International Airport.
   The deal had been rumored to be imminent for more than a week as
Eastern seeks cash to help it emerge from bankruptcy protection.
The bankruptcy court and government regulators have to approve the
sale, which is a key part of Eastern's reorganization plan.
   Separately, Eastern said it will sell the 14 Lockheed L-1011
aircraft currently used to serve the Latin American routes.
American, which has spent billions of dollars on new jets recently,
said it wasn't interested in the L-1011s. They range in age from
12.5 years to 17 years.
   Besides the routes and landing slots, Texas Air agreed to drop a
$1 billion lawsuit against Sabre, American parent AMR Corp.'s
computer reservations systems. Texas Air subsidiary Continental
Airlines claimed Sabre, which is used by travel agents to book
passengers and is the largest such U.S. system, unfairly favored
American flights.
   Although deal between American and Eastern had been expected,
negotiations broke down in August, apparently over the disposition
of the lawsuit.
   Analyst Helane Becker at Shearson Lehman Hutton Inc. said
American would have a leg up on European carriers trying to serve
the growing Latin American market because American could route
flights from Europe through its Miami hub, cutting three hours off
the trip.
   ``This transaction will allow our company to continue building
our international network, and it will make the U.S. a strong
competitor in Central and South America by linking that region to
American's extensive route system,'' Chairman Robert L. Crandall
said in a press release.
   American called a news conference for Miami Wednesday morning to
discuss the deal, which it said will create about 2,000 airport and
reservation jobs in that city during the next five years.
   Texas Air said Eastern would realize $349 million from the sale,
while Continental $102.5 million and System One, Texas Air's
reservation system, $19.5 million for the telecommunications
equipment needed to service the routes.
   ``The sale of these assets will enable Eastern Airlines to
continue on its course of successfully rebuilding as a smaller and
stronger airline from the future, with its operation at its Atlanta
hub,'' Texas Air said in a prepared statement.
   Eastern and Continental will continue to operate the routes
until American is ready to take them over, Texas Air said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>