<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0146 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2127EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Bush-Drugs     12-19 0332</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Drugs,300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Meets on Military Role in Drug War</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM RAUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush met with Defense Secretary
Richard Cheney and Attorney General Dick Thornburgh on Tuesday to
weigh a wider role for the military in the war on drugs,
administration officials said.
   The subject of the Oval Office session was a recent Justice
Department legal opinion suggesting the U.S. military could legally
arrest drug offenders overseas.
   Bush advocated use of the military for raids on strongholds of
drug kingpins during last year's presidential campaign. He hinted
at a military role in his Sept. 6 anti-drug speech to the nation,
but at the times aides said he did not envision an overseas mission.
   However, presidential spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said Tuesday's
session was ``to sort all this out,'' including possible use of the
military to interdict drug traffickers in the source countries.
   Bush has expressed recent frustration with the increase of
drug-related violence in Colombia and with his inability to
influence events in Panama. Panamanian strongman Manuel Antonio
Noriega is under indictment in Florida on drug trafficking charges.
   At Tuesday's White House session, Cheney presented a preliminary
report on the role of the military in the anti-drug effort to Bush,
said White House spokeswoman Alixe Glen. ``A final strategy will be
forthcoming,'' she said.
   White House officials over the weekend acknowledged receiving
the Justice Department opinion and said it was being studied.
   The legal opinion said that the 1878 law which prohibits the
military from funtioning as a police agency on U.S. soil has no
bearing overseas.
   The report was written by Assistant Attorney General William P.
Barr, head of the Justice Department's office of legal counsel, in
November at the behest of the White House. Its existence was
disclosed last week.
   At the Pentagon Tuesday, spokesman Pete Williams said the legal
opinion would not automatically mean an expanded military role in
the drug war.
   ``It's a Justice Department option, not a policy,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>