<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0108 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1425EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Cold-Fish-Shrimp     12-29 0475</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cold-Fish-Shrimp,0487</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mississippi Catfish, Georgia Shrimp Hurt by Southern Freeze</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GREENVILLE, Miss. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mississippi catfish farmers may have
lost up to one-fifth of an average monthly harvest because last
week's big chill froze fish ponds solid, industry officials say.
   In Georgia, state biologists fear that recent freezing coastal
temperatures will mean no chance for a healthy shrimp season next
year _ more bad news for a shrimping industry already reeling from
a poor fall crop and low prices.
   Most of the Delta's catfish processing plants reopened Friday
after cold weather forced them to close for about a week.
Mississippi processes about 7 million pounds of catfish weekly, or
about 80 percent of the catfish consumed in the United States.
   From 26 million to 30 million pounds of catfish may have been
lost, said Hugh Warren, executive vice president of the Catfish
Farmers of America, a trade association. Industry officials said it
will be at least another week before farmers know the full impact
of the freeze. Thawing ponds are just beginning to reveal dead fish.
   More than 2,700 workers at the state's largest catfish
processing plants have been off their jobs, he said.
   Farmers have suffered losses as high as 20 percent when ponds
have frozen previously, said Dick Stevens, president of Country
Skillet Processing Co. Country Skillet and Delta Pride Processors,
two of the industry's largest companies, process about 60 percent
of the nation's farm-raised catfish.
   ``The economic impact is very high,'' said Delta Pride President
Sam I. Hinote.
   Ponds froze last weekend, some with 6 inches of ice, when
temperatures dipped into the single digits. When ponds freeze,
ammonia builds up and oxygen supplies dwindle, killing fish.
   Delta Pride's two processing plants in Indianola and one in
Belzoni shut down Tuesday. Officials at Country Skillet said they
halted operations at one plant and cut back operations at the other.
   Georgia Department of Natural Resource officials, meanwhile,
began sampling waters in the Brunswick area Thursday and are
expecting test trawls to net more dead shrimp than live shrimp as
they move up the coast this weekend.
   The news comes a week after the department announced that the
winter shrimping season, which normally ends Dec. 31, would be
extended at least into January because of a bountiful shrimp
supply. Biologist Gordon Rogers said if last weekend's freeze did
the damage the department suspects, officials could rescind that
announcement next week.
   ``At worst, it is our suspicion that there are no shrimp to be
worrying about catching,'' Rogers said, adding that the state's
prime white roe shrimp crop could be reduced for up to 18 months.
   White shrimp, which are caught in the spring, fall and winter,
annually account for 80 to 90 percent of the Georgia crop. Brown
shrimp harvested in the summer bring in 10 to 20 percent of the
annual crop.
</TEXT>

</DOC>