<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0119EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Bush-Vacation     12-27 0737</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bush-Vacation,730</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON TODAY: Quail Hunting a Tradition for President Busyh</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM RAUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush is winding up his first year as
president pretty much the same way he ended the year before, and
the year before that, going back several decades: quail hunting on
a Texas ranch.
   Bush aides say they hope he'll have better luck than last year,
when dry conditions made the tiny game birds scarce.
   The president will spend several days isolated _ but never out
of touch, aides insist _ at the 10,000-acre Lazy F Ranch near
Beeville in South Texas, owned by his friend, Houston millionaire
Will Farish.
   ``It's been a tradition for the past 20 years,'' said aide
Stephen Hart, who worked for Bush as vice president and has been
along on several of the previous quail-hunting trips.
   ``They drive around the ranch in big specially designed trucks,
then hunt with dogs. If they can catch turkey, too, then that's a
big treat,'' Hart said.
   In the past, Bush has hunted quail with a 20-gauge shotgun,
dressed in snake-resistant chaps, heavy leather boots and an orange
hunting cap.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III, expected to be along on
the trip, is known to prefer turkey hunting, which requires greater
patience.
   But Bush, who likes to jump from event to event, has defended
the sport of quail hunting as more to his liking _ and has asserted
that the birds are not to be regarded as cute animals but as wily,
determined quarry.
   ``These aren't animals _ these are wild quail, '' Bush declared
during last year's trip in a remark that angered animal rights
groups. ``You've got to eat. Our forefathers ate by harvesting
game.''
   The Texas office of The Fund for Animals has written to Bush
asking him to cancel the hunt, and plans to have animal activists
travel to Beeville to protest his activities if he carries out his
hunting plans.
   It seems likely that Bush and Baker will discuss another wily,
determined quarry while on the ranch _ deposed Panamanian dictator
Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   Noriega's decision to go Sunday to the Vatican embassy in Panama
City, where he is currently in hiding, took a lot pressure off the
Bush administration as it seeks to help restore post-invasion order
in Panama.
   However, aides said Bush never wavered from his determination to
make the hunting trip, and that little _ short of a major crisis _
would force him to cancel the trip.
   The town of Beeville, population about 15,000, is throwing a
barbecue for the president tonight upon his arrival _ but probably
won't see him again. Once he enters the vast ranch, he is not
expected to be seen publicly in the area. He will fly by helicopter
directly to Houston on Friday.
   Meanwhile, the Chamber of Commerce of neighboring Goliad, Texas,
is fussing to the White House that the part of the ranch where Bush
hunts is actually in Goliad, not Beeville _ and that it should be
able to share in the publicity.
   But the sheriff of Goliad County, J.K. McMahan, says it's fine
with him if the president keeps a low profile. Referring to recent
stories that Colombian drug lords may have put a $30 million price
on the president's head, McMahan said recently: ``I don't want him
killed, period, but I damn sure don't want him killed in my
county.''
   Bush also plans to bracket his quail-hunting with two fishing
expeditions _ another endeavor in which the president has not had
much recent luck.
   Bush planned to fish for redfish in the Gulf of Mexico, off
Corpus Christi, today on his way to Beeville.
   And on New Year's Day, after spending several days in Houston,
including a side trip on Sunday to two military hospitals in San
Antonio to visit soldiers wounded in Panama, Bush will take about
five hours out on his return to Washington to fish for bass on a
private lake near Montgomery, Ala.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   The White House says it's glad that Time Magazine selected
Soviet leader Mikhail S. Gorbachev to be ``Man of the Decade'' in
its current year-end issue.
   ``We certainly congratulate him,'' said presidential spokesman
Marlin Fitzwater. ``He has contributed greatly to the changes in
Eastern Europe and reforms in his own country. They have all been
very productive to Western interests. We congratulate him on it.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>