<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1617EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania 1stLd-Writethru   12-24 1209</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania, 1st Ld - Writethru,a0747,1243</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Calls For Cease-Fire, Snipers Paralyze Capital</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos BUCH3, BUCH16, BUCH21</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS throughout with Ceausescu daughter arrested, cash and
jewelry seized, police surrendering in Timisoara, tunnels in Timisoara;
new info grafs 7,10-12,32, no pickup</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MORT ROSENBLUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The revolutionary government pleaded
for peace on Christmas Eve as soldiers and citizens waged a savage
war in the streets with secret police loyal to ousted dictator
Nicolae Ceausescu.
   Sniper fire paralyzed the capital, and bodies piled up in
morgues as anarchy seemed to grip this nation struggling to break a
quarter-century of Stalinist rule.
   The embattled revolutionary government issued a cease-fire call
in a bid to disarm not only pro-Ceausescu secret police but
vigilante groups that plucked weapons from dead soldiers and sought
personal revenge against the fallen regime's supporters.
   A few families carried freshly cut Christmas trees through the
capital during a morning lull in the fighting, but sniper fire by
pro-Ceausescu forces quickly cleared the streets.
   Secret police infiltrated the television station building _
headquarters of the revolutionary governing coalition _ and three
people were reported killed before army units subdued the attackers.
   Fighting between secret police and soldiers backing the revolt
continued in the capital, but the army appeared to be winning in
the western city of Timisoara, where the revolt began a week ago.
Four Western journalists, including Associated Press correspondent
John Daniszewski, were shot and wounded there over the weekend.
   Romanian radio said secret police used scores of secret safe
houses and vast networks of tunnels in Bucharest and in Timisoara
to store weapons and launch attacks.
   Ceausescu's downtown palace was connected to the maze of tunnels
and contained a bunker designed to resist nuclear attack, Bucharest
radio said.
   The revolutionary government said the Communist dictator who
ruled for 24 years was captured Saturday along with his wife,
Elena. Soviet television said they were found hiding in an
underground bunker.
   His son, Nicu, was reported arrested Friday and on Sunday a
daughter, Zoia-Elena, appeared dazed as she was shown on Romanian
television after she was caught at one of her Bucharest apartments.
   The television also showed jewelry and cash it said totaled
nearly $100,000 in U.S. currency that was allegedly seized from the
family. Ordinary Romanians are not allowed to hold foreign currency.
   The Bush administration and the French government both said they
would not object if the Soviets or other Warsaw Pact nations use
their militaries to assist the revolution in Romania.
   Thousands of people were believed killed as Ceausescu tried to
stop the massive protests that began on Dec. 15 in Timisoara, 300
miles southwest of Bucharest. The protests spread to the capital,
forcing Ceausescu to flee his palace Friday.
   Since then, army units backing the revolt have battled the elite
secret police and security forces loyal to Ceausescu. Hundreds and
perhaps thousands have died.
   Offers of emergency aid poured in from around the world, but
East bloc media said few supplies were able to get through because
of the fighting, some of the worst street battles Europe has seen
since World War II.
   Ceausescu's secret police and security guards are essentially
fighting for their lives against the revolutionaries, who have
vowed revenge for the massacres of unarmed citizens during the
protests.
   The U.S. Embassy in Bucharest on Sunday evacuated dependents and
some staff members in a convoy to Sofia, Bulgaria, said spokesman
Agi Kuperman.
   The British ambassador's residence in Bucharest was set on fire
Saturday night and burned until Sunday morning.
   Fighting raged near Bucharest airport, although Hungarian
television later said the airport was open. In the city center,
sniper fire brought barrages of shots from the army and volunteers.
Roadblocks often manned by children searched cars and passengers,
sometimes four times in two blocks.
   At Bucharest Emergency Hospital, doctors who had not slept in
three days said they had treated 2,000 civilians since Thursday. By
noon Sunday, 90 bodies had arrived at the morgue, one of many in
Bucharest.
   The East German news agency ADN said the National Salvation
Committee estimated more than 5,000 people were killed between
Friday and Saturday night.
   Bodies lay on concrete floors at Bucharest Emergency Hospital,
identity papers taped to bare chests. Sobbing family members spent
Christmas Eve looking for lost loved ones. Victims included a
pregnant woman.
   ``It is horrible murder,'' said Dr. Stepshan Miliesescu. He said
victims came in with single shots to the head from well-trained
snipers.
   Doctors had to sedate and strap down one security guard who
raved that the revolution had upset Ceausescu's socialist paradise.
   Several heard him repeat: ``You are criminals, and we will kill
you all.''
   Ceausescu was the lone East bloc leader to resist a wave of
democratic reforms sweeping the region. He imposed harsh austerity
programs, rationing and other hardships on the nation's 23 million
people to pay off the nation's $11 billion foreign debt.
   The National Salvation Committee said in was in control of the
nation and pledged in a communique Sunday that the courts would
mete out punishments of ``the greatest severity'' to ``the dictator
and his former lackeys.''
   Ion Iliescu, a leading figure in the committee, appealed for
unity.
   ``May the first free New Year bring to Romania, together with
the joy of liberation, the quiet and calm enabling us to assume all
the responsibilities of a people asserting its dignity,'' he said.
   The group called for a cease-fire and urged civilians and
pro-Ceausescu forces to disarm by 5 p.m. Christmas Day. People who
violate it ``will receive the strictest punishment.''
   In Timisoara, the Yugoslav news agency Tanjug reported that
pro-Ceausescu security forces who parachuted into the city Friday
night were beginning to fall into the hands of the army.
   Austrian television showed film of the security forces
surrendering and being marched off by soldiers. On Saturday in
Bucharest, some security men captured by the army were shot by
soldiers on the spot.
   AP correspondent Daniszewski was shot and wounded in Timisoara
on Saturday, as was John Tagliabue of The New York Times. Both were
reported in stable condition at a hospital.
   In Bucharest, groups of teen-agers with weapons snatched from
the dead ``are trying to carry out a vendetta against the
terrorists,'' said National Salvation Committee spokesman Stephan
Andreescu.
   ``These ... forces are trying to escape and are extremely
dangerous,'' Andreescu said of the secret police. But he claimed
the army was in ``complete control of the situation in the
country.''
   ``The terrorists are believed to be hiding in the subway and in
secret underground passages below the former presidential palace,''
Andreescu said. ``It will take days before it is all over.''
   The doctors at Bucharest Emergency Hospital said pro-Ceausescu
forces were holed up in secret apartments, firing at targets in the
street. The army could not respond with heavy weapons without
blasting neighboring apartments.
   ``They are fighting like Hitler's people at the end of World War
II, just to kill in desperation,'' said a Romanian news agency
editor who did not want to be identified.
   ``They killed thousands and thousands of people,'' he said,
recounting the last years of Ceausescu. ``They killed young people,
children. You cannot imagine how awful it was. We must write about
these things.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>