<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0126 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2031EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BusCrashTrial 1stLd-Writethru a0622 12-19 0515</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bus Crash Trial, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0622,0524</SECOND>
<HEAD>Testimony Nearing End in Mahoney Trial</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 2 grafs to UPDATE with testimony ended, picking up
3rd graf: `Mahoney, 36, ...; INSERTS 5 grafs after the 10th, ``It would
be ..., to UPDATE with testimony of last witness.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHARLES WOLFE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CARROLLTON, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Testimony ended Tuesday in Larry
Mahoney's trial on 27 murder charges and lawyers said the nation's
worst drunken-driving case might go to the jury Wednesday.
   Still to come were closing arguments and the judge's
instructions to the Carroll Circuit Court jury.
   Mahoney, 36, allegedly was drunk and driving on the wrong side
of Interstate 71 when his pickup rammed the front of a church bus
on May 14, 1988. Fire erupted from the bus' ruptured fuel tank and
24 children and three adults died. One adult and 39 children
escaped.
   In addition to the murder charges, Mahoney also is charged with
12 counts of first-degree assault, 42 of wanton endangerment and
one of drunken driving.
   The defense has claimed that Mahoney did not intentionally get
drunk and that the former school bus, a 1977 model manufactured by
Ford Motor Co. and Sheller-Globe Corp., was unsafe.
   Autopsies showed the fire, not the crash, killed the victims.
   Mahoney's lawyers pressed the bus-safety issue Tuesday,
rebutting a prosecution witness' testimony that school buses are
safer than other passenger vehicles.
   The prosecution testimony, from analyst William Boehly of the
National Highway Traffic Safety Administration, was based on the
accident rate per miles traveled by school buses.
   But Byron Bloch, an auto-safety design consultant from Potomac,
Md., testified for the defense that buses were safe only ``from
(Boehly's) narrow statistical perspective.''
   ``It would be erroneous to conclude that his data rubber-stamp
the accident bus as a safe bus,'' Bloch said.
   The final witness was Donald Wright, a local musician whose
testimony was intended to discredit Kelly Osborne, the man who
defense lawyers say tricked Mahoney into drinking vodka the night
of the bus crash.
   Osborne testified Monday that he mixed a vodka and Sprite for
Mahoney, but only at Mahoney's request. Osborne denied he ever
spiked anyone's drink.
   Wright testified that Jake Lansdale, a 79-year-old fiddler with
whom he plays, was incapacitated for nearly three hours after
drinking from a cup Osborne handed him during a performance in
August. Lansdale usually drank nothing when they played,
occasionally drank a beer, but had never been seen drinking liquor,
Wright said.
   But Wright could not swear that Osborne put anything in
Lansdale's cup, and said he did not know what made Lansdale
collapse.
   Judge Charles Satterwhite said Lansdale had been subpoenaed to
testify, but was excused because of illness.
   Special prosecutor Paul Richwalsky wrapped up his case Monday
with rebuttal witnesses and declined to call further witnesses
Tuesday.
   Attorneys said jurors would have two alternatives to the 27
murder charges _ second-degree manslaughter, punishable by five to
10 years in prison, and reckless homicide, punishable by one to
five years. In each case, a fine of up to $10,000 can be imposed.
</TEXT>

</DOC>