<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0297 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1834EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-JimWalter     12-20 0446</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jim Walter,0460</SECOND>
<HEAD>Parent of Jim Walter Corp. Faces Chapter 11 Bankruptcy</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TAMPA, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jim Walter Corp.'s parent company said
Wednesday it was prepared to file for Chapter 11 bankruptcy
protection in what would be a first among large firms taken private
by buyout specialists Kohlberg, Kravis, Roberts &amp; Co.
   Kohlberg Kravis formed Hillsborough Holdings Corp. as part of
its $2.4 billion takeover of the building materials company last
year. A bankruptcy court filing by the company could inject fresh
jitters into the junk-bond market that has financed such takeovers.
   Hillsborough officials said the bankruptcy filing was expected
to be made Dec. 27 if an exchange offer for $624 million worth of
the company's bonds was not accepted by at least 80 percent of the
company's bondholders.
   Kohlberg Kravis has apparently failed to persuade a group of
Hillsborough's senior bondholders to accept a proposed financial
restructuring of the company.
   ``If the pending exchange offers are not consummated on their
current terms and conditions, Hillsborough and certain of its
subsidiaries may have no alternative but to file voluntary
petitions for reorganization under Chapter 11,'' said
Hillsborough's spokesman David Townsend.
   If the offer is not accepted, Hillsborough faces the prospect of
having to repay its notes in full, which it told bondholders at a
meeting Tuesday that it could not do.
   A Chapter 11 filing would blemish the record of Kohlberg Kravis,
considered the dean of the leveraged buyout artists with the $25
billion RJR Nabisco deal to its credit. But the Hillsborough firm
has some peculiar problems, which are not necessarily symptomatic
of widespread weakness among LBOs, experts said.
   ``It's not going to be that devastating,'' said James Grant,
publisher of a New York interest rate newsletter and a critic of
leveraged buyouts. ``Hillsborough Holdings had problems of its own
that had nothing to do with the takeover.''
   The biggest problem, Grant said, came last summer when Jim
Walter was hit with a $3 billion asbestos-related lawsuit. Because
of the class-action suit, Kohlberg Kravis has been unable to sell
off Jim Walter's assets. And without the proceeds from the sales,
the company cannot meet its upcoming debt payments.
   Hillsborough is the third company owned by Kohlberg Kravis to
encounter financial difficulties in recent months.
   In August, Kohlberg Kravis confirmed that Seaman Furniture Co.,
a leading furniture retailer, could not meet its debt payments and
might not be able to continue operating. The company's debt
payments were later rescheduled successfully.
   SCI Television Inc., of which Kohlberg Kravis owns 45 percent,
is also involved in an exchange offer that is facing resistance
from bondholders.
   But neither of those Kohlberg Kravis holdings is as large as
Hillsborough.
</TEXT>

</DOC>