<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1116EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Shevardnadze 2ndLd-Writethru a0499 12-18 0589</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Shevardnadze, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0499,0605</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shevardnadze Opens Historic Two-Day Visit to EC, NATO</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 9 grafs to UPDATE with comments from Shevardnadze,
Eyskens. Pickup 5th pvs, `On Tuesday...</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT J. WIELAARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRUSSELS, Belgium (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard
Shevardnadze told Belgian officials today that the Soviet Union
wants to establish close economic ties with Western Europe and
switch to a market economy.
   Shevardnadze is on the first day of a two-day visit to Brussels,
where he will sign a new trade and economic cooperation agreement
with the 12-nation European Community trading bloc.
   He also will make an unprecedented visit to NATO military
headquarters, underscoring the rapidly changing East-West climate.
   `I never said integration (of the Soviet economy with the West)
would be easy. But we are taking the first step, laying the first
stone,'' Shevardnadze said in reference to the trade agreement
negotiated with the EC.
   Shevardnadze, who met briefly with reporters after talks with
Foreign Minister Mark Eyskens of Belgium, was asked about Soviet
promises to withdraw all its troops from Eastern Europe by the
start of the next century.
   ``We must find a reciprocal solution,'' he said. ``I'm thinking
of the U.S. presence ... We must have serious negotiations. We have
a mutual interest in stability in Europe.''
   Eyskens said after meeting with Shevardnadze that the Soviets
``want to break with their past.''
   ``They have concluded that the centrally planned economy is no
good,'' he said.
   Shevardnaze met with Prime Minister Wilfried Martens and was to
sign a trade and economic cooperation agreement at European
Community headquarters.
   On Tuesday, Shevardnaze will meet with NATO Secretary General
Manfred Woerner and the ambassadors of the 16 NATO nations at the
headquarters of the Western alliance.
   Community and Soviet negotiators concluded a trade and economic
accord Nov. 27 that provides for a gradual lifting of import quotas
on Soviet industrial goods and cites a dozen areas in which the two
sides may establish economic cooperation.
   These include science and technology, banking, transport,
agriculture, environmental protection, energy, raw materials and
mining.
   The accord excludes trade in goods that are considered
militarily sensitive, according to EC sources.
   The pact is the fourth between the community and an East
European country since the EC and the Moscow-led Comecon trade
group signed a mutual recognition accord June 25, 1988. Comecon
stands for Council for Mutual and Economic assistance.
   The EC has also concluded trade and economic cooperation accords
with Hungary, Poland and Czechoslovakia.
   These accords _ plus the ones the European Community's Executive
Commission is currently negotiating with Bulgaria and East Germany
_ are bound to dramatically boost economic relations between
Eastern and Western Europe.
   The mutual recognition agreement the community signed with the
10-nation Comecon group in 1988 ended a 30-year-period in which
Moscow and its allies routinely viewed it as an extension of the
NATO alliance.
   Moscow's partners in Comecon are East Germany, Poland,
Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Bulgaria, Romania, Vietnam, Mongolia and
Cuba.
   Speaking to reporters after a two-day NATO foreign ministers
meeting, Woerner sought to dispel any notion he and Shevardnaze
would engage in in-depth negotiations on Tuesday.
   He and other officials stressed the meeting would be on the
order of a courtesy call.
   Woerner said he and Shevardnaze would simply discuss ``matters
of common interest. This is a first contact. We will have an
exchange of views.''
   Even so, Foreign Secretary Douglas Hurd of Braitain described
the visit to NATO as ``a symbol of what's been happening'' in East
West relations.
</TEXT>

</DOC>