<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0159 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1807EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Reporters-Contempt     12-20 0375</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Reporters-Contempt,0386</SECOND>
<HEAD>Supreme Court Says Reporters Shouldn't Have To Testify</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JILL WILSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Journalists' confidential sources and
information they gathered must be ``highly material and relevant,''
and unavailable from elsewhere, before reporters can be compelled
to reveal them, the state Supreme Court has ruled.
   The 5-0 ruling released Wednesday, overturned contempt citations
against two West Virginia reporters.
   In September, Circuit Judge Patrick G. Henry III held in
contempt reporters Ron Hudok of The Evening Journal of Martinsburg
and Natasha Singh of WXVA-FM in Charles Town. They had refused to
testify at a hearing about Circuit Judge Thomas Steptoe Jr.'s
decision to fire an employee.
   ``In this case, the information sought to be obtained was
tenuous at best to the main purpose of the hearing, which was to
provide (the employee) a hearing on her discharge,'' the Supreme
Court said.
   Eight news media groups, including The Associated Press and the
West Virginia Broadcasters Association, had filed a legal brief in
support of the newspaper and radio station.
   ``The decision ... is really a victory for the people of West
Virginia because it allows reporters for all media to write the
comments and viewpoints of the people who live in this state,''
said Page Burdette, editor of The Evening Journal.
   Burdette said he hopes the issue will prompt lawmakers to pass
West Virginia's first ``shield'' laws for reporters. Such
legislation would help journalists protect news sources to whom
they've promised anonymity in return for information.
   Singh said she was relieved. ``I'm just glad I get to eat turkey
at Christmas and I don't have to be in jail,'' she said.
   The opinion, written by Justice Thomas Miller, said there could
be cases when reporters' information is pertinent to a legal
proceeding. In the case of Hudok and Singh, however, First
Amendment privilege should prevail, the opinion said.
   The case stemmed from Steptoe's decision to fire Magistrate
Clerk Linda Butner in June. The judge said she publicly injected
herself into a criminal matter pending before magistrate court by
talking to reporters.
   Steptoe had sought to force the reporters to testify about their
conversations with Butner, who Henry said is bound by judicial
ethics to refrain from commenting on court matters.
</TEXT>

</DOC>