<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0086 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1331EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Bush 4thLd-Writethru a0533 12-27 1019</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bush, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0533,970</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Sees No Danger of Noriega Disclosing Secrets</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Top 5 grafs new to move up context of ``blindside'' quote and
add quote on jailing Noriega in Panama; picks up at pvs 4th graf, The president,
deletes pvs 8th graf, Bush, asked, to conform; deletes last graf to shorten</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM RAUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CORPUS CHRISTI, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush said today that
ousted Panamanian ruler Manuel Antonio Noriega's knowledge of CIA
activities could not embarrass the U.S. government but that he
could try to ``blindside'' the U.S. judicial process.
   ``I think that's history, and I think the main thing is he
should be tried and brought to justice,'' Bush said at a brief news
conference as he arrived in Texas for a six-day fishing and hunting
vacation.
   He said a trial on drug-trafficking charges lodged against
Noriega in this country could result in ``some release of certain
confidential documents that he may try to blindside the whole
justice process.'' But, he added, ``The system works, so I wouldn't
worry about that.''
   Bush was asked if he would direct release of any documents
Noriega might request in order to avoid challenges to the fairness
of the trial as occurred in the case of Iran-Contra defendant
Oliver North. He replied, ``There'd be enough to see that he's
given a totally fair trial, certainly ....''
   Later, Bush appeared to leave open the possibility that Noriega
could be tried in Panama. He said there was a threat of Noriega
regaining power if he remained there ``unless he were in total
custody and sentenced to the prison sentence he deserves.''
   The president said he was personally involved in efforts to gain
custody of Noriega from the Vatican embassy in Panama, where
Noriega has been sheltered since Christmas Eve, but he had not
contacted either the papal nuncio in Panama City or Pope John Paul
II.
   Earlier, White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater told reporters
aboard Air Force One en route to Texas that Noriega ``can talk
about the CIA and Bush until he's blue in the face. It won't hurt
anything.''
   He was referring to things Noriega might reveal about his
previous close relations with the U.S. government, including the
period in the 1970s when Bush was CIA director and Noriega was an
intelligence source.
   ``We want Noriega here because he would cause trouble wherever
he goes ... We want him in a nice jail cell where we can keep an
eye on him,'' Fitzwater said.
   He said it would ``require a lot of diplomatic effort and a lot
of it on my part'' to address the concerns of Latin American
leaders who have been critical of U.S. military action in Panama.
   But he said that as they see democracy functioning in Panama and
Noriega brought to justice, they would ``begin to see the problem
that might have been caused by a prolonged conflict down there ...''
   Bush, taking questions yelled above the roar of helicopter
rotors at a naval air station, said there would be ``no time
limit'' on negotiations over Noriega.
   The president was asked about the reported refusal of the
Vatican to surrender Noriega, who has taken shelter in its Panama
City embassy, to U.S. authorities. ``That complicates things if
they said that,'' he said.
   Bush said that, however, he wanted more specific information on
the Vatican's position and would not give up hopes of winning
Noriega's extradition. ``We will continue to negotiate,'' he said.
   The president defended his decision to take the year-end
vacation in view of the Panama situation, claiming he did not think
it amounted to shirking his responsibility as chief executive
during a time of crisis.
   ``I'm not concerned about that at all. Why should I be?'' he
said. ``Things have gone well. It's winding down.''
   The president said that he would stay in constant touch with his
national security advisers in Washington by telephone, ``by secure
link,'' and he noted that Secretary of State James A. Baker III had
come along with him for part of the vacation.
   ``Look, I don't make any cover. I'm going to be enjoying myself
and I think the American people understand that,'' he said. ``I
think I've worked pretty hard all year.''
   On another subject, Bush said he hoped that stability could soon
be restored to Romania and said that the provisional government and
the army appeared to be doing a good job of restoring order.
   ``My concern is for tranquillity and freedom in Romania,'' Bush
said.
   The president said that he was ``touched'' by hearing a ``guy
singing a Christmas carol'' on Romania's state-run television.
   Claiming it was the first time that a Christmas carol had been
heard on the public airwaves in 40 years, Bush said, ``It made a
dramatic statement for me.''
   ``Democracy and freedom is on the move around the world,'' he
said.
   Bush, who wore a hunting jacket and the pinstriped pants of his
suit as he spoke briefly with reporters aboard the plane, said he
spent much of his Christmas holiday at Camp David, Md., on the
phone but ``got a great Christmas present'' in Noriega's overthrow
by U.S. troops on Dec. 19.
   The president and his wife, Barbara, were at Camp David with
their five children and their families, including 11 grandchildren.
   Describing his holiday, Bush said, ``It was cold, wonderful _
sleigh riding for the kids. It was great.''
   Earlier, Fitzwater said Bush will keep close tabs on
developments in Panama by telephone. He said Tuesday the
administration told the Vatican ``very directly'' it wants Noriega
returned for trial.
   Fitzwater said Bush was not taking a direct role in the
negotiations on Noriega's extradition.
   After fishing in the Gulf of Mexico later today near Corpus
Christi, Bush was to travel by helicopter some 60 miles to the
ranch of a friend near Beeville, where he will spend two days quail
hunting.
   He goes to Houston on Friday, where he will stay until Monday.
On Sunday, he plans a side trip to two military hospitals near San
Antonio to visit U.S. soldiers wounded in Panama.
</TEXT>

</DOC>