<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0199 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 2054EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SAfrica-Mercenary     12-22 0319</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SAfrica-Mercenary,0326</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mercenary Who Held Islands Says He's Negotiating With South Africa</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bob Denard, leader of the
mercenaries who last week were forced to yield their control of the
Comoros Islands, said Friday he was negotiating with authorities to
leave South Africa as soon as possible.
   Denard has been in South Africa since Dec. 15, the day French
troops landed in the Comoros off southeastern Africa and ended a
takeover led by Denard and fellow European mercenaries.
   The Presidential Guard, which was led by the mercenaries, had
controlled the three-island Indian Ocean nation, a former French
colony, since the shooting death Nov. 26 of President Ahmed
Abdallah.
   At his first news conference in South Africa, Denard on Friday
described his stay in South Africa as ``obviously temporary'' and
said he hoped to depart soon after he and his lawyer, who had just
arrived from Paris, worked out details. Denard, a Frenchman,
thanked South Africa for its hospitality.
   More than 30 of the mercenaries flew to Europe last week, but
Denard was allowed to stay in South Africa temporarily while he
negotiated for permanent residence elsewhere.
   Three of the mercenaries initially stayed with Denard in South
Africa, but Foreign Affairs spokesman Rusty Evans said two had
returned to France during the week.
   France and South Africa are the main donors of aid to the
Comoros, but they suspended assistance following Abdallah's death
in circumstances that remain unclear. Many Comoreans blamed Denard
for the killing, but he again denied Friday that he was involved.
   ``I am not an assassain. I did not kill President Abdallah,'' he
said. He has previously said one of the president's bodyguards shot
him.
   Denard has told South African authorities that he was wary of
returning to France because he could face criminal charges for his
role in an attempted coup in the West African country of Benin 14
years ago.
</TEXT>

</DOC>