<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1347EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     12-17 0499</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0517</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GREAT FALLS, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fifth-grade teacher Susan Nardinger is
rallying the faithful in this river city to defend its short
reputation, which has been assaulted once again by river rats in
Lincoln City, Ore.
   Students in Nardinger's class touched off the battle two years
ago, when they petitioned the Guinness Book of World Records to
declare the 201-foot-long Roe River northeast of Great Falls the
world's shortest river.
   Guinness editors agreed, and the Roe displaced Lincoln City's D
River in the 1988 edition of the record book.
   But Lincoln City was not about to be sold short.
   They remeasured the D River and announced that it was 120 feet,
mysteriously smaller than the last measuring. And, Guinness editors
notified the Lincoln City Chamber of Commerce recently that the D
River would be back in the books by the 1991 edition _ unless a
shorter river is found.
   Well, that's just what students in Great Falls intend to do, and
they'll look no farther than the Roe.
   Nardinger said the Roe could claim a length of only 30 feet
because it has two forks, and the students submitted the longer of
the two for consideration of the record.
   ``I stand behind the kids 100 percent,'' she said Friday.
   She dismissed the D River as an ``ocean water backup,'' not a
river at all and suggested Guinness officials take a look for
themselves.
   Molly Peterson, one of the students who helped petition on
behalf the Roe, took a more philosophical approach. She said the
Roe is still the shortest river, but ``records are made to be
broken.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>MIRA LOMA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 6-foot alligator out for an evening
stroll on a suburban sidewalk drew a neighborly reaction from Ruben
Hernandez. He tackled the meat-eating reptile, kept it safe for its
owner and refused to tattle.
   ``I grabbed the tail and put a foot on (the alligator's) back,''
he said. ``I started screaming to put the duct tape around the
alligator's mouth.''
   Hernandez, 32, said he took a few shots to the head wrestling
the 200-pound alligator when the beast whipped its powerful tail,
but he and his brother-in-law loaded the gator into their pickup
truck.
   When the sun came up Friday, Hernandez watched the huge reptile
lash at a chain holding it in the truck and questioned his bravado
of the previous night.
   ``I could have gotten hurt,'' he said.
   Hernandez said contacted the animal's owner and arranged to
return the beast. He refused to identify the owner, who officials
said lacked permits to keep the exotic animal.
   ``I can't imagine that anyone in possession of an alligator
legally would allow it to run loose in an area where it could come
in contact with people,'' said Eva Schultz, a warden for the
California Department of Fish and Game in Long Beach.
   She said it is illegal to keep an alligator without a special
permit, adding that those permits are rarely issued.
</TEXT>

</DOC>