<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0116 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 2033EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Nicaragua-US 1stLd-Writethru   12-30 0557</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nicaragua-US, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0560,0573</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Embassy Calls Expulsions `Drastic And Unjustified'</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with more Nicaraguan comment, background.
No pickup.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FILADELFO ALEMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANAGUA, Nicaragua (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A U.S. official on Saturday called the
expulsion of 20 U.S. diplomats from Nicaragua ``drastic and
unjustified'' retaliation for a search by U.S. troops of the
Nicaraguan ambassador's home in Panama.
   On Friday night, President Daniel Ortega gave the diplomats 72
hours to leave. He also ordered the mission to reduce its
administrative staff from 320 to 100. Most of those employees are
Nicaraguan nationals.
   ``We were at grave risk of a political-military clash with the
United States, which has maintained an aggressive attitude against
Latin American countries,'' Ortega said.
   The action came after U.S. troops invaded the Nicaraguan
ambassador's house in Panama City despite his protests. A senior
U.S. official in Panama City called the search a mistake and said
troops did not know they were in a diplomatic residence.
   The Nicaraguan Foreign Ministry said 15 U.S. diplomats would be
allowed to remain in the country, the minimum prescribed by the
Vienna Convention.
   ``The measure of the Sandinista government is drastic and
unjustified,'' said Louis Falino, a spokesman for the U.S. Embassy
in Managua who spoke to The Associated Press by telephone. Falino
was on the list of those expelled.
   President Bush said in Houston on Saturday that an apology had
been made.
   ``It's a screw-up and they (U.S. military officials in Panama)
have expressed their regrets that it happened,'' Bush said. He
added that ``it shouldn't have happened and that's been explained
to the Nicaraguans.''
   U.S. officials said soldiers were acting on a tip that a large
cache of weapons was stored at the home. Soldiers returned the
weapons after realizing it was the Nicaraguan diplomat's residence,
the State Department said.
   The search of Ambassador Antenor Ferrey's residence in Panama
City was ``outrageous...insolent'' and ``violated principles of
international law,'' Ortega said.
   ``They acted arrogantly, like Rambos!'' Ortega said.
   He claimed the U.S. soldiers stole more than $2,000 and took
some clothes from the residence. U.S. reaction to the charge was
not immediately available.
   Tension between the two countries increased after the Dec. 20
U.S. invasion of Panama and the overthrow of Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noriega. If it does not ease, it could give Ortega an excuse to
cancel presidential elections set for Feb. 25.
   ``We have never discarded the possibility'' of a U.S. invasion
of Nicaragua,'' said Manuel Rodriguez, political adviser at the
Nicaraguan Embassy in Panama. He spoke before the search, looking
down on U.S. troops manning barricades of wire and sandbags at the
embassy and checking identification on a side street.
   ``It's just that the results would not be the same as in Panama.
It would cost them a lot more.''
   Nicaragua's Soviet-equipped military is the largest force in
Central America.
   The United States has not had an ambassador in Managua since
July 1988, when the leftist Sandinista government expelled
Ambassador Richard Melton and seven other American diplomats to
protest alleged American interference in an opposition rally in
Nicaragua.
   The United States responded by expelling Nicaraguan Ambassador
Carlos Tunnerman.
   U.S. soldiers circled the Nicaraguan Embassy in Panama last week
in case Noriega sought refuge there. Nicaragua's Foreign Ministry
then ordered the U.S. Embassy in Managua surrounded.
</TEXT>

</DOC>