<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0939EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Czechoslovakia 1stLd-Writethru   12-20 0736</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Czechoslovakia, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0551,0756</SECOND>
<HEAD>Communist Party Chief Criticizes Party's `Negligence'</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE with Urbanek criticizing his Communist
Party for making mistakes. No pickup.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SYDNEY RUBIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Communist Party chief Karel
Urbanek today said the party leadership had made mistakes marked by
``negligence and irresponsibility'' that led the organization into
its worst crisis.
   Speaking to 1,500 delegates at a special party congress, Urbanek
also admitted his own guilt as a member of the ruling Politburo in
allowing hated hard-liners to remain in the party leadership.
   The party was expected to purge its ranks of many discredited
party leaders during the two-day meeting.
   The Communists have been rocked by two shake-ups in the
leadership to remove hard-liners and the loss of thousands of
members since the country's peaceful pro-democracy movement began
four weeks ago, changing the political orientation of the country.
   The congress, called to determine the party's future in the wake
of a revolution that swept a government led by non-Communist into
office, scrapped all its party statutes, which could pave the way
for a comprehensive organizational reform.
   Party spokesman Josef Hora told reporters the congress also
decided to divide the leadership duties between a general secretary
and a party chairman.
   Former Premier Ladislav Adamec, who resigned earlier this month
after failing to reach agreement with the opposition on a new
government, was thought to be a contender for one of the posts,
according to congress observers who spoke on condition of anonymity.
   On Nov. 24, the party ousted hard-line leader Milos Jakes and
others responsible for the crackdown on the ``Prague Spring''
reforms of 1968, and Urbanek replaced Jakes as party chief.
   The much despised Prague party boss, Miroslav Stepan, was ousted
two days later in a further leadership reshuffle that brought
unknown Communists to the top. Stepan's ouster was demanded by
massive protest rallies.
   Both Jakes and Stepan were later expelled from the party for
``serious political mistakes.'' They had refuted assertions by a
parliamentary commission that they were politically responsible for
a Nov. 17 police crackdown on peaceful student demonstrators that
ignited the ensuing democratic revolution.
   Urbanek said the ``party leadership manifested negligence and
irresponsibility worthy of punishment.''
   ``With self-criticism, I admit my part of the guilt in'' leaving
Stepan on the Poliburo, Urbanek said, adding that the decision was
``an extraordinary, politically serious mistake.''
   Outlining the crisis now faced by the party, Urbanek noted that
it had lost 66,290 of its 1.7 million members in the last month.
   Urbanek also revealed that the party faces bankruptcy,
disclosing that party dues were used to build recreation facilities
for the top brass ``about which the rank-and-file only learned
today.''
   The speech confirmed the total disarray in which the party finds
itself following the triumphs of the pro-democracy movement.
   The most recent victory came on Tuesday as the
Communist-dominated Parliament gave the new reform government a
vote of confidence, and endorsed opposition leader Vaclav Havel for
president.
   ``There is no doubt that the congress delegates have the duty
... to take the party out of its deepest crisis ever,'' the
Communist Party daily Rude Pravo said in a front-page editorial
today.
   Havel, a former dissident who emobdies the democracy movement,
said on the eve of the party congress that the party should become
``a modern political party which would participate as an equal
among equals in the pluralistic system...''
   Urbanek told Prague congress delegates Tuesday night that new
elections to the Politburo are not expected, but suggested it could
be replaced by a 21-member ``political executive committee.''
   Among the non-voting guests at the congress are former party
members expelled after the Soviet invasion of 1968 that crushed the
``Prague Spring'' Communist-led reforms.
   There are also 40 delegates from the new reformist Communist
Democratic Forum, a potential splinter group challenging Urbanek's
leadership which submitted a seven point list of demands.
   Earlier this week, the Democratic Forum spokesman, Rudolf
Prevratil, said ``the congress will show whether the movment can
live within the party.''
   The party was also likely to discuss the presidential elections.
Communist Premier Marian Calfa, who left for Moscow today and was
therefore not attending the party congress, gave an unprecedented
endorsement to Havel's candidacy.
   The parliament's presidium voted late Tuesday to reconvene the
house Dec. 29 at the presidential Hradcany castle to cast a public
vote for president. Havel is essentially the only candidate.
</TEXT>

</DOC>