<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0200EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-GoldenGlobes     12-28 0571</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Golden Globes,0586</SECOND>
<HEAD>Golden Globe Nominations Mix Likely Films With Unusual Selections</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN HORN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEVERLY HILLS, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mixing the predictable with the
unusual, the nominations for the 47th Annual Golden Globes honored
pop hits like ``When Harry Met Sally ...'' but ignored acclaimed
movies such as ``Henry V.''
   The Golden Globes, announced by the Hollywood Foreign Press
Association on Wednesday, often serve as a bellwether for the
Academy Awards. But some of this year's selections were so unusual
it seems unlikely the Oscars will follow suit.
   The foreign press, unlike the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and
Sciences, divides films and star performances into two categories,
drama and musical or comedy.
   Among the stranger nominations: Jack Nicholson, picked for best
actor in a musical or comedy for ``Batman,'' which almost everyone
considers a drama; and Bruce Willis, named for best supporting
actor for ``In Country,'' the movie in which Willis is the most
prominent player.
   The critically acclaimed Holocaust drama ``Enemies, A Love
Story'' was blanked, as was Steven Spielberg's ``Always.'' ``Henry
V'' and its star Kenneth Brannagh did not collect any nominations.
``Drugstore Cowboy'' was ignored as well.
   ``Born on the Fourth of July,'' ``Glory'' and ``When Harry Met
Sally ...,'' all films released in the second half of the year,
drew five Golden Globe nominations apiece. Earning four nominations
each were ``Dead Poets Society,'' ``Do the Right Thing'' and ``The
Little Mermaid.''
   Tom Cruise, who stars in ``Born on the Fourth of July'' as the
paraplegic Vietnam veteran Ron Kovic, received one of the movie's
five nominations, for best dramatic actor.
   The film was also nominated for best dramatic motion picture,
best director (Oliver Stone), best screenplay (Stone and Kovic),
and best original score (John Williams).
   ``Glory,'' the story of an all-black Civil War regiment,
collected nominations for best dramatic motion picture, best
director (Edward Zwick), best supporting actor (Denzel Washington),
best screenplay (Kevin Jarre) and best original score (James
Horner).
   The romantic comedy ``When Harry Met Sally ...'' was selected
for best musical or comic picture, best comic actor (Billy
Crystal), best comic actress (Meg Ryan), best director (Rob Reiner)
and best screenplay (Nora Ephron).
   Steven Soderbergh, the heralded director of ``sex, lies and
videotape,'' was nominated not for his directing but for his
writing. The film also was picked for best dramatic actress for
Andie MacDowell and best supporting actress for Laura San Giacomo.
   The Golden Globe voters paid little attention to some of this
year's box-office blockbusters, including ``Honey, I Shrunk the
Kids,'' ``Look Who's Talking'' and ``Ghostbusters II,'' which
received no nominations. ``Batman'' and ``Indiana Jones and the
Last Crusade'' earned only one each.
   In the foreign press' TV nominations, the leading nominee was
``L.A. Law'' with eight. ``Cheers'' and ``Lonesome Dove'' followed
with four each.
   Joining ``Glory'' and ``Born on the Fourth of July'' in the race
for best dramatic motion picture are ``Crimes and Misdemeanors,''
``Dead Poets Society'' and ``Do the Right Thing.''
   Apart from ``When Harry Met Sally ...,'' the battle for best
comic or musical movie includes ``Driving Miss Daisy,'' ``The
Little Mermaid,'' ``Shirley Valentine'' and ``The War of the
Roses.''
   The Golden Globes will be presented at the Beverly Hilton Hotel
on Jan. 20 and will be seen on the TBS Superstation in a show
produced by Dick Clark.
   The foreign press will present its honorary Cecil B. DeMille
award to Audrey Hepburn.
</TEXT>

</DOC>