<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0176 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2052EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Storms-ColdRdp 2ndLd-Writethru a0692 12-18 0901</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Storms-Cold Rdp, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0692,0918</SECOND>
<HEAD>Arctic Air Brings Winter to Dixie, Shatters Records in North</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Subs 7th graf, `At least ..., with 2 grafs to UPDATE deaths
total and total exposure deaths in Chicago.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto AX3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MITCHELL LANDSBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A Canadian delivery of sleet and ice sledded into the deep South
on Monday in a winter preview that cracked century-old temperature
records across the Midwest and clogged the Missouri River with a
75-mile ice jam.
   The bitter weather closed schools from Mississippi to Michigan,
and forecasters said no change was in sight. The cold is being
caused by a horseshoe-shaped flow of air that follows the West
Coast up to Alaska, chills out and plunges down through Canada into
the East and Midwest.
   ``It's simply a pipeline that carries ... the cold air
southward,'' said Ed Ferguson, deputy director of the federal
government's Severe Storms Forecast Center in Kansas City. ``And by
southward, I mean all the way to the Gulf of Mexico.''
   Southerners from central Mississippi to the Carolinas awoke
Monday to a Yankee's vista of freezing rain and sleet that made
driving hazardous and was blamed for at least one traffic death.
Hundreds of schools were closed.
   The National Weather Service said as much as an inch of sleet
and freezing rain covered north and central Georgia before dawn,
and freezing rain extended as far south as Savannah.
   Ice on Interstate 85 near Atlanta apparently contributed to a
crash that killed Atlanta Falcons tight end Brad Beckman,
authorities said.
   At least 19 deaths around the nation were blamed on the cold
during the weekend, including the deaths of two young Tulsa, Okla.,
girls who apparently were playing with a makeshift sled Sunday when
they plunged through thin ice on a lake. Two homeless people died
of hypothermia while sleeping in New York City subway stations.
   One weekend hypothermia death in Chicago brought to 10 the
number of people who have died from exposure in the municipal area
so far this winter, said a spokeswoman for the Cook County Medical
Examiner's office.
   A school bus carrying 43 children crashed into a station wagon
on a slippery highway Monday near Shapleighl, Maine, but none of
the children were seriously hurt, officials said.
   Monday's cold broke Dec. 18 records that had held for more than
a century in Columbus, Ohio, where it was minus 7; in Pittsburgh,
where it also was 7 below, and in Detroit, where it was minus 3.
   Other records included Parkersburg, W.Va., at 4 above,
Cincinnati at 3 below, Fort Wayne, Ind., and Cleveland at minus 5,
and Youngstown, Ohio, at minus 8.
   ``Good night, it's been unreal,'' said Pam Decker, co-owner of
Decker's Wrecker Service in Boonville, Ind., which was besieged
with calls about stalled and wrecked cars and the need to
jump-start dead or dying car batteries.
   The Missouri River turned to ice for about a 75-mile stretch
between Blair, Neb., just north of Omaha, and Sioux City, Iowa,
according to the National Weather Service.
   The ice jam had begun late Friday and grew over the weekend.
Officials feared that the ice floe could cause problems for
communities that pump their water from the river, and Weather
Service hydrologist Roy Osugi didn't hold out hope for an early
thaw.
   ``Nothing is going to bust it up except warmer weather,'' Osugi
said. ``We think it's going to stay in place at least this week
because it's going to stay very cold.''
   In St. Joseph, Mo., officials activated a new emergency pump as
a precautionary measure to keep water flowing to the city.
   There were similar problems in the town of Monroe, Mich., where
55,000 water customers were asked to conserve while workers Monday
cleared a frozen intake valve that also was clogged with Lake Erie
zebra mussels, a non-native species which has no natural predators
and is proliferating in the lake.
   In Crooksville, Ohio, officials declared a water emergency after
a series of water main breaks over the weekend. Parts of the small
town had been without service for three days.
   The cold also was the likely cause of a break in a 4-inch pipe
that let water surge through all 12 floors of a new hospital at
Ohio State University in Columbus, causing at least $1 million
damage and delaying its scheduled Jan. 16 opening, said OSU vice
president Richard Jackson.
   Farther west, the arctic weather system carried welcome snow to
Rocky Mountain ski resorts and wind chills of 35 below zero to
parts of Wyoming. It was 26 below at Jordan, Mont., and high
temperatures in some parts of Montana were expected to be below
zero.
   In Colorado, snowfall in the 24 hours that ended Monday morning
included 4 inches at Denver, 16 inches at Vail and 9\ inches at
Steamboat Springs _ which has gotten 99 inches in nine days, said
spokeswoman Barb Jennings.
   At Denver's Stapleton International Airport, spokesman Norm
Avery said crews were out before daybreak, clearing 10 runways.
However, he said flights were delayed up to an hour because of the
snow.
   Ferguson, of the Severe Storms Forecast Center, said the outlook
for most of the country is for below-average temperatures for the
next month or so.
   ``There's no promise that we can see in any of our projections
that we're going to have balmy weather in the middle of winter,''
he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>