<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 1735EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel Bjt   12-31 0686</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel, Bjt,0706</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shamir Sacks Minister for Meeting Wi$hPLO</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NICOLAS B. TATRO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir ignited a major
political crisis Sunday by firing a top Labor Party minister he
accused of meeting with PLO officials.
   Shamir accused Science Minister Ezer Weizman of defying
government policy against contacts with the Palestine Liberation
OrganizatiOnXand of conspiring ``behind the prime minister's back''
with the PLO.
   Vice Premier Shimon Peres, the Labor leader, said Shamir's
action provoked ``a very serious crisis.''
   ``The prime minister must rescind his decision,'' he said on
armed forces radio, adding ``we have nothing to compromise about.''
   Energy Minister Moshe Shahal, a leading Labor figure, suggested
Shamir wanted to ``torpedo the political initiative'' to avoid a
showdown with the United States over proposals for talks with
Palestinians and elections in the occupied territories.
   A meeting of American, Egyptian and Israeli foreign ministers is
scheduled for January in Washington.
   Labor leaders planned to meet with Peres to determine what to do
next.
   A Likud official who demanded anonymity suggested Labor would
stay in the government because it would not want to turn an
election into a referendum on whether to meet with the PLO.
   Although this was the most serious crisis of the year-old
government, there appeared to be some room for reconciliation.
   Shamir's dismissal letter does not take effect for 48 hours,
giving both parties time to work out a compromise as they have done
in repeated past crises over the past six years of coalition rule.
   Shamir said he hoped the government would not break up over the
issue. He sce Labor should not defend Weizman because he had
violated a government consensus against dealing with the PLO, which
he labeled a terrorist organization.
   ``Here's a Cabinet minister who not only acts against the
government policy, behind the prime minister's back, with our most
cangerous enemies (but) he ... instructs them how to confront our
arguments, how to conduct their relations with the United States
and how to spoil our moves.
   ``How long can we suffer this situation?'' Shamir said, thumping
his fist on a table.
   Shamir said Weizman, a 65-year-old former defense minister and
fighter pilot, had passed messages to PLO Chairman Yasser Arafat
and met with PLO offcials whom he declined to name.
   Weizman declined to say whether he met with anyone from the PLO
but said he had met with Dr. Ahmed Tibi, an Israeli-Arab doctor
whom foreign reports have identified as a go-between in Israeli-PLO
contacts. Weizman said he was later contacted by Israeli security
agents who advised him on what to say to Tibi.
   Israel radio reported t@aj the PLO meetings continued until
recently and were held with Peres' full knowledge and approval.
   It said they focused on an attempt to influence the PLO to
accept U.S. Secretary of State James A. Baker III's plan to arrange
talks between Palestinians and Israelis to revive the stalled peace
plan, and the make up of the Palestinian delegation for the talks.
Israel Television said that in recent months Weizman talked uuh
PLO officials in meetings arranged by Egypt.
   It also claimed Weizman talked with a PLO official in Zurich,
Switzerland, about Peace Now demonstrations in Jerusalem over the
weekend involving 15,000 Palestinians, Israelis and Europeans.
   The protests, which resulted in more than 25 injured and 60
arrested, angered rightwing politicians who claimed they were
arranged by the PLO.
   Weizman accused Shamir of hypocrisy, saying the prime minister
and other Israeli officials had met local PLO activists and
indirectly negotiated with the PLO through the United States.
   But Weizman said Shamir's action might force ``the state of
Israel to decide where it is headed.'-   ``We will have to finally decide
if we talk to Palestinians. ...
I have always said openly, in the press, TV, the Cabinet, that we
should talk to the PLO.''
   Arafat said in Baghdad, Iraq, Sunday that neither he nor any of
his officials had met with Weizman but said a planned meeting in
Moscow two years ago was canceled after Weizman failed to show up.
</TEXT>

</DOC>