<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0186 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1626EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-HomeSales 2ndLd-Writethru f0095 12-27 0565</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Home Sales, 2nd Ld-Writethru, f0095,0580</SECOND>
<HEAD>Existing Home Sales at Quickest Pace in Nearly a Year</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 14th gaf pvs to CORRECT sales rate in Midwest to 950,000
from 450,000; PICKS UP 15th graf pvs, `All of...; Also moved on general
news wires</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN CRUTSINGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Economics Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sales of existing homes advanced 3.2 percent
in November, with a big jump in activity in the South spurring the
fastest growth rate in 11 months, a real estate trade group
reported Wednesday.
   The National Association of Realtors said sales of existing
single-family homes rose to a seasonally adjusted annual rate of
3.59 million units last month, the best performance since sales
reached a rate of 3.92 million units in December 1988.
   The 3.2 percent October-to-November sales increase followed a
1.1 percent decline in October. It was the biggest percentage gain
since a 4.5 percent rise in August.
   Analysts credited declining mortgage rates for the upturn in
sales activity. But they said that housing sales presented a mixed
picture with some areas of the country such as the Northeast
hurting because of a rapid surge in prices in the past several
years.
   ``Some large, high-cost markets have experienced some softening
this year. However, many smaller, secondary cities are quite
strong,'' said John Tuccillo, chief economist for the realtors.
   He said the disparity in sales between high-cost areas and more
moderately priced markets should continue in 1990.
   Sluggish sales in high-cost areas has prompted some fears of a
coming housing recession, but Norman D. Flynn, president of the
realtors group, said the doomsayers would be proven wrong.
   ``People who are predicting hard times for housing are not
considering how much prices rose in high-cost areas over the past
few years,'' said Flynn, who cited the Northeast, where the median
price is up 85 percent from five years ago.
   Tuccillo predicted that falling mortgage rates would continue to
boost home sales in coming months. The national average for
fixed-rate mortgages dipped to 9.69 percent last week, down from a
high last March of 11.22 percent.
   The median price for homes sold in November edged up 0.4 percent
to $93,000.
   The West pulled ahead of the Northeast in November as the region
with the highest priced homes, recording a median resale cost of
$150,200 last month. The Northeast was second with a median price
of $145,800, followed by the South at $82,400 and the Midwest at
$70,900.
   The median is the point at which half the homes sold for more
and half for less.
   In November, the sales increase was led by a 9.2 percent jump in
sales in the South, where homes were sold at an annual rate of 1.42
million units in November. Sales were up 3.2 percent in the West to
an annual rate of 640,000 units. The Northeast posted a 1.7 percent
rise to an annual rate of 590,000 units.
   Sales in the Midwest were down 4 percent to an annual rate of
950,000 units.
   All of the percentage comparisons were with October sales rates.
When compared to sales in November 1988, the Midwest had a small
increase of 1.1 percent while activity in the South was up by 0.7
percent.
   However, sales in the Northeast are down 13.2 percent when
compared to a year ago while sales in the West are off by 5.9
percent compared to November 1988.
</TEXT>

</DOC>