<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0159 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1342EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-Cyprus-Reunification Adv07   12-28 1007</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Cyprus-Reunification, Adv 07,1039</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv07</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Jan. 7 or Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Grassroots Unity Movement Quietly Emerges on Cyprus</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALEX EFTY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For the first time since Turkey invaded
in 1974, openings are appearing in the line that divides Greek and
Turkish Cypriots. Some see it as the first sign of a breakthrough
toward reunification.
   Withlittle fanfare, ordinary Greek and Turkish Cypriots have
been in touch with each other to seek an end to 15 years of
political and religious division on this east Mediterranean island.
   ``Contact between the two communities has been increasing,''
noted columnist Petros Andreou in the Cyprus Mail, an
English-language newspaper published in the Greek Cypriot sector.
   ``At last, the two sides are beginning to understand each
other's position.''
   Events in Eastern Europe may have inspired the grassroots trend.
Since the Berlin Wall began to crumble in November several groups
from the rival communities have come together for the first time
since the Turkish army in 1974 seized the northern third of the
island in the wake of a short-lived coup by those seeking union
with Greece.
   The Moslem Turkish Cypriot minority declared the
Turkish-occupied north a republic in 1983, but it is recognized
only by Turkey.
   Cyprus still has a long way to go before the barriers come down
as they have in Europe. But columnist Andreou said that the
570,000-member Christian Greek Cypriot community's growing
awareness of social and economic problems is finally taking the
edge off their obsession with the island's divisions.
   ``People are beginning to realize that there's more to life than
the `national question','' Andreou wrote.
   ``Perhaps the same realization is crystallizing in the north. If
it is, then it's quite probable that people will eventually begin
to shed all their nationalistic fixations and instead start to deal
with what is really important _ how they can live in peace on this
island.''
   Since the invasion, Rauf Denktash, president of the northern
statelet, has banned Turkish Cypriots from visiting the Greek
sector and refused to allow Greek Cypriots to visit the north. The
Greek Cypriots have imposed no travel restrictions.
   But Denktash recently allowed the door to open a crack:
   _World War II veterans from the two communities who fought side
by side against the Germans held an emotional reunion in the
no-man's land of the United Nations-patrolled buffer zone in
December. Old comrades-in-arms embraced, complaining about their
separation and voicing hopes of a settlement.
   _Alpay Durduran, a member of the Turkish Cypriot Parliament and
leader of the newly formed opposition New Cyprus Party, attended a
public discussion in the Greek sector of Nicosia, the island's
divided capital, on whether the two sides could live together again
in harmony. He described his visit as ``a unique and historic
event.''
   _A month earlier, Denktash allowed Greek Cypriot journalists to
visit the Turkish sector for the first time since the invasion and
permitted Turkish Cypriot doctors to attend a buffer zone meeting
with Greek physicians.
   United Nations Secretary-General Javier Perez de Cuellar noted
in December: ``The recent relaxation in the crossing procedures by
the Turkish Cypriot side and the growing number of contacts between
groups of the two sides are positive developments which should be
built on.''
   Until now, most of the drive for reunification has come from the
Greek Cypriots, 200,000 of whom were forced to flee the Turkish
north. They left homes, businesses and roots put down many
generations ago.
   The Turkish Cypriots, outnumbered 5-1, believe that having their
own enclave affords protection from the sectarian violence that
plagued the island for years before 1974, when some 40,000 Turks
fled north from the predominntly Greek south.
   U.N.-sponsored talks between Denktash and President George
Vassiliou, the Greek Cypriot leader, on reunifying Cyprus in a
bizonal federation have deadlocked.
   The Greek Cypriots are reluctant to meet Denktash's demands for
political parity or make concessions they believe would be
tantamount to recognizing a state they and the United Nations brand
illegal.
   Denktash rejects U.N. resolutions calling for the withdrawal
from the north of an estimated 30,000 Turkish army troops and
35,000 to 50,000 Turkish settlers and the return of Greek Cypriots
who fled in 1974.
   Denktash argues that this would create security problems for his
community and trigger fresh intercommunal clashes.
   But an emerging opposition bloc in the north believes
reunification, with the proper guarantees for both sides, is the
right road.
   Durduran, the Turkish Cypriot member of Parliament, acknowledged
that both sides still fear and mistrust each other.
   ``Both communities have committed atrocities against each
other,'' he said. ``But if we want to live in a federated state
democratically, respecting human rights, we must avoid the mistakes
of the past.
   ``Today's challenge is: Can we honestly care about each other?
Can we escape from the past? Our mistakes will teach us how to
proceed to build a common future together.''
   A predominantly Greek Cypriot gathering loudly applauded his
words.
   The Greek Cypriot newspaper Phileleftheros said: ``It takes
courage and vision for a Turkish Cypriot politician to come to the
Greek Cypriot side and address a Greek Cypriot audience, ignoring
the overt and covert threats and intimidation of the chauvinists of
his side.''
   Denktash maintains that Turkish Cypriots oppose reunification.
But Durduran rejected that.
   ``The leadership in the north has tried to tie our tongues and
forbid us from using the word reunification,'' he said.
   ``When we talk in a language that annoys our leaders we get
bombs at our doors.''
   Two small bombs have exploded outside Duduran's home in
Nicosia's Turkish sector, causing slight damage, in recent weeks.
   Reunification is also supported by Mustafa Akinci, mayor of
Nicosia's Turkish sector, who for years has been quietly working
with his Greek Cypriot opposite number, Lellos Demetriades, to
build sectarian bridges.
   Akinci has said he will run against Denktash in presidential
elections in the north this coming spring. He's taking on
Denktash's powerful party machine, and an Akinci victory is seen as
very likely to spur reunification.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Sunday, Jan. 7</NOTE>

</DOC>