<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0118 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1341EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Panama-Hometown     12-22 0705</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Hometown,0729</SECOND>
<HEAD>Small Wisconsin Town Mourns Death of Soldier</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto XER1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT IMRIE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CONOVER, Wis. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A cigar box in a tavern was the first honor
this small community could offer a hometown soldier who was killed
during the U.S. invasion of Panama just days before his birthday.
   The box was placed in the tavern to raise money for a memorial
for Pfc. John Mark Price, who would have turned 23 on Christmas Eve.
   ``He did not have enough money'' to come home for the holidays,
said his mother, Diane Price. ``His presents are not under the
tree, they're in the mail.''
   This holiday season was the first since her husband's death
three years ago that Mrs. Price put up of Christmas tree and
decorated her house. Her husband, John, died suddenly of a heart
attack in October 1986.
   ``I lost a husband. I thought that was bad. But this is even
harder,'' she said in a telephone interview Friday.
   Mrs. Price said the Army had not released details of her son's
death during the invasion Wednesday. His body has been taken to
Dover Air Force Base in Delaware for preparation for burial.
   ``He will be buried by his dad,'' a weeping Mrs. Price said.
   Friends in Conover, a town of about 150 near the
Wisconsin-Michigan line, said they remembered the Army Ranger as a
polite, hard-working, jovial young man who enjoyed his military
service.
   ``He was an extremely friendly person and outgoing for a young
chap,'' Postmaster Lorrayne Maki said. ``He dearly was loved by
everyone. He was the most ideal American boy you would find.''
   Price was a paratrooper based at Fort Lewis, Wash. He enlisted
in the Army in 1988 to raise money so he could return to college,
his mother said. His two brothers are also in the Army.
   ``I just couldn't understand why he wanted to do it. I guess he
was a person who wanted a challenge,'' Mrs. Price said. ``Whatever
he was in, he gave it 100 percent. He was very religious and he
really loved the Lord.''
   Mrs. Price, an ambulance worker, said she talked to her son Dec.
10 and he hinted he was headed on a big mission, but he did not say
where he was going.
   ``He just said something big was going to happen, just watch the
news,'' she recalled.
   Penny Lafata, 30, talked with him during his last visit home in
June.
   ``He just really loved being in the Rangers. He was really
enthusiastic about it,'' she said. ``He talked about the survival
training, those kinds of things.''
   Price, who went by his middle name Mark, was the oldest of four
children. His sister, Ruth Ann, 21, attends college in Illinois.
His 20-year-old brother Jim is an infantryman based in Oklahoma,
and his brother, Dan, 19, is an artillery man bases in Kansas. Both
were returning to Conover on Friday.
   Townspeople started a collection to buy a memorial, probably a
bronze plaque, for Price. By Thursday night, a cigar box at the
Cocktail Corner tavern contained $10 for the ``Mark Price
Memorial.''
   Mary Ann Manijak said she would place coffee cans throughout the
town to collect more money.
   ``There are 50 states, and Conover, which is so small, to have
this happen to one of our boys...'' she said.
   At Eagle River Memorial Hospital, where Mrs. Price works, the
flag was at half-staff Friday, said Nancy Rozga, an ambulance
supervisor and friend of Mrs. Price. Hospital workers were passing
around an envelope for money, she said.
   Mrs. Price said she supported President Bush's decision to
mobilize troops in Panama to out Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   ``I am not angry about what happened. When there is war people
get killed,'' she said.
   Price graduated from Northland Pines High School in nearby Eagle
River in 1985. He attended college briefly in the Chicago area,
worked in a paint factory, returned to Conover and worked in a car
wash before joining the Army.
   ``He was small town kid. He knew everybody. He loved hunting,
fishing, the outdoors,'' Mrs. Price said. ``If God created a person
to live up here in the northwoods, it would be him.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>