<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1021EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-Panama-Smithsonian 1stLd-Writethru a0450 12-22 0328</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Smithsonian, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0450,320</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eds: New thruout with group rescued</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. troops in helicopters rescued 11 people
associated with the Smithsonian Institution early today, removing
them from a remote schoolhouse two days after they were abducted by
Panamanian troops.
   ``At 8:45 a.m., the Department of Defense notified the
Smithsonian that all 11 people from the Smithsonian Tropical
Research Institute in Panama were safe at Clayton Air Force
Base...,'' the Smithsonian said in a statement.
   The group, which had been working on the San Blas islands in the
Caribbean, were forced by Panamian troops to go to the mainland on
Wednesday, shortly after the U.S. invasion.
   They were reported to be free on Thursday, but they remained at
an isolated area on the mainland until their rescue by American
troops.
   ``Early accounts indicate that the group was picked up at a
remote schoolhouse between the towns of Carti and El Llano and
transported by U.S. military helicopters,'' the Smithsonian said.
   Before their rescue, members of the group had access to a radio
that enabled them to contact Smithsonian employees in Panama City,
according to Madeleine Jacobs, a Smithsonian employee.
   The group _ five Americans, five Panamanians and one Venezuelan
_ performed marine research on the coral reef.
   The Americans were identified as Dr. Nancy Knowlton, a
Smithsonian biologist; her daughter, Rebecca, 4; Preston Hardison,
a graduate student at the University of Washington; Steve Travers,
research assistant at the research institute, and Greg Summers, a
student at the University of Washington.
   Robert McC. Adams, secretary of the Smithsonian, praised
government officials for their help. ``We are extremely grateful
for all the assistance we have received ...,'' he said.
   Besides its station at San Blas and the headquarters at Panama
City, the tropical institute has several other stations throughout
the isthmus. About 200 people, including 140 tropical institute
employees and 60 visiting scientists and research fellows, work at
the institute.
   The Americans make up 34 employees.
</TEXT>

</DOC>