<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0319EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-US-ElSalvador     12-20 0655</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-El Salvador,650</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Officials Cite Progress in El Salvador, Despite Criticism</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Responding to congressional unrest over U.S.
policy toward El Salvador, Bush administration officials say
American aid to that country is yielding substantial benefits in
battlefield performance and in protection of human rights.
   A senior administration official who briefed reporters on
Tuesday said leftist rebels were ``sadly mistaken'' when they
assumed that the uprising they launched six weeks ago would produce
a popular uprising.
   In addition, the official said, the armed forces are showing an
increasing sensitivity to human rights concerns and, contrary to
popular wisdom, there has not been a resurgence of rightist death
squad activity.
   But Sen. Edward M. Kennedy, expressing skepticism about the
wisdom of U.S. policy, asked the General Accounting Office on
Tuesday to determine if U.S. military aid has been used effectively
in El Salvador's long battle against the rebels.
   Kennedy, D-Mass., said the results of the GAO investigation will
form the background of a congressional review early next year of
U.S. policy toward El Salvador.
   The effectiveness of the large and continuing U.S. aid program
is called into question by the strong rebel offensive mounted
against Salvadoran government forces last month, Kennedy said.
   The United States has provided El Salvador with well over $3
billion in economic and military aid over the past decade.
   Kennedy said he also wants to know if U.S. military personnel
inside El Salvador have any knowledge of the activities of
right-wing death squads and whether they are required to disclose
such information.
   A report issued over the weekend by Americas Watch, a New
York-based human rights organization, said rights violations in El
Salvador have been occurring at a ``breathtaking pace'' since the
rebel offensive began. The report documents abuses by both
government and rebel forces.
   The U.S. official, who briefed reporters on the condition that
he not be identified, said the number of unexplained deaths, after
a dramatic decline in the early 1980's, is still ``marginally
down'' despite occasional ``blips.''
   He said there is no hard evidence of a resurgence of death squad
activities either as the result of the victory by the rightist
party last March or of the offensive begun last month by the FMLN
rebels.
   ``The offensive is falling apart,'' the official said, asserting
that the rebels now are facing food and medicine shortages.
   He estimated that perhaps half of the rebel force of about 8,000
has been lost as a result of death, wounding, capture or desertions.
   The official said there is no conclusive evidence implicating
either the military or leftist forces in the unsolved murder of six
Jesuit priests in El Salvador last month.
   But Rep. Joe Moakley, D-Mass., a member of a special House panel
investigating the murders, said Tuesday there is circumstantial
evidence to implicate the Salvadoran military.
   Moakley said this is the case despite the fact that during a
week of questioning by the FBI, a Salvadoran woman, Mrs. Lucia
Barrera de Cerna, withdrew her story that the night of the murders
she saw armed men in military uniform near the priests' residence,
heard their voices and heard heavy gunfire.
   This change in the woman's testimony did not justify claims by
Salvadoran officials that Mrs. Barrera's testimony has been
discredited, thus proving that Salvadoran armed forces were not
involved in the murders, Moakley said.
   ``There is other circumstantial evidence to implicate the
military,'' Moakley said.
   He said Mrs. Barrera repeated her original story to members of
the special committee, declaring she had felt ``pressured'' to say
she had actually seen nothing that night after her FBI
interrogators made it evident they did not believe her.
   ``She did change her story at that time but told us that she did
so only to end the questioning of her,'' Moakley said.
   The State Department has denied ``absolutely and unequivocally''
allegations that she was mistreated during her interrogation.
</TEXT>

</DOC>