<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0552EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-JudgeConvicted     12-18 0554</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Judge Convicted,0572</SECOND>
<HEAD>Says He Will Fight Corruption Conviction</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID S. MARTIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EBENSBURG, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A suspended judge says he'll fight his
bribery and corruption convictions for seeking money from an
employee, an attorney and a bank in the course of official business.
   Former Cambria County Judge Joseph K. O'Kicki said he would
appeal Saturday night's jury verdict: ``I expect eventually the
justice system will allow truth to prevail.''
   Prosecutors alleged that greed motivated the 59-year-old judge
to rule like a monarch in the elegant 19th century courthouse in
the foothills of the southern Allegheny Mountains.
   He was convicted of bribery in asking for $500 from a court
employee for a job promotion never given, for demanding a favorable
loan from a bank with a guardianship case before him and for asking
an attorney for a ``commission'' after a generous award to the
lawyer's clients. He also was found guilty of official oppression,
a general charge incorporating elements of the other alleged
violations.
   O'Kicki was acquitted of open lewdness for allegedly calling two
former secretaries into his office while wearing only his underwear.
   He also was acquitted on a charge that he bribed a Johnstown
strip mining company, gave an unemployed coal miner inside
information in a money-making scheme and used court employees to do
personal chores for him.
   O'Kicki could be sentenced to a maximum of 26 years in prison
and fined $57,500. A sentencing hearing has yet to be scheduled.
   He will lose his job, $80,000 salary and pension upon
sentencing, the prosecutor said.
   Jurors returned the verdict after 16{ hours of deliberations
over two days, following a seven-week trial in Northampton County
Court.
   Defense attorney Richard Galloway argued for a mistrial because
one juror appeared to disagree with the others when they were asked
to stand individually and give their verdict on each count. But
Judge Richard Grifo denied the motion, saying he hadn't heard any
disagreement, and the Galloway promised to appeal.
   As the jury was polled, James C. Miller appeared to say, ``Not
guilty'' three times on the six guilty counts. He also apparently
replied ``guilty'' to one of the counts of which O'Kicki was found
innocent.
   ``I think there's no question the verdict is non-unanimous and
can't stand,'' Galloway said.
   Reached by telephone, Miller said he agreed with the other
jurors.
   ``I absolutely did,'' he said.
   Jury foreman Francis A. Bazyk said the jurors had been unanimous
before going into the courtroom. ``He was just overcome by
nervousness,'' Bazyk said of Miller.
   O'Kicki faces 16 other charges in a second trial focusing on his
private business dealings. That trial hasn't been scheduled.
   In his testimony during the seven-week trial, O'Kicki said he
was joking with attorney Richard J. Green Jr. about the commission.
   The judge claimed he had been persecuted by the state after he
drew the ire of Johnstown millionaire W.E. Schonek, a political
power broker and Lt. Gov. Mark Singel's father-in-law.
   O'Kicki said the millionaire was angry at him for encouraging
Schonek's brother, Rudolph, to make a stock gift worth more than
$200,000 to St. Francis College in Loretto.
   Schonek and Singel denied any involvement with the investigation.
   O'Kicki, elected to the bench in 1971, was suspended by the
state Supreme Court in June 1988 and was indicted in March.
</TEXT>

</DOC>