<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 2359EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WanderingTetons     12-25 0559</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Wandering Tetons,0575</SECOND>
<HEAD>Photos of Tetons Used in Ads For Points Far Distant</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Tuesday AMs report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JULIA PRODIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JACKSON, Wyo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Some advertisers promoting vacation spots
hundreds of miles from Wyoming have the power to move mountains.
   The picturesque Grand Teton and its sister mountains have been
used in ads for Amtrak, which doesn't run through Wyoming; and such
places as a resort in Montana and even a condominium in the heart
of the Rockies in Colorado.
   For the record, the Tetons have been standing firm in
northwestern Wyoming for eons.
   And while imitation may be the sincerest form of flattery, the
Jackson Hole Chamber of Commerce isn't happy to see the craggy
peaks plastered on brochures touting destinations that don't have a
view of the range even on a clear day.
   ``The Tetons are one of the most recognizable mountain ranges in
the world and we are more than a little miffed that our competitors
continue to use our assets to promote their areas,'' said Carol
Waller, the chamber's director of marketing. ``We are seriously
considering trademarking the Tetons _ I'm only half-joking.''
   While managers of those out-of-sight resorts responded with
shock or embarrassment when queried about their use of the Tetons,
none offered any apologies. Not even resort managers in Colorado,
which boasts of being home to the greatest skiing in the world.
   Larry Dempsey, general manager of the Crestwood condominium
hotel in Snowmass Village, Colo., just north of Aspen, said he
didn't even realize his magazine advertisement of a skier used the
Tetons as a backdrop.
   No matter, he said, the picture is representative of a winter
ski vacation in the Colorado Rockies _ even if the Tetons are
nearly 400 miles north.
   The ad agency that used the Tetons on the brochure couldn't say
much more than ``oops.''
   ``It was just a case of mistaken identity,'' said Bill Cutting,
of the agency Penna, Powers, Cutting and Haynes of Salt Lake City.
``Believe me, we had no intention of using the Tetons to advertise
a condo project in Aspen.''
   Still, he said, the Tetons do resemble Aspen's Maroon Bells.
   ``When you look at one mountain from 25 different angles, it
would be difficult to tell the difference,'' said Cutting. Besides,
he insisted, no one reading one of the brochures would know the
difference or care much, either.
   Except Waller. She is contacting the resorts to ask them to
retract their advertisements.
   One of those being contacted is the Fairmont Hot Springs Resort
in Gregson, Mont. It uses a brochure with a full view of the nearly
14,000-foot Grand Teton, crown jewel of the Teton range.
``Naturally inviting,'' the cover says.
   Resort Manager Ed Henrich said the Tetons were used when the
marketing company couldn't find any stock photos of Montana's
Pintlar Mountains.
   ``I was totally against it, but we had to get something out on
the market immediately,'' he said. ``No, you cannot see the Tetons
from Montana, but they look an awful lot like the Pintlars.''
   Waller says it's false advertising.
   ``I can't say how much it's hurting us, but we'd rather not
confuse people. They might see the beautiful mountains and wonder
if they are in California, Wyoming, Montana or Colorado. We'd just
like them to know they're in Wyoming,'' she said. ``They're not
portable.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>