<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0833EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Lithuania 1stLd-Writethru a0500 12-19 0490</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lithuania, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0500,0500</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lithuanian Communists May Split From Soviet Party</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 5th graf, `A small ...' to CORRECT street name.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK J. PORUBCANSKY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VILNIUS, U.S.S.R. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lithuanian Communists today opened a
congress aimed at breaking off from the Soviet Communist Party and
declaring themselves an independent organization that will compete
in a multiparty system.
   Earlier this month, Lithuania become the first Soviet republic
to delete from its constitution the article enshrining the leading
role of the Communist Party.
   Lithuanian party leader Algirdas Brazauskas opened today's
meeting of more than 1,000 delegates declaring that: ``Only by
joint efforrts can we justify the people's trust.''
   Outside, several hundred Lithuanians gathered on the steps of
the opera and ballet theater where the congress was being held.
They carried red, green and yellow Lithuanian flags and banners
backing the party's proposed split.
   A small group of demonstrators marched down Gediminas Avenue,
the main street, to protest against even a reformed Communist
Party. One sign proclaimed, ``Stop Communism in Lithuania,'' with
the word ``Communism'' painted red to simulate dripping blood.
   The congress is to last most of the week and observers expect a
vote on the party's status to take place Wednesday or Thursday.
   One Lithuanian observer, Romas Gudaitis, wrote in today's
edition of the youth newspaper Komsomolskaya Pravda that
``Lithuania right now is like a volcano.''
   He said, ``the political tension has reached its culmination.''
   A draft declaration on the Lithuanian Communist Party's status
proclaims it to be part of the world Communist movement, but says
nothing about its relationship with the Soviet Communist Party.
   Lithuanian Communist Party leaders on Dec. 7 led the republic's
Parliament in striking Article 6 of the Lithuanian Constitution,
which had declared the Communist Party to be ``the leading force''
in Lithuanian society.
   Parliament directed that legislation be prepared to allow for
the registration of other political parties, a move toward
developing in Lithuania what lawmakers in Moscow have refused to
allow countrywide.
   The Lithuanian Communist leaders say they need to reform the
party and break its formal monopoly on power if they are to have
any chance of success in local elections, which are scheduled for
Feb. 24.
   The Lithuanian Communist Party has lost 10,000 members, or about
5 percent of its membership, this year, according to party
statistics.
   Soviet Communist Politburo member Vadim A. Medvedev was sent to
Vilnius three weeks ago with a message from President Mikhail S.
Gorbachev urging the Lithuanian Communists not to break from the
Soviet party.
   ``It must not be allowed, it is inadmissable now to follow the
path of splitting Communists on the basis of national or social
background,'' Gorbachev, who is also Communist Party leader, said
in the message delivered by Medvedev.
   Lithuanian Communist leaders were summoned to Moscow in
mid-November for a meeting with Soviet party's ruling Politburo on
the question of splitting from the Soviet Communist Party.
</TEXT>

</DOC>