<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0131 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1847EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Shevardnadze 1stLd-Writethru a0587 12-19 0812</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Shevardnadze, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0587,0833</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shevardnadze Pays Unprecedented Call on NATO</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-East Germany, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 2 grafs after 5th pvs, `It is...' to UPDATE with Shevardnadze
in London. Pick up 6th, `Shevardnadze's unprecedented...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>LaserPhoto BRU1,3,11, LaserColor BRU4 ^By SALLY JACOBSEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRUSSELS, Belgium (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard
Shevardnadze on Tuesday symbolically ended 40 years of East-West
hostility and suspicion by paying a visit to NATO headquarters.
   He said the North Atlantic Treaty Organization and the Warsaw
Pact should stay in place to help ensure stability at a time of
tumultuous change on the European continent.
   Shevardnadze later went before the European Parliament, the
legislative arm of the European Community, and strongly cautioned
against quick efforts to unite the two Germanys. Leaders of the
12-nation trading bloc recently gave their strong backing to
eventual reunification.
   The Soviet official noted East Germany was an ally in the Warsaw
Pact and said:
   ``It is necessary to proceed on the basis of the postwar
realities, namely, the existence of two sovereign German states.
... A retreat from that is fraught with destabilization in Europe.''
   Later, Shevardnadze flew to London, where he got a strong
endorsement from Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher for keeping NATO
and the Warsaw Pact in place.
   Neither Mrs. Thatcher and Shevardnadze would give details of
their 2-hour discussion. But Shevardnadze said that ``on a number
of very important world issues, both global issues and regional
issues, we have a very good measure of agreement.''
   Shevardnadze's unprecedented visit to NATO headquarters on the
outskirts of Brussels was a dramatic sign of the reduced military
tensions between Western nations and their potential adversaries in
the East bloc. NATO was formed in 1949 to guard against the
security threat posed by the Soviet Union.
   After meeting with NATO Secretary-General Manfred Woerner,
Shevardnadze joked that his visit had been likened to traveling to
a volcano's crater. But he said he found ``a very friendly
atmosphere. So this was not a terrible thing.''
   Shevardnadze, who also met the ambassadors of the 16 NATO
nations, stressed the need for continuing the two alliances.
   ``We do believe the Warsaw Treaty and NATO at this crucial stage
in European development ... are able to play a very important
stabilizing role,'' he told reporters.
   Woerner, a former German defense minister, said Shevardnadze
mentioned in their private talks ``the very essential role of the
Americans here in Europe.''
   The officials said they agreed an East-West accord on slashing
conventional, or non-nuclear, weapons in Europe could be wrapped up
next year. They said the United States and the Soviet Union also
should reach agreement in 1990 on a new treaty cutting long-range
nuclear weapons.
   Woerner said Shevardnadze suggested formal contacts be set up
between the two military alliances. But the NATO chief said he
reminded Shevardnadze that NATO, unlike the Warsaw Pact, was a
voluntary association of democratically elected governments.
   William H. Taft IV, the American ambassador to NATO, said the
Warsaw Pact ``needs to do some more changing before it's a proper
partner in dialogue with NATO.''
   No surprises were reported.
   ``It was an important event (but) the importance was really a
symbolic one rather than substantive,'' said Gordon Smith, Canada's
envoy to NATO.
   Added Taft, ``It was more of a get-acquainted session.''
   In his speech to the European Parliament, Shevardnadze welcomed
U.S. Secretary of State James A. Baker III's recent call for NATO
to adopt a more political role in an era of reduced tensions. He
said the Warsaw Pact also must change with ``political aspects
prevailing over its military substance.''
   But the focus of his remarks was on the subject of German unity,
which has gained increasing attention with the opening of borders
between the two countries.
   Shevardnadze the question of borders in Europe was settled
permanently but the Germanys retained the right to
self-determination.
   He said there should be ``due regard for the special position of
the two German states and their responsibility to assure all
nations of Europe and the world that a threat of war will never
again come from the German soil.''
   He said a number of questions remained unanswered.
   ``Where are the ... guarantees that German unity would not
eventually create a threat to the national security of other states
and to peace in Europe,'' he asked.
   He wondered where a united Germany would fit into
military-political structures. ``One cannot seriously expect the
status of (East Germany) to change radically while the status of
(West Germany) would remain the same,'' he said.
   ``Surely the peoples of the Soviet Union are entitled to know
what any changes in Central Europe would mean for their future and
their security,'' he said. ``We paid the price of 20 million lives
for the existing European stability.''
   ``Furthermore, can the German people themselves forget the
national tragedy brought onto them by Hitlerism,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>