<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0296 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2102EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Ramada     12-20 0300</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ramada,0310</SECOND>
<HEAD>Completes Corporate Restructuring</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ramada Inc. Wednesday announced completion of a
corporate restructuring that includes the sale of its worldwide
hotel business and formation of a new company to operate its New
Jersey and Nevada casinos.
   Ramada shareholders approved the revised restructuring plan
earlier this month, agreeing to accept $1 and one share of stock in
the new company, Aztar Corp., for each share of Ramada stock.
   Gaming regulators in Nevada and New Jersey approved the plan a
short time later.
   Hong Kong-based New World Hotel (Holdings) Ltd. acquired
Ramada's more than 800 hotels and the Ramada name for $540 million.
   The company said it will operate 108 international hotels,
including 14 Ramada Renaissance hotels in the United States, under
the name Ramada International Hotels, and Prime Motor Inns Inc., of
Fiarfield, N.J., will operate or franchise Ramada Inns in the
United States and Rodeway Inns worldwide.
   Wilfried Grau, president and chief executive officer of the new
Ramada International Hotels, said New World acquired the Ramada
hotel business to quickly increase its share of the worldwide
market.
   ``In Hong Kong, New World is a highly regarded hotelier known
for its ownership stake in the Landmark Regent Hotel, rated one of
the top 10 in the world,'' Grau said. ``Once they decided to
develop their hotel interests on a global basis, rather than start
from scratch, they opted to buy an existing international name with
strong management.''
   Ramada International Hotels will be based in Hong Kong, but its
regional office for North America will be in Phoenix, Grau said.
   Aztar, the new company created by the restructuring, will
operate the Tropworld Casino and Entertainment Resort in Atlantic
City, N.J.; Tropicana Resort and Casino in Las Vegas, Nev.; and
Ramada Express Hotel and Casino in Laughlin, Nev.
</TEXT>

</DOC>