<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1414EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Congress     12-24 0643</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Congress,0662</SECOND>
<HEAD>200 Soviet Deputies Storm Out Over Georgian Deaths; Ligachev Accused</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAREY GOLDBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 200 deputies stormed out of the Soviet
Congress on Sunday to protest a defense of the army's brutal
crackdown on ethnic unrest in the republic of Georgia. It took a
personal appeal by President Mikhail S. Gorbachev to bring them
back.
   The discussion also implicated conservative Politburo member
Yegor K. Ligachev in the decision to send troops against Georgian
protesters in April. Nineteen protesters died when soldiers armed
with shovels, clubs and gas charged them. Another person was shot
to death later for violating a curfew.
   Delegates condemned those violent tactics on Sunday.
   Georgians, Balts, progressive deputies and others left the hall
to protest a speech by the chief military prosecutor, Alexander
Katusev, who defended the Soviet troops.
   Katusev's speech followed a congressional commission's report
blaming the army, local party leadership and Ligachev for the
incident.
   Ligachev chaired a meeting of top party leaders two days before
the clash that decided to back Georgian party leaders' request for
military help in breaking up the long-running protest, commission
Chairman Anatoly Sobchak said.
   Sobchak read a letter from Ligachev admitting that when the
leadership discussed the protest in the Georgian capital, Tbilisi,
Interior and Defense Ministry officials were informed of ``the need
to provide forces and means in case of dangerous and
life-threatening events.''
   But Ligachev said in the letter he went on vacation the next day
and only learned the extent of the violence from a television
report afterward.
   ``If some leader makes a decision, I'd like to say he bears
responsibility for that decision whether he finds out about its
results on television or in his office,'' Sobchak said.
   The Georgians and other deputies left the 2,250-member Congress
of People's Deputies after Katusev portrayed the Georgian
pro-independence protesters as armed subversives who provoked the
violence.
   Minutes later, Gorbachev, surrounded by security men and
reporters, emerged into the lobby and sought out the Georgian
delegates, some of them in tears, near the cloakroom.
   ``Why are they persecuting the Georgian people?'' a Georgian
teacher, Natella Bokuchava, asked Gorbachev. ``Defend us! Our
children are watching us.''
   Gorbachev soothed the Georgians with general remarks about
ethnic tolerance, and after they returned to the hall he made a
conciliatory speech assuring them of the high respect of the
Congress and the country.
   Congress later passed a resolution condemning the use of
violence against the Georgian protesters.
   Historian Yuri Afanasyev, a leader of a fledgling opposition
group, said he thought the walkout illustrated ``the further
consolidation of democratic forces.''
   Several dozen Baltic deputies have walked out of the Congress
occasionally to protest their helplessness as a vastly outnumbered
minority, but this was by far the largest walkout since the
Congress opened its first session in May.
   In other action on the last day of its 12-day session, Congress:
   _Followed the lead of Gorbachev and Foreign Minister Eduard A.
Shevardnadze in condemning the Kremlin's decision to send Soviet
troops into Afghanistan 10 years ago. The panel that examined the
decision said only four people were involved, all of them now dead:
then-leader Leonid Brezhnev, Defense Minister Dmitri Ustinov,
Foreign Minister Andrei Gromyko and KGB chief Yuri Andropov. One
deputy proposed the commission consider stripping all privileges
from their widows and families.
   _Was told that the Health Ministry's network of hospitals and
sanitariums reserved for the top party and government elite would
be abolished and given to the public by Jan. 1. Yevgeny Primakov,
head of the panel on privileges, also said the number of country
houses and cars used by officials would be cut.
   _Passed a resolution condemning the 1939 Soviet-Nazi pact that
led to the parceling up of much of Eastern Europe, including the
Baltic states.
   Legislatures in the Baltic republics have already condemned the
pact.
</TEXT>

</DOC>