<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0114 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1448EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-StubbornDad     12-29 0317</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stubborn Dad,0326</SECOND>
<HEAD>Father's Refusal To Believe Son Died Accidentally Leads To Murder
Arrest</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN FERNANDO, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man who refused to believe his
son's death was an accident conducted an independent investigation
that has led to the arrest of a man for investigation of killing
the son.
   Richard Froio, 50, launched his own campaign to uncover the
truth about the death of his son, Rocco Froio, 32, an alcoholic who
lived on the streets.
   Rocco Froio's body was discovered Aug. 18 in Studio City. After
an autopsy revealed that he had died of a heroin overdose, Los
Angeles detectives ruled the death accidental and closed the case.
   But the elder Froio was suspicious because he knew his son had
not used drugs for seven years, said Detective Charles Barnes.
   Because of the father's diligence, police obtained information
needed to arrest John Bird, 37, a transient, authorities said.
   A preliminary hearing for Bird is scheduled for Tuesday on
charges he killed the younger Froio with an injection of heroin
while he was asleep or unconscious.
   The elder Froio posted a sign near where his son's body was
discovered, seeking information about the death.
   ``He was very dedicated and instrumental in the case,'' Deputy
District Attorney Guadalupe Y. Gonzalez said.
   ``The sign kept getting knocked down and he would pass by it and
put it up again,'' Ms. Gonzalez said. ``He wandered around and
talked to people, asking them if they knew his son. He was trying
to reconstruct his son's last moments.''
   The elder Froio received several calls from homeless people who
said Bird had injected his son with heroin while he was asleep or
passed out. He relayed the information to police, who arrested Bird
on Oct. 21.
   If convicted, Bird faces a maximum sentence of 30 years to life
in prison for murder and the sale and transportation of heroin,
authorities said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>