<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1234EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Reporter'sNotebook     12-25 0615</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Reporter's Notebook,630</SECOND>
<HEAD>Even In Little War, Truth Is An Early Casualty</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEVEN KOMAROW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIO HATO, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Back in Washington, the brass was saying
how the landing zone was clear _ not a ``hot L-Z'' at all, thanks
to the proficiency of new Stealth fighter planes. But the GIs on
the ground told a different story.
   Excited from their first taste of combat, the soldiers described
how one paratrooper was shot in the door of his C-130 aircraft as
he prepared to jump; his Ranger comrades had to pull him back to
save his life.
   A little incident among many, demonstrating anew the primary law
of conflict: Even in a little war, the truth is an early casualty.
   The Pentagon said that forces defending this Panamanian army
compound were quickly subdued because U.S. Stealth jets slipped
past radar and bombed a nearby field to provide a distraction. Yet
U.S. paratroopers who took this Panamanian army compound said they
landed amid an intense firefight which claimed several American
lives and more than a dozen U.S. wounded.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Near Panama City was the ``Witch House,'' a modest residence
where Manuel Noriega was said to have kept his four Brazilian
voodoo witches.
   Soldiers said they apparently just missed getting the witches
themselves when they crashed into the house during Wednesday's
attack. But the evidence of the strange rituals which took place
there remained: a bucket of blood, animal entrails, and a variety
of seemingly random religious artifacts carefully arranged on the
desk.
   Before reporters were allowed in, the military removed what
soldiers said were packets of cocaine wrapped in tropical leaves.
Soldiers who confiscated the stockpile described their haul as
about 50 pounds of cocaine.
   At headquarters and in Washington, the generals said it was 50
kilograms. At 2.2 pounds per kilo, that would better back up the
U.S. claim that Noriega was involved heavily in the drug trade.
   It was possible the generals were referring to cocaine also
recovered elsewhere, but reporters never were able to reconcile the
figures.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Perhaps the most difficult term to grasp in the war area was the
word ``secure,'' as in, ``the area has been secured.''
   Early Thursday, reporters were told the area around the Marriott
hotel on the east side of Panama City was secured. But within
hours, an attempt to land a helicopter containing a news group at
nearby Patilla airport was waved off because of a firefight.
   The Southern Command headquarters also was supposed to be secure
when, on Thursday afternoon, a new battle erupted there.
   The area that was one of the first attacked and secured
Wednesday was that of the Commandancia, Noriega's downtown
headquarters. But reporters visiting the area Friday were told of
new sniper fire from the charred and shattered high rises.
   Soldiers nervously patrolled the streets while local residents
brazenly looted what was left in the buildings.
   One GI showed reporters a motorized, two-person tricycle with a
machine-gun mount in back. It was operated by Noreiga defenders to
whiz through the streets and fire upon the attacking Americans _
until they came in the crosshairs a U.S. soldier's M-60 machine gun.
   The GI proudly showed the spot a few yards away where the
Panamanian gunner's brains had landed.
   On Avenue A nearby, a young Panamanian man waved at the U.S.
troops trying to get their attention. He failed until he came up
with a grabber: he walked out and placed a live rocket-propelled
grenade round in the middle of the street.
   It seemed there was little security in the term secure.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDS: Stephen Komarow was a member of the Pentagon news pool in</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Panama.
</TEXT>

</DOC>