<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0140 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 2101EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Bush 4thLd-Writethru   12-27 1222</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush, 4th Ld-Writethru,a0674,1,070</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS grafs 4-5: ``In Washington,'' with observation of a
senior official that Noriega solution not near</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER CONNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEEVILLE, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush said Wednesday he is
determined to bring to justice Manuel Antonio Noriega ``for
poisoning the children of the United States'' with drugs, but he
conceded that the Vatican's refusal to give up thedeposed
Panamanian dictator does ``complicate things.''
   In a speech before a crowd of more than 800 at a barbeque dinner
in Beeville, near one of his favorite South Texcas hunting haunts,
Bush drew loud applause both when he promised to press to bring
Noriega to trial and to avoid ``hellacious cuts'' in the defense
budget.
   ``I am determined to bring him to justice. We have to work with
our friends in the Vatican. We have to certainly work with respect
with the new Endara government in Panama,'' he said. ``But I want
to see this man who is under indictment brought to justice for
poisoning the children of the United States of America'' with drugs.
   A senior official who spoke on condition that he not be
identified said in Washington that officials believe the Vatican
has not yet defined its position, and thus a resolution is not
close.
   But this official said the administration expects a solution
sooner rather than later because it is in no one's interest _ not
that of the United States, Panama or the Vatican _ to allow the
current state of affairs to drag on.
   Earlier, at a news conference upon landing in Corpus Christi,
Bush said he was putting ``no time limit'' on the quest to bring
Noriega, now holed up in the Vatican's embassy in Panama City, to
trial in the United States. Noriega was indicted in Florida on
federal drug trafficking charges in 1988.
   In his dinner remarks, Bush called the U.S. military operation
in Panama ``a superb effort'' and said it makes him determined to
resist calls for deep cuts in defense spending.
   ``I believe we should keep a ready force that is able to defend
American interests and American lives around the world,'' he said
from a stage surrounded by bales of hay.
   A banner read: ``Bee County is Bush Quail Country.''
   ``We're still going down the road of trying to get him sent
here,'' said Bush, starting a five-day hunting and fishing trip in
his adopted homestate of Texas. ``We will continue to negotiate.''
   He refused to criticize the Holy See, telling reporters ``we're
not posturing ourselves as trying to be calling people to task''
and saying it was no time for ``name-calling.''
   Bush appeared to leave open the possibility that Noriega could
be tried in Panama. He said there was a threat of Noriega regaining
power if he remained there ``unless he were in total custody and
sentenced to the prison sentence he deserves.''
   Answering questions at Corpus Christi Naval Air Station, where
he took pilot training in 1943, Bush exclaimed: ``Noriega turning
himself in was about as good a Christmas present as our soldiers,
Marines, airmen and the American people could want.'' He pronounced
the U.S. military intervention ``an amazingly well-coordinated,
superbly executed operation.''
   The president said he wasn't worried about taking a vacation
while U.S. troops remained active in Panama. ``Why should I be? ''
he asked. ``It's winding down.''
   Bush commenced his vacation as a Vatican spokesman, Joaquin
Navarro, said there was no legal way its embassy in Panama City
could hand over Noriega. In Washington, the Justice Department made
good on its Tuesday threat to seek a freeze on European bank
accounts where Noriega is believed to have stashed millions of
dollars in illegal drug profits.
   The president maintained Wednesday he had no concerns about
Noriega revealing U.S.-Panamanian intelligence secrets at a trial.
   He was referring to things Noriega might reveal about his
previous close relations with the U.S. government, including the
period in the 1970s when Bush was CIA director and Noriega was an
intelligence source.
   ``I think that's history, and I think the main thing is he
should be tried and brought to justice,'' Bush said at a brief news
conference.
   A U.S. trial could result in ``some release of certain
confidential documents that he may try to blindside the whole
justice process.'' But, he added, ``The system works, so I wouldn't
worry about that.''
   Earlier, White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater told reporters
aboard Air Force One that Noriega ``can talk about the CIA and Bush
until he's blue in the face. It won't hurt anything.''
   Bush, asked whether the United States would let Panama try
Noriega, replied: ``That would require a lot of conversations
because we don't want to do anything that even implies undermining
the sovereign power of Panama or the fact the government is
operating with the trust of the people.''
   The president said he was personally involved in efforts to gain
custody of Noriega from the Vatican embassy in Panama, where
Noriega has been sheltered since Christmas Eve, but he had not
contacted either the papal nuncio in Panama City or Pope John Paul
II. Bush did say he planned to hold talks with Secretary of State
James A. Baker III, his longtime friend and hunting partner, while
in Texas.
   Asked about U.S. demands that the embassy directly turn over
Noriega to U.S. authorities, the Vatican City spokesman said there
was no legal way that could be done. He said the embassy is
empowered to deal only with the government of Panama and no other
foreign government.
   On a related matter, Bush said it will take ``a lot of
diplomatic effort and a lot of it on my part'' to repair relations
with Latin countries offended by the U.S. invasion of Panama. He
said he thinks that once they see the democratically elected
government in place, and they see that Noriega is ``out of the
picture _ none of them supported him at all; they found him
outrageous _ then I think you begin to see the problem that might
have been caused by a prolonged conflict down there.''
   Meanwhile, the Justice Department Wednesday asked authorities in
Switzerland, France, Luxembourg and Britain to halt transactions in
bank accounts believed to hold $10 million Noriega amassed through
drug dealing.
   France and Switzerland responded by freezing accounts in four
banks.
   In another development, Panama's new government sent a
high-level economic team to Washington for talks with officials
from the State and Treasury departments and other agencies about
reviving that country's economy, blasted by months of U.S.
sanctions against the Noriega regime.
   The assistant secretary for inter-American affairs, Bernard
Aronson, said a U.S. delegation will be sent to Panama soon to
continue the talks.
   Meanwhile, Bush had some success in his fishing and hunting
expedition Wednesday. The president, who was plagued by bad luck
fishing at his home in Kennebunkport, Maine, last summer, caught
three fish off San Jose Island and showed off a huge, 22-inch
redfish to reporters to prove his claim.
   ``I wanted you to know we weren't lying,'' Bush told reporters
in Beeville. His fishing companion, Baker, showed off part of his
catch, a large trout. Baker caught four or five fish to Bush's
three.
   White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said Bush and Baker also
bagged 10 quail between them in a morning shoot.
</TEXT>

</DOC>