<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0143 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1533EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-Civilians Bjt   12-22 0620</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Civilians, Bjt,0640</SECOND>
<HEAD>Civilians Face Mounting Hardships in Panama</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALINA GUERRERO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of refugees on Friday
jammed soccer stadiums, churches and schools to seek shelter from
the fighting that has left the capital with a mounting shortage of
food and medicines.
   Reporters estimated around 3,000 refugees at a high school
soccer stadium in the neighboring city of Balboa, on the Pacific
entrance of the Panama Canal.
   ``They had water but we're very short of food,'' said a Red
Cross worker who like others refused to give his name for fear of
reprisals. He said U.S. Army units were providing some rations, but
it was not enough.
   Another 500 were at the Revolution Soccer Stadium in Panama
City, 200 at the capital's Venezuela high school, 100 at another
school and 100 more at the Santa Ana Roman Catholic Church.
   Untold thousands more roamed the streets, slept in public parks
or were taken in by relatives and friends. Many just knocked on
doors of strangers who took them in.
   Three families were living in a one family home in the Chorillo
neighborhood _ none had known each other before.
   ``I'm still very scared,'' said one man in a telephone interview
from his invalid mother's two-room apartment, where a total of 15
people were herded.
   ``First I fled to a stranger's home. But then I had to leave,
and I made my way through the fighting until I was able to reach my
mother's house.''
   A Red Cross spokesman said many people were donating food to the
refugees _ ``as much as they can spare.'' He said the organization
has been appealing for help.
   Looting remained rampant for the third consecutive day; there
were no policemen, not even to direct traffic.
   The police were part of fugitive strongman Manuel Antonio
Noriega's Defense Forces and the organization collapsed with the
U.S. military invasion Wednesday.
   Most stores remained closed. About 300 people lined up outside
supermarkets that opened their doors, and many complained there was
little left to buy.
   Even some gas stations that didn't open for business were looted
by motorists short of gasoline.
   First Vice President Ricardo Arias Calderon, who is also
temporarily the interior minister, on Friday named anti-Noriega
Majs. Ricardo Reyes Dutary and Juan Antonio Guisado to organize a
traffic and police force.
   Santo Tomas Hospital, one of the capital's biggest, on Balboa
Avenue overlooking Panama Bay, was crowded with dead and wounded
and running short of almost everything, from alcohol to analgesics
and surgical gauze.
   Dr. Elmer Miranda, the deputy director, said there were about
200 dead bodies in the basement and he heard from a colleague of
about 60 more in Gorgas Hospital, run by the U.S. Southern Command.
   Among the bodies was that of Spanish photographer Juan
Rodriguez, who was killed by U.S. troops near the Marriott Hotel,
and a Peruvian military attache, officials said.
   Miranda said the hospital's 21 wards were so full that some of
the less-seriously wounded were sleeping on the floors.
   All 21 wards of the hospital were full, and one official
estimated there were 1,000 wounded in the hospital. They said that
while many of Noriega's troops wear civilian clothes, they believed
most of the victims they had seen were civilians.
   They said most of the injuries were caused by flying glass and
bullets.
   U.S. troops visited the hospital during the morning, saying they
were ``just checking,'' according to two nurses.
   Doctors and nurses were working on 16 and even 24-hour shifts,
and the hospital was very short of food. ``They are all very tense.
Besides everything, not only is there no transportation but the
staff is scared to go outside,'' he added.
</TEXT>

</DOC>