<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0141 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0746EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv03   12-26 0459</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv03,0478</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv03</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Wednesday, Jan. 3</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is Wednesday, Jan. 3, the third day of 1990. There are 362
days left in the year.
   Today's highlight in history:
   On Jan. 3, 1959, President Eisenhower signed a proclamation
admitting Alaska to the Union as the 49th state.
   On this date:
   In 1521, Martin Luther was excommunicated from the Roman
Catholic Church.
   In 1777, General George Washington's army routed the British in
the Battle of Princeton, N.J.
   In 1833, Britain seized control of the Falkland Islands in the
South Atlantic. (Almost 150 years later, Argentina seized the
islands from the British, but Britain took them back after a 74-day
war.)
   In 1871, Henry W. Bradley of Binghamton, N.Y., received a patent
for oleomargarine.
   In 1938, the ``March of Dimes'' campaign to fight polio was
organized.
   In 1946, William Joyce, known as ``Lord Haw Haw'' for his
pro-Nazi radio broadcasts from Germany, was hanged in London.
(Although American-born, Joyce held a British passport.)
   In 1961, the United States severed diplomatic relations with
Cuba.
   In 1967, Jack Ruby, the man who shot presidential assassin Lee
Harvey Oswald on live television, died in a Dallas hospital.
   In 1983, Republican George Deukmejian was sworn in as
California's 35th governor, after eight years of the administration
of Democrat Edmund G. ``Jerry'' Brown Jr.
   In 1984, Navy Lieutenant Robert O. Goodman Jr., shot down during
a United States raid against Syrian anti-aircraft positions in
Lebanon, was freed by Syria after an appeal by the Reverend Jesse
Jackson.
   Ten years ago: Conservationist Joy Adamson, author of the
best-selling book ``Born Free,'' was killed in northern Kenya by a
servant in a wage dispute.
   Five years ago: President Reagan announced that his deputy chief
of staff, Michael K. Deaver, would be leaving the White House in
the spring to return to private life.
   One year ago: The 101st Congress held its opening ceremonies as
Democrats pledged cooperation with the incoming Bush administration.
   Today's birthdays: Comedian Victor Borge is 81. Consumer
reporter Betty Furness is 74. United States Ambassador Vernon
Walters is 73. Singer Maxene Andrews is 72. Actor Jesse White is
71. Sportscaster Hank Stram is 67. Record producer George Martin is
64. Actor Robert Loggia is 60. Actor Eddie Egan is 60. Actor Dabney
Coleman is 58. Journalist-author Betty Rollin is 54. Hockey player
Bobby Hull is 51. Singer Stephen Stills is 45. Actress Victoria
Principal is 40. Actor Mel Gibson is 34.
   Thought for today: ``To have reason to get up in the morning, it
is necessary to possess a guiding principle. A belief of some kind.
A bumper sticker, if you will.'' _ Judith Guest, American author
(1936- ).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Wed Jan 3</NOTE>

</DOC>