<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0431EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-RoseParade Bjt   12-26 0652</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Rose Parade, Bjt,0681</SECOND>
<HEAD>Indonesia's New Marching Band Ready for the World's Premiere Parade</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Thom cq.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN ROGERS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The century-old Tournament of Roses
Parade takes to the streets New Year's Day with millions of
flowers, amazing floats and some of the world's most distinguished
marching bands.
   Then there's a group of Indonesian musicians who just months ago
couldn't play trumpets and trombones.
   The 140-member Sampoerna Band Indonesia will be its country's
first representatives in Monday's parade, tournament officials said.
   The band has been practicing furiously.
   Even their director, Thom Jenkins, didn't know at first if
they'd be ready. Now, he said, they are.
   ``They really have worked extremely hard,'' Jenkins said during
a recent telephone interview from Surabaya, the Indonesian city of
4 million people in East Java where the band is based.
   ``Marching band instruments are not their native instruments, so
when we started they didn't even know what a trumpet was supposed
to sound like,'' he said.
   He has drilled the musicians, two-thirds of whom are women, for
40 hours a week for 11 months. The band also has marched and
marched and marched, three to four miles a day in the Indonesian
heat.
   Jenkins, who moved from Atlanta to Indonesia early this year to
work with the band, said the ensemble submitted an audition tape to
tournament officials because ``we wanted to shoot for the top.''
   ``Even over here the Rose Parade is known as the world's
premiere parade.''
   When they learned of their acceptance, Jenkins said they were
thrilled. ``I wish you could have seen their faces,'' he said.
   The Indonesians, who range from age 16 to 42, will join elite
company.
   They will be among the 22 bands, 60 floats and 29 equestrian
units that an estimated 1 million people are expected to turn out
to see. Millions more will watch on television.
   The band will march amid such high-technology floats as the
General Motors-United Auto Workers entry, which is a 33-foot-long
land vehicle of the future that converts into a 60-foot-tall robot
in seconds, and the city of Burbank's entry _ a 55-foot-long
``Be-Bop Malt Shop'' that pays tribute to '50s rock music and
nostalgia with a giant juke box and roller-skating waitresses.
   Other parade veterans are the Marine Corps and Salvation Army
units, as well as aggregations from Japan and Switzerland. The
University of Southern California and Michigan bands will be
high-stepping in the parade hours before the two schools' football
teams play in the annual Rose Bowl game.
   If they hadn't passed the audition, they would have tried again
next year, Jenkins said.
   But the group was ready, said Mike Riffey, chairman of the
Tournament of Roses music committee.
   ``They looked very good,'' he said. ``They're a very good band.''
   For the band members, the parade promises to be only one
highlight of the trip.
   Most get around Surabaya by bicycle or scooter and live very
modestly, Jenkins said. Only one band member has been outside the
country before, and Riffey said one person expressed concern about
where band members would bathe in an area with so few rivers as
Southern California.
   She was told about indoor showers, he said.
   The group's members are looking forward to sampling their first
American hamburgers, visiting Disneyland and Hollywood and going
skiing, Jenkins said.
   That latter experience might provide the greatest culture shock
of all, he said.
   ``These guys put on coats when the temperature falls to 80,'' he
said. ``Indonesia is on the equator and the temperature is usually
90 to 100.''
   But whatever the weather, the band is ready to play its
repertoire of Indonesian marching tuns and folk, pop and patriotic
songs, all of which work surprisingly well as marching music,
Jenkins said.
   ``They're very proud to be representing their country,'' Jenkins
said. ``Indonesia is a young country and patriotism is not
considered corny.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>