<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0096 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1831EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ChristmasRdp-US 1stLd-Writethru a0586 12-25 0765</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Christmas Rdp-US, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0586,0779</SECOND>
<HEAD>Christmas '89: GIs in Panama, Donors Replace Stolen Food for the
Needy</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Adds 3 grafs to update with Calif. heat, beach scene on Christmas.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-World Christmas, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By THEASA TUOHY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Volunteers in two cities hustled on Christmas day to cook up and
serve replacement donations after thieves stole thousands of
dollars worth of food for the needy, and it was the 50th Christmas
for Rudolph the Red-Nosed Reindeer.
   ``As far as Christmas goes, this is it, folks,'' Col. John
Richardson told The Charlotte Observer on Sunday from Panama, where
he was leading a task force of troops from Camp Lejeune near
Jacksonville, N.C. ``No sign of Bob Hope.''
   Several dozen pro-choice and AIDS activists demonstrated outside
St. Vibiana's Cathedral in downtown Los Angeles to protest the
Roman Catholic Church's stance against abortion and the use of
condoms. As Archbishop Roger Mahony said a Christmas mass Monday
morning, demonstrators carried signs that said ``Jesus Saves Souls.
Condoms Save Lives.''
   A Chicago center was back in business handing out food Christmas
Day after thieves stole thousands of dollars worth of turkeys,
hams, toys and clothing collected for a traditional Christmas Eve
giveaway to 1,500 needy people.
   ``We've had calls and people coming in from all over the city,''
Frank Campbell, spokesman for the Paul Hall Community Services
Center, said Monday. ``It's really been something to see. ... We'll
be here giving out food until everything runs out.''
   The hungry and homeless sat down at Atlanta's annual Christmas
feast and were served pizza _ because turkeys and a lot of
trimmings were stolen shortly before the meal was to begin.
   ``Luckily, people have answered our radio plea and are bringing
food to us,'' said Elizabeth Williams-Omilami, daughter of the
event's organizer, civil rights leader Hosea Williams. They had
estimated earlier that they could feed up to 40,000 and still
insisted they could feed everyone who showed up.
   U.S. soldiers injured in Panama and recovering at Wilford Hall
Medical Center in San Antonio exchanged presents with relatives in
specially set up rooms, said Staff Sgt. Rey Adame, a hospital
spokesman.
   Area residents volunteered to help sort gifts, cards and letters
sent to the GIs injured in Panama.
   ``You look around, you'll see the Yuletide season all over the
place here,'' Adame said.
   The children of the advertising copywriter who created Rudolph
50 years ago for a Montgomery Ward's promotion booklet said they
are grateful year-round for the residual payments they still get
from the storybook reindeer who guided Santa's sleigh with his
shiny nose.
   The writer's daughter, Elizabeth Decker of Lake Bluff, Ill.,
says that every Christmas season her father, Robert May, used to
look out the window at a statue of the reindeer and say ``Thank
you, Rudolph.''
   In Watsonville, Calif., 1,400 families stood in a line around
the block Christmas Eve waiting for the city's annual toy giveaway.
It took on new meaning this year after an estimated 1,200 homes and
businesses were destroyed in the agricultural town near the
epicenter of the Oct. 17 earthquake.
   George Romano, who has been collecting for victims since shortly
after the quake, delivered 5,000 toys to children living in a
makeshift trailer park.
   In the Los Angeles suburb of Monrovia, police Officer Ruben
Gonzalez said he was touched by the sight of a little girl crying
when her home went up in flames Saturday night.
   Fellow officers came up with $500, an amount matched by the
Monrovia Police Association. The six children of two families that
were ousted by the fire were given gifts to unwrap Christmas
morning in their Red Cross-provided hotel.
   Donations also came from a bike shop, a grocery store, and a
coffee shop Gonzalez stopped at during a break on his graveyard
shift. A tree lot donated a tree that was decorated with ornaments
taken from the police station tree.
   ``I didn't realize people would be so giving,'' Gonzalez said
Christmas Eve.
   Elsewhere in southern California, Christmas was a day for
bare-chested natives to smear on tanning oil and soak up some rays,
or try out Christmas gift surfboards and wetsuits.
   On the same day Miami had a record low of 30, the noon
temperature was 81 degrees in Oxnard, 78 in downtown Los Angeles
and 77 in Santa Barbara, Santa Monica, Oceanside, San Diego and
Palm Springs.
   ``I am really happy to be in L.A. We don't have a lot of
palms,'' said Christina Giourdas, a Lufthansa flight attendant from
West Berlin who visited a Venice beach cafe on Christmas Eve.
</TEXT>

</DOC>