<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0233EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-CatastrophicInsurance     12-22 0421</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Catastrophic Insurance,420</SECOND>
<HEAD>Refunds Checks Going to 27 Million Medicare Recipients</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN CRUTSINGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Economics Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nearly 27 million elderly people will get
refund checks in February and April to offset overcharges early
next year in their Medicare health premiums.
   The Treasury Department on Thursday announced an unusual
two-step process in which the government will overcharge the
elderly on their Medicare premiums and then turn around and mail
out refund checks.
   Bush administration officials said the process was necessary
because Congress repealed the controversial law providing Medicare
catastrophic health benefits after computers were set up to make
the deductions.
   The Treasury plans to issue a refund of $10.60 in February to
cover deductions of $5.30 in January and February. Another $10.60
refund will be issued in April to cover March and April deductions.
   Nearly 27 million Social Security beneficiaries who have
Medicare premiums deducted directly from their benefit checks will
be forced to pay an overcharge of $5.30 a month from January
through May. Officials said there was no way to adjust government
computers quickly enough to halt the withholding of the extra
premium for catastrophic coverage.
   The law providing catastrophic health coverage was intended to
prevent a serious illness from wiping out the finances of a
retiree. But it sparked a revolt among senior citizens who
complained that they already had sufficient coverage and did not
want to pay the higher costs of the new program.
   After President Bush signed the law repealing catastrophic
coverage on Dec. 13, members of Congress urged the administration
to come up with a plan to expedite refunds to retirees, arguing
that a Treasury-favored proposal to make only one lump-sum refund
late in the spring would penalize retirees on fixed incomes.
   ``I am pleased that millions of Medicare beneficiaries will not
be deprived of money they may urgently need,'' said Sen. David
Pryor, D-Ark. and chairman of the Senate Aging Committee. ``Five
dollars and 30 cents can be a lot of money to someone on a fixed
income.''
   The Financial Management Service, which issues the government's
checks, said it expects to complete the computer reprogramming in
time for the May Social Security checks to reflect the correct
Medicare premium.
   ``This two-phase plan will provide the most timely service to
recipients without jeopardizing over a quarter-billion other
payments, including regular Social Security benefits and tax
refunds, which we make at this peak time of the year,'''
Commissioner W.C. Douglas of the Treasury's Financial Management
Service said in announcing the decision Thursday.
</TEXT>

</DOC>