<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0444EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-YMCA-SovietUnion     12-27 0446</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-YMCA-Soviet Union,0462</SECOND>
<HEAD>International Youth Organization May Reopen in Soviet Union</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto CX1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CLIFF EDWARDS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The YMCA is gearing up for a return to the Soviet
Union after more than 70 years of exile.
   The Young Men's Christian Association has been working with
private groups in the Soviet Union since May to establish branches
in at least four cities, said Celeste Wroblewski, spokeswoman for
the U.S. YMCA.
   Robert Masuda, director of the international division, will
travel there this spring to speak with charitable organizations and
citizen groups about opening center in Leningrad, Tbilisi in Soviet
Georgia, and Novosibirsk and Omsk in Siberia, Ms. Wroblewski said.
   ``We will see YMCA programs aimed at developing Soviet citizens'
minds, spirits and bodies,'' said Nicholas Goncharoff, director of
the American YMCA's statesmanship programs, who first contacted
Soviet organizations.
   In addition to the four cities targeted, the organization also
might open a branch in Kiev, he said.
   ``The difference, however, is that they will be called the YFCA,
for Youth Families Christian Association,'' said Goncharoff, a
Soviet emigre who stayed at a New York YMCA during his first five
months in the United States in 1952. A spokesman for the Soviet
Embassy in Washington, D.C., said he hadn't heard about the YMCA
reopening in his country.
   ``Nowadays, there are so many organizations and we can't know
every one of them,'' said Andrei Parastayev, the embassy's first
secretary. ``There is a rise in political activities of the young
people, and of course they want to express themselves.''
   Goncharoff said the reforms of Soviet President Mikhail S.
Gorbachev have made it possible for the YMCA to attempt a return.
   ``Only since Gorbachev could such a historic event be
possible,'' he said in a recent interview. ``The last five years,
we began to explore actively the idea of YMCA in Russia.''
   The YMCA had firm roots in Czarist Russia, with branches mainly
devoted to physical activities for young men. But after the 1917
Bolshevik revolution, its doors in Petrograd _ now Leningrad _ and
many other cities were shut, Goncharoff said.
   Today, the organization intends to give Soviet youths training
in Western management styles and let them participate in exchanges
with American and Canadian youths, he said.
   ``There is a great excitement for solving community problems in
the Soviet Union, and that's what the YMCA is all about here,'' Ms.
Wroblewski said.
   The organization also plans to offer activities involving music,
theater and other arts, Goncharoff said.
   The YMCA was founded in London in 1844 as a conduit for
religious study. It has spread to 97 countries and serves about 30
million people, Ms. Wroblewski said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>