<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0303EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Poindexter     12-20 0612</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Poindexter,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>North's Testimony in Poindexter Trial to be Limited</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETE YOST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Restrictions on Oliver L. North's testimony
will make it more difficult to prosecute John Poindexter, says a
former chief counsel to the congressional Iran-Contra committees.
   U.S. District Court Judge Harold Greene ruled Tuesday that
North's statements at his own trial are off-limits for use in the
Poindexter case.
   North testified in April that he saw the former national
security adviser tear up a presidential finding retroactively
legalizing CIA assistance for a November 1985 shipment of Hawk
missiles to Iran.
   But North testified last week that his recollection on that and
other matters was influenced by Poindexter's immunized appearance
on Capitol Hill in 1987. Therefore, said Greene, North's trial
testimony as it relates to Poindexter may not be used, unless it
was a subject which Poindexter didn't address in his immunized
testimony.
   The court's obligations require it to ``err on the side of
protecting Poindexter's constitutional right not to be convicted
with the use of his own testimony,'' said the judge.
   Prosecutors ``may only elicit evidence'' from North based on his
statements prior to July 15, 1987, the day Poindexter began
testifying on Capitol Hill, said the judge.
   By saying he was tainted, North ``has snaked his way around''
the issue of having to testify about the finding being torn up,
said John Nields, former chief counsel to the House majority staff
in the congressional Iran-Contra hearings.
   Since North did not tell the congressional committees in 1987
that he saw Poindexter destroy the finding, he ``won't be able to
testify to it at the (Poindexter) trial'' and ``I don't think the
government has any other proof of it,'' said Nields.
   The government still could elicit information about the
finding's being torn up if Poindexter decides to testify in his own
behalf at his trial, which is scheduled to begin Jan. 22.
   The destruction of the finding relates to four of the criminal
charges against the former national security adviser. He is accused
of conspiracy, two counts of obstructing Congress and two counts of
making false statements.
   Poindexter destroyed the December 1985 finding on Nov. 21, 1986,
the same day he allegedly told Congress that no one in the U.S.
government knew until early 1986 that the shipment had carried Hawk
missiles.
   The prosecution says the finding which Poindexter destroyed is
``the most critical document in proving the falsity'' of another
document, a chronology which is an essential part of the
government's case against Poindexter. The chronology contains the
same false information which Poindexter allegedly gave to Congress
_ that no one in the government knew about the Hawk shipment until
1986.
   Paul Thompson, the National Security Council's legal counsel,
was present when Poindexter tore up the finding.
   But Thompson said in a deposition to Congress in August 1987
that he didn't realize at the time it was the finding that
Poindexter was destroying.
   ``One document we came to he ripped up ... saying `This is no
longer necessary' or `this has no future,''' Thompson recalled in
his deposition to Congress. ``That document turns out to have been
the finding.'' Thompson said he learned it was the finding when he
saw Poindexter admit it on television in his immunized testimony.
   North was convicted in May of three felonies in the Iran-Contra
affair. He is appealing the convictions on charges of altering and
destroying documents, accepting an illegal gratuity and aiding and
abetting an obstruction of Congress.
   The obstruction charge was related to a November 1985 shipment
of Hawks to Iran, which also forms the basis of some of the charges
in the Poindexter case.
</TEXT>

</DOC>