<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0631EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Panama-SecretPact     12-27 0315</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Secret Pact,0327</SECOND>
<HEAD>Newspaper: New Panamanian President Sworn In at U.S. Base</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Panama's new president and two vice presidents made
a secret pact to say they were sworn in on Panamanian territory,
although the ceremony actually took place on a U.S. military base,
it was reported today.
   Anticipating questions about the legitimacy of their government,
President Guillermo Endara and his vice presidents swore themselves
to secrecy about the ceremony at Fort Clayton, outside Panama City,
The Miami Herald reported, citing sources who demanded anonymity.
   Responding to previous reports he was sworn in at a U.S. base
during the U.S. invasion that ousted Panamanian ruler Gen. Manuel
Noriega, Endara told The Associated Press Saturday:
   ``I was sworn in on Panamanian territory, in a Panamanian home
after 1 a.m. (Wednesday). Then in the morning we went to Fort
Clayton.''
   He didn't identify the home's owners.
   Among those who signed the swearing-in document were Endara,
First Vice President Ricardo Arias Calderon and Second Vice
President Guillermo Ford. Also present were the vice presidents'
wives and several U.S. and Panamanian officials, the paper said.
   ``We were taken to Fort Clayton at about midnight, and told we
couldn't make outside phone calls or leave the room,'' one
participant told the Herald. ``The ceremony took place at about 2
a.m. (Wednesday), and we agreed to say it had taken place in
Panamanian territory.''
   The group stayed in a building at Fort Clayton until Wednesday
afternoon, when two mortar shots fired by Noriega forces hit the
ground nearby.
   Then they were shuttled to another building at the base, where
they remained until Thursday morning, about 30 hours after the
invasion started, the Herald reported.
   Then they went to Panama's Legislative Assembly building, where
U.S. forces established Endara's first provisional headquarters,
the paper said.
   Endara's government was elected May 7, but Noriega never let the
new leaders take power.
</TEXT>

</DOC>