<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0198 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0740EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-HolidayTravel     12-19 0591</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Holiday Travel,0616</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cold Weather Boosts Holiday Travel</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AMR-TWA Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES WEBB</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Residents of the nation's midsection may be
cursing the frigid weather, but some travel agents are praying for
more to boost business during the peak Christmas and New Year's
season.
   ``Snow and cold is a godsend to travel agents,'' said Cliff
Stern, president of Windy City Travel Inc. in Chicago. ``The phones
ring off the hook.''
   Airlines are helping the spur-of-the-moment travelers by lifting
advance-purchase requirements on discount tickets.
   But some industry observers said Monday the breaks from airlines
are a sign of a weak holiday travel season.
   ``Anytime you get a real sharp cold snap it often triggers
vacation destination ticket sales,'' said Stephen Dexter, an
airline industry analyst with Kemper Financial Services Inc. in
Chicago.
   ``What makes it abnormal this time around is the cold snap is
happening during a holiday season and the tickets are still
available. That should not happen,'' Dexter said.
   ``Typically people who decide suddenly that they are going to
escape the cold have to pay a pretty steep price. There are still
bargains out there for the last-minute guy.''
   Strong bookings for January through March indicate people are
postponing discretionary travel, said Susan Storb, general manager
of the vacation division for Rosenbluth Travel Agency Inc., in
Philadelphia.
   ``I just think it's just not as strong as it's been over the
past few years,'' she said of the holiday season.
   A number of airlines, under pressure to increase fares because
of recent cost increases, said earlier this month that they were
raising the prices on their popular deeply discounted fares,
commonly known as MaxSavers.
   But many airlines also announced they would waive the 14-day
advance-purchase requirement between Dec. 20 and Jan. 5, subject to
seat availability.
   There are restrictions: no refunds are allowed, and passengers
must buy tickets within 24 hours of making a reservation and must
stay over a Saturday night.
   But Stern and Dexter said airlines are adding discounted seats
that can be purchased on short notice and are close to the cost of
the MaxSavers.
   The record low temperatures are encouraging a trend toward
shorter, less planned vacations, said Greg DeClemente, vice
president for leisure travel at Thomas Cook Travel in New York.
   ``People are saying, `Hey, it's 7 degrees in Chicago, let's get
out of here for a few days,'' DeClemente said.
   Temperatures Monday morning were below zero in the Upper Plains,
in the teens in the Rockies and in the 20s along the Texas
Panhandle.
   Record low temperatures, ranging from minus 3 degrees to minus
10 degrees, were recorded over the weekend in Cleveland, Columbus,
Ohio, Elkins, W.Va., Paducah, Ky., and Indianapolis, Ind.
   Last-minute customers want to go ``anywhere that's warm and they
don't seem to care where,'' Stern said.
   ``They'll even settle for the sixties in Florida as opposed to
zero here.''
   In Los Angeles, where people don't have to flee the balmy
weather, the travel business is holding its own for the holiday
period, said Susan Kaplan, president of the Southern California
chapter of the American Society of Travel Agents.
   A general feeling that the economy is on a ``normal'' course may
be contributing to a slight increase in travel bookings, Ms. Kaplan
said.
   Things are not as rosy for some hotels in California.
   Fred Gholi, manager of the Sunset Plaza Hotel in Los Angeles,
said he doesn't expect to be more than 70 percent full during the
holidays.
   ``Compared with last year, it's terrible,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>