<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0634EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-HospitalDeaths     12-21 0632</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hospital Deaths,0649</SECOND>
<HEAD>Osteopathic, Public and Profit-Making Hospitals Have Highest Death
Rates</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DANIEL Q. HANEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation's most sophisticated hospitals, which
invest in the latest high-tech equipment and the best-trained
doctors and nurses, do the best job of saving sick people's lives,
a study today concludes.
   ``Our findings suggest that the resources utilized in hospitals
may have an impact on mortality,'' said Dr. Arthur J. Hartz, who
directed the study.
   He said the results may surprise many doctors, who often feel
that differences between hospitals are relatively unimportant in
patients' survival.
   The research found that hospitals are mostly likely to save
lives when a large proportion of their doctors are certified by
specialty boards and their nurses have RN degrees. The most
successful hospitals also tend to have large payrolls, high
occupancy rates and the most technologically advanced equipment.
   The study found that the lowest death rates are in private
teaching hospitals, the medical centers that train young doctors.
The highest rates were in osteopathic, public or profit-making
hospitals.
   ``All of our findings have the same possible explanation: They
reflect differences in quality,'' said Hartz, a physician at the
Medical College of Wisconsin.
   The study, based on federal statistics, is the largest to
attempt to settle a long-running debate over whether for-profit
hospitals are as good as their non-profit counterparts. While at
least two smaller studies have found no difference, the latest one
suggests that non-profit hospitals have an advantage.
   Private, non-profit hospitals had 114 deaths for every 1,000
patients. By contrast, the for-profit hospitals had 121 deaths.
   ``It could be that the physicians and nurses in the for-profit
hospitals, because of administrative pressures, deal with patients
in such a way that is detrimental to their health,'' said Dr.
Alfred A. Rimm, a co-author of the study.
   The study found that public hospitals, such as city and county
hospitals, averaged 120 deaths per 1,000 patients. The highest
death rate in all the categories studied was osteopathic hospitals,
which had 129 deaths.
   The best record was for private, non-osteopathic teaching
hospitals, which train interns and residents after medical school.
They had 108 deaths per 1,000 patients.
   ``I wouldn't go to anything but a high-tech university
hospital,'' commented Rimm.
   The study was based on 1986 data gathered on 3,100 of the
nation's nearly 6,000 hospitals by the Health Care Financing
Adminstration. The agency's latest figures, released Wednesday,
showed that 3.4 percent of all hospitals had higher-than-expected
death rates in 1988.
   The Wisconsin researchers and co-authors from the health care
administration used the figures to see how mortality rates differed
between various categories of hospitals. They adjusted the numbers
to reflect differences in the severity of illness of patients
admitted to the hospitals. The results were published in today's
issue of New England Journal of medicine.
   Michael Bromberg, head of the Federation of American Health
Systems, which represents for-profit hospitals, said the research
was flawed.
   ``This study represents an unfair comparison of hospitals that
are not alike,'' he said. ``A small rural hospital that is
for-profit is treated the same way as a big not-for-profit teaching
hospital with lots of doctors and lots of equipment for the purpose
of determining mortality. There is no way you can make such a
comparison and have it mean anything.''
   Martin Wall, senior vice president of the American Osteopathic
Hospital Association, noted that the nation's 160 osteophatic
hospitals fit into several of the other categories studied,
including for-profit and non-profit, teaching and non-teaching.
   ``Making our hospitals a separate category is inappropriate,''
he said.
   Doctors of osteopathy prescribe drugs, perform surgery and
receive the same training as medical doctors. They also believe
that disturbances of muscles and bones can underly disease, and
perform massage and other manipulation as part of their treatment.
</TEXT>

</DOC>