<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0163 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1902EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Panama-USSoldiers     12-22 0348</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-US Soldiers,0357</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S Soldiers Say Panamanians Fought Well</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The ``Cholos'' infantry company of
the Panamanian Defense Forces earned the respect of U.S. troops who
fought them.
   ``It took us a day and half. They stood and fought,'' said a
U.S. officer Friday. ``Roger that, sir'' one of his men added.
   The Cholos held stubbornly to their positions at Fort Amador, an
installation at the southern entrance of the Panama Canal that was
shared by U.S. and Panamanian forces.
   Some U.S. forces had been moved secretly into the residential
areas on the U.S side of the base. They moved out at 12:45 a.m.
Wednesday as the assault on Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega's
government began.
   U.S. forces were received with some enthusiasm by the general
public, although many residents of this city, wracked by savage
looting and littered with debris, were too frightened to go out on
the streets.
   Marine Lance Cpl. Tracy Scott Jones of Dallas said that after
the shock of the first day's battle, ``People were cheering us on.
They are on our side. They clapped as we rolled through the
streets. There was no hostility.''
   Lance Cpl. William Young of Seattle said civilians were
``friendly. They give us the thumbs up sign.''
   ``When you go out on a mission at night the situation is pretty
tense. You just look at the darkness and all you can see are the
shapes of people,'' said Young. ``But, then when you go out in the
day, people are pretty friendly.''
   A busload of civilians passing by the Nicaraguan Embassy on
Friday morning waved white hankerchiefs and cheered the U.S.
soldiers standing by their armored cars.
   The Americans, who cordoned off the embassy following rumors
that Noriega was there, smiled and waved back.
   Language was a problem. A young driver who wanted some
Panamanians to clear a roadway kept yelling at a Panamanian about a
``vehicle'' as the Panamanians looked puzzled.
   ``Say `car' instead of vehicle,'' another soldier said. ``It's
easier to understand.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>