<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0105 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 2159EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama 2ndLd-Writethru   12-25 0814</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama, 2nd Ld-Writethru,a0626, 2 Takes,0836</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Troops Surround Vatican Embassy, Where Noriega Sought Asylum</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with new fighting, Cheney quotes, other
details. No pickup.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PAN5</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOSEPH B. FRAZIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. troops kept a vigil Monday on
the Vatican mission where Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega sought asylum
as U.S. officials demanded the former strongman be turned over for
trial in the United States.
   Fighting was reported Monday night in downtown Panama City, and
diplomats reached at the Spanish Embassy said the nearby Chamber of
Commerce was on fire. U.S. troops in the area said they were taking
sniper fire about two hours after a 6 p.m. curfew.
   Dozens of U.S. soldiers, armored vehicles and helicopters ringed
the Vatican mission, where Noriega turned himself in Sunday five
days after the U.S. invasion overthrew his government, blasted his
headquarters and drove him into hiding.
   In Washington, the administration demanded ``in extraordinarily
tough terms'' that Vatican authorities turn Noriega over, a State
Department source said.
   Negotiations have brought ``a Mexican standoff,'' the official
said, with church authorities rebuffing the request and trying _
unsuccessfuly so far _ to find a country to take Noriega.
   Defense Secretary Dick Cheney, who arrived in Panama City to be
with U.S. troops Christmas Eve, said at a news briefing Monday that
Noriega had been ``very skillful'' in eluding capture and moving
every night.
   Cheney called the U.S. invasion ``the most surgical operation of
its size ever carried out, not only by our forces but by anybody
else's forces.''
   After congratulating U.S. soldiers on their mission and touring
Noriega's battered headquarters, Cheney met with leaders of the new
U.S.-backed government. He reiterated Washington's desire to have
Noriega brought for trial in the United States.
   The area of Monday night's fighting includes the Cuban Embassy,
which is surrounded by U.S. troops, as well as the Foreign
Ministry, where the government of new President Guillermo Endara
has set up shop.
   The secretary of the Spanish Embassy, Javier Herrera, said his
embassy's personnel lay on the floor during the firing, which
slackened after 45 minutes. He said Spanish Ambassador Tomas Lozano
called a U.S. colonel in charge of operations in the area and the
colonel said, ``I'm on the ground, too.''
   With the manhunt for Noriega over, Panamanians living in refugee
camps and Americans on patrol found something to celebrate. Near
Santo Tomas Hospital, infantrymen put up a tiny Christmas tree at
their post and a sign saying ``Feliz Navidad.'' They shared their
food with people from the neighborhood.
   ``Last night, people came over and wished us a Merry Christmas.
It's been a real nice Christmas,'' said Sgt. Clay Carnahan of
Lubbock, Texas. ``It makes you feel real good.''
   Garbage trucks moved through downtown. Workers shoveled
mountains of trash, the debris of frenzied looting, into the
vehicles as U.S. military police patrolled the streets and armored
vehicles stood guard.
   Endara, the U.S.-backed leader who took power minutes after the
U.S. invasion, visited refugees during a Christmas Mass at a camp
in a soccer stadium. He refused to comment on Noriega's status,
saying, ``It is a very delicate diplomatic matter with the papal
state.''
   The Vatican said Noriega took refuge in the embassy Sunday after
``expressing the will to end the conflict'' between U.S. soldiers
and his supporters.
   Vatican, Panamanian and U.S. officials could not say if Noriega
would be handed over to the United States, where he faces drug
charges, or be given asylum in another country. The Vatican has no
extradition treaty with the United States.
   Sources in Panama familiar with the situation told The
Associated Press the papal nuncio mentioned the possibility of
Noriega going to Spain or Cuba.
   Gen. Maxwell Thurman, chief of the U.S. Southern Command, said
he ordered the embassy surrounded to prevent supporters from
``blowing into the place.''
   U.S. soldiers had surrounded the Cuban, Libyan and Nicaraguan
embassies to prevent Noriega from seeking refuge there, but no U.S.
troops were around the Vatican building when Noriega drove in
Sunday afternoon.
   Asked why, Cheney said at the briefing: ``We had our hands full
carrying out our basic mission. ... We could not come in and
surround literally every embassy in Panama in the hopes that you
could head off Mr. Noriega.''
   Vatican spokesman Joaquin Navarro said Monday the ``concerned
parties'' would examine Noriega's case. Asked if a ``simple''
turnover of Noriega to the United States was foreseeable, Navarro
replied, ``Well, I don't think so. There isn't an extradition
treaty or anything.''
   The Vatican depicted the situation as an opportunity to bring
peace to Panama, and indicated it knew of Noriega's position before
he showed up Sunday afternoon.
   ``I can announce with satisfaction that the conflict in Panama
seems to be nearing a solution without further shedding of blood,''
a statement issued in Vatican City said.
   MORE
</TEXT>

</DOC>