<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0201EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-NuclearWeaponsPlant     12-19 0441</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Nuclear Weapons Plant,440</SECOND>
<HEAD>Advisory Committee Finds Radiation Safety Procedures Lacking</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JENNIFER DIXON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Texas nuclear weapons assembly plant where
radioactive gas was accidentally released last spring was
unprepared for such an emergency, an Energy Department advisory
committee says.
   ``It is still unclear that effective control of the situation by
an adequately prepared response team ever took place,'' John F.
Ahearne, chairman of the Advisory Committee on Nuclear Facility
Safety, said in a letter about the Pantex plant in Amarillo, Texas.
   The letter to Energy Secretary James D. Watkins, released
Monday, also raised questions about safety and environmental
practices at Pantex, the nation's only final assembly plant for
nuclear bombs and missile warheads.
   The committee said the response to the May release of tritium, a
radioactive gas, was of ``variable quality.''
   Radiation specialists and technicians responded properly to
minimize workers' exposure at the plant, the report said.
   ``Missing was recognition that this `unlikely event' could take
place, and thus adequate procedures, instrumentation and training
were lacking,'' the letter said.
   Although a quick and effective evacuation was conducted,
thereafter, ``events are marked by confusion, misread instruments
and uncertain actions. There appeared to be no plan to handle what
surely must be an anticipated accident,'' the report said.
   Pantex spokesman Tom Walton said the plant has begun correcting
problems or ``will be addressing those in the very near future.''
Some safety violations were corrected on the spot.
   The report said cleaning up the facility after the accident was
estimated to cost $1 million ``and the psychological trauma on the
individuals exposed.''
   Exposure to workers, however, was below federal guidelines
limiting radiation exposure and ``off-site exposure was trivial.''
   The letter said the committee found a ``lack of belief that
Pantex can have radiological accidents, in spite of the recent
tritium accident.''
   A ``tiger team'' of government and outside experts also recently
inspected the plant and found Pantex would be unable to respond
effectively to emergencies involving releases of radioactive
material.
   Watkins said those findings indicate workers lack adequate
protection from emergency and routine exposure to radioactive
releases and that the situation must be corrected immediately.
   The advisory committee, which spent two days in Amarillo last
month, found ``an apparent lack of sophistication and depth
regarding environmental problems'' at Pantex.
   Monitoring of possible ground water contamination with wells at
Pantex also has been less than systematic, the letter said.
   ``This issue has just not received a great deal of attention.
This is particularly unfortunate since ground water contamination,
if found, would be a threat to the sole source of drinking water
for the area,'' the letter said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>