<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0121 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 2202EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-CondoFire 1stLd-Writethru   12-23 0393</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Condo Fire, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0552,0402</SECOND>
<HEAD>Six Hurt, High-Rise Evacuated in Construction Site Fire</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 5 grafs to UPDATE with two more firefighters injured,
San Diego high-rise fire; pick up 5th graf, `Four hundred ...'; ADDS 2
grafs at end with details on San Diego fire. No pickup.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN ANTCZAK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A raging pre-dawn fire chased 106 residents
from a 14-story condominium, burned two construction sites and set
the roofs of five expensive homes ablaze before it was doused early
Saturday.
   Seven firefighters suffered minor injuries and an 89-year-old
woman was hospitalized for smoke inhalation. All were in good
condition, said Fire Chief Donald Manning.
   A fire also broke out Saturday morning on the top floor of a
15-story apartment building in San Diego. Six people were
hospitalized with minor injuries and dozens were evacuated.
   The Los Angeles fire broke out around 3:30 a.m. in a four-story
apartment building that was in the final stages of construction,
and spread to the condominium tower and to a three-story apartment
building. It hopped Wilshire Boulevard and ignited chemical drums
at a construction site and residential roofs downwind.
   The cause was unknown but arson teams were investigating,
Manning said.
   Four hundred firefighters battled the blaze in the neighborhood
between the exclusive Los Angeles Country Club and the University
of California, Los Angeles.
   Firefighters had to battle thick smoke and extreme heat to
evacuate the apartment building's residents.
   ``The smoke and the heat are so bad that firefighters are going
in to look for people on their hands and knees,'' said Sgt. Gene
Allen of the UCLA Police Department. Everyone was accounted for by
late morning, said Fire Department spokesman Ed Reed.
   Many of those evacuated were people in wheelchairs, Allen said.
   A damage estimate was not immediately available, but losses were
expected to be in the millions.
   Some residents said a sound resembling an explosion preceded the
outbreak of the fire.
   In San Diego, fire broke out around 8:30 a.m. in a 15th-floor
apartment and flames and heavy smoke spread to the 13th and 14th
floors, said a city fire dispatcher who declined to give her name.
   Firefighters contained the three-alarm blaze within an hour, the
fire dispatcher said. It was not known exactly how many people were
evacuated. Damage to the building was estimated at $300,000.
</TEXT>

</DOC>