<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0198 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0855EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a w PM-CensusQuestions Adv19   12-18 0657</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Census Questions, Adv 19,0697</SECOND>
<HEAD>PM-Census Questions, Adv 19,590</HEAD>
<HEAD>$Adv19</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Tue PMs Dec 19</HEAD>
<HEAD>What's New This Time</HEAD>
<HEAD>With-AM Census Forms</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a list of the questions on the Census
Bureau's 1990 short form, which will go to every household in the
nation.
   PERSONAL
   1. ``List ... the names of each person living here on Sunday,
April 1. ...''
   Same question as 1980.
   The first person listed, formerly known as the ``head of
household,'' has become the ``householder'' or ``reference
person.'' The choice of who to list first is entirely up to the
individual filling out the form.
   2. Asks how other residents are related to Person 1.
   Similar to the 1980 question.
   Choices range from husband@wife to other relatives to not
related. Spaces also offer such possibilities as roomer@boarder,
housemate, unmarried partner and other.
   3. Asks each resident's sex.
   As in 1980, the choices are male and female.
   4. Asks the race of each resident.
   This is similar to the 1980 question, offering such choices as
``white;'' ``black or negro;'' ``Indian (American),'' with a space
to write in the tribe; ``Eskimo;'' ``Aleut,'' and ``Asian or
Pacific Islander,'' with several checkoff boxes for Asian groups,
as well as a write-in space for choices not listed.
   5. Asks the age and year of birth of each resident.
   Similar to the 1980 question.
   6. Asks the marital status of each resident.
   This is the same as in 1980 except that it drops the question
about whether people have been married before and about whether
that marriage ended because of the death of a spouse.
   Choices include married, widoweed, divorced, separated and never
married.
   7. Asks each resident if he is of Spanish@Hispanic origin?
   Similar to the 1980 question.
   Choices include no, yes-Mexican, yes-Puerto Rican, yes-Cuban and
yes-other, with a write-in blank for detail.
   The long form adds 26 personal questions, including ones dealing
with state or country of birth, education, ancestry, military
service, disability, employment, income and commuting habits.
   HOUSING
   H1. ``Did you leave anyone out of your list of persons for
Question 1 because you were not sure if the person should be
listed. ...''
   Same as the 1980 question.
   H2. ``Which best descrbes this building?''
   Similar to 1980, choices include such options as mobile home,
one-family house or apartment building.
   H3. ``How many rooms do you have in this house or apartment?''
   Same question as in 1980.
   H4. Asks if the residence is owned or rented.
   Similar to 1980 but adds a category to separate homeowners with
mortgates from those whose mortgages are paid off.
   Other choices include rented for cash and occupied without
payment of rent.
   H5. ``Is this house on 10 or more acres?'' and ``Is there a
business or medical office on this property?''
   Similar to 1980, this questions separates farms and businesses
from single-family dwellings. That way, the value of a farm, estate
or commercial structure isn't calculated into average home prices.
   H6. ``What is the value of this peoperty?''
   Offers a series of checkoffs for people to evaluate their homes.
Similar to 1980 except that in 1980 the top category was ``$200,000
or more'' and now the top is ``$500,000 or more.''
   H7. ``What is the monthly rent'' and ``Does the monthly rent
include any meals?''
   The first question is similar to 1980 but adds more categories.
The top rent in 1980 was $500; now it's $1,000. The second question
is new and is designed to gather information on special housing for
the elderly, which often includes some meals in the rent.
   The long form adds 19 housing questions, including ones dealing
with the number of bedrooms, whether there are complete plumbing
facilities, if there is a complete kitchen, the presence of
telephone, the number of automobiles owned, the fuel used for heat,
the source of water, whether a public sewer is used and when the
building was built.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Tue PMs Dec 19</NOTE>

</DOC>