<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0116 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1709EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Lebanon 1stLd-Writethru a0580 12-27 0599</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0580,0618</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lebanon Asks Hostages' Release, Complains to U.N. About Israeli Attacks</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with Lebanon recognizing Panamanian,
Romanian governments, truce in effect. No pickup</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FAROUK NASSAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government on Wednesday appealed to
all kidnappers in Lebanon to release their hostages.
   Eighteen Westerners, including eight Americans, are being held
here, most by Shiite Moslem extremists.
   In other action, Lebanon recognized the new governments in
Romania and Panama and announced it was lodging an urgent complaint
with the U.N. Security Council about new Israeli attacks that
killed 12 people and wounded 31.
   In a separate development, a high-ranking Iranian envoy called a
cease-fire late in the day to halt five days of fighting between
rival Shiite Moslem militias in south Lebanon.
   Shortly afterward, police said the fighting dwindled to sporadic
sniping.
   ``The big guns gave fallen silent, and that's a good sign. But
unless the sniping is quickly halted, the situation could explode
again,'' said a police spokesman, who cannot be identified under
standing rules.
   Information Minister Edmond Rizk read the government's plea to
hostage-takers after a two-hour Cabinet meeting held under
President Elias Hrawi and Prime Minister Salim Hoss at an army base
in east Lebanon's Bekaa Valley.
   ``On the occasion of Christmas and the New Year, the president,
the prime minister and the council of ministers appeal jointly to
all hostage-holders to release them,'' the official statement said.
   The plea is likely to have no impact on pro-Iranian factions
holding most of the 18 hostages because government authority has
been eroded by 14 years of civil war between Moslems and Christians.
   The hostage held the longest is Terry Anderson, chief Middle
East correspondent of The Associated Press. He was abducted March
16, 1985.
   On Tuesday, Israeli ground and air attacks wiped out two
guerrilla bases of the Communist Party in central and southern
Lebanon. The ground assault was Israel's largest in Lebanon since
December 1988, and the air attack was the deadliest of 18 such
raids this year.
   Hoss' office said instructions were being transmitted to
Lebanon's U.N. mission to complain of ``this blatant aggression.''
   The complaint, issued Wednesday, reserved the right to request a
special meeting of the council, said M. Chawki Choueri, Lebanon's
permanent representative to the United Nations.
   Paratroopers backed by tanks and helicopter gunships destroyed a
guerrilla base of the Communist Party in southeast Lebanon before
dawn Tuesday and warplanes blasted a Communist command post at
sunset.
   Rescuers worked overnight to dig out victims from the rubble of
the two-story command post in Rmeile, 20 miles south of Beirut.
   Police put the final toll of the Rmeile attack at 10 killed, 28
wounded. Eighteen such air strikes have killed 28 people and
wounded 137 since Jan. 11.
   The earlier ground assault on the base in the southeastern
village of Nabi Safi killed two Communist guerrillas and wounded
three.
   In south Lebanon, the rival militias battled early Wednesday.
But Iran's first deputy foreign minister, Mohammad Ali Besharti,
said leaders of the Iranian-backed Hezbollah and the Syrian-backed
Amal militias pledged to abide by the cease-fire.
   Police said eight people were killed and 37 wounded in artillery
and tank fire duels Tuesday and Wednesday. That raised the overall
toll to 46 people killed and 187 wounded since the current round of
fighting erupted Saturday.
   The two factions have vied for control over Lebanon's 1.2
million Shiites, the country's largest sect, for more than two
years.
   Since the intermittent power struggle began in May 1987, 617
people have been killed and 1,766 wounded.
</TEXT>

</DOC>