<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0429EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-FernaldSettlement     12-23 0386</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Fernald Settlement,0399</SECOND>
<HEAD>Energy Department Drops Appeal in Fernald Lawsuit</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CINCINNATI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Energy Department has removed one hurdle
to a $78 million settlement with neighbors of the Fernald uranium
processing plant, and revealed another obstacle _ the fact that no
funds are available to pay it.
   The government announced Friday night it was dropping its appeal
of the settlement with 14,000 people who live around the southwest
Ohio plant. They sought the payment for alleged emotional distress
and loss of property values because of radiation releases from the
plant.
   But Stephen A. Wakefield, chief counsel for the Energy
Department, also said the Justice Department had advised him this
week he couldn't pay the $78 million from a federal contingency
fund as planned because the lawsuit wasn't brought against the
government.
   The original lawsuit targeted National Lead of Ohio Inc., which
ran the plant under federal contract until 1985. But the company's
operating contract with the Energy Department shielded it from
liability in such cases.
   The department will have to ask Congress for a special
appropriation to cover the settlement, Wakefield said. Payments
probably will be made in installments, he said.
   ``That's terrible,'' said Paul Nemann, one of three
court-appointed trustees overseeing the settlement. Government
lawyers promised when the lawsuit was settled last summer that the
money would be available by October, he said, but that month the
Energy Department appealed the settlement.
   Residents included in the settlement were happy the government
had dropped its appeal.
   ``We think it's really past time,'' said Lisa Crawford, ``My
question is, when are they going to put the money in the bank?''
   The plaintiffs contended in a 1985 lawsuit that releases of
radioactive material from the plant, which processes weapons-grade
uranium, had reduced their property values and caused them
emotional distress.
   The settlement clears the way for federal funds to pay for
long-term medical monitoring of the health of the 14,000 people
living within five miles of the Feed Materials Production Center at
Fernald, 18 miles from Cincinnati.
   Doctors will study whether an excess of cancers or other health
problems can be traced to radiation released from the plant, which
has operated for 38 years.
   The plant currently is run by Westinghouse Materials Co.
Operations were suspended earlier this year to intensify cleanup
efforts at the site.
</TEXT>

</DOC>