<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0095 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1456EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Schools-Projections     12-27 0477</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Schools-Projections,470</SECOND>
<HEAD>Women Seen Dominating Doctorates by 2000</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By W. DALE NELSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Women will be earning more doctoral degrees
than men by the year 2000, the Department of Education predicted
Wednesday.
   In a projection of educational statistics for the remaining
decade of the 20th century, the department also said elementary and
secondary school enrollments will increase dramatically and
teachers will be paid 14 percent more in real purchasing power.
   ``This publication will be a useful planning tool for our
nation's governors, federal, state and local leaders and members of
the business community,'' Education Secretary Lauro Cavazos said in
a statement.
   Women have been earning more associate, bachelor's and master's
degrees than men for the past several years, but 1999 is expected
to be the first year that they exceed men in the number of doctoral
degrees received.
   Men will continue their dominance of first professional degrees
in such fields as medicine and law, according to the study,
entitled ``Projections of Education Statistics to 2000.''
   Other highlights of the study include:
   _Secondary and elementary school enrollment is expected to reach
49.5 million by the time classes begin in the fall of 2000, an
increase of about 4 million students or 9 percent over the current
school year. Enrollment has declined 4 percent in the past 11 years.
   _The biggest shift will be in the secondary schools, since the
rise in enrollment reflects an increase in births that began in
1977 and has continued. Secondary school enrollment peaked at 15.7
million in 1976, has since declined steadily and is expected to
drop to 12.6 million students, its lowest since 1963, next year. It
is expected to climb to 14.8 million, an increase of 18 percent, by
the end of the century.
   _The average public school teacher is expected to earn 14
percent more in real purchasing power, after adjusting for
inflation, in the year 2000 than now. The national average in the
current school year is $31,200.
   _The number of classroom teachers will increase by an estimated
15 percent, reaching 3.1 million by the year 2000. Most of the
increase will be absorbed in secondary schools, which have lower
student-teacher ratios and a greater range of subjects.
   _The pupil-teacher ratio will continue to drop, although not as
steeply as in the 1980s. By 2000 the ratio for elementary and
secondary schools, both public and private, is expected to be 16.1
students per teacher. In the current year it is 16.9. In 1978 it
was 19.2.
   _Expenditures per pupil for public elementary and secondary
schools, now about $4,800, are expected to rise by 24 percent after
adjusting for inflation.
   _College and university enrollments are expected to increase
from 12.8 million to 13.4 million, a gain of 4 percent. Faculty
will also increase by 4 percent, from 741,000 in 1988 to 771,000 in
2000.
</TEXT>

</DOC>