<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0185 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0827EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-PolystyreneLawsuit     12-29 0641</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Polystyrene Lawsuit,0660</SECOND>
<HEAD>McDonald's Franchises, Recycler File Suit Against Ban</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BOB BAUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A plastics recycler and five companies
that own McDonald's franchises have gone to court to challenge the
city of Portland's ban on polystyrene foam products used in
restaurants and other food vending operations.
   Polystyrene, generally known under the brand name Styrofoam, is
widely used to package food and drinks in fast-food outlets.
   Mark Cushing, the plaintiffs' attorney, said the lawsuit
contends the ban, scheduled to take effect Monday, violates
Oregon's Solid Waste Control and Opportunity to Recycle Act as well
as the state and federal constitutions.
   ``In a nutshell, we contend that the city has no legal authority
to ban a recyclable product,'' Cushing said.
   The lawsuit, filed Thursday in Multnomah County Circuit Court,
seeks an injunction preventing any enforcement of the ban.
   City Attorney Jeffrey Rogers declined to comment on the merits
of the lawsuit, but said the city was prepared to defend the
ordinance.
   Although the ban takes effect on Monday, Rogers said the
ordinance won't be enforced until a judge rules on the request for
an injunction sometime in mid-January.
   Under terms of the ordinance, the city serves a written notice
when it receives a complaint from a citizen or a report from a
health inspector that a business is violating the ban. The city
must wait at least 20 days after the notice is received before
sending inspectors to the business to see if the foam ban still is
being ignored.
   If the ban is being violated, the business is subject to a $250
fine on the first offense and a $500 fine on subsequent offenses.
   The lawsuit was filed by Denton Plastics, a major plastics
recycler based in Portland, and five companies that own most of the
14 McDonald's franchises in the city. Also joining as plaintiffs
were Gerald Herman, described by Rogers as a ``longtime recycling
activist'' and two other companies _ Gage Industries, a Portland
plastics recycler, and Irwin Research and Development, a Yakima,
Wash., company that manufactures recycling equipment.
   ``I expect the number of plaintiffs to grow because already
calls are coming in from delicatessens and small restaurants
wanting to be a part of the activity,'' Cushing said.
   The City Council first passed the ordinance in November 1988 and
adopted it officially last January. On Dec. 13, the council voted
4-1 to table a proposal by Commissioner Bob Koch to require
recycling of the material rather than banning it.
   Barbara George, assistant to City Commissioner Earl Blumenauer,
said the council felt that although the industry has quit using
chlorofluorocarbons in the manufacture of polystyrene, ``they still
are using gases to blow air into the product and some of those are
still destroying the ozone layer.''
   Chlorofluorocarbons, which damage the earth's ozone layer, have
not been used in the manufacture of polystyrene for about three
years, Cushing said.
   The council also was concerned that the foam products weren't
biodegradable and would be difficult to recycle because of how
light they are, George said. The ban does not apply to packing
material or to polystyrene used in schools, hospitals and other
nonprofit institutions.
   ``I'm just surprised and sort of disappointed that it happened
three days before the implementation date,'' George said. ``The
council approved this a long time ago so people have had fair
warning. I know a lot of restaurants either were complying already
last year or have since complied with the council policy.''
   He also said the coated paper product that would replace
polystyrene is not recyclable and is two to three times as
expensive as polystyrene.
   The ban would affect 2,200 businesses in Portland, including
1,700 restaurants and 500 grocery stores with prepared food
operations.
   George said whether the replacement products are no less
biodegradable than polystyrene is open to debate.
</TEXT>

</DOC>