<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0352EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Freeze-Migrants     12-30 0515</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Freeze-Migrants,0532</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cruel Christmas: Stranded Migrants in South Florida</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILL LESTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FLORIDA CITY, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Christmas freeze that devastated
much of South Florida's winter vegetable crop has left thousands of
migrant farm workers economically out in the cold.
   Families of workers from Mexico and Central America gather here
each winter to pick crops from Immokalee in south central Florida
to the tip of the peninsula, hoping to pay their expenses and
escape the bitter weather. But this year, they find themselves
broke and unemployed.
   ``They incur expenses coming down,'' said Ada Rojas, who helps
migrant workers solve their problems. ``Once they get here they are
in very bad shape. Christmas is gone by and they have very little
money.''
   The record Christmas weekend freeze killed up to 90 percent of
the winter vegetable crops in South Florida just as the migrants
arrived. The cold also heavily damaged the citrus of Central
Florida, but much of that can be turned to juice.
   The crowd at the Everglades labor camp on Friday was signing
petitions to get government help in paying their rent and for basic
expenses while they wait the six to eight weeks for another round
of vegetable crops to mature.
   ``It hit at a very bad time,'' said Jeanee Elswick, director of
the state's migrant labor program.
   About 2,000 migrants live at the drab camp of white trailers
lined up behind a chain-link fence amid open fields that border the
Everglades. It is one of three camps for migrants in Dade County.
   Florida officials want them to travel 200 miles north to help
with a desperate citrus harvest, but acknowledge the lack of
housing would be a problem in the citrus-rich counties.
   Migrants earn up to $35 on a productive day, so affordable
housing is critical.
   Trailers at the Everglades camp rent for $50 a week, but afford
enough room for the large families of the farm workers.
   Food stamps were already being distributed in the camp.
   ``We're not satisfied only with food stamps,'' said Ramon
Salinas, a veteran of the camp. ``If we have to go all the way to
Tallahassee, we will. We have to pay rent, utilities, buy clothes
for the kids.''
   The idle crowd at the Everglades camp included bored children
wearing Mickey Mouse shirts and grandmothers in sneakers ready to
work. Many of the families have up to six and seven children.
   Gov. Bob Martinez declared a disaster statewide Thursday and
asked the federal government to approve low-interest loans for
farmers. But he's still collecting information before asking for a
presidential disaster declaration that could bring emergency
unemployment benefits.
   The freeze also idled about 15,000 farmworker families in Texas'
Rio Grande Valley. Plans to open four centers for displaced
agricultural workers have been postponed while the American Red
Cross, the Texas Department of Human Services and Hidalgo County
work out details.
   About 60 percent of the Rio Grande Valley's $80 million citrus
crop was lost to the freeze; 80 percent, or $20 million worth, of
the region's remaining vegetable crop was destroyed.
</TEXT>

</DOC>