<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0184 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0812EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-SwinkClosing     12-29 0435</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Swink Closing,0447</SECOND>
<HEAD>Swink Shutdown Caused No Customer Losses, Attorney Says</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LITTLE ROCK, Ark. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   No customer losses have been incurred
with the closing of Swink &amp; Co., a Little Rock bond company that
cited heavy trading losses for the shutdown, the company's attorney
says.
   The closing is due to ``unrealized losses because of market
value decline in government securities,'' Jim Dale Swink, the
firm's chairman and principal owner, said in a letter to state
securities regulators.
   Patrick R. James, Swink's general counsel, said in announcing
the closing Wednesday that the company was in the process of
self-liquidation.
   ``At this point, it appears there are no customer losses,''
James said. ``We notified the National Association of Securities
Dealers and the Arkansas Securities Department of these events.
Other than that, I have no comment.''
   All of Swink's half-dozen offices will close and about 100
workers will be out of work, James said. As of Wednesday, the firm
operated offices in Atlanta; Albuquerque, N.M.; Boca Raton, Fla.;
and other cities in Florida, he said. However, most of the workers
were in Swink's Little Rock office.
   State Securities Commissioner Beverly Bassett said the firm
likely has some small investors as clients, although much of the
bond house's business has been in underwriting municipal bond
issues. Swink sold bonds mainly to institutional buyers.
   Investors likely are protected because the Securities Investment
Protection Corp. insures Swink's accounts up to $100,000 in cash
and $500,000 in securities, Ms. Bassett said.
   She said she expected the securities dealers association to send
a representative from New Orleans to supervise Swink's liquidation.
   ``Basically, what our office will want to do is get with the
NASD to make sure somebody monitors to be sure customers are
covered'' by Swink funds or the insurance pool, Ms. Bassett said.
``We will also want to see if any state laws have been violated.''
   Swink has been plagued by run-ins with regulators and investors'
lawsuits since it opened in 1971 as Swink &amp; Brittenum Inc. By 1975,
the firm had split into two companies, Swink &amp; Co. and Jon R.
Brittenum &amp; Associates, run by the former University of Arkansas
quarterback.
   In 1986, Brittenum's firm failed, and he received a five-year
suspended prison sentence this year after pleading guilty to theft
by deception charges. He was ordered to perform 100 hours of
community service and ordered to pay what reportedly could turn out
to be millions of dollars in restitution.
   Swink's fortunes dipped more in recent years with the decline of
the bond market and government cutbacks on municipal bonding
authorities. Also, more Swink underwritings went sour.
</TEXT>

</DOC>