<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0821EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-SriLanka     12-29 0534</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Sri Lanka,0550</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pro-Indian Tamils Ambush and Kill 18 Tamil Tigers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEXTER CRUEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>COLOMBO, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pro-Indian Tamil guerrillas ambushed
and killed at least 18 members of the rival Tamil Tigers militia in
northern Sri Lanka, residents said today.
   The attack in the Vavuniya district occurred Thursday night,
barely 24 hours after the Tigers ambushed and killed 28 members of
another Tamil band in the same area.
   Tamil residents in Vavuniya, 135 miles northeast of Colombo,
said the People's Liberation Organization of Tamil Eelam attacked a
Tiger patrol in Musalkutti southwest of Vavuniya on Thursday
evening.
   The residents were contacted by telephone and spoke on condition
of anonymity.
   On Wednesday, the Tigers ambushed two trucks carrying members of
the Eelam People's Revolutionary Liberation Front, killing 28 of
them. Three Tigers also died in that battle just west of Vavuniya.
   The People's Liberation Organization of Tamil Eelam and the the
Eelam People's Revolutionary Liberation Front are allies in the
struggle for power against the Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam,
the strongest Tamil militant group.
   The front won control of the provincial council a year ago in
elections boycotted by the Tigers, who now are trying to dislodge
the front and force new elections.
   The Tigers also have been battling the Indian peacekeeping force
sent to Sri Lanka in July 1987 to disarm Tamil guerrillas who had
been fighting Sri Lanka's Sinhalese-dominated government for a
separate homeland in northeastern Sri Lanka. The two smaller Tamil
groups agreed to give up armed struggle, but the Tigers refused to
surrender their weapons an started attacking the Indian force.
   The Indians have been winding down their military presence and
pulled out of the Vavuniya area today. They have withdrawn from six
of the eight northeastern districts they once patrolled but remain
in the major population centers of Trincomalee and Jaffna.
   The peacekeeping operation grew out of a July 1987 peace plan.
The government of former Indian Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi said in
September its troowould take longer.
   Indian Foreign Minister Inder Kumar Gujral said the withdrawal
should be over by March 31.
   Sri Lankan Foreign Minister Ranjan Wijeratne said today he had
not been formally notified of India's new timetable.
   ``They (the Indians) appear to have decided on their own,''
Wijeratne said. He said he would have no further comment until he
received a detailed report from the Sri Lankan Embassy in New Delhi.
   An estimated 25,000 Indian soldiers remain in Sri Lanka. India
became involved because of the sympathies of its own politically
powerful Tamil minority of 60 million from their fellow Tamils in
Sri Lanka.
   Tamils make up 18 percent of Sri Lanka's 16 million people and
say the Sinhalese majority discriminates against them.
   More than 11,000 people, including 1,100 Indian soldiers, have
been killed in the northeast since the Tamil separatist revolt
started in 1983. Six thousand have died in backlash by Sinhalese
extremists in the Sinhalese heartland of central and southern Sri
Lanka who accused the government of making too many concessions to
the Tamils.
</TEXT>

</DOC>