<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0201EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-HomelessHoliday Bjt   12-21 0810</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Homeless Holiday, Bjt,0840</SECOND>
<HEAD>'Tis the Season? Homeless Suffer Cold Weather, Cold Shoulders</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT DVORCHAK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP National Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Commuters brush past the outstretched paper cup
as its holder serenades them in the subway with the hymn, ``There
Is No Secret What God Can Do.''
   Walter McKinney sings for his supper, which is soup and a bagel
when he can get it. ``I might have to sing 35 to 40 minutes to get
a dime,'' he said.
   It's the season of giving, and shoppers sashay to department
stores in mink coats and fur-lined boots.
   Over a pair of pajamas, McKinney wears four pairs of pants, two
shirts, two sweaters, two jackets and two coats. The sleeve on his
gray outercoat, a Pierre Cardin donated by a Wall Street
benefactor, was torn from cuff to shoulder in a tussle with a
policeman.
   His fur scarf came from a woman's coat found in the trash. His
feet are shod with Reebok sneakers salvaged from a shoe store's
garbage. The shoestrings are missing, seized after his last arrest.
That's standard police procedure so prisoners won't hang themselves.
   His raspy wailings strain to be heard above the screeching train
brakes and cranking turnstiles at a midtown subway stop.
   ``It's hard to get money from people today,'' McKinney lamented.
``They're fed up. They're distrustful. In a lot of cases, they're
hostile. They don't want to be bothered. ...
   ``There ain't no generosity.''
   A good day, McKinney says, brings $20 _ a nickle, or dime or
quarter at a time _ for five hours of gospel melodies and ramblings
on abortion, the death penalty and El Salvador. A bad day means an
empty cup and an empty belly.
   He's not alone in the streets. Homeless Vietnam vets, beggars in
wheelchairs and mooching musicians playing violins all have their
hands out.
   The competition makes for tough times even at this time of year,
when New York gift-wraps an entire Fifth Avenue building, hangs a
2-ton snowflake as a street ornament and adorns a 65-foot tree with
miles of lights.
   It seems like Christmas. And yet McKinney says police ran him
off when he was panhandling shoppers outside Bloomingdale's. He
says he's been kicked by security guards and tossed down escalators
by street gangs. He says he has been spat upon and pelted with
bottles.
   McKinney, twice divorced, says he has no other way to survive. A
native of Sanford, Fla., he hasn't had a job in 20 years and
prefers the streets to shelters, which attract gangs and psychos.
   ``There's no stigma to begging. It's better than stealing,'' he
said.
   If a day's collections are paltry, McKinney sifts for scraps in
the garbage. He interrupted an interview to retrieve a discarded
meatloaf sandwich.
   ``You got to take advantage of every opportunity,'' he explained.
   The hard life yields a hard look.
   McKinney's dreadlocks, which he says haven't been shorn in four
years, bulge from a painter's cap. A fresh scar runs from under his
right eye to his nose. His upper gum is toothless except for the
left canine.
   A canvas backpack pinned shut stores his Bible, a spare pair of
socks, his hat and gloves.
   ``Everything I have I found. I ain't bought nothing but food for
20 years,'' McKinney said.
   Well, not exactly. He's partial to quarts of Ballantine's beer.
His presmoked cigarettes are reclaimed from the floor.
   There's a momentary glimmer of Christmas at the Third Avenue and
53rd Street subway stop, where he offers his daily hymns. Someone
requests ``Silent Night.'' It's worth a quarter.
   With the day's take, he buys a beer and heads to Harlem to eat.
   At night, McKinney trudges the streets. Prostitutes are the only
other creatures walking.
   If he gets too cold, a subway corridor provides shelter. Or he
may just sleep on the train. His way of beating the chill: ``You
just keep moving.''
   Mornings find him at a bench in Battery Park, where hedges are a
windbreak. There he can rehearse or read his discarded newspapers.
   ``That bench is my home. It's the one place I can go and feel
safe and secure,'' McKinney said. ``I like to amble about, not be
hassled and bothered by the devils and demons.''
   Then he's off to Wall Street, where his ragtag clothes from a
giveaway bin clash with the gray flannel of brokers. He washes his
feet in restroom sinks of office buildings or Trinity Church.
   Eventually, his routine takes him back to the subway platform,
every day, holiday or not.
   Singing, he sticks out the modern day version of the tin cup _ a
crumpled paper coffee container decorated with scenes of Greek
temples and the words ``We Are Happy To Serve You.''
   ``I never asked for anything,'' McKinney said. ``I have the cup
out to receive if they care to give.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>