<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1813EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Elena     12-24 0688</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Elena,0710</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dictator's Wife a Pitiless Ruler</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIOREL URMA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Elena Ceausescu often was praised as
``the best mother of Romania'' and a ``scientist of world fame.''
   Insiders say she was ill-educated, arrogant, had a taste for
furs and expensive jewelry, and referred to ordinary Romanians as
``worms.''
   Official biographies even shaved two years off her age, to make
her one year younger than her husband, Nicolae Ceausescu. Mrs.
Ceausescu actually is 72, a year older than the deposed dictator.
   A member of the Politburo and the virtual second-in-command of
the country, she was one of the dozens of Ceausescu relatives who
held influential positions in the government. She often was at
Ceausescu's side in public.
   They acted much like a royal family, traveling together abroad,
conducting well-staged visits to farms and factories, and making a
regal promenade to greet lined-up guests at state receptions.
   Mrs. Ceausescu was said to be a trained chemist, and works by
her filled Romanian bookstores and were translated into foreign
languages. But they were believed to be ghost-written by other
scientists.
   Gen. Ion Pacepa, chief of Romanian intelligence operations
abroad until 1978 when he defected to the United States, said in a
book published last year that among his duties was to collect
classified technological information to be used in the books by
Mrs. Ceausescu.
   As chairman of the national council for science and education,
Mrs. Ceausescu was in charge of all curricula, from elementary
schools to higher education.
   The Marxist indoctrination and the official adulation amounting
to public worship of the Ceausescus have ``poisoned the soul and
mind of our children and deprived them of the genuine values of
Romanian and universal culture,'' Bucharest Radio quoted a Romanian
writer as saying Sunday.
   Official biographies listed Mrs. Ceausescu as being born in
1919. In fact, she was born in Petresti, a village in southern
Romania, in 1917.
   She met and married her husband when both were teen-age
revolutionaries.
   Her celebrated competence in science was less than genuine.
During her time as director of the Central Institute of Chemical
Research, she took the floor at several national conferences and
meetings but spoke on general matters. Whenever a specific
scientific theme arose, she deferred to a ``Comrade Engineer'' who
then had to explain the details.
   She joined the Communist Party in 1937 in Bucharest where she
worked in a textile factory.
   After Ceausescu's takeover in 1965, she rapidly rose in the
party hierarchy. She was named a member of the party executive
committee in 1973, and also was a member of the Politburo and first
vice premier.
   She once was elected ``queen'' of a workers' parade on May 1,
1939, and Mrs. Ceausescu lived like one once she and her husband
ruled Romania.
   Pacepa said he was ordered to ensure Mrs. Ceausescu could shop
for jewelry whenever she wanted.
   He also said he reported to her once a week with tapes secretly
recorded at the residences of their children _ two sons and a
daughter _ and other high officials, so she could keep tabs on them.
   Romanian TV on Sunday showed footage from one of Ceausescu's
residences, displaying some of her jewelry and Western currency
allegedly prepared in a bag for escape.
   They had a mountain retreat in the Carpathians, a villa at the
Black Se resort of Neptune, and a marble-floored mansion by a lake
on the outskirts of Bucharest. At the time of the uprising, work
was being completed on the huge presidential palace.
   One of her many expensive fur coats was found at the Communist
Party headquarters Friday and paraded in front of photographers
after she and her husband fled the capital by helicopter. They are
both in detention, and awaiting trial.
   Sources close to her entourage said she was cynical, and paid no
attention to the real needs of the 23 million Romanians, whom she
despised.
   ``The worms never get satisfied, regardless of how much food you
give them,'' she was once overheard saying, referring to their
complaints about food shortages that have plagued Romania for a
decade.
</TEXT>

</DOC>