<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1347EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-Pentagon-Drugs 1stLd-Writethru a0423 12-28 0732</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Pentagon-Drugs, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0423,700</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pentagon Proposes `Virtual Blockade' to Fight Colombian Drugs</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Top 8 grafs to include Fitzwater confirmation of overall plan;
picks up at pvs 6th graf, The operation</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSANNE M. SCHAFER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Military Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush is completing plans to have the
U.S. military interdict drug supply routes from Latin America, the
White House said today. A defense official said one proposal
includes drawing a ``much, much tighter noose'' around Colombia
with a virtual air and sea blockade.
   Bush's spokesman, Marlin Fitzwater, confirmed that ``final plans
are now being made'' to interdict ``supply routes in South and
parts of Central America,'' but he offered no specifics.
   The overall program is evolving from proposals that senior
military commanders submitted to Defense Secretary Dick Cheney. He,
in turn, relayed them to the White House.
   Fitzwater, speaking with reporters today in Corpus Christi,
Texas, confirmed that Bush is mapping plans to use the U.S.
military to disrupt the drug supply routes from Latin America.
   ``We have decided to take certain actions to help the countries
of Latin America interdict those supply routes,'' he said. ``We are
anxious to work closely with Colombia. Whatever actions we would
undertake in this regard will be done with the closest consultation
with them and coordination with them.''
   Bush is slated to attend an anti-drug summit in Colombia in
February.
   Although the military's interdiction operation could be launched
before the summit, the senior defense official declined to offer a
start-up date for the maneuver.
   ``It's supposed to be a big-time operation,'' said the official,
who spoke on condition on anonymity. ``We want to make it
impossible for any drugs to come out of there by air or sea.''
   The operation would involve positioning an aircraft carrier
battle group and its accompanying air wing off the Caribbean coast
of the South American country, the source said in a recent
interview.
   The Pentagon official stressed that there would be no question
of U.S. military shooting down planes flown by suspected drug
dealers.
   ``There are no plans to start blowing people out of the sky,''
the official said. ``The role would be one of support and focus on
forming a much, much tighter noose.''
   The official said the plan was being formulated in cooperation
with the Colombian government and is not designed to impede the
export of legal products.
   The official cautioned there were problems involved in such an
effort. First of all, he said, the plan could be delayed because
the U.S. military's attention has been diverted by the Panama
invasion.
   And ``one weak link'' in the massive operation could be the
hand-off to Colombian authorities, who are expected to take up the
enforcement role, he said.
   In addition, the official pointed out, because the drug problem
is so pervasive, the drug lords most certainly will choose more
land routes to move their illicit products.
   ``They've got a lot of money and they're not fools,'' the
official said. ``We know this is a hydraulic problem. No sooner do
you squeeze and close off one route than it spurts out through
another.''
   The official said the plan could be altered by the president.
   The maneuver targets Colombia ``because that country is one of
the major flow points (for drugs). We are proposing a virtual air
and sea blockade,'' the official said.
   The Navy will play the key role in the operation, the official
said, because of its ability to put airborne warning and control
planes, E-2C ``Hawkeyes,'' in the air from carriers.
   Such planes, with saucer-like radar equipment mounted on their
frames, are able to keep tabs on drug-smuggling suspects in planes
or ships because they can track surface and air targets over a wide
region.
   The anti-drug summit is slated to be held in Cartagena, a port
city 680 miles north of Bogota. It is located in a Medellin cartel
stronghold in a country ravaged by bombings and assassinations
since Colombian President Virgilio Barco declared war on the drug
traffickers three months ago.
   Peru has decided to resume joint anti-drug operations with the
United States a week after canceling the activities as a protest of
the U.S. military intervention in Panama, U.S. and Peruvian
officials said Wednesday.
   The Peruvian Embassy said joint operations resumed because ``the
fight against drugs is so important.'' Last week, Peru also
canceled plans to participate in the summit.
</TEXT>

</DOC>