<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1150EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>b i PM-Romania 7thLd-Writethru   12-23 1065</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania, 7th Ld-Writethru,a0523,1101</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Ceausescu and His Wife Reported Captured</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 10 grafs to UPDATE with dictator to be tried, other
arrests. Pickup 8th pvs, `A provisional...'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dictator Nicolae Ceausescu and his
wife, Elena, were captured by the army today, one day after a
bloody popular revolt swept them from power, the new provisional
government said.
   Ion Iliescu, a member of the provisional government, known as
the National Salvation Committee, said on Romanian television that
the ``dictatorial family, Nicolae and Elena Ceausescu, was
captured.''
   Referring to Ceausescu as a ``poison hyena,'' Iliescu said the
former hard-line Communist president, who had ruled since 1965, and
his wife, the second most powerful person in the country under the
old regime, would be tried.
   Iliescu also announced the capture of Emil Bobu, the third most
powerful person in the country, and Ceausescu's brother, Ilie,
formerly a deputy defense minister. No other details on the
reported captures were provided.
   Romanian radio, like the television in the hands of the
anti-Ceausescu forces, also swiftly reported the announcement of
the captures.
   If the Nicolae Ceausescu's capture is confirmed, the development
should provide a big boost to army soldiers and civilians still
battling better-equipped security forces loyal to Ceausescu in
fighting that has claimed hundreds of lives nationwide since the
dictator was ousted Friday.
   Ceausescu and his wife fled Bucharest on Friday in a helicopter
from the roof of the presidential palace, ending his 24 year rule.
   Their son, Nicu, a regional Communist Party chief, had already
been captured and shown on Romanian television.
   Before today's announcement, numerous conflicting reports on
Ceausescu and his wife had said they were captured, then escaped;
that they had fled the nation; and that they were directing their
forces from outside Bucharest.
   However, today's announcement was the first definite word from
the opposition that Ceausescu was in their hands.
   A provisional government comprised of generals and dissident
politicians and backed by the army declared itself for democracy
and free elections but was clearly having trouble maintaining
control today.
   Bucharest radio and TV repeatedly appealed to people and army
units to rush to the capital and aid soldiers outnumbered by the
enemy security forces.
   State television said the Soviet Embassy pledged personnel and
equipment to aid the popular forces, but Czechoslovakia's CTK news
agency quoted the embassy as saying any aid would be restricted to
food and other non-lethal material.
   In Moscow, President Mikhail S. Gorbachev said his country was
standing by with assistance, but he failed to promise anything more
than medicine.
   ``We have to support them from the point of view of medical help
and maybe some other kinds of help, but to bring in forces, I think
that's impermissible,'' Premier Nikolai I. Ryzhkov said.
   At least eight Romanian embassies abroad switched loyalties to
anti-Ceausescu forces as the armed revolt entered its second day,
among them legations in Moscow, Austria, Canada, Yugoslavia, Poland
and Israel.
   Romanian emigres in touch with Bucharest said untrained
civilians are being enlisted by anti-Ceausescu forces.
   ``We expect the army to win in the end. But the Ceausescu
security forces are well-trained, well-armed, and they are fighting
for survival,'' said Mrs. Iolanda Stranescu, president of the
British Romanian Association in London.
   Gorbachev said ``a number of other measures'' were being worked
out with Warsaw Pact allies, and that a special working group was
monitoring events in Romania. He provided no other details.
   Fighting was fierce in Bucharest, where the army and civilians
who took up arms were defending state television and radio
headquarters and trying to capture the fire gutted presidential
palace from Ceausescu loyalists.
   As dawn broke over Bucharest, anti-Ceausescu soldiers posted
atop the TV building fought with pockets of loyalists in nearby
apartment buildings in a firefight that lit up the early morning
sky.
   Rocket-propelled grenades slammed into the TV building and
defenders answered with machine-gun and rifle fire.
   Bucharest radio reported intense combat in Brasov, the country's
second-largest city, and fighting in another central city, Sibiu.
   It said more than 12,000 people had been killed in Timisoara
alone since the uprising began Dec. 15 with demonstrations in that
western city.
   Scattered gunfire continued today in Timisoara, residents
reclaimed the streets after the army appeared to establish control.
   The slaughter of demonstrators by security forces in Timisoara
touched off in this country of 23 million people the quickest and
bloodiest revolution Eastern Europe has seen in turmoil this year
that has toppled one-party Communist rule in Poland, Hungary, East
Germany and Czechoslovakia.
   Among the Timisoara dead were 7,614 people first detained then
executed, said the Bucharest radio report, which was impossible to
independently verify.
   The radio also announced that all political prisoners had been
released.
   The fighting in Romanian cities today blocked urgently needed
medical supplies, the International Committee of the Red Cross in
Geneva reported.
   Sokeswoman Marjolaine Martin said an Red Cross workers flown
from Geneva to Bucharest with four tons of supplies Friday were
unable to reach the center of Bucharest this morning because of the
fighting.
   Ms. Martin said the Red Cross also had reports that trucks with
medical supplies trying to cross into Romania from Hungary also
remained blocked today because the ``borders are closed.''
   Early this morning, a tank belonging to the anti-Ceausescu army
units crushed veteran French television reporter Jean-Louis
Calderon during the chaotic fighting outside the Central Committee
headquarters.
   Calderon, 31, was reporting on the clash when he was run over by
one of about 30 armored vehicles that entered the square.
   Elsewhere in the capital, an Associated Press reporter saw
pro-uprising soldiers bring reinforcements of tanks and heavy
artillery to direct against the presidential palace.
   Taxis with red crosses rushed the wounded to hospitals. In the
city's emergency hospital, about 50 bodies were piled in one room.
Most were civilians.
   ``That was just one room in one hospital,'' said producer
Wolfgang Roehr of a British VisNews TV crew at the hospital. ``We
saw trucks full of what must have been hundreds of coffins.''
   Bucharest radio said military helicopters piloted by
pro-Ceausescu forces dropped leaflets in the city center that
warned the popular forces to ``stop before its too late.''
   The new government had arrested key figures from the ousted
regime, including the interior minister and the chief of the secret
police, who later went on national radio to urge support for the
uprising.
</TEXT>

</DOC>