<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1416EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Christmas-Pope     12-25 0532</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Christmas-Pope,0547</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pope Prays for Eastern Europe, Emerging from ``Nightmare'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-World Christmas, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FRANCES D'EMILIO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VATICAN CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pope John Paul II offered a special prayer
for the people of Romania and expressed hope in his traditional
Christmas message that the spirit of the holiday will reach across
his native Eastern Europe.
   In his gold robes and miter, the pope emerged at noon on his
balcony overlooking sun-dappled St. Peter's Square, where tens of
thousands of faithful and tourists listened to the annual ``Urbi et
Orbi,'' Latin for ``to the city and to the world.''
   ``May the light that came into the world on this blessed day
shine in your hearts and in your homes always,'' the pope said in
English, his head bowed.
   ``The world longs for peace,'' John Paul declared, then listed
conflicts worldwide: Lebanon, the Holy Land, Central America,
Africa and Asia.
   After his words about Eastern Europe and especially Romania, the
pope paused for a few seconds and lifted his head.
   ``May this old Europe of ours also receive you, O Word
Incarnate!'' he said. ``Deep within her she carries the imprint of
your gospel from which she has derived her culture, her art, her
concept of the inviolable dignity of man.''
   ``May this Europe open her doors and her heart to understand and
receive the anxieties, the fears and the problems of the nations
which seek her help,'' the pope said.
   ``May she respond with the strength and the generosity of her
Christian roots to this very special moment of history ... which
the world is now experiencing as if awakened from a nightmare and
opened up to a better hope.''
   Although he did not name the countries, it was clear the pope
was referring to Czechoslovakia, East Germany, Bulgaria, Hungary,
and his native Poland, where Communist regimes this year have seen
their once-absolute power shaken and diluted.
   In Romania, a popular revolt ousted the hard-line Communist
leader, Nicolae Ceausescu, but thousands of people are believed to
have died in fighting between pro- and anti-Ceausescu forces.
   ``In particular, bless at this hour, O Lord, the noble land of
Romania, which is celebrating this Christmas in fear and trembling
with sorrow for the many human lives tragically lost and in the joy
of having taken once more the path of freedom,'' the pope said.
   He paused to bring his folded hands to his face as if deep in
thought, then looked up after a few seconds and finished his speech.
   In keeping with his custom, the pope ended his public appearance
by saying ``Merry Christmas'' in 53 languages, beginning in Italian
and ending in Latin.
   In his message, the pope also prayed for guidance for
negotiators involved in arms control agreements and denounced the
``self-interest'' or ``lack of concern'' that aggravates pollution.
   He also cited the plight of ethnic and religious minorities and
refugees without citing specific nations or groups.
   The pope did not mention Panama, where ousted dictator Gen.
Manuel Antonio Noriega has sought refuge at the Vatican Embassy to
evade U.S. troops sent in to capture him. More than 200 people have
died as a result of the fighting.
</TEXT>

</DOC>