<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0714EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-PanamaFunerals     12-28 0702</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama Funerals,0721</SECOND>
<HEAD>4 Soldiers, Sailor Killed in Panama Are Buried</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Four soldiers and a sailor who died in the U.S. invasion of
Panama were buried with full military honors before scores of
military personnel, elected officials and clergyman.
   The funerals were held Wednesday in West Virginia, South
Carolina, Massachusetts, Rhode Island and Alabama. Altogether, 23
American troops died in the fighting last week.
   In Central Falls, R.I., some 300 mourners filled Notre Dame
Church for the funeral of Army Cpl. Ivan Perez, a native of
Colombia who grew up in Rhode Island. The 22-year-old Perez was
killed in an ambush by forces loyal to Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega,
the Army said.
   ``This isn't the Christmas that any one of us planned,'' the
Rev. Dennis Reardon told mourners. ``We are grateful to him for the
sacrifice he made. We value and appreciate all the honors and
awards being given to him today.''
   Gov. Edward D. DiPrete and U.S. Sen. Claiborne Pell were among
those at the ceremony.
   In Princeton, W.Va., Army Pvt. 2 Kenneth Douglas Scott, 20, was
buried in the snowy mountains he called home as about 100 mourners
looked on, including his foster parents and the woman he had
planned to marry next month.
   ``I think the one thing that makes us all go on is that they did
not die in vain,'' said state Director of Veterans Affairs John
Moon.
   A military honor guard from Fort Knox, Ky., saluted Scott's
casket one by one at a Princeton funeral home.
   Scott, who joined the Army in June and was stationed at Fort
Polk, La., died serving with the 6th Infantry Division in early
fighting in Panama City on Dec. 20, according to the Defense
Department.
   At St. Agnes Parish church in Arlington, Mass., about 550
family, friends and sympathizers, including Roman Catholic Cardinal
Bernard Law, mourned Navy Lt. j.g. John Connors.
   Connors, a 25-year-old Arlington native, had volunteered for
service in Panama. He had joined the Navy in 1987 and served in the
special operations unit known as the SEALS, or Sea, Air and Land
teams. The Pentagon did not release the circumstances of his death.
   ``We celebrate a common loss and recognize a common grief,''
said the Rev. John McIntyre, one of Connors' teachers at Boston
College High School. ``We do not come here this morning to find
anything like sense, because there is no sense.''
   Among the mourners was the new Panamanian ambassador to the
United Nations, Eduardo Vallerino, who lives in the neighboring
town of Belmont.
   In Seneca, S.C., nearly 400 people attended the funeral of Army
Specialist Phillip S. Lear, one of three South Carolina natives
killed during the invasion.
   The infantryman who had planned to get married when his tour was
over next summer died Dec. 20 of gunshot wounds while American
troops were mopping up an area near Rhiohato Air Force Base, about
65 miles west of Panama City.
   The service at the United Assembly of God Church for the
21-year-old Westminster native was attended by scores of military
personnel from each branch of the service. Lear was buried at the
Oconee Memorial Park and, like the others, given a 21-gun salute.
   The Rev. Harvey Gainer described Lear as a soldier who
``willingly gave his life in what he believed was an effort to
protect American lives and his country.''
   Maj. Gen. John A. Renner handed an American flag to Lear's
mother after the burial and thanked her ``on behalf of the
president of the United States and a very greatful nation ... for
the selfless and honorable service of your son.''
   At Fort Mitchell National Cemetary in Alabama, two military
brothers buried a third brother, Army Sgt. Michael DeBlois, at a
ceremony attended by about 40 friends and relatives.
   DeBlois, 24, of Columbus, Ga., was eulogized as a good soldier
who turned in an honorable performance in Panama, despite an
earlier flesh wound he received when hit by debris from an
exploding building.
   The radio operator was one of two soldiers killed when someone
tossed a grenade inside a building in Panama City that had been
``cleared'' by U.S. troops, according to DeBlois' squad leader.
</TEXT>

</DOC>