<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0131 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1544EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-FamilySlaying Bjt   12-29 0676</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Family Slaying, Bjt,0699</SECOND>
<HEAD>Community Baffled by Brutal Execution of Family</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HILARY APPELMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DRYDEN, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   On a freezing evening three days before
Christmas, the Harris family received the last visitor they would
ever see.
   One after another, Tony and Delores Harris, 15-year-old Shelby
and 11-year-old Marc were tied up and shot in the head, then doused
with gasoline and set on fire.
   Their partly charred bodies were discovered the next morning,
Dec. 23, after a neighbor heard a smoke alarm. Police said there
was no sign that an intruder had forced entry to the house.
   ``These were very outgoing people who would open the door to
anyone,'' said state police Capt. Carl Shaver.
   Police have not publicly suggested a motive. State troopers and
FBI agents have been at the Harris home all week, searching for
evidence and questioning neighbors.
   A brown and tan van was taken from the Harrises' garage; it was
discovered later in the parking lot of a nearby mall. Police have
said they are looking for a bicyclist who was seen riding along
Ellis Hollow Road shortly before nightfall on Dec. 22.
   Christmas wreaths and red ribbons still flutter from the
doorways of the gray, two-story house, and a white wooden sign
shaped like a goose reads ``Welcome Friends.'' Inside, unopened
Christmas packages lie under the tree.
   The Harrises lived in Ellis Hollow, an affluent section in the
rural town of Dryden, a quiet neighborhood set between forested
hills about five miles from downtown Ithaca in western New York
state.
   Residents say they can't remember much more than a burglary or
two in recent years, and Tompkins County Sheriff Robert Howard says
there hasn't been a murder there ``in a long, long time.''
   People left their doors unlocked and neighbors watched each
other's children.
   ``About the worst thing that happens here is a car accident in
the winter,'' said Pat De Mane, who lives two houses from the
Harrises.
   Residents now peer cautiously through their windows before
answering the door.
   People described the Harrises as active and well-liked in the
community.
   ``You can't think of anyone that would have a grudge against
them,'' said Ann Parziale, a friend of Mrs. Harris. ``To do
something like this _ you're really speechless.''
   The family moved to Ellis Hollow in 1986, when Harris, who would
have turned 40 this week, was named sales director of Deanco, a
Syracuse-based electronic equipment distributor. Mrs. Harris'
father built the large frame house for them, friends said.
   Delores ``Dodie'' Harris, 41, knew everyone and organized pie
bees and cookie exchanges. She was active in the PTA and the Ellis
Hollow board, and she opened a crafts and gift shop, ``The Grey
Goose,'' in a barn next to the house because she was worried about
not having enough to do, Parziale said.
   ``She enjoyed meeting people and knowing people,'' Parziale
added. ``If there was a job to be done, she would do it. When no
one wanted to put out the PTA directory, Dodie did it.''
   Mrs. Harris had planned a party for her husband's birthday on
Saturday, the day funeral services for the family will be held.
   The couple were very involved in their children's lives,
Parziale said, going out of town to watch Shelby's tennis matches
and Marc's hockey games and getting to know their friends.
   ``They were very careful about where Shelby babysat ... they
knew her friends and her boyfriend,'' she said. ``The kids were not
home alone a lot.''
   ``People can't understand how it could happen,'' she said.
``This is a very wholesome, family-oriented community.''
   ``Those things aren't supposed to happen here, in this
community,'' said Edgar Clemens, a retired schoolteacher who has
lived on Ellis Hollow Road for 26 years.
   ``I don't think anybody around here slept Saturday night,'' said
one neighbor who said she was afraid to give her name. ``We're all
pretty nervous around here.
   ``I've opened the door to people whose cars have broken down. I
don't think I'll do that any more.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>