<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0295 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0555EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f BC-White-CollarSentences Adv26   12-22 1113</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-White-Collar Sentences, Adv 26,1149</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv26</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Tuesday Dec. 26</HEAD>
<HEAD>Prison to Probation: Disparity Marks Wall Street Punishments</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEFAN FATSIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ivan Boesky gets three years in prison for
masterminding an unprecedented insider trading swindle. Fraud-mate
Boyd Jefferies squeals on others and is freed in appreciation.
   Admitted stock manipulator Salim B. Lewis will work as an
executive in a drug rehabilitation clinic after pleading guilty;
stock parker Paul A. Bilzerian will go to prison after a jury
conviction.
   As the number of cases resolved in the government's Wall Street
fraud investigation grows, one thing is clear: Disparity, not
clarity, has been the main characteristic of punishments.
   Whether ordering prison time or probation, federal judges in
Manhattan who have meted out sentences in the crackdown have
decried financial swindling and said they were ``sending a
message'' to Wall Street.
   But the message has varied, and judges, defense lawyers and
legal experts appear troubled over whether securities professionals
who plead guilty or are found guilty by juries should go to prison
at all.
   ``You are a perfect example of the serious burdens placed upon a
court in trying to deal with this kind of conduct,'' U.S. District
Judge Mary Johnson Lowe told Lewis, a respected trader and former
Securities and Exchange Commission adviser, before sparing him
prison time last week.
   ``You should be sentenced in a way so that your talents will not
be wasted,'' she said. ``Warehousing your body will be a deterrent.
But it will do little to benefit society.''
   Lowe's comments were cheered by lawyers who said the punishment
fit the crime _ an isolated incident of scheming to boost a stock
price.
   But it was the first time a securities felon received only
probation without cooperating with the government. A wide majority
of those who have come before the bench in the last three years
have gone to prison.
   ``Judges will deny it, but there's no doubt that if you plead
guilty the sentence will be lighter than if you go to trial,'' said
Elkan Abramowitz, whose client stockbroker Robert Chestman is
serving a two-year term after an insider trading conviction.
   Jefferies, who collaborated with Boesky, was placed on probation
and fined $250,000. He provided information that led to successful
prosecutions of Bilzerian, Lewis, GAF Corp. and its vice chairman,
James T. Sherwin.
   Bilzerian, a Florida investor, got four years after he was
convicted of making millions by illegally concealing ownership of
stock in takeover targets by temporarily ``parking'' it with
stockbroker Jefferies. Among stock-related offenses, Bilzerian's
term has been the longest.
   The longest overall has been eight years for David Bloom, a
24-year-old aspiring financial adviser who was convicted of mail
and securities fraud for bilking investors of $15 million he spent
on art, fast cars and luxury homes.
   Manhattan U.S. attorney's office records show that of 43
individuals prosecuted for securities-related offenses since 1986,
23 have been sentenced to prison against six placed on probation.
The remaining either were acquitted or are awaiting trial or
sentencing.
   ``You see more sentences of imprisonment now than you did 10 or
15 years ago in white-collar fraud cases,'' said criminal defense
lawyer Alan Kaufman, who has represented several Wall Street
professionals.
   Many defense lawyers believe the benchmark for securities
offenses should be the three years for Boesky, who was accused of
rampant insider trading and cooperated with prosecutors in the case
that has embodied Wall Street's scandals.
   Others say that for first-time violators, straight probation and
community service should be the standard, along with hefty fines
and expulsion from the profession _ punishments they say hurt
financial executives most while replenishing federal coffers.
   ``White-collar criminals should be treated differently,''
Abramowitz said. ``They do not pose a physical threat to society.
(Financial crime) does not grip the city with fear.
   ``It does affect the ethical quality of our society, and to that
extent it is important and should be prosecuted. But the punishment
should be comparable with the crime in that framework.''
   While judges more and more send a message via prison sentences
that white-collar criminals shouldn't get preferential treatment
just because they are predominantly white, male and wealthy,
``warehousing'' a stock manipulator costs taxpayers.
   According to the U.S. Bureau of Prisons, it cost $26.60 a day,
or about $9,700 a year, in fiscal 1988 to keep an inmate at a
minimum-security prison camp, where most Wall Street felons are
sent.
   The number of inmates at such facilities _ the lowest security
level in the federal prison system _ was 12,623 as of Dec. 5, up
6.1 percent from 11,898 at end of fiscal 1988 and 18 percent from
10,686 the previous year.
   Off Wall Street, financial scammers increasingly are getting
lengthy prison terms _ hotel queen Leona Helmsley's four years for
tax evasion and televangelist Jim Bakker's 45 years for fraud have
been the most publicized.
   New federal criminal sentencing guidelines threaten to increase
the use of prison even more.
   The guidelines, which apply to crimes committed after Nov. 1,
1987, and as such haven't been used in most of the Wall Street
cases, provide strict sentences for each offense. In white-collar
cases, the length of the term often is determined by the dollar
amount of the fraud.
   Judges have little room to apply discretion based on other
elements, such as whether community service might be more effective
for defendant and society. Lewis, for instance, whose crime
occurred in 1986, would have received a mandatory prison sentence
under the guidelines.
   ``They do not take into consideration the differences in conduct
and people,'' said securities lawyer Gerald Lefcourt. ``They
attempt to make things uniform where it is impossible to do that.''
   According to a U.S. Sentencing Commission study, 57 percent of
criminal tax-law convicts in 1985 received only probation. Under
the guidelines, the figure would have been 3 percent. In fraud
cases, 59 percent got probation; under the guidelines, it would
have been 24 percent.
   ``The guidelines made a deliberate effort to increase the
severity of white-collar sentences and will greatly increase the
frequency of prison sentences,'' said University of Chicago
criminal law professor Albert Alschuler.
   ``You really ought to think about taking the white-collar
offender and reducing him to bankruptcy before you start piling on
prison sentences,'' he said.
   Defense lawyers generally agree incarceration is necessary in
some white-collar cases, but say it's counterproductive and
wasteful to send nonviolent felons into a prison system already
overflowing with hard criminals.
   Lefcourt said: ``The attitude of the country is somehow you can
solve complicated problems in people's condition by just throwing
the book at everybody. I think that's very unfortunate.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End advance Tuesday Dec. 26</NOTE>

</DOC>