<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0231 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1644EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-AutoLayoffs Bjt   12-19 0698</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Auto Layoffs, Bjt,0719</SECOND>
<HEAD>Assembly Layoffs Starts Domino Effect</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FREDERICK STANDISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Auto Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Struggling U.S. automakers are likely to announce
more assembly plant layoffs in coming days, adding to the 107,000
workers who will be idled in January and causing a domino effect in
the industry's supply chain.
   Sources at Chrysler Corp. and General Motors Corp., speaking on
condition of anonymity, said Tuesday that more temporary assembly
plant shutdowns probably will be announced later this week. Ford
Motor Co. said Monday that 11 of its 16 assembly plants would be
down for at least a week each next month.
   The layoffs, coupled with slumping sales and scant prospects of
quick relief, mean there's a recession in the auto industry, some
analysts have said.
   In all, the Big Three say 35 of their 54 U.S. assembly plants
will halt production for at least a week each in January, affecting
more than 107,000 employees. That comes amid predictions of
continued weak sales in early 1990.
   ``Maybe there really is a recession if you're talking about GM,
Ford and Chrysler,'' said analyst Kathleen Heaney of Nikko
Securities Co. International Inc. of New York.
   However, she said, the whole industry is suffering a less severe
sales slump than the Big Three. Japanese cars, whether made in the
United States in ``transplants'' or in Japan, are enjoying healthy
sales, she said.
   But the recent sales slump and impending layoffs among the Big
Three automakers, which make nearly two-thirds of the cars and
trucks sold in the United States, paint a darker picture.
   ``There's no question that the fourth-quarter experience has
been one of doom and gloom,'' said analyst Scott Merlis of Morgan
Stanley &amp; Co. of New York. He, like others, expected the Big
Three's slumping sales to continue into the first half of the year.
   Ford Vice Chairman Harold Poling said Tuesday that if the
Federal Reserve Board takes steps to stimulate the economy, as many
economists believe it will, Ford's plant shutdowns could be held to
the 11 announced Monday.
   ``I would think that the actions we have taken will get our
inventories in line,'' said Poling, who will become Ford chairman
in March, when Donald Petersen retires. ``And if we see some action
on the part of the Fed to reduce interest rates, then I think that
those actions might be enough.
   ``In the event that we don't see the actions taken ... then it
may not. It's just very difficult to predict that.''
   It's also difficult to predict the domino effect of closing an
assembly plant, mainly because of the adoption of the
``just-in-time'' manufacturing system. In this strategy, parts
arriving at an assembly spend little, if any, time in a warehouse,
going instead directly from the truck or train to the assembly line.
   The system cuts costs and lets manufacturers keep tighter
controls on quality by spotting a problem in a component before
taking delivery of a large number of them.
   Assembly plants, which can employ 1,500 to 4,000 people apiece,
receive components from a variety of suppliers, some owned by the
manufacturers and others that are independent.
   Those suppliers may have different policies about their own
production schedules when an assembly plant stops making vehicles.
   If the supplier is an outside company, it may have other
customers for its products or an in-house retail system which
maintains a market for its products even when the assembly plant
closes.
   For instance, if a manufacturer announces that a car plant will
be shut down for a week, a steelmaker works right up to the time
that the assembly plant stops.
   The steel company then has several options, which ranging from
building its own inventory to selling to other customers to halting
production and laying off workers.
   This makes it difficult to estimate how many layoffs in the
supply industry may stem directly from assembly plant closings.
   Sheldon Wesson, a spokesman for the American Iron and Steel
Institute in Washington, said automakers are steel companies'
biggest customers.
   ``What tends to happen here in the relationship between steel
and automotive,'' he said, ``is as soon as the automotive industry
sneezes, steel reaches for a handkerchief.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>