<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0086 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1411EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Bush-Budget Bjt   12-19 0714</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Budget, Bjt,710</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush to Propose Record Spending, Weighs User Fees</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM RAUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush worked Tuesday toward a final
version of a 1991 budget plan that sources said would include a
record $1.24 trillion in spending. Meanwhile, he signed a
deficit-fighting bill trimming the budget for this year.
   Despite Bush's ``no new taxes'' vows, the new federal budget
also is likely to propose a series of new excise taxes, including a
fee on the sale of certain recreational equipment and vehicles,
said officials who spoke on the condition of anonymity.
   White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater confirmed that the Office
of Management and Budget was weighing such a levy, among other
``user fees.'' However, Fitzwater added, ``The budget is not final
and the decisions have not been made in the final sense.''
   Administration sources said the White House had tentatively
decided to propose new excise taxes on such recreational gear and
vehicles as camping equipment and off-road vehicles, to pay for
conservation measures.
   Other sources said Bush has tentatively decided against a new
excise tax on the sale of boats and recreational vehicles, even
though an earlier budget-office draft contained such fees.
   Bush plans to resolve all outstanding issues on the new budget
before he leaves town Friday for a ten-day Christmas vacation. The
1991 budget, for the fiscal year that begins next Oct. 1, goes to
Congress on Jan. 22.
   Bush's signature on the $14.7 billion budget reconciliation bill
closes the book on the 1990 budget _ with total spending put at
just under $1.2 trillion _ and lifts an order that had imposed
$16.2 billion in mandatory cuts last October.
   ``The across-the-board cuts imposed would have disrupted some
important federal activities had they remained in effect all
year,'' Bush said in signing the measure.
   Bush praised Congress for making the new cuts ``in a manner
consistent with my pledge not to raise new taxes.''
   In Congress, debate on the deficit-reduction package broke down
into partisan wrangling as the White House sought unsuccessfully to
use the measure as a vehicle for its bid for a lower capital gains
tax.
   To accomplish the needed savings, the bill retains $4.6 billion
of the across-the-board cuts and enacts $6 billion in new taxes and
fees, mostly on corporations.
   It makes up the rest by trimming Medicare payments to doctors
and hospitals, cutting some farm programs, stretching out payments
in some federal retirement programs, and speeding up collections on
payroll and gasoline taxes.
   As for the fiscal 1991 budget, while officials will not discuss
it publicly, an outline is slowly taking shape that sources say
will include:
   _Military spending of $292 billion, just $1 billion over the
current level. Reduced world tensions are responsible for some of
the defense slowdown, expected to be the smallest percentage
increase in a decade.
   _No major new initiatives, but modest increases in some
programs, including the environment, education, AIDS research, and
anti-crime and drug efforts, generally reflecting many of Bush's
first-year initiatives.
   _The abolition of some minor programs, but nothing like the
proposed wholesale agency terminations unsuccessfully proposed by
former President Reagan; cuts in Medicare funds and the proposed
sale of some federal assets.
   _A renewal of Bush's campaign for a lower capital gains tax, a
cut the administration sees as a big revenue-raiser.
   _A revival, in slightly different form, of Bush's 1988 campaign
proposal under which Americans could save up to $5,000 a year in
special tax-free ``family savings accounts'' for funds deposited 10
or more years.
   _An overhaul and consolidation of the government's credit
programs, seeking to save tax dollars by streamlining bookkeeping
on a wide range of government loans.
   The administration must come up with some $40 billion in deficit
savings in a mix of spending cuts and revenue increases to get the
budget deficit down _ on paper at least _ to the $64 billion
deficit target in the Gramm-Rudman budget balancing law for fiscal
1991.
   The target for fiscal 1989 was $100 billion.
   The budget-writing chore is being made easier this year by
Bush's decision to keep the increase in defense spending down, and
by a still healthy economy, now in its eighth year of recovery with
inflation holding steady at a moderate 4 percent to 5 percent.
</TEXT>

</DOC>