<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0091 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1716EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-KKK-Cocaine     12-26 0579</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-KKK-Cocaine,0598</SECOND>
<HEAD>Klan Launches Campaign to Rid Streets of Cocaine; Police, NAACP Wary</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LAKELAND, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ku Klux Klan groups have kicked off a
campaign to rid Lakeland streets of crack cocaine dealers _ a move
that the NAACP and police view with suspicion.
   A ``Krush Krack Kocaine'' initiative calls on Klan members to
act as eyes and ears for police, gathering the goods on drug
dealers and forwarding the information to law-enforcement
authorities, group leaders say.
   ``We're not requesting that our people become vigilantes,'' said
Thom Robb, grand wizard of the national Knights of the Ku Klux Klan
in Harrison, Ark.
   But two recent incidents involving leaders of separate Klan
groups have caught the attention of police and the NAACP.
   George David Kirkland of Lakeland, the 44-year-old state kleagle
of the Knights of the Ku Klux Klan, was questioned by police last
month after he tried to make a citizen's arrest of a uspected
prostitute and drove her to the police station.
   The woman, who was black, told police Kirkland identified
himself as a police officer and told her she was under arrest. The
woman did not want to press charges and police released Kirkland.
   On Dec. 13, undercover detectives stopped Donald Lloyd Spivey of
Kathleen, the 40-year-old grand dragon of the Florida Knights of
the Ku Klux Klan, on suspicion of impersonating a police officer.
   Authorities decided not to accuse him of the third-degree felony
because he did not try to assert authority.
   The two Klan groups, which are not affiliated, are both focusing
on the north side of Lakeland, which is preodminantly black and
which city officials say is the area suffering most from drug and
violent crime problems.
   Spivey, in a recent interview, said his followers began citizen
patrols about eight months ago, splitting up in teams of five to
cruise crime-ridden areas.
   ``We have come into contact with several drug dealers and have
dealt with them accordingly. We talked to them and prayed with them
a little bit, and they moved to Tampa.''
   Kirkland said of drug dealers: ``We can get the addresses and
send them in and let the law take care of it.''
   ``We would look at the Klan as we would any informant,'' said
Police Chief Ron Nenner.
   But he warned that any law violations would be vigorously
pursued.
   Sheriff's Lt. Francis Hart declined to confirm whether the Klan
had offered its information-gathering services, saying it would be
unfair to all informants if he revealed their identities.
   ``I see no problem with them as long as they conduct themselves
appropriately. We don't promote anyone taking the law into their
own hands,'' he said.
   Don Brown, president of the Lakeland chapter of the National
Association for the Advancement of Colored People, said his group
often offers tips to law enforcement authorities. He welcomed the
Klan's participation unless they are targeting certain ethnic grups.
   ``If the Klan is sincere in their endeavor and their efforts are
to expose the drug dealers whether black, white or Hispanic, I
commend them,'' he said. ``But if they are doing this to target
certain ethnic groups, I think it is appalling and they should be
punished without mercy and with passion.''
   In North Carolina, a Klan group tried to join the state's
``Adopt-A-Highway'' program, an anti-litter campaign which credits
volunteers who spruce up a section of highway by erecting a sign
bearing their names. In October, state Transportation Secretary Jim
Harrington denied the group's request.
</TEXT>

</DOC>