<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0169 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0108EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-HolidaySales Bjt   12-27 0687</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Holiday Sales, Bjt,0709</SECOND>
<HEAD>Santa Brings a Mixed Bag to Retailers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARYBETH NIBLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Bargain hunters had reason to rejoice this Christmas, but store
owners had less cause for celebrating.
   Retailers rang up mostly respectable holiday sales gains but
many relied on profit-eating discounts to woo customers.
   Kurt Barnard, publisher of the newsletter Retail Marketing
Report, said Tuesday that judging by the evidence so far, his
prediction of a 5 percent increase in holiday sales this year looks
accurate.
   To eke out the estimated increase _ which falls short of 1988's
7 percent rise above the prior year _ retailers had to accept lower
prices that pinched their profits.
   ``I think the consumer had a very, very merry Christmas and I'm
not so sure that the retailers did from a profit point of view,''
said analyst Linda R. Morris of PNC Financial Corp. in Philadelphia.
   Many stores still are stuck with too much inventory, so
post-Christmas price cutting is expected to be more extensive than
normal, Barnard said.
   Holiday shoppers lived up to their reputation as procrastinators
and didn't spend heavily until the final days before Christmas,
helping to salvage the season for some retailers. Last year, a
belated buying surge boosted business and more than made up for
earlier weakness.
   ``Thank goodness it came and pulled out the Christmas season,''
said Irwin Greenberg, president of Hess's Department Stores Inc.
Earlier, sales at the chain had been erratic _ healthy when the
weather was favorable for shopping and poor when it wasn't, he said.
   This past Saturday was the best day ever for Hess's, a
Pennsylvania-based chain of 76 department stores operating in 11
Eastern states and owned by Crown American Corp.
   Like other retailers, Greenberg said Hess's made a special
effort to get shoppers in the door. ``We were as promotional as you
can get. I don't know how you can get more promotional than this
Christmas season.''
   For Hess's, the merchandising tactic paid off. A big increase in
sales volume offset the price markdowns and the chain appears
likely to register unexpectedly strong fourth-quarter sales,
Greenberg said.
   Not every retailer had to resort to unusually intense
price-cutting. Dayton Hudson Corp., which operates the Target
discount chain and the Dayton Hudson and Mervyn's department
stores, said business this year was slightly less promotional than
in 1988. However, sales were good.
   ``We are very pleased with the results,'' said Kenneth A. Macke,
chairman and chief executive officer of the Minneapolis-based
retailer. ``We continue to expect a strong fourth quarter.''
   Deep discounts, giveaways and other promotional gimmicks have
been fiercest in the most competitive areas of the country,
particularly in cities where department stores owned by heavily
indebted Campeau Corp. operate.
   Campeau stores such as Bloomingdale's, The Bon Marche, Burdines,
Lazarus and Rich's have been under pressure to generate sales to
cover the parent company's debt payments.
   Stores emphasizing clothing indicated they enjoyed better
results than general merchants, continuing a yearlong pattern.
Frigid weather in many parts of the country sent shoppers searching
for overcoats, sweaters, scarves and similar cold-weather garb,
retailers said.
   J. C. Penney Co. Inc., which does the bulk of its business in
clothing, finished the holiday season strongly, said spokesman
Duncan Muir. He said double-digit sales gains occurred at many
stores around the country run by the Texas-based retailer.
   The nation's biggest retailer, Sears, Roebuck and Co., benefited
from a late surge in shopping, which reached a high point Saturday,
spokesman Ernest Arms said. But overall Sears holiday sales
probably will turn out to be about even with last year, when the
retailer reported a 12.1 percent jump in sales over 1987.
   Most of the major American retailers will issue reports Jan. 4
on their sales in the weeks between Thanksgiving and New Year's Eve.
   Cynthia Turk, a retail specialist with the accounting firm
Deloitte &amp; Touche, estimated that chains achieved sales gains of 5
percent to 8 percent over last year.
   ``The higher gains within this average clearly are among the
specialty stores,'' she said. ``There is, however, a lot of
disappointment because of the weak profitability environment.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>