<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1257EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Pastor     12-25 0587</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Pastor,0607</SECOND>
<HEAD>Protestant Pastor Sparks Revolution With His Belief</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALEX BANDY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUDAPEST, Hungary (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Protestant pastor who sparked
Romania's revolution by inspiring his congregation to defend their
faith is a quiet clergyman eager to resume his parish duties.
   The revolution that toppled President Nicolae Ceausescu began
Dec. 15 in the western city of Timisoara, when several hundred
people formed a human chain around the parish church of Laszlo
Toekes to prevent his arrest.
   That gesture grew into massive protests for freedom that
resulted in a bloodbath as thousands were gunned down by
Ceausescu's forces.
   The brutality of that massacre ignited the hatred and anger of
the country's 23 million people, who had suffered immense hardship
under Ceakusescu's repressive leadership.
   A chant often heard in the nationwide protests that finally
toppled Ceausescu Friday was ``Timisoara! Timisoara!''
   Toakes was named to the National Salvation Committee that was
formed to run the country, but the soft-spoken minister said he
planned to remain in his western village and build up a
congregation there.
   Born in 1952 in the Transylvanian city of Cluj, Toekes, a
Reformed Protestant, resisted stifling oppression to campaign for
religious and ethnic rights.
   Of ethnic Hungarian extraction and the son of a Protestant
minister, Toekes has been suspended from ministering to his
parishes and moved to other areas when the state deemed that his
influence among his congregation had grown too strong.
   In April, he was again suspended by his church superiors from
practicing in Timisoara, where he had been since 1986.
   Toekes refused to comply with the order. His home was repeatedly
attacked, and he received threatening notes.
   Toekes said in October that reforms in Eastern Europe had
``created favorable political circumstances'' for Romania and ``I
am among those who have had enough of silence and being silenced.''
   After masked men reportedly broke into his home in November and
threatened to kill him and his family, he moved into the church
with his pregnant wife and sent their son to stay with grandparents.
   On Saturday, Toekes told two Hungarian visitors that when the
unrest started in Timisoara, he was abducted and beaten by security
guards.
   He said he was interrogated for three days at the parish in the
Transylvanian village of Mineu. On Thursday, he was asked to sign a
document stating he had not been mistreated and the interrogating
officers asked him for forgiveness, the Hungarian MTI news agency
reported, quoting the Hungarians who visited him.
   Toekes' cause has been taken up in Hungary, where the plight of
the estimated 1.7 million ethnic Hungarian minority in Romania has
become a chief concern.
   Relations between the two countries have long been strained over
the territory of Transylvania, which had belonged to Hungary for
centuries before it was awarded to Romania in a 1920 treaty. Except
for a brief period during World War II, it remained with Romania.
   In 1988, Toekes joined 16 people in signing a petition opposing
a plan to move ethnic Hungarians from rural villages to government
housing complexes. Hungary and Western human rights activists said
the plan would destroy village culture and ethnic traditions.
   Since the revolutionaries took over the state TV and radio in
Bucharest Friday, ethnic Hungarians again have been allowed a voice.
   ``I believe that now for the first time in centuries there is a
historical opportunity for the Hungarian and Romanian peoples to
extend a hand to each other in friendship,'' Toekes was quoted by
his Hungarian visitors as saying.
</TEXT>

</DOC>