<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0210 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1701EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Bond-Receivership     12-29 0513</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bond-Receivership,0534</SECOND>
<HEAD>Brewing Interests Put In Receivership</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PERTH, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Australian brewing interests of Bond
Corp. Holdings Ltd. were placed in receivership Friday by a state
Supreme Court after National Australia Bank Ltd., a major lender,
requested the action.
   The court decision raised speculation that similar action might
be taken by Bond's other creditors and force into receivership the
entire group of companies held by the company, which is controlled
by millionaire Alan Bond.
   ``In theory, it could trigger the repayment of every other
facility we have,'' said Peter Lucas, executive director of Bond
Corp. ``It could bring Bond down.''
   Bond, chairman of the cash-strapped media, brewing, natural
resources and property company, vowed to fight the decision and
immediately launched rival court action to fend off the
receivership.
   The court ruling in the state of Victoria followed Bond Corp.'s
disclosure that it planned to sell its Australian brewing assets,
among Bond's main businesses.
   The move cast further doubt on the future of the G. Heileman
Brewing Co., based in La Crosse, Wis. Bond purchased Heileman in
1987 for about $1.3 billion and reportedly still owes about $850
million after selling the profitable Heileman Baking Co. and other
Heileman subsidiaries.
   In November, Heileman announced it was given a waiver on its
loans from U.S. and Canadian banks. The company said the agreements
with creditors would give it until next June to rebound from a
declining market share and sales.
   Telephone calls by the Associated Press to Heileman offices
Friday in La Crosse were not answered.
   National Australia Bank, which requested the court action, is a
major lender to Bond Corp. National Australia Bank heads a
syndicate of banks which it says is owed 880 million Australian
dollars, or $695 million U.S., by Bond Corp.
   The banks include First National Bank of Boston, Hong Kong &amp;
Shanghai Banking Corp., Toronto Dominion Bank, Mitsubishi Trust &amp;
Banking Corp. and Standard Chartered PLC of Britain.
   Bond issued a statement Friday saying the brewing units have not
missed any principal or interest payments to the Australia bank-led
syndicate.
   Bond Corp. also stated that, ``In light of the strong financial
condition of the breweries, there is absolutely no foundation for
the allegation that a serious deterioration in the business puts
the lenders at risk.''
   The Bond units included in Friday's court action include Bond
Brewing Holdings Ltd., Bond Brewing Investments Pty., Swan Brewery
Co., Castlemaine Perkins Ltd., Tooheys Ltd. and BBH Securities Pty.
   The bank's announcement came hours after Bond Corp. announced it
had reached agreement to sell its Australian breweries to its 58
per cent owned Bell Resources Ltd. for 2 billion Australian
dollars, or $1.6 billion U.S.
   Bond Corp. had proposed in May to sell its brewing assets,
including Heileman. But the company later changed plans and
postponed the sale of the U.S. company.
   In its fiscal year ended June 30, Bond Corp. lost 980.2 million
Australian dollars, the largest annual loss in Australian corporate
history. Much of the loss was due to one-time write-downs of the
value of some of Bond Corp.'s assets.
</TEXT>

</DOC>