<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0222 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 2310EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Japan-Markets 1stLd-Writethru f0292 12-28 0341</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Markets, 1st Ld-Writethru, f0292,0353</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar Surges, Share Prices Rise Slightly</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: New throughout to UPDATE with Nikkei close for day and dollar
morning close.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Share prices on the Tokyo Stock Exchange rose
slightly Friday in the last session of 1989 trading, while the U.S.
dollar surged against the Japanese yen.
   The Nikkei Stock Average of 225 selected issues rose 38.93
points, or 0.10 percent, finishing the year at 38,915.87. The Tokyo
exchange's key barometer began the year at 30,243.66, increasing
8,672.21 points during 1989.
   The stock exchange closed for the day at the end of the morning
session for the New Year's holiday, which runs from Saturday
through Wednesday, Jan. 3.
   On the foreign exchange market, the dollar opened at 143.45 yen,
up 1.30 yen from its close here Thursday of 142.15 yen, and moved
from 143.35 to 143.60 yen during morning trading. It finished the
morning session at 143.30 yen, up 1.15 from the previous day's
close here.
   Dealers attributed the higher stock market start to dollar
selling on a news report that Japan's ruling Liberal Democratic
Party might lose an election for the powerful lower house of
Parliament early next year.
   But Shinzo Yamamoto, a dealer with Daiwa Bank, said the rise was
caused more by year-end position adjustments.
   With dollar-based account settlements becoming due, ``some
dealers found themselves short on collection and bought dollars,''
he said.
   On the stock exchange, a dealer with Nippon Kangyo Kakumaru
Securities Co. said transactions of trading firm issues dominated
the selling.
   ``This shows that the new year will open with trading firm
issues at the center of trading,'' he said, speaking anonymously.
   ``That the year ended with four consecutive days of increases
shows the great expectations dealers have for next year,'' the
trader added.
   He said that although the tremendous rise in the Nikkei showed
the health of the Tokyo markets, dealers were dissatisfied by the
pattern of this year's growth.
   ``Performance has not improved in proportion to the increase in
the Nikkei average,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>