<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0118EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Panama-Miami     12-23 0489</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Miami,0507</SECOND>
<HEAD>Vietnam Vet Helps 28 Americans to Safety in Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KIM MARTIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The staff of a Panama City hotel helped hide a
group of Americans from Panamanian Defense Forces troops who were
looking for American citizens to take hostage after the U.S.
invasion, members of the group said.
   ``We were playing hide and seek with the PDF,'' said Jay
Skinner, an Eastern Airlines pilot. ``The Marriott employees helped
us stay one step ahead of them.''
   On Tuesday night, hours before U.S. troops launched their
military action to oust Panamanian Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega,
Skinner and his crew arrived in Panama City on a routine flight
from Miami.
   At 1 a.m. Wednesday they awoke at the Marriott Hotel to the
sound of gunfire.
   ``I woke up when it started,'' said Skinner, 45, who was a
helicopter pilot in Vietnam. ``I saw the tracers going and heard
gunshots and I said `Here we go.' ''
   The pilot and his co-pilot, Ron Smith, peered out their windows
and saw smoke and gun-toting Panamanians. The invasion had begun.
   After staying in his room all night, Smith phoned downstairs for
breakfast about 9:00 a.m.
   ``That's when the hotel employees came up and took us down to
the basement,'' Smith said. Hotel staff explained that the PDF was
after U.S. citizens.
   While the PDF searched the hotel's upper floors, the crew and
other Americans hid in the basement. Some of the flight attendants
hid inside industrial-sized washing machines, while Smith said he
covered himself with a cloth and hid in a ditch.
   Skinner said the group changed hiding places frequently. He said
his military training helped him lead troops from the 82nd Airborne
to the group's final hiding place Wednesday night.
   He first established telephone contact with Eastern, and worked
out a code to help the troops pinpoint the group's location.
   ``They came right to us,'' he said. ``It worked like a
fine-oiled machine.''
   Smith and Joseph Andraos, the crew's second officer, both
praised Skinner's skill in handling the situation.
   ``Jay Skinner is an example of what a captain should be,'' said
Andraos. ``He kept things under control.''
   Skinner, Smith and Andraos were greeted with cheers from fellow
Eastern employees when they brought their empty plane back to Miami
International Airport Friday afternoon.
   Earlier in the day, a chartered Eastern flight also reached
Miami with Skinner's flight crew and 57 other hotel guests _
including those Skinner protected from the PDF.
   The fighting upset the gambling streak of one of the passengers,
Fairborn Maxwell, a 45-year-old Jamaican who was in the casino when
the Panamanians stormed the hotel. They briefly held him but
released him when they found he was not American.
   ``I was winning with a stack of chips when they came in and took
us,'' he said ruefully.
   He brought his chips back to Miami, because he couldn't cash
them in.
</TEXT>

</DOC>