<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0603EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-HellgateFire Bjt   12-30 0719</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hellgate Fire, Bjt,0744</SECOND>
<HEAD>Blast, Fire at New York Power Station Kills Two, Injures 30</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LARRY NEUMEISTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A gas explosion at a power station named
Hellgate shot balls of flame hundreds of feet into the sky, blacked
out thousands of buildings and traffic lights and brought subways
to a halt.
   Two people were killed and 30 injured.
   ``It was like the `War of the Worlds,' everybody was
panicking,'' said Angel Rivera, 27, who rode a bus through Bronx
streets that were left without traffic signals Friday afternoon.
``It was a real scary sight.''
   An estimated 450,000 subway commuters joined the chaos on the
streets when trains were stopped because the signals went out.
   Electricity to the subway tracks was uninterrupted, and
conducters brought the trains slowly to the nearest station, where
transit workers guided commuters out of darkened stations with
flashlights.
   Power was blacked out for five hours to more than 130,000
customers in a two-square-mile area on Manhattan's Upper East Side
and in a three-square-mile area of the Bronx.
   While large parts of the city were unaffected, the Upper East
Side and the Bronx were clogged with huge traffic jams as the
blackout shut off traffic signals. By rush hour, traffic officers
were posted at many intersections.
   The power loss stopped subway service throughout the Bronx and
part of Manhattan for more than six hours, and delayed commuter
trains to neighboring Westchester County and Connecticut.
   A pillar of smoke was visible throughout the metropolitan area
from the fire at Consolidated Edison Co.'s Hellgate Station on the
East River in the Bronx.
   Authorities said a utility worker's backhoe ruptured a 26-inch
natural gas line, causing the explosion. Heat from the fire melted
the backhoe. About 50 cars also were destroyed.
   Outside the power plant, the body of Lou Seminerio, a mechanic
in his 50s, was found about 25 feet from the backhoe. It was
unclear if he was the one operating the machine, said utility
spokeswoman Laurie Hanson.
   A teen-age boy suffered a heart attack when he jumped into the
frigid East River to escape the flames, and he died Friday night,
said Capt. Jeffrey Armstrong of Emergency Medical Services. Six of
the 30 people who suffered injuries were seriously hurt, he said.
   The explosion left a crater 25 feet wide and 10 feet deep.
   ``We heard a roar, saw a ball of fire, and the building started
to shake,'' said Jay Escudero, 44, who was in a lunchroom at a
depot a quarter-mile away when the gas line ruptured.
   When he and other workers ran outside, ``You could feel the heat
where we were standing, three or four hundred yards away,''
Escudero said. ``It sounded like when thunder hits, but the roar,
instead of subsiding like with thunder, kept getting louder and
louder.''
   ``The roar sounded like Niagara Falls,'' said John Mulligan, a
fire department spokesman.
   Bronx Borough President Fernando Ferrer said the explosion
``unleashed all hell.''
   Hundreds of firefighters, some in fire boats, battled the blaze
in freezing weather.
   About an hour after the explosion, workers cut off the gas
feeding the fire by closing three valves on the gas main, utility
spokeswoman Pat Richardi said.
   ``When the valve was turned, the flames got smaller and smaller
and smiles got bigger and bigger,'' said Paul Laddomada, 41, who
works for the Department of Environmental Protection a half-mile
from plant.
   Hellgate Station is a former generating plant that controls
electrical service for parts of the Bronx and Manhattan, and is a
crossover point for gas and power lines, Richardi said. It is near
Hell Gate, a section of the East River known for its dangerous
currents.
   The fire spared the switching station itself, but the intense
heat ruined several power lines, causing the power outages.
   People flooded hardware stores in search of flashlights,
batteries and candles. When regular candles ran out, they bought
birthday candles. Some restaurants coped by lighting candles;
others closed.
   At the Metropolitan Museum of Art, about 20,000 people found
themselves groping in semi-darkness relieved only by emergency
lights, guards' flashlights and light from skylights. Most museum
visitors remained calm.
   ``We're troupers, we've certainly had our share of blackouts in
New York,'' said Marianne Ranick. ``And it's another story for the
end of 1989.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>