<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0233 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1554EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WKD--Friday Adv29-31   12-18 0823</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--Friday, Adv 29-31,0845</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv29</HEAD>
<HEAD>$adv30</HEAD>
<HEAD>$adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Weekend Editions, Dec. 29-31, and thereafter</HEAD>
<BYLINE>AP WEEKEND ENTERTAINMENT AND ARTS</BYLINE>
<HEAD>Music Makers: A Punk by Any Other Name</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HILLEL ITALIE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gavin Friday is a punk. His hair isn't spiked,
his clothes aren't torn and his music might seem too sophisticated.
But still, he's a punk. Punk is an attitude, Friday insists.
Worrying about looks and sound runs against everything punk stands
for. And, according to Friday, punks were around long before Johnny
Rotten picked up a microphone and screamed. That means Oscar Wilde,
Jacques Brel and Bob Dylan are punks, too.
   ``When I was 17, around 1976-77, I shaved my head and became a
punk,'' explained the 30-year-old Irish singer-songwriter, who
named his new album, ``Each Man Kills the Things He Loves,'' after
a Wilde poem. ``It was great for a while, but the media made it all
fashion.
   ``The whole message was if you have something to say, say it.
Get up on the stage and say it. That was the best thing about punk.
You don't have to practice your guitar for six years, just get up
and try.''
   Friday admires writers such as Wilde and Bertolt Brecht, who
used humor and irony to coat stinging social satire. In that
spirit, the album's title track sounds like a demented vaudeville
tune. The music rolls and crashes like a ferris wheel sprung from
its girders, like a merry-go-round speeding out of control.
   The lyrics are sung gleefully, your worst nightmare delivered
with the warmth of a Christmas carol.
   ``I really just relate to the words in my own way and put the
melody to the way I felt it should be,'' he said in an interview.
``The words are really dark, but I didn't want to sing them like
that. I wanted a circus type of feel.''
   He never sounds happier than on Dylan's ``Death Is Not the
End.'' Cheer up, he sings, no matter how bad life gets, death is
not the end. Change the lyrics to an advertisement for deodorant,
and you might never know the difference.
   ``It interests me how people don't read that much anymore in
general, and I wonder if people listen to lyrics in songs. I did it
singsong so pople will join in. Then they think, `Hey, what am I
singing? What are those words?' That element really attracts me.
Like life is cabaret, no problems, right? Uh, uh.''
   Friday grew up in Dublin, the eldest boy of six children in a
strict Roman Catholic household. It didn't take long to rebel. By
age 10, he was a rock 'n' roll fanatic and hung out with kids who
felt the same way, such as young Paul Hewson, the future Bono Vox
of U2 fame.
   ``We were kids that related to music and we thought we were
God's gift to the world,'' Friday said. ``Every kid thinks he's
special. You're heading into puberty and you don't know who you
are. Everyone misunderstands you.
   ``You're thinking, `Leave me alone, I want to grow up,' and
music becomes your best friend. I loved Marc Bolan, Roxy Music and
David Bowie. I thought I was the only man in the world who felt
that way. It's weird when you find other people like that.''
   Bono got mad and got rich. Friday got mad and stayed mad. His
first band, ``The Virgin Prunes,'' was harsh, even by punk
standards. Critics loved them, but popularity was out of the
question. Eventually, Friday lost patience as well.
   He was tired of the punk scene. All that sound and fury was
boring him. So he began listening to Brecht and Kurt Weill and
looked for a collaborator with a classical background who could
help arrange the music. In 1986, Friday found his man in Maurice
Roycroft, nicknamed ``The Man Seezer.''
   ``He had studied theology and philosophy, worked in a choir and
studied cello and piano since he was four,'' Friday said.
   ``It was inspiration with all these idiots you work with who are
trying to do what (Jimi) Hendrix did 20 years ago, or Bowie, or U2.
He was into Brecht and Weill. It was like chalk and cheese. He was
so focused, I had to push him out, and he tried to pull me in.''
   For Friday, punk is a universal language. Classical musicians
are welcome, so are 19th century poets. Emotion matters more than
form or content. That's why Friday covers Brel's ``Next,'' using a
punk's disgust to practically spit out the French composer's
tortured lyrics.
   ``It's angry, really angry: `Don't ever be next.' `Don't ever
stand in line for those guys.' `Be your own person.' I saw him
(Brel) on video doing this in French in about 1984. I couldn't
understand a word he said, but ... I knew what he was talking
about.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Weekend Editions, Dec. 29-31</NOTE>

</DOC>