<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0301 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2127EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-AutoIncentives     12-20 0292</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Auto Incentives,0302</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ford Announces New Incentive Program</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DEARBORN, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ford Motor Co. on Wednesday announced a
new incentive program that doubles some cash rebates and adds two
full-size cars to the list of affected vehicles.
   The news reflected the increasing problems automakers face
because of slow sales and a sluggish economy, which has forced them
to sharply curtail production plans.
   Ford's announcement came the day after Vice Chairman Harold
Poling said he hoped the industry would return to the days when
vehicles were sold on their merits instead of on cash-back offers
and cut-rate financing. Ford officials said there was no conflict
between Poling's comments and the incentive program.
   Like other automakers, Ford provides incentives to dealers in
addition to the advertised customer incentives. Dealer incentives
may be used at the discretion of the dealer for advertising,
marketing or passing along to consumers.
   Ford's new incentive program includes rebates ranging from $500
to $4,000, depending on vehicle, and interest rates ranging from
4.8 percent to 10.9 percent, depending on model and length of loan.
   The program is in effect until Feb. 5.
   Last Friday, Chrysler Corp. announced a new incentive program
significantly boosting cash rebates. That program expires Jan. 31,
but the company guaranteed that if rebates are increased later,
Chrysler would make up the difference in the rebate for anyone
buying a vehicle between now and the end of next month.
   For the first time, Chrysler put incentives on its popular
minivans.
   Ford's announcement Wednesday included incentives for the first
time on its full-size Ford Crown Victoria and Mercury Grand Marquis
cars. Interest rates on Ford's minivan, the Aerostar, were lowered
to a range between 4.8 percent and 10.9 percent, depending on the
length of the loan.
</TEXT>

</DOC>