<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0145 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2001EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-UN-US     12-19 0535</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-UN-US,0551</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Envoy Praises General Assembly</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER JAMES SPIELMANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>UNITED NATIONS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. Ambassador Thomas Pickering hailed
the 44th General Assembly Tuesday as ``one of the most
constructive, realistic sessions in recent memory'' for its
approach to human rights, disarmament and other issues.
   Pickering, in a reception for reporters, praised the 159-member
assembly for ``stepping away from governments which have come to
power without the support of the people; respect for human rights;
and a willingness to come to grips with such worldwide concerns as
drugs, human rights, terrorism and the environment.''
   He noted the assembly, which opened in September, had embraced a
consensus position on many issues, echoing the cooperative approach
to the West initiated by Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev.
   ``Those who defended authoritarian regimes or clung to failed
political and economic ways were clearly out of step at this
session,'' he said, referring to Cuba, Panama and Nicaragua.
   ``The 44th General Assembly set the scene for a concrete
chemical arms control initiative by President Bush and a positive
response from Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard Shevardnadze,''
Pickering said.
   During his speech to the assembly in September, Bush proposed
deep cuts in the U.S. and Soviet poison gas stockpiles.
Shevardnadze endorsed that idea but counterproposed ending
production of chemical weapons as well. U.S. and Soviet negotiators
are now reconciling the two approaches.
   ``The general debate set the tone, with speeches which stressed
optimism and pragmatism, downplayed confrontation and welcomed
improved East-West relations and the U.N.'s renewed activism in
helping to resolve regional conflicts,'' Pickering said.
   ``This session had its down sides as well,'' he noted.
``Unbalanced resolutions on the Middle East, Central America and
SoUthern africa continue to be pursued here,'' he said.
   Last week, Vice President Dan Quayle visited the United Nations
and said the assembly should repeal its 1975 ``Zionism is Racism''
resolution.
   Soviet Deputy Foreign Minister Vladimir Petrovsky said later in
the week that his country did not favor a repeal, saying it would
provoke a confrontation.
   Pickering said the United States would push for repeal only when
sensed it would win on the issue, saying a defeat would have the
effect of giving renewed emphasis to the original resolution.
   Among the areas of agreement cited by Pickering were consensus
resolutions to ban driftnet fishing on the high seas; calling for a
free and sovereign Afghanistan; opposing terrorism; denouncing
apartheid and calling for a non-racial, democratic society in South
Africa.
   Pickering praised the record number of votes in favor of a
comprehensive political settlement to the Cambodian conflict, and
record number of votes against the annual Arab attempt to eject
Israel from the assembly.
   Namibia's free and fair elections were a highlight of the year,
he said, as were resolutions criticizing human rights violations in
Iran, Afghanistan, El Salvador and Chile.
   Pickering criticized the Palestine Liberation Organization's
attempt to upgrade its status from an organization to a non-voting
member nation, saying America ``preferred that this issue had never
been raised.''
   Action on that move was deferred until at least next year after
the United States threatened to cut off its $216 million annual
dues payment.
   On Friday, the assembly concludes its annual fall session.
</TEXT>

</DOC>