<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0353EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Salvador-Witness     12-18 0410</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Salvador-Witness,0427</SECOND>
<HEAD>Witnesses to Priest Killings Tell Story</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Salvadoran couple who witnessed the massacre
of six Jesuit priests described a night of terror they blame on
their country's military.
   The couple later recanted the account, but now say that was
because they were intimidated under questioning by FBI agents and a
Salvadoran colonel, The New York Times reported today. U.S.
officials, including President Bush, have denied there was any
intimidation.
   The story of Lucia Barrera de Cerna and her husband, Jorge
Cerna, and their accusations of intimidation have been widely
reported by church and human-rights groups. Today, a brief,
first-hand account from the couple appeared in the Times.
   ``I felt terrible, terrible, when I changed my version, but I
changed it out of fear,'' Mrs. Cerna told the paper Sunday.
   The slaying of the priests, their housekeeper and the
housekeeper's daughter in San Salvador on Nov. 16 came at the
height of an offensive by leftist rebels, and provoked widespread
anger among those who immediately suspected it was the work of
death squads allied with the military.
   The Cernas took their story to foreign embassies and were
brought to Miami on Nov. 23 to be protected and interviewed by U.S.
authorities.
   Mrs. Cerna said she was awakened about 1 a.m. the night of the
massacre by gunfire and looked outside to see five men, at least
two in camouflage fatigues, carrying rifles and wearing caps with
visors.
   ``They looked like the soldiers I have seen on the streets, the
ones with uniforms who patrol parts of the city,'' she told the
newspaper.
   One of the priests was speaking as the men entered their
building, she said.
   ``Then the firing increased and the father stopped speaking,''
she recalled.
   Cerna said he saw seven or eight men wearing soldiers' uniforms
with wide suspenders and belts.
   ``I believed at that moment that they were soldiers of the
army,'' he said. ``I believed that because the whole area we were
in was controlled by the army and because no private citizen could
walk around with the curfew and the patrols.''
   The Cernas said they recanted that version of events under tough
questioning and accusations by two FBI agents and a man they later
learned was Lt. Col. Manuel Antonio Rivas Majia, head of El
Salvador's U.S.-financed Special Investigative Unit.
   They have been granted humanitarian parole status by U.S.
immigration officials and given work permits good for a year.
</TEXT>

</DOC>