<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0118 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1720EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Poindexter 1stLd-Writethru a0663 12-19 0718</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poindexter, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0663,710</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge Limits North Testimony in Poindexter Trial</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Updates with comment from Iran-Contra Committee counsel, inserting
2 grafs after 15th graf, North testified</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETE YOST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal judge Tuesday placed strict limits
on the prosecution's use of Oliver L. North as a witness in the
Iran-Contra trial of former National Security Adviser John
Poindexter.
   U.S. District Court Judge Harold Greene said prosecutors ``may
only elicit evidence'' from North based on statements he made
before July 15, 1987, the day Poindexter began testifying on
Capitol Hill before a national television audience.
   The restriction means the government is unable to use most of
the testimony North gave at his own trial, last April, during which
he frequently mentioned Poindexter, his former White House boss.
   However, prosecutors will be allowed to elicit evidence from
North based on his testimony to Congress, which he gave prior to
Poindexter's testimony, said the judge. The government also will be
permitted to delve into subjects to which Poindexter did not
testify.
   Poindexter's trial is scheduled to begin Jan. 22 on charges of
conspiracy, two counts of obstructing Congress and two counts of
making false statements.
   At a pre-trial hearing last week, North repeatedly said he was
unable to separate in his mind his own experiences in the
Iran-Contra affair from what he learned by watching and reading
Poindexter's testimony.
   The judge was openly skeptical of North's contention, but said
he would accept the assertion in order to protect Poindexter's
rights.
   ``The court takes North's alleged inability to differentiate
with a grain of salt,'' said Greene. ``It seems unlikely that a
witness who was a major and active participant in the events
themselves would be unable to distinguish between the version of
events described in another's testimony.''
   The court's obligations, however, require it to ``err on the
side of protecting Poindexter's constitutional right not to be
convicted with the use of his own testimony,'' said the judge.
   Greene denied Poindexter's motion to dismiss the indictment on
grounds that it had been tainted by his congressional testimony,
which he gave under a guarantee that it would not be used against
him in court.
   ``The court is confident that the government's trial witnesses
will testify from knowledge that is independent of the information
elicited from Poindexter at the congressional hearings,'' said the
judge.
   Greene also allowed Iran-Contra prosecutors Dan Webb and Howard
Pearl to remain in the case, rejecting assertions by Poindexter
that they had been tainted by exposure to his congressional
testimony. Greene said neither prosecutor has any recollection of
the contents of Poindexter's testimony and therefore could make no
use of it.
   A 1972 Supreme Court ruling says the prosecution must derive all
its evidence in a case from sources wholly independent of testimony
a defendant gave under a grant of immunity.
   Greene's ruling means North will be limited in his testimony
about a presidential finding which Poindexter tore up on Nov. 21,
1986. The December 1985 finding retroactively legalized a November
1985 shipment of Hawk missiles to Iran.
   North testified at his trial that he watched Poindexter tear up
the finding _ which relates to four of the five criminal charges
against the ex-national security adviser. But North testified last
week that he was certain it was the finding that was destroyed only
because Poindexter admitted it in his immunized testimony on
national TV.
   ``I think that North has snaked his way around that'' and won't
have to testify at the trial about Poindexter tearing up the
finding, said John Nields, former chief counsel to the House
majority staff in the congressional Iran-Contra hearings.
   Nields said that since North did not tell the congressional
committees that he saw Poindexter destroy the finding, he ``won't
be able to testify to it at the trial'' and ``I don't think the
government has any other proof of it.''
   The prosecution says the finding which Poindexter destroyed is
``the most critical document in proving the falsity'' of another
document, a chronology which is an essential part of the
government's case against Poindexter.
   Poindexter is accused of telling Congress the same day he
destroyed the finding that no one in the U.S. government knew until
1986 that the November 1985 shipment to Iran contained Hawk
missiles.
   py
</TEXT>

</DOC>