<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0202EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-SigningSanta     12-22 0321</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Signing Santa,0330</SECOND>
<HEAD>Signing Santa Makes Christmas Complete for Deaf Children</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LISA PERLMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GRAND RAPIDS, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dozens of giggling children lined
up to see Santa Claus at the shopping mall fell silent and watched
intently as 10-year-old Jeannette Johnson climbed into his lap and
started talking with him.
   Jeannette and Santa used sign language to speak. Jeannette is
deaf, making Bruce Partridge one of the few Santas to whom she can
tell her wishes.
   With hands fluttering, she told him what presents she wanted _
including a guitar. ``If it's very loud I can feel it,'' she said.
   Using his white wool-gloved hands, Santa promised to stop by on
Christmas Eve. ``Ho, ho, ho,'' doesn't exactly translate, so he
made the sign for laughter, a kind of rotating motion from the
belly.
   This is the third year that Partridge, a Kent County sheriff's
deputy, has put his sign language talents to as St. Nick.
   ``Adults think it's such a small thing, but it's so important
for kids to believe that Santa can sign, too,'' Partridge said.
   ``Deaf kids grow up in a hearing world, on the outside looking
in. But they don't want pity; they want to participate. ... This is
one way to show them it's OK to be deaf.''
   Partridge, 36, began signing about five years ago to communicate
with deaf relatives and because he occasionally dealt with deaf
citizens on the job.
   Now a part-time interpreter at a local school district,
Partridge and another Grand Rapids man began posing as Santas for
an annual potluck dinner for deaf people a few years ago and
``decided that there were other deaf children in the area who might
like to talk to Santa.''
   While deaf children may miss out on the bell choirs and holiday
music, Partridge believes that after seeing Santa, ``they go away
happy that they can have Christmas, too.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>