<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0128 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2034EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Japan-Soviet     12-19 0452</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Soviet,0467</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet, Japanese Officials Leave Treaty Talks Empty-Handed</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ERIC TALMADGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soviet and Japanese officials failed to reach an
accord to formally settle World War II in their latest round of
talks with progress stymied by a territorial dispute dating back to
1945, officials said Tuesday.
   Soviet Deputy Foreign Minister Igor Rogachev suggested that
Tokyo and Moscow exchange drafts of a peace treaty to formally
settle World War II. But Japanese officials showed little
enthusiasm, insisting progress must first be made toward resolving
the dispute over the Kuril Islands.
   The dispute over the group of small islands north of Hokkaido,
Japan's northernmost main island, has been the most difficult
obstacle to concluding the treaty.
   Japan has demanded that the islands, held by the Soviets since
the closing days of the war in 1945, be returned. It has said no
peace treaty can be worked out until the issue is resolved.
   The Soviets have called on Japan to renounce its claim and
recognize ``postwar realities.''
   ``The time has come to exchange drafts of the treaty, a treaty
that will be the conclusive settlement to World War II,'' Rogachev
said at a news conference after meeting with Japanese Foreign
Minister Taro Nakayama.
   ``Their overall position hasn't changed,'' Foreign Ministry
spokesman Taizo Watanabe said. He added that Tokyo saw the offer as
a Soviet attempt to ``prompt procedures in their direction.''
   Both sides agreed in December to form a working-level group to
discuss the treaty, and Rogachev led the Soviet delegation at the
group's fourth round of talks Monday.
   Rogachev acknowledged that the nearly seven hours of
negotiations Monday broke down because of the territorial issue.
   The veteran Soviet diplomat, in Tokyo on the final leg of a
five-nation tour of Asia, said Moscow is taking into consideration
recent statements by Japanese leaders indicating a desire for
improved relations.
   During a visit to Tokyo last month, Alexander Yakovlev, a
Politburo member and close adviser to Soviet President Mikhail
Gorbachev, hinted at a ``third route'' to a solution, raising hopes
here.
   Rogachev, however, offered no such route, saying only that
though the Soviet claim to the islands hasn't changed, relations
continue to improve ``bit by bit, and within a certain framework.''
   He said that along with defining Japan-Soviet borders, the
treaty should reflect an agreement to cooperate in the economic
development of the Soviet Far East and Pacific coast areas.
   Rogachev said the next round of talks will be held early next
year. Japanese officials hope to hold talks before Soviet Foreign
Minister Eduard Shevardnadze visits in March.
   Rogachev said he and Nakayama also discussed Gorbachev's
scheduled visit to Japan in 1991, a first for a Soviet president.
</TEXT>

</DOC>