<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0534EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-HarvardTrademark     12-29 0460</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Harvard Trademark,0472</SECOND>
<HEAD>The Question Is: Will They Spell It Hahvud?</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALLISON J. PUGH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAMBRIDGE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Harvard University, whose name has been
emblazoned on sweatshirts from Los Angeles to Maine as well as on
shot glasses, towels, watches and boxer shorts, has decided to make
the name a trademark.
   Under new licensing procedures, Crimson-themed boxer shorts may
still be allowed. But string bikinis? Maybe not.
   Licensing will protect Harvard name, according to Ellen Mitchell
of the Harvard Office of Patents, Copyrights and Licensing.
   ``We just don't want it to be outrageous,'' she said. ``We don't
want to look silly.''
   More than 100 U.S. colleges and universities already issue
licenses for the use of their name, including the seven other Ivy
League colleges, according to the office of Robert Scott, vice
president for finance.
   Margot Naulleau, international licensing coordinator for
Champion Products Inc., one of the main suppliers of athletic wear
with college insignias, said Harvard was one of the last big
schools in the country to issue a trademark.
   But Harvard officials had a good explanation.
   ``It's simply that we are very old and very conservative. It
took us a long time to decide if it was something that we ought to
do,'' said Joyce Brinton, director of the patent office. She said
there was no incident that led to the decision to apply for a
trademark, such as a particularly egregious product on the market.
   ``It was just that the time has come,'' she said.
   Before the Harvard Corporation decided in June to apply for a
trademark on the name from the U.S. Patent and Trademarking Office,
Brinton's office had ``inquiries from many, many manufacturers''
about getting a license.
   ``I think most of the companies have felt uncomfortable that
they don't have a license from Harvard,'' said Brinton. Those
companies worried that if they didn't have a license, they ran the
risk of being left with hundreds of products if the school's
lawyers suddenly cracked down on the name's usage, she said.
   Harvard ran a few trial programs before moving towards licensing
on a broad scale. At the school's 350th anniversary in 1986,
Harvard wanted to ensure commemorative items were of high quality.
Another program licensing the trademark in Japan has been booming,
bringing in $130,000 in royalties annually.
   Under the new licensing procedure, if someone wants to make a
product bearing the name Harvard, Harvard University, or the
school's insignia, they must first show designs and samples to
demonstrate the quality of the product before Harvard will grant a
license.
   And the cost of renting the Harvard name? A bargain, Mitchell
said. Brinton said companies that market Harvard products pay a
flat fee of $300 and sales royalties of 7{ percent.
</TEXT>

</DOC>