<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0121 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1641EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-BushText 2ndAdd   12-21 0703</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Bush Text, 2nd Add,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHN: his election.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Q: Mr. President, in light of what you've said about the Endara
government getting started, the need for stability, the need for
some kind of police action down there, we really are in a kind of
an open-ended military occupation there, aren't we, sir?
   A: Well, I wouldn't say it's open-ended, except it's open-ended
as far as going after Noriega _ open-ended in terms of the
restoration of order in Panama, cleaning up a few elements _
rag-tag elements of this so-called ``dignity battalion.'' If you
ever talk about a misnomer, that's it _ ``dignity battalion'' _
going after them. The PDF units have pretty _ been rolled up. But,
we will keep whatever force is necessary there until our military
are satisfied and recommend to the President that they be
withdrawn. I want them out of there as soon as possible.
   Q: Mr. President, just to follow up, if I could, sir. In he
planning of this operation, surely you must have recognized that
these actions would be needed and some force would have to be on
the ground there for awhile. What estimate did you have, as you
undertook this operation, as to how long it would take?
   A: Brit, no day _ number of day estimate was given to me. I
think everyone recognized some of that would depend on when Noriega
was brought to justice, some of that dependent on how a
restructured PDF behaved.
   Q: Mr. President, what do you know about Americans held against
their will, and what are you doing now to free them?
   A: I'm looking for help on that because we don't have a count.
And if there are a lot of them, we don't know about it. But, I just
had a briefing _ I don't know whether Cheney's still here.
   Q: Well, the Pentagon said, sir, there were 12 open cases.
   A: Well, I'll tell you, that included probably those Smithsonian
people who have now been released, and I think there may have been
9 or 10 of those. So _ but, I'd just have to get Marlin to get back
to you.
   Q: Well, does that indicate that that's not a priority in the
reporting to you _
   A: No. It indicates to me that it's very hard to know what's
going on when there's a firefight and a battle, because we heard
all kind of rumors. We had calls from your network _ your chairman
of the board _ urging us to go in and take the _ (some laughter) _
take the _ no, he did! And I understand it. He had a reporter that
he _ a producer that he felt was held. We've gone there. That place
is secure, I'm told. But, I don't know that we can tell him this
minute about that _ the life of that individual. But, we will keep
on going till we can tell him about the life of that individual.
   There's been an awful lot of interest in the Marriott Hotel.
But, I'm very pleased to say that it is secure. And we've had heads
of corporations, we've had news organizations other than his,
concerned about their people. And we must be as responsive as we
can.
   Yeah, John and then Charles.
   Q: We are hearing _ we're hearing that American _
   A: Then Ellen.
   Q: _ troops and tanks have surrounded the Cuban and Nicaraguan
embassies in Panama City, and that in Managua the Nicaraguans have
retaliated by surrounding our embassy there with their own tanks.
Are you hearing the same thing?
   A: We were told that is not true.
   Q: That is not true?
   A: Yeah. As of a briefing I just had.
   Charles?
   Q: Mr. President, you've referred to the elected government of
Mr. Endara. As you know, there was never an accurate final count
that confirmed that even though most polls suggested he had
probably won by a 3-to-1 margin. In talking with him _ or in the
future, have you encouraged _ or would you encourage him to seek
again elections that would verify that he, indeed, or whoever would
be a legally elected president?
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>