<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0093 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1422EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel     12-27 0495</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel,0511</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israel Extends Emergency Regulations in Occupied Territories</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LOUIS MEIXLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Parliament on Wednesday extended for two years
emergency regulations that allow the military to hold Palestinian
prisoners from the occupied territories inside Israeli territory.
   In the occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip, shops were closed by a
general strike called by the Moslem fundamentalist movement Hamas,
or Zeal. The strike was first ordered for Christmas but was delayed
when Palestinian Christians objected.
   Israeli troops shot and wounded four Palestinians in clashes
with stone-throwing youths in the Gaza Strip, Arab hospital
officials said.
   At least 640 Palestinians have been killed by Israelis in the
2-year-old uprising against Israeli occupation. Forty-three
Israelis also have died, and 162 Palestinians have been slain by
fellow Arabs on suspicion of collaborating with Israel.
   The latest death of a suspected collaborator occurred Wednesday,
when Jawad Hassan Mahmoud Tmaizi, 40, died of wounds suffered in an
attack by fellow Arabs the previous day.
   The 120-seat Knesset, or parliament, extended the Emergency
Regulations of 1967 for two years at the request of the government.
The vote was 29-9.
   The regulations permit the military to hold Palestinians
arrested in the occupied lands in Israeli territory. They make
Israeli law applicable to Israelis in the territories but not to
Palestinians, who are judged in military courts.
   ``This means there are different laws for Jews and Arabs. This
bill perpetuates discrimination,'' Amnon Rubinstein of the liberal
Shinui Party said during the Knesset's brief debate on the issue.
   The army is holding about 9,000 Palestinians and has jailed more
than 40,000 during the uprising.
   Many have been held in the Ketziot prison camp in Israel's Negev
desert, and the United States and human rights group have
repeatedly complained that imprisonment there violates the Geneva
human rights convention rule against moving prisoners out of
occupied territory.
   Also Wednesday, about 1,300 American and European peace
activists toured towns in the West Bank, but witnesses said the
army blocked one bus of about 50 people from entering Jericho,
while letting a second one through later.
   Marina Sereni, spokeswoman for the ``1990: Time for Peace''
movement, said the army gave no reason for the action. The army
spokesman's office said it had no information about the bus.
   Ms. Sereni said the group was appealing to authorities to
reverse a ban on visits by the peace activists to Palestinian
refugee camps.
   Elizabeth Donini, an Italian delegate from Torino, also said the
army intended to block Palestinians from the West Bank and Gaza
Strip from joining the group's ``peace chain'' demonstration
Saturday.
   ``We are here to stress Palestinian rights, and this act is
unjust,'' she told reporters. ``We are here to demonstrate
together, Palestinians, Israelis and Europeans, and stress the
importance of peace.''
   Army officials have refused to comment on newspaper reports that
Palestinians from the territories will be barred from taking part
in the forming of a human chain around Jerusalem's Old City.
</TEXT>

</DOC>