<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0160 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1536EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-People     12-20 0923</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0960</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Hispanic character who used to begin
every comedy routine ``My name, Jose Jimenez'' is being resurrected
to sell cars.
   Comedian Bill Dana, who created Jose, declared the character
``dead'' in 1969 after complaints that it was an unfavorable
stereotype.
   ``Jose has become very sophisticated over the years,'' Dana
said. ``Nowadays we call him Jose Everyman.''
   Dana has signed a contract with Cardin and Cherry, the Nashville
advertising agency whose Ernest P. Worrall character has been
played into a hit by actor Jim Varney.
   Dana has kept busy over the years as an advertising executive,
actor, scriptwriter and songwriter. Last year he appeared on David
Letterman's late-night talk show and popped up as an aged priest on
an episode of ``The Golden Girls.''
   He just completed writing his second episode for ``Matlock.''
   Dana, in Nashville on Wednesday to begin filming commercials for
a local car dealer, said viewers can expect to see many changes in
Jose 25 years after ``The Bill Dana Show'' was on network
television.
   ``The only thing he kept is his wide-eyed innocence,'' Dana said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jacqueline Onassis and the Wampanoag Indians are
close to settling a dispute over a strip of Martha's Vineyard
beach-front property, attorneys for both sides said.
   An agreement over the 264-foot stretch was expected to be
reached at a hearing scheduled for Feb. 2, said Paul Sulla, a
Boston attorney for the Wampanoag. Sulla said Tuesday that he could
not discuss details he said are still being worked out.
   ``There have been negotiations but we're not quite there yet,''
said Onassis attorney Brian Hurley.
   Mrs. Onassis bought a 17 percent interest in the beach property
in 1980 from one of the 25 Wampanoag Indians. Since then she has
waged a court battle over the remaining interest in the land, which
is surrounded by her private 380-acre retreat.
   She has offered a land swap and visitation rights to the areas
the Wampanoag consider sacred. But the descendants of the island's
original settlers want to keep their share of the beach because
they say it plays an important part in their heritage.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Eds: Vernica is cq in 4th graf</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former President Reagan offered his
assistance to a woman on welfare whose home was burglarized of
nearly $1,200 in Christmas gifts as she visited her cancer-stricken
daughter.
   Reagan told Blanche Griffin, 34, in a phone call while she was
at a police station Tuesday that he and his wife, Nancy, would help
her in any way they could, said police Capt. Carley Mitchell.
   Residents, police officers, firefighters and local vendors also
have rallied to the aid of Ms. Griffin.
   The woman had just returned home from visiting her 9-year-old
daughter, Vernica, at Cedars-Sinai Medical Center on Monday when
she discovered the theft of gifts she said she had saved money for
all year.
   The stolen gifts included a battery-powered toy police
motorcycle, dolls and a blackboard. Also stolen were household
items and all her children's clothing.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Singer Michael Jackson was among the hordes of
tourists who attended the Radio City Music Hall Christmas show and
shopped at a toy store this week.
   Jackson drew curious crowds and a gaggle of photographers
Tuesday as he stopped at F.A.O. Schwarz and then took in the 2 p.m.
Christmas show at Rockefeller Center.
   Leaving the Music Hall by a back entrance, Jackson tried to
remain incognito by wearing a hat, dark glasses, a scarf pulled up
over his nose and mouth, and not even one glove.
   The Daily News reported that Jackson got to meet the animals
from the Christmas spectacle backstage, and that he kissed the
camels.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>COVINGTON, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Carroll O'Connor says he is eagerly
awaiting the return of Howard Rollins, his co-star on the NBC
series ``In The Heat Of The Night,'' who has taken time off to
recover from an unspecified illness.
   O'Connor said Rollins is a ``vital part of the series,'' adding,
``I miss him professionally and personally and want him back on the
set.''
   Rollins entered a hospital several weeks ago after having chest
pains. Tests showed he had no heart problems, and he is due back at
work ``as soon as he is able to physically withstand our very
strenuous work schedule,'' O'Connor said.
   The show about Southern lawmen is filmed on location in the
Covington area.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Liver transplant recipient Wendy Marx was
stunned to learn Olympic track star Carl Lewis had crusaded on her
behalf for a donor.
   ``I was still in CPU (the cardiopulmonary unit) when the nurse
said, `You must be somebody special to have Carl Lewis visit
you,''' Marx recounted. ``I said, `Carl Lewis didn't visit me.' She
said, `Yes he did, and I got his autograph.' I thought she must be
crazy.''
   The Nov. 27 transplant was successful and Marx was released from
Pacific Presbyterian Medical Center to a hospital-run apartment
Wednesday.
   It was only after a donor was found through a national search
and the operation was performed on the then-comatose Marx that the
22-year-old advertising company office manager learned of Lewis'
televised appeal for a donor.
   Marx's brother, Jeffrey, a Pulitzer Prize-winning journalist has
been working for the past year on the athlete's autobiography.
   Marx's family was told on Thanksgiving that she had as little as
24 hours to live. In a rare reaction to hepatitis B, her immune
system had destroyed her liver.
</TEXT>

</DOC>