<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 2053EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RoseParade     12-31 0416</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rose Parade,0427</SECOND>
<HEAD>Crowds Gather for 101st Annual Tournament of Roses Parade</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL FLEEMAN</BYLINE>
<HEAD>Associated Press Writer</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of people bearing sleeping
bags, ice chests and lawn chairs gathered Sunday, vying for a spot
along the 5{-mile route for the 101st Tournament of Roses Parade.
   Parade watchers started looking early and often for a prized
stretch of sidewalk, keeping Pasadena police officers busy shooing
them away until noon Sunday.
   After that, everything was legally up for grabs, and folks
started to stake their claims along Orange Grove and Colorado
boulevards. A few minutes after noon, every foot of the parade
route was lined with people.
   A pizza restaurant was making deliveries on the sidewalks, while
entrepreneurs were selling motor home parking spaces at every
parking lot, front lawn and driveway within eyeshot of the parade.
Some fraternity members were guarding as many as 20 folding chairs.
   The crowd gathered Sunday under clear, warm and sunny skies, but
the National Weather Service forecast a mostly cloudy New Year's
Day in Pasadena, with overnight temperatures in the low 40s,
accompanied by light winds.
   Vivian and Gary Larrick of Laverne parked their motor home near
the route and set up lawn chairs Sunday morning.
   ``The kids are going to stay here,'' said Mrs. Larrick, sitting
along Colorado Boulevard near a used car lot converted to a
campground. ``We're going to stay in the motor home. We're not
crazy.''
   The festivities that begin with the morning Rose Parade were to
continue Monday afternoon with the 76th Rose Bowl football game,
between Southern Cal and Michigan, where game time temperatures
should warm up to the low 60s, with a chance of showers at game's
end.
   About 1,100 police officers were on hand. Police last year
reported about 320 arrests before the parade, most for public
drunkenness and fighting.
   Officials in the past several years have routinely predicted 1
million visitors for the parade, and have done so again for 1990.
   Tournament officials said some 350 million television viewers
were expected to tune in worldwide as the parade is broadcast to 90
countries. The Rose Bowl game also will be broadcast live to Europe
for the first time.
   This year's parade theme was ``A World of Harmony,'' and the
marching order included 60 floats, 22 bands, and 275 equestrians,
all led by Sen. John Glenn, D-Ohio, the grand marshal. Glenn was
one of America's first seven astronauts and the first U.S.
astronaut to orbit the Earth.
</TEXT>

</DOC>