<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0098 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1643EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Angola     12-30 0423</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Angola,0438</SECOND>
<HEAD>President Puts Forward Peace Plan, Rejects Cease-fire Proposal</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LISBON, Portugal (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Jose Eduardo dos Santos of
Angola on Saturday offered a new plan for ending his country's
civil war that calls for elections within five years.
   But Eduardo dos Santos said his regime still was committed to
socialism and one-party rule. He also rejected a cease-fire plan
offered by President Mobuto Sese Seko of Zaire, who is trying to
mediate the conflict.
   The Angolan president outlined his proposal in a New Year's
message, portions of which were broadcast on Lisbon radio.
   He called for a cease-fire and for rebels and government
soldiers to allow people and goods to move safely around the
country.
   The proposal includes recognition of the legitimacy of the
current government. It also called for incorporating the rebels of
guerrilla leader Joseph Savimbi into the Angolan army.
   In addition, the president called for the participation of all
Angolans in the affairs of the nation and for legislation on the
right of association.
   He proposed a census of the population and a revision of
election legislation, leading to national elections within five
years.
   But he added that his proposals did not imply abandoning
Angola's socialist vocation or one-party system.
   The two sides have been fighting a civil war since Portugal
granted independence to Angola in 1975.
   Savimbi is backed by the United States and South Africa and the
government is supported by Cuba. Under a peace accord signed
December 1988, Cuba agreed to withdrawn troops from Angola and
South Africa was to relinquish control of Namibia.
   However, the the Angolan government and Savimbi's forces have
been unable to reach a cease-fire accord.
   Mobuto mediated a cease-fire agreement between Savimbi and
Eduardo dos Santos on June 22 in Gbadolite, Zaire, but the truce
collapsed soon afterward. Later talks ended in deadlock with
renewed fighting.
   In his speech, the Angolan president rejected new proposals for
a cease-fire reportedly put forward within the past few days by
Mobuto.
   Eduardo dos Santos said that the proposed cease-fire omitted
provisions agreed upon during the Gbadolite meeting.
   He said the truce verification provisions in the Mobuto proposal
were more suited to conventional rather than guerrilla war.
   Earlier this week, Savimbi said government forces had launched a
major offensive against rebel strongholds in the south.
   The Angolan president made no reference to the reported fighting
in the south, according to the reports reaching Lisbon. But the
Portuguese news agency LUSA earlier quoted Angolan government
officials as denying a major offensive was under way.
</TEXT>

</DOC>