<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0196 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1847EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-AncientMusic     12-20 0623</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ancient Music,0637</SECOND>
<HEAD>Historical Instrument Group Evolved From One Man's Birthday Parties</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHY EYRE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JACKSON, Miss. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   People who march to a different
philosophical drummer in Mississippi can find liberal camaraderie
to the beat of such old instruments as sacbuts, lutes, krummhorns,
cornettos and viola da gambas.
   The Mississippi Academy of Ancient Music Inc. brings in groups
reviving the old inmstruments and period music, providing social
gatherings for many who may not feel comfortable at traditional
Southern black-tie affairs, Academy President Rich McGinnis says.
   The academy formed in 1981, evolving from elaborate Thanksgiving
weekend birthday parties for the late civil rights activist Ernst
Borinski.
   ``It was kind of the one place where liberal Jackson could
meet,'' said McGinnis, a Tougaloo College chemistry professor, of
the Borinski parties.
   Borinski, who died in 1983, was a Polish-German Jew who fled
from Nazi Germany to the United States in 1938 and had taught
sociology at Jackson's historically black Tougaloo College since
1947.
   He is credited with initiating many academic forums across the
state during the 1950s and 1960s where both blacks and whites met
to discuss civil rights issues. The former German judge also served
as undergraduate mentor for a large number of black lawyers
including Reuben Anderson, Mississippi's only black Supreme Court
justice since Reconstruction and the first black to graduate from
the University of Mississippi Law School.
   ``Borinski would always have a birthday party just after
Thanksgiving. It was in a very European style,'' McGinnis recalls.
``He would have a little party for his friends from the college and
so forth, other friends from Jackson. In fact, actually it was a
lot of civil rights people. ...
   ``One time he was at an ACLU auction and he bought an evening of
music from Jean Paul, the St. Andrews (Episcopal) choir master.
Jean Paul wanted to play `Shadow of Your Smile' or something like
that all night on the piano _ but here's a college professor, so he
figures he'd better do something serious. So he brought some music
over that they were doing at St. Andrews.''
   Borinski liked the very old music which Jean Paul played and a
month before his next birthday, he told McGinnis he'd like to have
a similar performance again. McGinnis called on Max Garriott, a
tour guide and professional musician in Vicksburg who is now vice
president of the Mississippi Academy of Ancient Music.
   ``I knew Max had composed some Baroque-style music for parties.
So he wound up composing special birthday music for Borinski _ some
of it adapted from Baroque music and some of it original,''
McGinnis said.
   The parties grew, with 250 to 300 people at Borinski's 80th
birthday in 1981, he said.
   The birthday parties were ``one of the crazy things that led
into all this,'' he said.
   ``And it kind of kept that little group of people together'' who
now support the ancient music academy.
   McGinnis and Garriott said their group is now funded by various
grants from the National Endowment for the Arts, the Mississippi
Arts Commission and other public and private sources. It is host to
performances by about four professional groups each year, with
audiences averaging about 200.
   Most of the performers come from Europe because it is in the
forefront of the growing revival of historically authentic
performances on period instruments, McGinnis said. Jackson is often
the groups' only Southern stop on their American tours.
   ``We present music from 1200 to 1800 _ 600 years worth of music.
And if you go to one concert and don't like it, or if you do like
it, it doesn't mean you'll react the same way to the next one,
which may be completely different music,'' McGinnis says.
</TEXT>

</DOC>