<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0948EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CovenantHouse     12-21 0465</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Covenant House,0479</SECOND>
<HEAD>Father of Accuser Says His Son is a Liar and Thief</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SAMUEL MAULL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The father of a former male prostitute who
accused the Rev. Bruce Ritter of misusing Covenant House money and
engaging in a sexual affair called his son an emotionally troubled
liar and a thief.
   ``And he has a pattern of intentionally hurting people who try
to help him, particularly people who've become a father figure to
him,'' Alton Kite said of his son, 25, who used the name Timothy
Warner when he made the allegations against the founder of Covenant
House, an acclaimed shelter for runaways.
   Kite said at a news conference Wednesday that his son's behavior
is caused by a diagnosed personality disorder and that he has
received psychiatric treatment.
   Kevin Lee Kite's charges of financial improprieties by the Roman
Catholic priest are being investigated by the district attorney's
office.
   Colleen Roche, a spokeswoman for the Manhattan district
attorney's office, had no comment on the elder Kite's remarks.
   The younger Kite, using another alias, was taken in by Covenant
House in New Orleans early last year. He was moved to New York
after he said he feared associates involved in drug running and
prostitution would kill him.
   Earlier this month, Kevin Kite charged that he and Ritter began
a sexual affair shortly after he was given haven here. The former
prostitute said that in return for sex, Ritter put him in an
apartment, enrolled him in a college, bought him clothes, a TV set
and a computer and gave him spending money.
   Ritter and other Covenant House officials denied the sexual
allegations and any financial wrongdoing.
   Kite's father, a junior-college accounting teacher in a town
near Dallas, said he decided to speak out after Covenant House
officials told him about his son's charges against Ritter.
   ``Kevin has caused people great problems and hardship with his
dishonesty before,'' Alton Kite said. ``I would like to help
someone who has suffered because of him.''
   He said he has spent thousands of dollars and suffered
immeasurable heartache trying to compensate his son's victims,
which include friends and neighbors.
   ``We're still paying for it,'' Kite said. ``His mother and I are
both teachers. We have almost no resources left, financially or
emotionally.''
   Kite said he had not spoken to his son since January.
   James Harnett, executive director of Covenant House, said that
the younger Kite ``lied to us about his name, lied to us about his
age, about his hometown and about his life being in danger. We also
know he's a thief _ his father has confirmed that.''
   Covenant House, founded by Ritter in New York, manages 17
shelters with more than 2,000 beds in the United States, Toronto
and Latin America.
</TEXT>

</DOC>