<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0008EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-MailBombs 4thLd-Writethru a0671 12-29 0971</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mail Bombs, 4th Ld - Writethru, a0671,0993</SECOND>
<HEAD>Group Claims Responsibility For Bombings, Threatens Further Attacks</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS grafs 7-10, `He said ..., with 7 grafs to UPDATE with FBI
quote on authenticity of the letter; WAGA's 11 p.m. report, detail that
Ms. Love was raised in suburb where Vance was killed.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARC RICE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An unknown group has claimed responsibility for
mail bombs that killed a federal judge and a civil rights lawyer,
and has threatened future assassinations ``anytime a black man
rapes a white woman,'' authorities said Thursday.
   The claim was made in a letter received Wednesday by WAGA-TV in
Atlanta from a group calling itself Americans for a Competent
Federal Judicial System, said Al Adams, a spokesman for the Postal
Inspection Service in Atlanta.
   The letter was postmarked Dec. 21 in Atlanta. An NAACP official
said his organization received a similar letter on Dec. 22.
   In its 6 p.m. news broadcast, WAGA-TV released excerpts of the
letter from the group, which claimed it ``assassinated Judge Robert
S. Vance and attorney Robert Robinson in reprisal for atrocities
committed on Julie Love,'' a white woman who was robbed, raped and
murdered in Atlanta in 1988.
   ``Two more prominent members of the NAACP shall be assassinated,
using more sophisticated means, as part of the same reprisal,'' the
letter said.
   William L. Hinshaw, special agent in charge of the FBI
investigation in Atlanta, said in a statement Thursday evening that
none of the agencies investigating the mail bombings was familiar
with the group.
   ``We believe that the letter received by WAGA is authentic
because it contained information which has not been made known to
the public and which is known only to someone closely associated
with the construction and mailing of the bombs, and to law
enforcement,'' Hinshaw said.
   He said the letter made a threat against the television station
if it did not air portions of the letter.
   ``Because the letter indicated that additional attacks might be
forthcoming if the TV station did not comply with the stated demand
to read a portion of the letter, we encouraged WAGA to broadcast
that portion of the letter and distribute this information to other
news organizations,'' Hinshaw said.
   WAGA reported at 11 p.m. that the letter told of a secret
meeting the group held Dec. 19 in Montgomery, Ala., after the two
fatal bombings. The station said members from Georgia, Florida and
Alabama gathered ``to draft new orders'' and to go public with
their mission.
   ``Investigators have confirmed to officials of WAGA-TV that the
document may be authentic and related to the recent bombing
attacks,'' Hinshaw said.
   Authorities have been investigating a series of mail bombs that
killed Vance, an 11th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals judge at his
home near Birmingham, Ala., on Dec. 16 and Robinson, a Savannah,
Ga., lawyer two days later.
   The bomb that killed Vance was mailed to his home in Mountain
Brook, Ala., the same suburb where Ms. Love grew up.
   ``Anytime a black man rapes a white woman in Alabama, Florida or
Georgia in the future, Americans for a Competent Federal Judicial
System shall assassinate one federal judge, one attorney and one
officer of the NAACP,'' the letter said.
   The group criticized the 11th Circuit on which Vance served, for
what it called reluctance ``to stress the importance of blacks to
demonstrate civil responsibility.''
   ``This failure created a climate that has spawned an alarming
number of savage acts of violence by black men against white
women,'' the letter said.
   It cited the slaying of Ms. Love, 27, a pre-school fitness
teacher who disappeared July 11, 1988, after her car ran out of
gas. Her remains were found a little over a year later, in a wooded
lot near an inner-city neighborhood.
   Two young black men, Emmanuel Fitzgerald Hammond, 24, and
William Maurice Porter, 20, have been charged in the slaying.
Porter pleaded guilty in November and is expected to testify
against Hammond in his forthcoming trial.
   Sources close to the bomb investigation said last week that
follow-up threatening letters received by targets of the mail bombs
contained references to ``Americans for a Competent Judiciary.'' At
the time, the FBI said it did not know the significance of the
references.
   Two other bombs were safely removed from the 11th Circuit
building in Atlanta and NAACP headquarters in Jacksonville, Fla.
   Investigators believe the attacks may have been carried out by
white racists.
   Earl Shinhoster, Southeastern regional director for the NAACP,
said security precautions were being taken by NAACP workers at the
600 Southeastern branches, 130 of which are in Georgia.
   Shinhoster said he received an unsigned letter at his office
Dec. 22 that used similar language as that in the letter sent to
WAGA. But the television station's letter, Shinhoster said, ``is
much more specific.''
   The typewritten letter to the NAACP, also postmarked in Atlanta,
also mentioned the Americans for a Competent Federal Judicial
System.
   Before being appointed to the federal bench, Vance preached
moderation on racial issues while chairman of the Alabama
Democratic Party. Robinson, a Savannah city alderman, was black and
did legal work for the NAACP.
   A Hagerstown, Md., judge was wounded by a bomb last week, but
investigators said they have all but ruled out a connection to the
other attacks.
   On Aug. 21, an anonymous letter was sent to Jackson, Miss., TV
station WAPT declaring war on the 11th Circuit, authorities said.
The next day, a tear gas canister exploded at the Atlanta office of
the Atlanta NAACP, injuring eight people.
   Vickie Taylor, assignment editor at WAPT, said Thursday that the
August letter was not signed by any group in particular but that
it, too, complained in similar language about partiality in the
judiciary.
   Ms. Taylor said her station has not received any follow-up
letters recently.
</TEXT>

</DOC>