<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0218 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1144EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APArts:Off-Hollywood-Missouri Adv28   12-22 1067</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP Arts: Off-Hollywood-Missouri, Adv 28,1095</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv 28</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Thurs PMs, Dec 28 and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>``White Palace'' Films on Location</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   This is another in an occasional series of
articles on the proliferation of moviemaking outside Hollywood.
Tempted by friendly officials eager to please, filmmakers are
flocking to out-of-state locations, spending billions of dollars
that once would have stayed in California.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>By LORI DODGE</NOTE>
<NOTE>Associated Press Writer</NOTE>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Only a handful of bystanders watched as actor
James Spader strode out of Ed's Sandwich Shop, tossed his scarf
over his right shoulder and turned around to do it over again and
again and again.
   Hollywood comes to midtown St. Louis.
   If it weren't for the fact that the street was blocked off for
the cameras, the sight hardly would have stopped traffic.
   ``It's not like we're setting houses on fire,'' said Spooky
Stevens, the publicist for the movie ``White Palace,'' starring
Spader and Susan Sarandon. ``After 20 minutes of standing out here
and freezing to death, they'll go home.'' Sure enough, most people
didn't stay long, but then St. Louisans have gotten used to having
the ``White Palace'' crew around town.
   In fact, movie-making has become more and more routine all
across Missouri in recent years, thanks in part to the efforts of
the Missouri Film Commission and the St. Louis Film Partnership,
both just a few years old.
   The commission was formed in 1985 as a program of the state's
Department of Economic Development. The partnership was started two
years later. It is funded by the St. Louis County Economic Council,
the city of St. Louis, the St. Louis Convention and Visitors
Commission, the Regional Commerce and Growth Association and the
Regional Cultural and Performing Arts Development Commission.
   The two groups have jumped headfirst into a worldwide tussle for
movie dollars, competing with more established film commissions in
other states, cities and even foreign countries. All try to woo
filmmakers with slick catalogs, location scouting and expert
technical help.
   Still, even though 42 states have film offices and actively
compete for business, California remains the film leader of the
United States, with New York close at its heels.
   Though not always cheaper, it's easier to make a movie outside
California. One-stop, state-controlled film offices are preferred
to California's patchwork approach, where local governments issue
permits with fluctuating fees and have requirements that are 70
years old.
   
   And the long-held belief that Hollywood could re-create anything
from the Tara plantation in ``Gone With the Wind'' to the Las Vegas
Strip in ``One From the Heart'' has been abandoned by filmmakers
who want greater realism.
   ``It's very stale to shoot in the same place,'' said Kate
Arnold, production coordinator for the Missouri Film Commission.
``Authenticity is important these days.''
   It's important for the cities and states that land the films,
too. During the first year of its existence, the film commission
helped bring in $4.1 million to the state's economy. Last year, the
film industry meant $16.5 million to Missouri.
   ``On-location filming is a growing industry that brings dollars
and jobs to the state,'' said Gary Gonder, manager of the
commission. ``These major projects also put the spotlight on
Missouri, which helps our state industrial recruitment efforts,
too.''
   Since May, four features have been filmed in the state:
   _ ``White Palace,'' based on St. Louisan Glenn Savan's first
novel about a yuppie St. Louis advertising executive who, after the
death of his young wife, becomes obsessed with a lusty, older woman
who works in a fast-food restaurant. All but three days are being
filmed in and around St. Louis, and the movie is expected to be
released in the fall of 1990.
   _ ``Mr. and Mrs. Bridge,'' starring Paul Newman and Joanne
Woodward and filmed around Kansas City. Based on two novels, ``Mrs.
Bridge'' and ``Mr. Bridge'' by Evan S. Connell, the story spans 40
years in the lives of a quintessential American couple in Kansas
City. Shooting is completed, and the movie is expected to be
released next summer. Arnold said that while Newman was filming in
Kansas City, the makers of Cordon Negro champagne spent more than
$1 million there to film a commercial with him.
   _ ``Miss Missouri,'' a French production filmed in Kansas City
and surrounding communities. The story is about a former Miss
Missouri who travels to Europe and falls in love with a Frenchman.
Afraid he will discover that she had been married before and has a
child, she flees and returns to her home. The shooting is
completed, and the movie is scheduled to premiere at the Cannes
Film Festival next spring.
   _ ``Detour,'' an independent production directed by Kansas
Citian Wade Williams and filmed mostly in Kansas City. It's a new
version of a 1945 movie about a man who picks up a hitchhiker and
gets involved in murder. The shooting is scheduled to be completed
in December.
   What sold the movie moguls on Missouri?
   In the case of ``White Palace,'' a big reason was the desire to
capture the real flavor of St. Louis, where the story takes place.
``Why try to import natural flavor when you have it right here?''
said Stevens.
   The efforts of the two film commissions paid off, too, she said.
   But sometimes winning the hearts of a movie producer doesn't go
so smoothly.
   The makers of ``Parenthood,'' a story supposedly set in St.
Louis, opted to forfeit realism for warm weather and shoot in
Orlando, Fla. But then again, ``Escape From New York'' was shot in
St. Louis, not New York.
   Janis Rockwell-Strong, executive director of the St. Louis Film
Partnership, set about luring the producers of ``White Palace'' to
St. Louis months before their cameras rolled into town. When she
heard that the movie rights to the book had been bought, she
started firing off letters.
   ``I said I'm from St. Louis, this is a book from St. Louis and I
want you to know we're interested,'' Rockwell-Strong said.
   Over the following months, Rockwell-Strong took dozens of
pictures of various St. Louis neighborhoods and sent them off to
the producers. Then she took them around town when they came to
look for themselves.
   ``I rented the van and we showed them St. Louis,''
Rockwell-Strong said. ``We showed them the various looks.''
   It worked. Filming began Oct. 25.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv PM Thurs Dec. 28</NOTE>

</DOC>