<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1523EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-HUD-Senate     12-17 0637</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-HUD-Senate,620</SECOND>
<HEAD>Panel to Explore `Roots' of Corruption</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM M. WELCH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The scandal-plagued Department of Housing and
Urban Development must establish ``a new level of credibility''
before Congress will back significant new housing programs,
according to the head of a Senate panel that plans a new probe of
the department.
   Sen. Bob Graham, D-Fla., chairman of the newly appointed
subcommittee on HUD investigations, said multibillion-dollar abuses
uncovered at HUD during the Reagan administration are the result of
deep-rooted problems in the way the agency's housing subsidy
programs are structured.
   He said his panel will open hearings soon after Congress
reconvenes in January aimed at finding ways to change federal
housing subsidies for the poor to make influence-peddling and
mismanagement more difficult and more detectible.
   ``It may be that the plunder reached new heights during the
Pierce era, but it is not by any means the first time there have
been scandals similar to those that have come out in the last few
months,'' Graham said, referring to former HUD Secretary Samuel R.
Pierce Jr.
   ``Our approach is going to be one of trying to understand and
legislate on why these programs of HUD have been so subject to
plunder for an extended period of time,'' Graham said.
   ``Clearly, the original objectives of these programs is not
being achieved.''
   Graham's investigative panel was appointed by Senate Banking
Committee Chairman Don Riegle, D-Mich. He commented in a recent
interview in his office during the congressional recess.
   Graham contended that a package of management reforms proposed
by HUD Secretary Jack Kemp and enacted by Congress as one of its
final actions before recessing for the year did not end all the
potential for abuse in housing laws.
   He said developers continue to be able to ``layer'' their
federal subsidies from HUD, combining multifamily housing grants
with other subsidies, including low-income housing tax credits.
   Graham is among the Senate cosponsors of a bill that would
overhaul most housing programs aimed to benefit low-income people,
and which has been pushed strongly by advocates of increased
federal housing aid.
   That legislation did not advance during this year's session, and
Graham suggested it was unlikely to move until his panel makes its
report.
   ``There has to be a new level of credibility in the department
and in the programs before it is likely the Congress will support
significant new housing initiatives,'' Graham said.
   Still, the Senate committee's move to investigate HUD has raised
questions about its timing and motives, since furor over the fraud,
influence-peddling and mismanagement at HUD seems to be fading
after first gaining attention last spring.
   A House subcommittee headed by Rep. Tom Lantos, D-Calif.,
conducted nearly 30 hearings over eight months. It subpoenaed
Pierce and his former aides _ prompting Pierce and three others to
refuse to testify on grounds of self-incrimination. Attorney
General Dick Thornburgh has begun a preliminary inquiry into
whether a special prosecutor should be appointed to investigate
Pierce.
   Graham's probe also comes as Kemp has voiced anger at Congress
for appropriating millions of dollars to specific HUD projects that
the department's own staff says is unnecessary or wasteful.
   Talbot ``Sandy'' D'Alemberte, a Florida attorney hired by Graham
to lead the panel's staff, said the probe would not focus on the
scandal's ``rats,'' as the Lantos probe did, and would not create
the sensation that the House panel did with its parade of witnesses
invoking 5th Amendment rights.
   D'Alemberte is a former dean of the Florida State University Law
School and president-elect of the American Bar Association.
   Graham said his panel would focus instead on ``vulnerability''
to abuse in housing laws and probably would not try to compel
testimony from witnesses who have refused before the Lantos panel.
He said it would conclude hearings in 60 to 90 days.
</TEXT>

</DOC>