<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0198 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 2007EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Panama-Wounded 1stLd-Writethru a0806 12-22 0660</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Wounded, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0806,0675</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soldiers Receive Purple Hearts; Some Being Released</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf to raise reference to number of medals awarded.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos SA3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KELLEY SHANNON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN ANTONIO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soldiers wounded during the U.S. invasion of
Panama received Purple Heart medals and other awards from the Army
Chief of Staff who said he was proud of their ``selfless
commitment.''
   Gen. Carl Vuono, a member of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, handed
out more than 200 military honors and chatted briefly with soldiers
at two military hospitals in San Antonio where those hurt in Panama
are being treated.
   Vuono told the soldiers he spoke with President Bush and, ``He
wanted me to tell you and every other troop down here how proud he
is of each and every one of you for your sacrifice.''
   He gave Purple Hearts to Pvt. Christian Robinson of Federal Way,
Wash.; Pfc. Bobby Miller of Franklin, Pa., and Spec. 4 Albert
Harris, of Jackson, Miss. All three suffered gunshot or shrapnel
wounds in the attack.
   A pool of reporters was only permitted to accompany Vuono to
Wilford Hall Medical Center for the presentation to the three
soldiers. In addition to Wilford Hall, where 112 soldiers were
hospitalized, he visited nearby Brooke Army Medical Center, where
89 more were being treated.
   Military officials would only say that more than 200 awards were
presented, including Purple Hearts, infantry-combat badges and
other awards. The Purple Heart is awarded to members of the armed
forces wounded or killed in action.
   Lt. Col. Johnny Whitaker said 53 servicemen were to be flown out
late Friday afternoon to military bases in Georgia and North
Carolina.
   Two soldiers wounded in Panama were released Friday and another
seven were transferred to other medical centers. Another 21 were
flown in early Friday.
   The commander of a C-141 transport plane that brought the 21
injured servicemen to Kelly Air Force Base early Friday said the
soldiers he transported were in ``good spirits.''
   ``They were glad to be coming back to the United States. We were
glad to bring them,'' Air Force Capt. Peter Debusmann said.
``They're just glad to be coming home, back to the States, and home
for Christmas. And they're worried that their parents are worried
about them.''
   A reception center for families was set up at Fort Sam Houston
in San Antonio. Housing was arranged for the families, and several
San Antonio hotels offered complimentary or discounted rooms to
relatives of the injured.
   Lee Olivara of Cincinnati, brother of wounded Army Staff Sgt.
Louis R. Olivara, said Friday that his brother seemed to be
recovering all right from wounds to the head and chest.
   ``I think he's going to be all right,'' Lee said. He said his
parents, Ralph and Barbara Olivara of Branson, Mo., were expected
in later Friday.
   Lee Olivara said Louis, a member of the 2nd Battalion, 75th
Rangers, was separated from other members in his unit when he was
shot.
   ``He had told me that he saw the sun rise and the sun set and he
woke up in the darkness and said `I'm in trouble. I need to get
some help or I'm going to die.' Then he realized he had the radio
and he made the call.''
   ``He was in and out of consciousness and he was unable to move.''
   When U.S. servicemen are hurt overseas, they usually are brought
to San Antonio, home to four Air Force bases and an Army post.
Wilford Hall is one of the nation's main military hospitals, and
Brooke is a leading burn unit.
   Richard and Linda Turner of DeSoto, Texas, visited their son,
Pvt. Richard Turner Jr., who suffered a concussion when a bullet
grazed his helmet.
   ``He's in very good condition ... shaken up quite a bit but he's
in good condition physically,'' Mrs. Turner said. ``He saw one of
his friends killed. He cried quite a bit.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>