<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0093 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1702EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-SECEnforcement     12-26 0646</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SEC Enforcement,640</SECOND>
<HEAD>SEC Veteran Selected to Head Enforcement; New Fraud Unit Announced</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN CRUTSINGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Economics Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Securities and Exchange Commission Chairman
Richard C. Breeden on Tuesday selected agency veteran William C.
McLucas as the SEC's new head of enforcement and announced creation
of a new fraud unit covering the sale of securities by financial
institutions.
   McLucas, 39, will succeed Gary Lynch, who resigned as SEC
director of enforcement in July after heading some of the agency's
biggest insider trading investigations.
   The enforcement job, which does not require Senate confirmation,
is considered the second most powerful position at the SEC and it
is Breeden's first major appointment since President Bush tapped
him as chairman last summer.
   McLucas, who has worked in the enforcement division for the past
12 years, had been considered one of the front-runners for the
post, but Breeden said he had considered three other SEC attorneys
and several persons from outside the agency before making the final
selection.
   Breeden said the SEC had decided to create a 25-attorney special
unit to investigate overly aggressive sales of securities by
savings and loans and other financial institutions.
   Such sales have been a major focus of congressional hearings
into the activities at Lincoln Savings and Loan Association, the
Irvine, Calif.-based S&amp;L whose failure is expected to be the
biggest in U.S. history, costing taxpayers as much as $2 billion.
   Lincoln Savings' parent company is American Continental Corp.,
headed by Arizona businessman Charles H. Keating Jr. When American
Continental filed for protection under the bankruptcy laws, it left
shareholders and investors holding nearly worthless stocks and
bonds.
   Included in this group were some 22,000 small investors who
purchased nearly $200 million in corporate bonds at Lincoln's 29
Southern California branches. About two-thirds of these investors
were elderly depositors. At congressionaly hearings, some of these
investors testified that they wrongly believed that the bonds they
were purchasing were federally insured.
   Breeden said that the new SEC unit would try to prevent other
financially troubled S&amp;Ls from turning to fradulent practices in a
desperate effort to raise cash.
   ``We intend to see to it that when people are sold securities,
they are provided all the necessary information,'' Breeden said.
   Lynch, who resigned to join a New York law firm, received
widespread praise for a series of big insider trading cases,
beginning with the exposure of stockbroker Dennis Levine. Lynch
also spearheaded cases that resulted in a $100 million settlement
with speculator Ivan Boesky and a record $650 million settlement of
a massive civil fraud cause with junk bond-giant Drexel Burnham
Lambert Inc.
   In May 1986, the SEC filed charges against Levine, whose
cooperation led to Boesky, who in turn implicated Drexel Burnham in
the largest securities fraud case ever brought by the government.
   Lynch took over the enforcement division in 1985 at a time of
turmoil after his predecessor, John Fedders, stepped down amid
allegations that he beat his wife.
   Lynch was credited with restoring morale at the agency. The
scandals in recent years have forced Wall Street's big brokerage
houses to re-evaluate their compliance and ethics codes and led
Congress to increase the penalties for insider trading.
   At the news conference, Breeden noted that Congress has boosted
the SEC budget by almost 20 percent this year to $168 million,
providing enough new money to hire an additional 100 lawyers.
   He said it was important for the SEC to police the securities
industry in such a way that individual investors will have renewed
confidence. Individual investors have left the market in droves in
recent years, partly out of fears raised by the huge gyrations in
stock prices that occurred in October of 1987 and 1989.
   During the 1970s, the SEC's enforcement division first gained
attention under Stanley Sporkin for pursuing corporations that
maintained political slush funds and paid bribes to win overseas
business.
</TEXT>

</DOC>