<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0926EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Korea-Students     12-18 0468</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Korea-Students,0482</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hundreds Of Students Battle Riot Police</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL SHIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of students hurling firebombs
and rocks fought riot police in Seoul and two other cities today to
protest the arrest of a fugitive radical student leader.
   Fierce fighting broke out on the streets around campuses after
Im Chong-suk, 23, and five student bodyguards were overpowered and
arrested by 20 plainclothes police at a Seoul university earlier in
the day.
   Police said there had been arrests in the clashes but had no
figures. At least one student suffered serious burns in a clash at
Seoul's Hanyang University and was hospitalized.
   Im has been on the police wanted list since March with a reward
equivalent to $7,400 offered for information leading to his arrest.
He is head of the outlawed National Council of Student
Representatives, or Chondaehyop.
   Police said Im would be charged with violations of the National
Security Law governing sedition and communist activity. Im told
reporters at police headquarters he had planned to discuss Korean
unification in a scheduled television interview when he was
apprehended. The interview was not held.
   The most serious fighting of the day was reported in the
southern city of Kwangju, where about 800 students, hurling
hundreds of firebombs, battled police for two hours around Chosun
University.
   ``Release Im Chong-suk!'' the state television, KBS, quoted
students as shouting as they charged about 1,000 riot police.
   KBS showed scenes of columns of protesters with masks and
hankerchiefs over their faces attacking police, who fired tear gas.
   The tear gas drifted onto the Kwangju campuses of four middle
and high schools in the area, forcing them to temporarily suspend
classes, KBS said.
   About 400 students fought riot police with firebombs and rocks
for an hour in front of the main gates of Hanyang University, where
Im is a senior. Police hurled rocks back at the students.
   In the southern port city of Pusan, groups of up to 20 students
stormed six regional offices of an opposition party, demanding Im's
release and protesting a compromise Saturday between ruling and
opposition parties aimed at ending the long dispute over corruption
and misdeeds under former President Chun Doo-hwan. Students want
Chun arrested and punished.
   Meanwhile, police detained about 120 students who staged street
demonstrations near a courthouse where a woman student and a
Catholic priest are on trial for making illegal trips to Communist
North Korea.
   ``Free the flower of unification!'' and ``Abolish national
security laws!'' the students shouted as they were loaded into
police buses. Most were released later with warnings, police said.
   Inside the courtroom, Im Su-kyong, 20, was in the fourth day of
her trial on charges of violating the National Security Law for
visiting North Korea without government authorization.
   The two Ims are unrelated.
</TEXT>

</DOC>