<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0206EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Romania-Students     12-30 0567</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Students,0585</SECOND>
<HEAD>Students Vow to Retrun to Streets if Leaders Stray From Reforms</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERRY LEONARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Student demonstrators who helped
topple Communist dictator Nicolae Ceausescu say they will take to
the streets again if the provisional government strays from the
path of democracy.
   Students were among the anti-government protesters who shouted
down Ceausescu at an official rally in Palace Square on Dec. 21,
and they were among those killed when security forces opened fire.
   Now in the days following the ouster and execution of Ceausescu,
the students say they have an obligation to those who have fallen
to guarantee the reforms.
   ``We don't have any weapons but to protest. We can do nothing
but strike,'' said Diana Ghionea, an education student and veteran
of the bloody demonstrations that helped trigger the revolution.
   ``We have two representatives in the provisional government. If
they (the others) don't listen to them we will be organizing a
protest and a strike,'' said Diana Voicu, another young veteran.
   Student demonstrations are new to a country where Ceausescu
crushed dissent movements during his autocratic 24-year rule.
   ``It's nobility around here to be able to say you were in the
square on Thursday,'' said Ms. Ghionea, referring to the day they
shouted down the dictator.
   ``I was almost killed three times over that weekend but my
friends saved me, pulling me aside in the shooting,'' she said.
   Older Romanians praise the students for their courage, telling
reporters that nothing would have started, would have been
possible, without the students.
   But the students worry that the people will settle for too
little. They hope for the best from the self-proclaimed provisional
government but intend to hold it to its promise of free elections
and national reform.
   ``There is change now. The people are so happy to get rid of
Ceausescu that they think anything will be better,'' said Ms.
Ghionea.
   ``We didn't have food until now, and now we have TV. We had only
two hours of TV now we have eight. The old people think this is
freedom. They think, `What do the students want?' This is not
freedom.''
   Other students at the university nodded approval as the young
women told reporters that the students have a debt to all of those
who died in overthrowing the dictatorship.
   The students met Thursday to form the Democratic Student League,
a group they say will push for educational reform and seek
educational assistance from abroad for the university.
   Ms. Ghionea and Ms. Voicu insisted the league would be
apolitical, seeking only to improve the educational system. It
seeks to shorten the hours in class from 10 to eight a day, to
raise education standards, to end political interference in the
curriculum and end compulsory military training for women.
   ``Ceausescu wanted to keep us in class so long that we would not
have time to meet and to think,'' said Ms. Voicu.
   The students said they will not allow the league to become an
instrument of their political dissent because educational reforms
are so vital.
   But they emphasize that does not mean the students will not
become political, that they will not take to the streets again to
try to preserve their vision of the revolution.
   Ms. Ghionea echoes the voices of so many other, older Romanians.
   ``We can't go back again,'' she says. ``We can't.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>