<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0113 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1447EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-NIHRules     12-29 0296</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-NIH Rules,280</SECOND>
<HEAD>NIH Scrapping Conflict-of-Interest Guidelines</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH MESCE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The National Institutes of Health is scrapping
proposed conflict-of-interest guidelines that stirred controversy
among scientists and will go back to the drawing boards to draft
new options, officials said Friday.
   The guidelines proposed for the federal research agency last
September were an attempt to ensure the integrity of
government-funded projects by preventing researchers from having a
financial interest in the outcome of their work.
   But many scientists said the proposal would hamper efforts to
turn academic research into commercial products and could cost the
United States its competitive edge in biomedical research.
   The proposal suggested that NIH grant recipients disclose their
and their familiy's financial interests and said government-funded
researchers should have no equity interest in any company that
would benefit from their research. It also proposed barring
researchers from sharing information with companies until it is
publicly available.
   NIH received more than 600 comments on the proposal, said NIH
spokeswoman Ann Thomas.
   Dr. Louis Sullivan, secretary of the Department of Health and
Human Services, said Friday that he has asked NIH to submit to him
new options ``that properly treat potential abuse while keeping the
research process free of unnecessary burdens and disincentives.''
   ``While there is a crucial need to protect against possible
abuses in the research system, it is also important that we not
impose on our scientific community regulatory burdens which may be
unnecessary or counterproductive,'' Sullivan said.
   ``Likewise, it is important that we not unnecessarily jeopardize
the international leadership position we have built up through
years of cooperative government and private investment,'' he said.
   He said any changes will be implemented through the formal
regulatory process, rather than as guidelines as the original
proposal suggested.
</TEXT>

</DOC>