<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0142 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1740EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-BushText 1stAdd   12-18 0773</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Bush Text, 1st Add,a0650,640</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHN: good year.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Q: You mentioned _ noted that you were successful on no new
taxes last year. How should we read your lips for next year? Are
you taking the same vow and is it as irreversible and irrevocable
as it was this year?
   BUSH: As far as I'm concerned, it is. But I can say that I kept
my promise to the American people, and I want to continue keeping
it.
   Q: Mr. President, I think on the minds of everyone today in
terms of headline news is Panama. Do you _
   BUSH: It's certainly on my mind as a headline news, I'll tell
you.
   Q: Well, you said these were the things on your mind, so it _
   BUSH: No, but you're _ I'm glad you raised it, because if you
hadn't, I had intended to, because it was clearly on my mind.
   Q: What are you going to do? Is it _ I'm not going to say what
are you going to do.
   BUSH: No, but let me just say one thing and put it into context.
One of the frustrations that I've had during this year is that _ is
the whole Panama situation _ an enormous frustration. I see a
little more reason to be hopeful in Nicaragua, although I have some
serious concerns now about how free and fair those elections are
going to be, having talked to Bob Beckel and Mary Matalin in that
thing. But, no, I'm glad you brought it up, Helen, because it's an
enormous frustration to me that the democratic system that was
voted on in Panama was totally put down by force.
   Q: What are your options _
   Q: What can you do about it? I mean, you have exhausted a lot of
_
   BUSH: For one, I can tell you how strongly I feel about it,
which I've just done. And, two, review whatever actions might be
available. And three, not discuss what they might be.
   Q: Well, do you feel you do have options?
   BUSH: I think a president _ all presidents have options, but
they don't discuss what they might be.
   Q: Including military options?
   BUSH: Presidents have options, but they don't discuss what they
might be.
   Q: Well, does the murder of this officer _ American officer down
there over the weekend _ does that show that actually the United
States is pretty powerless to do anything in Panama _ that they can
do this and get away with it?
   BUSH: It's an enormous outrage and a matter of enormous concern
to this President.
   Q: Is there anything you can do about it?
   BUSH: It's an enormous outrage and of tremendous concern to this
President, and I would refer you to the previous question and
answer.
   Q: Mr. President, on the budget, you say you're nearing the end
of the budget process. But it seems to me you want to stay in
concrete on most of the things that were a part of the Cold War.
You want the nuclear bombs in the air 24 hours a day and you don't
seem to want to retreat. Who's the enemy?
   BUSH: Helen, we`re having a massive re-evaluation of intentions,
as well as military threat. And we have set a very aggressive arms
control agenda, and I'd like to see us take those steps. And I
think the Soviets want to move forward in these areas of chemical
reduction, or elimination, START, CFE. So let's go forward with our
eyes open and do that. And I think that's exactly what Mr.
Gorbachev wants to do. And Mr. Gorbachev _ they still have an
enormous deployment of troops against U.S. forces, NATO forces.
They still have an enormous arsenal and modernized nuclear weapons.
But the steps we're taking can make the determination as to what
the threat remains for the '90s. And so I will not take any naive
unilateral action, but I'm determined to move forward on a sensible
program of evaluation, and on a sensible program of arms reduction,
which includes conventional forces.
   Q: So there won't be any big cuts this year?
   BUSH: You saw the numbered bandied about out there, and I'll
stand by that number, although, I can't confirm exactly what the
final figure is going to be, because we're right down to the wire
right now. But if people are looking for us to go up there with
massive cuts now, I would say to them, look, put your energies on
helping us get the kinds of agreements that will enable everybody
to recommend massive cuts.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>