<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1304EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-McDonalds-Checks     12-30 0387</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-McDonalds-Checks,0399</SECOND>
<HEAD>No More Checks Accepted For That $2.88 Burger-And-Fries Bill</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MINNEAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   McDonald's customers in Minnesota are losing
a privilege dating from a kinder, gentler time that is unheard-of
for fast-food customers in most states: paying for their burger and
fries with a personal check.
   Starting Monday, company-owned outlets of the fast-food chain
throughout the state will stop accepting checks. But it's not bad
checks, it's the high cost of living that's to blame.
   The decision was prompted by the mounting cost of check
processing, said Steve Kopel, operations manager for McDonald's
regional office in Bloomington.
   ``We're a high-volume, penny-profit business,'' he said.
Processing can cost 6 to 10 cents, depending on where the bank is
located, and while losses from bad checks are part of the problem,
``we really haven't seen a great increase,'' he said.
   Company officials said the idea of paying by check for a $3 Big
Mac meal has been unheard-of in other states. Other national
fast-food retailers said Minnesota is one of the few states where
they will take checks.
   Though company-owned McDonald's are nixing checks, restaurants
operated by independent licensees can set their own check policies,
said Kopel. Some already have banned them, he said.
   Consumer reaction to the policy will be closely monitored by
company executives through January. ``We're going to certainly
apply some common sense to this,'' Kopel said.
   Some of McDonald's competition, such as the company-owned White
Castle and Burger King restaurants, have long refused to accept
checks, even in Minnesota. Company-owned Taco Bells in Minnesota
recently quit taking checks.
   Minnesota remains one of the few places in the country where
other major fast food chains, such as Kentucky Fried Chicken and
Arby's, continue to accept them.
   ``The problem here is if you don't accept checks, people will
walk away,'' said Judy Cook, president of the Minnesota Retail
Merchants Association. Minnesotans assume it's their right to pay
by check rather than cash, even for the smallest amount, she said.
   By contrast, she said, ``people on the East and West coasts
don't write checks for under $10.''
   ``It may be that Minnesota is a more trusting community,'' Cook
added.
   But not everyone can be trusted. Some merchants complain that
the number of worthless checks coming their way has increased over
the past few years, she said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>