<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0218 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1332EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--IndianFood Adv31-2Takes   12-18 0996</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Indian Food, Adv 31-2 Takes,1019</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 31</HEAD>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<HEAD>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 4 b&amp;w photos.
ColorFoto subscribers get 3 35mm slides.)</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   You're probably aware of the origins of corn,
squash and beans. But did you know American Indians also gave us
blue corn tortillas, fried squash blossoms and black bean soup?
Native American dishes are showing up on some of the trendiest
menus in the country. If you ask Barrie Kavasch, a longtime expert
on America's oldest ethnic cuisine, it's about time.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By NANCY SHULINS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Newsfeatures Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRIDGEWATER, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Barrie Kavasch's Saturday night dinner
parties in the mid-'60s were notorious among her neighbors.
   At a time when most suburbanites were ``Mastering the Art of
French Cooking,'' with boeuf bourguignon and chocolate mousse, the
unassuming housewife and mother of two was stunning guests with
dandelion fritters and smoked eel stew.
   While many Americans were cooking French, Kavasch was cooking
American. Native American. Her platters of fried squash blossoms,
nasturtium salad and conch stew ``could utterly astonish even the
most sophisticated people,'' she recalls.
   Not anymore.
   Today, many of the same foods that once confounded Barrie
Kavasch's neighbors are showing up on some of the trendiest menus
at some of the hottest restaurants in the country.
   And Kavasch is in great demand as a teacher and lecturer; she's
as apt to be baking pumpkins and frying cornpones at museums,
universities and cooking schools as in her Bridgewater kitchen.
   In February, she'll team up with a chef at the Harvard Club in
New York to produce a five-course American Indian dinner for 300
distinguished guests. In May, she'll prepare a similar banquet for
culinary historians in Boston.
   Having spent much of her life a somewhat solitary booster of
American Indian foods, Kavasch, who is not of Indian heritage,
suddenly finds herself with lots of company. Though still far from
mainstream, Indian foods are enjoying a renaissance amid a national
passion for Southwestern and Cajun dishes and a growing concern
over diet and health.
   ``There's more acceptance that people should eat high
carbohydrates, more grains and more vegetables,'' says Mark Miller,
owner and chef at the much-heralded Coyote Cafe in Santa Fe, N.M.
   ``If you look at diets made up of grains and complex
carbohydrates that will take us right back into Indian food,'' adds
Miller, whose Indian-influenced creations include wild tumbleweeds
with grilled venison and dried cherry-chili sauce. His new
cookbook, ``Coyote Cafe,'' due out in January, is sprinkled with
American Indian legends and poetry.
   At the Mansion on Turtle Creek in Dallas, another culinary
landmark, chef Dean Fearing's offerings include grilled game with
cornpones and wild rice sauce, and Texas antelope stew on posole
tortillas.
   At Arizona 206 in New York, former executive chef Brendan Walsh
had diners lining up for a taste of the Southwest in the Big Apple,
with corn flour pastas and pumpkin seed sauces.
   ``Southwestern food _ especially New Mexican food _ is probably
60 percent Indian-influenced and 40 percent Spanish,'' says Jane
Butel, a former New Mexico home economist whose ``Tex-Mex
Cookbook'' helped launch the craze a decade ago.
   While most people are quick to recognize the Spanish element,
they are far less aware of the Indian influence, adds Butel, who
recently opened a traditional New Mexican restaurant, Pecos River
Cafe, in New York.
   That's not surprising, says Jack Weatherford, an associate
professor of anthropology at Macalester College in St. Paul, Minn.
``There's a tendency to want to emphasize European heritage and
minimize native heritage,'' he says.
   ``European food is prestige food. We simply don't value American
Indian foods enough,'' adds Weatherford, who traced Indian
contributions to medicine, agriculture, cooking and other areas of
modern life. His resulting book, ``Indian Givers,'' will be
published by Ballantine Books in January.
   While most people are aware of the origins of corn, beans,
squash, pumpkin and turkey, they tend not to know Indians also gave
the world guacamole, tomatoes, potatoes, tortillas, tacos and
tamales, Weatherford says.
   Few people think about Indians while eating lobster, oysters,
scallops, clams and roe, not to mention smoked salmon, fried
catfish and clam chowder. Barbecue was an Indian invention, as were
tomato sauce, clambakes, Brunswick stew, crab cakes, baked beans,
maple syrup, baked apples and cranberry sauce.
   ``Most regional American cuisines stand on an Indian base,''
says Weatherford. Consider the liberal use of maple syrup, seafood
and beans in the Northeast; hominy, grits, sweet potatoes and
pecans in the South; and red beans, cayenne pepper, file and
crayfish in Cajun and creole dishes.
   Though the latter are often associated more with French than
Indian cooks, he says, ``these foods are no more French than tacos
and tamales are Spanish. Creole and Cajun foods came to us via the
mixture of people who incorporated French, blacks and Indians into
their heritage. The resulting food is primarily Indian, secondarily
black, and only tangentially French.''
   Sixty percent of foods grown in the world today came from North
and South American Indians, Weatherford says. ``The American Indian
larder contained a tremendous variety of foods. The Indians of the
Andes produced more types of crops than all the farmers of Europe
and Asia combined.
   ``And a recent report by the Academy of Sciences identified 70
fruits, vegetables and grains we never use in this country that
would be appropriate for use.''
   Quinoa, an ancient grain that once grew wild in North America,
is being reintroduced. With the highest protein content of any
grain, quinoa, now grown experimentally in the Rockies, can be used
as a wheat substitute for flour, pasta and other products.
   Though slightly less nutritious, amaranth, also grown in the
West, is still higher in protein than all European grains, and is
being sold ground or as a cereal. Chef Miller recently experimented
with amaranth in making tamales and found them ``earthier, with a
stronger grain flavor'' than their corn counterparts.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>