<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0086 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1722EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ColdRdp 1stLd-Writethru a0578 12-25 0956</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cold Rdp, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0578,0977</SECOND>
<HEAD>Light Snow Dusts Cold-Ravaged South</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 8th graf, ``The temperatures,'' with 3 grafs to UPDATE
with all-time record low, other records, ice blocks Washington re-enactment;
SUBS 18th graf, ``A water crisis,'' with 3 grafs to UPDATE with Charleston
water, ice-jam flood.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WLN1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROGER PETTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   More snow fell Monday on the frozen Deep South, where
Wilmington, N.C., had its most Christmas snow on record, and
Florida utilities asked people to turn off holiday decorations to
save electricity for heat.
   Citrus growers in Florida and southern Texas inspected frost
damage in their groves.
   Frozen rivers and pipes interfered with water supplies in some
southern cities, and the Carolinas dug out after a rare December
blizzard.
   Temperatures turned balmy across much of the Plains in the wake
of last week's surge of Arctic air that broke hundreds of low
temperature records. Nebraska warmed into the 40s and it was the
first time in 10 days that Indiana had no readings at or near zero,
the weather service said. But a new wave of cold began pushing
southward into Minnesota with wind chills of about 40 below zero.
   Sections of Georgia, northern Florida and northern Alabama got a
dusting of snow on Christmas, and light snow even was reported
along the coast of the Gulf of Mexico at Mobile, Ala.
   It was only the sixth time since 1878 that Atlanta got holiday
snow, and the first Christmas snow in Mobile since record-keeping
began in 1871.
   However, temperatures began to ease. At Birmingham, Ala., the
temperature rose to 33 degrees shortly before noon _ the first time
in 92 hours the mercury had been above freezing. Temperatures also
eased in Florida, but the day started with a record of 30 degrees
in Miami.
   The temperature fell to an all-time record low of zero at the
airport for Wilmington, N.C., which was partly paralyzed by the
cold and the record 15 inches of snow that fell Sunday. The
previous all-time low at Wilmington of 5 above had stood since
February 1899.
   Other record lows Monday, all in Florida, were 29 at Fort
Lauderdale, 46 at Key West, and a record-tying 33 at Miami Beach,
the National Weather Service reported, a far cry from last week
when temperatures hit record lows in more than 100 cities a day.
Monday's low for the Lower 48 states was 17 degrees below zero at
Houlton, Maine.
   Elsewhere, the cold prevented the annual re-enactment of George
Washington's famous Revolutionary War crossing of the Delaware
River to capture British troops at Trenton, N.J. ``We couldn't get
our four boats into the river because it was a sheet of ice,'' said
James Gallagher, who has played the role of Washington since 1985.
   Airports remained closed at Wilmington and at Myrtle Beach, S.C.
   Temperatures warmed up a few degrees in South Carolina, but on
the north coast, which received well over a foot of snow in places,
melting snow was expected to re-freeze on roads and make driving
treacherous during the night.
   Residents of Florida contended with rotating brownouts, and in
some instances blackouts, as utilities tried to keep up with demand
for electricity.
   Some people went without power for as long as 12 hours. ``You
can't heat a house, cook a meal or take a shower,'' said Ellen
Kirschner of Pinellas County.
   Mike Mahoney, spokesman for Tampa Electric Co., appealed Monday
to families in a six-county area to forgo Christmas tree lights to
save energy.
   Two of North Carolina's three main natural gas companies asked
consumers to turn down their heat Monday to ease demand on tight
supplies.
   ``We are drawing from all of our emergency supply sources,''
said Charles Zeigler, chairman and president of Public Service Co.
of North Carolina.
   Numerous burst water pipes were reported because of the cold,
and water pressure was low partly from people letting water run to
avoid frozen pipes.
   ``We've got low pressure all over the city because of the broken
lines and people can't conserve,'' said John von Sprecken, head of
the Mobile, Ala., water system.
   ``We probably have thousands of people with busted pipes. We've
shut off literally hundreds,'' Charleston Commissioners of Public
Works Manager Steve Kinard said Monday.
   A water crisis continued at Jackson, Miss., where five days of
cold had frozen the Pearl River, the city's source of water. City
and private crews worked to break ice around the municipal water
plant. The National Guard was called out Sunday to haul water to
the city.
   Water stood up to 2 feet deep in parts of Marshall, N.C., after
ice jammed at a dam, backing up the French Broad River.
   It was the second straight day of cold ravaging Florida's $3.5
billion citrus crop. Wind was light Christmas eve, meaning groves
that escaped unharmed the previous night suffered freeze damage.
Stiffer wind prevents frost from settling on the fruit.
   ``Apparently there is a lot of iced fruit,'' said Dick Whalley,
a spokesman for Florida Citrus Mutual, the state's big grower
cooperative.
   But strawberries fared better, said Roy Parke of Parkesdale
Farms, a berry farmer in Plant City, Fla. A lack of wind allows
irrigation systems to build an even layer of ice on fragile plants
to hold them at 32 degrees. Wind scatters the water from
sprinklers, allowing lower temperatures to get to the plants.
   ``We got good ice cover and I figure I'll be able to save 80
percent,'' Parke said Monday.
   At Harlingen, Texas, citrus grower Joe Kutzenberger said no
fruit that wasn't harvested before Friday and Saturday's cold can
be salvaged.
   ``It appears to me even the canneries wouldn't accept it because
the fruit has been frozen so bad,'' Kutzenberger said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>