<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0126 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 2236EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Egypt-Syria     12-23 0278</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Egypt-Syria,0286</SECOND>
<HEAD>Egypt, Syria To Be Reconciled</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DALIA BALIGH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAIRO, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A top-level Syrian envoy said Saturday the
presidents of Egypt and Syria will soon meet to put an end to a
12-year rift.
   The emissary, Vice President Abdel-Halim Khaddam, strongly
indicated after talks with President Hosni Mubarak that the two
countries will resume diplomatic relations.
   Khaddam, the highest ranking Syrian official to visit Egypt
since 1977, arrived Saturday with what he called ``a message of
amity and brotherhood'' from President Hafez Assad to the Egyptian
leader.
   ``The coming meeting between the two presidents will lead to
practical and concrete results in rectifying the status of
Egyptian-Syrian relations,'' Khaddam told reporters after
conferring privately with Mubarak for about 1{ hours.
   Asked specifically whether the summit would bring restored
diplomatic ties, Khaddam said: ``When we speak about rectifying the
status of relations, we mean a comprehensive approach, not a narrow
one.''
   Egypt and Syria together fought Israel in the 1973 Middle East
war, but Syria broke ties four years later in response to
then-President Anwar Sadat's historic visit to Jerusalem in
November 1977, which led to a peace treaty.
   Syria was only one of 17 Arab states that broke ties with Egypt
over its peace initiative with Israel. All but Syria and Libya have
since renewed ties.
   Khaddam said the summit ``will be in the very near future.'' He
said Assad and Mubarak would decide where and when to meet.
   Egyptian-Libyan relations improved considerably this year
without full diplomatic reconciliation. Mubarak and Libyan leader
Moammar Gadhafi have met three times since October and have agreed
on broad economic cooperation between their countries.
</TEXT>

</DOC>