<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1122EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Speeding     12-25 0556</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Speeding,0575</SECOND>
<HEAD>Speeder Gets His $11,000 Ticket Reduced, Still Says System is Fair</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MATTI HUUHTANEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HELSINKI, Finland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 41-year-old businessman fought for
four months to get his $11,400 speeding fine reduced to $1,050, but
he still says Finland's traditional system of punishment based on a
person's wealth is fair.
   Police in August nabbed Rainer Rooth for driving his BMW 75 mph
in a 50 mph zone, and tax authorities set the $11,400 fine based on
his 1987 income.
   Penalties for exceeding the speed limit by more than 10 mph are
based on what the offender says is his annual income. The minimum
is $5.
   The principle of paying fines according to earnings has been
around for years, and Finns say the fine is the fairest way to
punish offenders. Even Rooth, who may have received the highest
fine on record, doesn't argue with it.
   ``I think the system is just, but there has to be some kind of
limit,'' said Rooth, who built a tourist attaction based on the
Wild West.
   When ticketed, Rooth told police he was getting no income from
his business, which was heavily in debt.
   The case went to the tax authorities, who ruled that Rooth's
earnings in 1987 was roughly $300,000 and set the fine at $11,400.
Rooth protested, and the case was twice adjourned.
   ``I didn't earn that kind of money when the offense occurred,''
Rooth said in an interview.
   On Wednesday, the court reduced the fine to $1,050. Rooth
estimated he paid at least $3,000 with legal costs included.
   ``I tell you, the taxman was after me, it's as simple as that.
The new fine is still not right, but I can live with it. Another
appeal would probably cost just as much,'' he said.
   Kauko Aromaa, a Justice Minstry researcher, said the system of
fines based on income was a ``just way to punish people.''
   The ``day-fine'' is at most one-third of an offender's daily
income based, on gross annual earnings. The number of day-fines an
offender is given is determined by the severity of the offense.
Rooth was given 27 day-fines for his high-speed driving.
   In 1987, the day-fine system was used in 350,000 cases ranging
from traffic offenses, burglaries, drunken driving, embezzlement
and assault.
   Police admit the system has flaws.
   ``Sure, we know that most of those we stop in a speed trap lie
about their pay, but we can't check them all. But mostly, if they
make it credible enough, we won't doubt it,'' said Antti Kivela,
duty officer at the Helsinki Traffic Police Department.
   ``Obviously, when someone who drives a big BMW says he doesn't
have a source of income we are going to suspect something _ that
guy was asking for it,'' Kivela said of Rooth.
   Kivela said that the average speeding fine around Helsinki is
from $120 to $240, but $1,000 fines were not uncommon.
   In a widely publicized case last year, a northern court rejected
as too low the fine given to Matti Ahde, who was then Parliament
speaker.
   A quick check found that he lied about his income.
   ``Sure there's a loophole in the system. It is almost as if we
are challenging people to give wrong information because it's not a
crime to lie about your income to the police,'' said Aromaa.
</TEXT>

</DOC>