<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0183 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 2038EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-YE--Yearin'89 4thLd-Writethru b0625-b0626 12-29 1025</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-YE--Year in '89, 4th Ld-Writethru, b0625-b0626,1057</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv00</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release in Year-End Editions</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: UPDATES graf 11, ``Even Romania...,'' to include Ceausescu execution.</HEAD>
<HEAD>So Much History in Such a Small Package</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhotos, Graphics</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MITCHELL LANDSBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The wind blew and the earth shook. And the wall came down.
   There it is: 1989 in review. A year of disasters that rivaled
Old Testament plagues, of triumphs that challenged credulity _ a
year that led people, again and again, to the same words: ``I never
thought I'd see the day.''
   For a while, it seemed that this would be the Year of the Oil
Spill. Then the Year of the Hurricane. Then the Year of the
Earthquake.
   But the last turbulent year of the decade will be remembered,
finally, as the year the Iron Curtain lifted.
   Twenty-six years earlier, John F. Kennedy had stood before the
Berlin Wall and said of free citizens everywhere: ``Let them come
to Berlin.'' In 1989, they came _ and from the least imaginable
direction. They came from the East.
   ``What joy!'' a West Berliner exclaimed; and people from East
and West Berlin danced and laughed and hugged atop a wall that no
longer divided them.
   ``We live in exciting times,'' President Bush observed. ``The
rapidity of change is mind-boggling.''
   Indeed it was.
   In Poland, the Solidarity trade union was illegal at the
beginning of the year; it had ousted the Communist government by
the end. Then came Hungary, East Germany, Czechoslovakia: One by
one, Eastern Europe's ruling Communist parties followed Poland's
lead and agreed to step aside and allow democratic, multi-party
elections.
   Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev had loosed the shackles
that once bound Eastern Europe. And after a seasick summit with
Bush in the tempestuous Mediterranean, he declared that the Cold
War was over.
   Even Romania, among the most stalwart of the old-line Communist
states, was overwhelmed by democratic fervor that drove President
Nicolae Ceausescu from his palace and ultimately to his death
before a firing squad.
   Images of Eastern Europe's peaceful revolution will stick in the
memory for a long time, but so will a sadder picture: a lone man
standing before a phalanx of tanks near Beijing's Tiananmen Square.
   It had been a hopeful spring in the square, where tens of
thousands of students demonstrated daily to demand democratic
change. Military officers at first balked at suppressing the
protesters _ 100 officers signed a statement saying the army ``will
never shoot the people.'' But, on June 3, the army began shooting
the people.
   The death toll may never be known. Estimates ranged from 300 to
3,000.
   Brute force blocked democracy in China, but U.S. troops
forcefully imposed it in Panama, where an invasion just before
Christmas ousted the dictatorship of Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega
and installed an elected president.
   On a smaller scale, too, it was a year of tumultuous transition.
   The TV lights went out for televangelist Jim Bakker, who got a
45-year prison term for conspiracy and fraud.
   Zsa Zsa Gabor finally starred in a film that everyone remembers
_ her trial on cop-slapping charges. She played Beverly Hills'
official court jester, and was rewarded with a conviction and jail
term.
   Leona Helmsley was the queen of a hotel empire, but she was
mocked and reviled outside her kingdom and was sentenced to four
years in prison for tax evasion.
   Pete Rose became as closely linked with betting as batting, and
agreed to a lifetime suspension from the game to which he'd devoted
his life.
   John Tower, President Bush's choice as secretary of defense,
lost the nomination and a sizable chunk of his reputation when he
was pilloried as a liquor-tippling ``party animal.''
   House Speaker Jim Wright resigned in a furor over outside
income; Tom Foley took his place.
   Time merged with Warner. Sony merged with Columbia. Mike Tyson
split with Robin Givens.
   The year's obituaries noted the passing of both famous and
infamous:
   Irving Berlin and Bette Davis, Lucille Ball, Robert Penn Warren,
Salvador Dali, Vladimir Horowitz, Herbert von Karajan, Laurence
Olivier, Mel Blanc.
   Ferdinand Marcos, Ayatollah Khomeini, Emperor Hirohito. Abbie
Hoffman. Rep. Claude Pepper.
   Sugar Ray Robinson, A. Bartlett Giamatti. Secretariat.
   Mass murderer Ted Bundy was put to death; other killers died at
their own hands. They included Patrick Purdy, who killed five
schoolchildren in Stockton, Calif.; Joseph Wesbecker, who killed
eight people in a printing plant in Louisville, Ky.; and Marc
Lepine, who systematically gunned down 14 female engineering
students in Montreal.
   Ramon Salcido allegedly killed his wife, two daughters, and four
other people near Santa Rosa, Calif., before fleeing to Mexico. He
was captured five days later and awaits trial in California.
   More than 20,000 Americans died of AIDS. Scientists continued
searching for a vaccine and a cure, and the government tried to
find new ways to make experimental drugs available more quickly.
   People worried about homelessness and hunger, abortion and child
care, flag-burning and the ``greenhouse effect.''
   The most-honored movie of the year _ ``Rain Man'' _ suggested
that the ``Me Decade'' ethic might be softening. It was the story
of a fast-talking wheeler-dealer from Southern California who found
some measure of humanity in caring for his autistic brother.
   Then again, the Grammy Award for best song went to Bobby
McFerrin's ``Don't Worry, Be Happy.''
   Historically speaking, the year began on a chilly, cloudy day in
January when George Bush took the oath of office as the 41st
president of the United States.
   ``A new breeze is blowing,'' he declared in his inaugural
address, ``and a nation refreshed by freedom stands ready to push
on: There is new ground to be broken, and new action to be taken.''
   If presidencies are defined by symbols and styles, Bush set out
to cast his as open, informal, active _ sort of an aerobic Teddy
Roosevelt. He opened the White House to the public the day after
his inauguration; he met with the press far more frequently than
did President Reagan; and he seemed at times to be cultivating an
image as the Triathlete President _ jogging, golfing, fishing,
speedboating, playing tennis, tossing horseshoes, tussling with
grandchildren.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>