<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 2244EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AbortionPoll     12-17 0370</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Abortion Poll,0382</SECOND>
<HEAD>Poll Indicates Changes In Views Toward Abortion.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A nationwide poll published Sunday suggests a
shift in tolerance toward abortion compared to the results of a
similar survey last spring.
   According to the poll conducted for The Boston Globe and WBZ-TV,
37 percent of the 1,000 registered voters surveyed said they
supported legal abortion ``in all circumstances,'' compared to 25
percent nine months ago.
   Eleven percent said abortion should not be legal in any case,
compared to 19 percent in March, according to the Boston Sunday
Globe.
   There was little change over the question whether abortion
should be legal ``in certain circumstances.'' Fifty-three percent
said ``yes'' in December, compared to 51 percent in March.
   The random telephone survey by KRC@Communications Research of
Cambridge had a margin of error of plus or minus 3 percent.
   On the question of whether public funds should be used for
abortions for women who cannot afford them, 49 percent of the
December sample said the money should be available and 34 percent
said it should not be used.
   In March, 35 percent of those asked said public funds should be
available, while 49 percent said the government should not earmark
money for abortions.
   The December poll posed a question that was not asked in March:
``In general, do you think that a woman should or should not be
able to obtain an abortion?'' Sixty-eight percent said she should
and 25 percent said she should not.
   The Globe said the December poll sought to assess interest in
laws passed in Pennsylvania following the July U.S. Supreme Court
ruling that gave states more authority to regulate abortions.
   Seventy-six percent said they favored for their state the
Pennsylvania rule requiring a woman seeking an abortion to be
advised by medical workers about fetal development, abortion risks
and alternatives and wait 24 hours before the procedure is done.
The law was opposed by 16 percent.
   Sixty-one percent favored the idea of a Pennsylvania law that
requires a woman seeking an abortion to tell her husband unless he
is not the father, cannot be found, would threaten the woman if
told or the pregnancy was caused by rape. It was opposed by 31
percent.
</TEXT>

</DOC>