<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1054EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-SouthAfrica     12-18 0415</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-South Africa,0426</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge Orders Release Of Ex-Policeman Held In Death Squad Probe</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID CRARY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A judge today overruled police
investigators and ordered the release of a former policeman
detained in the assassination of two white left-wing activists.
   Police had opposed the release of Calla Botha, saying there was
evidence linking him to a right-wing group responsible for
political assassinations.
   Johannesburg Supreme Court Justice J.C. Kriegler granted an
application filed by Botha's father, a retired police colonel,
seeking release of his son. Kriegler said there was insufficient
evidence connecting Botha to death squads.
   Botha was detained without charge on Nov. 30 as part of an
investigation into the assassinations of David Webster, a
university lecturer and human rights activist, and Anton Lubowski,
the only white office-holder in Namibia's main independence
movement, the South-West Africa People's Organization.
   Both were shot outside their homes _ Webster in Johannesburg on
May 1 and Lubowski in Windhoek, Namibia, on Sept. 12.
   In a court affidavit last week, police Brig. Floris Mostert
described Botha as the ``handler'' for Donald Acheson, who is held
in Windhoek awaiting trial for Lubowksi's murder.
   Another former policeman, Ferdinand Barnard, remains detained in
Johannesburg in the case. Mostert said Botha and Barnard were held
briefly in June after they were uncovered monitoring the movements
of one of Webster's activist colleagues.
   Police say the Webster-Lubowski case is not directly related to
investigations of claims that death squads within the ranks of the
national police force killed government opponents on the orders of
high-ranking officers.
   One black ex-policeman has pleaded guilty to committing a murder
as part of such a death squad, and a white former captain, Dirk
Coetzee, fled abroad after telling a newspaper he commanded a death
squad.
   In other developments today:
   _Police headquarters reported five more deaths in factional
fighting in black townships around the port city of Durban.
Authorities say more than 100 people have been killed in the area
this month in violence related to a three-year feud throughout
Natal Province between Inkatha, a relatively conservative Zulu
political organization, and supporters of militant anti-apartheid
groups.
   _Police freed four black activists who staged a three-week
hunger strike after they were detained without charge while leading
an unauthorized protest in Alexandra, an impoverished black
township near Johannesburg.
   Obed Bapela, a spokesman for the anti-apartheid Alexandra Civic
Organization, said the four had suspended their fast Friday after
police informed them they would soon be freed.
</TEXT>

</DOC>