<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0120 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1728EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Israel-Iran     12-19 0475</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Iran,470</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Confirms Israel Buying Iranian Oil</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The State Department said on Tuesday that
Israel made a major oil deal with Iran as part of a reported effort
to win the release of three Israeli soldiers being held in Lebanon.
   Department spokeswoman Margaret Tutwiler said Israel informed
the United States of the oil deal a month ago. She declined to say
whether the United States approved of the deal.
   ``Foreign countries do not seek U.S. approval for oil purchases
from a third country,'' she added.
   The United States has no diplomatic relations with Iran and is
worried about the possibility of Iranian-backed terrorist incidents
against American targets in Europe or Africa during the holiday
season.
   Iran is one of six countries which, according to the State
Department, supports international terrorism.
   NBC News disclosed the oil transaction Monday night, saying that
Israel paid Iran $36 million and that one purpose was to encourage
Iran to use its influence to help free three Israeli soldiers being
held in Lebanon.
   The United States is backing the deal in hopes that it could
lead to the release of American hostages held in Lebanon, NBC said.
   Ms. Tutwiler said the United States does not make deals for the
release of U.S. hostages, but she refused to offer an opinion as to
whether there is any objection to Israel carrying out negotiations
on behalf of the hostages.
   In addition to winning the radical Moslem country's help in
seeking the release of Israelis, the oil purchases and a potential
spare parts deal are intended to bolster Iran's position against a
common enemy, Iraq, NBC said.
   Iran's Islamic fundamentalist leaders are generally hostile to
Israel but the country's struggling economy is sorely in need of
foreign currency.
   Spokesmen for Israel's Energy, Foreign and Defense ministries on
Tuesday refused to comment on the report. The Defense Ministry also
refused to allow reporters to talk to Uri Lubrani, mentioned in the
NBC report as the man who dealt with the Iranians in Switzerland.
   Lubrani is responsible for Israel's Lebanon policy and served as
ambassador to Iran before the revolution that swept Ayatollah
Ruhollah Khomeini to power.
   Joseph Alpher of the Tel Aviv University's Jaffee Center for
Strategic Studies, executive editor of the center's annual ``Middle
East Military Balance'', said Israel had other considerations that
could justify ties with Iran, apart from seeking the release of its
prisoners.
   ``Iraq is getting stronger every day by acquiring chemical and
non-conventional arms that threaten us,'' Alpher said on Israel
Television. ``There is a reason to see to it that Iran can continue
confronting and diversing the Iraqi forces.''
   ``Beyond that, Iran has oil, Iran has Jews and all these are
good reasons for renewal of connections with Iran, without any
relation to the governing regime,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>