<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0194 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0114EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-StockFraud-Lewis Bjt   12-19 0687</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Stock Fraud-Lewis, Bjt,0708</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stock Speculator Sentenced To Work in New York Drug Clinic</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEFAN FATSIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A light sentence of three years probation for
admitted stock manipulator Salim B. ``Sandy'' Lewis is another sign
that on Wall Street it pays to settle.
   Lewis pleaded guilty to three counts of securities violations
rather than face trial and was sentenced Monday to work in a New
York drug rehabilitation clinic and pay a $250,000 fine rather than
go to prison.
   Some securities law experts said the term appeared fair for
Lewis' crime _ jacking up the price of Fireman's Fund Corp. stock
in May 1986 _ but raised the question of whether white-collar
felons were being treated too leniently.
   In her sentencing speech, U.S. District Judge Mary Johnson Lowe
told Lewis that ``your skills should not be wasted in warehousing
you.'' She also said his admission of guilt was a mitigating factor.
   ``Where you run into problems is the kid who sells a little
marijuana or cocaine and gets three years,'' said Alan Bromberg, a
securities law professor at Southern Methodist University. ``I'm
not sure he's doing any more social harm. It's just that he's not
capable of doing as much social good.''
   Lewis was ordered to work 40 hours a week for one year at Daytop
Village, a Manhattan-based drug rehabilitation clinic. He must work
20 hours a week at the clinic in the second and third years of his
probation. Lewis will work at Daytop as an executive consultant;
the idea to work there was his.
   Boyd L. Jefferies, the former Los Angeles stockbroker who
identified Lewis as part of a plea deal in which he cooperated with
the government, in July was sentenced to five years probation and
community service and fined $250,000.
   Two other figures in the Wall Street scandals still await
sentencing after pleading guilty to securities crimes: former
takeover strategist Martin Siegel and former stock arbitrager
Robert Freeman.
   Observers said the Lewis case could bear on sentencing GAF Corp.
Vice Chairman James T. Sherwin, who was convicted last week of
stock manipulation in a case also before Lowe. Sherwin has done
extensive work for a refugee relocation agency, as Lewis had worked
with drug-addiction agencies and the poor.
   Lewis, 50, a prominent Wall Street veteran, had faced up to 15
years in prison and a $750,000 fine. His firm, S.B. Lewis &amp; Co.,
was fined $400,000 for violating federal securities laws.
   The stock manipulation raised the value of Fireman's Fund stock
immediately before a longtime Lewis client, American Express Co.,
sold a large amount of shares in a new public offering.
   American Express _ which invested $4 million to help Lewis start
his brokerage in 1980 _ was never charged, and there is no proof
that it or Lewis profited from the manipulation. But under federal
securities laws, profit isn't necessary to commit a crime.
   Lewis maintained he was not motivated by greed but by a desire
to punish rival speculators attempting to bid down the price of
Fireman's Fund in anticipation of the new stock offering. The
government disagreed.
   ``Lewis' attempts to portray himself as a misguided watchdog of
the markets are simply not supported by the facts, which show
instead a straightforward market manipulation designed to assist a
close business associate, American Express,'' prosecutors said in
court papers.
   Columbia University securities law professor John C. Coffee Jr.
said Lewis' contention that no one was harmed in the manipulation
was misplaced.
   ``People were buying these securities as a price that was
inflated and artificial,'' he said.
   Prosecutors alleged that at Lewis' request, Jefferies bought
more than 400,000 shares of Fireman's Fund on May 8, 1986,
successfully driving its price up 12{ cents to $38 a share.
   A day later, American Express announced it would sell 8 million
shares of its 41 percent-owned Fireman's Fund at $41.50 a share, a
new stock offering that had been widely expected.
   Prosecutors said American Express made $88 million from the sale
but they never offered evidence that any of that profit was tainted
by what Lewis did.
</TEXT>

</DOC>