<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0243 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0504EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-SPE--Bride&amp;Groom:TalkFirst     12-18 0289</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-SPE--Bride &amp; Groom: Talk First,0291</SECOND>
<HEAD>SPECIAL EDITION</HEAD>
<HEAD>Bride &amp; Groom: Talk First</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Don't get so wrapped up in the excitement of
courtship and planning your wedding that you put off planning your
marriage, cautions a mental health specialist.
   Talking things out is the key to starting and maintaining a good
marriage, says Donna J. Rankin, associate professor of community
and health nursing at Loyola University. ``When you think to
yourself, we'll talk about this later, that later may be too late.''
   Subjects that are best aired before the ceremony include
parenting, finances, career and educational plans, dealing with
relatives and friends, compatibility, sexuality and other shared
intimacies, and religion and spirituality, both for the couple and
the children they will have.
   ``Everything is fair game for discussion at this point,'' says
Rankin. ``Too many couples think they can talk later, but if you
don't do it now, will you ever get around to it?''
   Rankin says most problems emerge after the honeymoon phase, a
period which which can last for just a few months or as long as
several years. Then the reality sets in, and you see your partner
as he or she really is. Rankin says this can be revealing but not
necessarily negative.
   ``Many of the couples I see for counseling yearn for `the good
old days' of their marriage, wishing it could be like the marriage
was previously,'' she says. ``You can't expect marriage to grow
without change, but change can hurt and requires adjustment by both
parties.''
   Rankin advises couples to have a serious discussion of their
life together at least once a year and suggests anniversaries as a
good time. ``Examine where you've been and where you're going.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>