<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0154 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0753EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a w PM-WalterMears ADV28   12-27 0793</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Walter Mears, ADV 28,0810</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv 28</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release PMs Thurs Dec 28 and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Noriega: Cloistered Fugitive Picks Own Prison</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WALTER R. MEARS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Temporarily, at least, Manuel Antonio Noriega
picked his own prison by taking refuge at the Vatican embassy in
Panama City _ where Secretary of Defense Dick Cheney thinks the
ousted military boss might be a long-term resident.
   That's not what the administration wants, but worse things could
happen, and have. So long as the deposed military boss of Panama is
a cloistered fugitive, he is isolated, silenced and confined to
small compound, living in a spare, single room.
   Despite Washington's sharp demands that the Vatican turn over
Noriega, the U.S. stake to the right of embassy refuge seems more
important than his case, so long as he is out of power and
neutralized. American embassies sometimes have been havens for
dissenters, notably in Cold War Hungary and now Beijing.
   U.S. officials argue that Noriega should not be granted asylum
because he is a common criminal, not a political fugitive. In his
case there is solid evidence of it, but totalitarian governments
have no difficulty constructing criminal charges against their
dissenters.
   Chinese dissident Fang Lizhi and his wife took refuge in the
American embassy in Beijing more than six months ago, after the
government crushed the democracy movement and began a purge of its
leaders. He's still there, despite repeated protests from the
Chinese, who say the United States is interfering in their internal
affairs.
   For 15 years, Cardinal Josef Mindszenty lived in asylum in the
U.S. Embassy in Budapest. He had been freed from a Communist prison
in the Hungarian uprising of 1956, and took refuge at the embassy
after the Soviet Union put down that rebellion. The Vatican finally
was able to arrange his release to the West in 1971.
   Embassies are considered to be the territory of the nations they
represent, and when they choose to grant haven, even the most
dictatorial of regimes have accepted it.
   Now, as Cheney said, lawyers and diplomats are trying to figure
out what happens next in the Noriega case. He left open the
possibility that it could be nothing.
   Cheney said Tuesday that the embassy is surrounded, with no way
out for Noriega and no way in for U.S. authorities. ``It could be
that they'll have a long-term resident in their embassy in Panama
City,'' he said.
   Noriega would hardly seem a welcome guest; church leaders
including Monsignor Jose Sebastian Laboa, the papal nuncio in
Panama City, had long been critics of the general's regime. The
Vatican embassy had been a refuge for Noriega opponents when they
needed one.
   Unless there is a deal to let Noriega go to exile rather than to
U.S. trial, the ousted dictator can keep hiding, but he can't run.
   ``At present, if he leaves the embassy under any circumstances,
he will in fact be arrested by U.S. forces and returned to the
United States,'' Cheney said Tuesday.
   Embassy refuge does not apply outside an embassy compound, so as
soon as Noriega stepped outside guarded Vatican mission, he could
be seized.
   The way around that would be a diplomatic deal to let him go
into exile. It would have to be distant and silent, lest he regain
his voice and try to incite his supporters against the new
government.
   For all the demands that Noriega go on drug trial, the
administration had been willing as recently as October to let him
go into exile without prosecution if he yielded power.
   The Vatican has no extradition agreement with the United States
so if the church decided Noriega should be expelled from the
diplomatic mission, it would be to the custody of the Panamanian
government.
   The Panamanian constitution forbids the extradition of any
citizen. Guillermo Endara, the new president installed with
American protection after Noriega was ousted, said if his
government had custody, he could not deliver the dictator for U.S.
drug trial.
   The fledgling Endara government, apparent winner of the May
elections Noriega annulled, needs to establish itself and display a
power to govern independent of the United States. Yielding up
Noriega would be counterproductive. But the Endara government could
put him on trial as a killer; there have been U.S. hints that
prosecution in Panama might be acceptable.
   Until and unless the diplomats find a solution, Noriega
presumably stays put, a captive in spare surroundings that mock the
luxuries of his days in power, the cash, cocaine and voodoo cults
said to have been his lifestyle.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Walter R. Mears, vice president and columnist
for The Associated Press, has reported on Washington and national
politics for more than 25 years.
</TEXT>

</DOC>