<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0178 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2208EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-Comandancia     12-21 0503</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Comandancia,500</SECOND>
<HEAD>Norieg's Headquarters Wreck</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   EDITOR'S NOTE: The following is a pool report by Kathy Lewis of
The Houston Post, Bill Clayton of the Houston Chronicle, Kevin
Merida of The Dallas Morning News and Dick Thompson of Time
magazine.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The ``Comandancia'' complex that was
the nerve center for Manuel Antonio Noriega's regime is a dank and
gutted ruin today, bristling with U.S. soldiers trying to root out
the last snipers of the dictator's forces still roaming the city.
   A group of reporters, escorted into the area for a look at the
sites of the heaviest fighting in the U.S. invasion, were hustled
back into the van with a warning from soldiers: There was
occasional sniper fire from a high-rise apartment building that
makes a backdrop to the comandancia.
   The entrance to the area, a poor section of Panama City called
Chorrillo, was littered with the wreckage of three cars. Across the
intersection, someone had painted on the bottom of a billboard:
``Yanqui go home.''
   Soldiers backed a tanklike personnel carrier into the burned-out
remains of a laundry, commanding a view of a nearby intersection.
Up the street a hydrant gushed water into the gutter, adding to the
stench of the burned and soaked rubble. Streets were filled with
twisted corrigated metal roofing, burned stocks of weapons, pieces
of blocks and tile. High-rise buildings were deserted and large
portions of the area had been reduced to blackened rubble and
twisted pipes.
   Outside the commandancia, an iron fence was strung with colored
lights for Christmas. Walls were blackened or pocked with 50 cal.
bullet holes, or simply blown away. The roof was twisted and iron
bars hung limply from the windows. Said one soldiers: ``There was
an awesome amount of firepower put on this place.''
   A broken scene in front of the commandancia lay is disarray, the
plastic figures shattered. At the end of the block, a soldier
points out the ``G-2'' headquarters, where it is alleged much of
the harassment of detained Americans had occurred. The structure
had much less damage than the turquoise-and-white commandancia
building.
   At the edge of the rubble of the several blocks around the
commandancia was a grisly scene from the early fighting: A compact
car, mashed to one-third its height with a body sprawled across the
remains of the front seat. Soldiers explained that when the U.S.
assault moved into the area, a patrol found the auto with its
occupants handing out AK-47 assault rifles to Noriega fighters. One
U.S. armored personnel carrier just rolled over the car, a soldier
said. Thirty feet down the street was a similarly squashed hulk of
anorther small car.
   Among the graffiti and advertising placards of the downtown area
could frequently be seen the painted slogqn ``Yanqui go home.''
Noriega's visage smiled out from the sides of some of the
buildings, in paintings that carried the slogan ``General of Peace
_ a commander for a long while'' or, ``For Panama, my life. Not a
single step backward.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>