<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0234 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0140EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-FundsDisclosure     12-22 0504</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Funds Disclosure,0521</SECOND>
<HEAD>SEC Proposes Stiffer Disclosure Rules for Mutual Funds</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN M. DOYLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Securities and Exchange Commission is
seeking public comment on proposed new rules that would require
mutual funds to simplify and expand the information they are
required to supply investors.
   The SEC agreed to submit the proposals to public scrutiny on
Thursday.
   One proposals seeks to clarify descriptions of funds to
investors, a second would provide better measures of fund
performance and a third would require disclosure of who is making
fund investment decisions.
   At least one of the proposals, requiring funds to identify those
managing their stock portfolios, is expected to meet with the
stiffest industry opposition, SEC staffers acknowledged.
   ``I would say the majority of the industry people that we've
heard from think it's a bad idea,'' said Kathryn McGrath of the SEC.
   Ms. McGrath, head of the SEC's Division of Investment
Management, conceded that previous attempts to implement a fund
manager disclosure rule were ``blown out of the water by a wave of
criticism.''
   The Investment Company Institute, a mutal fund industry group,
opposes portfolio manager disclosure, claiming it would be an
additional burden for the funds and create a ``superstar'' system
of fund managers.
   ``We did not agree with the fund manager disclosure, which
places undue emphasis on the cult of personality. It ignores the
actual basis on which funds hire advisers,'' said Betty K. Hart, a
spokeswoman for the trade group.
   ``In 1972, 1982 and 1984 this issue has come up and we have
always opposed it. We still oppose it. There are some very
succesful funds that run by committee,'' she added.
   Ms. Hart said the ICI was willing to go along with the
disclosure rule in just two instances: ``where a fund promotes an
individual to the press and the investment public, or if the
individual is of such critical importance to the advisory
organization that it would cease to exist in the same manner if
they left.''
   The two other proposals are less controversial. To simply
information in a mutual fund's prospectus, the SEC staff suggested
shortening tables listing a fund's total return per share.
   To provide investors with more information to easily evaluate a
fund, the staff proposed following one of two alternatives: A
fund's managers would be required either to discuss and analyze its
fiscal year performance in relation to its investment objectives or
compare its total returns over one-, five- and 10-year periods to
the performance of a securities index.
   The commission, which regulates investment companies as well as
the securities industry, voted to submit the proposed rules for a
60-day public comment period.
   Following that period, Ms. McGrath said her staff will review
comments _ both pro and con _ make any changes deemed necessary and
submit the proposed rule changes to the commissioners ``and they
will vote it up or down.''
   She said the staff hoped to submit the proposals to the
commission by late spring or early summer.
</TEXT>

</DOC>