<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0094 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1654EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BundyLegacy     12-23 0692</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bundy Legacy,0718</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mother of Bundy Victim Says She's Finding Peace</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VERN ANDERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOUNTIFUL, Utah (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   This Christmas is the first in 15 years
that Belva Kent has been at peace. The irony does not escape her
that it was serial killer Ted Bundy who made the respite possible.
   Just before his Jan. 24 execution in Florida, Bundy confessed to
having killed her 17-year-old daughter, Debra, and at least 22
other young women in the 1970s. The condemned man also indicated on
a map torn from an atlas where he dumped three of his eight victims
in Utah.
   Numerous searches over several months in central Utah netted
hundreds of animal bones but only a single human kneecap. It was
among 10 bags of bones collected by searchers in early May near a
road leading into Fairview Canyon, 150 miles south of Salt Lake
City.
   That was where Bundy, a former Utah law student, had said to
look.
   Within days, Belva Kent, her ex-husband, Dean, and two of their
three surviving children went with detectives to the rock-strewn
hillside.
   ``We were very peaceful down there,'' Belva Kent said in an
interview Friday night. ``I came home feeling better than I have in
15 years.''
   It took longer for Dean Kent. But after some weeks he concluded
that Bundy, in this instance, hadn't been lying.
   ``Based on what we had known from his confession, his
description fit the area. I'm confident it's a good possibility
that's where he disposed of the remains,'' Dean Kent said.
   ``It's given me peace of mind to believe that's what happened.''
   The state medical examiner said the kneecap was likely that of a
young woman, but there was no way to determine if it was Debra
Kent's.
   Debra Kent disappeared the night of Nov. 8, 1974, from a high
school parking lot in Bountiful, 10 miles north of Salt Lake City.
She had left a play early to pick up her younger brother, Bill, at
a roller rink.
   Even though the Kents had been certain for years that Debra was
a Bundy victim, his confession and execution struck them in
surprising ways.
   ``I had anticipated a much different feeling than I had,'' Dean
Kent said. ``I'd felt some of the bitterness would be relieved, but
that isn't the case. I think I'll carry that to my grave.''
   Belva Kent, 53, relived the grief all over again.
   ``Everyone says you're not given more than you can handle, but
I've been questioning that a bit lately,'' she said.
   After Debra disappeared, her brother, Bill, blamed himself. His
bitterness toward Bundy was matched only by his inability to stifle
the pain. Five years ago, after his marriage broke up, he died at
26, in an alcohol-related auto accident.
   Within months of Bill's death, Dean Kent started drinking,
walked out on a 29-year marriage, quit his job as an oil company
executive and fathered a child. He lives alone now, trying to come
to grips with his shattered life.
   ``I certainly feel he was the cancer that destroyed our
family,'' Kent said of Bundy.
   Belva Kent had raised five children and never worked outside the
home. Her self-esteem departed with her husband.
   ``But then there comes a point where you see the bitterness
doesn't get you anywhere,'' she said, so she got a job and has been
working since.
   Last summer, Belva Kent was diagnosed as having a benign brain
tumor behind her forehead the size of a tangerine. Surgery had to
be put off when doctors found she also was suffering from multiple
sclerosis.
   Then, in a reaction to an anti-seizure medication, Belva Kent's
entire body blistered and peeled, leaving her right eye tearless.
   Belva Kent's been back to work for three weeks now, slowly
regaining strength for the brain surgery she will have in late
spring.
   ``I guess it's not my nature to feel sorry for myself,'' she
says. ``Besides, other people suffer, too. It's just that my
hardships are more obvious.''
   After Debra disappeared, the Kents kept the front porch light
burning day and night. It's kept on now, Belva says, as a memorial.
</TEXT>

</DOC>