<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0101EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Romania-Christmas     12-25 0464</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Christmas,0483</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romanians Freely Celebrate Christmas for First Time in Decades</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MORT ROSENBLUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Romanian faithful today are
celebrating the Christmas miracle that freed them from a Communist
dictator who trampled religious freedoms and even kept Christmas
music off the radio.
   ``There were so many years when I did not come to church for
fear of the government,'' said one worshiper, Victoria Ionita, on
Christmas Eve. ``Now there is shooting in the streets, but I come
because of trust in God.''
   Christmas music rang out Sunday throughout Romania for the first
time since Communists took over in 1947.
   But fighting raged on between soldiers backing the provisional
government and security forces loyal to dictator Nicolae Ceausescu,
who was ousted in a popular uprising Friday and later arrested.
   A few families carried freshly cut Christmas trees through
Bucharest early Sunday, but sniper fire by Ceausescu supporters
quickly cleared the streets.
   For many Romanians, Ceausescu's downfall was a Christmas miracle
from St. Dimitrius, the 12th century holy man whose relics lay in
the gilded and frescoed cathedral the deposed dictator wanted to
destroy.
   ``This was a painful re-enactment of the Bible,'' said Patriarch
Teoctist, the gray-bearded pontiff of Romania's Orthodox Church.
``Ceausescu was a follower of Herod, and when Herod was seeking
Jesus Christ he ordered the killing of many thousands of children.''
   On Oct. 26, the eve of St. Dimitrius Day, churchmen prayed for
the overthrow of Ceausescu. It came, they said, as an answer to
that prayer.
   ``Everybody believes that,'' said Teoctist, with a sly smile.
``Don't forget, we are believers.''
   Outside the cathedral, old couples and young men lighted candles
and bowed. A woman in a green coat, Letitia Patrut, spoke of
students slain during the uprising who would miss Christmas.
   ``These young people, how they sacrificed for us!'' she said.
``We must pray for these poor young people who defended the
people.''
   One woman was so badly shaken she paused long moments between
words. She had fasted since Friday night in sympathy for the
victims. To emphasize her point, she fished from her pockets two
bullets she had dug from her wall.
   Patriarch Teoctist said Romanians have remained a deeply
religious people despite political adversity.
   He said 85 percent to 90 percent of Romanians are Orthodox
Christians and that he was encouraged by how many people came to
church during the dictatorship.
   ``Freedom of religion is indescribably important. Romanians
lived all these years with their church, and now they realize how
they escaped from a nightmare,'' the patriarch said.
   He said Ceausescu wanted to destroy the partriarchal residence
and possibly even the cathedral. ``Every day I feared I would wake
up and someone would tell me the bulldozers were coming.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>