<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1203EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Obit-Beckett 2ndLd-Writethru a0504 12-26 1126</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Obit-Beckett, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0504,1154</SECOND>
<HEAD>Playwright of Despair Dead At 83</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 8th graf, `That theme ...' with new reaction.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PAR2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHARLES CAMPBELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nobel Prize-winning author Samuel Beckett, who
created a world of everlasting despair and left theatergoers
``Waiting for Godot,'' died at age 83 of respiratory failure and
was buried today, his publisher said.
   The playwright, poet and novelist whose work depicted death and
decay as mankind's sole and inescapable destiny, was buried this
morning at Montparnasse Cemetery in a private ceremony, said
publisher Jerome Linden.
   Beckett died Friday in Paris, Linden said.
   Jack Lang, culture minister of France, Beckett's adopted home,
called him ``an immense writer, exceptionally exacting, who has
profoundly marked his century.''
   The Irish-born author of ``Godot'' and ``Endgame'' rejected the
redeeming optimism that might have made him more accessible to a
mass audience and gained him earlier recognition as one of the
century's greatest writers.
   His was a stark world peopled with vagabond couples trapped by
an apocalyptic sense of doom and caught in a never-ending,
master-slave dialectic often laced with wry Irish humor.
   Beckett's work was a cry of agony and compassion at the hopeless
misery, futility and loneliness of human existence, which he called
a slow death.
   That theme reappears in the dozens of plays, novels, poems and
short stories he wrote in both French and English during a career
that spanned more than 50 years.
   ``He was a man of great imagination. He was in a sense a quiet
leader,'' British playwright Harold Pinter told Independent Radio
News. ``He was in the forefront of modern literature. He was
totally original and a man of great courage, not only in himself,
but in his work. His work knew no bounds really. He didn't accept
any limitations.''
   Critics were scandalized by his experiments on the stage.
``Breath,'' which premiered in 1970, had no actors, no dialogue and
no action _ just a heap of gloomily lit garbage cans onstage, a
baby's screams and the amplified sound of heavy breathing. The play
lasted just 30 seconds.
   Until French director Roger Blin rescued the long-published but
never performed ``Waiting for Godot'' from obscurity in 1952,
Beckett's pessimistic and often difficult style limited his
audience to an intellectual elite.
   The play, about two tramps waiting for a third, was a huge
success and brought the author instant world renown. It was
translated into and performed in more than 20 languages, and it
helped Beckett win the Nobel Prize for literature in 1969.
   Always shy and withdrawn, Beckett refused to attend the award
ceremonies in Stockholm. He sent his publisher instead and fled to
Tunisia to escape the news media. The citation described Beckett as
``a pioneer of a new modesty of expression in fiction and the
theater ... whose writing rises like a cry for mercy from all
mankind.''
   Beckett was secretive about his private life. He granted only
rare interviews, and was one of the few writers to refuse to appear
on ``Apostrophes'' _ France's most popular book review television
show.
   Even the date of Beckett's birth was wrapped in mystery. He said
he was born in Dublin on Good Friday, April 13, 1906. But his
biographer, Deirdre Bair, suggested he was really born a month
earlier, with Beckett shifting it to the anniversary of the
crucifixion as a symbolic boost to his self-made legend.
   The son of a surveyor, Beckett enjoyed a comfortable,
upper-middle class Protestant upbringing. Though he said he had ``a
happy childhood,'' he once admitted to ``always feeling lonely.''
   He studied modern languages at Trinity College, Dublin, and
first came to Paris in 1928 to lecture in Engish at the prestigious
Ecole Normale Superieure.
   In Paris he met another Irish exile, James Joyce, who was to
have a profound influence on his future writing. ``Joyce had a
moral effect on me,'' Beckett said later. ``He made me realize the
meaning of artistic integrity.''
   After Beckett's father, William France Beckett, died in Dublin
in 1933, his mother urged Beckett to drop his literary ambitions
and take up some serious profession.
   To escape her and the middle-class atmosphere of his family,
Beckett settled permanently in Paris in 1937.
   Beckett's move came at a time when international tension was
mounting, but he said ``I preferred France at war to Ireland at
peace.''
   In 1938, Beckett was stabbed in a Paris street brawl. A deep
knife wound pierced his lung and narrowly missed his heart. A
pianist passing by on her bicycle stopped to help the gravely
injured man and have him taken to hospital.
   The girl, Suzanne Deschevaux-Dumesnil, though six years his
senior, became his lifelong companion and they finally married in
secret in 1961.
   Ms. Deschevaux-Dumesnil died July 17 in Paris at the age of 89.
The couple had no children.
   During World War II the couple worked with the underground
Resistance movement in Nazi-occupied France and Beckett was awarded
the Croix de Guerre with a gold star in 1945.
   Beckett, who all his life shunned politics, later said he joined
the Resistance not to help France win the war, but ``to fight the
Germans who were making life hell for my friends.''
   Indeed, despite his rejection of the limelight, Beckett was a
loving and loyal friend. He would spend hours in Left Bank cafes
listening to his painter friends _ including Holland's Van Velde
brothers, the English painter Jack B. Yeats (William Butler Yeats'
brother) and Alberto Giacometti _ talk about their work.
   He also met France's leading Surrealist writers and eventually
translated several poems of Paul Eluard and Andre Breton.
   Beckett was not just a serious intellectual, and he was known as
the man who preferred referring a newspaper's sports pages to
reviews of his own plays.
   Beckett attributed his success to an ``intuitive sense of
despair,'' rather than to talent.
   He once described himself as ``doomed to spend the rest of my
days digging up the detritus of my life and vomiting it out over
and over again.
   ``Optimism is not my way. I shall always be depressed, but what
comforts me is the realization that I can now accept this dark side
as the commanding side of my personality,'' he said.
   In later plays written in French and first performed on the
Paris stage, Beckett developed his theme of man's losing battle
against destiny. In ``Endgame,'' a blind paralytic laments his fate
while his senile and crippled parents die of despair in garbage
cans.
   ``There are no landmarks in my work,'' he said. ``We are all
adrift. We must invent a world in which to survive, but even this
invented world is pervaded by fear and guilt. Our existence is
hopeless.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>