<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1051EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Revolution Bjt   12-30 0680</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Revolution, Bjt,0699</SECOND>
<HEAD>Theater of Absurd During Revolt, Everyone Wants a Role</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto FRA5</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MORT ROSENBLUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The teen-age revolutionary guard found
no guns in the reporters' rented Ford, but there were those six
suspect Bulgarian apples in the trunk. To make sure they weren't
bombs, he placed one on the ground and stomped it into applesauce.
   At another roadblock farther down, a man with a menacing
mustache and a murderous mien peered at a reporter's U.S. passport
and frisked him. Finding him harmless, the guard seized the
reporter's shoulders and, overcome with the day's emotion, planted
moist kisses on each of his cheeks.
   The uprising against Nicolae Ceausescu was not your
run-of-the-mill revolution.
   On the first evening of upheaval, the American reporter found a
mild-mannered hospital worker who had had enough of dictatorship.
``I'll help you,'' he said, ``but first I must drop this off.'' He
indicated a large yellow sports bag. ``It's full of Molotov
cocktails.''
   But for the chilling omnipresent mayhem, it was less a
revolution than spontaneous free-form theater of the absurd. And
everyone wanted a role.
   Checkpoints blossomed at subway stops, street corners and
doorways. On boulevards downtown, they were three to a block.
Sometimes soldiers manned them, but not usually.
   At one, a 9-year-old blond boy examined a reporter's papers,
nodding gravely. He was armed with a short stick better suited to
jabbing toads on a summer afternoon.
   At another, six scowling teen-agers circled a car and aimed
AK-47 assault rifles at the passengers. From their awkward, nervous
gestures, it seemed doubtful any of them knew a safety catch from a
trigger.
   In firefights, the dictator's die-hard killers held off
ill-trained soldiers and amateur revolutionaries, often amid a
tragicomedy of errors.
   During a night-long siege of the television station, a woman
popped regularly from the elevators to assure all occupants that
things were under control. Once, however, she emerged shrieking
hysterically. Defending soldiers were in a fierce gunbattle with
their own men across the road.
   Near the television, which was simultaneously the heart of the
revolution and the seat of its provisional government, paranoia ran
wild.
   Racing against a deadline, a carload of journalists stopped for
a thorough search. Guards poked into the car battery and examined
coins in pockets. From a short distance, guards at a second
roadblock watched, weapons ready. Finally cleared, the car rolled
on, only to be searched again by the second group.
   The paranoia was murderous. Late one night, CBS crews outside
the television station watched army guards open fire on a lone
pedestrian walking toward them in the dark. Over the deadly rattle,
his last words were hardly audible: ``Don't shoot. I'm a doctor.''
   CBS correspondents Martha Teichner and Bob Simon saw the scene
because sentries held them at gunpoint against a tank from 11:15
p.m. to 6 a.m. Finally, they resorted to playing on the old
Latino-Balkan machismo.
   Simon told them that Teichner was getting sick.
   ``The minute the words `sick' and `woman' got together,
everything changed,'' Teichner said. ``They took us inside, laid
blankets over me and found some candy. Suddenly the same guys who
were trying to kill us were giving us these little sweets.''
   Throughout the revolution, the leitmotif was an unceasing string
of communiques and serious talk from television, immediately
renamed Television Free Romania.
   At the most dramatic moments, the screen showed Ceausescu and
his wife, Elena, bundled out of an armored personnel carrier and
put on trial. Finally, they were shown shot against a wall, and
their bullet-torn bodies were pictured close-up.
   Mostly, it was discussion. From time to time, the talking heads
were replaced by snatches of opera, Christmas carols or an
occasional Tom &amp; Jerry cartoon. As doctors sewed up wounds and
commandos routed out terrorist snipers, Snow White's dwarfs sang,
``Whistle While You Work.''
   But on Thursday night, Romanian television ran its first
full-length Western feature film in some time, and people gazed at
their screens in rapt attention, sometimes solemnly.
   It was Charlie Chaplin's ``The Great Dictator.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>