<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0158 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1427EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a PM-BusinessMirror Adv28   12-27 0562</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Business Mirror, Adv 28,0577</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv28</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release PMs Thursday, Dec. 28</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Retransmitting to correct category code.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Uprisings As Much Economic As Political</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN CUNNIFF</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Analyst</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The fury of Romanians against their former
government is revealed partly by the economic statistics. Romania,
in recent years, has been the economic backwater of Eastern Europe.
   Alone among those nations _ Bulgaria, Czechoslovakia, East
Germany, Hungary and Poland _ the country's gross national product
and industrial production declined in 1988.
   Its GNP last year, in fact, was about where it was in 1980,
while almost every other developed nation, communist and
non-communist, registered increases. In that time China more than
doubled its GNP.
   While Romania's neighbors increased exports between 1980 and
1986, its exports stagnated. Romania's population of 23 million is
exceeded only by that of Poland, but Romania's imports were lower
than any fraternal East Bloc country.
   Its per capita gross national product of $5,500 also remains the
lowest in Eastern Europe, less than one-half that of East Germany,
and it is falling.
   Whereas East Germans had an automobile-to-population ratio of
one to five, in Romania the ratio was just a bit more than one in
100. While Romanian meat production averaged 70 kilograms per
capita, that of Hungary was 160.
   In effect, the old government was leading the nation into
economic decline and lower living standards at a time when growth,
if perhaps slowly, was the rule in every other European country,
possibly excluding tiny Albania.
   The profile of economic deterioration amid growth emerges from
research completed in August and published in September by the
Central Intelligence Agency. It shows a vivid contrast between
communist and capitalist nations.
   The figures also suggest the urgent need of the Soviet Union to
renovate and spur its own economy, in which growth rates have
steadily deteriorated in recent years.
   The CIA research shows Soviet GNP falling from average annual
growth of 4.8 percent in 1961-65 and 4.9 percent from 1966-70, to
3.1 percent in 1971-75, 2.1 percent in 1976-80 and 1.9 percent in
1981-85.
   After a 4 percent spurt in 1986, mainly the result of a 10.3
percent surge in agricultural production, the GNP growth rate
subsided to 1.3 percent in 1987 and 1.5 percent in 1988.
Agricultural production shrank in the latter years.
   Reviewing the numbers, and contrasting them with those of the
capitalist world, it's clear that the economies of the communist
countries as a whole were becoming outmatched.
   In 1988, the annual rate of GNP growth in the United States,
Canada, Japan, Australia and all countries of Western Europe,
Yugoslavia excepted, exceeded that of the Soviet Union and the
Soviet bloc nations of Eastern Europe.
   Even the economies of the less developed countries, taken as a
whole, showed a growth rate of 3.7 percent, or higher than the
Soviet Union and the Communists nations of Eastern Europe.
   Among the large communist nations, a swiftly industrializing
China stands out, registering a growth rate of 11.2 percent in
1988, the third time since 1983 in which it has reached
double-digit levels.
   The stark contrast between the communist and non-communist
nations that emerges from the data emphasizes the economic origins
of the upheavals.
   In an age of developing communications, that contrast was
obvious to all, except perhaps for a few leaders.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End advance PMs Thursday, Dec. 28.</NOTE>

</DOC>