<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0205 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2201EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-EasternEurope-Churches Adv24   12-21 0772</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Eastern Europe-Churches, Adv 24,0791</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv24</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 24, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Democracy Brings Challenges, Opportunities to Church in Eastern Europe</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserGraphic</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID BRIGGS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Democratic changes sweeping across Eastern Europe are making it
easier to practice religion, but church officials foresee a new set
of challenges in the suddenly more open religious marketplace.
   ``The new market for destructive religious cults will be Eastern
Europe,'' said Rabbi A. James Rudin, interreligious affairs
director of the American Jewish Committee. ``This will be an area
of people who are in a sense almost innocent to the claims of
cults.''
   And in the land where Martin Luther nailed his 95 theses to a
church door in Wittenberg in defiance of Roman Catholic authorities
in 1517, starting the German Reformation, church members are
demanding new freedoms, including the right to participate in the
church's decision-making.
   People are asking if ``the new thinking and openness is valid in
society is it not valid for church structures?'' said the Rev.
David Nelson, Vienna-based secretary for Europe of the Evangelical
Lutheran Church in America.
   The new freedoms, from open borders to reduced restrictions on
worship and church membership, were fought for by most of the
churches themselves, and are generally welcomed.
   Last week, government officials in Czechoslovakia said they were
drafting laws to ensure freedom of religion. Soviet Leader Mikhail
S. Gorbachev, who met with Pope John Paul II this month, has
pledged a new law guaranteeing freedom of worship, and steps have
already been taken to clear the way for legalizing the banned
Ukrainian Catholic Church.
   Church members who once faced restrictions ranging from the loss
of coveted civil jobs to imprisonment are eager for the laws to
change, according to Western observers.
   ``There certainly is an opinion that the changes now under way
in Eastern Europe are very favorable to the work of the Christian
church,'' said Nelson.
   But with the new opportunities, U.S. experts say, come a host of
new challenges, particularly in nations where the majority
religious group enjoyed a special status as the only independent
institution.
   In a paradox, the Lutheran church in East Germany and elsewhere
found that being stripped of its power over the last 40 years freed
the church to focus on its mission of being an advocate for the
powerless, said the Rev. Steven Boehme who spent 2{ years in East
Germany for the National Council of Churches.
   ``In their weakness was indeed their strength. And further from
the seat of power is closer to the heart of things,'' said Boehme
of the Christian Church (Disciples of Christ), who returned home
Oct. 30.
   ``The church will have to reflect on what it has learned in the
last 40 years.''
   He said he hopes the church under the new freedoms welcomes more
plurality within its ranks and becomes ``the voice of those left
behind'' during any hardships that result from economic reforms.
   Nelson said clergy and laypeople who have quietly accepted the
actions of church leaders over the decades are beginning to
scrutinize church hierarchy more, particularly church officials who
were viewed as collaborators with the old regimes.
   In that way, they are starting to catch up with decades of
theological changes in the West giving greater authority to lay
members of congregations.
   But Gerard Powers, an adviser on Eastern Europe in the Office of
International Justice and Peace of the U.S. Catholic Conference,
said many churches in Eastern Europe have had to rely on pre-World
War II theological texts, and are not up-to-date on even major
changes such as the Second Vatican Council in the early 1960s.
   ``In general, there's no doubt because of the restrictions on
the Catholic Church in Eastern Europe and other churches, one
effect of that is the church has not kept up with changes in the
universal church,'' Powers said.
   Rabbi Rudin expressed concern about ``residual anti-Semitism.''
He cited the controversy in Poland over delays in the promised
removal of a Carmelite convent from the edge of the Auschwitz death
camp and derisive remarks by East German and Hungarian leaders
about the ``Jewish media'' and ``rootless cosmopolitans,'' which he
called old code words for anti-Semitism.
   ``As we move to a global village, religious commmunities will
have to live and work together in ways we have not done before,''
said Rudin, who was in Poland in the fall organizing conferences
between Catholic and American Jewish leaders.
   Still, U.S. observers look ahead hopefully as change unfolds in
Eastern Europe.
   ``Religious freedom can only benefit all the churches there,''
said Powers, ``and we should celebrate it.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, Dec. 24</NOTE>

</DOC>