<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0616EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Panama-Wounded     12-26 0481</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Wounded,0497</SECOND>
<HEAD>Army Secretary Pays Christmas Visit To Soldiers Wounded In Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto SA1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KELLEY SHANNON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN ANTONIO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soldiers wounded in Panama, wearing Purple
Hearts on their pajamas, enjoyed Christmas visits with relatives
and celebrated the news that Gen. Manuel Noriega turned himself in.
   ``I feel glad that the beast is in chains,'' Staff Sgt. Terence
Merlo said Monday during a visit to Wilford Hall Medical Center by
Army Secretary Michael P.W. Stone.
   Merlo, who is in the military police, said he wished the man who
had run Panama had turned up somewhere other than in the Vatican
Embassy, where he requested asylum Sunday.
   ``I'm not sure that it was the best place for him to turn
himself in for us to get gratification and achieve our ends,'' said
Merlo, who suffered at least four gunshot wounds to the abdomen and
a nick on the temple.
   Stone visited wards stacked with Christmas presents and full of
visiting relatives at Wilford Hall and Brook Army Medical Center,
where more than 80 servicemen were being treated.
   ``We have been vigilant in our defense of our values and the
threat to the national interest. But vigilance has its price,''
Stone said after the visit. ``We honor the soldiers for their
patriotism, bravery and courage.''
   As he made his way around hospital rooms, giving Army medallions
as gifts, Stone heard firsthand about the fighting.
   Merlo, 40, with his wife, daughters and other relatives at his
side, said he and MP Spec. Robert Cuschleg of Columbus, Ohio, were
ambushed in the darkness during the first day of the U.S. attack.
Cuschleg, in the next bed, had a finger amputated because of an
injury.
   Pfc. Mike Heyne, 21, of Ashland, Ohio, also at Wilford Hall,
said he hoped Noriega's surrender would allow American troops to
come home soon.
   ``I'm glad he did it this early,'' said Heyne, who was wounded
by mortar fire. A small jar containing some shrapnel doctors
removed from his waist sat next to his bed, and Heyne said he
planned to keep it as a souvenir.
   First Sgt. Jose Western, 31, recovering at Brooke, also
expressed delight that Noriega's whereabouts were finally known.
   ``I'm glad Noriega surrendered. It doesn't matter where he is,
as long as he surrendered,'' said Western, of Fort Ord, Calif.
   So far 250 soldiers, including 15 on Monday, have been brought
to San Antonio after being wounded in Panama. Three died en route
and one died after arrival.
   Dozens have been transferred back to home bases or discharged,
leaving 52 at Wilford Hall and 34 at Brooke Army Medical Center.
   On Christmas morning, soldiers read newspapers reporting
Noriega's surrender and displayed Purple Hearts from their pillows
or pajamas.
   Relatives exchanged gifts with the soldiers and some attended
two Christmas Day services as they stayed at the hospitals with
their wounded loved ones.
</TEXT>

</DOC>