<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1138EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Yugoslavia 1stLd-Writethru a0504 12-18 0527</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Yugoslavia, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0504,0542</SECOND>
<HEAD>Premier Introduces Economic Recovery Plan</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE with premier introducing economic recovery
plan, political changes. No pickup.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DUSAN STOJANOVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BELGRADE, Yugoslavia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Premier Ante Markovic today proposed
a new convertible currency unit in Yugoslavia as part of a sweeping
reform plan to save the Communist nation from its worst economic
crisis.
   About 160,000 workers staged a half-hour ``warning'' strike in
the republic of Montenegro today to pressure the government into
adopting urgent measures to contain hyperinflation, hovering at
2,000 percent.
   The strike coincided with the start of a three-day Parliament
meeting, at which Markovic unveiled his proposals.
   A solution to the problems ``is not possible without a
completely new economic and political system that would ensure
economic efficiency and political democracy with full freedoms and
human rights,'' Markovic said.
   Markovic said one new ``convertible dinar'' would be worth
10,000 old dinars. Yugoslavs should from now on be able to freely
purchase foreign currencies with dinars in local banks, he said.
   The exchange rate would be fixed at seven dinars for one West
German mark and remain unchanged until June 30, 1990, Markovic said.
   Until now, the dinar rate was adjusted daily compared to foreign
currencies and has lost value rapidly as inflation has soared.
   One U.S. dollar would be worth 12 new dinars, instead of the
current 120,000 dinars, Markovic said.
   The dinar was pegged to the West German mark because of its
``greatest stability'' on world money markets, Markovic said.
   He specified the changeover would take place Jan. 1, 1990, if
Parliament approves the package.
   Markovic's government, which took over in March, has threatened
to resign if the plan is rejected.
   Legislators have moved quickly to introduce market mechanisms as
a way out of Yugoslavia's economic crisis, which includes a $17
billion foreign debt and 17 percent inflation.
   Yugoslavia's last re-evaluation of the dinar occurred in 1965.
   At today's meeting, Markovic also announced tight monetary and
budgetary controls; free formation of interest rates which in the
past have been set by the country's National Bank; and government
control of prices on electricity, gasoline, rail transport, rents,
postal services and medicines.
   The central bank would for the first time become ``fully
autonomous'' in conducting monetary policies in accordance with
market mechanisms and will no longer be allowed to print money in
order to cover state deficits, Markovic said.
   The government also proposed to Parliament changes in the
country's criminal code, including dropping the so-called ``verbal
offenses'' under which thousands of people have been prosecuted for
privately or publicly criticizing the Communist regime.
   The state Tanjug news agency said ``the last warning to the
government'' was staged in the underdeveloped republic because its
policy has ``brought a large part of Montenegro's population to the
edge of famine and social misery.''
   Similar strikes were expected to take place in the country's
largest republic of Serbia on Wednesday and in the poorest region,
Macedonia, on Thursday.
   The state-run trade union of Montenegro reportedly said in a
proclamation that unless Markovic introduces urgent measures to
raise living standards, ``a much longer general strike will ensue.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>