<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0227 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1918EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-MobilDismissal     12-19 0482</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mobil Dismissal,0497</SECOND>
<HEAD>Seek to Keep Secret Documents in Wrongful Firing Case</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DANIEL J. WAKIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEWARK, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mobil Oil Corp. is trying to keep under
wraps court documents that a former executive wants to use as proof
to show the oil giant fired him for refusing to conspire in a
coverup of environmental problems.
   Mobil argues that most of the documents are irrelevant to Valcar
Bowman Jr.'s case, and says it is happy to release portions _
mostly sentences and paragraphs _ of the papers that it considers
central to his claims.
   The nation's second-largest oil company behind Exxon Corp.,
denying it has anything to hide, also argues that the reports are
self-criticisms encouraged by environmental regulators, and that
revealing them would discourage industry attempts to be candid
about environmental conditions.
   U.S. District Judge Harold A. Ackerman scheduled a hearing for 4
p.m. Wednesday to decide whether the documents should be kept
secret.
   On Dec. 11, Ackerman dealt the company a setback in the case,
ruling that enough evidence existed for a trial to take place on
Bowman's claims.
   Bowman says he was wrongfully fired in April 1986 from his job
as manager for environmental affairs at Mobil Chemical Co.'s
Princeton, N.J. office.
   He lost his job, Bowman says, because he refused to ``sanitize''
environmental assessment reports about conditions at plants in the
chemical division. The changes were suggested by company lawyers.
   Bowman was told to submit the reports to company lawyers after
he refused to cooperate with what he charged was an attempt to foil
investigators from examining environmental records at Mobil's
Bakersfield, Calif., chemical plant.
   The company ordered him to remove records following a raid at a
Torrance, Calif., plant, Bowman alleged.
   Mobil denies wrongdoing, calling Bowman's claims a
``garden-variety'' wrongful firing lawsuit. The company said it had
a right to terminate Bowman, and did so as part of an economic
cutback. Mobil also denies seeking to mask environmental problems,
and accused Bowman of releasing secret company documents to
competitors.
   Mobil also says changes in the environmental reports were minor
matters of wording and typographical errors.
   The focus of Wednesday's hearing is expected to be 20 or so
assessment reports, some filed by each side.
   They are ``the heart of the case,'' said Bowman's attorney,
Stephen B. Wiley. The reports are ``all directly relevant to the
proceeding and should be available to the public,'' he said. ``It's
a public proceeding.''
   Wiley said Mobil was seeking to exclude the public from
Wednesday's hearing, but Mobil attorney Richard Reibstein denied
that.
   ``The reason we're protecting the privacy of these reports is so
we can continue to do them,'' said Mobil Chemical's general
counsel, Ron Neill. ``The whole objective here is in the public
interest.'' If companies felt their self-criticisms could ever be
splashed across newspapers, they would be discouraged from making
such evaluations, he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>