<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0097 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1516EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-State-JunkBonds     12-27 0438</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-State-Junk Bonds,0449</SECOND>
<HEAD>California Eyes Curb on Sale of `Junk Bonds'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SACRAMENTO, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   State regulators, spurred by the
collapse of Lincoln Savings and Loan, intend to prohibit the sale
of high-risk junk bonds from the offices of California's
state-chartered thrifts.
   A temporary order will be issued next week by the state Savings
and Loan Department, Chief Deputy Commissioner William Davis said.
He said his agency will then begin procedures to make the order
permanent.
   The order will affect about 117 state-chartered S&amp;L offices.
Currently, no junk bond sales are taking place in any California
thrift offices, although such practices have occurred in the past,
Davis said.
   ``Just so no one gets that idea in mind, we are saying you can't
do it,'' Davis said Tuesday. ``We just don't think it is a good
idea.''
   An estimated 23,000 investors _ mostly retirees in Southern
California _ claim they lost nearly $250 million when they
purchased uninsured corporate bonds sold by American Continental
Corp., primarily through the 26 offices of Lincoln Savings, its
wholly owned subsidiary.
   The Irvine-based thrift was seized in April by federal
regulators. The takeover is expected to cost $2.5 billion, the
nation's largest thrift bailout.
   Many investors said that because the bonds were sold at savings
and loan offices, they assumed they were insured against loss. The
bonds, sold in 1987 and 1988, now are considered virtually
worthless.
   Davis said similar rules on the sale of junk bonds are
apparently being drafted by the U.S. Office of Thrift Supervision
and by the U.S. Savings and Loan League, a trade association for
the industry.
   John Jones, a spokesman in Washington for the Office of Thrift
Supervision, said Wednesday he didn't know of any such orders.
   The chairman of the federal Securities and Exchange Commission,
Richard Breeden, suggested earlier this year that Congress consider
a ban on junk bond sales from S&amp;L offices. New regulations passed
by Congress already require S&amp;Ls to get rid of their own junk-bond
investments by 1994; those rules don't apply to companies that are
using S&amp;L offices to sell junk bonds to the public.
   At Lincoln, the actual approval to sell the bonds was given by
the state Department of Corporations, which is under fire for its
role.
   With that approval, the state Savings and Loan Department gave
Lincoln Savings permission to lease space in each of its offices
for employees of American Continental to sell the bonds.
   ``There was nothing illegal or illicit about what they were
doing,'' Davis said. But many of the senior citizens were not
knowledgeable enough to realize the risk they were taking, he added.
</TEXT>

</DOC>