<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0130 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1720EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Flight103-USMemorials     12-21 0685</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Flight 103-US Memorials,0703</SECOND>
<HEAD>Flight 103: `A Lot of Tears, A Lot of Anger, A Lot of Unanswered
Questions'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Flight 103 Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto XCAR2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GENEVA COLLINS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Relatives and friends of Americans killed when Pan Am Flight 103
blew up a year ago over Lockerbie, Scotland, honored the 270
victims on Thursday. Bells pealed on the anniversary of the tragedy.
   Pan Am took out full-page ads in newspapers here and abroad
urging the public to pray ``for these and all other victims of
terrorism all over the world'' at 2:02 p.m. EST, the exact time
that the plane exploded.
   In addition to holding memorials at Kennedy, Heathrow and
Frankfort airports, Pan Am spokeswoman Pamela Hanlon said, ``all of
our employees did pause at 2:02 at their workplaces around the
world, observing a moment of silence.''
   Pan Am offered to fly families of victims to memorial services
in Lockerbie. About two dozen attended.
   Those marching past Pan Am headquarters in New York City were
mostly silent in the 20-degree temperatures, although some carried
signs with messages such as ``270 people murdered over Scotland''
and ``We are all victims of Pan Am Flight 103.'' Many wore
photographs of loved ones pinned to their coats. It was an exercise
some relatives go through each month in front of Pan Am to
publicize what they say was lax security that allowed the bomb to
be planted on the plane.
   The protest was followed by a memorial service at St. George's
Episcopal Church attended by about 300 people. The name of each
victim was read aloud and 270 white carnations were placed on a
large Christmas wreath.
   Mary Allen DeSantis, an aunt of 25-year-old victim Julian
Benello, said the memorial activities consist of ``a lot of tears,
a lot of anger and a lot of unanswered questions.''
   Jeannine Boulanger, of Shrewsbury, Mass., whose 21-year-old
daughter died in the crash, said she was angered over Pan Am's ad
asking for a moment of silence for the victims.
   ``That's the reason we're here. Because there was too much
silence,'' she said.
   About 200 people lighted candles and placed remembrance roses at
a service at Holy Trinity Church in Washington, D.C. Dignitaries on
hand included Sir Antony Acland, Britian's ambassador to the United
States, who read a passage from the New Testament.
   ``Terrorism is on the rise and has become a plague of our world
today,'' Bert Ammerman of River Vale, N.J., whose brother Tom was
killed, told the gathering.
   Ammerman, president of a support group of Flight 103 victims'
relatives, also sent an open letter to President Bush urging
stepped-up efforts to punish those responsible for the bombing.
   ``Obviously, nothing you can do will bring back our loved
ones,'' he told Bush in the letter. ``But without appropriate
retaliatory action, terrorist groups and the outlaw nations of the
world will, quite understandably, assume that American citizens are
easy prey any time they want to make their point on the world
stage.''
   Many memorials, like ones in Greensburg, Pa., and Ramsey, N.J.,
consisted of chiming bells at 2:02 p.m. EST.
   Bells also pealed one year to the minute at Syracuse University,
which lost 35 students. Although most students had already departed
for Christmas break, 550 people attended a campus memorial last
week.
   Many of those who lost friends and relatives preferred to mourn
in seclusion.
   In Massachusetts, Emily Pescatore said she could not make it
overseas to commemorate the anniversary of her son's death, so she
arranged for a service Thursday night in a Dedham church that was
to include a candle-lighting ceremony and a bagpipe processional.
Other families of victims were expected to attend; 19 New
Englanders were killed in the explosion.
   John Boland, of Nashua, N.H., who lost his son Stephen, 21, said
he wants publicity about the event to fade because every reminder
is painful.
   ``We have a good two or three weeks, and then we're sitting at
supper, watching the 7 o'clock news, and see a plane coming down,''
he said. ``I don't want to watch it. I've seen that plane come down
enough.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>