<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0830EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Romania-Chronology     12-22 0296</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Chronology,0303</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chronology of Recent Developments in Romania</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a chronology of recent events leading up to today's
reported ouster of Nicolae Ceasescu, Romania's hard-line president
and Communist Party chief.
   Nov. 24 _ Ceausescu is reappointed to another five-year term and
rejects the democratic reforms being adopted elsewhere in Eastern
Europe.
   Dec. 15-16 _ Protesters ring a church in the western town of
Timisoara where authorities want to evict a minister who campaigned
for rights of ethnic Hungarians whose villages were being razed by
the government.
   Dec. 17 _ Thousands of people join the crowd at the church and
riots occur when authorities try to remove the minister. Police
reportedly fire guns and water cannon to disperse crowds. Some
casualties are reported.
   Dec. 18 _ Dozens of deaths a reported in clashes between police
and demonstrators in Timisoara. Romania seals its border with
Yugoslavia. In spite of the violence, Ceausescu travels to Iran for
a state visit.
   Dec. 19 _ Shooting and fires are reported in several cities in
western Romania. Witnesses say up to 400 protesters may be dead.
Soldiers armed with automatic weapons patrol Bucharest streets,
troops surround the capital.
   Dec. 20 _ 10,000 anti-Ceausescu demonstrators reportedly march
unhindered through Timisoara. The government puts troops on a
nationwide alert. Ceausescu returns from Iran as scheduled, blaming
``fascist, reactionary groups'' for the unrest. Witnesses and
diplomats say up 2,000 demonstrators may have died.
   Dec. 21 _ Security forces supported by tanks attack
anti-Ceausescu demonstrations in Bucharest, and 13 people are
reported killed.
   Dec. 22 _ News agencies report the military joins with
demonstrators to overthrow the government. Ceausescu and his wife
fly from the presidential palace by helicopter and are reported to
be fleeing the country.
</TEXT>

</DOC>