<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0303EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Buchwald-Paramount     12-29 0392</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Buchwald-Paramount,0403</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge Ponders Theft Issue In Buchwald Suit</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LINDA DEUTSCH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A racial issue was raised in closing
arguments in a suit accusing Paramount Pictures of plagiarizing Art
Buchwald's idea for a story about an African prince for the Eddie
Murphy movie, ``Coming to America.''
   Superior Court Judge Harvey Schneider took the lawsuit under
submission Thursday after arguments by Buchwald's lawyer and an
attorney for Paramount Pictures.
   Schneider said he would issue a written ruling ``relatively
soon.'' Attorneys said that could mean within three to 15 days.
   Paramount lawyer Robert Draper drew a mild rebuke from the judge
when he tried to inject a racial issue into the lawsuit.
   ``Eddie Murphy is black and Eddie Murphy is a mega-star, and
Eddie Murphy has to make a living,'' attorney Robert Draper began.
``He's not white like Mr. Buchwald. He's not an Eastern
establishment writer like Mr. Buchwald.''
   At that point, Schneider interrupted the attorney's closing
argument.
   ``I don't perceive this to be a case about race,'' the judge
said.
   ``I disagree with your honor,'' said Draper. But he dropped the
subject and moved on to argue there aren't sufficient similarities
between Buchwald's script idea, ``King for a Day,'' and Murphy's
box office hit, ``Coming to America'' to show that one was based on
the other.
   Attorney Pierce O'Donnell, representing Buchwald, argued there
are at least 14 points and perhaps as many as 35 points of
similarity between the scripts. Both involve an African member of
royalty coming to the United States, living in a ghetto, working at
a fast food restaurant, falling in love and taking home a bride.
   O'Donnell cited Paramount's 1983 contract with Buchwald to
produce his brief treatment entitled, ``King for a Day,'' and said
it was clearly the inspiration for Murphy's film. Buchwald is
seeking $5 million in actual damages and unspecified punitive
damages from the studio.
   ``Hollywood makes movies, but not without ideas,'' O'Donnell
declared. ``At minimum, what Paramount bought was an idea, a
concept. It was unique. It was original ... as it turned out, this
was a $400 million idea.''
   Schneider pressed both lawyers to tell him what elements would
combine to prove that a movie was based upon another script or
idea. He called the issue amorphous and said the evidence had
failed to clarify it.
</TEXT>

</DOC>