<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0168 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2014EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Somalia-Ship     12-18 0303</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Somalia-Ship,0312</SECOND>
<HEAD>Somalia Confirms Rebels Seized Italian Ship</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOGADISHU, Somalia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Somalia acknowledged Monday that
northern rebels seized an Italian ship and its crew of 16 more than
a week ago and still held them. The rebels said the ship was
delivering fuel to government troops.
   A source from the rebel Somali National Movement said in
Djibouti the ship and its crew of two Italians and 14 Somalis were
taken without a fight off northern Somalia, carrying fuel from
Djibouti.
   The source, speaking on condition of anonymity, said Astaldi
Consortium, an Italian contruction company, leased the ship, the
Kwanda, to the Somali government to transport fuel and supplies to
troops battling the rebels.
   In Rome, Astaldi chairman Mario Astaldi confirmed the ship was
seized and the crew held, but said the Kwanda, a converted military
landing craft, was carrying fuel not for Somali troops but for a
consortium of Italian construction companies building roads in
northern Somalia.
   At a Monday briefing for foreign military attaches in Mogadishu,
Somalia's capital, the armed forces confirmed the seizure on or
about Dec. 11 and said the ship was carrying 350 tons of petroleum
products, mostly diesel fuel, according to diplomatic sources.
   They said the craft apparently was captured by rebels in
speedboats armed with machineguns.
   Astaldi said his company was in daily contact with the ship.
   ``Everyone is fine and they are aboard the Kwanda under guard,''
he said.
   Astaldi said the ship was at anchor and the rebels were taking
off the fuel.
   He cautioned news media ``not to prejudice the negotiations
under way to free the crew.''
   The Somali National Movement has fought Somalia's autocratic
government since 1981 and recently stepped up its offensives.
President Mohamed Siad Barre has ruled the Horn of Africa nation
since taking power in a 1969 coup.
</TEXT>

</DOC>