<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0601EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BroussardsReunited     12-20 0613</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Broussards Reunited,0631</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ecclesia Leader to Regain Custody of Children</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARILYNN WHEELER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The four children of Ecclesia leader
Eldridge Broussard Jr. are returning to their father's care for the
first time since their 8-year-old sister was beaten to death by
four of his followers.
   ``I want them home in time for Christmas,'' Judge Robert J.
Morgan said in setting today as a deadline for the children to be
released to their parents.
   ``It will be good to get my children back,'' Broussard told
reporters at the conclusion of the four-day custody hearing.
   A Clackamas County Circuit Court judge agreed last month to
allow custodial visits to resume between Broussard, his wife and
their surviving children.
   The Broussard children, ages 5 to 11, have been in state care
since the sensational child abuse case erupted. Thirty-three
Ecclesia children remain in foster homes, according to the state
Children's Services Division.
   On Oct. 14, 1988, the body of Dayna Broussard was taken to a
rural fire station by members of the Ecclesia Athletic Association,
a religious and athletic training group founded by Broussard in the
Watts section of Los Angeles.
   The next day, state juvenile authorities were dispatched to
Ecclesia's farmhouse east of Portland, where they found 55 hungry,
abused children crammed into four bedrooms. The youngsters were
loaded onto buses and turned over to the Children's Services
Division.
   Broussard, who was in California at the time of the beating,
defended the four Ecclesia staff members charged with first-degree
manslaughter.
   He denied that he was a cult leader and that the Ecclesia
children had been mistreated. But during the trial, four of the
children testified how they had witnessed young Dayna's punishment
for taking food from another child's plate. They said they were
forced to watch and count the blows _ more than 800.
   In May, three men and a woman were convicted in the killing, and
they were sentenced to maximum 20-year prison terms in June. Later,
a fifth member was convicted of criminal mistreatment for beating
other children.
   By that time, the Ecclesia Athletic Association had disbanded
and Broussard, who once defended his group on Oprah Winfrey's
television show, had begun to fade from the public eye.
   On the anniversary of the beating death, 40 of the children
remained in foster homes. Children's Services Division officials
said their parents had refused to admit past abuses or to promise
they would be safe from abuse.
   The following week there was a turning point in the case, when
Broussard appeared at a custody hearing for his 3-year-old nephew.
For the first time, he acknowledged that Ecclesia members had been
culpable in his daughter's death.
   The response was immediate from Morgan, who ruled the boy could
be returned to his parents by year's end.
   The following month, Broussard and his wife returned to court to
request custody of their own children.
   Broussard broke into tears while defending his assertion that
adult Ecclesia members put group concerns ahead of the children's
needs.
   Morgan told Broussard he was moved by his show of emotion.
``Maybe it's says something that hasn't been said before,'' said
Morgan. ``Everyone is sorry it happened. It's now history. We must
look ahead.''
   On Nov. 16, the Broussards' custody request was granted.
   The parents were given a list of 11 conditions to meet, among
them that corporal punishment would be forbidden and that the
children must attend public schools and undergo regular mental
health counseling.
   State Children's Services Division spokesman Bart Wilson
confirmed Tuesday that the Broussards were give the final go-ahead
on Dec. 13, but he declined to reveal further details of the
family's plans.
</TEXT>

</DOC>