<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1210EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Bush-Panama Bjt   12-23 0794</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Panama, Bjt,770</SECOND>
<HEAD>Political Risk for Bush Grows as Panama Operation Drags On</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERENCE HUNT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP White House Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush's order to send American troops
into combat in Panama, initially greeted with broad support in
Congress, could backfire politically if casualties continue to
mount and the United States becomes bogged down there.
   The dangers are clear.
   How high will the U.S. death toll climb? Will deposed ruler
Manuel Noriega continue to evade U.S. forces that were once
confident of capturing him?
   Will the fragile government of Guillermo Endara, installed by
the United States but dependent on U.S. power for his authority,
take hold?
   How long before U.S. forces can be withdrawn?
   And, what about American hostages?
   The hazards were demonstrated after Bush declared the situation
``pretty well wrapped up'' Thursday and military officers described
it as a mopping-up operation.
   On Friday, Noriega loyalists attacked the headquarters of U.S.
military forces and Gen. Maxwell R. Thurman, commander in chief of
the U.S. Southern Command, said U.S. forces were still fighting ``a
real war.''
   The stubborn resistance prompted the Pentagon to order an
additional 2,000 soldiers into Panama, backing up a force of nearly
24,000 already there.
   For now, the political support for Bush's action seems to be
holding.
   ``We're in the adrenalin-pumping stage, the first
rally-around-the-flag moments,'' said Stephen Hess, a Brookings
Institution senior fellow and specialist on the presidency. ``There
hasn't been any major downside but you can start seeing it coming.''
   University of Virginia political scientist Larry Sabato said,
``The first reaction is to support the president but then the
doubts start seeping in and the worries and the questions.''
   William Schneider, a senior fellow at the American Enterprise
Institute and a political analyst, said, ``The only question is
whether it's going to work and whether it's going to work quickly.
   ``Americans don't like to make an open-ended commitment
anywhere, particularly where it involves the loss of American
lives,'' Schneider said.
   ``Americans believe we should win or get out. In Grenada, we
won. In Lebanon, we got out.''
   Bush said U.S. forces will chase Noriega ``as long as it
takes.'' He said the deployment of combat troops in Panama is
open-ended as the chase continues and U.S. forces try to restore
some semblance of order to the country.
   Already, there are demands in Congress for American troops to be
brought home quickly.
   But Rep. Les Aspin, D-Wis., chairman of the House Armed Services
Committee, said some U.S. forces might have to remain as police
until ``Christmas Eve a year from now.''
   A military operation initially described as a three- to four-day
mission now stretches into the indefinite future.
   White House officials insist, however, that the operation is
following the script they envisioned.
   White House press secretary Marlin Fitzwater said Gen. Colin
Powell, the chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, briefed Bush
last Sunday on the risks and ``laid it out almost exactly as it
materialized.''
   He said Powell accurately predicted Noriega would not be
captured immediately, that hostages might be taken and that there
would be a protracted period before U.S. forces would wrest control
of Panama City from Noriega's Panamanian Defense Forces and his
so-called Dignity Battalions.
   Fitzwater also said the U.S. death count will not be large.
   ``It doesn't seem likely there would be large-scale engagements
with large amounts of casualties,'' he said.
   Before the invasion, U.S. intelligence sources had reported that
Noriega was drinking heavily and that his mental state had
deteriorated.
   ``General Noriega ... has been acting irrationally, beyond his
normal conduct,'' said Sen. Sam Nunn, D-Ga., chairman of the Senate
Armed Services Committee.
   Nunn said administration officials, in private briefings for
Congress, ``made a very strong case'' for the invasion. However,
there are fears that public opinion may turn against Bush if the
operation drags on.
   Hess said Bush ``probably doesn't have more than a month of real
grace. The trick is always that it doesn't become our war.''
   Schneider, the AEI analyst, said, ``The best outcome for the
Bush administration would be for this guy to be dead, not make
trouble for anybody.''
   But the Panamanian leader remains at large, while U.S.
casualties mount. And even if he is captured, the onetime CIA
operative could make some embarrassing demands for secret documents
if brought to trial in the United States.
   ``He knows where a lot of skeletons are buried in Central
America and some of them may be very close to Bush's office,''
Schneider said, noting contacts between Bush's vice presidential
staff and key figures in the Iran-Contra affair.
   ``If Noriega's caught,'' Schneider said, ``that's not the end of
the matter.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Terence Hunt is chief White House correspondent
for The Associated Press.
</TEXT>

</DOC>