<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0171 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 2242EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-MormonAttacks     12-29 0476</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mormon Attacks,0498</SECOND>
<HEAD>Leftists Bomb Temple, Threaten Mormons and U.S. Agents</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LIMA, Peru (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pro-Cuban rebels dynamited a Mormon temple in
an interior city and left leaflets threatening church workers and
U.S. drug agents, a radio report said Friday. It said the threat
was in response to the U.S. invasion of Panama.
   Police said the rebels also bombed a bank in suburban Lima.
   In neighboring Chile, suspected members of another radical
leftist group doused a Mormon chapel in Santiago with gasoline and
set it on fire.
   All three attacks caused damage but no casualties.
   Several temples of the Utah-based Mormon church and U.S.
cultural centers have been attacked in both countries in recent
days.
   Radio Programas broadcast its report from the jungle city of
Tarapoto, 435 miles north of Lima, saying rebels of the Tupac Amaru
Revolutionary Movement bombed the Mormon temple there Thursday
night.
   The report said the rebels left behind leaflets telling Mormon
church workers and U.S. drug agents to leave the department of San
Martin within 10 days.
   Authorities in Tarapoto could not be reached Friday to confirm
the story, and a U.S. Embassy spokesman in Lima said he had no
information.
   The U.S.-built anti-drug base at Santa Lucia is in San Martin
department. Twenty to 40 Americans, including agents, contract
helicopter pilots and mechanics, are stationed there to help
Peruvian police in raids against clandestine airstrips and drug
laboratories used in the cocaine trade.
   Tupac Amaru rebels dynamited three Mormon temples and a
Peruvian-American cultural center Tuesday in the northern coastal
city of Chiclayo and another center Friday in Arequipa in the
southern highlands.
   The pro-Cuban Tupac Amaru launched its armed insurgency against
Peru's elected government in 1984. The group takes its name from a
18th century mestizo revolutionary who fought Spanish colonial rule
in the Andean highlands.
   In the bank bombing, police said Tupac Amaru rebels detonated
explosives at the Bandesco bank branch in residential San Isidro.
   In Friday's attack in Santiago, police said the fire was quickly
extinguished at the small chapel in Villa Frei, a working-class
neighborhood.
   The Lautaro Commando, a radical leftist organization, claimed
responsibility for the attack, police said.
   It was the fifth attack on Mormon chapels since Sunday in
Santiago and provincial cities. In the other attacks, four chapels
were damaged by bombs. No one claimed responsibility for those
blasts.
   In one case, the attackers wrote slogans on chapel walls
condemning the Panamanian invasion.
   Late Thursday, a bomb exploded at the bathroom of the U.S.
cultural center in downtown Santiago, causing damage but no
victims, police said.
   The Lautaro group took responsibility for dozens of attacks on
Mormon chapels in the last few years, saying the church is ``a tool
of Yankee imperialism.''
   The group takes its name from an Indian chief who fought the
Spanish conquerors in the 16th century.
</TEXT>

</DOC>