<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2354EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Germany-Menuhin     12-18 0311</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Germany-Menuhin,0319</SECOND>
<HEAD>Famed Violinist Conducts Benefit for Decaying East German Cities</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In a benefit concert to help rebuild decaying
East German city centers, Sir Yehudi Menuhin conducted the renowned
East German State Orchestra as it performed for the first time in
West Berlin.
   The opening of East Germany's borders Nov. 9 allowed East
Germany's famous orchestra to travel easily to the great hall of
the Sender Freies Berlin radio station for Monday's hastily
arranged concert.
   For more than four decades, the 73-year-old violinist has taken
his music around the world to play benefits, first for the Allied
Forces in World War II, for fellow Jews who had survived the
Holocaust and much later for German-Jewish reconciliation.
   In an interview during the intermission of the concert, which
was broadcast live and could be heard in East Berlin, Menuhin said
the time was past to think badly of Communists and that all should
now focus on East-West cooperation.
   The classical program included works by Ludwig van Beethoven and
Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart.
   Speaking German in the interview, Menuhin said he had last
played in Berlin in 1929 as a teen-ager at the Berlin Philharmonic
with the legendary conductor Bruno Walter.
   He said that the opening of the wall was a ``phenomenon which is
very moving and unbelievable.''
   ``Music has managed to get over the wall,'' he said. ``That is
not possible everywhere, but you feel when you go to countries
where people suffer or can't say what they want that music has a
value that is hard to imagine in other countries.''
   The centers of many historic German cities like Leipzig, Weimar
and Jena have been ravaged by pollution, poor city planning and
shoddy post-war construction.
   Menuhin joins other famous musicians such as Mstislav
Rostropovich and Daniel Barenboim in staging benefits for East
Germany since the wall was opened.
</TEXT>

</DOC>