<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0160 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1603EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-Symposium-SouthAsia Adv31   12-26 0830</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Symposium-South Asia, Adv 31,0850</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 31, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WORLD SYMPOSIUM '90s: South Asia _ Threshhold of Change</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EARLEEN FISHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Afghanistan, Pakistan, India and Sri
Lanka _ a swath of turbulence through South Asia _ enter the 1990s
still trying to sort out their individual and overlapping destinies.
   Each of the four nations is on the threshhold of change,
teetering between the possibility for passable stability and the
specter of more chaos, political, military or both.
   The most dramatic conflagrations are the two wars anchoring each
end of this geographical arc that begins at Afghanistan and ends in
Sri Lanka off southern India.
   Afghanistan's civil war through the 1980s was a proxy
battlefield for the ideological war and balance of power between
the United States and the Soviet Union. With the Red Army's
withdrawal in early 1989, the superpower involvement is less overt
but not yet over.
   In contrast, Sri Lanka's tangle of ethnic and political killing
is one of those messy and obscure wars that have little bearing on
the affairs of other nations.
   For India and Pakistan, the coming decade offers a testing
ground for democracy and a chance to continue the thaw of
hostilities that took them to war three times in the past.
   In India's case, both the concept and practice of democracy have
been entrenched since independence from Britain in 1947.
   But the derailment of the Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi in
November's elections has given Indians the opportunity to prove
their democracy has truly come of age.
   As new Prime Minister V.P. Singh contends with his implausible
coalition of Hindu right-wingers, secular centrists and
increasingly anachronistic communists, India will discover whether
it can find enduring leadership outside the Congress Party dynasty
of prime ministers that began with Gandhi's grandfather, Jawaharlal
Nehru, and, except for brief hiccoughs, passed on to Gandhi's
mother, Indira Gandhi.
   In his first few days of office, Singh took encouraging steps
toward resolving the separatist Sikh revolt in Punjab and now must
capitalize on them.
   In Pakistan, which also became independent in 1947, when it was
carved out of British India to give Moslems a nation separate from
the Hindus, democracy has had a far more spasmodic and difficult
birth.
   Prime Minister Benazir Bhutto, who attained office through the
ballot box in 1988 after the death of the coup-installed president,
Gen. Mohammad Zia ul-Haq, must tread carefully. Her government
supplanted 11 years of military rule but is still juggling an array
of threats.
   Moslem fundamentalists reject the very idea of a woman heading a
government. Less dogmatic politicians simply want their chance to
grasp power. And although the armed forces may have retreated from
the front lines of political office-holding, they are unwilling to
relinquish their not-so-behind-the-scenes power.
   Afghanistan's President Najib, the ex-secret police chief who
with Soviet backing muscled aside an even harsher Kremlin protege
in 1986, has proved an adept player of the Afghan game. But he is
only a survivor, not a victor. Ostensibly, his chief enemies are
the mujahedeen, the fractured alliance of Moslem guerrillas armed
by the United States and neighboring Pakistan.
   But Najib must also contend with the power-hungry opponents
within his own People's Democratic Party of Afghanistan. As
Communist Party power delines in Eastern Europe so, too, could it
subside in Afghanistan, whose tribal society has never been fertile
ground for either Marxism or centralized government.
   The Soviets continue to supply and coach Najib's government,
while the United States continues to aid the mujahedeen, or Islamic
holy warriors, through its ally, Pakistan.
   India, the region's strongest military power, is still embroiled
in a border dispute with Pakistan over Kashmir. On the Indian side
of the contested frontier, increasingly violent Moslem militants
want Kashmir to join Pakistan or become independent.
   India also must re-assess the role of regional policeman it
eagerly embraced in the late 1980s when it sent troops to the
Maldives in the Indian Ocean to thwart a coup and to Sri Lanka to
try to halt internal strife between the Sinhalese majority and
Tamil minority.
   The Maldivian deployment was a success, but India had mixed
success as a peacemaker in Sri Lanka and is now pledging a speedy
end to its 2{-year military adventure.
   Indian intervention set in motion the long-overdue but still
incomplete formula to help Tamils wrest more political power from
the Sinhalese-controlled central government.
   But this foreign-inspired political pact, coupled with India's
bulldozer approach to peacekeeping, touched off even greater
violence by popping the cork on a bottle full of evil genies.
   Tamils and Sinhalese rarely fight each other any more. Instead,
Tamils are killing Tamils and Sinhalese are killing Sinhalese in
fights for dominance within each ethnic community.
   Still, the 1990s offer Sri Lanka the chance _ perhaps its last _
to climb out of anarchy before the skeleton of democracy succumbs
to the flames of war.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Sunday, Dec. 31</NOTE>

</DOC>