<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1435EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-Corruption     12-17 0725</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Corruption,0752</SECOND>
<HEAD>East Germans Feel Betrayed, Angry as Corruption Revelations Grow</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-East Germany, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KEVIN COSTELLOE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When she lived in near poverty with a young
son, Romy Koecher often heard East Germany's Communist leaders
proclaim they were doing everything they could for the country.
   Now, as disclosures grow about the lavish living of former
leader Erich Honecker and his ousted cronies, she feels deeply
betrayed.
   ``I always knew there were privileged layers in society,'' says
the 32-year-old art historian. ``But people just didn't know the
extent of what was going on.''
   For years, Honecker manipulated the official news media to
proclaim a phoenix-like recovery from the ashes of World War II and
accused the West of waiting to plunder East Germany.
   But according to recent revelations, Honecker and his friends
were themselves plundering the country. There were fancy hunting
lodges, imported foods and clothes, shining Volvos.
   So far, the allegations have hit mainly a several dozen top
Communist Party members, and much of the ousted leadership faces
criminal prosecution. Seven former Politburo members are in jail,
and Honecker is under house arrest.
   Wandlitz, the compound where the party bosses lived, is being
turned into a health center for children. The compound includes an
indoor swimming pool, perfectly manicured grounds and houses that
are the envy of the rest of the nation's 16.3 million people.
   Honecker's summer retreat, complete with two restaurants, is
being turned into a tourist hotel that can accommodate 50 people.
   ``I never knew there were these mafia-like organizations,'' said
Ms. Koecher, referring to businesses set up to hide financial
irregularities.
   The accusations of corruption reached a peak on Dec. 1, when one
member of Parliament suggested the disgraced leaders stashed $54
billion in Swiss bank accounts.
   While prosecutors have not used that figure, they have said that
hundreds of millions of dollars left the country.
   The reform movements in other Soviet bloc countries have not led
to anything like East Germany's anti-corruption fervor.
   Opposition leader Vaclav Havel said that if he is elected
Czechoslovakia's president he will try to prevent a ``witchhunt''
against the Communists.
   ``There must be justice, but not revenge,'' Havel said.
   Polish Prime Minister Taduesz Mazowiecki, a member of the
Solidarity opposition, has cut off government subsidies that helped
the Communist Party build a vast bureaucracy and acquire companies,
buildings, hotels, fleets of cars and garages. The government has
said it has no plans to recover property, however.
   The best-known Soviet case involved Yuri Churbanov, son-in-law
of the late Kremlin leader Leonid I. Brezhnev. Churbanov, former
deputy interior minister, was convicted a year ago of taking bribes
and is serving a 12-year prison term.
   The current leaders are fanning popular resentment of
corruption, in part to deflect any criticism of them.
   ``The whole thing is being played up,'' says Guenther Buch, a
West German government expert on East German affairs. ``Certainly,
people knew about it. But before, people were punished if they
started talking.''
   ``Now they're venting their anger,'' he said.
   Buch said he fears the resentment could turn into violence,
especially if there are disclosures of corruption in the middle and
lower levels of the Communist Party.
   In an interview with the Communist newspaper Junge Welt,
opposition leader Rainer Eppelmann said he believes there also are
cases of corruption in the four parties long allied with the
Communists.
   The former head of one of those parties, the Christian
Democrats, already is under investigation for unspecified financial
irregularities.
   Part of East Germany's anti-corruption campaign is in the hands
of a commission headed by new Communist Party chief Gregor Gysi.
   Gysi, a 41-year-old lawyer, has promised to uncover all abuse
but has cautioned against ``tearing ourselves to pieces.''
   One of the best-known cases of corruption so far is that of
Alexander Schalck-Golodkowski, wanted for overseeing a ring that
sold weapons to countries in South America, Africa and the Middle
East.
   The former top-ranking government official is in a West Berlin
prison and says he will fight any extradition attempts.
   He has said he was repaying about $30 million to East Germany
from Swiss bank accounts, but that is only a small part of what the
nation's official news media claim he embezzled.
   ``Schalck-Golodkowski is worried he'll be sacrificed if he is
sent back,'' says his West Berlin lawyer, Peter Danckert.
</TEXT>

</DOC>