<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0086 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1347EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-HongKong     12-21 0425</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Hong Kong,0437</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Conservative Party Chairman Denounces Hong Kong Plan</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The former Conservative Party chairman on Thursday
denounced as ``folly'' the government's plan to give residence
rights to 225,000 Hong Kong people.
   Norman Tebbit said he would join other Tory rebels to vote with
the opposition Labor Party against the policy, which he said has
split Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher's Conservative Party ``from
top to bottom.''
   Conservatives have expressed concern the plan will encourage a
wave of immigration in Britain. The Labor Party called it
``divisive and elitist.''
   Tebbit spoke in favor of the past Conservative policy allowing
no further large-scale immigration and said British people fear
they will be ``swamped by people of different culture, history and
religion. ... The fact is that most people in Britain did not want
to live in a multicultural, multiracial society, but it has been
foisted on them.''
   The plan announced Wednesday by Foreign Secretary Douglas Hurd
aims to prevent a crippling brain drain from Hong Kong before it
reverts to rule by China when Britain's lease on the colony expires
in 1997.
   Hurd told the House of Commons that a maximum of 50,000 key
people in Hong Kong, plus their families, would be given full
British citizenship. He estimated the total at 225,000.
   Some 50 Tory members pledged to vote against the measure when it
is put to the House of Commons in the spring. Another 20 to 30
Tories might abstain, the British news agency Press Association
estimated.
   The Conservatives have 374 seats in the 650-seat Commons. Labor
has 229.
   ``The government's decision ... has split the party from top to
bottom,'' Tebbit said in an article he wrote for London's Evening
Standard. ``There is no doubt that in the Cabinet itself, the home
secretary and the foreign secretary led bitterly opposed factions.
   ``The word at present is that the final rebellion will be more
like 50 than 100.''
   He said party officials who ``saw the danger'' of Mrs.
Thatcher's policy ``failed to prevent such a folly.''
   Speaking earlier on BBC radio, Tebbit said the residence rights
would involve more than the number indicated by Hurd. It would mean
``wives and husbands, sisters, cousins, aunts and grandmothers,''
Tebbit said.
   About 3.25 million Hong Kong Chinese have British passports, but
no residence rights.
   Earlier, Foreign Office official Francis Maude repeated the
government's aim was not to encourage immigration from Hong Kong
but to allow key people to stay there under the Chinese by giving
them an ``escape route'' if they needed it.
</TEXT>

</DOC>