<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0947EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Bethlehem-Christmas     12-23 0513</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bethlehem-Christmas,0527</SECOND>
<HEAD>Palestinians Vow Clashes to Mark Holiday</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HAITHAM HAMAD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BETHLEHEM, Occupied West Bank (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israeli paratroopers closed
stores and ordered Bethlehem holiday shoppers home today after a
clash with masked youths near the traditional site of the birth of
Christ.
   In another development, visiting South African Archbishop
Desmond Tutu bowed his head in silent prayer at a memorial to slain
Palestinians and told Arab religious leaders and activists: ``We
support your struggle for ... statehood and independence.''
   In the occupied Gaza Strip, three Palestinian youths were
wounded by gunshots in clashes with troops, Arab hospital officials
said.
   In Bethlehem, masked youths burned tires and hurled stones at
army patrols across from the Church of the Nativity. The site marks
the manger where tradition holds Jesus was born.
   Troops dispersed the stonethrowers by shooting in the air and
firing tear gas into the narrow alleyways of the nearby
marketplace, where the youths fled.
   Paratroopers and purple-bereted troops from the elite Givati
brigade ran through the marketplace shouting ``Ruhi el-beit,''
Arabic for go home, to holiday shoppers and demanded that local
youths use brooms to sweep the streets clean of debris from the
burning tires.
   One enraged woman shopper turned to a soldier and said: ``You
can't close the shops, this is our holiday,'' but the soldier
ordered her home.
   Slogans were seen throughout the town calling for increased
clashes with troops to mark the holiday.
   ``Let's escalate against the Zionists on Christmas Day,'' was
spray-painted in black on one stone wall. It was signed by the
clandestine underground leadership of the uprising.
   The underground leadership had ordered merchants to stay open
until 5 p.m. and not close at noon to mark a Palestinian strike
that has been in force since the start of the uprising against
Israeli occupation two-years ago.
   At least 637 Palestinians have been killed by Israeli troops or
civilians since the Palestinian revolt began. Forty-three Israelis
also have died in the violence and Palestinians have slain 161 of
their fellow Arabs on suspicion of cooperating with Israeli
authorities.
   Also today, the Islamic fundamentalist Hamas movement canceled a
Christmas Day strike after protests from Palestinian Christians and
resheduled the work stoppage for Dec. 27.
   On Jerusalem's Temple Mount, a site regarded as holy to both
Jews and Moslems, Tutu joined Moslem religious leaders and
Palestinian activists including leading PLO-supporter Feisal
Husseini in a moment of prayer at a stone memorial for slain
Palestinians.
   The stone prayer platform was built in memory of the more than
600 Palestinians killed by Israeli-supported Christian militiamen
in 1982 at the Sabra and Chatilla refugee camps near Beirut.
   ``We support the struggle of the Palestinian people in their
longing for statehood and independence,'' Tutu told the gathering
of about 30 Palestinian dignitaries. ``We are struggling for our
own self-determination in South Africa.''
   ``We pray that the day will come soon when a Palestinian state
will exist side by side with a Jewish state and Arab and Jew will
hold hands together,'' said Tutu, who arrived Friday on a five-day
pilgrimage.
</TEXT>

</DOC>