<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1422EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Noriega-Precedent 1stLd-Writethru a0508 12-30 0760</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Noriega-Precedent, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0508,690</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pope Freely Turned Over Surratt, Suspected in Lincoln Assassination</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: SUBS 12th graf pvs, bgng: Unfortunately, Surratt, with 3 grafs
to note differences in Surratt, Noriega cases. Picks up 13th graf pvs,
The arresting</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RUTH SINAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   There is historical precedent for the Vatican
agreeing to turn over a fugitive to the United States, although the
Holy See maintains it cannot surrender ousted strongman Gen. Manuel
Antonio Noriega from its embassy in Panama.
   The Vatican adopted an entirely different position when asked to
turn over one of the suspected conspirators in the 1865
assassination of President Abraham Lincoln, John H. Surratt Jr.
   Surratt, a young Confederate spy who had conspired with John
Wilkes Booth to abduct Lincoln in 1864, fled after Booth shot
Lincoln on April 14, 1865.
   Surratt, a devout Catholic, changed his name to John Watson and
joined Pope Pius IX's Zouaves Regiment in late 1865 or early 1866.
The unit was part of the army that defended the Papal States, at
that time an independent country about the size of West Virginia,
against claims by Italian nationalists.
   Surratt was located in 1866 with the help of an informer who
recognized him and reported to U.S. authorities, whereupon
Secretary of State William H. Seward notified Secretary of War E.M.
Stanton.
   ``As we have no treaty of extradition with the papal government,
it is proposed that a special agent be sent to Rome to demand the
surrender of Surratt,'' Seward wrote Stanton on May 28, 1866.
   Accordingly, the U.S. envoy to the Vatican, Rufus King, sought a
meeting with the pope's foreign minister Cardinal Antonelli to tell
him about Surratt.
   ``His Eminence was greatly interested by it, and intimated that
if the American government desired the surrender of the criminal,
there would probably be no difficulty in any way,'' King wrote
Seward on Aug. 8.
   Several months later, having ascertained that Watson was indeed
the fugitive Surratt, Seward instructed King to ask the cardinal
``whether his Holiness (the pope) would now be willing, in the
absence of an extradition treaty, to deliver John H. Surratt upon
authentic indictment and at the request of this department, for
complicity in the assassination of the late President Abraham
Lincoln.''
   So eager was the Vatican to help the United States, that it did
not even wait for an official request and ordered Surratt arrested
immediately.
   ``Some surprise perhaps may be expressed that Surratt was
arrested by the Papal authorities before any request to that effect
had been made by the American government,'' King wrote Seward.
Vatican authorities ``gave me to understand that the arrest was
made with the approval of his Holiness, and in anticipation of any
application from the State Department.''
   The Surratt and Noriega cases are similar in that the Vatican
still doesn't have an extradition treaty with the United States _
or Panama _ but the two incidents differ in another significant way.
   In the present instance, the Vatican says its embassy can't,
under international law, give up an asylum-seeker to a third
country _ the United States. It can only give up Noriega to Panama,
the Vatican says, if it decides Noriega doesn't qualify as a
political asylum case.
   Surratt's case didn't end with papal cooperation, however, for
the fugitive proved to be wilier and more agile than the six men
sent to escort him from his regiment to Rome on Nov. 8, 1866.
   The arresting officer reported to his superiors that Surratt,
alias Watson, ``leapt from a height of 23 feet on a very narrow
rock,'' landed on a garbage heap, and disappeared.
   King received repeated assurances and documentation from
Cardinal Antonelli proving the Vatican's good faith in the affair
and describing efforts to locate Surratt. In fact, several days
after the escape, the papal war minister Gen. Kauster ``called to
inform me of a rumor which had reached him'' that a wounded Surratt
had checked himself into an Italian hospital near the papal
frontier, King wrote Seward.
   A U.S. diplomat gave chase from Rome, but missed Surratt, who
had set sail for Egypt on Nov. 17, 1866.
   Surratt eventually was tracked down in Alexandria, and a U.S.
warship brought him back to the United States.
   A postscript to the affair:
   Surratt's mother, Mary, who ran a boarding house that Booth and
his co-conspirators had used as a meeting place, was hanged along
with three other group members.
   Surratt was tried by a civil court in Washington in 1867. He was
freed by a hung jury.
</TEXT>

</DOC>