<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0141EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>b i AM-Panama 5thLd-Writethru a0417 12-20 1029</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0417,1064</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Fighting In Panama Between U.S.-Panamanian Troops</HEAD>
<HEAD>LEADS with 15 grafs with details of fighting; Picks up 16th pvs,
`A U.S. ...'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Machine-gun and cannon fire resounded
through the capital Tuesday night as U.S. tanks and truckloads of
American troops headed toward Panama's military headquarters in an
apparent bid to oust Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   The Panamanian leader had said Friday that Panama was in a
``state of war'' with the United States and the following day a
U.S. Marine lieutenant was killed by Panamanians in what American
officials called an unprovoked attack.
   U.S. troops in Panama have been on maximum alert since and on
Monday a U.S. military officer wounded a Panamanian police officer
in what he said was self-defense.
   An Associated Press reporter saw 24 U.S. tanks and at least four
trucks carrying American troops head in the direction of Panamanian
Defense Forces headquarters on Tuesday night. Troops in olive
uniforms ran through the luxury Marriott Hotel and lights in the
hotel went out.
   Channel 8, television station of the U.S. Southern Command,
issued an Echo level alert, its highest, and said movement by
unauthorized U.S. personnel was prohibited.
   The roar of planes and helicopters were heard over the city.
   Earlier Tuesday, Panama accused the U.S. forces of violating its
air space with ``observation planes and helicopters'' in
preparation for military action.
   Frequent movements of U.S. soldiers and equipment have been seen
within U.S. military installations the past three days, and
appeared to escalate Tuesday at Howard Air Force Base. About 12,000
American soldiers are stationed along the Panama Canal.
   The United States has tried to oust Noriega, who controls the
Panamanian military and the country, since he was indicted on
federal drug trafficking charges in February 1988.
   U.S. sanctions have depressed the economy, but have not budged
Noriega, and two coup attempts _ most recently in October _ failed
to unseat him.
   An NBC News broadcast Tuesday showed what it said were C-141
Starlifter transport planes landing in Panama in the afternoon. It
said one plane was landing every 10 minutes and that security had
been tightened around the air base.
   Later Tuesday, a New York Times reporter and a Reuters reporter
were detained for about an hour by U.S. military police when they
tried to enter Howard air base to determine whether U.S. forces
were landing.
   The Times reporter's notebooks were confiscated by the U.S.
Army, the Times said in New York, and the two reporters were
released without incident.
   An AP reporter who drove through Howard air base Tuesday night
saw at least 10 large transport planes, an unusually high number.
There also were six to eight helicopters parked there, in contrast
to the usual three or four.
   It was not clear what kind of planes they were or whether they
transported troops or cargo.
   A U.S. Southern Command spokesman said earlier Tuesday ``no
unusual military activity'' was taking place. Later he said he knew
nothing about the reported arrival of C-141 planes.
   At Fort Clayton, headquarters of the U.S. Army South, tanks were
pulled into a circle in an open area and troops climbed on and off
them in routine cleaning and exercises Tuesday afternoon.
   Trucks and armored personnel carriers also were moved into
public view.
   Telephone lines to the Southern Command offices at Quarry
Heights and to officers' homes were busy late Tuesday. Access to
Quarry Heights is limited, but a public road goes through Howard.
   Earlier Tuesday, C-141 planes were seen in the air around Fort
Bragg, N.C., home of the Army's 82nd Airborne division. It was not
known if they were connected to any U.S. military activity in
Panama.
   Fort Bragg spokesmen would say only that Army units there were
taking part in a routine ``emergency deployment readiness
exercise.'' Sgt. Bobby Feibel, a spokesman for the division, said
he had no information on reports that some of the division had left
Fort Bragg.
   In California, soldiers of the 7th Infantry Division (Light)
were mobilized Monday at Fort Ord Army base, also for a readiness
exercise, said base public affairs officer Jim Davis.
   ``As a matter of policy, we do not address destination, unit
size, unit designation, or times of departure,'' Davis added.
   Lt. Pascual Gonzalez, director of civil aviation, said Panama
has ``a critical situation'' with the United States. ``We think the
level of aggression and intimidation will increase,'' he told The
Associated Press.
   ``There are helicopters flying during the night over our
installations,'' he said.
   At the State Department in Washington, spokeswoman Margaret
Tutwiler said Noriega's declaration last week that a state of war
existed with the United States, followed by ``indiscriminate and
unprovoked violence against Americans, clearly increases tensions
in Panma.''
   Ms. Tutwiler would not say what contingencies or options were
under consideration.
   Panamanian officials say the American officer was killed when he
and three others drove a car past checkpoints, then fired at
Noriega's military headquarters building, wounding two civilians
and a soldier.
   The United States says the four were unarmed, in civilian
clothes, when they got lost near the headquarters.
   Lt. Robert Paz, 25, who had been in Panama since September, was
killed when the group fled civilians and soldiers who tried to
force them from their car at the checkpoint, Southern Command said.
   On Monday, a U.S. Army officer wounded a Panamanian police
corporal because he thought the man was about to draw a weapon,
according to Southern Command.
   Police Cpl. Cesar Tejada, who was shot once in the left arm,
told journalists permitted to interview him in a hospital Tuesday
the American had initiated the incident.
   ``I was merely standing there, doing my job, when this car went
by at high speed and the driver fired two shots at me,'' he said.
``I never gave him a reason for it.''
   Journalists also were permitted to interview another patient,
Alex Correa, who said he belonged to the security detail at
military headquarters. Correa said he was shot in the arm Saturday
by the Americans.
   Southern Command officials have said repeatedly the only
shooting was by Panamanian troops.
   Noriega has denied the drug charges.
</TEXT>

</DOC>