<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0143 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 2153EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HmongShooting     12-28 0542</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hmong Shooting,0560</SECOND>
<HEAD>Humphrey Rejects Investigation Request but Agrees To Review Other
Issues</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY R. SANDOK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ST. PAUL, Minn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The state's attorney general refused
Thursday to reopen an investigation into the fatal shootings of two
13-year-old Hmong boys by a police officer.
   ``For me to go forward with (a new investigation) would raise
serious ethical questions,'' Hubert H. Humphrey III said after
meeting for about two hours with a coalition representing
Minnesota's minority communities.
   A Dakota County grand jury on Dec. 8 refused to indict Kenneth
Murphy, an Inver Grove Height police officer, for the fatal
shootings Nov. 15 of Ba See Lor and Thai Yang, both from St. Paul.
   The boys were shot in the back as they fled from a stolen car.
   The officer told authorities he believed Yang was pointing a gun
at him. Police found no weapon, but they believe Murphy mistook a
screwdriver found near the boys' bodies for a pistol.
   The attorney general's office investigated the shooting at the
request of Dakota County authorities and presented the case to a
Dakota County grand jury, which on Dec. 8 declined to indict Murphy.
   Humphrey defended the state's investigation Thursday, and said
the case could not be reopened unless significant new evidence were
disclosed.
   Although Humphrey refused to reopen the case, members of the
coalition said they were satisfied with his plan to appoint a task
force to look into their other concerns.
   ``We had what I would consider a very good meeting,'' said Steve
Zachary of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored
People.
   John Huyen, president of the Vietnamese-American Association,
said the coalition's main concern is to prevent future incidents.
   About 350 people attended a vigil for the dead boys in the
Capitol Rotunda while Humphrey met first with the boys' families
and then with the coalition representatives.
   Among the coalition's other requests were:
   _Annual training for all law enforcement officers and attorneys
representing law enforcement agencies on the use of deadly force
and on the cultural diversity in their communities.
   _A code of conduct for law enforcement officers with special
emphasis on the use of deadly force.
   _Creation of panel with powers of a grand jury to review
allegations of police misconduct and violations of the proposed
code of conduct.
   ``What we need to do is turn the tragedy of these circumstances
into the opportunity to realize that we must confront racism and
discrimination,'' Humphrey said. ``We must use this as an
opportunity to look toward the future as to how we can prevent that
in Minnesota.''
   Yusef Mgeni, president of the Urban Coalition of Minneapolis and
an organizer of the vigil, said the minority communities were
united in protesting the deaths.
   ``This is not just a Southeast Asian issue,'' Mgeni said. ``It
affects all communities of color.''
   Mgeni said there were parallels between the Inver Grove Heights
shooting and other recent shootings of minority members in the Twin
Cities, as well as in incidents of alleged police brutality against
non-whites.
   The vigil was held ``to keep this and similar cases in the
public eye,'' Mgeni said, ``and to try to prevent an incident like
this from reoccurring, with anybody's children: white, black, red,
brown or yellow.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>