<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0203 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0820EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv26   12-18 0442</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv26,0461</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv26</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Tuesday, Dec. 26</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is Tuesday, Dec. 26, the 360th day of 1989. There are five
days left in the year.
   Today's Highlight in History:
   On Dec. 26, 1776, the Battle of Trenton was fought during the
Revolutionary War. Gen. George Washington's troops captured 1,000
Hessian soldiers in a major defeat for the British.
   On this date:
   In 1799, the late George Washington was eulogized by Colonel
Henry Lee as ``first in war, first in peace and first in the hearts
of his countrymen.''
   In 1865, James H. Nason of Franklin, Mass., received a patent
for a coffee percolator.
   In 1893, the future leader of China, Mao Tse-tung, was born in
Hunan province.
   In 1917, during World War I, the U.S. government took over
operation of the nation's railroads.
   In 1931, the Pulitzer Prize-winning musical play ``Of Thee I
Sing'' opened on Broadway.
   In 1941, Winston Churchill became the first British prime
minister to address a joint session of the U.S. Congress, warning
that the Axis would ``stop at nothing.''
   In 1944, in the Battle of the Bulge, the embattled U.S. 101st
Airborne Division, surrounded by German forces in Belgium, was
relieved by units of the 4th Armored Division.
   In 1947, heavy snow blanketed the Northeast, burying New York
City under 25.8 inches of snow in 16 hours. The same day, Los
Angeles set a record high temperature of 84 degrees.
   In 1972, the 33rd president of the United States, Harry S.
Truman, died in Kansas City, Mo.
   In 1975, the Soviet Union inaugurated the world's first
supersonic transport service with a flight of its ``Tupolev-144''
airliner from Moscow to Alma Ata.
   Ten years ago: Ayatollah Khomeini delivered a speech in which he
described Iran's confrontation with the United States as ``a
struggle between Islam and paganism'' that was ``likely''' to turn
into out-and-out war.
   Five years ago: Friends and families of the 27 miners killed in
the Wilberg Mine fire a week earlier gathered for a memorial
service in Castle Dale, Utah.
   One year ago: Another body from the bombing of Pan Am Flight 103
was found, bringing the confirmed death toll to 240. In all, 270
were killed.
   Today's Birthdays: Actor Richard Widmark is 75. Comedian,
composer and author Steve Allen is 68. Comedian Alan King is 62.
Record producer Phil Spector is 49. Actress Jane Lapotaire is 45.
Baseball player Carlton Fisk is 42. Baseball player Chris Chambliss
is 41.
   Thought for Today: ``Christmas is over and Business is
Business.'' _ Franklin Pierce Adams, American journalist and
humorist (1881-1960).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Advance for Tuesday, Dec. 26</NOTE>

</DOC>