<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0257 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1714EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-MoneyFunds     12-21 0369</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Money Funds,0381</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rose in Latest Week to $367.11 Billion</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Interest rate figures reported by Donoghue's Money Fund Report
are for week ended Tuesday. All other figures are for the week ended Wednesday.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Assets of the nation's 469 money market mutual
funds rose $208.2 million in the latest week, the Investment
Company Institute said Thursday.
   The rise to $367.11 billion in the seven-day period ended
Wednesday, followed a revised decline of $243.9 million the
previous week to a revised total of $366.90 billion, the
Washington-based mutual fund trade group said.
   The decline originally was reported as $336.3 million to a total
of $366.81 billion.
   The funds' assets hit a record high $368.23 billion in the week
ended Nov. 21, 1989.
   The Investment Company Institute said that in the latest week,
assets of 227 general purpose funds rose $831.1 million to $120.51
billion, assets of 98 broker-dealer funds dropped $244.4 million to
$158.78 billion, and assets of 144 institutional funds dropped
$378.5 million to $87.82 billion.
   The seven-day average yield on money market mutual funds rose in
the week ended Tuesday to 7.91 percent from 7.90 percent the
previous week, according to Donoghue's Money Fund Report, a trade
journal based in Holliston, Mass.
   The 30-day average yield fell to 7.92 percent from 7.95 percent,
Donoghue's said.
   The average maturity of the portfolios held by money funds was
42 days, down from 43 days, Donoghue's said.
   The newsletter Bank Rate Monitor said its survey of 100 leading
commercial banks, savings and loan associations and savings banks
in the nation's 10 largest markets showed the effective annual
yield available on money market accounts rose to 6.36 percent as of
Wednesday from 6.35 percent a week earlier.
   The North Palm Beach, Fla.-based newsletter said the effective
annual yield available on special savings accounts, called Super
NOW accounts, was unchanged from last week at 5.08 percent.
   Bank Rate Monitor said the effective annual yield was 7.95
percent on six-month certificates of deposit, down from 7.98 the
previous week. Yields were 7.98 percent on 1-year CDs, down from
8.00 percent; 7.94 percent on 2{-year CDs, down from 7.96 percent;
and 7.95 percent on 5-year CDs, down from 7.96 percent.
</TEXT>

</DOC>