<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0153 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1527EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s e BC-APN--TheaterWeek Adv07   12-26 1026</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Theater Week, Adv 07,1050</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv07</HEAD>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Jan. 7</HEAD>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<HEAD>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 1 b&amp;w photo.)</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL KUCHWARA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Drama Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In the middle of the musical ``Grand Hotel,'' a
young German baron suddenly declares his feelings for an older
woman, a ballerina making the last of her many ``farewell'' tours.
   He sings a passionate love song that soars from the stage and
over the audience. The singer is David Carroll, one of a new
generation of golden-voiced leading men making their mark on the
Broadway musical this season.
   Among the others are Gregg Edelman, who plays a writer of 1940s
detective novels, and James Naughton, who plays the writer's
fictional creation in ``City of Angels''; Bob Gunton, who shaves
beards and slits throats as the murderous barber in a revival of
``Sweeney Todd,'' and Cris Groenendaal, now starring in the
long-running but still sold-out ``Phantom of the Opera.'' In the
tradition of Alfred Drake, John Raitt, Richard Kiley and John
Cullum, these men are performers who can act as well as sing.
   Carroll ranks among the best of them. ``Love Can't Happen,'' his
big number in ``Grand Hotel,'' gets hearty applause. It's a
smashing musical moment in a show that celebrates movement over
music. Director and choreographer Tommy Tune never lets the story
stop in this adaptation of Vicki Baum's novel about the goings-on
in a luxury hotel in 1928 Berlin.
   And ``Grand Hotel'' may finally give the 39-year-old Carroll the
long Broadway run he deserves. It almost happened in 1988 when he
played the Russian grandmaster in ``Chess.'' The show had a
glorious score but a short life in New York, although Carroll got a
Tony nomination out of it.
   Most people remember ``Grand Hotel'' from the 1932 MGM movie,
not the novel. The film starred John Barrymore as the baron and
Greta Garbo as the ballerina, but the motion picture is not what is
on stage at Broadway's Martin Beck Theater.
   ``We're not doing the movie, especially where my part is
concerned,'' Carroll was saying the other day. ``The baron is
supposed to be much younger than the ballerina. In the book, it's
beautifully written when he sees her fragility and the wrinkles on
her face. That's what we're playing.
   ``I saw the movie on TV the other night, and Barrymore looked to
be in his 50s. And Garbo looked younger than he was. But they were
doing Louis B. Mayer's version.''
   Tune made sure everyone knew the novel. He gave everyone in the
cast a copy of it before they began rehearsals.
   Carroll has been with the show from its first workshop
production last year. The show rehearsed at the shabby Hotel
Diplomat near the theater district. The hotel's once-splendid
ballroom provided the right ambiance for rehearsals, and its
architecture even inspired Tony Walton's set design.
   Tune, the man behind such musical hits as ``The Best Little
Whorehouse in Texas,'' ``Nine'' and ``My One and Only,'' reworked
the show extensively in Boston before bringing it to Broadway in
November.
   The book was revised, and Maury Yeston, the composer of
``Nine,'' edited and augmented the original score by Robert Wright
and George Forrest. It was Yeston who wrote ``When Love Comes'' for
the baron.
   ``This song came along and all of a sudden, it crystallized the
two characters,'' Carroll says. ``The ballerina finally said,
`You're young.' And the baron finally said, `I like older women.'
It hadn't been clear enough. I don't think the audience could tell
if I really like her or not. If I was trying to pull the wool over
her eyes that would have made me an unsympathetic character.''
   Carroll has been stage-struck forever.
   ``My parents had a lot of show albums,'' he says. ``As
newlyweds, they saw `South Pacific' on a fluke about 11 days after
it opened. It was played a lot around the house.''
   Growing up on Long Island and in Connecticut with two brothers
and two sisters, Carroll always sang. ``We played the records and
sang at the top of our lungs,'' he recalls. He also journeyed into
Manhattan to see musicals.
   ``I saw `Oliver!' from the balcony and loved it. Of course, I
wanted to be one of those kids right away. I went home and told my
parents I was going to the High School of the Performing Arts like
the kids on `Wonderama' and that was it. But it didn't quite work
out that way.''
   Dartmouth came first and detours into art and architecture.
   ``But I was spending so much time in the theater department that
I said, `Let's try it.'''
   Since he started to sing professionally in 1974, Carroll has
worked in all kinds of musicals.
   ``Fortunately, when I came to town I found a voice teacher who I
still have,'' he says. ``He taught me how to sing so I'll be able
to sing until I'm 60.''
   Carroll's resume is diverse. He has done a revival of ``Where's
Charley?'' and a revue called ``Rodgers and Hart,'' and he sang
opposite Linda Ronstadt in a pop, English-language version of ``La
Boheme.'' He has also had his share of short-lived shows such as
``Seven Brides for Seven Brothers,'' ``Oh, Brother!'' and ``Wind in
the Willows.''
   ``I always liked doing musicals, but I didn't want to be some
stiff, musical comedy leading man who couldn't dance and couldn't
act,'' Carroll says. ``I like doing the whole thing.''
   He got to California with the national tour of ``Deathtrap,''
starring Brian Bedford. Los Angeles meant a lot of television
movies playing roles such as Valerie Bertinelli's husband or
Melissa Gilbert's boyfriend. But the parts weren't very challenging
and the directors not inspiring. He came back to New York in 1983
and hasn't left.
   ``I missed the theater and just realized I was more of a city
person,'' Carroll says. ``Besides, the driving drove me nuts. I'm
not a car person. I don't have one in the city now and get along
just fine _ as long as I can crank out eight performances a week.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>

</DOC>