<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 1217EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Rehnquist     12-31 0595</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rehnquist,560</SECOND>
<HEAD>More Judges Needed To Fight Drug War, Rehnquist Says</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD CARELLI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government's war on drugs cannot be won if
Congress does not create more federal judgeships, Chief Justice
William H. Rehnquist said Sunday.
   One of every four criminal cases handled by the nation's federal
courts is drug-related, Rehnquist said, adding, ``Some courts,
especially in border states, are approaching the outer limits of
caseload and fatigue from handling drug-related cases.''
   In his annual year-end report on the federal court system, the
chief justice said, ``From a federal law enforcement perspective,
the war on drugs will fail if the judiciary is not given the
judgeships necessary to do the job.''
   He urged Congress to ``take immediate action'' to create the 59
additional trial judgeships and 16 more appellate judgeships
requested last October by the U.S. Judicial Conference, the
policy-making arm of the federal court system. Rehnquist heads the
conference.
   To date, Congress has authorized 575 federal trial judgeships
and 168 appellate judgeships. No new judgeship has been created
since 1984.
   Rehnquist warned against creating ``an hour-glass-shaped law
enforcement system'' to battle illegal drug trafficking.
   ``Huge personnel assets have been added to bring about more
prosecutions and huge assets have been devoted to prisons to house
the convicted,'' he said. ``But without the judge power to handle
the added workload there will be a bottleneck in the middle.''
   Rehnquist cited statistics indicating that federal trial judges
now handle nearly four times as many drug cases as they did in 1980
_ from about 3,000 a year to over 11,000 a year.
   The greatest bulk of drug-related cases, as well as most
criminal cases, are handled by state courts.
   A spokesman for the Administrative Office of the U.S. Courts
said 68 percent of all new criminal cases filed in federal courts
in Iowa are drug-related; 60 percent in northern West Virginia.
   Statistics indicate that in the area of Texas encompassing the
cities of Houston, Galveston, Laredo and Corpus Christi, drug cases
represented 24.4 percent of all criminal cases in 1985 but now
represent 53.6 percent.
   Rehnquist said one of every 10 cases reaching federal appeals
courts is drug-related, representing more than half the criminal
cases handled by the appeals courts.
   He also asked President Bush and Congress to fill existing
judicial vacancies, now numbering 61.
   ``Nine of these are `judicial emergencies,' having been vacant
for over 18 months,'' Rehnquist said.
   The administrative office said two of those nine vacancies exist
in federal trial courts in New York City. The remaining seven are
in appeals courts based in New Orleans, San Francisco and the
District of Columbia and in trial courts in Pennsylvania, Colorado,
the Virgin Islands and Guam.
   On another subject, Rehnquist praised Congress for recently
voting to raise the salaries of all federal judges _ by 35 percent
as of next January.
   And he said a 1988 law that gave the Supreme Court greater
discretion over the cases it chooses to review ``is having a very
beneficial impact on the court's selection of cases.''
   Through the first two months of its 1989-90 term, the nation's
highest court has granted review in significantly fewer cases than
in past terms.
   Referring to the Dec. 16 killing in Birmingham, Ala., of Judge
Robert S. Vance, a member of the Atlanta-based 11th U.S. Circuit
Court of Appeals, Rehnquist said, ``It serves as a ready reminder
that judges, like other law enforcement officers, find themselves
literally on the firing line as a result of the duties of the
office that they hold.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>