<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0956EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Poland-Police     12-29 0460</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Poland-Police,0475</SECOND>
<HEAD>Interior Ministry Proposes Creation of New Police Force</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Interior Ministry today presented
plans to create an independent police force responsible for keeping
public order and protecting citizens as part of ongoing reforms in
the ministry, the PAP news agency said.
   Interior Minister Czeslaw Kiszczak outlined the proposals to
create a new force based on the present civic militia during a
meeting with President Wojciech Jaruzelski, the agency said.
   Regular police work such as controlling traffic and pursuing
criminals is now carried out by the civic militia, which in the
past was also responsible for represssing the opposition and
militant priests, bugging telephones and monitoring letters between
private citizens.
   Kiszczak told Jaruzelski that a name for the new police force
was still under discussion as is the design of new uniforms, the
state news agency reported.
   ``The police would be independent and would handle only tasks
concerning protection of public order and protection of
individual's security and their property,'' the agency said.
   Kiszczak, one of only four Communist ministers in the cabinet,
said that a new Office for the Protection of the State would be
created to oversee activities by the intelligence and
counter-intelligence services.
   Kiszczak told Jaruzelski that the Interior Ministry, which now
controls the civic militia, was conducting consultations with the
Solidarity-led government and members of Parliament about the
proposals.
   When the discussions are completed, Kiszczak said he would ask
Prime Minister Tadeusz Mazowiecki to start procedures to present a
draft law on the new police force to parliament, PAP said.
   There are now about 1,250 crimes per 100,000 people annually,
but there are increasing incidents of car break-ins and other
crimes being reported as the economic situation in Poland worsens.
   The Interior Ministry has already taken dramatic steps to
improve its image that was tarnished during years of repression
against society.
   Just two weeks after Parliament approved the new Solidarity-led
government on Sept. 12, the Interior Ministry ordered the
disbanding of all units of the widely feared and despised
paramilitary ZOMO riot police.
   The helmeted squads, with shields and batons were a regular
feature at opposition demonstrations. They were replaced by
``special preventive patrol units.''
   The International Institute for Strategic Studies put the number
of ZOMO at 28,000.
   In October, the ministry also said it would disband the ``Fourth
Department'' which oversaw the activities of the clergy. Four
members of the Fourth Department were convicted of the 1984 murder
of Rev. Jerzy Popieluszko, a popular pro-Solidarity priest.
   The interior ministry also announced at the time that the secret
police would disband undercover units and turn off listening
devices.
   Parliament in November disbanded the 328,510-member paramilitary
volunteer police force, known as ORMO. Solidarity lawmakers called
the ORMO a ``relic of Stalinism.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>