<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0272 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1309EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-Panama-Markets 4thLd-Writethru   12-20 0560</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Markets, 4th Ld-Writethru,0582</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar Up on Panama Invasion, Other Market Reaction Muted</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS grafs 18-19, `I think ... South America, with two grafs
to CORRECT attribution to Baker sted Byers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIVIAN MARINO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The surprise attack by U.S. forces in Panama helped push the
dollar higher today, but other financial markets reacted only
mildly to the military intervention.
   On Wall Street, the Dow Jones industrial average was up about 4
points to the 2,700 level by noon EST. But in the broader market,
declining stocks slightly outnumbered advances on the New York
Stock Exchange.
   U.S. Treasury bond prices were unchanged to slightly higher in
midday trading in New York.
   President Bush ordered troops into action following several days
of tension triggered by the weekend shooting death of a U.S.
military officer in Panama by defense forces controlled by Gen.
Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   Currency dealers said the dollar rose sharply against other
major currencies just after the military action became known early
today.
   In Japan, the dollar closed at 144.23 yen, up 0.43 yen from
Tuesday. It started the trading day at 143.92 yen and ranged
between 143.90-144.25 yen. By midday in Europe, the dollar was up
against all currencies except the yen while gold prices moved
higher.
   The dollar remained firm in early New York dealings.
   In times of international tension, investors often look for safe
havens and usually turn to the dollar and precious metals.
   Gabriele Schmitt, a trader with the Bank of New York, said she
expected the dollar to be stable in the near term because of the
uncertainty in Panama.
   ``There are still a lot of question marks,'' she said. ``Noriega
still has a lot of support in his country ... I wouldn't rule him
out entirely.''
   But stock analysts said most investors did not view the unrest
in Panama as a reason for making big changes in their strategies.
   ``The initial reaction is one of a non-event. It might have an
impact if it becomes a prolonged situation,'' said Dennis E.
Jarrett, a technical analyst with Kidder, Peabody &amp; Co.
   Larry Wachtel, a vice president for Prudential-Bache Securities
Inc., agreed: ``We've been involved in limited (military)
engagements before. This looks like a military engagement that will
be over shortly.''
   Wachtel said oil and defense stocks were getting a boost from
the Panama invastion, however.
   The oil futures market initially rallied on the news amid
concern that the closure of the Panama Canal might disrupt oil
shipments, but prices fell back later in the trading session.
   On the New York Mercantile Exchange, the February contract for
West Texas Intermediate, the leading grade of U.S. crude oil, was
down around 5 cents at $21.21 per 42-gallon barrel by midday today.
   The January home heating oil contract, strengthened in recent
days from a cold spell that hit parts of the nation, was up 0.54
cent to 76.85 cents a gallon, after rising nearly 2 cents earlier
in the trading session.
   ``I think the reaction to the Panama closure was totally
irrational,'' said Bob Baker, an energy analyst with
Prudential-Bache Securities Inc. ``Our crude oil supplies simply
won't be disrupted.''
   Baker said that only a small percentage of crude shipped to the
United States passes through the Panama Canal and the tankers that
travel through the canal could be re-routed around South America.
</TEXT>

</DOC>