<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0911EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AliensDefense 1stLd-Writethru a0495 12-20 0663</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Aliens Defense, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0495,0681</SECOND>
<HEAD>Illegal Immigrants Fighting U.S. Government With Fifth Amendment
Cudgel</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 13 grafs to RAISE legal argument; PICKS UP 17th graf
pvs, `One of ...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARLENE LEVINSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thirty-eight Latin American stablehands seized at
a racetrack a year ago have taken the Fifth Amendment, challenging
the government to prove they are illegal aliens. The government
says it doesn't have to to deport them.
   While illegal immigrants often don't know their rights and
prefer to go home rather than fight to stay, the Boston cases are
being regarded as a test of aliens' rights.
   The Immigration and Naturalization Service ``is saying the
government doesn't have to come up with any evidence at all,'' said
attorney Susan Akram, who is orchestrating the aliens' defense.
``The INS has never brought a shred of evidence.''
   ``It's a test of what the government burden is,'' said Akram,
head of the Political Asylum Immigration Representation Project.
``Can the government haul anybody in off the streets and deport
them if they refuse to answer questions based on their
constitutional right not to do so? This is ridiculous.''
   The defendants were among 83 Salvadoran, Mexican, Brazilian and
Cuban stablehands rounded up Oct. 21, 1988 at Suffolk Downs during
a dawn workout.
   Of the 83 people, six were found to be in the United States
lawfully. Some went home, while others admitted their illegal
status and applied for asylum.
   The rest invoked their Fifth Amendment guarantee against
self-incrimination at their deportation hearings. They want the
government to prove they are here illegally.
   That isn't happening. Instead, INS attorneys are using an
argument allowed in civil cases: that silence alone is ground for
deportation.
   Charles Wheeler, director of the National Center for Immigrants'
Rights in Los Angeles, called this development alarming.
   ``It's disturbing if the immigration judge is making an
inference from their silence that a person is an alien,'' he said.
``It reverses the whole idea that you are innocent until proven
guilty.''
   But an INS official says the government is following precedent
well-established in civil cases.
   ``The government doesn't have to do any more,'' said Michael
Creppy, acting deputy counsel for the INS in Washington. ``This is
nothing new. The law is pretty clear in this matter. To me it's
just a tactic to be able to stay here.''
   Among the 38 aliens who invoked the Fifth Amendment was
21-year-old Salvadoran. His story is typical, said Akram, who
requested the man be identified only as Jay.
   One of 10 children in a farming family, Jay is from the
mountains of El Salvador, where the army and the anti-government
guerrillas have been waging war. He said both sides terrorize the
inhabitants.
   Jay told his attorney that by age 19, he was forced to act four
times as a lookout on a guerrilla patrol. He knew better than to
object after seeing a friend's face shot off for refusing to act as
a guerrilla informant.
   Last year, Jay fled, taking a bus to Mexico. From there, he
crossed the U.S. border undetected and made his way from California
to Massachusetts.
   Two months ago, Jay had his day in Immigration Court. The
attorney for the INS questioned him about where he came from and
how he got here.
   Jay replied in Spanish, ``I refuse to answer under the
protection of the Fifth Amendment of the United States because my
answer could incriminate me.'' The INS lawyer then asked the judge
to deport him.
   Jay's case is on appeal before the Board of Immigration Appeals.
   Wheeler said the use of the Fifth Amendment in deportation cases
is rare but crucial.
   ``It's an important defense and it would be a tragic betrayal if
this was taken away from aliens,'' he said.
   The INS' Creppy said the agency feels it will win.
   ``When you weigh the public interest versus the aliens'
interest, this is a case that is clear,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>