<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0167 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1203EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--RightBites-FinickyKids Adv01   12-28 0681</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Right Bites-Finicky Kids, Adv 01,0696</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv01</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Monday, Jan. 1, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Peanut Butter Again? Should A Parent Worry?</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY MacVEAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Peanut butter sandwiches and apple juice day
after day _ after day. Dinner table negotiations over exactly how
many peas a child will eat, how many forkfuls of spinach. What's a
parent to do?
   ``Finicky is pretty normal for lots of kids,'' said Vicki
Lansky, author of ``Feed Me! I'm Yours.'' And common sense will
indicate whether a child has gone beyond fussy to worrisome.
Parents should not be short-order cooks or spend every dinner
pleading, ``Eat your broccoli,'' Lansky said.
   Easier said than done, right?
   Dinner needn't be a battleground if parents make non-negotiable
rules, which most children will follow, said Dr. William Dietz of
Boston's New England Medical Center, citing the wide use of cod
liver oil a generation or so ago.
   ``Talk about a terrible food. But the message and the culture
was that cod liver oil was good for kids. So millions of kids
obediently opened their mouths and swallowed that stuff, and it was
awful,'' he said.
   ``It's more the dynamic than the child's eating, per se,'' said
Ellyn Satter, author of ``How to Get Your Kid to Eat ... But Not
Too Much.'' ``I recommend a division of responsibilities in
feeding, which says essentially that the parent is responsible for
what is offered and when and where. ... It's up to the child to
decide what to eat, and whether to eat.''
   Parents have to judge whether a finicky child truly doesn't like
what's on the table, is trying to get attention, or has some other
motive.
   ``A lot of times kids are trying to push their parents to see
how far they can go,'' said Martha Stone, a nutritionist at
Colorado State University. ``Saying yes and no to food is one way
of exerting control.''
   It's also natural for children to play with food.
   Toddlers are ``exploring, trying to develop a sense of what does
or doesn't taste good, learning how to feed themselves. All those
add up to finicky,'' said Dr. Ronald Kleinman of Massachusetts
General Hospital.
   Telling a child who refuses to eat that there's no more food
until the next meal is OK. ``That throws the situation back to the
child, a choice of eating, or being hungry,'' Stone said. Parents
must be consistent about such rules, Dietz said. ``You have to be
wiling to let them go hungry.''
   Parents also should respect strong food dislikes and not give
rewards for eating. If a child rejects a food once, serve it again,
as many as 10 times. Sometimes children need to grow accustomed to
new tastes. And try to wait out food jags, which begin around 18
months and can occur throughout childhood.
   What counts is a balanced diet _ protein, fruits and vegetables,
dairy and grains _ even if only one or two things are eaten from
each group.
   ``They don't have to have variety in their lives at that age,
they have to have the nutrients to grow,'' Kleinman said. With his
own children, now 12 and 14, Kleinman and his wife only made food
an issue if meals were skipped. ``We kind of insist that at least
two times a day we see them eating a meal.''
   It's important to get a pediatrician's opinion on whether a
child's weight is appropriate for height, several experts noted.
But despite reports of well-off parents underfeeding youngsters to
keep them thin, children are more likely to face problems today
from too much food. They should not be forced to clean their plates
and usually are the best judges of how much to eat, Stone said.
   ``Keep in mind that the grownup way of eating is not necessarily
a pattern to be admired or emulated,'' Satter said. ``Grownups have
pretty systematically learned to ignore their internal cues.''
   The best way to prevent obesity, she said, is to nurture
children's ``exquisite senstivity to their own hunger.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Jan. 1</NOTE>

</DOC>