<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0166 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2337EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Hungary     12-19 0453</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hungary,0468</SECOND>
<HEAD>Parliament Approves Hungarian Austerity Program</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUDAPEST, Hungary (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Parliament on Tuesday approved the
government's strict austerity program for next year, but wrangled
over budget cuts demanded by Western creditors and has yet to adopt
a budget.
   Negotiations with the International Monetary Fund for
hard-currency loans hinge on adoption of the budget. The loans are
needed to help transform the economy to work on market forces.
   Ernoe Kemenes, head of the National Planning Office, told the
hushed house that if it does not accept the austerity plan, within
months Hungary would be unable to finance the economy and living
standards would inevitably drop.
   The budget deficit is likely to reach $800 million this year.
The IMF wants that cut to $156 million in 1990 as a precondition to
further loans.
   A crucial $1 billion World Bank loan hinges on the IMF
agreement, as does a $1.14 billion loan from the European Community.
   Kemenes said interest payments next year on the $20 billion
foreign debt would amount to $1.5 billion. Payment on principal
would stand at $1.9 billion.
   Kemenes said in his initial report on the government program
that it foresaw cutting subsidies to loss-making companies from
$1.09 billion to $308 million.
   This would mean bankruptcy proceedings would be initiated
against 50 firms. Premier Miklos Nemeth has said that could send
the number of unemployed to about 100,000.
   The program also foresees Hungary cutting back its trade with
member countries of the Soviet-led COMECON trading bloc. Kemenes
said this would mean a cut of 20 percent in exports to these
countries, which in turn is likely to contribute to unemployment.
   He said agreement also was with the IMF on devaluing the forint.
   Finance Minister Laszlo Bekesi said last week that if parliament
rejects the budget, the government would ``have no option but to
resign.''
   A big item of controversy is the proposal to cut housing
subsidies, which now make up about 16 percent of the budget.
   The plan envisages raising rents by 50 percent as of January and
levying hefty taxes on those who enjoy low interest rates on
home-purchase loans.
   More than 20 deputies took the floor in the housing debate and
all of them rejected the government proposal, according to the
official MTI news agency.
   The deputies argued that it was unfair to place such a burden on
the population and could lead to serious political consequences, an
apparent reference to possible strikes and demonstrations.
   The house adjourned debate Tuesday and planned to vote
separately on the housing issue Wednesday before debating the
budget.
   This session of parliament is also to discuss the date for next
year's free elections _ the first multiparty elections in more than
40 years.
</TEXT>

</DOC>