<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0098 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1725EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-Music     12-23 0370</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Music,0379</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bernstein Conducts Concerts in Honor of East European Freedom</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH G. SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Beethoven's Ninth Symphony became an ode to
freedom on Saturday as Leonard Bernstein united musicians from East
and West at the start of a Christmas musical gala to honor Eastern
Europe's struggle for freedom.
   Hundreds of people dressed in their finest poured into the
gleaming Schauspielhaus in East Berlin on Saturday afternoon for a
rehearsal before two official concerts of Beethoven's Ninth
Symphony.
   Bernstein was invited to perform by Justus Frantz, performance
director of West Germany's Bavarian Radio, to celebrate the
historic events in East Germany that led to the opening of the
country's borders Nov. 9.
   ``I just couldn't say no,'' Bernstein said as he stepped
backstage after the nearly two-hour rehearsal. Young people mobbed
the legendary conductor for autographs outside the concert hall
before he returned to West Berlin.
   Bernstein conducted the Ninth Symphony at the first concert
Saturday night in the West Berlin Philharmonic. He will conduct a
second performance in East Berlin on Christmas morning.
   Frantz said Beethoven's Ninth Symphony was chosen because of the
symbolism of the final movement of the piece, which is based on
Friedrich Schiller's Ode to Joy with its plea for world brotherhood.
   ``Europe is opening up. All men are becoming brothers and so we
chose the Ninth Symphony and musicians from all nations as a salute
to freedom,'' Frantz told The Associated Press.
   East Germany officially drops visa requirements for West German
travelers on Sunday, and the performance in West Berlin was timed
to end as the clock struck midnight.
   The international orchestra includes musicians from West and
East Germany, Great Britain, the Soviet Union, France and the
United States, the four victorious World War II allies still
technically responsible for governing Berlin.
   The 71-year-old American conductor is the latest in a series of
world-renowned musicians to travel to Berlin since the wall began
to crumble on Nov. 9.
   Sir Yehudi Menuhin conducted a benefit concert in West Berlin
this month to help rebuild decaying East German city centers and
Mstislav Rostropovich and Daniel Barenboim also played in West
Berlin shortly after the concrete barrier was opened.
</TEXT>

</DOC>