<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0041EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-US-Romania Bjt   12-23 0351</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-Romania, Bjt,350</SECOND>
<HEAD>US May Aid New Leaders in Romania</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bush administration will consider aid to
the new government taking shape in Romania once it dismantles the
system inherited from ousted President Nicolae Ceaucescu and
institutes reforms, officials say.
   The White House and the State Department hailed the demise of
Ceaucescu's hard-line government Friday and expressed hope for a
peaceful transition to democracy.
   State Department deputy spokesman Richard Boucher credited the
``courageous and persistent action by the Romanian people'' who
prevailed ``in the face of great odds and despite bloody
repression.''
   Ceausescu's ouster seemed to foreshadow an improvement in
U.S.-Romanian relations, which have been under severe strain,
particularly since last weekend when anti-government uprisings
began.
   Ceaucescu's repressive policies contributed to Romania's loss of
U.S. trade privileges last year. The administration was about to
impose additional sanctions Friday but reversed itself after
Ceaucescu was forced out.
   White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said U.S. aid would be
considered ``once reforms are made'' by Romania's new authorities.
   Boucher gave a cautious welcome to the designation of a former
diplomat, Corneliu Manescu, to form an interim government.
   He said Manescu's career has been distinguished and he noted the
one-time foreign minister has been a leading advocate of political
reform in Romania.
   Fitzwater said the United States is ready for better relations
with the new government if it ``moves along a path of general
democratic reform. The United States pledges its strong support and
assistance.
   ``We hope that Romania will soon join the other countries in
Central and Eastern Europe which have ushered in a new era of
cooperation between East and West,'' the spokesman said.
   Boucher said the State Department formed a task force Thursday
night to monitor events in Romania and ordered the partial
evacuation of the U.S. Embassy in Bucharest when the situation
appeared to be worsening.
   With the dramatic turn of events Friday morning, the evacuation
order was rescinded but embassy dependents who wished to depart the
country were allowed to do so. About 20 chose to leave Friday,
Boucher said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>