<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0154 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1655EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-PollutedParks     12-20 0298</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Polluted Parks,300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Oregon Lawmaker Wants Clean Air Act Amendment</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GREENE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   National parks need special protection from
air pollution that the Environmental Protection Agency has failed
to provide, an Oregon lawmaker said Wednesday in calling for a
special amendment to the Clean Air Act.
   ``Manmade pollution is creeping into our parks and wildernesses,
robbing us of what makes them special,'' Rep. Ron Wyden, D-Ore.,
said at a news conference. He was joined by former Arizona Gov.
Bruce Babbitt.
   The problem is especially acute in the open spaces of the West,
which scientists believe are particularly vulnerable to sulfur
dioxide and other pollutants, he said.
   The problem has gotten so bad, he said later in an interview,
that polluted air has become as much a health problem as a
visibility problem. He said it is affecting visibility at airports,
observatories on isolated peaks and military testing grounds.
   ``Federal officials have a choice: Either clean up our parks or
adopt rules to warn Americans of health problems they may face from
visiting polluted parks,'' he said.
   The 1977 Clean Air Act contains a provision to protect the
national park system against visual pollution. But Wyden said EPA
has concentrated only on the ``simple problem of plume blight _
pollution from a few distinct sources near the park.''
   Wyden said he would try to amend the act in the Energy and
Commerce Committee early next year. The Senate will be taking up
its version of the bill as its top priority in 1990.
   Wyden's proposal would require EPA to identify sources of
emissions, provide for federal implementation of controls if states
do not act, broaden the categories of areas protected and give
federal park and wilderness officials earlier notice of permit
applications.
</TEXT>

</DOC>