<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 2154EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Cheney-Panama 3rdLd-Writethru a0819 12-24 0448</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cheney-Panama, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0819,0456</SECOND>
<HEAD>Precede PANAMA CITY</HEAD>
<HEAD>Cheney Visits Troops in Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS thruout with Cheney, Thurman quotes, ADDS byline, no pickup.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DORALISA PILARTE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOWARD AIR FORCE BASE, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Defense Secretary Dick
Cheney arrived in Panama on Sunday to share Christmas dinner with
U.S. troops and celebrate Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega's decision to
seek asylum.
   ``I am delighted that General Noriega has finally been run to
ground,'' said Cheney after being told, as his plane approached
Panama, that Noriega had sought political asylum at the Vatican
Embassy.
   ``I think it is clear at this point that the Panamanian people
have no use for him, that he has had to take sanctuary in a foreign
embassy,'' said Cheney.
   He spoke to reporters shortly after his plane landed at Howard
Air Force Base four miles west of Panama City.
   ``He no longer is a factor in Panama. Now it is up to the
lawyers and the diplomats to figure out what is next,'' Cheney
said. ``As far as I'm concerned, the military has done its job.''
   Although there were 26,000 U.S. military personnel in Panama,
there were none around the embassy when Noriega arrived there. An
informed military source said Noriega, the ousted Panamanian
strongman, drove himself or was driven to the embassy at about 3
p.m. and entered unaccompanied.
   Gen. Maxwell Thurman, chief of the U.S. Southern Command, said
he ordered the embassy surrounded afterward because ``I have the
security responsibility for all of Panama, so I don't want digbats
(Dignity Battalions loyal to Noriega) blowing into the place. I
would not want them to come with an armored car and blow their way
into the embassy.''
   ``I can imagine all the Vatican lawyers are going to be up at
this hour,'' he added.
   It was unclear whether Noriega's decision will hasten the
withdrawal of U.S. troops from Panama, said Col. Miguel Monteverde,
a Pentagon spokesman. Military officials hoped Noriega's decision
to seek asylum would ``take the spirit to resist'' out of scattered
Noriega loyalists who were still fighting, Monteverde said.
   Cheney went to Panama to ``spend Christmas with troops in the
field ... and of course to celebrate'' Noriega's surrender,
Monteverde said.
   ``He is very interested in how they're doing, but I think he
wants to show in a very real way that he appreciates their
sacrifice in giving up Christmas and putting themselves in harm's
way,'' Monteverde said.
   Cheney will return to Washington either Monday evening or
Tuesday morning, Monteverde said.
   President Bush announced the surprise Cheney trip after a
briefing at the Pentagon on Sunday, the fifth day of the U.S.
invasion that drove Noriega from power.
</TEXT>

</DOC>