<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0199 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1454EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv22   12-21 0469</FIRST>
<SECOND>njbru</SECOND>
<HEAD>BC-History, Adv22,0484</HEAD>
<HEAD>$adv22</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Friday, Dec. 22</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is Friday, December 22, the 356th day of 1989. There are
nine days left in the year. Tonight is the first night of Hanukkah,
the Jewish Festival of Lights.
   Today's highlight in history:
   On December 22, 1944, during the World War II Battle of the
Bulge, the Germans demanded the surrender of encircled American
troops at Bastogne, Belgium. Brigadier Gen. Anthony C. McAuliffe
reportedly replied: ``Nuts!'' The Americans held out until
additional U.S. forces ended the siege four days later.
   On this date:
   In 1775, a Continental naval fleet was organized in the
rebellious American colonies under the command of Ezek Hopkins.
   In 1807, Congress passed the Embargo Act, designed to force
peace between Britain and France by cutting off all trade with
Europe.
   In 1864, during the Civil War, Union Gen. William T. Sherman
sent a message to President Abraham Lincoln from Georgia, saying,
``I beg to present you as a Christmas gift the city of Savannah.''
   In 1894, French army officer Alfred Dreyfus was convicted of
treason in a court-martial that triggered worldwide charges of
anti-Semitism. (Dreyfus was ultimately vindicated.)
   In 1941, British Prime Minister Winston Churchill arrived in
Washington for a wartime conference with President Roosevelt.
   In 1963, an official 30-day mourning period for President
Kennedy ended.
   In 1971, the United Nations General Assembly voted to ratify the
election of Kurt Waldheim as secretary-general.
   In 1977, 36 people were killed when a 250-foot-high grain
elevator at the Continental Grain Company plant in Westwego, La.,
exploded.
   Ten years ago: Pope John Paul II issued a strong denunciation of
the holding of American hostages in Iran, saying the holding of
hostages was in ``violation of unquestionable principles of
international law.''
   Five years ago: In a case that drew national attention, New York
City resident Bernhard Goetz shot four black youths on a subway
train, claiming they were about to rob him.
   One year ago: President-elect Bush announced more appointments,
including Dr. Louis W. Sullivan as secretary of Health and Human
Services, Samuel K. Skinner as Transportation secretary and Manuel
Lujan Jr. as interior secretary. Brazilian environmentalist
Francisco ``Chico'' Mendes Filho was shot and killed.
   Today's Birthdays: Lady Bird Johnson is 77. TV personality Gene
Rayburn is 72. Former House Speaker Jim Wright is 67. Actress
Barbara Billingsley is 67. Actor Hector Elizondo is 53. Retired
baseball player Steve Carlton is 45. ABC News correspondent Diane
Sawyer is 44. Retired baseball player Steve Garvey is 41. Singers
Robin and Maurice Gibb are 40. Golfer Jan Stephenson is 38.
   Thought for Today: ``A burning purpose attracts others who are
drawn along with it and help fulfill it.'' _ Margaret Bourke-White,
American photojournalist (1904-1971).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Advance for Use Friday, December 22</NOTE>

</DOC>