<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0143 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1828EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Bombs-CourtCases     12-29 0541</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bombs-Court Cases,0553</SECOND>
<HEAD>Group Claiming Mail Bombs Cites Desegregation, Attacks on Whites</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Mail Bombs</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARC RICE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The group which has claimed responsibility for
the mail bomb deaths of a federal judge and an attorney expressed
ire over court rulings in school desegregation cases, an area in
which both victims were involved.
   The letter claiming responsibility for the violence also decried
the legal system's handling of crimes by blacks against whites,
particularly mentioning last year's slaying of Julie Love in
Atlanta, a case never touched by the two men killed in the
mid-December bombings.
   The letter, from a group calling itself Americans for a
Competent Federal Judicial System, said 11th U.S. Circuit Court of
Appeals Judge Robert S. Vance and Savannah attorney Robert Robinson
were ``assassinated ... in reprisal for the atrocities inflicted
upon Julie Love.''
   The letter, which was sent to WAGA-TV in Atlanta and disclosed
Thursday, said the 11th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals must be shown
that ``protecting the innocent warrants a higher court priority
than granting the blacks' demand for white teachers for their
children.''
   The letter did not refer to specific cases.
   However, Vance was on the 11th Circuit panel that directed
suburban Atlanta's DeKalb County school system this year to
transfer about 120 veteran teachers from majority white schools to
predominantly black ones in a long-running desegregation case there.
   A school desegregation case in Savannah also was before the 11th
Circuit this year. Vance did not sit on the panel that heard the
Savannah case, but Robinson had represented the NAACP in that suit.
   The letter threatened that ``two more prominent members of the
NAACP shall be assassinated, using more sophisticated means'' as
part of the reprisal for Ms. Love's death.
   A federal judge, an attorney and an NAACP officer will be
killed, the letter added, ```anytime a black man rapes a white
woman in Alabama, Florida or Georgia in the future.'' The
Atlanta-based 11th Circuit hears federal appeals from those three
states.
   Ms. Love, a white preschool fitness teacher, disappeared July
11, 1988, and her body was found last August. The search for her
was highly publicized in the area, with ``Have You Seen Julie
Love'' posters ubiquitous.
   Following the discovery of her body this year, two black men
were arrested, one of whom has pleaded guilty to murder, rape,
kidnapping and armed robbery. The other man is awaiting trial for
murder.
   The DeKalb County school case dates back to 1969, when the
system was first placed under a federal court order to desegregate.
The 11th Circuit last year overturned a district judge's ruling
that by 1988 DeKalb County had done its best to integrate the
73,000-student system.
   The appeals court's subsequent ruling that DeKalb must take
further steps toward integration recently went before the Supreme
Court, where the justices this month refused to intervene.
   In Savannah, a lengthy school desegregation case was decided in
October when the 11th Circuit ruled that a ``magnet school'' plan
offered by the school system was appropriate for integration. The
National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, which
had argued that the plan still left many black students in
segregated schools, has not yet said whether it will appeal.
</TEXT>

</DOC>