<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0199 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0741EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-ManvilleTrust     12-19 0436</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Manville Trust,0450</SECOND>
<HEAD>Manville to Speed Up Payment to Asbestos Victims' Trust</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN M. DOYLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Manville Corp. says it will accelerate payment
of a $50 million note to the asbestos victims' trust fund created
by its bankruptcy reorganization, according to the Manville
Personal Injury Settlement Trust.
   In a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission on
Monday, the Trust said it had been exploring ways to improve
liquidity after a plan for Manville to repurchase $500 million of
its preferred stock fell through earlier this month.
   ``One of those alternatives is an offer by Manville to
accelerate the payment of its $50 million Trust note,'' the SEC
filing said.
   The note was to be repaid in two equal payments on Sept. 15 1990
and the same date a year later.
   ``The Trust and Manville have agreed in principle that Manville
will pay the $50 million principal amount of the note together with
accumulated interest of approximately $8 million to the trust on or
about Dec. 28, 1989,'' the three-page filing with the SEC said.
   Spokespersons for both Denver-based Manville and the Washington,
D.C.-based trust confirmed that an agreement in principle had been
reached.
   ``Manville and the trust anticipate that discussions will
continue, from time to time, regarding mutually acceptable methods
for improving the trust's financial flexibility and enhancing value
for all shareholders,'' the SEC filing said.
   In October, Manville _ a forest products and construction
materials concern _ offered to purchase about $500 million of its
preferred stock from the trust at market prices. On Dec. 7,
however, both the trust and Manville announced that plan had been
withdrawn because of a failure to agree on details of the agreement.
   Both Manville and the Trust said they anticipated future
discussions ``regarding mutually acceptable methods for improving
the trust's financial flexibility and enhancing value for all
shareholders.''
   The trust was created as part of Manville's bankruptcy
reorganization in the late 1980s after a wave of health claims over
asbestos-related diseases forced the company to seek protection
from creditors under Chapter 11 of federal bankruptcy law.
   The trust was created on Nov. 28, 1988, the same day Manville
emerged from reorganization proceedings.
   Since then, the trust has settled more than 15,000 personal
injury cases, paying out more than $600 million to injured victims.
   The trust owns 50 percent, 24 million shares, of Manville's new
common stock as well as convertible preferred stock and a $1.8
billion bond.
   Beginning in 1992, the trust will receive 20 percent of
Manville's net profits, under the terms of the agreement that
created the trust.
</TEXT>

</DOC>