<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0957EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-Panama-Risk     12-20 0787</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Risk,790</SECOND>
<HEAD>America's Last Resort _ Send in the Marines _ Carries Risk</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush, sensing an opening brought
about by a series of events last weekend in Panama, moved to end
almost two years of frustration by sending in the Marines to oust
Gen. Manuel Antonio Noreiga from power.
   The operation may answer critics who ridiculed the decision to
stay off to the side during the failed October coup attempt, but
the early hours of fighting showed the attack was fraught with
military and diplomatic risk.
   Bush's initial concern is that Noriega be found by U.S. forces
quickly, with minimal loss of life, and brought to Florida for
trial on drug trafficking charges.
   In the early going, Noriega was elusive and American soldiers _
at least nine of them _ died. Some 7,000 soldiers and Marines were
sent overnight into Panama to bolster the 12,000 Americans already
stationed there.
   Substantial bloodshed could turn political and public opinion
against the Panama operation, especially if Noriega was to remain
at large. It wasn't clear from the initial reaction whether
Congress or the American public would support an operation that
involved extensive bloodshed and drags on inconclusively for days
or even longer.
   If the operation seems more like Vietnam than Grenada, Bush is
in trouble.
   Most of the initial congressional reaction was supportive. But
Sen. Claiborne Pell, a Rhode Island Democrat and chairman of the
Senate Foreign Relations Committee, said, ``Personally, unless very
clear evidence emerges of a direct threat against the Panama Canal
or against American people or installations, I would not have
engaged in such unilateral or such go-it-alone action'' without the
support of other Central American nations.
   The administration braced for criticism from many in Latin
America, given the aversion throughout the hemisphere to U.S.
unilateral action. Officials believed some would argue the
operation was a direct violation of the United Nations and
Organization of American States charters, both of which stress the
importance of non-interference in a country's internal affairs.
   In Bush's view, Noriega had to go and nothing else had worked.
   The United States had used an impressive array of weapons _
diplomatic, economic, political _ against Noriega for almost two
years but he seemed to be able to laugh off everything Washington
tried.
   Unlike Chinese leaders, Noriega was held in such ill repute that
he never was a candidate for a we-can-do-business-together visit
from national security adviser Brent Scowcroft.
   Noriega seemed entrenched, surviving repudiation by neighbors
and growing economic deprivation among his countyrmen. He called an
election, then threw out the returns when the results didn't please
him. When rebel officers had him in their clutches last October
during a coup attempt, Noriega managed to talk his way out of it.
   Since February 1988, Washington had been saying, ``Noriega must
go.'' But he wouldn't, and didn't.
   One key question mark is the degree to which President Guillermo
Endara is perceived as the legitimate leader of Panama.
   His strength is that he is seen as the winner of the May
elections but his burden is that he was sworn in as president an
hour before the U.S. military operations began in earnest this
morning.
   Another potential risk is that the 35,000 Americans living in
Panama, including U.S. servicemen, may be the targets of resentment
_ or worse _ from Panamanians who believe the invasion was uncalled
for.
   Is it possible the outrage among some Panamanians will be such
that acts of sabotage will be carried out against the Panama Canal?
   The irony of today's action is that when the Bush administration
took office, there seemed to be a greater disposition to try to
work in concert with other Latin American countries to solve the
Noriega problem.
   A U.S.-backed OAS mediation effort begun last spring with the
aim of achieving a democratic transfer of power collapsed in August.
   The impetus for direct U.S. action seemed to gain in October
when Bush was widely criticized for not acting more assertively in
support of the rebel insurrection against Noriega.
   If Bush was looking for an excuse to act, a series of events
starting last Friday gave him his opening. One was a Panamanian
government declaration of a ``state of war'' with the United States.
   Another contributing factor was the tense situation which
ensued, marked by the death of one U.S. serviceman and the
harassment of a U.S. Navy couple. In both cases, members of the
Panamanian military were involved.
   Bush had had enough, and the stage was set for the most
controversial decision of the Bush presidency.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   George Gedda has covered foreign affairs for The
Associated Press since 1968.

</TEXT>

</DOC>