<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0231 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2059EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-Panama-KellyText 8th(Final)Add   12-20 0924</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Panama-Kelly Text, 8th (Final) Add,a0844 et. seq.,840</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHN: generally C-5s.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Q: When did that happen?
   GEN. KELLY: The Apaches went down, oh, two weeks ago.
   Q: General _
   Q: And how were the other aircraft shot down?
   GEN. KELLY: Which other aircraft?
   Q: (Inaudible.)
   GEN. KELLY: Groundfire. Mostly groundfire. In one case, one hit
a wire. I think the other three were groundfire, weren't they _
   Q: Small arms _
   GEN. KELLY: Pretty much, yeah.
   Q: Small arms, rockets?
   ADM. SHEAFER: Small arms, to the best of our knowledge.
   Q: General, you said at the beginning that you did not find any
evidence that any attack was being planned on the Canal. Had you
expected to find some?
   GEN. KELLY: We had to be prepared for that. You know, the Canal
is one of the major reasons that we're in Panama. The treaty gives
us the right to protect and defend the Canal, so that's a duty that
we have. Incidentally, all of my bosses understand clearly that
we're going to adhere meticulously to the provisions of that
treaty, and that's part of the basis that we went down. So yeah, we
were very concerned about it. And if you put the Panama Canal out
of business for a couple of years, that would represent an economic
difficulty in the military.
   Q: General _
   Q: When will the reinforcements arrive?
   GEN. KELLY: Which reinforcements?
   Q: The 2,500 you're sending down of military police.
   GEN. KELLY: The 7th Infantry Division should be completed
sometime tonight. The reason I say that is there is fog up at
Travis, and when we can get them out is a little bit difficult to
predict. But right now, we've got 31 airplanes for them; 21 are in
the air. The MPs left this morning, starting at eight, to the tune
of one airplane per hour, so there were 25 airplanes. And I sat
down and figured that out _ took a little while _ but about 25
hours will put them in there sometime. And I think we'll even beat
that, so, say, 7:15 tomorrow morning _
   Q: General, have you heard anything about Costa Rica offering
sanctuary to Noriega if he crosses over and lays down his arms?
   GEN. KELLY: I have not.
   Q: General, did you have difficulty getting control of the radio
station that was continually broadcasting for Noriega?
   GEN. KELLY: We didn't have difficulty getting control of it
because we weren't trying to get control of it. We had difficulty
getting it off the air. We are still working on that, and we expect
to be successful very shortly.
   Q: How are you doing that? Can you describe that?
   GEN. KELLY: I can't tell you how we plan to do it, but we plan
to do it.
   Q: Could you give us a little better breakdown on the
casualties? We heard earlier firefights at the Comandancia. Was it
also at Rio Hato _
   GEN. KELLY: Firefights went on here at Rio Hato. We sent our
troops in well-armed and superbly trained. And I know that sounds
like bragging, but that's just the truth; they were. So they're at
an advantage with almost anybody else anywhere. And the Rangers, of
course, went in at Rio Hato. They had TACAIR assisting them right
before they went in. There wasn't _
   Q: What kind of TACAIR?
   GEN. KELLY: I'm not going to say, but we had TACAIR there. The
Marines didn't have major enemy forces in their area. Their vital
and key job was to keep the Bridge of the Americas open, which, of
course, is the lifeline in Panama. The fighting up here in the
airborne area turned out to be stiff in places, but overall not all
that difficult _ witness Battalion 2000 not putting up much of a
fight. I don't think we had too much trouble down here with the
Cavalry squadron, the Panama Vieja.
   The fighting around the Comandancia initially was probably as
stiff as any that we ran into, but when we finally went into it
this afternoon, it had been unoccupied; they had left. I think one
of the reasons that the casualties were as low as they were was
that we _ we had well-trained soldiers, we had the helicopter
gunships, we had the AC-130s, which is an airforce gunship which is
extremely accurate. And we took advantage of the tools that we had
in order to protect our soldiers, and sailors, and airmen, and
Marines.
   MR. WILLIAMS: Ladies and gentlemen, thank you very much. We need
to get _ we need to get General Kelly back to the command post. Let
me just make two notes here. First of all about your question about
contacts with people, obviously there were contacts with the people
that have now been _ now taken over as the duly elected leaders of
Panama. They were clearly contacted before the operation and said
they supported it. As Secretary Cheney and I think General Powell
said this morning, they already answered the question about contact
with the PDF, and the answer is no. As to Mr. Engberg's questions
about our knowledge of people in the hotel, we're well aware of
that. The Secretary is aware of it. I think General Kelly referred
to that early on. So we are clearly aware of the situation.
   Thank you all very much.
   Q: (Off mike) _ if there's any word? Will there be another
briefing?
   MR. WILLIAMS: Not today.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   END _ PANAMA-KELLY TEXT, 9 Takes
</TEXT>

</DOC>