<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0101 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1407EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-LandlordDiscrimination     12-18 0338</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Landlord Discrimination,0349</SECOND>
<HEAD>State Supreme Court To Hear Appeal In Landlord Discrimination Case</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TONY KENNEDY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MINNEAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Minnesota Supreme Court has agreed to
hear the appeal of a landlord accused of discrimination for denying
housing to an unmarried couple.
   ``As I see it, this is one of the most important First Amendment
issues in the country,'' said James Anderson, attorney for landlord
Layle French.
   Anderson argues that some forms of discrimination ``are good.''
   ``I'm very encouraged by the Supreme Court agreeing to hear the
case,'' Anderson said Monday.
   French, 33, was fined $1,048 in June by an administrative law
judge who decided he violated the state's anti-discrimination law
when he reneged on an agreement he made in February 1988 to rent
his house in Marshall to Sue Parsons.
   Parsons had said she intended to live in the house with her
fiance, and French later decided that would be against his
religion. The couple now are married.
   French is a member of the Marshall Evangelical Free Church, an
independent Christian church.
   The state Court of Appeals rejected French's appeal. Anderson
said the Appeals Court panel ruled that the state's compelling
interest to eliminate discrimination was enough to override
French's religious belief.
   ``The court of appeals didn't go far enough,'' Anderson said.
``You have to look at the sort of discrimination. If it's
discrimination against race, or women, or a physical handicap, then
yes, religion should not override those.
   ``But other forms of discrimination are good. Layle is
discriminating against what many people view as immoral.''
   Stephen Cooper, the state commissioner of Human Rights, said
French overlooks the fact that his action violated Parsons'
religious freedom.
   ``The biggest threat here is Mr. French imposing his religious
beliefs on tenants,'' Cooper said. ``He stands for the lack of
religious freedom. That's exactly what we fled the rest of the
world for 200 years ago.''
   Peter Popovich, chief justice of the state Supreme Court, said
he did not know when the case would come up.
</TEXT>

</DOC>