<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0112 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0553EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DigestBriefs     12-25 0604</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Digest Briefs,0631</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. troops and armored vehicles
ringed the Vatican Embassy early today after deposed strongman Gen.
Manuel Antonio Noriega escaped a massive search, took refuge and
asked for asylum.
   About 40 soldiers kept watch in the pre-dawn darkness as a
Blackhawk helicopter, its running lights turned off, landed several
times across the street from the embassy, then took off.
   A reporter said he did not see the chopper pick up or discharge
anyone.
   An official at the Vatican said the nunciature could try to turn
Noriega over to the new government or arrange for safe passage to
another country but not put him in the hands of the United States,
where he faces drug trafficking charges.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The hunt for Manuel Antonio Noriega is over,
but President Bush still is searching for ways to bring the
ex-Panamanian dictator to justice even though he is now closeted in
the Vatican ambassador's home, a White House spokesman says.
   Bush learned at Camp David late Sunday afternoon, shortly after
returning from a Pentagon briefing, that Noriega had surfaced
seeking asylum at the residence of the papal nuncio in Panama City
after five days on the run.
   The first reaction from White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater
was that Noriega's ``reign of terror is over.''
   But drug-trafficking indictments still hang over Noriega's head,
and U.S. authorities are weighing options for dealing with the
fugitive ex-dictator.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The provisional government appealed
for a cease-fire by pro-Ceausescu forces who killed thousands in
vicious weekend street battles, and Christmas carols rang out for
the first time in 42 years.
   There were reports that as many as 80,000 people died and
300,000 were wounded since the popular revolt that ousted Communist
President Nicolae Ceausescu began Dec. 15.
   Hungary's Budapest Radio and the British Broadcasting Corp.
reported the same figures Sunday night, quoting ``authoritative
sources in Bucharest,'' but giving no details.
   The reports, like others on casualties, was impossible to verify
independently. But if accurate, the Romanian uprising would be the
bloodiest anti-Communist revolt ever, its death toll far eclipsing
that of the Hungarian revolution of 1956, in which about 30,000
people are believed to have lost their lives.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>JOHNSON CITY, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Firefighters today found a 16th body
and searched for 11 people missing from a fire that swept through a
high-rise retirement home.
   The Christmas Eve fire injured 51 people, including about 25
firefighters, authorities said.
   About 145 people were living at the John Sevier Retirement
Center, but authorities said they didn't know how many were in the
11-story building when the fire broke out.
   ``But it being Christmas Eve, many residents were out of the
building visiting families and many relatives were visiting at the
center,'' city spokeswoman Linda Gordon told reporters.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BATON ROUGE, La. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A huge fire continued today at the
nation's second largest petrochemical refinery after an explosion
ignited storage tanks holding millions of gallons of oil and
lubricants, killing one worker.
   A 4-square-mile area around the refinery, including a section of
Interstate 110, remained closed today.
   The blast shattered windows up to six miles away and was felt up
to 15 miles away. The fire sent a plume of thick, black smoke 500
feet into the air. Flames engulfed eight storage tanks holding more
than 4 million gallons of oil and lubricants, and two separator
units, which remove water from oil, officials said.
   It was believed ignited by a gas release, but what caused the
release was under investigation, said plant Manager Ed Galante.
</TEXT>

</DOC>