<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1346EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Panama-Medicine     12-26 0378</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Medicine,0390</SECOND>
<HEAD>Group Sends First Shipment of Medical Supplies to Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRIAN MURPHY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FORT LAUDERDALE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A group led by the cousin of
U.S.-backed Panamanian President Guillermo Endara sent its first
shipment of medical supplies to Panama Tuesday and announced
further plans to send medicine and food.
   The estimated $50,000 worth of supplies, including plasma and
antibiotics, was accompanied by a physician to help distribute the
items at Panama City's two main hospitals.
   ``We realize this is just a small amount of what's needed, but
at this point anything is a help. These supplies are urgently
needed,'' said Luis Endara Jr., whose cousin was sworn in as
president last week after a U.S. invasion toppled the government of
Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   The supplies, mostly donated to the Help Panama group from
several South Florida hospitals, were packed in boxes and filled
nearly every available space aboard the twin-engine Lear 25 jet.
Other items sent included syringes and needles, intravenous
solutions and orthopedic devices.
   Dr. Roberto Reyna said he would spend several hours in Panama to
allocate the 2,500 pounds of supplies before returning late Tuesday
to Fort Lauderdale-Hollywood International Airport.
   Reyna said the group hopes the campaign for medical and food
provisions will expand nationwide.
   ``The next flight, I hope we have a 747,'' he said.
   Help Panama also has opened accounts at two Miami banks to take
donations, Luis Endara said.
   A cargo ship with six 40-foot containers of food is expected to
leave Miami on Friday for the four-day voyage to Panama, he said.
   Earlier this week, the U.S. Air Force sent medical supplies
aboard a C-5 cargo plane to Panama to aid injured civilians. The
U.S. military has not released figures on civilian casualites or
injuries.
   Luis Endara said he plans to continue relief and fund-raising
efforts in the United States and does not foresee a direct role in
his cousin's government.
   The situation at Panamanian hospitals was complicated by the
Noriega regime using medical supply areas to hide arms, according
to Roberto Dominguez, who was named the Panamanian consul in Miami
on Tuesday.
   ``It's going to take a lot more shipments like these to return
the hospitals to where they should be,'' Dominguez said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>