<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0109 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1946EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-Romania     12-19 0478</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Romania,490</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Condemns Romanian Repression</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM DRINKARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United States on Tuesday condemned the
violent suppression of political dissent in Romania, saying the
Bush administration is reviewing its already limited relationship
with the hard-line East Bloc country.
   ``We call upon the Romanian government to cease these outrageous
policies and allow its citizens freely to exercise their
fundamental human rights,'' State Department spokeswoman Margaret
Tutwiler said, reading an official statement denouncing ``the
brutal use of security forces against the people of Timisoara.''
   The extent of the weekend violence in Timisoara, a city 500
miles west of Bucharest, was difficult to determine because the
government was apparently suppressing news of the events, she said.
   Two U.S. Embassy officials have been sent from Bucharest to try
to get first-hand information, she said.
   White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater also harshly criticized
the Romanian government.
   ``The demonstrations in Timisoara and elsewhere were a result of
the systematic denial of human rights to the people of Romania,
particularly to members of the Hungarian minority,'' Fitzwater said
Tuesday.
   ``The repressive measures undertaken by the Romanian government
are totally unjustified and stand in stark contrast to the positive
changes taking place elsewhere in Eastern Europe,'' he said.
   Ms. Tutwiler said U.S. Ambassador Alan Green will await the
report from the Embassy officials and the return of leader Nicolae
Ceaucescu from an official trip to Iran before deciding whether to
file an official diplomatic protest.
   ``The demonstrations were an obvious manifestation of broad
popular discontent with the policies of the Romanian government and
a clear expression of the Romanian people's desire to join their
neighbors in embracing democratic reform and economic freedom,''
the State Department statement said.
   ``It is sadly regrettable that Romania remains the only Warsaw
Pact country to reject all political and economic reforms,'' as
well as the only signatory to the Helsinki human rights accord to
refuse to acknowledge the commitments it made under that agreement,
Ms. Tutwiler said.
   She said international borders and the Bucharest airport have
been closed to foreign visitors and all international telephone
lines into Romania were getting busy signals.
   The few U.S. citizens in Timisoara known to the Embassy are
safe, she said.
   The United States, Ms. Tutwiler said, is coordinating its
response to the Romanian crackdown with NATO and European Economic
Community allies.
   ``I can tell you we are currently reassessing our bilateral
relationship, including economic, scientific and other areas to
determine if there are other actions which can be meaningfully
taken,'' she said.
   U.S. trade with Romania has declined by half since 1988 when it
renounced most-favored-nation status to get out from under U.S.
freedom-of-emigration requirements the status imposes. The only
trade remaining is about $300 million annually, primarily imports
of Romanian refined petroleum products.
   ``Our relations have deteriorated seriously since then,'' Ms.
Tutwiler said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>