<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0196 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1526EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-WallStreet3pm     12-26 0328</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Wall Street 3pm,0345</SECOND>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prices were little changed in extremely light
trading on Wall Street today as inflation concerns weighed on the
stock and bond markets.
   The Dow Jones average of 30 industrials was up 0.21 at 2,711.60
as of 3 p.m. EST.
   The broader market was also little changed. Advancing issues
were almost even with decliners, with 671 stocks rising, 665
falling and 560 unchanged on the New York Stock Exchange.
   Volume on the Big Board came to a light 64.05 million shares
with one hour of trading left. Many traders extended their
Christmas holiday into this week.
   Stocks tracked the bond market for much of the session,
declining in early trading as bond prices slumped. Wall Street
later shook off the drop in Treasury issues and the Dow Jones
industrial average moved up more than seven points.
   But in late afternoon, when bond prices continued to drop,
stocks gave up their gains. Treasury prices skidded because of a
surge in oil prices after several oil companies reported refinery
shutdowns.
   The January price for a gallon of home heating oil surged nearly
11 cents to 92.60 cents on the New York Mercantile Exchange in late
afternoon, while the Treasury's 30-year bond was down about 1]
point, or $13.75 per $1,000 in face amount. The bond's yield soared
to 7.99 percent from 7.88 late Friday.
   Rising energy prices are considered a harbinger of higher
inflation and, in turn, higher interest rates.
   The most-actively traded stock on the NYSE was Bank of New
England, which rose \ to 7}.
   Exxon was down | to 50[ after a weekend explosion shut down a
major refinery in Texas. American Express was up ~ to 32}, IBM was
off } to 94| and Sears, Roebuck was up { to 37\.
   The NYSE's composite index of all its listed common stocks fell
0.14 to 191.81. On the American Stock Exchange, the market value
index fell 0.15 to 370.69.
</TEXT>

</DOC>