<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0181 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1413EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-PRI--AIDS Adv28   12-26 0831</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-PRI--AIDS, Adv 28,0853</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv28</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Thursday, Dec. 28, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>AIDS Not Simply a Disease of the Young, Drug-Addicted</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   T. Franklin Williams, a geriatrics physician, is
director of the National Institute on Aging, one of the 13
institutes that comprise the National Institutes of Health of the
Department of Health and Human Services.

</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By Dr. T. Franklin Williams</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BETHESDA, Md. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The speed with which society has responded
to the AIDS epidemic is heartening, yet there is one group that
society has not begun to attend to in terms of its risk: older
Americans.
   The fact is, 10 percent of all reported cases of acquired immune
deficiency syndrome have involved people aged 50 and over. And more
older people are believed to be infected, although not yet
experiencing symptoms.
   With increased age comes a decline in immune system functions,
making older people more susceptible to a variety of illnesses such
as cancers and infections. Because of these changes in immune
function, AIDS may affect older people differently than it does the
young. Data from the Centers for Disease Control suggests that most
older people infected with the AIDS virus have developed disease
symptoms more quickly than younger patients.
   The older population also receives the highest rate of blood
transfusions. Blood banks now assure safer blood products than
before 1985, when the public blood supply was not yet being
screened for the virus. By then, however, many older people had
already been exposed to possibly contaminated transfusions. As a
result, blood transfusions are the second most common cause of AIDS
in people over 50 (after sexual contact). Moreover, no one knows
how many people received infected blood and are now unknowingly
infecting spouses or sexual partners.
   Older AIDS patients who have early symptoms also risk going
undiagnosed. Because early symptoms of AIDS, such as fatigue, loss
of appetite and swollen glands, are similar to other more common
illnesses, many people _ including health professionals _ may
dismiss them as minor ailments.
   Medical experts predict that a cure or vaccine against AIDS is
not likely to be found in the near future. So preventing the spread
of AIDS will very much depend on behavioral changes, such as using
condoms when sexually involved with someone other than a mutually
faithful, uninfected partner.
   Prevention also begins with education. AIDS is not spread by
casual contact, but rather through sexual relations, use of
infected needles and blood transfusions. Reliable, up-to-date
information is available from many sources. The Public Health
Service sent a brochure, ``Understanding AIDS,'' to every home in
the country. Call the National AIDS Hotline, 1-800-342-AIDS for
another copy; other hotlines also can answer specific questions.
   Researchers are working to understand AIDS and how to treat
people who are infected. Treatment for the symptoms usually
involves some drug therapy, such as AZT (azidothymidine), which
currently is being used in many patients to prolong life. Other
promising drugs are also being tested.
   People exposed to the virus should stay in touch with a doctor
who is well-informed about the latest research. For help finding an
expert, call a medical school's infectious disease department or
the National AIDS Hotline.
   You can make a valuable contribution by offering to help groups
in your community who work with AIDS patients. Many operate on a
shoestring and depend heavily on individual contributions of time
and money. These groups include the American Red Cross, March of
Dimes, Boys Clubs and Girls Clubs, and the local YMCA. Their phone
numbers are listed in your directory, and they will be glad to tell
you how to get involved with education, fund-raising drives or
volunteer programs.
   In the years ahead, individuals willing to offer their services
to AIDS patients will be increasingly needed. Volunteers can
contribute a great deal without endangering their health. For
example, as people with AIDS become more disabled, they have
trouble meeting their daily needs; they appreciate help with
shopping, cooking meals, or just regular visits for talking.
   For more information on volunteer programs, call your health
department or the National AIDS Hotline.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   The following local and national organizations also offer
information:
   National AIDS Hotline: 1-800-342-AIDS; 1-800-344-SIDA (for
Spanish); 1-800-AIDS-889 (for hearing-impaired).
   American Red Cross, AIDS Public Education Office, 1730 E Street,
N.W., Washington, D.C. 20006. (Local chapters offer a variety of
written material.)
   National AIDS Information Clearinghouse, P.O. Box 6003,
Rockville, MD 20850; (301) 762-5111, 1-800-458-5231. (The
clearinghouse offers free government publications and information
about resources.)
   National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, Office of
Communications, Building 31 Room 7A32, Bethesda, MD 20892. (One of
the National Institues of Health, NIAID will respond to written
requests for information on AIDS research and clinical trials of
promising therapies.)
   National Institute on Aging, Public Information Office, Federal
Building Room 6C12, Bethesda, MD 20892; (301) 496-1752. (One of the
National Institutes of Health, the NIA offers information on a
range of health issues of concern to older people.)
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Dec. 28</NOTE>

</DOC>