<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0138 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0738EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv31   12-26 0412</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv31,0433</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 31</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is Saturday, Dec. 31, the 365th and final day of 1989.
   Today's highlight in history:
   On Dec. 31, 1946, President Truman officially proclaimed the end
of World War II.
   On this date:
   In 1775, the British repulsed an attack by Continental Army
Gens. Richard Montgomery and Benedict Arnold at Quebec. Montgomery
was killed.
   In 1857, Britain's Queen Victoria decided to make Ottawa the
capital of Canada.
   In 1862, President Lincoln signed an act admitting West Virginia
to the Union.
   In 1879, inventor Thomas Edison first publicly demonstrated his
electric incandescent light in Menlo Park, N.J.
   In 1943, a near-riot of bobby-soxers in New York's Times Square
greeted Frank Sinatra's singing engagement at the Paramount Theater.
   In 1961, the Marshall Plan expired after distributing more than
$12 billion in foreign aid.
   In 1974, private United States citizens were allowed to buy and
own gold for the first time in more than 40 years.
   In 1977, Donald Woods, a white South African editor banned by
the government from practicing journalism because of his campaign
against racial laws, fled the country.
   In 1978, Taiwanese diplomats struck their colors for the final
time from the embassy flagpole in Washington, marking the end of
diplomatic relations with the United States.
   In 1986, 97 people were killed and more than 140 injured when
fire broke out in the Dupont Plaza Hotel in San Juan, Puerto Rico.
   Ten years ago: The United Nations Security Council approved a
United States-sponsored resolution threatening Iran with economic
sanctions unless it released the American hostages within a week.
   Five years ago: Bernard H. Goetz, who had shot four youths on a
New York City subway because, he said, they were going to rob him,
surrendered to police in Concord, N.H.
   One year ago: President Reagan and Soviet President Mikhail
Gorbachev exchanged New Year's messages in which both leaders
expressed optimism about future superpower relations.
   Today's birthdays: Composer Jule Styne is 84. Nazi hunter Simon
Wiesenthal is 81. Television producer George Schlatter is 57. Actor
Anthony Hopkins is 52. Actress Sarah Miles is 48. Singer John
Denver is 46. Actor Ben Kingsley is 46. Fashion designer Diane Von
Furstenberg is 43. Singer Donna Summer is 41.
   Thought for today: ``The fatality of good resolutions is that
they are always too late.'' _ Oscar Wilde, Irish poet, playwright
and author (1856-1900).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sun Dec. 31</NOTE>

</DOC>