<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0349EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BirthCenters     12-28 0656</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Birth Centers,0679</SECOND>
<HEAD>Study: Birth Centers Safe Alternative for Many Women</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DANIEL Q. HANEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Many women can opt for the homey surroundings of
birth centers instead of hospital obstetrical wards without undue
risk to themselves or their babies, said a study published today.
   ``Normal birth ought not be considered a sickness requiring
hospitalization,'' said Dr. Allan Rosenfield, a co-author of the
study.
   The study found that women who were at low risk of complications
do just as well in birth centers that are located outside hospitals
as they do having babies in hospitals, and they are far less likely
to have Caesarean sections.
   Rosenfield, an obstetrician who is dean of Columbia University's
School of Public Health, said that ``properly screened, this is a
reasonable alternative to a hospital delivery for women who prefer
it.''
   The study, based on nearly 12,000 childbirths, was intended to
answer lingering doubts about the safety of birth centers.
   Despite the positive findings, however, some physicians remained
skeptical.
   In an editorial published with the findings in today's New
England Journal of Medicine, Drs. Ellice Lieberman and Kenneth J.
Ryan of Brigham and Women's Hospital in Boston said that more
research will be necessary ``to evaluate fully the safety of
delivery in free-standing facilities.''
   The Boston doctors criticized the study because it failed to
include all the birth centers in the United States or to enroll a
comparison group of women who gave birth in hospitals.
   They said that birth centers should be located inside hospitals,
which have the emergency equipment needed to deal with rare,
unexpected complications.
   ``Hospital-based birth centers combine the best of both
facilities by offering the atmosphere of a birth center without
sacrificing the safety of a hospital,'' they wrote.
   Presently, 132 free-standing birth centers operate in the United
States and deliver about 20,000 babies annually. Typically, women
are assisted by midwives rather than physicians.
   The study was organized by the National Association of
Childbearing Centers and directed by Judith P. Rooks, a
nurse-midwife at Columbia.
   ``The whole idea is to make it like women's homes and to give
them the control they want over their childbirth experience,'' said
Eunice K.M. Ernst, the association's director. ``We take the
position that birth is a family event, and for the majority of
women it's a normal event in their lives.
   ``It's true that it can become complicated and require medical
intervention. But women have the right to consider it normal until
proven otherwise.''
   Ernst noted that birth centers cost one-third to one-half less
than hospital deliveries.
   The study was based on the experiences of all 11,814 women who
used 84 of these centers over a 2{-year period. They were typically
white, middle-class and well educated.
   Among the findings:
   _71 percent had only minor or no complications during childbirth.
   _8 percent had serious emergency complications, and 1 in 6 had
to be transferred to hospitals.
   _No women died. The newborn death rate was 1.3 per 1,000 births.
The rate of infant deaths and abnormalities was similar to that
seen in large studies of low-risk hospital births.
   _4 percent of the women had Caesarean sections. Nationally,
about 25 percent of women deliver their babies surgically.
   _99 percent of those who gave birth in the birth centers said
they would recommend the the centers to friends, as would 97
percent of those who were transferred to hospitals.
   Safety has been the primary concern about birth centers. The
American Academy of Pediatrics and the American College of
Obstetricians and Gynecologists have discouraged their use until
better data are available.
   Questions were also raised by an Institute of Medicine review in
1982. The latest research was intended to answer these concerns.
   ``We did the study because we really wanted to know if birth
centers were safe,'' said Rooks. ``We looked very carefully and
hard. We did not find an excessive incidence of poor outcomes from
these birth centers.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>