<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0114 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1918EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Panama-Deaths 1stLd-Writethru   12-26 0706</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Deaths, 1st Ld - Writethru,a0643,570</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pentagon Releases Names of Dead</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: DELETES 21st graf, which 20th graf, Lt. Paz, killed before the
invasion, and ADDS graf on CWO Owens. FYI and contrary to pvs editors note,
this list is now identical to one transmitted for Mon AMs, though in different
order</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Pentagon has been releasing the names of
servicemen killed in the Panamanian invasion as their next of kin
are notified. Here are the names released as of late Monday
afternoon.
   _Cpl. Garreth C. Isaak, a Marine born Dec. 28, 1966, and a
native of Greenville, S.C. Isaak entered the Marine Corps on May
29, 1985.
   _Cpl. Ivan D. Perez, 22, of Pawtucket, R.I. Perez, an Army
infantryman based at Fort Polk, La., entered the service in 1985.
   _Pfc. Scott Lee Roth, 19, of Killeen, Texas. He was a military
policeman stationed at Fort Hood, Texas.
   _Specialist Phillip S. Lear, 21, Westminster, S.C. He was an
infantryman based at Fort Lewis, Wash.
   _Lt. j.g. John Patrick Connors, born March 28, 1964, and a
native of Arlington, Mass. Connors entered the Navy on May 20,
1987, and was a member of the Navy's special operations unit known
as the SEALS, based at Little Creek, Va.
   _Chief Engineman Donald Lewis McFaul, born Sept. 20, 1957, and a
native of San Diego, Calif. McFaul entered the Navy on June 26,
1975, and was a SEAL based at Little Creek, Va.
   _Boatswain's Mate 1st Class Christopher Tilghman, born Dec. 2,
1959, and a native of Kailua, Hawaii. Tilghman entered the Navy on
Jan. 18, 1979, and was a SEAL based at Little Creek, Va.
   _Pfc. Jerry Scott Daves, born Sept. 8, 1969, and a native of
Hope Mills, N.C. Davis was a member of the 1st Battalion, 504th
Parachute Infantry Regiment.
   _Torpedoman's mate Second Class Issac George Rodriguez, born
March 22, 1965, and a native of Missouri City, Texas. He was a SEAL
who entered the Navy on Feb. 24, 1983.
   _Pfc. James William Markwell, born May 29, 1968, and a native of
Cincinnati, Ohio. He was a medic who entered the Army on Feb. 23,
1989.
   _Pvt. 2 Kenneth Douglas Scott, born May 20, 1969, and a native
of Princeton, W.Va. He was an infantryman who entered the Army on
June 15, 1989.
   _Spec. Alejandro I. Manriquelozano, born Oct. 3, 1959, and a
native of Lauderhill, Fla. He entered the Army on Jan. 20, 1988.
   _Pfc. John Mark Price, born Dec. 24, 1966, and a native of
Conover, Wis. An infantryman, Price entered the Army on July 19,
1988.
   _Pfc. Roy Dennis Brown Jr., born March 21, 1970, and a native of
Buena Park, Calif. An infantryman, Brown entered the Army on Oct.
19, 1988.
   _Spc. William D. Gibbs, born July 27, 1967, and a native of
Marina, Calif. An infantryman, Gibbs entered the Army on Aug. 6,
1985.
   _Staff Sgt. Larry R. Barnard, born Dec. 8, 1960, a native
Hallstead, Pa., An infantryman and Ranger, Barnard entered the Army
June 5, 1980.
   _Pfc. Vance T. Coates, born Jan. 27, 1971, and a native of Great
Falls, Mont. An infantryman, Coates entered the Army Feb. 2, 1989.
   _Pfc. Martin D. Denson, born Sept. 12, 1968, and a native of
Abilene, Texas. An infantryman, Denson entered the Army Jan. 18,
1989.
   _Chief Warrant Officer Andrew P. Porter, born April 20, 1964,
whose home was listed as Saint Clair, Mich. Porter was an aviator
in the 7th Infantry division based at Fort Ord, Calif., who entered
the Army on Aug. 24, 1982.
   _Sgt. Michael Deblois, born Sept. 30, 1965, from Dubach, La., a
member of the 508th Infantry Regiment, 82nd Airborne Divison, Fort
Bragg, N.C.
   _Pvt. James Allen Tabor, born Jan. 6, 1971, of Montrose, Colo. A
heavy weapons specialist in 325th Parachute Infantry Regiment, Fort
Bragg, N.C., he entered the service on July 5, 1989.
   _1st Lt. John Wessel Hunter, born Jan. 29, 1959 of Victor, Mont,
an aviator with the 160th Aviation Battalion based at Fort
Campbell, Ky.
   _Chief Warrant Officer Wilson B. Owens, born April 25, 1960, of
North Myrtle Beach, S.C. An aviator with the 160th Aviation
Battaltion based at Fort Campbell, Ky., Owens entered the Army on
Feb. 23, 1979.
</TEXT>

</DOC>