<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0348EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-WashingtoninBrief     12-30 0598</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Washington in Brief,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Disability Benefits To Rise Jan. 1</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   New rules taking effect the first day of the
new year will raise the amount of money recipients of government
disability benefits can earn, says the Department of Health and
Human Services.
   HHS Secretary Louis Sullivan said Friday that the increases
``will serve as an additional incentive for many disabled Americans
to return to work and improve the quality of life for themselves
and their families.''
   The rules will affect recipients of Supplemental Security Income
program and the Social Security Disability Insurance program who
are not blind.
   Under the disability insurance program, recipients are allowed
to earn up to a certain amount and still receive benefits. On Jan.
1, that level will increase for the first time in more than a
decade.
   The new rules will change the trigger for the ``trial work
period'' during which a disability insurance recipient continues to
receive benefits for nine months after returning to work. Since
January 1979, a recipient has entered a ``trial work period'' when
he earns more than $75 per month or works more than 15 hours per
week. That will increase to $200 or 40 hours.
   Also under the disability insurance program, when the
recipient's earnings reach the ``substantial gainful activity''
level, which has been set at $300 per month since January 1980,
benefits can continue only under certain conditions. That trigger
will rise to $500.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>NIH Scrapping Conflict-of-Interest Guidelines</NOTE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The National Institutes of Health is scrapping
proposed conflict-of-interest guidelines that stirred controversy
among scientists and will begin laboring anew to draft new options,
officials say.
   The guidelines proposed for the federal research agency last
September were an attempt to ensure the integrity of
government-funded projects by preventing researchers from having a
financial interest in the outcome of their work.
   But many scientists said the proposal would hamper efforts to
turn academic research into commercial products and could cost the
United States its competitive edge in biomedical research.
   The proposal suggested that NIH grant recipients disclose their
and their families' financial interests and said government-funded
researchers should have no equity interest in any company that
would benefit from their research. It also proposed barring
researchers from sharing information with companies until it is
publicly available.
   NIH received more than 600 comments on the proposal, said NIH
spokeswoman Ann Thomas.
   Dr. Louis Sullivan, secretary of the Department of Health and
Human Services, said Friday that he has asked NIH to submit to him
new options ``that properly treat potential abuse while keeping the
research process free of unnecessary burdens and disincentives.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Stepped-Up Anti-Drug Program Allots Four-Fold Increase to</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   California
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   California will receive a nearly four-fold
increase in federal money for anti-drug abuse programs in the
Justice Department's first allocation of state aid under a
stepped-up program approved by Congress, the department says.
   Attorney General Dick Thornburgh said Friday that the money is
part of the Bush administration's efforts to help communities
``attack the problem at the point of consumption.''
   He said the department is urging states to incorporate
recommendations of President Bush's national drug control strategy
into their programs.
   California, the first state to receive funds for fiscal year
1990, will get $39.7 million, almost $30 million more than its 1989
grant of $10.8 million. Under a plan adopted by California, nearly
65 percent of the money will be distributed to local communities.
   The department said its Bureau of Justice Assistance is
receiving and reviewing grant applications from other states.
Congress appropriated $395 million for the grants.
</TEXT>

</DOC>