<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0224 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1548EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-EthanolPlane 1stLd-Writethru   12-19 0580</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ethanol Plane, 1st Ld-Writethru,0597</SECOND>
<HEAD>First Atlantic Crossing Made By Ethanol Plane</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: CORRECTS spelling of pilot to Shauck, sted Schauck, in grafs
8, 9, 12, 16 and 18.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATRICK McDOWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It wasn't quite Lindbergh, but a Texas university
professor earned his footnote in aviation history Tuesday when he
completed the first trans-Atlantic flight in an ethanol-fueled
airplane.
   Max Shauck, a mathematics instructor at Baylor University in
Waco, Texas, landed at the small Toussus-le-Noble airport southwest
of Paris after a one-hour flight from Tours.
   He set out with Italian co-pilot Grazia Zanin from Waco on Sept.
15 in a light experimental aircraft that carried them through often
rough weather to Canada, the Azores, Portugal, Spain and finally
France.
   ``We feel we have proved that ethanol is a very reliable fuel,''
Shauck said. ``You can't get across the Atlantic on an unreliable
fuel.''
   Proving the merits of the relatively cheap, non-polluting
ethanol compared to standard fuel drove Shauck make the journey,
which he funded himself at more cost ``than I care to think about.''
   Ethanol is essentially an alcohol fuel made from vegetable
matter, usually corn in the United States and sugar beets in
Europe. Shauck, who also does air pollution research at Baylor,
says ethanol retails for about $1.20 per gallon in the United
States compared to $1.80 for high-octane aviation fuel.
   ``It produces more power, it burns cooler and there's a lot less
pollution,'' he said. ``But we had to go out of our way sometimes
to find it.''
   Indeed, Shauck and Zanin's flight log includes a hodgepodge of
small stopovers in North America chosen chiefly because ethanol
could be delivered there.
   These included Paducah, Ky.; Newark, Ohio; Hazelton, Pa.; and
Suffolk, N.Y. The plane also stopped at Shauck's hometown of
Mansfield, Ohio.
   In Canada, they stopped at Moncton and St. Pierre-et-Miquelon
before lifting off from St. John's, Newfoundland on Oct. 20 for
Flores in the Azore Islands, a 2,000-mile crossing made terrifying
by rain and thunderstorms.
   ``It's a long way over a lot of water when you're flying a
little plane looking for little islands,'' he said. ``We didn't
have sophisticated navigation equipment.''
   They waited in the Azores for nearly three weeks for a shipment
of ethanol to arrive before flying to Lisbon Nov. 10. Shauck, 54,
and Ms. Zanin, 33, made stops in Bilbao, Spain, and Bordeaux,
Rochet-Sur-Yon and Tours in France.
   Technically, they became the first people to cross the Atlantic
in an ethanol-fueled plane the minute they touched down in
Portugal, but the original plan they filed with American
authorities was from Suffolk County, N.Y., airport to Paris.
   The fiberglass aircraft, a sort of flying wing built by the
Velocity Corp. of Sebastian, Fla., featured elevators, normally
found on the tail, at the front of the airplane and a propellor
mounted on the back.
   The whole contraption weighs about 2,100 pounds and can reach a
top speed of 200 mph.
   Shauck resists comparison with American aviator Charles
Lindbergh, first man to cross the Atlantic in a flight from New
York to Le Bourget airport in Paris on May 31, 1927.
   ``He is a hero,'' Shauck said. ``Everything now is different
than it was in his day. I avoided going to Le Bourget because I
didn't want to be compared to him.''
   Shauck said he would take a commercial flight back to Texas, but
that the aircraft will make one more trip _ to Ms. Zanin's
hometown, Trieste.
</TEXT>

</DOC>