<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0173 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1346EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a AM-ReligionToday Adv22   12-19 0734</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Religion Today, Adv 22,0756</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv22</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Friday AMs, Dec. 22, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Two Christmases _ Secular and Religious _ Coincide And Compete</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE W. CORNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Religion Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Although they happen simultaneously and go by the same name,
there are two types of Chirstmas celebrations taking place these
days _ the religious and the secular. They mingle, and also compete.
   Some people maintain the secular aspects have overshadowed the
original religious purpose to the point of threatening to displace
it, thus undermining the sometimes complementary values of both.
   ``We're in danger of losing Christmas,'' says the Rev. John F.
MacArthur Jr., pastor of Grace Community Church in Sun Valley,
Calif.
   ``It may now be the biggest and most popular of all holidays,
but Christmas is in jeopardy just the same. A subtle but sure
erosion is eating away the season's true significance.''
   Its significance is God's incarnation in the birth of Jesus,
``God With Us,'' McArthur writes in a book of that title published
by Zondervan. He says the essential is being obscured.
   Efforts both to secularize and ``to mythologize the Christmas
story'' are robbing it of basic meaning, reducing it ``to little
more than an elaborate fable,'' he says.
   ``Most people don't know which details are biblical and which
are fabricated,'' he writes, with ``facts lost in the mythology
that has overgrown the account.''
   The story of Jesus' birth is no allegory, but is rather an event
in which ``God has given the greatest Christmas gift of all time''
_ his identification with humanity, McArthur says.
   He says secularizing influences also have eroded the real point
of the celebration, making it the ``ultimate holiday for committed
hedonists,'' with spiritual values smothered in ``crass
consumerism.''
   ``Drunken parties, self-indulgence, madcap spending and obscene
gluttony all characterize the way much of the world celebrates
Christmas,'' he says, calling for re-emphasis on worship and ``real
joy and gladness.''
   He says some secular traditions _ the decorations, family
visits, get-togethers with friends, the exchange of gifts _ ``add
to the joy of the season and they're all legitimate,'' including
Santa and his reindeer.
   But he says the real underpinning of the holiday is crumbling
under the secularizing tide, and urges commitment to revitalizing
that basic purpose.
   The Rev. James M. Wall, editor of the weekly Christian Century,
says the ``two Christmases travel on parallel tracks, but they
offer dramatically different perspectives.''
   He points out the ``secular Christmas'' draws on ``religious
imagery to evoke emotions regarding gift-giving and selflessness''
and ``memories of home and the joy of receiving gifts.''
   ``But it never acknowledges a basic contradiction in its
approach: no gift ever delivers what we long for,'' Wall says.
``What we long for is a connection to the eternal _ something no
train set or bicycle can provide.
   ``We encounter this disappointment as children, but we continue
to long for fulfillment when we hear the promises of the season.
When it is all over, if we have been locked into the mind-set of
secular Christmas, we are left with the post-Christmas depression.''
   In that sense, Wall writes editorially, Christmas ``can carry
seeds of its own destruction. Put too much reliance on finding
happiness in the event itself and you are doomed to disappointment.
   ``The celebration of a religious event for secular purposes is
bound to leave the human spirit unsatisfied.''
   Neverthless, he says, society works energetically to uphold the
secular Christmas and crowd out the religious version.
   ``The word that God became human is so absurd to the secular
mind-set that it must be greeted with an all-out defense of the
secular version of goodness and truth,'' he says.
   In responding to the ultimate mystery of God's revelation in
history, ``either we accept the gift and stand in awe that such a
thing is possible, or we vigorously deny even the possibility that
ultimacy could embrace us in such a fashion,'' Wall adds.
   ``If one is to insist that all truth is confined to the rational
mode, as the modern Western mind-set demands, then the Christmas
event must either be viewed as a quaint fable or translated into a
secular celebration.''
   But once the religious dimension fades, the grounds for goodness
are gone, Wall says, and as a Dostoevsky character warns,
``everything is permitted.'' Or to paraphrase the cynical Ebenezer
Scrooge:
   ``Christmas without a transcendent God is humbug.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Fri AMs, Dec. 22</NOTE>

</DOC>