<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0177 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1150EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a w PM-TexasClout Adv01   12-29 0707</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Texas Clout, Adv 01,0726</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv01</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Mon PMs, Jan. 1, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Texans Start Year With Heralded Clout Diminished</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JENNIFER DIXON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Texans strode into Washington last January
confident the Lone Star was in ascendancy _ laying claim to the
White House, the House speakership and a passel of Cabinet posts
and congressional committee chairmanships.
   They begin the new year with their influence on the Bush
administration undiminished, but their clout in Congress has been
decimated by death, illness, a retirement and the resignation of
their most powerful member.
   Rep. Michael Andrews, a Houston Democrat, says Texas is coming
off a ``windshift year.''
   Some Texans fear their legendary clout _ which they predicted
was waxing at the start of 1989 _ has waned so much that the state
is now at a disadvantage in fighting for the government largesse
that has traditionally come their way.
   Early on, the Senate refused to confirm President Bush's choice
of John Tower as secretary of defense after exploring allegations
of womanizing and excessive drinking by the former Texas senator.
   Three months later, in June, House Speaker Jim Wright abandoned
a 34-year career in the House and resigned from the most
influential position in Congress amid an ethics investigation of
his personal finances.
   In August, Rep. Mickey Leland of Houston was killed when his
bush plane slammed into a remote mountain in Ethiopia on its way to
a refugee camp.
   In October, after suffering abdominal pains, Rep. Jack Brooks,
dean of the Texas congressional delegation, was hospitalized for
six weeks for an inflammation of the pancreas.
   And on Dec. 1, Rep. Marvin Leath, an influential Democrat on the
House Budget and Armed Services committees, announced he would not
seek a seventh term in 1990.
   Despite the setbacks, the Texas delegation still landed $225
million to begin building the superconducting super collider, a
giant particle accelerator that scientists hope will help them
understand the origins of the universe, and fended of a potential
attempt to cut $100 million in Pentagon funding for Sematech, a
national semiconductor research consortium in Austin.
   Texas also saw the Pentagon chose Dyess Air Force Base as a site
for rail-based MX missiles _ a project that supportors say
guarantees the Abilene installation a mission into the next century
even as budget cutters slash military spending.
   But they still face a tough fight to maintain research and
development funds for another military project being built in Texas
_ the V-22 Osprey aircraft _ and they failed to obtain tax breaks
for the state's troubled oil and gas industry.
   Rep. John Bryant, a Dallas Democrat, says he's afraid the
delegation's weakened presence in Washington leaves it vulnerable
to new attacks this year by other members of Congress who believe
Texas has long gotten more than its fair share from the federal
government.
   Bryant, who in April announced he was a candidate for state
attorney general, decided in December to pull out of the race and
stay in Washington, where he can keep an eye on next year's budget
as a member of the House Budget Committee.
   He says the super collider, Sematech and the space station,
being built in Houston, all may be under seige in 1990.
   When Congress reconvenes later this month, he says, it will do
so ``for the first time in modern history without a Texas member in
a key position to protect our state's interests in the budget
process.''
   Still, Texas is hardly without well-positioned members of
Congress.
   Its senior senator, Democrat Lloyd Bentsen, is chairman of the
Finance Committee. In the House, Brooks heads the Judiciary
Committee, Rep. Henry B. Gonzalez is chairman of the Banking,
Finance and Urban Affairs Committee, and Rep. Kika de la Garza is
chairman of the Agriculture Committee.
   ``We still have a lot of power there,'' says Bentsen, the 1988
Democratic vice presidential candidate and a potential presidential
candidate in 1992.
   Bentsen's fellow senator from Texas, Republican Phil Gramm, puts
it this way:
   ``Before all this happened, Texas had the greatest degree of
influence in Washington of any state in the union. Texas still has
the most influence of any state in the union.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Mon PMs Jan. 1</NOTE>

</DOC>