<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1246EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AChristmasCat Bjt   12-23 0720</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-A Christmas Cat, Bjt,0741</SECOND>
<HEAD>On Christmas Eve, Author Saves a Stray Cat; Best-Seller Born</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY12</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DONNELLY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   On a frosty Christmas Eve some years ago, author
Cleveland Amory was in ill spirits. Manhattan sparkled with a fresh
blanket of snow, but it didn't matter. He wasn't a man prone to
merriment and he was alone.
   But that night a woman rapped on his door asking for help to
catch a cat in an alley between two midtown towers.
   Amory reluctantly followed her outside and amid the debris, he
saw the cat _a ghost of a cat, really, bone-thin, dirty, wet and
shivering. He put the cat in his coat and he turned for home.
   So begins a true tale called ``The Cat Who Came for Christmas,''
and so began a relationship that changed cat and curmudgeon.
   Now the book is on a New York Times best-seller list for the
third consecutive Christmas, climbing to No. 2 in the newspaper's
paperback non-fiction category. More than 1.5 million copies have
been sold.
   The relationship, now in its 12th year, has never been so
trusting _ or so set in its ways.
   The story details their first year together, including the
trouble in naming the white cat (Polar Bear was eventually agreed
to), the trouble in traveling with a cat, the trouble with putting
a cat on diet food and the trouble with having guests.
   Polar Bear, though, had no trouble in laying down the law: Amory
must adjust to a life of being cat-owned.
   He has.
   ``You can't help but be, because they suddenly are in control,''
said the 72-year-old Amory, who had always owned dogs.
   Amory, a big bear of a man with thick, gray hair brushed
straight back from his broad forehead, is the founder and head of
the Fund for Animals. The New York-based anti-cruelty society has
been instrumental in saving infant harp seals in Canada, wild
burros in the Grand Canyon and wild goats on Navy-owned San
Clemente Island off the Southern California coast.
   The former newspaper reporter and editor also wrote six books,
including ``The Proper Bostonians,'' ``The Last Resorts,'' and
``Who Killed Society?'' He turned his attention to animal rights
more than 20 years ago after seeing a bullfight in Mexico and a
``bunny bop'' in Harmony, N.C., in which townspeople encircled
rabbits and clubbed them to death.
   Amory spends much of his time now selling his Christmas book:
One day last week he gave 13 radio interviews in a little more than
two hours. In each interview, he mentioned the tens of thousands of
animals in shelters and on the streets in need of homes.
   His story about Polar Bear, one reader wrote, ``has been
responsible for more cats being saved or adopted than any other
book.''
   ``That letter meant more to me than any of the others,'' Amory
said in an interview in his one-bedroom apartment overlooking
Central Park. The apartment is full of Polar Bear's toys: little
stuffed mice, balls on a string, catnip pouches. There's also
``Polar Bear's Christmas tree,'' decorated with cat cards.
   Green-eyed Polar Bear _ he's somewhere between 12 to 14 years
old _ was at his feet. He's plump despite diet dinners. And he
isn't very friendly, leaving the room after a pat from a visitor.
   ``He doesn't like anything that hasn't happened before. And he
doesn't need to meet any people he hasn't met before,'' said Amory.
``I think he's gotten to be more of a one-man cat.''
   And Amory is a one-cat man. They seem to have taken on some of
the same attributes in their advancing ages. They're both a bit
slower afoot and a bit quicker to snap. ``He has acquired some of
my worst traits,'' Amory said. ``Like my quick temper. He's
certainly developed toward being a curmudgeon.''
   This night before Christmas, like past ones, Amory plans to
venture out around New York while Polar Bear sleeps. He is on a
mission _ for animals.
   One year he persuaded police to order carriage horses off the
streets because of bitter cold.
   This Christmas Eve, he'll look down alleys for other Polar Bears.
   ``Every Christmas Eve, I think about finding him,'' he said,
stroking his cat. ``I'll be looking terribly careful for strays.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>