<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0127 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1701EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel-Panama     12-21 0363</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Panama,0374</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israel TV Says Noriega Seen in Last Day on Island off Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israel television said Thursday that Gen.
Manuel Antonio Noriega, a fugitive from U.S. justice since American
forces invaded Panama this week, was spotted within the last 24
hours on the luxurious island of Contadora.
   Israel television correspondent Hanan Azran told The Associated
Press that Noriega and Mike Harrari, a former agent in Israel's
Mossad intelligence agency and a top Noriega aide, were on
Contadora, 40 miles southeast of Panama City, planning an escape to
Nicaragua where they would ask for asylum.
   Azran said the television report was based on two phone calls he
received from ``people who are close to Mike and the weapons
business there.'' He said similar phone calls were also made to the
Panamanian embassy in Tel Aviv.
   Azran said the callers, who he would only further identify as
native Spanish speakers, said Noriega and Harrari were spotted with
their aides on Contadora within the last 24 hours.
   ``They explained to me that Harrari's plan is to cross the
border into Costa Rica and then Nicaragua,'' Azran said.
   Contadora first came to public attention when the Shah of Iran
stayed several months there after he was exiled from his country.
   Contadora was where the foreign ministers of four Latin
countries, Mexico, Venezuela, Colombia and Panama, met in 1981 to
negotiate the first attempts at peace in Central America. The four
later expanded to a group of eight including South American
countries, but Panama was later suspended from the group.
   Azran said Harrari and Noriega plan to go from Contadora to
Chiriqui, a small town in the north of the country, which ``Noreiga
has already prepared for himself with his own people.''
   Azran said he was told the two men would then cross with their
forces into Costa Rica and later Nicaragua.
   Harrari, a renegade Mossad agent, is regarded as a top Noriega
advisor.
   Israel's foreign ministry refused to comment on Harrari's
actions saying the ministry does not comment on the actions of
private citizens.
   There was no immediate comment on the Israeli television report
from U.S. or Panamanian officials.
</TEXT>

</DOC>