<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0527EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-OilBoom     12-18 0584</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Oil Boom,0603</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Drilling Technology Inspires Dreams of Oil Boom</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BIG WELLS, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For most of the decade this corner of
south Texas suffered the double whammy of drought and the oil bust.
But a new drilling technology has pumped up hopes of a new boomtime.
   The technology involves horizontal drilling, which industry
observers say might make billions of barrels of additional oil
reserves economical to bring to the surface.
   ``It's like a prairie fire. It will expand through our industry.
It's very exciting,'' said Philip Crouse, who heads a consulting
company in Dallas.
   The promise of the technology can be seen in the south Texas
fields, which are filled with rig after rig.
   ``Oryx, Oryx, Majestic, Weber, Oryx. ... That's nine you can
count from right here. It's unbelievable,'' said petroleum engineer
Ed Riddle, listing the rigs by their company name.
   A quarter-mile away is the Leta Glasscock No. 10, which some
call the hottest oil well in Texas. It is said to have a potential
of 5,470 barrels per day.
   Even at its current allowable rate of 1,312 barrels per day, the
well would increase daily oil production for all of Zavala County
by about two-thirds over last year.
   ``I never thought I'd see flow rates like this domestically. For
this, I thought I'd have to go to the Middle East,'' said Riddle,
who works for Charlie Winn, the owner of Glasscock wells No. 10 and
No. 12.
   This region is known as the Pearsall Field, part of a geological
formation that runs northeast from above Laredo past Austin.
   Characterized by numerous small oil reservoirs that run
vertically, the Pearsall Field enjoyed its last heyday almost a
decade ago. More recently, it was considered to be played out.
   But in the last few months, the newly refined technique of
horizontal drilling has hit it big again.
   Shallow depleted oil reservoirs are prime targets for horizontal
drilling, which was updated in recent years to become more
efficient.
   The technique involves drilling vertically for about 1,000 feet
and then placing horizontal drills into oil reservoirs. It works on
shallow reservoirs that have little subterranean pressure left.
   ``That was a dead field, now it's considered the best prospect
in the Lower 48,'' said Bill Fuqua, president of Dallas-based Basin
Resources, which is investing heavily in the Pearsall Field.
   In all of last year, the Texas Railroad Commission issued 61
drilling permits for the field; in the first 11 months of this
year, the commission issued 175 permits.
   ``Prior to April or May, you could have bought all the leases in
this county for $30 to $50 an acre. All you wanted. Now, if there
is any open, it would go as high as $300, and the only thing left
is small tracts or town lots in Dilley,'' said Frio County Clerk
Mona Hoyle, who has leased 240 acres of her own property.
   In Dilley, drilling rigs are working north and south of town of
2,500 residents about 70 miles south of San Antonio. For the first
time, leases are being sold on city lots.
   Even local government is getting into the game. Two weeks ago,
the Dilley City Council voted to take lease bids on the city park
and the city airport, following the example of the Dilley school
district.
   Crouse says this is only the beginning.
   ``Early estimates say that probably 200 wells will be drilled
horizontally for the year, but I think that is a low estimate,'' he
said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>