<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1107EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Soviet-Lithuania 2ndLd-Writethru a0518 12-26 0602</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Soviet-Lithuania, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0518,0615</SECOND>
<HEAD>Communists Urge Gorbachev To Go To Lithuania To Discuss Party Split</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 9 grafs to UPDATE with Gorbachev directed to visit
Lithuania to discuss party split; Picks up 6th graf, ``At Monday's ...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK J. PORUBCANSKY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Communist Party Central Committee today
directed Mikhail S. Gorbachev and other top party officials to
travel to Lithuania to try to heal the break with that
independent-minded Baltic republic's party.
   Gorbachev on Monday bitterly criticized Lithuanian Communists
for their declaration of an independent party _ the first crack in
the unity forged by Vladimir Lenin before the 1917 Bolshevik
revolution.
   But he also urged caution. Lithuanian Communist leader Algirdas
Brazauskas, who urged the republic's Dec. 20 break with Moscow, was
quoted as telling Lithuanian radio that such a visit by Kremlin
officials would be ``good and useful.''
   The two-day meeting of the policy-making party Central Committee
found it ``reasonable for Soviet Communist Party General Secretary
Mikhail S. Gorbachev to make a trip to Lithuania,'' said an
announcement by the Tass news agency.
   Gorbachev and other officials will meet with Lithuanian party
officials and members of the public to find out their opinions on
Lithuania's drive for independence.
   After a visit by Gorbachev and other officials, another Central
Committee meeting will be held to make a firm decision on the
dispute with Lithuania, Tass said. There was no indication when the
visits or the next Central Committee meeting would be.
   Tass said the Central Committee also approved Gorbachev's
opening statement to the meeting, in which he mixed tough criticism
of Brazauskas and other party officials with calls for restraint
and reason.
   Thousands of Lithuanians rallied today in Vilnius' Cathedral
Square in support of the split, said Eduardas Potasinskas, an
editor at Lithuanian television.
   Potasinkas also reported on Brazauskas' comments, saying the
Lithuanian leader praised the Central Committee decision in a radio
interview shortly after the meeting ended today.
   At Monday's meeting, Gorbachev said: ``No part of the Soviet
Communist Party has the right to decide the question about its
independent existence with its own program and rules, not taking
into account the position of the Soviet Communist Party as a whole.
   ``And this means that the Communist Party of Lithuania was and
remains a part of the united Soviet Communist Party,'' said
Gorbachev, who is party general secretary as well as the country's
president.
   Tass, in a report on the first day of the Central Committee
meeting, said Gorbachev accused the leaders of the Lithuanian party
as having ``gone over to playing up to nationalist, separatist
forces.''
   Gorbachev tried for several months to head off the split that
the Lithuanian party declared in Vilnius, and at the Congress of
People's Deputies meeting in Moscow on Saturday lashed out at
separatists.
   ``Today, to realize the right to self-determination through
secession means to blow up the union, set the people against each
other and sow conflict and blood and death,'' Gorbachev said at
that meeting. ``That's what separatists are pushing us toward.''
   He also told the Central Committee that the Soviet government
should consider the legal status of public movements that are
``carrying out separatist activities and whipping up nationalist
terror.''
   Gorbachev did not identify any such organizations, but in the
context of the debate he likely was referring to Lithuania's
Sajudis and other organizations pushing for broad sovereignty and
ultimately complete independence from the Soviet Union.
   Nevertheless, according to a text of his statement published by
the Communist Party daily Pravda today, he urged ``maximum
restraint'' to allow emotions to calm down.
</TEXT>

</DOC>