<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0224 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0313EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-ZubeTube Bjt   12-21 0496</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Zube Tube, Bjt,0514</SECOND>
<HEAD>Company Sees Success With `Zube Tube'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto DC1</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also on general news wires.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GREG SMITH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FAIRFIELD, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   There's not much to the Zube Tube, the
Ultimate Cosmic Sound Machine. But then, there wasn't much to the
Hula-Hoop, either.
   The 39-inch-long brightly colored cardboard tube can produce
sounds from ``Star Wars'' battles and MTV-style echoes to Gregorian
chants, whale songs and the ocean's roar.
   ``The number of noises you want to make are as infinite as your
imagination,'' said Judy A. Walls, senior vice president of Ritam
International, Ltd., a toy company in the southeastern Iowa town of
Fairfield.
   ``There's no batteries, no electricity,'' she said. ``I think
everybody is just `electroniced' out.''
   Inside the 2}-inch diameter tube is a spring that acts as an
acoustic coil. The spring is connected at each end by custom-made
plastic cups. A hole on the side of the tube allows a child's _ or
an adult's _ finger to reach in and pluck the spring, which
produces the myriad of sounds.
   A person can also speak into the hole, as well as either end of
the tube, to produce even more sounds.
   ``We feel it's going to be the next Hula-Hoop. In its first 18
months, they sold something like 100 million hula hoops,'' Mrs.
Walls said. ``We plan on doing the same thing. I think three years
is realistic.''
   Some 200,000 Zube Tubes have been sold since it was marketed in
mid-September, she said. The suggested retail price is $9.95.
   Toy and gift companies in Finland, Switzerland, Germany, France,
England and Canada have inquired about the tube.
   Sandy Watsey, Ritam executive vice president, said that while in
London, a group of company officials went to Harrod's to tape a
video using the department store's Zube Tube display. However, they
ended up filming an empty display because the store was sold out,
she said.
   ``They say over there that the Zube Tube is more popular than
Nintendo,'' Ms. Watsey said.
   The concept of the Zube Tube was developed by Bob Deissler, who
was studying physics at Case Western Reserve University in
Cleveland.
   ``I was playing with a slinky and it happened to touch a
Styrofoam cup,'' said Deissler, who was visiting the 10-year-old
toy company this week.
   Intrigued by the sound, Deissler experimented with a different
type of spring about a year later.
   ``It worked really great. That's when I really decided to pursue
it,'' he said.
   Deissler applied for and received a patent in 1980 and contacted
several large toy companies, but none were interested. Deissler
later moved to Fairfield.
   Ritam snapped up the product and developed the concept. The
company's other claims to toy fame are electronic games called
Monty Plays Scrabble and Master Monty, which sell about 10,000
units a year, Mrs. Walls said.
   Zube Tube beats them hands down. She said the company now is
turning out up to 5,000 Zube Tubes a day.
</TEXT>

</DOC>