<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1018EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RomanianSlaying     12-26 0348</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romanian Slaying,0359</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romanian Immigrant Reportedly Slain in Homeland</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FULLERTON, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Romanian immigrant living in
California was killed by security forces as he tried to deliver
relief supplies in his embattled homeland, family members said.
   Ionel ``John'' Antimie, Jr., 21, a four-year resident of
Fullerton, was gunned down by forces loyal to executed former
Romanian dictator Nicolae Ceausescu over the weekend, his father,
Ionel Antimie Sr. said through an interpreter.
   The State Department could not immediately confirm the report,
but planned an investigation, spokesman Philip Covington said
Monday.
   The family got the news Christmas morning from friends in
Portland, Ore., who were able to get a phone call through to the
East European nation and talked with the victim's brother,
Constantine, 32, Antimie said.
   The two brothers had been on a holiday driving tour through
Europe, their family said, and also had planned to visit Ionel
Antimie's girlfriend, Angelica Hij, 16, who lives in Cluj, Romania,
for the holidays.
   But when news of civil unrest in Romania broke, the brothers
delayed their journey in Germany and bought food, medicine and
other relief supplies worth ``thousands of dollars,'' Antimie said.
   The Oregon friend told Antimie that the brothers, traveling in a
rented car with their supplies, were stopped by uniformed security
officers who opened fire, killing Ionel Antimie but apparently
allowing his brother to flee.
   Constantine Antimie told the friend he had returned to the
shooting site and recovered his brother's body, his father said.
   Ionel Antimie Jr. helped run the family's contracting business.
He left Romania with his parents, four brothers and two sisters in
1985, according to a sister, Elena Furdui. Two brothers and one
sister stayed behind in Romania, she said.
   Tens of thousands of people have died in Romania in recent weeks
during the popular revolt. Ceausecu was executed by firing squad
Monday.
   The Antimie family notified the State Department Monday.
   Covington said the State Department will help if it can, but the
government does not usually track injuries or deaths of U.S.
residents who are not citizens.
</TEXT>

</DOC>