<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0141 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1427EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama Bjt 2Takes 12-20 0865</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama, Bjt, 2 Takes,0891</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT ^U.S. Troops Take Panama; Noriega Escapes</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos PAN1-3,NY21-22, LaserColor PAN5, NY20,24</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Panama time is same as EST.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. troops smashed the regime of
Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega on Wednesday and installed a new
government, but the military ruler who antagonized a superpower
fled into hiding and his loyalists seized some Americans.
   More than 20,000 troops backed by warplanes began their invasion
shortly after midnight Tuesday under a full moon, pounding
Panamanian military installations in and around the capital with
mortar, cannon and machine-gun fire.
   In the early afternoon, smoke rose from the shattered
headquarters of Noriega's Defense Forces and sporadic gunfire was
heard in the distance. Widespread looting broke out.
   In the San Miguelito neighborhood to the northeast, attack jets
bombed and helicopters strafed a Defense Forces barracks atop a
hill.
   More than 50 bodies were counted by one hospital early in the
fighting but more bodies flooded in after daybreak. Officials in
Washington said nine American servicemen were among the dead.
Hundreds of people were wounded.
   President Bush said he ordered the invasion after Noriega said
Panama was in a state of war with the United States and after the
shooting death last week of a U.S. Marine lieutenant.
   He said the attack was a mission to capture Noriega and bring
him trial in the United States for allegedly trafficking in
Colombian cocaine.
   ``Gen. Noriega's reckless threats and attacks upon Americans in
Panama created an imminent danger to the 35,000 American citizens
in Panama,'' Bush said in speech to the nation.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III said the action was
ordered after the administration received unconfirmed reports that
Noriega intended to attack a U.S. residential neighborhood in
Panama.
   Pamana's national radio reported about 40 Americans had been
``detained,'' while Cable News Network said at least 10 Americans
were held hostage. Troops loyal to Noriega were seen taking at
least two Americans away from Panama City's Marriott Hotel.
   Opposition leader Guillermo Endara, winner of the May 7
elections that were voided by the Noriega-controlled government,
was sworn in as president and given immediate U.S. backing.
   Bush later ordered that economic and political sanctions be
lifted and authorized federal drug agents to pursue arrests in
Panama.
   But provisional President Francisco Rodriguez and Foreign
Minsiter Leonardo Kam, both installed by Noriega, held a news
conference at the Foreign Ministry office in the capital and
declared they still governed.
   ``The government controls the situation in the country and its
institutions,'' Rodriguez said. ``We are prepared to resist.''
   It was clear, however, that U.S. troops controlled the capital.
   The huge assault by Marines, infantrymen, sailors, airmen and
paratroopers was the bloody pinnacle of Washington's long war with
Noriega, a bellicose career soldier who had a strong core of
support among working class people and who seemed to delight in
defying the mighty United States.
   Noriega survived two coup attempts from within the Panamanian
Defense Forces that he headed, including one October insurrection
in which he was briefly captured. He survived Washington's best
non-military efforts to oust him, including harsh economic
sanctions that severely depressed the economy.
   There was strong evidence in the two previous coup attempts of
dissatisfaction within the military with Noriega, and it was
unclear how much of his support was holding after the U.S. attack.
   In his address, Bush said he intends to turn over the Panama
Canal as required under existing treaties.
   Noriega has denied the drug charges and claims the United States
wanted him out so it could renege on 1977 treaties that cede
control of the Panama Canal by the year 2000.
   At the Fort Clayton U.S. base outside the capital, U.S. charge
d'affaires John Bushnell said Noriega ``may take to the hills and
be very hard to find ... but he wouldn't have a significant force
to actually do anything.''
   ``We will chase him, and we will find him,'' Gen. Colin Powell,
chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, said in Washington.
   Powell said that nine American servicemen were killed, 39 were
wounded and one was missing.
   Rodriguez said more than 60 Panamanians died in the fighting,
and several hundred were wounded, mostly civilians. He said U.S.
troops in the Chorillo area, where the fighting was heaviest, did
not allow the Red Cross to enter the area.
   A man indentified only as Major Caballero said on National Radio
that ``40 Americans have been detained,'' but that figure could not
be confirmed.
   Two paramilitary Panamanian troops arrived at the capital's
Marriott Hotel at about 9 a.m. and took away three Americans. The
soldiers then asked the front desk for a list of guests and where
they were staying. The desk said it did not give it to them.
   Pentagon spokesman Pete Williams said U.S. forces in Panama were
aware of hostages taken from the Marriott. ``We will make efforts
to take care of that,'' said Williams, declining to elaborate.
   Williams said he did not know how many Americans were being held.
   Earlier in the invasion, Panamanian troops held 12 foreigners at
the Marriott, including eight Americans, for about two hours.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>