<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1403EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CBSProducer     12-21 0404</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-CBS Producer,0416</SECOND>
<HEAD>CBS Asks U.S., Central American Officials to Help Find Missing Producer</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAY SHARBUTT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Television Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   CBS asked officials of the United States and
Central American countries for help in finding one of its news
producers seized by gunmen in Panama, the president of CBS News
said Thursday.
   CBS' efforts won't stop until the producer, Jon Meyersohn, is
returned safely, David Burke said in a memo to his staff.
   Panamanian gunmen abducted Meyersohn, 33, and ABC News producer
Robert Campos on Wednesday morning as they stood in the lobby of a
hotel in Panama City. Campos, 31, was freed unharmed that afternoon.
   The two were among hundreds of journalists in Panama covering
the U.S. military assault to topple Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega,
and were staying at the Marriott Hotel in Panama City.
   Dozens of guests trapped at the seaside hotel were rescued late
Wednesday when U.S. paratroopers shot their way past armed people,
some believed to be Noriega loyalists, to reach the building.
   Meyersohn is married to ABC News producer Julie Hartenstein and
based in New York. He was producing reports for the ``CBS Evening
News'' when abducted with Campos and the hotel's resident manager,
Daniel Sarria.
   Sarria also still is missing.
   Burke told CBS News employees that ``every effort is being made
to locate Jon and bring him to safety.''
   That effort includes requests to the White House, the State
Department and the Pentagon, he said, and ``we also have been
working nonstop with countless other governments and private
individuals both in the U.S. and Central America.''
   His memo did not specify which Central American governments or
individuals were asked for help. Burke was not available Thursday
to comment.
   Meyersohn, with CBS News for 10 years, earlier this month helped
cover anti-government demonstrations in Czechoslovakia.
   He later produced reports on Soviet President Mikhail S.
Gorbachev's meeting with Pope John Paul II in Rome, and the Malta
summit conference of Gorbachev and President Bush.
   Born in Illinois, raised in New York City and educated at the
University of Chicago, Meyersohn joined CBS News in 1978 as desk
assistant in its radio division. He later became an associate
producer for the ``CBS Morning News.''
   He took a year's leave to study as Benton Fellow at the
University of Chicago, then returned to CBS News in 1984 as a
producer in its Chicago bureau.
</TEXT>

</DOC>