<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0169 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 2034EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WKD--SantaFeArt Adv05-07   12-26 0951</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--Santa Fe Art, Adv 05-07,0973</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv05-07</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Weekend Editions, Jan. 5-7, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WEEKEND ENTERTAINMENT AND ARTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>The Artists: Santa Fe Folk Art Will Become Enduring Classic</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ED MORENO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SANTA FE, N.M. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Real adobe bricks and mud are rarely used
these days to build houses, and even the supply of real cornhusks
to wrap homemade tamales is drying up.
   Nowadays, plaster stucco gives that adobe look and restaurants
wrap tamales in paper. Even popular forms of folk art, such as the
ubiquitous howling coyote, are mass-produced in China.
   It has become increasingly difficult to distinguish authentic
Santa Fe art from imitation. But rather than diluting the genre,
those who help define Santa Fe style believe New Mexico's unique
amalgamation of Indian, Hispanic and Anglo-European cultures will
sustain its popularity long after the fad has faded.
   ``People talk about the fad aspect, but the fact remains that
Santa Fe style is rooted in centuries of human history,'' says
Christine Mather, co-author of the book, ``Santa Fe Style.''
   That's good news for the thousands who came this Christmas
season in search of a wreath of red chili peppers, a classy poster
from a famous Southwestern or Indian artist or simply to experience
Christmas Eve singing Christmas carols around a pinon bonfire on
Delgado Street.
   It means that Santa Fe style, its architecture, simplicity and
warmth, will never go completely out of style.
   ``I don't think it will ever die,'' says Joan Cawley, an art
wholesaler with a gallery on fashionable San Francisco Street.
   If anything, its popularity is expanding. With sales of more
than 100,000 copies, Mather's book has helped put Santa Fe style
into the American vernacular. Ellen Bradbury, who operates a Santa
Fe tour service, says this Christmas season seems busier than ever.
Cawley's art business is growing on every continent.
   The style emerged from the traditions, practices and
architecture of the Pueblo Indians, with their heavy, asymmetrical,
multi-story homes, and the Spanish, who brought European religious
traditions to New Mexico in the 1500s.
   Popularized by a colony of artists in the 1920s and '30s, Santa
Fe culture is reflected in simple, comfortable clothing, turquoise
and silver jewelry and honest, spicy cuisine, along with an
affinity for dirt streets, tolerance of the eccentric, appreciation
of a stunning blue sky and, in some quarters, almost paranoid
defense of the fine and folk arts.
   The most enduring features of the Santa Fe look will be its
building styles, which some experts believe will join the gallery
of classic historic and architectural styles such as colonial
American, Victorian and Old South.
   The decision to copy California mission style and establish and
foster a Santa Fe architectural movement was made early in the
1900s when it became apparent that the city, relegated to the end
of a spur off the Santa Fe Railroad main line, would never again be
a major trading center.
   Community leaders adopted what architectural historian Boyd
Pratt calls Spanish pueblo revival style, and passed the city's
first historic styles ordinance, which has remained relatively
intact.
   Its characteristics are typified by the heavy, low-profile
Palace of the Governors and the state Museum of Fine Arts facing
the central plaza, renovated soon after statehood in 1912.
   The latest wave of Santa Fe popularity began more than a decade
ago, at about the same time northern New Mexico artisans began
producing small, carved animal figures, including howling coyotes.
   The coyote has mythical meaning to many Indian tribes, sometimes
creator and benefactor, often mischief-maker and destroyer. More
than that, it has a distinctive image that is simple, decorative
and affordable, says gallery owner Davis Mather.
   Mather, husband of the author, began featuring the carvings of
several local artisans in 1978. Now the work of Felipe Archuleta
and a half-dozen others resides in museum collections. On display
at Mather's gallery is the next fad: carved, wooden, painted,
wall-hanging snakes.
   The carved coyotes, snakes and their knock-offs and
reproductions on T-shirts, pottery and canvas are not universally
popular among some Santa Fe residents who say they trivialize the
value of their town.
   ``It's stupid. There are coyotes everywhere,'' says artist Corri
Merritt. ``Somebody said it would peak next month, but I doubt it.''
   Cartoonist Jerry Milord has lampooned the excesses and
capitalized on the local pique with a colorful hit poster entitled
``Another Victim of Santa Fe Style.''
   The poster is set in a classic, Santa Fe-style room, with beamed
ceilings, a kiva or beehive fireplace with stucco benches and a
niche with a small santo (wooden figure representing a saint)
inside. Against the walls are a carved wooden trastero (hutch), a
chili ristra, a buffalo skull and carved, painted snakes against
the walls. A howling coyote and leather drum rest on the Mexican
tile floor.
   A woman, lying supine on a woven Navajo rug, is decked out in
turquoise squash blossom necklaces and silver concha belts, wearing
a velvet shirt and pleated skirt and cowboy boots. A painted snake,
which appears to have wriggled off the wall and bitten its owner,
slithers out the door.
   ``The people who buy them are, like, laughing at themselves,''
says Milord. ``It's not a mean thing.''
   An old, classy town such as Santa Fe, which has withstood
conquests, revolts, reconquests and immigration of all varieties,
may see the coyote fade from popularity, knowing it will likely
return.
   Twenty to 30 years from now, Mather predicts, a clever Santa
Fean will dig into his trunk and emerge with paper napkins
emblazoned with a bandana-scarfed coyote, its mouth pointed upward
howling at the moon.
   It will begin yet another revival _ of Santa Fe kitsch.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Weekend Editions, Jan. 5-7</NOTE>

</DOC>