<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0207 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1724EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Dollar-Gold     12-28 0489</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dollar-Gold,0504</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar Ends Higher In U.S. Dealings</HEAD>
<HEAD>Precede LONDON BC</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dollar finished sharply higher in domestic
trading Thursday after putting in a mixed performance overseas.
   Gold prices fell. On the Commodity Exchange in New York, gold
bullion for current delivery settled at $398.60 a troy ounce, down
$2.20 from Wednesday. Republic National Bank in New York quoted a
late bid for gold at $399.50 an ounce, off $1.50.
   Trading was thin in Europe, where the dollar was buffeted by
trading in other currencies. Dealers in Frankfurt said the Bank of
England and the central bank of the Netherlands intervened to curb
the strength of the West German mark against their currencies.
   But when dealings shifted to the United States, the dollar moved
sharply higher on technical factors, traders said. The dollar's
biggest move came against the Japanese yen, which was adversely
affected by reports of political uncertainty in the face of coming
elections.
   The dollar traded in seesaw fashion throughout the session. Its
moves were ``accentuated by the thin market,'' said Michael
McDonald, a trader at Harris Trust and Savings Bank in Chicago.
   ``The (West German) mark remained the strongest currency in the
world,'' he said, noting that interest-rate differentials are
tipping in favor of West Germany over the United States. Further
bolstering the mark is the assumption that the opening of East
Germany will spur a demand for West German products.
   In Tokyo, the dollar rose to a closing 142.15 Japanese yen from
142.10 yen on Wednesday. Later in London, it rose to 143.15 yen. In
New York the dollar closed at 143.55 yen, up from 142.00 yen on
Wednesday.
   In London, the British pound fell to $1.6137 from $1.6255 late
Wednesday. In New York it cost $1.6045 to buy one pound, cheaper
than Wednesday's $1.6275.
   Other late dollar rates in New York, compared with late
Wednesday included: 1.6875 West German marks, up from 1.6855;
1.5390 Swiss francs, up from 1.5295; 5.7675 French francs, up from
5.7600; 1,264.15 Italian lire, up from 1,263.75, and 1.1568
Canadian dollars, down from 1.1574.
   Other late dollar rates in Europe, compared with late Wednesday
included: 1.6905 West German marks, up from 1.6895; 1.5385 Swiss
francs, up from 1.5355; 5.7665 French francs, down from 5.7760;
1.9000 Dutch guilders, down from 1.9080; 1,264.50 Italian lire,
down from 1,266.00, and 1.1563 Canadian dollars, down from 1.1587.
   Gold fell in London to a late bid price of $399.50 a troy ounce,
from $406.25 bid late Wednesday. In Zurich, the metal fell to a
closing bid of $400.00, from $406.00 bid late Wednesday. Earlier in
Hong Kong, gold fell $6.88 to close at a bid $401.61.
   Silver prices also declined. On New York's Comex, silver bullion
for current delivery settled at $5.150 a troy ounce, down from
$5.240 on Wednesday. Silver bullion fell in London to a late bid
price of $5.15 a troy ounce, from $5.41 bid late Wednesday.
</TEXT>

</DOC>