<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0202 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0814EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv25   12-18 0474</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv25,0494</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv25</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Monday, Dec. 25</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is Monday, Dec. 25, the 359th day of 1989. There are six
days left in the year. This is Christmas Day.
   Today's Highlight in History:
   On Dec. 25, 1818, the Christmas carol ``Silent Night,'' by Franz
Joseph Gruber and Joseph Mohr, was sung for the first time, at the
Church of St. Nikolaus in Oberndorff, Austria.
   On this date:
   In A.D. 336, the first recorded celebration of Christmas on Dec.
25 took place in Rome.
   In 1066, William the Conqueror was crowned king of England.
   In 1223, St. Francis of Assisi assembled one of the first
Nativity scenes, in Greccio, Italy.
   In 1776, Gen. George Washington and his troops crossed the
Delaware River for a surprise attack on Hessian forces camped at
Trenton, N.J. The crossing is depicted in the famous painting by
Emanuel Leutze.
   In 1821, the founder of the American Red Cross, Clara Barton,
was born in Oxford, Mass.
   In 1868, despite bitter opposition, President Andrew Johnson
granted an unconditional pardon to all persons involved in the
Southern rebellion that resulted in the Civil War.
   In 1889, Lila Bell Acheson Wallace, who co-founded Reader's
Digest with her husband, De Witt Wallace, was born in Virden,
Manitoba.
   In 1926, Hirohito became emperor of Japan.
   In 1931, the Metropolitan Opera House in New York broadcast an
entire opera over radio for the first time. Listeners throughout
the United States and overseas heard ``Hansel and Gretel.''
   In 1941, during World War II, Japan announced the surrender of
the British-Canadian garrison at Hong Kong.
   In 1977, Charlie Chaplin, known to millions of fans around the
world as the ``little tramp,'' died in Switzerland at age 88.
   Ten years ago: Four clergymen from the United States were
allowed to meet with groups of American hostages in Iran for a
second day in order to hold Christmas services.
   Five years ago: Vietnamese troops launched an offensive against
rebel camps in Cambodia, seizing the largest camp the following day.
   One year ago: Christmas services were held in Lockerbie,
Scotland, where residents mourned the loss of 270 lives in the
bombing of Pan Am Flight 103 along with relatives of the victims.
   Today's Birthdays: Entertainment entrepreneur Lord Grade is 83.
Bandleader Cab Calloway is 82. Actor Mike Mazurki is 80. Singer
Tony Martin is 76. Actor Gary Sandy is 44. Former football player
Larry Csonka is 43. Singer Barbara Mandrell is 41. Actress Sissy
Spacek is 40. Singer Annie Lennox is 35.
   Thought for Today: ``Christmas waves a magic wand over this
world, and behold, everything is softer and more beautiful. If only
for one short day, ill will is set aside, and the effect upon our
lives is miraculous.'' _ Norman Vincent Peale, American clergyman.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Advance for Monday, Dec. 25</NOTE>

</DOC>