<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0094 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1455EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Lebanon     12-28 0425</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon,0439</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cease-Fire Between Rival Shiite Moslem Forces Collapses</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By AHMED MANTASH</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KFAR MELKI, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rival Shiite Moslem militiamen traded
grenade-throwing assaults behind artillery and tank cannon barrages
in south Lebanon Thursday, hours after agreeing to a cease-fire
organized by Iran.
   The upsurge of hostilities at midday around this hamlet came on
the sixth day of heavy fighting that has left 46 people killed and
187 wounded.
   Police said no new casualties were reported from the fighting
between the Iranian-backed Hezbollah, or Party of God, and the
pro-Syrian Amal militia.
   The two factions have been vying for more than two years for
control of the 1.2 million Shiites who make up the largest sect
among Lebanon's four million population.
   Amal leader Nabih Berri visited the frontline at Kfar Meshki and
said his militia was determined to evict Hezbollah from two
villages captured when the fighting erupted Saturday.
   ``The fate of south Lebanon is being decided at this region,''
Berri told reporters as he climbed out of his bulletproof
limousine, toting an AK-47 assault rifle.
   ``We will stop shooting only when they (Hezbollah) return to
their original lines,'' said Berri, who doubles as minister of
water and hydraulic resources in the Lebanese government.
   His fighters unleashed thunderous rocket barrages from
multibarreled launchers at Hezbollah positions on the eastern
flanks of Kfar Melki as he spoke. Palls of black smoke billowed
from the targets.
   Iran's first deputy foreign minister, Mohammed Ali Besharati,
negotiated the truce, which began Wednesday night. The fighting
resumed 12 hours later.
   Besharati held a new round of talks with Hezbollah and Amal
leaders Thursday to try to shore up the cease-fire.
   In another development, Beirut's Moslem sector observed a
two-hour strike as the Lebanese Communist Party buried members
killed in Israel's ground and air attacks two days ago.
   Schools, shops, cafes, restaurants and other businesses were
closed throughout west Beirut as party members carried the coffins
of seven slain colleagues through the streets to a mosque before
burial.
   ``Your blood will be avenged!'' and ``The enemy will pay
heavily!'' shouted thousands of mourners as the procession,
escorted by long lines of armed militiamen, reached the mosque.
   The seven were among 12 people killed in separate ground and air
attacks against the Communist guerrilla base in southeast Lebanon
and a party command post in the coastal town of Rmeile south of
Beirut.
   Two other victims were buried at their south Lebanon hometown of
Kfar Meshki on Thursday shortly before the upsurge of
Amal-Hezbollah fighting nearby. The three remaining fatalities were
civilians.
</TEXT>

</DOC>