<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0156 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 2019EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Harari     12-29 0567</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Harari,0583</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israeli Aide to Noriega Led Bungled Spy Mission</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LOUIS MEIXLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The former Israeli spy who was arrested in
Panama as a top aide to Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega headed one of
the most bungled operations in the history of Israel's Mossad
intelligence agency.
   Michael Harari, whose arrest by U.S. troops was announced
Thursday, was described by an American diplomat in Panama as a
security adviser to Noriega and an instructor to the Panamanian
Defense Forces.
   Israeli newspapers reported that Harari had considerable
influence in Panamanian politics. He was once appointed by Noriega
as Panama's honorary consul general in Israel.
   But he is best known, according to the daily Yediot Ahronot, as
the head of a team of 15 Mossad agents who set out to kill a
leading Palestinian terrorist but instead murdered a hapless
Moroccan-born waiter in a Norwegian resort.
   Spokesmen for the Israeli Foreign and Defense ministries refused
comment Friday on Harari's arrest in Panama, saying he was a
private citizen. But his exploits have been described extensively
in newspapers and books.
   Yediot said Harari helped Noriega recruit Israeli mercenaries
for his personal bodyguard over the last year and noted that a
second Israeli, Eliezer Ben Giton, surrendered to U.S. troops
outside the Vatican mission in Panama, saying he was ``responsible
for the personal security of General Manuel Noriega.''
   The Haaretz daily said Harari was convinced to leave Panama last
year by Israel officials, who were under strong U.S. pressure to
cut contacts with Noriega. But the former Mossad agent later
returned.
   Israel's ambassador to Panama, Reuven Ben-Eliezer, told Israel
army radio he did not know Harari.
   ``I don't know who Harari is, I didn't see him, I didn't meet
him, I didn't get orders from him, and he also didn't receive''
orders from Israel's embassy in Panama, Ben-Eliezer said in the
interview broadcast Friday.
   ``He is a private Israeli. I don't know what he did there. He
did business and he was appointed by Noriega as honorary general
consul for Panama in Israel,'' Ben-Eliezer said.
   Harari, 62, was born in Tel Aviv in a religious family that
objected to his joining the Israeli army. He eventually became a
colonel.
   Yediot said Harari was chief of Mossad's special operations when
he headed the unit trying to kill the leader of the Palestinian
Black September group, which massacred 11 Israeli athletes at the
1972 Munich Olympics.
   The case is described in the book ``The Quest for the Red
Prince'' by Israeli authors Michael Bar-Zohar and Eitan Haber.
Haber, now the spokesman for Defense Minister Yitzhak Rabin,
refused to comment on the case.
   In the book, the team leader is referred to only as ``Mike,''
but sources familiar with the case say it was Harari.
   According to the accounts, Harari's squad traced the man they
believed to be Ali Hassan Salameh, known as the Red Prince, to the
resort of Lillehammer, Norway.
   Two agents killed the man on May 23, 1973, but the victim turned
out to be Ahmed Boushiki, a Moroccan-born waiter living in
Lillehammer with his Norwegian wife.
   The embarrassment was heightened when six of the Israeli agents
involved in the mission were arrested by Norwegian police.
   The real Salameh was eventually killed when a bomb planted by
Israeli agents engulfed his car in flames on a Beirut street on
Jan. 22, 1979.
</TEXT>

</DOC>