<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0900EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-WorldChristmas 2ndLd-Writethru   12-25 0835</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-World Christmas, 2nd Ld-Writethru,a0476,0860</SECOND>
<HEAD>Celebration Amid Violence And Hope</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 20 grafs to UPDATE with Christmas messages from pope
and Queen Elizabeth; picks up 19th pvs, `Lebanese celebrated...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY17,18</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Pope John Paul II today prayed for Romanians ``celebrating this
Christmas in fear and trembling,'' mourned the thousands killed in
the overthrow of the Communist dictator and praised the wave of
democracy sweeping his native Eastern Europe.
   Romanians lit candles for peace, Panamanians braved gunfire to
celebrate the holiday and Lebanese shopped in sandbagged stores.
   Millions throughout the formerly orthodox Communist states of
Eastern Europe enjoyed their first Christmas in four decades with
the promise of freedom.
   Thousands of joyous West Germans took their first stroll on the
other side of the Berlin Wall on Sunday after East Germany lifted
visa and currency requirements in time for the holidays.
   In the pope's traditional Christmas message, John Paul prayed
for peace worldwide and said Merry Christmas in 53 languages as
tens of thousands of faithful and tourists stood in the sun-dappled
St. Peter's Square.
   ``In particular, bless at this hour, O Lord, the noble land of
Romania, which is celebrating this Christmas in fear and trembling,
with sorrow for the many human lives tragically lost and in the joy
of having taken once more the path of freedom,'' the pope said, his
head bowed in prayer.
   After his words about Romania, in which thousands of people have
been killed in the popular revolution that overthrew Communist
dictator Nicolae Ceausescu, the pope paused for a few seconds and
lifted his head.
   He praised the peaceful changes sweeping other Eastern European
countries and asked Europeans to ``open her doors and her heart to
understand and receive the anxieties, the fears and the problems of
the nations which seek her help,'' the pope prayed.
   ``May she respond with the strength and the generosity of her
Christian roots to this very special moment of history... which the
world is now experiencing as if awakened from a nightmare and
opened up to a better hope.''
   In Bucharest, Romania, people lit candles in Romana Square today
for those who died in the struggle to overthrow Ceausescu's rule.
   On Sunday, some families carried freshly cut Christmas trees
during a lull in fighting between a revolutionary government and
forces loyal to Ceausescu, who was ousted Friday. Sniper fire later
cleared the streets.
   Snipers also made streets in Panama City dangerous, and many
families in the city of 1 million had nothing to give their
children.
   ``What am I going to tell my 6-year-old daughter? I cannot tell
her Santa Claus was killed by a bomb,'' one woman in a middle-class
neighborhood said.
   Some resorted to looting. Looters packed boxes and bags from
debris-strewn shops. At one supermarket a man said he arrived too
late for food, but had clothes for his children.
   ``This is their Christmas,'' he said.
   Another toted a case of champagne. ``This is mine,'' he said
grinning.
   Still, Christmas lights twinkled in some homes not wrecked by
shelling and fighting.
   Thousands of U.S. troops who invaded Panama on Wednesday to
drive from power the country's strongman, Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noriega, spent the holidays without Christmas trees or loved ones.
   But 21-year-old Sgt. Ernie Nieto said he was ``just glad to see
Christmas. The other night (in combat) I just wanted to see sunup.''
   In London, Queen Elizabeth II said ``it would be splendid'' if
all nations united to stop further environmental damage. The
queen's traditional Christmas message urged ``a particular
tenderness towards this earth, which we share as human beings.''
   Lebanese celebrated Christmas with a desperate intensity. Many
tried to blot out the horrors and the hardships brought by 14 years
of civil war.
   ``I want to spend the coming week drinking, dancing and just
living. Who knows if we'll be alive tomorrow?'' said Khalil Accad,
a Christian in east Beirut.
   Streets were choked with traffic as shoppers jammed stores, many
of which had sandbags outside to protect against gun shells.
   Eighteen Western hostages spent another Christmas in captivity
in Lebanon. For American Terry Anderson, chief Middle East
correspondent for The Associated Press, it was his fifth Christmas
as a hostage.
   In Bethlehem on the Israeli-occupied West Bank, soldiers with
rifles stood watch atop the building where the Bible says Jesus was
born, but few tourists gathered for the traditional Christmas Eve
celebrations.
   ``It doesn't feel like Christmas at all,'' complained tourist
Eijah Kivi of Turku, Finland, surveying the sparse gatherings and
the stores closed by Palestinians protesting the Israeli occupation.
   South African Archbishop Desmond Tutu delivered a sermon at the
biblical Shepherds' Field on the West Bank. He prayed that Arabs
and Jews will find peace and endorsed the Palestinian call for an
independent state.
   Thousands of Filipinos lit candles in front of homes, businesses
and military camps in an appeal for peace in their troubled land,
where at least 113 were killed during a coup attempt earlier this
month.
</TEXT>

</DOC>