<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0108EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-LatamReax     12-23 0806</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Latam Reax,0828</SECOND>
<HEAD>For Latins, Panama Action Revives Images of Old Uncle Sam</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KEVIN NOBLET</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SANTIAGO, Chile (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.S. invasion of Panama has inflamed
Latin American sensitivity about national self-determination and
revived the old image of a militaristic, meddling Uncle Sam.
   From the Rio Grande to Cape Horn, and including the Caribbean,
government officials, newspapers and other opinion-makers have
roundly condemned the military action as improper and immoral.
   The force and unanimity of the reaction reflects just how
passionately Latin Americans embrace the principle of
non-intervention, coupled with a persistent sense of vulnerability
toward the superpower to the north. It overshadows universal
revulsion toward Noriega, who was seen as a throwback to the
thuggish dictators of the 1950s.
   ``Given the simplistic and emotional way the United States is
used to dealing with sensitive issues _ that of drug trafficking,
for instance _ what is there to guarantee that in the future the
U.S. won't decide that this problem has become unmanageable in
Colombia?'' asked respected columnist Enrique Santos in the
independent Bogota daily El Tiempo.
   ``One excess could lead to another,'' he warned.
   El Tiempo said in an editorial that the U.S. action in Panama
``wounds the sensibility of a continent with a collective memory of
other interventions.''
   On a half-dozen occasions during the 1900s, the United States
has dispatched troops to Latin American or Caribbean nations to
effect and enforce political change. The most recent cases were
Grenada in 1983 and the Dominican Republic in 1967.
   Joaquin Balaguer, the Dominican Republic's president, said the
new U.S. action, ``in spite of the expressed motives which deserve
all our respect and sympathy, is condemned by the Dominician
government and people.''
   The government of Barbados, which backed the invasion of
Grenada, criticized the new action as did the Barbados-based daily
The Nation, one of the Caribbean's largest newspapers.
   ``No excuse this time, Mr. Bush,'' The Nation said in an
editorial headline. It said it supported the Grenada investion
because it was carried out with regional support. ``We did not see
the Americans then in the role of an aggressive superpower,
trampling on weak opponents and acting on its own. We do in this
case.''
   Across the region news of the fighting in Panama has dominated
front pages and television broadcasts. Some of the coverage has
been laced by stinging editorial comment.
   In Rio de Janeiro, the independent daily Jornal do Brasil ran an
editorial cartoon depicting President Bush as a caveman with a bone
in his hair, a club and a U.S. flag worn bearskin-style. In a
front-page analysis the newspaper said: ``The big stick to which
President George Bush resorted in imposing his order on Panama
could reveal its most twisted effect: the boomerang.''
   On the other hand, not a single Latin American leader defended
Noriega's harsh reign.
   Mario Vargas Llosa, a novelist and conservative presidential
candidate widely expected to win election in Peru, described
Noriega as ``a disgrace and embarrassment to all the people of
Latin America.'' He said the principle of non-intervention could
not be invoked to justify Noriega's dictatorship, but nonetheless
expressed regret over the invasion and called for the withdrawal of
U.S. troops.
   The conservative Bogota daily El Siglo said the U.S. invasion
had transformed Noriega ``from a victimizer into a victim.''
   In the most forceful response of a Latin American leader, Peru's
leftist president, Alan Garcia, recalled his country's ambassador
to the United States and proposed postponing a Feb. 15 drug summit
in Cartagena, Colombia, with Bush, Garcia, President Virgilio Barco
of Colombia and President Jaime Paz Zamora of Bolivia.
   ``I cannot meet with the leader of an invading nation,'' Garcia
said. ``Holding a dialogue with a pistol on the table cannot be
permitted.''
   Peru's government also suspended joint operations with U.S. drug
agents in the country's coca-growing Huallaga Valley.
   The Barco government in Colombia said it would not hurry to
recognize the new Panamanian presidency of Guillermo Endara, whose
swearing-in at a U.S. military base as the invasion got under way
was seen by many Latin Americans as embarassingly staged.
   Fernando Color de Mello, the president-elect of Brazil, Latin
America's largest country, called the invasion ``a regrettable
episode'' that runs contrary to global currents in favor of
self-determination and political liberalization, ``especially in
Eastern Europe.''
   The seven leading Latin American democracies of Peru, Brazil,
Mexico, Colombia, Venezuela, Uruguay and Argentina have been
adamant in pressing the principle of non-intervention as a solution
to Central America's political conflicts. In response to the U.S.
invasion, the countries pushed a resolution in the Organization of
American States strongly condemning it.
   President Carlos Salinas de Gortari of Mexico said the invasion
``is contrary to the principles that regulate international
relations.''
   Mexico's political parties, in their first unanimous action in
many years, also blasted the invasion.
</TEXT>

</DOC>