<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0105 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1920EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Brazil     12-19 0637</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil,0661</SECOND>
<HEAD>Socialist Bitterly Admits Defeat in Presidential Election</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TODD LEWAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRASILIA, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The socialist candidate for president
bitterly conceded defeat Tuesday after official election returns
showed his conservative rival, Fernando Collor de Mello, was the
clear winner in the weekend vote.
   ``Collor de Mello won the election, but he won't do anything he
promised during the campaign,'' said Luis Inacio Lula da Silva.
``He will govern in favor of big business, the armed forces and the
International Monetary Fund.'' Da Silva said his Workers Party and
other left-wing parties that backed him will form a ``shadow
government to prevent Collor de Mello from commiting abuses.''
   Collor de Mello has refused to make a victory speech until the
winner is officially announced by the Superior Electoral Court.
That is expected Wednesday.
   With 93.9 percent of the vote counted, official returns showed
Collor de Mello with 32,884,545 votes, or 43.7 percent, and da
Silva with 29,975,927 votes, or 38.9 percent.
   Officials said the remaining ballots were blank or improperly
filled out and considered null.
   ``The president-elect is anxious to speak to the nation, but he
will only do so when the (Elecotral) Court confirms his victory,''
said Claudio Humberto Rosa e Silva, Collor de Mello's press
spokesman.
   Leaders of Collor de Mello's 10-month-old National
Reconstruction Party met with outgoing President Jose Sarney's
economic ministers and began negotiating alliances with political
leaders.
   The rightist party, with less than 3 percent of seats in
Congress, lacks legislative weight needed to take emergency
measures to revive the economy. Brazil's annual inflation rate is
1,500 percent, and it's $110 billion foreign debt is the biggest in
the Third World.
   ``We are going to form a government of national unity, excluding
no one,'' said Renan Calheiros, Collor de Mello's chief adviser.
   Collor de Mello was also trying to open channels of
communication with the liberal wing of the Roman Catholic Church,
unions and leftist parties that backed da Silva.
   Workers Party officials appeared to reject any offer of
conciliation.
   ``Mr. Collor de Mello has a program and suporters that conflict
with our program and with the way of handling politics in Brazil,''
said party president Luiz Gushiken. ``There's no sense in us
joining a Collor government.''
   Meanwhile, Sarney said he would step down from office early if
Congress votes to shorten his five-year mandate.
   ``If the Congress wishes, I won't be an obstacle,'' said Sarney,
a civilian who took office in 1985 in an Electoral College vote
coordinated by the country's top generals.
   The president-elect is scheduled to succeed Sarney for a
five-year term March 15, 1990, but pressure is mounting for Sarney
to resign early. On Sunday, two Cabinet ministers said the new
president should take office soon to adopt economic measures.
   The election Sunday marked the return of democratic rights after
a right-wing miltiary regime ruled from 1964 to 1985.
   The 82 million-member electorate also passed judgment on two
decades of rapid but unequal growth, which led to the economic
problems.
   Collor de Mello and da Silva were the top vote-getters in a
field of 21 candidates in first-round balloting Nov. 15. Neither
obtained a majority needed to win, and the two went to a runoff
election.
   Da Silva called for immediate suspension of payments on the
foreign debt, land and urban reforms and redistribution of wealth.
   The Workers Party candidate won in most major cities.
   Collor de Mello, 40, a free market advocate who pledged a
crackdown on corruption in government, won a huge majority among
uneducated rural voters in the impoverished north and northeast.
   The last popularly elected president of Brazil was Janio
Quadros. He abruptly resigned in 1961 after seven months in office,
citing ``occult forces.''
   In 1964 the military overthrew Quadros' successor, liberal
vice-president Joao Goulart, and ruled until 1985.
</TEXT>

</DOC>