<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0225 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2052EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Panama-SecretDecision 1stLd-Writethru   12-20 0838</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Secret Decision, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0726,840</SECOND>
<HEAD>EDS: SUBS for pvs grafs 14-15 five new grafs, bgng Fitzwater on Wednesday,
to update with new remarks by Fitzwater that include additional details
and color; picks up pvs 16th graf, At the Pentagon...</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM RAUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For two days, President Bush masked his plan
to oust Panama's Manuel Antonio Noriega with a studied show of
business-as-usual.
   He gaily greeted guests at a White House Christmas party just
hours before the full scale military operation began.
   Outraged at the slaying of an American Marine and concerned
about quickly deteriorating conditions in Panama City, Bush decided
on Sunday to mount the assault to topple Noriega's regime,
administration officials said.
   Bush had been seriously mulling such a strike since the abortive
Oct. 3 coup attempt against Noriega, officials said. In fact, the
plan for a preemptive U.S. move against Noriega actually had been
developed months earlier.
   Sources said one of the first to learn of the go-ahead was Vice
President Dan Quayle, whom Bush briefed at a brunch on Sunday.
   The president went over final plans for the assault at a Tuesday
afternoon session with Quayle, Secretary of States James A. Baker
III, Defense Secretary Richard B. Cheney, national security adviser
Brent Scowcroft and Colin L. Powell, chairman of the Joint Chiefs
of Staff, said officials who spoke on the condition of anonymity.
   The Oval Office meeting, in keeping with the secrecy shrouding
the decision, was billed by White House officials as a sssion
between Bush, Cheney and Thornburgh on ``the role of the military
in the war on drugs.''
   In keeping the decision so closely under wraps, the onetime CIA
chief was following a familiar pattern of secrecy _ one also
reflected in his sending clandestine high-level missions to Beijing
and in keeping private for four months his plan for a Mediterranean
superpower summit.
   Bush attended White House Christmas parties both Monday and
Tuesday evenings, buoyantly greeting guests and posing for
photographs.
   At Tuesday's party, Scowcroft, his deputy Robert Gates and White
House Chief of Staff John Sununu all put in brief appearances
before returning to their offices to wait for the U.S. military
strike.
   A day after he made the decision to use force in an attempt to
topple Noriega, Bush refused to rule out a military response in a
Monday interview with The Associated Press and other news agencies.
He expressed ``enormous frustration'' with Noriega's continued
strong-arm tactics. But otherwise he gave no hint at what was to
come.
   The business-as-usual theme extended to other administration
officials as well on Tuesday. Public information officers at the
Pentagon went home at their regular quitting time.
   And, in the White House, presidential press secretary Marlin
Fitzwater was joined by a small group of reporters in his office to
watch evening network news accounts of unannounced U.S. troop
movements to Panama. Fitzwater said he knew nothing about the
reports.
   Fitzwater on Wednesday said the harrassment of Americans in
Panama is what finally persuaded the president to use force.
   ``The president was somber through the night (Tuesday night),
worried about the possiblity of casualties, and anxious for any
word of specific military progress.''
   Bush watched Fitzwater's announcement of the action on the
television in his study near the Oval Office, then made notes on a
5-inch by 7-inch blue notepad as he talked to various world leaders
by phone, the spokesman said.
   Bush cancelled virtually all of his scheduled events and
meetings on Wednesday so he could concentrate on the action in
Panama, receiving frequent military updates through the day and
evening.
   One event he did not cancel, Fitzwater said, was yet another
Christmas party scheduled for Wednesday evening.
   At the Pentagon, Secretary of Defense Cheney told reporters that
the order ``went out late on Sunday to implement a plan that had
been in existence for some time. It was one of the first items I
was briefed on when I became Secretary of Defense last spring.''
   Powell, the chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, suggested a
concern that Noriega might do something to jeopardize the Panama
Canal in the absence of a U.S. strike. And a congressional
intelligence source cited reports in recent months of a
deterioration in Noriega's mental health and heavy drinking.
   In any event, Bush, criticized in some quarters for being
indecisive and timid in failing to capitalize on last October's
coup attempt, apparently was determined not to let another
opportunity pass.
   Bush informed congressional leaders by phone of his plan about
an hour before the first shots were fired. Senate Republican Leader
Bob Dole of Kansas said Bush phoned him at 11:15 p.m. ``He said
he'd appreciate my support.'' Dole said he gave it to him.
   Bush stayed in the Oval Office until 4:05 a.m. EST, spending
much of the time phoning allied and Central American leaders to let
them know what he was doing, before heading to his personal
residence for a brief sleep before his 7 a.m. address to the nation.
</TEXT>

</DOC>