<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0215 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1940EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-MailBombs-Jacksonville 1stLd-Writethru a0810 12-20 0726</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mail Bombs-Jacksonville, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0810,0742</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jacksonville NAACP Says Work Will Continue Despite Bomb Scare</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Inserts 1 graf after 11th, ``We've come ..., to UPDATE with
comment from white Council member. Willye in 9th graf is correct</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto JV1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RON WORD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JACKSONVILLE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Civil rights leaders said Wednesday
they've made progress in this northeast Florida city, but the
mailing of a bomb to NAACP headquarters recalls recent racial
tensions that had begun to fade.
   The bomb disarmed here Tuesday was similar to devices which
killed a federal appeals court judge and a Savannah, Ga., civil
rights leader.
   Bombs mailed to the 11th Circuit Court of Appeals in Atlanta and
to the Jacksonville office of the National Association for the
Advancement of Colored People were disarmed without causing any
damage or injuries.
   Possible links to NAACP school desegregation efforts have been
identified in all four cases, leading to theories that a racist
group may be responsible.
   Racial tensions were heightened here in September when three
black City Council members were ordered arrested after they walked
out of a meeting to protest lack of funding for predominantly black
areas in the city budget.
   One of them, attorney Deitra Micks, was arrested in a City Hall
women's room and hauled back to the council meeting in handcuffs.
The arrests were ordered by City Council President Tillie Fowler,
who is white, so the council would have a quorum.
   ``And all of a sudden this happened, so it just brings up this
whole issue of race again,'' the Rev. John Newman, a black
minister, said Wednesday. ``Jacksonville is sitting on a racial
powder keg, I'm sorry to report.''
   Black leaders said they were angry about Tuesday's discovery of
the bomb, but it will not deter them from their work.
   ``We will go on with our business as usual. We will not let this
incident stop us from doing the job we have set out to do,'' said
Willye Dennis, the local president of the NAACP. She received the
explosive package Monday, but didn't have time to open it then.
   She had a more optimistic view of racial tension in the city.
   ``We've come a long way in Jacksonville, but we have a long way
to go,'' she said.
   City Council member Terry Wood, who is white, said he believes
tensions have eased since the walkout. ``But there are elements on
both sides who can point to certain events and say improvements are
superficial,'' said Wood.
   Newman, pastor of the Mount Calvary Baptist Church, said the
organization has received criticism from both whites and blacks for
its positions.
   ``On one hand we have threats from whites, perhaps racists, who
want to destroy us because of positions of ideology ... and on the
other hand, to try to stop drugs we have threats from blacks who
happened to be drug dealers who want to blow us away,'' Newman said.
   The FBI said Wednesday that all four bombs had Georgia postmarks
or return addresses.
   FBI agent William Hinshaw, in charge of the Atlanta office, said
the first parcel bomb, addressed to federal Judge Robert S. Vance,
was mailed last Thursday from Newnan, Ga., to Vance's home in
Mountain Brook, Ala., a suburb of Birmingham. Vance was killed and
his wife was seriously injured.
   The bomb that killed Savannah, Ga., alderman and attorney Robert
E. Robinson on Monday is believed to have been mailed Friday from
Macon, Hinshaw said. The bomb found in Jacksonville also was mailed
Friday from Macon, he said.
   Another bomb was mailed Saturday from the Atlanta area to the
11th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals clerk's office in Atlanta,
Hinshaw said.
   The investigation is concentrating in part on possible links to
NAACP school desegregation efforts:
   _ The 11th Circuit hears federal appeals from Georgia, Florida
and Alabama, including desegregation cases.
   _ Vance, an 11th Circuit judge, wrote the court's September
ruling in favor of the Jacksonville NAACP in its desegregation suit
against Jacksonville schools.
   _ Robinson was the Savannah NAACP's local counsel and helped
with an NAACP suit against the Savannah schools. The NAACP lost
that case at the 11th Circuit, and the three-judge panel did not
include Vance.
   _ Robinson also had advised the Jacksonville NAACP chapter in
its desegregation case, according to a Jacksonville activist, the
Rev. Fred Newbill.
</TEXT>

</DOC>