<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0085 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1325EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China     12-27 0713</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China,0732</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dialogue With Students Brings Hard Questions About Deng, Jiang</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM ABRAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Defiant students shouted out criticisms of Deng
Xiaoping and his hand-picked successor Wednesday in a dialogue with
a senior government official.
   The Beijing University students, in a two-hour meeting with
State Council spokesman Yuan Mu, also sought China's response to
events in Romania and hissed when Yuan stressed that China won't
veer from its socialist road.
   Yuan's meeting with the students appeared timed to the overthrow
of Romania's dictator Nicolae Ceausescu, which has rekindled sparks
of student activism smothered by the June crackdown on the
student-led pro-democracy movement.
   At least three illegal posters have gone up at Beijing and
Qinghua universities in recent days commenting on Romania's
uprising, according to Chinese and Western sources. One poster
said, ``Learn from Romania.''
   Another, one of two at Beijing University, described Ceausescu
as a ``lost dog'' who might try to flee to China, whose leaders had
regarded him as a friend. All the posters were torn down swiftly by
authorities.
   It was one of the first open acts of opposition to the
government on the campus since it was in the forefront of the
crushed student movement.
   A student who attended the meeting said about 300 students with
tickets issued by official student associations were allowed to
attend the meeting, and only university-approved student leaders
could read questions submitted in advance.
   But one student shouted out a question asking why former party
chief Zhao Ziyang was purged following the June turmoil and blamed
for China's economic and political problems when it was his mentor,
senior leader Deng Xiaoping, who has decided policy in the past
decade.
   Yuan didn't answer, and also didn't respond when a student asked
why Deng had suddenly anointed new party chief Jiang Zemin as the
``core'' of China's new leaders after allowing the ouster of two
tried and experienced revolutionaries, Zhao and former party
General Secretary Hu Yaobang.
   Hu, whose death in April set off the pro-democracy movement, was
also dismissed from office, in January 1987, after being blamed for
failing to stop student rallies for democratic reform.
   The students asked the whereabouts of Zhao, who has not been
seen in public since May, and were told he is in Beijing. They also
asked about Wang Dan, the Beijing University student who was one of
the leaders of the spring movement.
   Beijing City party Secretary General Yuan Liben said he was
under arrest, but provided no other details.
   When asked about Romania, Yuan Mu replied: ``No matter what the
situation is in the rest of the world, China will always walk the
path of socialism, uphold the socialist flag and adhere to the
leadership of the Communist Party of China.''
   The student participant said Yuan spoke with vehemence, standing
up and banging his hand on the table.
   But when he went on to repeat familiar socialist principles,
some students made hissing noises. ``The students were very brave
to do that in these times,'' the student said.
   Some students also yelled out questions about the legitimacy of
two student leaders who were reading questions. In May, when
independent student organizations were formed to challenge the
officially sanctioned student unions, students voted the two out of
office. The independent unions have since been declared illegal and
the sanctioned groups restored to their former place.
   The student said the session ended without all the questions
being answered but that both sides appeared glad to terminate the
largely fruitless dialogue.
   Since June, university students have been subjected to a
campaign of heavy political indoctrination and have been forced to
write ``confessions'' repenting their activities during the
demonstrations.
   Students say another major uprising is unlikely at present
because of the political repression and close surveillance, but
that anger over the bloody military attack in June when hundreds,
and perhaps thousands, of demonstrators were killed has not
subsided.
   In addition to the poster at Beijing University, another poster
was seen recently outside the Central Drama Academy urging students
to remember June. At least six people were arrested Dec. 9 when
students from the Beijing College of Aeronautics unfurled a banner
in front of the central TV station reading: ``Motherland, why are
you so poor?''
</TEXT>

</DOC>