<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0230 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2057EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-Panama-KellyText 7thAdd   12-20 0930</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Panama-Kelly Text, 7th Add,a0844 et. seq.,810</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHN: the dictator.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Q: Excuse me, General. What _
   ADM. SHEAFER: Let me add one thing to what he said. The comments
he made about payday should not be taken lightly. When you retire
from the PDF after 26 years of service, you retire on 100 percent
of your salary.
   Q: General, I know you said you don't like making predictions,
but how long do you think this mop-up operation will take? And what
role do you see the U.S. military playing down in Panama _ say,
over the next one to two weeks?
   GEN. KELLY: I would say that the mop-up is difficult to figure.
We had hoped to be able to have it done within about three days.
The role we will play is assisting the Panamanians who are a
sovereign state and have a President now who will begin to
function, I'm certain, in maintaining order initially and
recapturing control of their institutions like the police. You
know, the Panamanian police are no different now than they were
before. I think they have to get organized and get decent
leadership, but they can go back out and maintain order.
   Q: Excuse me, if I can follow up. Will U.S. soldiers be playing
a police function down there after the mop-up?
   GEN. KELLY: That's conceivable. We have some MPs down there.
They have police training, and we may have to assist the
Panamanians for as short a period of time as possible. That's a
policy decision _ that's not my decision, and then _ and we'll get
guidance on it.
   Q: It's always been presumed, General Kelly, that the area
outside the city of Panama, along the Costa Rican border, has been
the most friendly towards Noriega, and it's always been speculated
that if he got into trouble, he would run into that area. Have you
secured that area?
   GEN. KELLY: We _ we're not going to tell you everything that
we've done, but the preponderance of our forces right now in the
areas that I laid out for you initially where the major combat
elements of the PDF are _ I think that the _ the first thing we
felt we had to do was take on the PDF regular units in the vicinity
of the capital, and to assist the Panamanian people, the vast
majority of whom live there, as you know, in reestablishing their
democracy and supporting the duly elected government of the
country. When that's done _ and hopefully, that won't take too long
_ we'll then have opportunities to do other things, possibly.
   Q: General, is _ (inaudible) _ still going on at this point in
the country?
   GEN. KELLY: Right now _ I just checked before we walked over
here _ and not very much. As I said, in the airborne area _ and
they got in late a little bit because of the bad weather _ they
finished off their job this afternoon, were going in late this
afternoon up to Fort Cimarron to check on Battalion 2000, and found
they weren't even there. So, in terms of major fighting going on
right now, there is none.
   Q: General, what about _
   Q: General, what _ General _ excuse me _ when were the _ two
questions. When were the Shermans taken down to Panama? And the
other question is, the U.S. representatives had contact with some
of the Noriega opposition people before the Force went down. Was
there any contact with PDF people thought to be sympathetic?
   GEN. KELLY: To answer your first question first, when was the
Shermans taken down? Some time ago. But not a long time ago.
   Q: A month, or _
   GEN. KELLY: Maybe about that. And the reason I don't give you
specific data is because I don't remember it, but it's in that
ballpark. In terms of contacts with anybody, he didn't, I didn't,
and nobody I know did. We had a mission to go down and that's what
we did.
   Q: Well, I mean, the people in the embassy told the pool this
morning that they had had contacts with some of the political
opposition I guess Monday.
   GEN. KELLY: They _ they may well have, but what I was told to do
was get the 82nd and the Rangers and the others ready to go, and
that's what _ that's what we did.
   Q: General, what about reports that Noriega may be either in
Nicaragua or Cuba or he may have fled the country, and what would
that do to your efforts to capture him?
   GEN. KELLY: If he's gone to Cuba or Nicaragua, it'd obviously
slow our efforts down a little bit, I guess. (Laughter.) It _
   Q: Can you tell me if he's in _ that he's in Panama?
   GEN. KELLY: We think he is.
   ADM. SHEAFER: We have no reason to believe that he's outside of
Panama.
   GEN. KELLY: If Noriega's left Panama, by the way, he's utterly
without influence. You know, former dictators are not the same as
elder statesmen. He's liable to sit on some beach until somebody
stops by to say hello to him. (Laughter.)
   Q: General, are the Apaches normally based in Panama?
   Q: (Inaudible) _ Tactical Air Command _
   GEN. KELLY: Sir?
   Q: Are the the Apaches normally based in Panama and could you
describe how the other helicopters were brought down?
   GEN. KELLY: Well, the Apaches are not normally based in Panama
and the helicopters were all brought down in larger airplanes,
generally C-5s.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>