<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0206 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2259EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s w BC-WalterMears Adv24   12-21 0776</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Walter Mears, Adv 24,0794</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv24</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 24, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Bush's Once-Vague Phrase Gaining Meaning</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WALTER R. MEARS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Withstanding parodies and put-downs, President
Bush's Thousand Points of Light have flickered from a cryptic
campaign slogan into a federal program to foster the volunteer
spirit in America.
   Not bad, given that Bush himself once confessed he wasn't really
certain what the phrase meant, much as he liked the lilt of the
words.
   So there are a thousand points of light _ at least there are
supposed to be _ glittering from the national Christmas tree on the
Ellipse behind the White House. And the president's point-of-light
lieutenant has been issuing citations recognizing ``daily points of
light,'' individuals and organizations engaged in community service
to help solve social problems.
   ``We will single out the few because they represent the many,''
Bush said. ``We hope that by highlighting their achievements, and
the ways they've found to serve, we can inspire others to serve.''
   And yes, there is a point-of-light man at the White House. C.
Gregg Petersmeyer, a Denver businessman who worked in the Bush
campaign, is director of the Office of National Service; his
assignment is to mobilize the campaign for volunteer efforts. The
administration will be seeking congressional backing for a Points
of Light Initiative Foundation, to manage a nationwide drive to
enlist people in community service.
   The government already has programs to organize volunteer
efforts, among them VISTA, ACTION, and the Older American Volunteer
program. Congress approved an extension of those programs through
1993 just before adjourning this year.
   Bush is expected to ask Congress to provide $25 million in each
of the next four years to help finance the foundation, with
matching amounts to be sought from private donors. The goal,
according to Petersmeyer, will be to encourage every citizen to get
involved in at least one community service activity. Every business
also will be asked to join the effort to mobilize volunteers to
cope with hunger, homelessness, drug abuse, juvenile crime and
other social ills.
   The president appointed an advisory committee headed by retiring
Gov. Thomas Kean of New Jersey to plan the foundation and work on
the legislation to create it. At its first meeting, Petersmeyer
told the five members that power is flowing from the government to
the people with the effort to promote volunteerism.
   The panel is to meet again next month to deliver its final
report to Bush.
   So far, as least, the points of light do not seem to have
multiplied, despite the president's emphasis on volunteer efforts.
A Gallup poll conducted six weeks ago showed no measurable increase
in charitable or social service activities during the past two
years.
   According to that survey, 41 percent of Americans say they are
involved in volunteer work. Two years ago it was 39 percent. The
numbers go up sharply when the question is of charitable
contributions rather than volunteer work. More than 70 percent said
they had made donations to charity in the past year.
   The phrase that has become the Bush theme on voluntary efforts
dates from his speech to the Republican National Convention in
1988. Bush ticked off names of 10 organizations, from the Grange to
the Business and Professional Women of America, and called them all
elements in ``a brilliant diversity spread like stars, like a
thousand points of light in a broad and peaceful sky.''
   ``I will keep America moving forward, always forward, for a
better America, for an endless enduring dream and a thousand points
of light,'' he said as he concluded.
   Speechwriter Peggy Noonan is credited with writing the line.
   Bush grabbed it and ran, although he tripped now and then as he
repeated the refrain during the campaign. He spoke of ``a thousand
points of life,'' and of ``a thousand shining hills.'' And at
first, he acknowledged that he couldn't define exactly what it
meant.
   But eventually, practice made perfect.
   When Gov. Michael Dukakis complained in a campaign debate that
``I don't know what that means,'' Bush said that was typical of
big-spending liberals who think the government should do
everything. He said he was talking about the enormous number of
people and organizations willing to help others.
   It was part of his inaugural address, ``a thousand points of
light ... all the community organizations that are spread like
stars throughout the nation, doing good.''
   Now it is part of his administration.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Walter R. Mears, vice president and columnist
for The Associated Press, has reported on Washington and national
politics for more than 25 years.
</TEXT>

</DOC>