<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0129 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1542EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania Bjt   12-29 0902</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania, Bjt,0935</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands of Secret Police in Custody; New Gov't Changes Nation's
Name</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALISON SMALE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of secret police loyal to
Nicolae Ceausescu's shattered regime were reported in custody
Friday and the new government said it would begin steering the
country toward democracy.
   The revolutionary government also said that it has begun putting
secret police on trial.
   The government, a disjointed collection of former officials and
intellectuals that has changed almost daily, made new moves to
strengthen its hold on the country and reiterated its commitment to
free elections in April.
   The leadership also changed the country's name and flag to
reflect the clean break with Ceausescu's harsh Communist rule,
which was toppled one week ago after 24 years of oppression.
   The National Salvation Committee, which has declared itself the
interim government, pledged to honor all of Romania's international
commitments, including membership in the Soviet-led Warsaw Pact
military alliance.
   The government had told Ceausescu loyalists still waging
sporadic guerrilla attacks to lay down their arms by 5 p.m.
Thursday or face execution.
   Cazimir Ionescu, a vice president in the National Salvation
Committee's 145-member governing council, said Friday that several
thousand loyalists had surrendered or been captured in the week
since Ceausescu was toppled.
   The government's newly formed Military Council issued a ``last
call'' for surrender or else the pro-Ceausescu forces will face
trial and be ``summarily sentenced.''
   The council said the army was ``in full control'' nationwide and
that military tribunals set up to put the special police forces on
trial had begun their work ``and will continue to try all acts of
terrorism.''
   Deputy Foreign Minister Cornelieu Bogdan said he hoped the
trials would involve ``due process,'' but said he did not know how
defendants would be judged.
   ``The death penalty may be abolished by then,'' he said.
   He said the prisoners included some generals and high-ranking
officers.
   There was scattered shooting in the capital Thursday night, but
Bogdan said ``the main danger from the terrorists,'' has passed.
   A snowstorm and high winds swept Bucharest on Friday. A column
of about 20-30 tanks was seen rolling through the center of town
with soldiers waving at people as they passed.
   The provisional leadership announced it would honor all
international commitments, ``including those taken under the Warsaw
Pact,'' Bogdan said.
   The country's new leaders are likely to meet the leaders of the
six other Warsaw Pact countries for the first time in Sofia,
Bulgaria, on Jan. 9, when the Soviet-led Eastern trading bloc
Comecon meets.
   Interim President Ion Iliescu reportedly became friends with
Soviet leader Mikhail S. Gorbachev when both were college students
in Moscow.
   It will be the first time the leaders of the seven East bloc
countries will meet since all of those countries have embraced
democratic reforms.
   On Friday, Iliescu and interim Premier Petre Roman met with
Hungarian Foreign Minister Gyula Horn to discuss possible Hungarian
aid. Horn was the first foreign minister to visit Bucharest since
the revolution.
   Ceausescu and his wife, Elena, were executed Monday for grave
crimes against Romania.
   The couple was captured Dec. 23, then shuttled about in a
constantly moving armored car for the last three days of their
lives, Britain's Independent Television News said. It quoted Capt.
Mihail Lupoi, identified as a senior army official, as saying that
Ceausescu was kept in the moving car to prevent rescue attempts.
   Lupoi also said Ceausescu was a diabetic but refused to take his
daily insulin does during his last days.
   Meanwhile, Romania's former defense minister was given a hero's
funeral on Friday. Gen. Vasile Milea died of a gunshot wound Dec.
22, senior officers have said.
   Before fleeing his palace in the face of revolt, Ceausescu had
denounced Milea and claimed he had committed suicide. But Romania's
new leaders say he was executed for refusing to order army troops
to fire on demonstrators. The army ultimately sided with the
protesters to drive Ceausescu from power.
   Milea's funeral in a small hall at the Military Academy was
shown on national TV.
   The new leadership has received support and recognition from
several Western countries and a special envoy of French President
Francois Mitterrand met Friday with First Deputy President Dumitru
Mazilu.
   The leadership, in a communique issued late Thursday, pledged to
abolish one-party rule and establish a democratic, multiparty
system and hold free elections in April.
   It also called for a free press and minority and religious
rights; changed the country's official name from the Socialist
Republic of Romania to Romania; and removed the communist symbol
from the flag.
   The government on Thursday also appointed new ministers, with a
special focus on the economy.
   But the government also said it had the right to issue decrees
that carry the force of law. Bogdan said such power was needed to
maintain order.
   Ionescu also defended the former Communist leaders in the new
interim leadership, saying they are needed to get the country back
on its feet.
   ``Many Communist Party members are indispensible,'' he said.
   Because Ceausescu took the toughest line in Eastern Europe on
dissent, Romania was never able to develop the dissident network
that formed the core of opposition movements in Hungary, East
Germany and Czechoslovakia.
   Dissidents in those nations all play a key role in the
government. On Friday, dissident playwright Vaclav Havel was
elected president of Czechoslovakia.
   Already this week, several political parties announced their
formation.
</TEXT>

</DOC>