<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0217 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1948EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Panama 5thLd-Writethru 2Takes 12-20 0743</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Panama, 5th Ld-Writethru, 2 Takes,a0854,680-1,280</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS graf 12: ``Bush, up,'' with Bush attending Christmas
party; INSERTS graf 30: ``Peru withdrew,'' to note Peru ambssador withdrawn;
ADDS two grafs on Quayle phone calls; breaks into 2 takes</HEAD>
<HEAD>Bush Says Military Strike `Decapitates' Noriega From Dictatorship</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERENCE HUNT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP White House Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush said Wednesday he ordered the
military strike in Panama to seize Manuel Antonio Noriega and end
``reckless threats and attacks'' against Americans. Noriega eluded
capture and the administration put a $1 million bounty on his head.
   Even though Noriega dropped out of sight, the United States
said, ``As a practical matter, we have decapitated him from the
dictatorship.''
   The White House announced a $1 million reward for information
leading to his capture. In addition, Panamanians were offered $150
for each firearm they surrendered.
   Pentagon officials declared the operation in Panama a military
success, saying Noriega's forces mostly had fled or were fleeing
though some fighting continued.
   Reaction from Congress, both Democratic and Republican, was
mostly favorable.
   Bush, hoping to break a nearly two-year stalemate with Noriega,
dispatched 9,500 soldiers and Marines to back up the 13,000 U.S.
troops already in Panama for a 1 a.m. assault against army bases
and the general's headquarters.
   In a televised address from the Oval Office, a somber Bush told
the nation, ``I took this action only after reaching the conclusion
that every other avenue was closed and the lives of American
citizens were in grave danger.''
   In the fighting _ codenamed ``Operation Just Cause'' by the
Pentagon _ 15 U.S. military personnel were killed, many more were
wounded and one was missing. In addition, a woman dependent was
killed, the Pentagon said.
   Four helicopters crashed, believed to have been brought down by
gunfire.
   Noting the loss of American lives, Bush said, ``No president
takes such action lightly.''
   Lt. Gen. Tom Kelly, Army deputy chief of staff, said, ``One dead
American is too many, but thank God the numbers don't appear too
high right now.'' He said, ``It looks like the organized resistance
is a thing of the past.''
   Bush, up much of the night, monitored the fighting in Panama. He
took a break Wednesday evening to attend a White House Christmas
party.
   Some Americans were reported taken hostage in the Marriott Hotel
in Panama City. Late in the day, U.S. Marines arrived at the site
and escorted many Americans out of the building.
   Kelly called Noriega ``a crafty devil'' and said he had not been
spotted Wednesday.
   He said U.S. forces had observed Noriega several times on
Tuesday. ``We thought we had a pretty good idea of where he was
last night. We went there and he wasn't there.''
   ``He has gone to ground,'' Kelly said. Even so, he expressed
confidence Noriega would be located, saying ``we have every spigot
turned on'' to find him. He said there was no indication Noriega
had left Panama.
   The general said ``much of the PDF (Panamanian Defense Forces)
is fleeing in the face of the U.S. military units.''
   He added, ``We have a concern that they have gone off into the
jungle. There is every chance that we will go off after them.''
   Kelly said he expected the canal to reopen Thursday.
   Bush said the United States would withdraw its force as soon as
possible. Secretary of State James A. Baker III said he could not
speculate how long U.S. troops would remain in action.
   Bush was roundly criticized when he kept U.S. forces on the
sidelines during an unsuccessful coup attempt against Noriega on
Oct. 3.
   In contrast, congressional leaders generally supported the
president's decision to use force.
   ``When there is the engagement of U.S. forces in the field, it
behooves all of us to give that support,'' House Speaker Thomas
Foley said.
   ``It was made necessary by the reckless actions of Gen.
Noriega,'' said Senate Majority Leader George Mitchell, D-Maine.
   But Rep. Don Edwards, D-Calif., called Bush's action ``a
trigger-happy act of gunboat diplomacy'' which violates the
Constitution. And, Sen. Claiborne Pell, D-R.I., chairman of the
Senate Foreign Relations Committee, said Bush should not have acted
without the support and aid of other Central American nations.
   William J. Bennett, the director of national drug control
policy, said of Noriega, ``I think we can safely conclude that this
ends his career as a drug trafficker. He's not running drugs. He's
not running Panama. He's just running. And that's good.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>