<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 2318EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama 9thLd-Writethru a0860 12-24 1427</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama, 9th Ld - Writethru, a0860,1470</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Noriega Asks Vatican Embassy for Asylum</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 6 grafs to UPDATE with sources saying possibility
of asylum in Spain or Cuba discussed, details. Pick up 5th pvs, `Word that...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos DOD1,2,3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DOUGLAS GRANT MINE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ousted dictator Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noriega sought refuge at the Vatican embassy Sunday after five days
on the run, and he requested political asylum to evade U.S. troops
sent to capture him.
   As word spread that Noriega had surfaced, hundreds of people
converged on the two-story embassy, which was surrounded by U.S.
troops and armored vehicles. A helicopter hovered overhead. Some
young men yelled that Noriega should be lynched.
   Although U.S. officials expressed relief and pleasure, Noriega's
move may have thwarted a main purpose of the invasion launched last
week: the capture of the elusive leader so he could stand trial in
the United States on drug charges.
   The Italian news agency ANSA quoted the papal nuncio in Panama
City, Monignor Sebastiano Laboa, as indicating he would not hand
over Noriega to the United States or U.S.-installed government in
Panama.
   Sources familiar with the situation said the papal nuncio had
mentioned to other diplomats the possibility of Noriega going to
Spain or Cuba.
   The papal nuncio is the Vatican's diplomatic representative in
Panama, and under international law, embassies are sacrosanct
ground.
   Word that the elusive Noriega had resurfaced came first from
Gen. Maxwell Thurman, chief of the U.S. Southern Command. President
Bush announced later in Washington that Noriega had surrendered and
``his reign of terror is over.''
   Noriega turned himself in just hours after three high-ranking
members of his army surrendered and another pledged loyalty to the
U.S.-backed government.
   In a dispatch from Panama City, ANSA quoted unidentified sources
as saying Noriega sought political asylum to negotiate his transfer
to another country.
   The report also said there were 32 people in the embassy,
formally known as the papal nunciatura, including high officials of
the Panamanian Defense Forces and political parties of the Noriega
regime.
   The Rev. Joseph Esspeteri, the nuncio's secretary, confirmed
that Noriega was at the embassy but refused to say whether he had
been granted asylum or anything else on his status. Vatican
Secretary of State Agostino Casaroli, leaving midnight Mass at St.
Peter's Basilica in Rome, declined to comment on Noriega's action.
   Noriega's move appeared to put the Vatican in a delicate
position, with a choice of offending the United States by refusing
to turn Noriega over or appearing to condone the U.S. invasion by
doing so.
   ``It's a very complex problem,'' said a senior Vatican official
early Monday. The official, who works in foreign policy issues and
spoke under the usual ground rule of anonymity, noted that the
Vatican has no tradition or policy of accepting asylum seekers.
   ``I don't think they could directly hand Noriega over to the
Americans, who are an invading army,'' the official said. ``They
would be recognizing the Americans as the local authorities.
Instead, they could hand him over to the government there on
condition of a fair trial.''
   Noriega arrived by car at the embassy about 3 p.m., said an
informed military source. At the time, there were no U.S. troops
around the building, which occupies about half a city block in a
well-to-do Paitilla neighborhood.
   Witnesses said they saw several former officials of the
Noriega-controlled government entering the Vatican Embassy this
afternoon, including Manuel Solis Palma, who was acting president
on Sept. 1.
   In Panama City, shattered after five days of fighting between
U.S. troops and Noriega loyalists, people banged pots and pans
together, cheered and honked horns when they heard the news about
Noriega.
   ``Now we can have Christmas!' said one man, who grabbed a friend
and hugged him. ``I don't have a turkey in the house, we don't even
have any hamburger. All we have is a can of sardines, but what the
hell!''
   ``Is it true?'' yelled a woman on a balcony. She squealed with
delight when told it was.
   ``Mission accomplished,'' said a passing cab driver. ``That
coward.''
   Noriega had been at large since U.S. troops invaded Panama at
midnight Tuesday in an effort to capture him. The Bush
administration offered a $1 million bounty for the military
strongman.
   Ironically, opposition leader Guillermo Endara, installed as
president shortly after the invasion, obtained shelter at the papal
nuncio's residence in October after being beaten and thrown out of
his office by Noriega's soldiers.
   There was no immediate comment from the Vatican. There was no
answer at the phone number of Vatican spokesman Joaquin Navarro in
Vatican City.
   U.S. Defense Secretary Dick Cheney, who flew to Panama, said he
was ``delighted'' at the news on Noriega.
   ``He no longer is a factor in Panama,'' Cheney said. ``Now it is
up to the lawyers and the diplomats to figure out what is next. As
far as I'm concerned, the military has done its job.''
   Thurman said he had the embassy surrounded because ``I have the
security responsibility for all of Panama, so I don't want (Dignity
Battalions) blowing into the place. I would not want them to come
with an armored car and blow their way into the embassy.''
   The 26,000-member U.S. force, bolstered by reinforcements sent
in Saturday, made headway earlier Sunday in its fight to put down
the resistance of Noriega holdouts after three high-ranking members
of Noriega's army surrendered and another pledged loyalty to the
U.S.-backed government.
   U.S. authorities said about 1,800 of Noriega's original 15,000
Defense Force members were still fighting U.S. troops. It was not
immediately clear how Noriega's move Sunday would affect them.
   Since the invasion, 25 U.S. soldiers and two American civilians
have been killed, according to the Pentagon. One soldier was
missing, and 281 were wounded, U.S. officials said.
   The U.S. military said 154 Panamanian soldiers had died, 113
were wounded, and 2,969 had been captured.
   Dr. Elmer Miranda, director of Santo Tomas Hospital, put the
Panamanian death toll at 260 and said many victims were civilians.
   Many families in the capital of 1 million had nothing to give
their children on the usually joyous holiday in this predominantly
Roman Catholic nation.
   ``What am I going to tell my 6-year-old daughter? I cannot tell
her Santa Claus was killed by a bomb,'' said one woman in a
middle-class neighborhood.
   A few Christmas lights twinkled in some homes, but most shops
and supermarkets were looted bare. Food and medical supplies were
dwindling, and officials were arranging to fly in fresh supplies.
   ``Three more looting days until Christmas,'' observed one
visitor.
   Many neighborhoods formed groups to clean up streets littered
with glass and trash and put up Christmas lights.
   ``We have to forge ahead and not be thinking this country is
sinking without a chance to make a better future,'' said a man who
lost about $100,000 when his furniture store was looted.
   At his first presidential news conference Sunday, Endara said he
wished the ``foreign army'' could leave soon but that it probably
would take Panama longer to return to normal.
   ``I wish it were a month,'' he said. ``But I don't think so. I
do not know when.''
   Col. Luis del Cid, a key military commander charged with drug
smuggling along with Noriega, said he would turn himself in to U.S.
military authorities because he was worried about the safety of his
10 children.
   Del Cid, commander of the 5th Military Zone in the provincial
capital of David about 200 miles outside Panama City, had ordered
David's airfield blown up Wednesday to prevent the landing of
American aircraft. He said he would surrender when U.S. troops
reached the city.
   Noriega, Del Cid and 14 others were indicted on drug charges in
U.S. federal court in Miami in February 1988.
   Also Sunday, Lt. Col. Daniel Delgado, Lt. Col. Arnulfo Castrejon
and Lt. Col. Carlos Arosemena turned themselves in to U.S. troops
in Panama City.
   U.S. troops discovered a cache of arms in a rented house near
Noriega's family home in an upper-middle class section of the city.
Found were 300 G-3 rifles, 72,000 rounds of ammunition, at least
360 concussion grenades, about 300 AK-47 assault rifles with 20,000
rounds of ammunition and 30 light anti-tank weapons.
   Neighbors said the house had been rented by Noriega, said Sgt.
John Stowe.
   The house was sparsely furnished with two bunkbeds, a sofa, TV
and VCR with a supply of tapes including two copies of ``Rambo
III,'' ``Tougher Than Leather,'' ``Messenger of Death,'' ``Midnight
Run'' and ``Going Undercover.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>