<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0095 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1724EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     12-26 0381</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0395</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Drinks are on the house at Pasta Too
restaurant. No, it's not the holiday spirit: The owners have been
giving them away for more than 4 years because they can't afford a
liquor license to sell alcohol.
   ``Hey, it's an extra little bennie (benefit) for the adults,''
said Jim Leddy, who recently frequented the restaurant in suburban
Bethel Park with his wife, Stephanie, and their daughter, Natalie.
   Pasta Too has been offering complimentary drinks to adults as
``a nice gesture'' for about 4{ years, owner Raymond Piacquadio
says.
   Piacquadio said his business is too small to pay the $40,000 or
more needed for a license to sell beer and wine. So for those who
want it, he gives it away _ plastic cups of Meisterbrau draft and
glasses of Gallo chablis and burgundy.
   It's perfectly legal, according to Steve Sandrovich, a
supervisor in the Pittsburgh office of the state police Bureau of
Liquor Control Enforcement. Nothing in the liquor code prohibits an
unlicensed establishment from giving away free beer, wine or liquor
to sober, orderly adults 21 and older.
   It is illegal, however, for a licensed business to give away
liquor.
   No purchase is necessary at restaurants giving away free drinks,
Sandrovich said.
   ``If you come in and say, `I just want the free beer,' they have
to give it to you,'' he said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>GLENWOOD SPRINGS, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A thousand or more revelers plan
to plunge into the New Year in this resort town's giant hot
spring-fed pool.
   The annual New Year's Eve splash has become a tradition in this
mountain town northwest of Aspen.
   ``At midnight, the pool is jammed,'' resident Nick Isenberg
said. ``At 12:05 a.m., it's empty.''
   The outdoor pool, billed as the world's largest, is actually two
pools just footsteps apart. One measures 400 feet by 100 feet and
the other 100 feet by 75 feet.
   The pool normally closes at 10 p.m., but remains open until 1
a.m. on New Year's morning, spokeswoman Lisa Wiggins said.For the
usual $5.25 admission fee, the staff provides party hats and
noisemakers.
   Those driving home from the bash may be relaxed, but they won't
be tipsy. No drinking is allowed at the pool, not even on New
Year's Eve.
</TEXT>

</DOC>