<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0088 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1048EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-PoliceProbe 1stLd-Writethru a0476 12-22 0524</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Police Probe, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0476,0534</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Official Ordered Jailed in Fraud Case</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 4th graf, `Magistrate Virginia...', to add possible maximum
sentence, Weiner's age; SUBS 12th graf, `The fraud...', with 3 grafs to
add more detail on Thursday testimony, background. Picks up 13th graf,
`Weiner said...'.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURA WISNIEWSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A former police official accused of defrauding
investors and of stealing from the department was ordered jailed to
keep him from fleeing before his next court appearance.
   Kenneth Weiner, former deputy chief of the Detroit Police
Department, was arrested early Thursday at Detroit Metropolitan
Airport.
   He was carrying dozens of charge cards, airline flight coupons,
a passport and $3,100 in Canadian money, FBI agents testified at
Weiner's U.S. District Court bond hearing.
   Magistrate Virginia M. Morgan sent Weiner, 43, to jail without
bond on a federal fraud charge until his pretrial hearing Jan. 2.
The charge, which carries a possible sentence of five years in
prison and a $250,000 fine, stems from his alleged involvement in a
scheme to defraud investors of $20 million.
   Morgan said Weiner has an ability to manipulate the system, to
appear or disappear whenever it was in his interest to do so.
   Weiner's attorney, Robert Harrison, said an appeal will be filed
immediately but acknowledged Weiner likely will be held until after
Christmas.
   `He's very unhappy right now, obviously,'' Harrison said outside
the courtroom. ``He feels the truth did not come out.''
   Harrison said the flood of media reports on the mystery of
Weiner's whereabouts in the past few weeks tainted the case, making
Weiner appear evasive.
   ``He's a man who travels in his own name all over the country,''
Harrison said.
   He said Weiner was flying to Detroit from Los Angeles to meet
with his attorneys regarding an Internal Revenue Service
investigation.
   Police Chief William Hart recently accused Weiner of stealing
from a $1.4 million Detroit police secret service fund used for
undercover operations. Weiner had access to the fund from 1980 to
1986.
   FBI Agent Thomas Cannistra, who has been investigating Weiner
since May 1986, testified Thursday that Weiner sent $1.3 million
from the secret service fund to dummy corporations in California.
   Federal investigators have said that two of the corporations
named by Cannistra paid a $3,000 monthly rent bill for a house in
Beverly Hills, Calif., occupied for two years by Hart's daughter
and son-in-law. Hart has denied knowing about the rent payments.
   Cannistra said the fraud charge is unrelated to the police
investigation but is from a pyramid investment scheme involving the
sale of gold and silver. He said between $5 million and $10 million
remains missing from the scheme.
   Weiner's court troubles began in 1986 when Caine Steel Co. of
Detroit filed a civil suit against him, charging that he defrauded
the company of $379,000. He was accused of duping as many as 90
investors out of about $20 million in a scheme that involved
trading of gold and silver.
   The alleged investment scheme used new investors' cash to
provide large returns to previous investors. Such plans collapse
when new investors can't be found.
</TEXT>

</DOC>