<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2352EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Aquino-Press Bjt   12-18 0664</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Aquino-Press, Bjt,0681</SECOND>
<HEAD>Aquino's Love Affair With The Press Sours Amid Coup Crisis</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT H. REID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Corazon Aquino's
relationship with the press is a love affair gone sour.
   Once she praised the media for helping her take power. Now, she
threatens legal action against those news outlets deemed to be
aiding the forces bent on toppling her.
   Seeking to repair the damage wrought by the recent failed coup,
Mrs. Aquino on Monday told reporters that the government would
revoke the franchise of broadcasters who violate regulations
against airing ``subversive propaganda.''
   ``With regard to print media, it's an entirely different
matter,'' Mrs. Aquino said. ``We will base this on any article that
will incite to rebellion. If such an article does appear in any of
the newspapers, then we will go to court to file charges against
the erring individual or the publication.''
   She gave no indication what standards would be used in
determining whether reports ``incite rebellion.''
   A senior U.S. official, speaking on condition he not be named,
defended government plans in the wake of the Dec. 1-9 coup attempt,
the most serious of six in her nearly 4 years in power. He said
there had been examples in American history when presidents imposed
controls during grave national emergencies.
   But media controls of any sort are a sensitive issue in a
country emerging from years of strongman rule under the late
President Ferdinand Marco, a country uncertain of the strength of
its democratic institutions.
   ``The government assault on press freedom has begun,'' said the
newspaper Malaya. ``What is frightening is the mere thought that
the Aquino government, swept into power on the promise of rigid
observance of the citizens' rights and liberties, would entertain
the idea of muzzling the press.''
   Since Marcos was ousted, more than 20 English, Tagalog and
Chinese-language newspapers have appeared in the capital, and the
Manila press has become one of the most free-wheeling in Asia.
   The government's move clearly aims to limit access to media,
particularly radio, for rebels still at large. Ironically, some of
Mrs. Aquino's stalwarts complained of stringent measures undertaken
to limit access to opposition groups under Marcos.
   During the February 1986 uprising that toppled Marcos, Mrs.
Aquino's allies carefully cultivated foreign reporters and local
journalists bold enough to challenge the government's version of
events. On the first anniversary of the Marcos ouster, the
government awarded certificates of thanks to foreign journalists
who covered the 1986 uprising.
   So far, the National Telecommunications Commission has closed
just two radio stations _ a pro-Marcos outlet in Manila and another
broadcaster in Cebu. The Cebu station was later allowed to reopen.
   After an August 1987 coup attempt, some independent stations
aired taped interviews with renegade Lt. Col. Gregorio ``Gringo''
Honasan, also believed to have been a leader of the recent putsch.
   No statements from rebels have been broadcast since they gave up
their last position Dec. 9.
   Newspaper executives say they have received no directives
telling them what to print. But several, speaking on condition of
anonymity, say they fear such a move in the future if the political
situation worsens.
   On Monday, the Philippine Daily Globe reported that military
Chief of Staff Gen. Renato de Villa asked that another newspaper,
the Philippine Daily Inquirer, be closed for ``inaccurate
reporting'' during the coup attempt but that de Villa was overruled
by the administration.
   Neither de Villa nor the presidential palace has commented on
the report. In a front-page editorial today, the Inquirer suggested
de Villa ``stick to soldiering and leave newspapering to those who
understand its mission and operation.''
   Even before the coup attempt, Mrs. Aquino's relations with the
Manila press had deteriorated. Columnists regularly lambasted the
administration for inefficiency, alleged corruption and favoritism
of presidential relatives.
   Reporters covering the president often complain that access is
limited to weekly ``mini-press conferences'' in which Mrs. Aquino
answers a limited number of questions, often with vague, standard
responses.
</TEXT>

</DOC>