<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0212 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0102EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-HBJPresident     12-21 0447</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-HBJ President,0462</SECOND>
<HEAD>Peter Jovanovich Named President of Publishing Giant Run By Father</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ORLANDO, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Peter Jovanovich has been promoted to
president and chief executive officer at Harcourt Brace Jovanovich
Inc., making him second in command after his father, HBJ Chairman
William Jovanovich.
   The younger Jovanovich, 40, formerly served as executive vice
president of the Orlando-based publishing and insurance company. He
succeeds Ralph D. Caulo, 54, whose resignation is effective Dec. 31.
   Caulo has resigned to ``enter other ventures in central Florida
and in Austin and San Antonio, Texas,'' the company said Wednesday.
William Jovanovich, 69, remains as chairman of the board of HBJ.
   Caulo's position at the publishing gaint has appeared in
jeopardy since last summer, when HBJ announced plans to sell its
six theme parks. The company also said at the time that it would
allow Caulo to leave his post to manage the parks.
   But an HBJ executive close to sale negotiations told the Orlando
Sentinel that Anheuser-Busch Cos. Inc., which bought the parks in
November for $1.1 billion, wanted to employ its own park executive.
   William Jovanovich, the Sentinel reported in Thursday's
editions, sought to oust Caulo in order to place his son Peter in a
better position to later assume leadership of the company.
   Caulo could not be immediately reached for comment.
   In 1987, HBJ assumed nearly $3 billion in debt to fend off a
takeover bid by British press mogul Robert Maxwell. The sale last
month of its theme parks, including four Sea World parks, to
Anheuser-Busch was made to help pay off that debt.
   With the sale, HBJ reduced its debt by about $930 million to
about $1.63 billion, analysts say.
   Elizabeth Bramwell, an analyst at Gabelli &amp; Co., a New York
brokerage, said she believes Jovanovich's move to the HBJ
presidency ``is a constructive move'' that signals a determination
to turn the company's full attention to publishing, its core
business.
   ``They took their eye off the eight-ball and expense in
publishing and expenses this year got out of control,'' Bramwell
said.
   Ivan Obolensky, senior vice president at Josephthal &amp; Co.,
another New York brokerage, expressed doubt that the promotion of
Peter Jovanovich will make a big difference at HBJ. ``It's not a
big change; it's the leopard changing its spots.''
   Obolensky said he is concerned that HBJ remains vulnerable to a
hostile takeover.
   In his new position, Peter Jovanovich will supervise HBJ's
elementary and secondary school publishing. For the past five years
he has managed HBJ's other publishing businesses, including
university, medical, scientific and trade books, and fiction and
non-fiction titles.
   The younger Jovanovich joined HBJ in 1980 after working for
Macmillian Inc., another publishing house.
</TEXT>

</DOC>