<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0243 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0809EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Whitbread-Allied-Lyons     12-22 0312</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Whitbread-Allied-Lyons,0325</SECOND>
<HEAD>Whitbread Sells Liquor Businesses to Allied-Lyons</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Whitbread &amp; Co. PLC, a British brewer, said Friday
it is selling its liquor division to Allied-Lyons PLC, a major
British liquor company, for the equivalent of $877 million.
   The deal follows Whitbread's announcement in October that it had
decided to concentrate on brewing and leisure retailing activities,
particularly pubs, restaurant chains and hotels.
   Whitbread's liquor division is made up of two main companies,
James Burrough Distillers, which produces brands such as Beefeater
Gin and Long John Scotch whisky, and the Buckingham Wine Co., which
imports and distributes wines and liquors in the United States.
   Whitbread's 85 percent holding in the Atlas Peak Vineyards in
California, as well as Julius Wile Napa Californian wines are
included in the deal.
   Pre-tax profit of the businesses being sold was $38 million in
the year ended Feb. 2. The company didn't break out after-tax
profit and revenue.
   Allied-Lyons' acquisition follows its $325 million takeover of
Dunkin' Donuts, a U.S.-based doughnut and coffee franchise
restaurant chain. It obtained control of Dunkin' Donuts on Thursday.
   ``The sale (of the liquor division) will help us strengthen
Whitbread's balance sheet and provides us with the resources to
develop our beer brands,'' said Peter Jarvis, Whitbread's group
managing director.
   He added: ``These (liquor) businesses are better able to achieve
their full potential as part of a significantly larger
international drinks group.''
   Allied-Lyons said, ``The acquisition will enhance our already
strong position in the world wines and spirits market.''
   The deal will provide it with valuable brand names, additional
production facilities and valuable stocks, Allied-Lyons said.
   Allied-Lyons' main brands include Ballantine's and Teacher's
Scotch whiskies, Canadian Club whiskey, Courvoisier cognac, Tia
Maria coffee liqueur, Harvey's Bristol cream sherry, and Coburn's
port.
   Completion of the sale, which must be cleared by British
regulators, is expected by the end of January.
</TEXT>

</DOC>