<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0942EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Jordan 2ndLd-Writethru   12-19 0631</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Jordan, 2nd Ld-Writethru,a0479,0648</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Government To Lift Martial Law, Seeks Vote Of Confidence</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 3 grafs to UPDATE with anti-corruption campaign;
Picks up 3rd graf pvs, `Under martial ...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMAL HALABY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AMMAN, Jordan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister Mudar Badran told the new
Parliament today his government will lift martial law, which for 22
years has banned large public meetings and allowed authorities to
restrict freedom of speech.
   Badran, seeking a vote of confidence from the newly elected
legislature, added that until martial law is formally revoked most
of its provisions will be ``frozen'' effective immediately.
   He also vowed his administration will crack down on corruption
by public officials and criticized former governments for deficit
spending that swelled Jordan's $8.3 billion foreign debt.
   Under martial law, which King Hussein imposed after the 1967
Arab-Israeli war, authorities also can close newspapers at any
time, effectively inhibiting free criticism of officials. It also
provides for special courts.
   Most candidates in last month's general elections called for the
lifting of martial law and many demanded the legalization of
political parties, which currently are banned.
   Badran said a constitutional court will be formed to secure
citizens' rights as stipulated by the constitution.
   He lifted legal immunity from government officials and said he
would put forward legislation requiring an officeholder to present
``a comprehensive and documented report of all his possessions.''
   The announcement of such a financial disclosure requirement was
aimed at ensuring the integrity of public officials.
   The government of Prime Minister Zeid Rifai, which resigned
earlier this year after bloody rioting, was widely accused of
corruption.
   The largest bloc in the new lower house is made up of Islamic
fundamentalists or their sympathizers.
   ``I announce in this Parliament that martial law is now
considered frozen ... until such laws are constitutionally
abolished in the near future,'' Badran told the lower house of
Parliament.
   It was the latest in a series of moves towards democracy and
liberalization announced by the king and by Badran's government,
which was formed Dec. 6.
   The lower house has to approve all laws and has the power to
throw out prime ministers and their Cabinets. Still, King Hussein
can block any laws in the royally appointed Senate or through a
veto, and he has frequently used the power to dissolve Parliament
and rule by decree.
   Last month, Hussein promised a ``gradual reduction'' in the
activities of the martial law courts and said their
responsibilities would be transfered to civil courts.
   On Dec. 10, Badran announced his government would return
confiscated passports and promised further amnesties for political
prisoners, after 48 were released by the previous government.
   He told Parliament then that he ordered authorities to give all
Jordanian citizens freedom of movement and the right to work, in
accordance with the king's instructions.
   Badran said he did not know how many passports had been
confiscated, but security sources said the number was more than
8,700. Many of those whose passports were confiscated had said
security officials intervened to bar them from jobs.
   The November elections were the first nationwide poll since 1967
when Israel captured the West Bank from Jordan. Hussein last year
renounced Jordan's claim to the West Bank in favor of the Palestine
Liberation Organization.
   The fundamentalist Moslem Brotherhood Movement captured the most
seats in the lower house of Parliament _ 25 out of a total of 80 _
but Badran earlier this month formed a government without the
movement that advocates stricter Islamic laws.
   By law, the new 23-member Cabinet has to appear before lower
house for a vote of confidence within 30 days. If approved by a
simple majority of 41 votes, the government will be installed. If
not, King Hussein will have to name a new prime minister.
</TEXT>

</DOC>