<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0452EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CDC--Measles     12-22 0370</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-CDC--Measles,0382</SECOND>
<HEAD>Measles Explosion Bringing Increased Death, Too</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Measles has claimed more lives in 1989 than in
any year since 1971, mainly among unvaccinated preschoolers and
schoolchildren whose shots didn't work, federal health officials
say.
   So far this year, there have been 42 deaths among 14,714
reported measles cases, compared with 90 deaths among 75,290
measles cases reported in 1971, measles specialist Dr. William L.
Atkinson of the national Centers for Disease Control said Thursday.
   But Atkinson said the seemingly higher fatality rate _ 2.9
deaths per 1,000 measles cases so far in 1989, compared with 1.2
deaths per 1,000 cases in 1971 _may be deceptive. He suspects that
many milder cases have gone unreported in some urban areas this
year.
   As it is, there have been five times as many measles cases
reported in 1989 as the 2,876 reported by this time last year.
   In the first six months of this year, 30 percent of the cases
occurred in children under 5, who are too small to be covered by
school-vaccination laws, while 51 percent occurred among people
5-19.
   Half the cases were among people who had been vaccinated, the
CDC said.
   The CDC recommended this fall that children be given two
vaccinations, one at age 15 months, the second at about age 5. That
strategy is designed to break the spread of measles among
schoolchildren who were vaccinated young _ and had to prove it to
get in school _ but whose vaccinations, for some reason, failed to
protect them.
   But the new double-dose recommendation will do nothing to combat
the outbreak of measles among unvaccinated preschoolers, Atkinson
noted.
   ``We've got to find some sort of clever ways to motivate parents
to get their kids vaccinated,'' he said. ``A 15-month-old doesn't
walk in on his own.''
   Federal health officials believed measles eradication was within
reach early in this decade; just 1,497 cases were reported in 1983.
   But the disease, characterized by fever and a red, spotty rash,
has bounced back, although it remains far less common than it was
before a measles vaccine was introduced in 1963. Before then, it
was not unusual for the nation to report half a million cases a
year.
</TEXT>

</DOC>