<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1236EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Lebanon     12-24 0508</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon,0525</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rival Moslem Militias Battle For Second Day</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By AHMED MANTASH</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SIDON, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rival Shiite Moslem militias battled
Sunday for the second day with tanks and artillery in the hills of
south Lebanon, ignoring a cease-fire appeal from Iran.
   Police said 15 people were killed and 53 wounded in the clashes
between the Iranian-backed Hezbollah, or Party of God, and the
Syrian-armed Amal in the Iqlim al-Tuffah, or the apple province in
south Lebanon.
   By police count, 32 people have been killed and 98 wounded since
fighting erupted before dawn Saturday, when Hezbollah forces
overran four Amal-held villages in the southern panhandle.
   Amal rushed reinforcements from Beirut to the south Sunday.
About 2,500 fighters, backed by tanks, counterattacked under a
barrage of heavy artillery and recaptured two villages, Mjaidel and
Kfar Hatta, police reported.
   The fighting is the latest flare-up in a 2{-year-old power
struggle between the rival factions for supremacy of Lebanon's 1.2
million Shiites, the country's largest sect.
   The casualties raised the overall toll since May 1987 to 603
killed and 1,677 wounded.
   The fighting spread to Moslem west Beirut during the night with
Hezbollah and Amal fighters clashing in the Hamra commercial
district.
   Police said the clash erupted when Amal militiamen firing
machine guns and rocket-propelled grenades tried to storm a
Hezbollah religious center. A dozen guards defending the center
held them off for four hours before Syrian troops moved in and
enforced a truce.
   Several cars were wrecked in the fighting and the steel shutters
on several shops were blown off. But police said there were no
casualties reported in the clash.
   Mohammad Ali Besharati, Iran's deputy foreign minister, who flew
from Tehran to the Syrian capital, Damascus, had declared a
cease-fire after meeting Amal leader Nabih Berri, who is also
Lebanon's Water Resources Minister; Sheik Subhi Tofeili, a senior
Hezbollah cleric; and Hussein Musavi, the organization's top
security chief.
   Berri blamed Hezbollah for starting the fighting. Hezbollah
accused Amal of preventing fundamentalist guerrillas from attacking
Israel from south Lebanon.
   Amal opposes raids on Israel on the grounds it provokes
reprisals against the predominantly Shiite south.
   Sheik Mohammad Mahdi Shamsheddin, the senior Shiite religious
leader in Lebanon, also arrived in Damascus seeking to negotiate an
end to the bloodshed.
   As darkness fell, the fighting centered around two other
villages seized by Hezbollah, Kfar Milki and Kfar Kila, about five
miles northeast of Sidon, provincial capital of south Lebanon.
   Reporters who reached Kfar Hatta said virtually every house in
the village of 2,000 people had been damaged by shells and gunfire.
Broken power cables dangled on burned-out cars.
   Amal's military commander in Kfar Hatta, Mashour Ghossein, told
reporters: ``We'll stop fighting only when we regain every inch of
territory seized by Hezbollah.''
   The disputed villages sit atop a chain of strategic hills that
control the main supply routes to Hezbollah's strongholds further
south in Jbaa, Ein Bouswar and Jarjou.
   These Shiite-populated towns have long been used by Hezbollah
guerrillas for attacks on the Israeli-backed South Lebanon Army
militia in south Lebanon.
</TEXT>

</DOC>