<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1215EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Czechoslovakia 5thLd-Writethru a0510 12-29 0801</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Czechoslovakia, 5th Ld - Writethru, a0510,0823</SECOND>
<HEAD>Havel Elected First Non-Communist President in 41 Years</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 2 grafs after 13th graf, ``He never ...' with Bush,
Walesa, others sending congratulations.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SYDNEY RUBIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Parliament today crowned the
nation's peaceful revolution by electing playwright and opposition
leader Vaclav Havel as Czechoslovakia's first non-Communist
president in 41 years.
   In an unprecendented public vote that was televised nationwide,
the Communist-dominated parliament, or Federal Assembly,
unanimously chose Havel, who was jailed for five years by the
previous hard-line Communist leadership for speaking out against
totalitarianism.
   ``I will not disappoint you, but will lead this country to free
elections,'' Havel told hundreds of cheering supporters from a
balcony of the presidential Hradcany Castle after his election.
   ``This must happen in a decent and peaceful way so that the
clean face of our revolution is not sullied. It is a task for us
all.''
   The election of Havel, 53, is the crowning achievement of the
popular revolt that began only 41 days ago. It comes amid
democratic reforms in Poland, Hungary, East Germany, Bulgaria and
Romania.
   Havel and his wife, Olga, then walked across the courtyard from
the castle to the St. Vitus Cathedral for a special Mass of
thanksgiving given by Czechoslovakia's 90-year-old Roman Catholic
prelate, Cardinal Frantisek Tomasek.
   At the entrance to the Gothic cathedral, several young girls
presented Havel with bouquets of white lillies.
   ``We came to St. Vitus ... to thank God for the great hope that
has opened before us in the last days of this year,'' Tomasek told
the crowd.
   The cathedral filled with Antonin Dvorak's ``Te Deum'' played by
the Prague Philharmonic and choir after the short service.
   The lawmakers' meeting was opened by Alexander Dubcek, champion
of the ``Prague Spring'' reforms crushed in 1968. He was returned
to power Thursday when parliament elected him chairman of the body.
   Dubcek and Havel are to serve until free legislative elections
are held next year.
   Havel, whose works were banned until recent weeks by the
Communists, was praised by Communist Prime Minister Marian Calfa as
``a man who is faithful to his beliefs despite persecution.''
   ``He never accepted offers from his friends or recommendations
by his enemies to emigrate where the conditions of his life would
have been more comfortable,'' Calfa told the deputies in his
nominating speech.
   President Bush was among foreign leaders today sending their
congratulations to Havel. He pledged U.S. support for the rebirth
of democracy in Czechoslovakia and the White House said his
election ``marks a fitting end to a year of astonishing change in
Eastern Europe.''
   In Warsaw, Poland, Solidarity leader Lech Walesa welcomed ``with
great joy'' Havel's election and wished him strength in carrying
out his new responsibilities.
   In a scene unimaginable only a few weeks ago, Havel walked with
Dubcek up the red carpeted aisle of the castle hall to the flourish
of a military band, the applause of Communist deputies and the
flashes of camera bulbs.
   He signed the oath of office under the draped red, white and
blue flag of Czechoslovakia.
   As the band played the national anthem, 20 cannon salvos
resounded throughout the city.
   Within the next few months, parliament is expected to pass new
laws guaranteeing freedom of expression and religion and the right
of assembly and petition. Reforms already are being carried out for
a free-market economy.
   Havel helped form the opposition group Civic Forum on Nov. 20,
three days after a police crackdown on a peaceful student protest
for democratic reforms.
   Within weeks of the creation of Civic Forum, Communists leaders
voted themselves out of power and Miroslav Stepan, considered
reponsible for the police crackdown, was under arrest facing
charges that could bring him up to 10 years in jail.
   Havel, already respected for his battle for human rights,
overnight became the most popular man in Czechoslovakia.
   ``Havel for President'' buttons appeared on lapels, and campaign
posters covered every wall in central Prague.
   He has said he would be a ``working president'' to guide the
country to democratic elections.
   After the elections, parliament will choose a new president for
a full five-year term. Havel has said he's not interested in that
job and wants to go back to writing.
   The president's duties are largely ceremonial, but the position
holds great symbolic importance, especially now.
   Dubcek endured 20 years of humiliation at the hands of hard-line
Communists who ousted him as party leader and banished him for
trying to increase freedom with the ``Prague Spring'' reforms,
which were crushed by a Soviet-led invasion.
   The ``Prague Spring'' involved economic reform and
decentralizing control. The idea was proposed nearly 20 years later
by Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev, and reform began sweeping
one country after another in Eastern Europe last fall.
</TEXT>

</DOC>