<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0225EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-FarmScene     12-28 0809</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Farm Scene,790</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ag Department Working on New Slug-Killing Chemical</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Agriculture Department scientist has
duplicated a quackgrass chemical that is deadly to slugs, those
slimy things that nibble at backyard gardens and farm crops.
   The slug-killing chemical is emitted into the soil by quackgrass
after it is killed. Thus, the department said Wednesday, when
farmers destroy quackgrass they also kill some slugs.
   ``The poison is highly specific to slugs,'' said weed scientist
Roger D. Hagin. ``It has been tested with no ill effects on three
species of freshwater snails, as well as mammals in general.''
   Hagin, who works at the agency's Plant Protection Research Unit
in Ithaca, N.Y., has successfully isolated and synthesized the
quackgrass compound. A patent on the material is in the works,
which could clear the way for commercial development of a new
lethal bait for slugs.
   Commercial poisons are available now to kill slugs, but those
also are toxic to birds and animals, he said. The quackgrass
treatment could be applied at much lower rates and at less cost.
   Hagin field-tested the compound for two years in snapbeans,
alfalfa and other crops. He said the snapbean yields were nearly
doubled as a result of reduced slug damage.
   Quackgrass is widespread and competes strongly for fertilizer
and water in crops such as corn, soybeans and forages, Hagin said.
   ``Most of the crops that grow in temperate regions have problems
with quackgrass,'' he said. ``Cattle will graze it fairly well, but
there are other things you'd rather have them eat.''
   Slugs are especially troublesome in humid areas and have taken a
heavy toll of West Coast strawberry fields and citrus orchards.
Hagin said they also interfere with corn production on the East
Coast.
   Further, slugs are a serious problem in no-till or
minimum-tillage farming, where the soil is not cultivated heavily.
   ``We're currently looking at the possibility of using the slug
poison compound as a seed treatment in minimum-tillage
situations,'' Hagin said. ``We might be able to get the crop plants
to take this material up as a defense against slug attacks.''
   Hagin accidentally discovered the quackgrass connection in 1981
after he had used herbicides to get rid of weeds before he planted
no-till corn on land where red clover had been raised.
   ``When the corn was about six inches tall, I noticed that slugs
were attacking it heavily,'' he said. ``But there were little
islands in the field where quackgrass had been growing with the
clover, and in those areas the slugs weren't attacking the corn at
all.''
   Quackgrass is known to leave two ``allelopathic'' chemical
compounds behind in the soil that inhibit the growth of certain
other plants. But those are different from the compound that kills
the slugs, Hagin said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Snow cover helped protect winter wheat from
the arctic blasts that ripped across the Great Plains into the
fruit and vegetable areas of Florida and Texas, says the
government's Joint Agricultural Weather Facility.
   ``Cold temperatures and lack of moisture stressed winter wheat
in Oklahoma and Texas,'' the facility said Wednesday in its report.
``The extent of the freeze damage was still unknown.''
   The report covered the week of Dec. 18-24 and noted that ``a
brutal blast of arctic air'' tumbled temperatures to record lows in
many areas.
   Below-normal readings in major citrus and vegetable areas of
Florida and Texas caused widespread damage, although losses have
not been fully determined, the report said.
   The facility is operated jointly by the departments of
Agriculture and Commerce. Weekly reports cover general crop
conditions but do not include production forecasts.
   Besides destroying undetermined quantities of citrus and
vegetables, the sub-normal readings slowed the peanut harvest in
south Texas, although 97 percent had been completed by the end of
the week.
   ``In the Rio Grande Valley, freeze damage to sugar cane was
expected to be light to moderate,'' the report said. ``In Florida,
sugar cane suffered some freeze damage but the extent was unknown.
In Louisiana, sugar cane harvest was slowed by cold temperatures.''
   The severe cold put stress on cattle and other livestock
throughout the Great Plains, Corn Belt, Delta and the Southeast,
the report said.
 
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Belgium may develop as a potential market for
U.S. frozen yogurt exporters, says an Agriculture Department report.
   John M. Beshoar, U.S. agricultural counselor in Brussels, said
Belgian consumers are ``beginning to develop a taste'' for yogurt.
One company introduced the frozen product in early 1989 with four
flavors: exotic fruits, strawberry, raspberry and vanilla.
   ``Because many consumers are unfamiliar with the new dessert,
the company is developing a new product _ a mixture of ice cream
and yogurt _ to encourage more consumers to try it,'' he said. ``If
this product is successful, it could pave the way for similar
frozen dairy treats.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>