<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0246 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0506EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-SPE--Bride&amp;Groom:Showers     12-18 0320</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-SPE--Bride &amp; Groom: Showers,0325</SECOND>
<HEAD>SPECIAL EDITION</HEAD>
<HEAD>Bride &amp; Groom: Showers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   No bridal couple really needs to start out with a lifetime
supply of salt and pepper shakers but no coffeemaker. So if you`re
giving shower or wedding gifts, make use of bridal registries to
avoid duplicates or wrong patterns. Or personalize your gifts.
   Bridal registries at local stores are recommended by Jacqueline
Greenwood, Black &amp; Decker's bridal program manager. ``Listed here
are gifts the bride has indicated she wants and needs. One can't go
wrong giving a gift from this list,'' she says. ``Make sure to
purchase it at the store where the registry is, so that it will be
crossed off and no one will duplicate the gift.''
   But if getting a gift idea from the registry seems too
impersonal and routine, go ahead and make a creative, personal
choice, she says. And giving a personal gift to the bride, instead
of a household item, is appropriate if you're a friend of the
bride. ``Roommates in college? Get a college memento _ perhaps a
framed photograph or painting of the campus,'' she suggests.
   Greenwood advises thinking first of items that are in nearly any
household but perhaps not owned by someone just setting up
housekeeping. For example, if you choose a spice rack, fill it up
with a variety of spices to start with.
   Appliances are among the most common gifts, and irons,
coffeemakers or blenders will be among those needed. A personal
touch suggested by Greenwood is to pair a corn popper with
membership in the local video rental store.
   She cautions that the giver should think small, choosing compact
versions of kitchen appliances, since the couple's first home
likely will be compact.
   And if you're giving a shower party, pick a theme that will help
organize the gift choices _ such as something for every room in the
house or apartment.
</TEXT>

</DOC>