<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0209 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1130EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-Inflation 3rdLd-Writethru   12-19 0844</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Inflation, 3rd Ld-Writethru,0867</SECOND>
<HEAD>Consumer Prices Rise 0.4 Percent in November</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 2 grafs after 5th pvs, bgng: However the, with market
reaction, separate report on real earnings</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVE SKIDMORE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Consumer prices rose a moderate 0.4 percent in
November as higher food and heating costs more than offset cheaper
gasoline, the government said today.
   The seasonally adjusted increase in the Labor Department's
Consumer Price Index, which translated into an annual inflation
rate of 4.9 percent, followed a brisk 0.5 percent rise in October
and relatively modest hikes from June through September.
   The price spurt was slightly higher than many analysts had been
expecting. The government blamed the rise on a jump in natural gas
and electricity costs and an increase in prices at supermarket
checkout counters for beef, eggs, fresh vegetables and dairy
products.
   Through the first 11 months of this year, consumer prices have
risen at an annual rate of 4.6 percent, up only slightly from the
4.4 percent price gains in both 1988 and 1987.
   However, the year-to-date figure masks a roller-coaster ride
that saw prices rising at a 6.7 percent annual rate for the first
five months of the year, moderating through the summer and then
returning to about average for the past two months.
   The November inflation number, a notch above the 0.3 percent
rise anticipated by many analysts, dampened hopes in financial
markets that the Federal Reserve Board would lower interest rates
this week. The Dow Jones average of 30 industrials slipped 1.50 to
2,696.03 in the first half hour of trading.
   Meanwhile, the Labor Department said in a separate report that
Americans' average weekly earnings, after adjusting for inflation,
fell 0.7 percent last month following a 0.6 percent rise in October.
   In another economic report, the Commerce Department said housing
starts fell 4.7 percent in November, reversing a 13 percent jump a
month earlier. New homes and apartments were built at a seasonally
adjusted annual rate of 1.36 million units last month, down from a
revised 1.43 million units in October.
   Leading the November advance in consumer inflation was a 0.6
percent boost in food prices, the steepest since May. Dairy
products jumped 1.7 percent, the third consecutive sharp increase.
The price of fruits and vegetables soared 1.8 percent, the second
big gain in a row.
   Economists are attributing the dairy price hikes to last year's
drought, which caused many farmers to slaughter milk cows.
   Gasoline prices fell 2.1 percent in November following a 0.9
percent rise in October. However, other forms of energy were more
expensive. The index for natural gas and electricity rose 1.5
percent, while fuel oil edged up 0.2 percent following a big 2.5
percent gain a month earlier.
   Overall, energy prices fell 0.1 percent last month. Prices
excluding the volatile food and energy sectors, a measure
considered a better gauge of underlying inflationary pressures,
were up 0.4 percent following a 0.5 percent gain in October.
   The cost of medical care, which has been increasing at an 8.5
percent rate over the past year, was up 0.8 percent in November, in
line with previous increases.
   Clothing costs edged up 0.1 percent in November, following two
months of steep increases that coincided with the introduction of
fall lines.
   In other areas, new-car prices rose 0.8 percent, tobacco was
down 0.1 percent and entertainment costs climbed 0.2 percent.
   Before taking into account normal seasonal changes, the Consumer
Price Index stood at 125.9 in November. That meant that a
hypothetical selection of goods and services costing $100 in the
1982-84 base period would have cost $125.90 last month, up from
$120.30 a year ago.
   The Bush administration is predicting an improvement in consumer
inflation next year to the 4.1 percent range, not far below the
projections of most economists.
   However, private analysts generally don't share the
administration's optimistic belief that inflation will continue to
decline in 1991 and beyond. They predict the Federal Reserve Board,
which influences economic growth by its control of interest rates
and the money supply, won't engineer the sustained period of
sluggishness necessary to flatten wage increases.
   Analysts attribute the most recent spate of dampened price
activity in part to the central bank's year-long campaign, ended
last spring, of pushing interest rates higher. Since then, the Fed
has sought to avoid a recession by allowing rates to decline.
   ``We don't think the Fed really has the strength of will to
reach its zero inflation goal,'' said Cynthia Latta, an economist
with DRI-McGraw Hill, a Lexington, Mass., forecasting firm.
   The 5.4 percent unemployment rate in November, she said, matched
the rate at the start of the year and was not appreciably above the
15-year low of 5 percent, reached in March.
   ``Services are 55 percent of the (consumer index) ... and I
don't think there's been very much easing in the labor market,''
she said. ``The pressure is still toward larger wage increases.''
   Last week, the Labor Department said its index for wholesale
prices, which does not include services, declined by 0.1 percent in
November.
</TEXT>

</DOC>