<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0183 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1531EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s w BC-WeeklyFarm Adv24   12-19 0839</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Weekly Farm, Adv 24,0860</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv24</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 24, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Bloated USDA Office Network Needs Trimming, Says GAO Report</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Some day, some year, Congress may get serious
about trimming the sprawling network of offices maintained by the
Agriculture Department that reaches into virtually all of the
nation's 3,150 counties.
   Various administrations and USDA analysts have been saying for
44 years that a remodeling is long overdue. The General Accounting
Office says it's time for another try.
   ``Most senior USDA officials we spoke with, and many studies
over time, recognize the need to streamline USDA, particularly its
field structure,'' says the GAO, the investigative arm of Congress.
   But the GAO, which is still studying how to make the department
leaner and more effective, says grassroots ties with Congress and
specific USDA agencies have ``kept the department from adjusting to
changes'' in the real world.
   The structure of USDA is formidable. There are 36 agencies in
the department that carry out policies and programs. In 1988, for
example, USDA spent more than $44 billion and employed more than
110,000 full-time people in more than 15,000 places around the
world. In addition, finances funds more than 17,000 county office
employees.
   ``Despite dramatic changes in the agribusiness sector, USDA's
basic organizational structure has changed ittle,'' the GAO said in
a recent interim report to Agriculture Secretary Clayton Yeutter.
``Its agencies are tradition bound and highly resistant to change.''
   The department ``still maintains a multibillion-dollar,
1930s-designed field delivery structure, although today's farmers
are far fewer in number and operate in a global agribusiness
environment,'' it said.
   A final report by GAO is in the works and will include specific
recommendations for improving operations.
   But inefficiencies of USDA's huge administrative apparatus are
hardly news. Each year Congress has the opportunity in the
appropriations process to review costs and how they are handled.
Each year Congress hears grumbles from one group or another about
USDA bumbling in the administration of various programs.
   Additionally, as Congress is doing now, it can modify or design
new programs during the development of farm legislation. The 1985
law, for example, expires next year and lawmakers are trying to put
together a new package.
   What it boils down to, in many cases, is the fear of many rural
communities _ usually county seats _ that they may lose their USDA
offices, sometimes the biggest job source in town.
   ``Most of USDA's farm service agencies were established during
the 1930s in response to the Great Depression,'' the GAO report
said. ``In that era, communication and transportation systems
limited the geographic boundaries covered by any single field
office.''
   Because of these and other reasons, USDA established a highly
decentralized field office system to serve the large number of
small, widely dispersed, family owned farms. From 1932 to 1948,
USDA employment grew from 22,000 to 79,000.
   The GAO review included a look at a number of department
agencies, including the Agricultural Stabilization and Conservation
Service (ASCS), Farmers Home Administration (FmHA), Soil
Conservation Service (SCS) and Extension Service (ES).
   According to the review, the ASCS and SCS maintain offices in
about 85 percent of the nation's 3,150 counties; the FmHA has
offices in more than 60 percent; and the ES has them in nearly all
of the counties.
   In all, the four agencies operate approximately 10,600 county
offices. Additionally, the Federal Crop Insurance Corp. operates
through a network of government office and private insurance agents
who are ``often located close to or with one or more'' of existing
USDA field offices, the report said.
   Although GAO found many senior department officials agreeing on
the need for streamlining the delivery system for farm programs,
most thought it too difficult politically.
   ``For example, two officials, who believed the current structure
was costly and ineffective and needed to be changed, also believed
such change would be politically unpalatable and too disruptive,''
the report said.
   As early as 1945, proposals were made to streamline USDA's field
structure, the GAO said. And there have been eight major studies
the past 20 years.
   Of the various kinds of streamlining, GAO found ``collocation''
of offices under one roof _ which leaves the structure generally
intact _ to be the most successful.
   ``Collocating offices often reduces program delivery costs
through sharing equipment, technical expertise and tasks,'' the
report said. ``Program recipients also benefit by being able to
transact all their USDA business in one location.''
   In a 1985 study, the department found that ASCS, SCS, FmHA and
ES were totally collocated in 1982 in 476 counties. Not counting
ES, the agencies were collocated in 1,438 counties.
   ``However, the report stated that from 1982 to 1985, collocated
offices were separating more frequently than offices were
collocating, and that collocation did not necessarily lead to
increased cooperation among the agencies,'' the GAO said.
   Moreover, it said, USDA ``no longer tracks collocations in the
detail needed for management to determine the extent to which
counties are collocated.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, Dec. 24</NOTE>

</DOC>