<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0107 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1403EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-SinkingShip 5thLd-Writethru a0553 12-29 0378</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Sinking Ship, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0553,0384</SECOND>
<HEAD>600-foot Vessel Sinking 800 Miles from Hawaii</HEAD>
<UNK>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to UPDATE with crew working to save ship,
additional detail. Picks up 5th graf, `Anderson said....'</UNK>
<DATELINE>HONOLULU (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Chevron tanker pulled alongside a sinking
freighter today that 28 crewmen were fighting to keep afloat in the
North Pacific.
   The tanker delivered additional pumps to reverse the flow of
water into two of the Bulka's cargo holds and stood by 800 miles
northeast of Oahu to rescue the 600-foot scrap-metal carrier's crew
if necessary, Coast Guard spokesman Keith Spangler said.
   Spangler said the Greek officers and Philippine crew were out of
danger unless the ship sank rapidly.
   ``It seems to us they still have a chance to save the ship,''
Spangler said. ``It's just a wait-and-see game to see if the pumps
will do it.''
   One of the cargo holds was flooded and a second was filling
rapidly, said Air Force Sgt. Neil Anderson of the Joint Rescue
Coordination Center in Honolulu. The cause of the leak was unknown.
   ``The vessel is bowed down and listing slighting toward
starboard,'' Anderson said. ``As it lists more as it fills up the
crew probably will have to abandon ship.''
   Spangler said the ship was listing 6 degrees to starboard and
was down 15 feet at its bow.
   Anderson said the vessel was owned by a Greek shipping company
based in Athens, Bacolitsas and Sons, but did not know if the ship
was registered there. He said the ship was bound for either North
or South Korea and was carrying scrap metal, but didn't know the
tonnage.
   The tanker Chevron Colorado was diverted to the foundering
vessel and passed three pumps to the Bulka this morning, Hubbard
said. The Coast Guard cutter Sassafras was expected to reach the
area Saturday.
   The crew, equipped with life vests and life rafts, was prepared
to abandon ship if the pumping failed, Hubbard said.
   Winds in the area were 10 to 15 mph and seas were running about
six feet, according to Roy Matsuda, marine forecaster at the
National Weather Service office in Honolulu.
   A Coast Guard C-130 search and rescue airplane was on the scene
and in radio contact with the Bulka, Hubbard said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>