<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0739EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Panama-Hostages     12-20 0605</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Hostages,0636</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hotel Guests Told, `We Can Kill You. Don't Think We Won't'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Candice Hughes, an AP correspondent based in
Mexico City, had just checked into the Marriott Hotel when the
fighting began. Here is her account of how she and other foreigners
were held hostage by armed Panamanians.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>___</NOTE>
<NOTE>By CANDICE HUGHES</NOTE>
<NOTE>Associated Press Writer</NOTE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The fighting had just broken out in Panama
City when a group of men dressed in civilian clothes and armed with
assault rifles surrounded the Marriott Hotel and began rounding up
guests.
   For the next 4{ hours, the men held us hostage, told us about
their comrades who had already fallen in the battle and threatened
to kill us.
   ``A lot of Panamanians have died, and we can kill you,'' one of
them told New York Times correspondent Lindsey Gruson. ``Don't
think we won't.''
   I had just checked into the hotel and come down to the sunken
terrace when I saw armed men running in a crouched position by the
swimming pool. Right about the same time I heard gunfire.
   It was about midnight, and the U.S. assault had started.
   I made for the hotel's main building with several other
reporters when a man with an assault rifle appeared and said, `Hit
the floor.'
   He herded us over into the lobby, which was full of people.
   The gunmen took peoples' passports, they searched my bag.
   About a dozen of the men took charge of me and 11 other
foreigners, including two other correspondents.
   I never saw more than 20 armed men in the hotel.
   They told us they had surrounded the building. `We're being
invaded, so we're taking hostages,' the man who appeared to be
their leader said.
   They did not threaten me personally, but they made it clear that
they could kill us all. There were about eight Americans in our
group.
   Gruson and I tried to persuade the men to let us call our
offices to tell the story of the invasion.
   We saw them herding the guests and staff into the grand
ballroom. A man in a silk bathrobe kept saying to the captors,
``I'm Chilean! I'm Chilean!''
   The armed men eventually let me retrieve my bag and notebook _
my money had been taken _ and they let me remain in the lobby.
   Gruson went upstairs where he said he was threatened by one of
the gunmen, who kept pointing his assault rifle at him. At one
point, the gunman put the muzzle of his weapon against Gruson's
mouth, he told me later.
   About 1:45 a.m., a few other hostages and I were herded into a
red van at gunpoint and driven to a private home in the wealthy
neighborhood where the Panmanian leader, Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noriega, lives. We were ordered into the service area off the
kitchen and made to sit on the floor.
   Our captors let us have water and smoke cigarettes.
   We were there until 4 a.m. I kept hearing aircraft passing low
overhead, sporadic gunfire from automatic weapons. Things were
tapering off.
   Between 3:30 a.m. and 4 a.m., the phone rang three times.
   More hostage-takers showed up. Then a man who appeared to be
their leader said, ``We're going to let you go. We don't want to
kill you. Tell the truth about Panama. We're not killers.''
   ``There are hundreds of dead in the Central Barracks.''
   The men seemed very sad. One was crying.
   They put us back into a van and let us out in the street. I
raced to a private home and called the AP office.
</TEXT>

</DOC>