<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0098 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1449EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Flight103-Suspect     12-21 0600</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Flight 103-Suspect,0618</SECOND>
<HEAD>Flight 103 Suspect Convicted on Separate Terrorism Charges</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Flight 103, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EVA JANZON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>UPPSALA, Sweden (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Palestinian suspected in the bombing of
Pan Am Flight 103 was convicted Thursday in a series of terrorist
attacks in northern Europe four years ago, along with three
co-defendants.
   The Palestinian, Mohammed Abu Talb, was sentenced to life in
prison, which in Sweden generally means 20 years at most behind
bars. He is expected to be expelled after serving his time, the
court said.
   The verdicts were delivered on the first anniversary of the
bombing of Flight 103 over Lockerbie, Scotland, which killed 270
people.
   A Swedish newspaper Thursday said new evidence had surfaced
linking Abu Talb to the attack, including a calendar found in his
apartment with the date Dec. 21 circled.
   Abu Talb, a 35-year-old former bodyguard in the radical
Palestine Popular Struggle Front, and co-defendant Marten Imandi
received life sentences for bombing the Northwest Orient airlines
office in Copenhagen in 1985. One person was killed and more than
20 were wounded.
   Two brothers, Mahmoud and Moustafa Al Mougrabi, were given
sentences of six years and one year respectively for their
involvement in three attacks in Copenhagen and Amsterdam.
   All the defendants were acquitted in a fourth incident in
Stockholm in 1986. The case was decided by a judicial panel.
   ``The type of crime ... is extremely serious. It is directed
against the lives and property of innocent people. Society must
react very strongly against such crimes,'' said the court in its
100-page decision.
   Abu Talb's attorney said he would appeal the conviction, which
was based largely on the testimony of Mahmoud Al Mougrabi.
   In addition to the Northwest Orient office, the men were
convicted in bombings at a Cophenhagen synagogue, where seven
people were hurt, and the offices of El Al Israel airlines in the
Danish capital and in Amsterdam. No one was injured in those
explosions.
   Abu Talb was arrested in May in connection with the attacks. He
came under suspicion in the Lockerbie case after Swedish
investigators established he had been in Malta about the time the
Lockerbie bomb may have been prepared. The altitude-sensitive bomb
apparently was hidden in a radio-cassette recorder, which was
placed in a suitcase and wrapped in clothing bought in Malta.
   Abu Talb's lawyer, Sven-Erik Sjogren, repeated his client's
denial that he was involved in the Flight 103 incident and said his
trip to Malta was for business.
   Last month, police seized clothing from Abu Talb's home in
Uppsala, about 40 miles north of Stockholm, to compare it with
shreds found in Lockerbie and with clothing from a boutique in
Malta.
   Sjogren has challenged the legality of the raid, but he said he
understood the clothing already had been flown to Malta for
analysis.
   A Swedish newspaper, Dagens Nyheter, reported Thursday that
Scottish detectives were disappointed with the results of the
examination in Malta.
   Dagens Nyheter said further evidence has surfaced linking Abu
Talb with Lockerbie. Police found a 1988 calendar with the date
Dec. 21 circled, it said.
   After the police raid, Abu Talb's wife also was recorded in a
wiretapped telephone call warning another Palestinian, who was not
identified, to ``get rid of the clothes immediately,'' the paper
said. Police later seized a suitcase from the family she called,
the paper added.
   Abu Talb came to Sweden from Syria with his wife and child on a
false Moroccan passport under the name of Belaid Massoud Ben Hadi.
He settled in Uppsala and ran a store specializing in Arabic foods
and videotapes.
</TEXT>

</DOC>