<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0028EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Windsors'Mansion     12-27 0784</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Windsors' Mansion,0802</SECOND>
<HEAD>Villa of Duke and Duchess of Windsor Reopens in France</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Wednesday AMs report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUZY PATTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Edward VIII gave up his throne to marry Wallis
Simpson 53 years ago, but the romantic Windsor legend has come
alive again at their mansion in the Bois de Boulogne.
   In early December the wrought-iron gates of the final and
favorite residence of the duke and duchess of Windsor were thrown
open for a high tea given by Mohammed Al Fayed, the Egyptian tycoon
who paid more than $8 million to renovate the mansion.
   The owner of the Hotel Ritz in Paris and the Harrods department
store in London, Al Fayed plans to keep the mansion open for
friends and approved groups of visitors.
   ``Theirs was the love story of the century,'' Al Fayed said of
the Windsors. He undertook renovation with the blessing of Mayor
Jacques Chirac and the City of Paris, which is still the official
owner of the villa.
   Al Fayed said he had been shocked to see the dilapidated
condition of the villa when he visited after the duchess's death in
1986, with moldy walls and tags on the furniture and art objects
destined for the auction block.
   ``It was a sight I know would have appalled the duke and
duchess,'' he said, having seen the villa in its heyday at a dinner
party given by the duchess, the American socialite divorcee whom
the duke had married in defiance of the royal family.
   So Al Fayed took things in hand. Supervised by an Anglo-American
team of decorators, the leaky roof was repaired, the interior was
given a coat of paint, tapestries and woodwork were restored.
   Personal valuables were left in place, including framed intimate
letters and photographs and silver and crystal on the dining-room
table as if the Windsors were expecting guests. Countless porcelain
pug dogs around the house commemorate the Windsors' family pets who
always were given pride of place.
   ``I feel on top of the world,'' said Sydney Johnson, 69, the
duke's personal valet for more than 30 years, who is now
occasionally in attendance dressed splendidly in gold and red
livery as he was in the old days.
   ``I cried all through the party Mr. Al Fayed gave three years
ago to celebrate his lease on the house,'' said Johnson, a Bahamian
who was hired during World II when the duke was the governor of the
Bahamas. ``The restoration is so authentic I expect to see the
duchess stepping down the staircase asking, `How do I look?'''
   Also on hand are the Windsors' chauffeur of 20 years, Gregoire
Martin, and his wife, Maria. Martin said he had hidden 5,000
personal photographs in a bathroom to keep them from prying eyes
during the duchess's 14-year widowhood following the duke's death
in 1972.
   The house looks as if the Windsors just stepped out for a stroll
in the Bois; books are at the bedsides, brushes and combs are in
the bathrooms and some of the duchess's lingerie are tidily wrapped
in tissue in her dressing room.
   The duke's bed has its original velvet cover with his Prince of
Wales insignia and motto, ``Honi soit qui Mal y Pense,'' which
translates, roughly, as ``Shame on him who thinks evil of it.''
   By his bedside sprawls a touching little chimney-sweep rag doll
cherished by the duke, given to him by his mother, Queen Mary, who
publicly disowned him after his indiscreet marriage.
   The duchess's bedroom is a symphony of ``Wallis blue'' and cream
moire silk, with attractive imitation Louis XV and XVI furnishings
and a priceless Venetian l8th century marquetry chest. Visitors
also see a raft of stuffed pug dog dolls and framed needlepoint
works by the duke, who loved needlepoint almost as much as golf,
commemorated in souvenir golf balls all over the place.
   The duchess's bathroom is an artwork in itself, decorated by
Dimitri Bouchene, a Russian artist who designed stage sets for
Diaghilev and Pavlova.
   Under a Napoleonic-style striped silk tent ceiling, the bathroom
walls are covered with Bouchene's floral and animal murals, with a
group of his Christmas cards framed in glass lining the doors like
a gallery exhibition.
   One of the villa's first visitors was the British-born actress
Joan Collins, who asked Al Fayed if he planned to use the house for
his own parties.
   ``I will indeed,'' he said, adding that he plans to keep the
mansion staffed and open to small group visits by special request.
   In 1991, he said, he will send an exhibition of mementoes to
London and other British cities, as well as to New York and to the
duchess's birthplace, Baltimore.
</TEXT>

</DOC>