<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0143 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1743EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Pantex     12-18 0349</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pantex,350</SECOND>
<HEAD>Advisory Committee Finds Radiation Safety Procedures Lacking</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JENNIFER DIXON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Pantex nuclear weapons assembly plant in
Texas appeared to have no plan to handle May's accidental release
of radioactive gas, according to an advisory committee report to
Energy Secretary James D. Watkins released Monday.
   ``It is still unclear that effective control of the situation by
an adequately prepared response team ever took place,'' John F.
Ahearne, chairman of the Advisory Committee on Nuclear Facility
Safety, said in a letter to Watkins.
   The letter also raised questions about safety and environmental
practices at Pantex, the nation's only final assembly plant for
nuclear bombs and missile warheads.
   The committee said the response to the May release of tritium, a
radioactive gas, was of ``variable quality.''
   Radiation specialists and technicians responded properly to
minimize workers' exposure at the plant outside Amarillo, but
``missing was recognition that this `unlikely event' could take
place, and thus adequate procedures, instrumentation, and training
were lacking,'' the committee said.
   Although a quick and effective evacuation was conducted,
thereafter, ``events are marked by confusion, misread instruments,
and uncertain actions. There appeared to be no plan to handle what
surely must be an anticipated accident.''
   Exposure to workers was below federal guidelines limiting
radiation explosure and ``off-site exposure was trivial.''
   A team of government and outside experts recently inspected the
plant and found Pantex would be unable to respond effectively to
emergencies involving releases of radioactive material.
   Watkins said those findings indicate workers lack adequate
protection from emergency and rountine exposures to radioactive
releases and that the situation must be corrected immediately.
   Pantex spokesman Tom Walton said the plant had begun correcting
problems, or ``will be addressing those in the very near future.''
Some safety violations were corrected immediately, he said.
   ``We of course are already looking at those things they've
identified and in areas that we need to improve, obviously, we're
going to make improvements,'' Walton said.
   Occupational Safety and Health Administration investigators, who
also inspected the plant, found more than 300 safety violations,
dozens of them serious.
</TEXT>

</DOC>