<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0287 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1848EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-GreatNorthern 1stLd-Writethru   12-22 0426</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Great Northern, 1st Ld-Writethru,0439</SECOND>
<HEAD>Court Rules Against Georgia-Pacific in Takeover Battle</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: EDITS throughout to UPDATE with comment, tighten; No pickup</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DIRK BEVERIDGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal judge Friday rejected a request
by Georgia-Pacific Corp. to move up a meeting of Great Northern
Nekoosa Corp. shareholders to consider a $3.8 billion takeover
offer.
   U.S. District Judge Gene Carter said he did not want to cut off
debate prematurely in the merger battle and rejected
Georgia-Pacific's motion for a temporary restraining order and
preliminary injunction.
   ``This discussion is of great concern to the public, and the
public's interest as well as that of the shareholders is served by
letting the discussion mature,'' Carter said.
   ``... harm may accrue to Great Northern and the public if the
deal is rushed to completion and it is then determined that the
newly formed corporation is in violation of the antitrust laws,''
the judge said.
   Atlanta-based Georgia-Pacific asked Carter on Thursday to move
the Great Northern shareholders meeting from March 20 to within 30
days, saying it wants shareholders to have a quick say in the rival
paper maker's merger offer.
   Georgia-Pacific also sought to force Norwalk, Conn.-based Great
Northern to provide it and the court with 72 hours notice of any
financial restructuring that could make the $63-a-share tender
offer less attractive.
   Great Northern already has agreed to provide Georgia-Pacific
with information on any changes it makes, and Georgia-Pacific could
challenge any changes if it thinks they are improper, Carter's
ruling said.
   Georgia-Pacific on Friday extended its offer through Jan. 5 and
said 73 percent of Great Northern's shares had been tendered. It
said it was disappointed with the ruling.
   Great Northern spokesman Stephen Hill called ruling
``wonderful.''
   Carter has not yet ruled on another Georgia-Pacific motion
seeking to set aside part of the ``poison pill'' provisions in
Great Northern's bylaws intended to thwart a hostile takeover.
   Hill said the deal would violate antitrust laws, an issue to be
decided in a federal trial scheduled to begin Wednesday in
Bridgeport, Conn., in a lawsuit brought by Great Northern.
   The ruling Friday came in motions filed in a separate lawsuit
challenging Great Northern's poison pill and Maine's antitakeover
law.
   The Federal Trade Commission in Washington had faced a Thursday
deadline for deciding whether it believed the proposed merger would
run afoul of antitrust laws, but an FTC spokeswoman said no
announcement was planned.
   Georgia-Pacific said the deadline passed without any action by
the FTC, ``satisfying one of the material conditions to
Georgia-Pacific's offer.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>