<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0207 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1927EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Panama-Miami 1stLd-Writethru a0785 12-20 0745</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Miami, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0785,0763</SECOND>
<HEAD>Noriega's Lawyers: General Will Die Before Allowing Capture</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 8 grafs after 9th, ``The general ..., to UPDATE with
Takiff comment on declaration of war, Rubino comment on drug charges; picks
up 10th graf, `A trial ...</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL WARREN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. officials made plans Wednesday for the
possible extradition of embattled Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega in
the event he is captured, but his attorneys said he would rather
die than surrender.
   Noriega would be flown to a military base in south Florida and
transferred to a secure location to await trial in Miami on federal
drug charges, said a U.S. Marshals Service official who spoke on
condition of anonymity.
   But his attorneys said Noriega, who was in hiding Wednesday as
more than 20,000 U.S. troops stormed through Panama, may never be
captured.
   ``He's a fighter,'' said Miami attorney Raymond Takiff, who said
he talked with his client Monday evening and remained in contact
with the general's aides Wednesday. ``I feel unhappily secure in my
belief that he will be killed, he will not be captured. Should that
occur, the truth will never come out.''
   The Justice Department and the Marshals Service refused to
release details about Noriega's possible extradition or where he
would be detained, citing security concerns.
   ``If General Noriega is apprehended and brought here for trial,
he would be given the same treatment as any other person accused of
a crime _ no more, no less. All his rights will be protected,''
said U.S. District Judge William M. Hoeveler, the trial judge in
the Miami indictment.
   Noriega and 16 associates face federal drug-trafficking
indictments returned by grand juries in Miami and Tampa in 1988. He
would be tried first on the Miami charges, Justice Department
spokesman David Runkel said.
   Another Noriega attorney, Frank Rubino, echoed the sentiment
that the general would never allow U.S. forces to take him alive.
   ``The general is alive, well and somewhere in Panama, and he is
on top of the situation, as far as leading his forces,'' said
Rubino, who predicted the presence of U.S. troops would lead to
more bloodshed.
   President Bush cited Noriega's declaration Friday of a state of
war as a reason for the invasion, but Takiff vehemently denied the
general ever declared war on the United States.
   Noriega's U.S. attorneys had agreed to publicly resign if he
declared war, and closely examined a copy of the text in which he
apparently made the declaration, Takiff said.
   ``What was said by Noriega and by the national assembly was that
because of events, the country was living as if they were in a
state of war,'' he said. ``We were satisfied that he had never
declared war on the United States.''
   ``No one, no matter how strained the context, could consider
that a declaration of war,'' said Takiff, acknowledging that he did
not know if Noriega had departed from his prepared text in his
speech to the assembly.
   Rubino said the drug charges against Noriega were politically
motivated.
   ``Before the United States used the CIA in a covert way to
topple governments. Now they are using indictment diplomacy,''
Rubino said.
   Former U.S. Attorney Robert Merkle, who brought the Tampa
indictment against Noriega and now practices law in Clearwater,
said the military dictator is just another criminal.
   ``The indictments were not instigated by the State Department
and they were not brought for any political purpose whatsoever,''
Merkle said. ``All this yammering about indictment for political
purposes is pure hogwash.''
   A trial is scheduled Jan. 8 in Miami for two of Noriega's
co-defendants, but prosecutors had requested a continuance before
Wednesday's actions because they need more time to prepare their
case.
   ``The government will come to court with strong evidence against
General Noriega,'' said Richard Gregorie, the former chief
assistant U.S. attorney who presented the Miami indictment to a
grand jury in February 1988.
   In the two indictments, Noriega is charged with accepting $10
million in bribes from Medellin Cartel drug traffickers to protect
smugglers and cocaine shipments, launder cash and supply drug
laboratories. He faces up to 145 years in prison and more than $1.1
million in fines if convicted.
   ``If Noriega's not rounded up soon, he could probably go to Cuba
or Nicaragua, or he could start up a guerrilla movement with all
the arms he has stashed away,'' said Luis Endara, a cousin of
Panama's new president, Guillermo Endara.
</TEXT>

</DOC>