<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0093 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1049EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-PentagonText 5thAdd   12-20 0739</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Pentagon Text, 5th Add,740</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON: protect them?</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Cheney: Well, I think a key part of the plan that Gen. Powell
may want to address was to wrap up the PDF as quickly as possible,
if you will, and to provide security for the Americans living in
the area. We reached the judgment that, in the long run, Americans
were going to be more secure, that their safety was likely to be
greater, the risk likely to be reduced if we acted now rather than
if we waited and let the situation continue to spiral out of
control.
   Q: Mr. Cheney ... do you think there will be additional
casualties as the mopping up continues?
   Cheney: I don't have any way to know that. I don't have any way
to know.
   Q: What are the last pockets of resistance? Can you run over
that, Colin, and tell us?
   Powell: Oh, there is a little bit at the Comandancia, just some
sniping coming out, and we still have a slight problem down on Fort
Amador area with the 5th Infantry company. But that's pretty much
it. There's a little bit of firing out by the Pacora River Bridge,
but it's really not ...
   Q: The MO has basically been for resistance, and then they sort
of break up and fade off into the neighborhoods? Is that ...
   Powell: That's what we have seen.
   Q: How do you deal with that, in the days or hours ahead here,
if you have a lot of armed people who at least formerly were
pro-Noriega.
   Powell: What we have to find out is whether or not they are an
armed resistance force or just individuals who now are just
criminals and thugs running around the countryside. We'll just have
to wait and see how it plays out.
   Q: Do you have large numbers of PDF now willing to work with
you? Have you begun the liaison?
   Powell: We'll still sorting out the pieces. We have a fairly
significant number of detainees, I'll call them for the moment, and
we'll sort that over time _ sort that out over time. You've just
got to bear with us. We're only a few hours into this.
   Q: Gen. Powell, you've said several times that Noriega, Mr.
Noriega personally is a fugitive. Yet Panamanian broadcasts suggest
that he's still running the show militarily. What have you got to
indicate that he is in fact a fugitive on the run?
   Powell: Because he is a fugitive. We're looking for him. He's
not running anything, because we own all of the bases he owned
eight hours ago.
   Q: How convinced are you that you will get Noriega, and will you
call this operation a success if you don't?
   Powell: I'm not a fortune teller as to whether we will get him,
or when we will get him. I think the operation is a success already
because we cut off the head of that government and there is a new
government that was elected by the Panamanian people, waiting,
willing and ready to take over. And I hope that's what will happen.
I hope what we will do is assist them in standing up and taking
over, and I think the people of Panama will rally to this
government.
   Q: General, would you say that the operation has lasted more
than what you expected? Did you intend it to be a more a surgical
strike, or do you think ...
   Powell: I had no set timelines in mind. I really wasn't sure. It
could have been over quickly. It could linger for days or weeks. I
just don't know, and I'd just be wildly speculating with you at
this time. I'll know better later in the day, I think.
   Q: Does that mean the operation _ the operation isn't over and
we need to get _ (inaudible)
   Q: Have we communicated with the Soviet Union, and did they
protest?
   Cheney: I'll direct you to the State Department.
   Q: Thank you all very much.
   Powell: Could I just say that I hope you recognize how
complicated an operation this was, and how competently it was
carried out by the Armed Force of the United States. We all, the
Secretary and I, all of our associates, deeply regret the loss of
American life. But that's sometimes necessary in pursuit of our
national interests and in the fight for democracy.
   Thank you.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>END</BYLINE>

</DOC>