<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1225EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-BushInterview 3rdLd-Writethru a0536 12-18 0905</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bush Interview, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0536,850</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Won't Rule Out Military Response to Panama Shooting</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Subs pvs 11th graf, ``It's an,'' with 2 grafs to update with
new White House comment on Panama; picks up pvs 12th graf, He also</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERENCE HUNT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP White House Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush today called the weekend
slaying of an American officer in Panama ``an enormous outrage''
and said he is reviewing a range of options in response. He
pointedly did not rule out military action.
   ``I think a president, all presidents, have options, but they
don't discuss what they might be,'' Bush said. He repeated the
answer when asked if military action was among the options
available.
   He said the U.S. failure to drive Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega
from power in Panama was ``an enormous frustration'' of his first
year in office.
   The president made his comments in an Oval Office interview with
reporters from The Associated Press and three other news agencies.
His remarks followed the shooting Saturday night of a U.S. military
officer who was in a car with other Americans trying to flee a
crowd of Panamanian troopers and civilians.
   Bush's voice was raspy, showing signs of the laryngitis that
forced him to cancel a speechmaking trip to New York last Friday.
   On other topics, the president:
   _Defended anew his decision to send two top aides to China to
rekindle relations for the first time since the bloody suppression
of pro-democracy demonstrators last June. He said he does not know
when Chinese dissident Fang Lizhi would be able to leave the U.S.
Embassy in Beijing, where he has taken refuge since the crackdown.
   _Said the administration is undertaking a ``massive
re-evaluation of intentions as well as military threat'' by the
Soviet bloc in light of the radical political changes sweeping
Eastern Europe.
   _Said ``as far as I'm concerned'' his 1988 campaign pledge
against new taxes still stands.
   _Shrugged off a published report that Colombian drug lords have
placed a $30 million price on his head. ``There is nothing to it,''
he said and added he was confident the Secret Service could protect
him when he attends a regional drug summit in Colombia on Feb. 15.
   The administration was quick to blame Noriega for the weekend
violence in Panama. White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater today
condemned ``a climate of aggression'' there and said Noriega seems
to have granted a ``license for harassment'' against Americans.
   In the interview, Bush said of the fatal shooting of the
American officer: ``It's an enormous outrage and a matter of
enormous concern to this president.''
   He also defended his decision to send the high-level delegation
to China 10 days ago, even though Chinese leaders remain
unrepentant about the massacre of pro-democracy students.
   Speaking of his gesture, he said, ``I don't think it's a
salute'' to the hard-line leaders i Beijing. He spoke of it as a
decision to end the isolation of a country of more than 1 billion
people.
   Bush said the criticism of his move was ``not a good rap'' but
that a president has to be willing ``to take a little heat from
time to time. It hasn't been that much.''
   On another foreign policy front, the president said that signs
of moderation in Iran after the death this year of Ayatollah
Ruhollah Khomeini have not been backed up by concrete action.
   Bush said he feels a ``personal frustration'' that the American
hostages in Lebanon remain in captivity, adding: ``It's on my mind
an awful lot.'' He said he wrote a personal note recently to the
relatives of the hostages.
   Fielding a question on the domestic agenda, the president
renewed his pledge against any new taxes. Asked if the vow he took
for 1989 would remain in effect next year, he said: ``As far as I'm
concerned it is.''
   Bush appeared unswayed by arguments in Congress that the massive
political changes in the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe should
translate into big spending cuts for the Pentagon.
   ``I will not take any naive unilateral action and I am
determined to move forward on a sensible program of evaluation and
a sensible program of arms reduction which includes conventional
forces,'' he said.
   Bush said he and Gorbachev should push ahead on a range of arms
control steps, including chemical weapons and conventional forces
in Europe.
   ``So let's go forward with our eyes open and do that,'' Bush
said. ``And I think that's exactly what Mr. Gorbachev wants to do.''
   In an opening statement, the president said he and Gorbachev
both want to wrap up a treaty before their scheduled summit in June
1990 to cut strategic nuclear weapons arsenals nearly in half.
   He also pledged that the United States would take ``an active
and appropriate role'' in encouraging democratic changes in Eastern
Europe.
   On his overture to China, Bush refused to say whether he won any
concession from Beijing in return for the United States taking the
first step to renew contact.
   ``I'm not going to discuss what I did or didn't get ..,'' he
said. You see, I still believe that sometimes to affect change you
talk in confidence.''
   Defending his decision to go first, Bush said: ``You do what you
think is correct. If you screw something up, you say, `Hey, I was
wrong.' If you're right, you don't get instant credit for it. So
you just try to do your best.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>