<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0114 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1621EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-BushText ??Takes 460-up 12-21 0510</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Bush Text, ?? Takes, 460-up</SECOND>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is the transcript of President Bush's
news conference Thursday afternoon.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   PRESIDENT BUSH: I have a brief statement, to be followed by a
brief press conference because I have a pain in the neck.
(Laughter.) Seriously.
   Q: Why?
   PRESIDENT BUSH: That's your first question?
   Q: No. (Laughter.)
   PRESIDENT BUSH: Okay. I'll go ahead. Well, our efforts to
support the democratic processes in Panama and to ensure continued
safety of American citizens is now moving into its second day. I'm
gratified by the decision and effect of the precision and the
effectiveness of the military forces in achieving their objectives.
I'm pleased that the Endara government is taking charge, and they
made several appointments today _ starting to govern the country.
   The young men and women involved in the exercise have
demonstrated the highest standards of courage and excellence in
defending America's interest and protecting American life. They
have been outstanding. In carrying out the mission of our nation,
there has been and they have sustained a tragic loss of life.
Military casualties are a burden which a nation must endure and all
presidents have to face up to, but which we can never accept. And
maybe it's just this time of year, but I don't think so. But
particularly _ just a second _ particularly at this time of year,
my heart goes out to the families of those who have died in Panama,
those who have been wounded.
   This operation is not over, but it's pretty well wrapped up. And
we've moved aggressively to neutralize the PDF (Panamanian Defense
Forces), to provide a stable environment for the freely elected
Endara government _ and I mentioned that. It helps to ensure the
integrity of the Panama Canal and to create an environment that is
safe for American citizens.
   Gen. Noriega is no longer in power. He no longer commands the
instruments of government or the forces of repression that he's
used for so long to brutalize the Panamanian people. And we are
continuing the efforts to apprehend him, see that he's brought to
justice.
   I appreciate the support that we've received, strong support
from the United States Congress, from our Latin American neighbors,
from our allies, from the American people. And it's always
difficult to order forces into battle, but that difficulty is
mitigated by the moral and personal support that is granted by our
friends and allies.
   You've received detailed briefings from the Pentagon on the
logistical aspects, and I might say that I think (Secretary of
Defense) Dick Cheney and (Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff
Gen.) Colin Powell have done _ and ably assisted by others _ have
done an outstanding job of keeping the American people informed.
   I wanted you to know that as we move into the days ahead, we
will continue to support the Endara government, to help establish
stability in the country, to allow those desires for freedom and
democracy to flourish.
   And I'll be glad to take some questions.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>