<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0218EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Radiation-WeaponsPlants     12-22 0383</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Radiation-Weapons Plants,380</SECOND>
<HEAD>Watkins Says Arms Plants Might Need Health-Protection Changes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Energy Department is considering whether
to modify its nuclear weapons plants in response to a report that
exposure to low-level radiation may carry more cancer risk than
previously believed.
   A National Research Council committee said in a report this week
that exposure to low-level radiation poses a cancer risk three to
four times greater than previously thought.
   Many workers in the 17 major weapons facilities work with
equipment that emit low-level radiation, and recent government
reports on plants in Ohio, Colorado, Tennessee and Texas said
workers have too little protection from radiation exposure.
   On Thursday, the department released copies of a memorandum from
Energy Secretary James D. Watkins ordering his acting assistant
secretary for environment, safety and health, Peter N. Brush, to
assess the implications of the radiation study for the weapons
program.
   ``Your report should include recommended options for modifying
operations where such changes appear warranted,'' Watkins wrote in
the memo dated Wednesday. He did not indicate whether he believed
any changes would be necessary.
   Watkins asked for an interim report within 90 days and a final
report by June 30, 1990.
   The National Research Council committee used new methods of
estimating and assessing the health effects of radiation, and it
concluded that a 1980 study by another NRC committee significantly
underestimated the cancer risk from low-level radiation.
   The risk for solid tumor cancer is three times greater than the
earlier estimate, and the risk from leukemia is four times greater,
the committee concluded.
   And the committee found a much greater danger for mental
retardation among unborn babies exposed to low-level radiation from
the eighth to 15th weeks after conception. Its study was based
partly on the medical history of 76,000 survivors of the 1945
atomic bombings in Japan, health studies of workers at nuclear
facilities and the records of patients treated with X-rays for
certain medical conditions.
   In a separate report released Wednesday, another NRC committee
said past and current releases of radiation from the nuclear
weapons plants appear to be too low to have caused any significant
increase in risk to public health. It added, however, that the
Energy Department should do more to study the health effects.
</TEXT>

</DOC>