<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0202 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 2052EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Britain-Falklands 1stLd-Writethru a0805 12-22 0275</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Falklands, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0805,0282</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prime Minister Calls for Improved Relations with Argentina</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with consular ties restored Thursday,
quotes, details. No pickup.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher called Friday for
improved commercial and diplomatic relations with Argentina, but
she also insisted Britain retain control of the disputed Falkland
Islands.
   In a Christmas address to the 1,800 islanders, Mrs. Thatcher
said Britain, in recent talks with the new Argentine government,
had not wavered from its position that control of the South
Atlantic islands is not negotiable.
   Her message followed the restoration Thursday of consular ties
between Britain and Argentina, severed at the time of the 1982
Falklands War.
   Consular flags were hoisted Friday in London and Buenos Aires,
but full diplomatic links between the two countries remain severed.
   In the speech broadcast by the British Broadcasting Corp., Mrs.
Thatcher said Britain would uphold its commitments to residents of
the Falklands.
   Argentine troops invaded the British colony off southern
Argentina in 1982. Britain sent troops and drove out the invaders
in a 74-day war.
   Argentina has claimed sovereignty to the islands it calls the
Malvinas since 1832.
   The prime minister commended the Falklands' growing prosperity
from its fishing industry and independence.
   ``You're deciding the kind of life you want for yourselves and
your children, and you're taking a greater share of responsibility
for your own affairs,'' Mrs. Thatcher said in the message,
broadcast on the BBC's World Service ``Calling the Falklands''
program.
   On Argentina, Mrs. Thatcher said: ``We want to improve ordinary
commercial and diplomatic relations because that is in the
interests of us all, including the Falkland Islands.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>