<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0178 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1407EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-PRI--Homes-Considerations Adv28   12-26 0464</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-PRI--Homes-Considerations, Adv 28,0479</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv28</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Thursday, Dec. 28, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Factors to Consider in Choosing a Nursing Home</HEAD>
<HEAD>With BC-PRI--Untie the Elderly</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   When considering the use of restraints, weigh potential benefits
such as safety and comfort against potential negatives including
the loss of mobility, depression and anxiety, says the Nursing Home
Coalition of New York State.
   In addition, family members and nursing home residents should
watch for these signs of possible abuse of physical restraints:
   _DISCOLORATION: Is there redness, bruising, blanching or welts?
   _PAIN: Do the restraints cause pain in wrists, waist, chest or
feet?
   _BEHAVIOR: Is there squirming in an attempt to get comfortable?
Does the resident bend forward trying to loosen restraints or rock
back and forth?
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   People trying to choose a nursing home can gather important
information by relying on their senses. Sarah Burger of the
National Citizens' Coalition for Nursing Home Reform suggests
considering these factors:
   _SIGHT: How do resident look? Are they up, dressed, clean,
chatting among themselves and staff, or slumped in a wheelchair? Do
rooms look personal or institutional?
   _SOUND: Is there a general level of chatter as in a normal
household? Or is there noise blaring from the TV and cries of help
or ``nurse''?
   _SMELL: Does the home smell good or does it smell of urine or a
cover-up of heavy disinfectant? Does the food from the kitchen
smell good?
   _TASTE: Eat a meal if you can. If not, ask residents how the
food is. Are they eating it?
   _TOUCH: Are handrails, bathrooms, etc., clean to the touch?
Residents will reach out to you. Take their hands. Are they clean,
with well-lubricated skin and trimmed nails, or are the hands
sticky or dry, with ragged nails?
   Also ask about quality of care and payment policies, the
coalition says.
   _QUALITY OF CARE: Ask residents and their families, physicians,
clergy and others what they think about various facilities. Visit
as many nursing homes as possible. Find out about staff. Is there a
trained social worker and a trained activities director? Do they
have assistants? How does the home handle potential staffing
shortages? Does staff turn over quickly?
   _PAYMENT: Most nursing home residents, even if they pay
privately when they enter, run out of money. Unless someone is sure
they can pay indefinitely with private funds, they should choose a
home that accepts Medicaid, find out what their state's Medicaid
eligibility rules are, and what their rights are or will be as a
Medicaid nursing home resident.
   Contact your state Office on Aging to get the name and telephone
number of the nearest long-term care ombudsman program. Ombudsmen
are empowered by law to serve as advocates for nursing home
residents and to assist with complaints.

</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Dec. 28</NOTE>

</DOC>