<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0173 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1355EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-PRI--UntietheElderly Adv28-2Takes   12-26 1242</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-PRI--Untie the Elderly, Adv 28-2 Takes,1268</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv28</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Thursday, Dec. 28, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Routine Restraint of Nursing Home Residents Causes Growing Concern</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NANCY BENAC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   William Harmon used to spend each day tied to
a chair in a nursing home, sometimes in a stupor, sometimes
pleading for release.
   ``They'd just sit there all day long, everybody tied in
restraints,'' said Mabel Harmon, who moved her 70-year-old husband
out in August. ``I don't think he would be living now if he hadn't
gotten out of there.''
   Harmon's situation was not unique. Two out of five residents of
American nursing homes routinely are tied to their beds or chairs,
ostensibly to prevent injury. Yet concern is mounting that
restraints may do more harm than good.
   Harmon now is at Stapeley in Germantown, a Philadelphia home
that is one of the growing number in the United States using no
restraints.
   ``Since he's been over at Stapeley, he'a a completely different
person,'' Mrs. Harmon said. ``He does what he wants to do. He
answers your questions. He walks up and down the hall. He goes into
the lounge.''
   Nursing homes say they use restraining devices such as lap
belts, wheelchairs with locking trays, and vests tied to beds or
chairs mainly to keep residents from falling or wandering away and
to control aggressive behavior.
   Critics say restraints often are used for convenience and seldom
eliminate the risk of injury. They say restraints can create
problems including emotional withdrawal, depression, injuries
incurred trying to get free, strangulation, constipation,
incontinence, pressure sores, loss of bone mass, weakened muscles,
decreased ability to walk and eventual invalidism.
   ``We have to ask ourselves: What price safety?'' said Jill
Blakeslee, director of health services for The Kendal Corp., a
non-profit Pennsylvania corporation governed by Quakers that has
pioneered the concept of restraint-free nursing homes in the United
States. ``Safe and quality care can be given to our frail old
people without tying them to their beds and their chairs.''
   Kendal and the Senate Committee on Aging this month sponsored a
symposium, ``Untie the Elderly: Quality Care Without Restraints,''
where Blakeslee urged: ``Think about yourself as you grow old. Is
that what you would want?''
   Michael Plevyak's family chose to place his 74-year-old mother,
Genevieve, who has Alzheimer's disease, at Friends Hall in West
Chester, Pa., because it uses no restraints.
   ``The only thing she desires to do is move about and walk,'' he
said. ``That's why we're so thrilled that she is in a facility that
allows her to engage in the one activity she gets any joy out of.''
   Forty-one percent of nursing home residents were restrained in
1988, up from 25 percent in 1977, federal surveys show. Thirty-five
people in U.S. and Canadian nursing homes strangled or suffocated
because of restraints from 1980 to 1987 and two burned to death
trying to escape by lighting their restraints, the Press-Telegram
of Long Beach, Calif., reported in a 1987 investigation.
   In U.S. and Canadian nursing homes studied over the last decade,
restraint rates ranged from 25 percent to 85 percent, Neville
Strumpf and Lois Evans of the University of Pennsylvania School of
Nursing reported in the January 1989 issue of the Journal of the
American Geriatrics Society.
   Family members initially may be horrified that a relative is
restrained, but medical professionals ``can talk people into a big
variety of things that afterwards they must wonder about,'' said
Lynne Mitchell-Pederson, a nurse at St. Boniface General Hospital
in Winnipeg, Manitoba. St. Boniface has nearly eliminated
restraints since a patient strangled in 1981.
   On the other hand, there are attorneys and family members
``wanting and willing to sue if a home doesn't use protective
devices to protect the safety of the resident,'' said Fred Watson,
administrator of the Christian City Convalescent Center in Atlanta.
``We've got to get over that hurdle.''
   Christian City was restraint-free when it opened 12 years ago
but began using the devices under pressure from insurers, doctors
and families, Watson said. It now restrains 20 percent to 30
percent of its patients, but is reducing that.
   The widespread use of restraints is widely attributed at least
in part to nursing homes' fear of being sued, but some attorneys
say reliance on restraints as a shield against litigation is
largely unneeded.
   A study of cases found that use of restraints led to more
successful lawsuits than non-use, said Philadelphia attorney Alan
Reeve Hunt, chairman of Kendal's board. For example, an Alabama
jury in June held a nursing home liable for $2.5 million in the
strangulation of an 86-year-old woman in a restraint vest that was
on backwards. The ruling is under appeal.
   Restraints ``became a standard of care without ever being
tested,'' said Sarah Burger, a consultant for the National
Citizens' Coalition for Nursing Home Reform. ``Everybody just
assumed they did good.''
   Growing concern about negative effects and recognition that
restraints don't eliminate legal risk are spurring a reduction in
their use. Thirteen U.S. nursing homes are known to be
restraint-free, according to Kendal. Tough new federal rules take
effect in October, and Florida has untied 3,000 people since August.
   ``There's a contest going on to see who's going to be the first
restraint-free facility,'' said Florida licensing director Connie
Cheren.
   ``This is not a movement in its infancy,'' said Nancy Dubler, an
attorney in the Department of Social Medicine at Montefiore
Hospital and Medical Center in New York. ``This is a discussion on
the verge of bringing change.''
   The new federal rules ban ``physical restraints imposed or
psychoactive drugs administered for purposes of discipline or
convenience, and not required to treat the resident's medical
symptoms.'' Nursing homes for the first time will have to ``show
that they have tried every other conceivable means to solve the
problem,'' Burger said.
   Removing restraints requires creative, individualized
alternatives, said Beryl Goldman, Kendal associate director for
health services. For example, doors that sound a buzzer when opened
might be installed on wanderers' rooms, brightly colored tape in
front of exits helps discourage confused residents from leaving,
and rocking chairs can soothe residents who need to be in motion.
   One home was able to avoid restraining an 85-year-old woman who
constantly paced with a doll but needed rest so her ulcers could
heal, said Joanne Rader, director of mental health at Benedictine
Nursing Facility in Mount Angel, Ore.
   Staff members filled the doll with seven pounds of birdseed.
``Now, when she's walking with the doll, she has a very heavy baby.
So they said, `Oh, that baby's so heavy. Why don't you sit down and
put your feet up?' That's a heck of a lot more fun than tying a
person down,'' Rader said.
   St. Boniface's Mitchell-Pederson cited the case of an
Alzheimer's patient who disrupted meals and stole food. ``When we
asked, `Could he be hungry?' and doubled his calorie intake, he
stopped stealing food. ... In this case it was his diet that needed
attention; restraints compounded the problem.''
   An 85-year-old woman restrained in a chair for fear she would
wander off and fall down the stairs was given rubber-soled shoes
instead of slippers and ``was thus allowed to wander at will
throughout the building,'' she said.
   ``There's tremendous excitement out there ... toward developing
and implementing a non-restraint philosophy,'' Rader said. ``It's
no fun to be the one who has to tie someone down when they don't
want to be tied down.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>