<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0201EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-CorcoranResignation     12-19 0664</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Corcoran Resignation,660</SECOND>
<HEAD>Corcoran Gallery Loses Director in Furor Over Controversial Art</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT M. ANDREWS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The venerable Corcoran Gallery of Art is
looking for a new director to succeed Christina Orr-Cahall, the
victim of harsh criticism for canceling an exhibit last summer that
contained sexually explicit photographs.
   After less than two years on the job, Ms. Orr-Cahall resigned
Monday ``in the hope that my decision will help to eliminate or
abate those extraneous and disruptive difficulties'' that have
plagued the Corcoran for the past six months.
   The Corcoran board of trustees agreed overwhelmingly to accept
her resignation effective Feb. 1. Gallery president Freeborn G.
Jewett Jr. praised her ``professional skill, courage and loyalty''
and said she had always acted ``in the utmost good faith.''
   Jewett said he would appoint a search committee within a week to
nominate a successor to Ms. Orr-Cahall, who plunged the
120-year-old Corcoran into a maelstrom last June when she canceled
an exhibition of works by the late photographer Robert Mapplethorpe
two weeks before the show was scheduled to open July 1.
   Ms. Orr-Cahall said she was trying to avoid embroiling the
Corcoran, the oldest art gallery in Washington and the third oldest
private museum in the country, in an impending congressional battle
over grant-making policies of the National Endowment for the Arts.
   Sen. Jesse Helms, R-N.C., and other conservative members of
Congress bitterly attacked the endowment, an independent federal
agency, for underwriting the national tour of the Mapplethorpe
show, which contained homoerotic and sadomasochistic images and
pictures of nude children.
   The exhibit, organized by the Institute of Contemporary Arts in
Philadelphia, had appeared in Philadelphia and Chicago without
incident. After the Corcoran's cancellation, it was shown before
large crowds at the Washington Project for the Arts, another local
private gallery.
   Ms. Orr-Cahall's cancellation, which the Corcoran board approved
on two occasions, was severely criticized by the artistic
community. Artists protesting that the Corcoran was stifling
freedom of expression withdrew plans for two exhibitions of
contemporary art at the Corcoran and threatened the opening of a
third show.
   Artist Lowell Nesbitt withdrew a $1.5 million bequest to the
Corcoran from his will and said he would give the money instead to
the Phillips Collection, another private Washington art gallery.
   Plummeting staff morale worsened when Jane Livingston, the
Corcoran's chief curator, resigned. She had arranged for the
Mapplethorpe show to appear at the gallery. A representative of the
staff asked Ms. Orr-Cahall to resign at one point, but she refused.
   In her resignation letter to the Corcoran trustees, Ms.
Orr-Cahall, former chief curator of the Oakland Museum in
California, said it was time for the Corcoran to look to the future
``and to make every effort to assure that it is not consumed by the
kind of contention that distracts the institution from achieving
its goals.''
   Jewett said in a statement that the Mapplethorpe controversy
``has interfered with the Corcoran's capacity to address its full
energies and attention to the curatorial and educational tasks of
the museum and the school that are the institution's fundamental
responsibilities.''
   The board appointed a special committee in September to study
ways to repair the damage. One member, board chairman David Lloyd
Kreeger, told reporters that panel was divided over whether Ms.
Orr-Cahall should stay or leave the Corcoran.
   The panel, he said, left the decision up to the full board,
which he said also was divided. The dispute was resolved last
weekend when the director indicated her intention to quit. She
delivered her resignation letter to Jewett shortly before the board
met at midday Monday.
   Kreeger said the board was not concerned about the Mapplethorpe
cancellation, which Ms. Orr-Cahall had admitted was a mistake, but
was upset by the ``continued barrage'' of criticism that had
tarnished the Corcoran's reputation.
   Expressing hope that Ms. Orr-Cahall's resignation will lay the
controversy to rest, Kreeger vowed that ``there is going to be a
resurgent and a new and dynamic Corcoran.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>