<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0197 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0133EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-S&amp;LBailouts Bjt   12-19 0677</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-S&amp;L Bailouts, Bjt,0695</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Administration Orders Sale of Failed S&amp;Ls' Assets</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also on general news wires.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVE SKIDMORE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bush administration is telling regulators
to begin selling real estate and other assets from failed savings
and loans even before the government officially closes the
institutions.
   Regulators ``should ... immediately begin shrinking such
institutions' balance sheets in a coordinated and orderly manner,''
instructs a document obtained Monday by The Associated Press.
   The administration, in a 91-page strategic plan, also is telling
regulators to discourage influence-peddling by keeping a public log
of all attempts by ``senior public officials'' or their staffs to
influence their decisions.
   The plan, scheduled for release by the end of the year, was
prepared by the Resolution Trust Corp. Oversight Board, an
administration panel headed by Treasury Secretary Nicholas F.
Brady. The board sets policy for the Resolution Trust Corp., a new
entity run by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corp., an independent
regulatory agency.
   Under pressure from critics to increase the pace of its savings
and loan bailout, the administration plan outlines its approach to
the huge task of selling more than $300 billion in S&amp;L assets.
   As of Dec. 8, the RTC had control of 280 failed S&amp;Ls, having
disposed of 33 since its creation Aug. 9. It expects to get
jurisdiction of at least another 220 insolvent thrifts in the next
2{ years.
   Most of the 33 S&amp;L resolutions so far have involved transferring
the deposits of the failed institution to a healthy bank or S&amp;L,
leaving the government with the thrifts' bad loans and repossessed
real estate.
   Critics say unless the RTC starts selling S&amp;L assets soon, the
properties will deteriorate, driving up the taxpayer cost of the
bailout.
   Earlier this month, the Shadow Financial Regulatory Committee, a
group of university professors and other private analysts, warned
that if the RTC continued on its present course, it could soon
exhaust its available cash.
   The oversight board is directing the RTC to develop a national
program to sell S&amp;L assets even before the institutions are closed
or sold to new investors. As part of that, it suggested packaging
and selling mortgage loans owned by the thrifts.
   The plan also:
   _Gives the RTC a June 30 deadline to finish reviewing the
bailout deals put together by its predecessor, the Federal Savings
and Loan Insurance Corp.
   _Tells the agency to ``provide financing of (real estate) assets
sparingly and only when necessary.'' The financing should be
considered a concession and be reflected in a higher purchase price
for the property, it said. Without such financing _ in effect a
government loan _ some analysts contend the agency won't be able to
sell many properties.
   _Says failed S&amp;Ls deteriorating at the fastest rate should be
closed first, but says the agency shouldn't waste time developing a
precise priority schedule.
   _Allows the RTC to sell a minority-owned thrift to another
minority institution without opening the sale to non-minority
bidders. It permits the agency to finance the sale, at market
rates, for as long as nine months. In most cases, the RTC is
forbidden from keeping an interest in institutions it sells for
longer than six months.
   _Orders the agency to make public all documents spelling out the
terms of bailout deals, including the estimated cost to the
government and the economic assumptions underlying the estimate.
   Despite its length, the plan leaves a number of important issues
unresolved. For example, it tells the RTC to ``develop a
mechanism'' to raise additional funds to finance S&amp;L bailouts until
it can sell thrift assets. However, it gives the agency no guidance
on the politically charged question of whether the additional funds
should be added to the federal budget deficit.
   It also gives the RTC wide latitude in deciding how to sell
insolvent S&amp;Ls, including selling the whole institution with good
and bad assets, selling only the good assets and marketing the bad
assets separately, keeping all the assets for later sale, and
dismantling the thrift and selling it branch by branch.
</TEXT>

</DOC>