<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0136 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2101EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Iger-ABC     12-19 0385</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iger-ABC,0398</SECOND>
<HEAD>ABC Program Chief Doesn't Fear Roseanne Barr Will Leave ABC</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAY SHARBUTT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Television Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Roseanne Barr's threat to leave her top-rated
``Roseanne'' doesn't worry ABC's programs chief, who said Tuesday
he assumes she'll do a third season of the television comedy series.
   Robert A. Iger said he hasn't discussed the matter with Barr,
but just ``took a wait-and-see attitude. I'm not that worried.''
   ``I'm outta there,'' Barr said earlier this month on NBC's
``Today'' show when asked what she'd do with her television career
if her movie ``She-Devil'' was a hit. If the movie flopped, she
said, ``I'm going to leave TV anyway.''
   ``I've spoken with her since that quote. ... I didn't address
that comment at all,'' Iger said. ``I just let it go.
   ``She has a contract to do the program and I assume she'll be
back.''
   Iger, ABC Entertainment president, spoke at a news conference
where he also said:
   _ ABC has ordered eight episodes of ``Elvis,'' a new half-hour
dramatic series about rock idol Elvis Presley's early years in the
mid-'50s. The new show may premiere in February, rather than March,
when ABC's other mid-season replacement series will begin.
   _ James L. Brooks, writer of such TV comedy hits as ``The Mary
Tyler Moore Show,'' ``Taxi,'' and ``The Tracey Ullman Show,'' has
signed an exclusive ABC deal to develop comedies for the network.
   _ He's ``not aware of any backlash'' from ABC affiliates over
the network's unusual decision earlier this year to try selling
programs to its network rivals, including NBC, with whom ABC is
working on a development deal.
   Conceding that ABC's decision ``raises eyebrows,'' Iger said it
was necessary if Brandon Stoddard, president of ABC Productions, is
to attract top creative talent for the network's production
division.
   Top talent might balk if limited to just one potential buyer, he
said, and that's why ABC made its decision ``to allow him to sell
in multiple directions, including another network.''
   ``I know it's under way,'' he said of the NBC-ABC deal. ``I do
not know the status of it at this time.'' He didn't elaborate on
the project.
   He said there has been talk of NBC offering ABC a ``potential
movie ... but to my knowledge that's not in the present
development.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>