<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1310EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Judge-Explosion 5thLd-Writethru a0554-a0558 12-18 0988</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Judge-Explosion, 5th Ld - Writethru, a0554-a0558,1016</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Suspected Bomb Found in Atlanta; Link to Judge's Slaying Probed</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: COMBINES pvs urgent series; minor editing throughout.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY11</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BYRD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police today removed a suspected bomb delivered
to the 11th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals building, two days after
a package bomb killed one of the court's judges at his home in
Alabama, authorities said.
   ``There could be a significant connection between the two
packages,'' said Jim Holland, postal inspector at Birmingham, Ala.,
where authorities are investigating the blast Saturday that killed
Judge Robert S. Vance.
   Two flak-jacketed police officers removed a package in a bomb
disposal container from the court building today. Employees were
evacuated from the building and sent home for the day.
   Maj. W.W. Holley said the device appeared to be a pipe bomb and
was discovered during a random sample of the morning mail. The
package measured about 10 inches by 10 inches by 4 inches and was
wrapped in brown paper, he said.
   In Birmingham, FBI agent Allen Whitaker said agents and postal
inspectors were sent to Atlanta ``because of the apparent
similarity between the devices.''
   Whitaker said the Atlanta package was addressed to ``someone in
the court system.'' He would not give the name or say where the
package was postmarked.
   ``This is a fast-breaking lead,'' he added.
   The 11th Circuit, which has 12 judges plus six in
semi-retirement, hears cases from Florida, Georgia and Alabama.
Vance worked in Birmingham.
   Federal judges around the country had been advised after Vance's
death not to open packages received in the mail until they could be
inspected.
   The FBI said it was giving top priority to finding out who
mailed the bomb that killed Vance, the third federal judge to be
assassinated in 10 years. The three are believed to be the only
federal jurists killed this century.
   FBI agents said the search for Vance's killer was aided by a
hospital bed interview Sunday with his wife, Helen, who was listed
today in serious but stable condition with wounds suffered in the
explosion at his home in Birmingham's most exclusive suburb.
   Vance, 58, who fought for racial moderation and progressive
stands in Alabama during 11 years as state chairman of the
Democratic Party, was killed instantly when the package, shoe
box-size and wrapped in brown paper, blew up, police said.
   Authorities said Vance had received no threats on his life
before the explosion and hadn't requested protection.
   On speculation of a possible connection to drug cases Vance may
have handled, FBI spokesman Tom Moore said Sunday, ``It is not
being ruled out, but it is no more prominent than several other
avenues we are following. We are reviewing his full caseload.''
   The head of the federal Drug Enforcement Administration office
in Miami discounted any link between the bombing and drug cartels.
``It's pretty far-fetched if someone says it's drug connected,''
said Tom Cash.
   Vance was appointed to the federal appeals court in 1977.
   ``As a member of the 11th Circuit Court of Appeals, they heard
many appeal cases related to drugs from Miami,'' said Sen. Howell
Heflin, D-Ala., a longtime friend of Vance. ``There's speculation
in that regard, but nobody knows.''
   Authorities said the 11th Circuit caseload was varied, although
most cases were drug related. Vance took several controversial
stances, including:
   _In 1985, he told an attorney seeking to block the deportations
of about 1,500 Cuban refugees that the ``government can keep the
detainees in the Atlanta pen until they die.''
   _Later that year, he was on a panel that cleared the way for
prosecution of Ku Klux Klansmen in a bloody 1979 confrontation with
black civil rights marchers in Decatur.
   But investigators said the attack might have been unrelated to
his work. In the nearby suburb of Hoover, about six pipe bombs were
left in mailboxes of residents during the past year, The New York
Times reported today, citing unidentified FBI officials. Only one
of the bombs detonated, injuring the person thought to have planted
it, but authorities said they could have been lethal, according to
the newspaper.
   One recipient, Chriss Doss, was a former associate of Vance in
the Alabama Democratic Party, the Times said.
   Within 24 hours of Vance's death, William M. Dempsey, a
spokesman for the U.S. Marshal's Service in Washington, said
marshals around the country were notified by wire to contact each
of the 1,500 federal judges or magistrates in their jurisdiction.
   Moore said all members of the federal judiciary may request
special security.
   U.S. District Judge Marvin Shoob of Atlanta said marshals
advised him not to open packages unless he knew who was sending
them. He said they called later and advised him not to open any
packages at all.
   ``We all think this isn't going to happen to us. When it does,
you realize everyone is exposed,'' he said.
   Whitaker said all 50-plus FBI agents in the area were involved
in the case, which was called the bureau's most important
investigation.
   Mrs. Vance spoke with investigators and ``provided information
that will be helpful,'' Whitaker said.
   The bomb caused substantial damage to the kitchen area, Moore
said. ``Indications are that it was delivered by regular U.S.
mail,'' not special delivery, Moore added.
   The two other federal judges slain were U.S. District Judge
Richard Daronco, 56, who was shot and killed at his suburban New
York home in May 1988, and U.S. District Judge John H. Wood Jr.,
63, who was killed by a sniper outside his home in San Antonio,
Texas, in 1979.
   Both assassinations were connected to cases the judges handled.
   Moore said Mrs. Vance, who received lacerations and internal
injuries from the explosion, and other members of her family are
being guarded. The couple, married 36 years, had two sons, Robert
S. Jr., a Birmingham lawyer, and Charles, a medical student and
Ph.D. candidate in psychology at Duke University.
</TEXT>

</DOC>