<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0919EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-US-Panama 2ndLd-Writethru 2Takes 12-22 0610</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-Panama, 2nd Ld-Writethru, 2 Takes, a0554,620-1100</SECOND>
<HEAD>OAS Urges U.S. Withdrawal; Bush Says Troop Return Is Unpredictable</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDs: Inserts grafs 14-19 w@ additional Bush, Warner quotes. Edits
1st Add to tighten.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HARRY F. ROSENTHAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United States' intervention in Panama was
rejected today by Latin American neighbors who called for an end to
the bloodshed and a U.S. withdrawal. President Bush notified
Congress that he could not predict the ``precise scope and
duration'' of the military operation.
   The War Powers Act requires the president to formally notify
Congress anytime he commits military force. In a written message,
Bush accused deposed Panamanian leader Manuel Antonio Noriega of
directing ``vicious and brutal acts'' against Americans and
asserted that the lives and welfare of U.S. citizens had been
``increasingly at risk.''
   ``Although most organized opposition has ceased, it is not
possible at this time to predict the precise scope and duration of
the military operations or how long the temporary increases of U.S.
forces in Panama will be required,'' Bush said.
   In Panama City, thousands of U.S. troops were settling in to
restore order in the chaotic streets while in Washington, within
blocks of the White House, the Organization of American States'
political council voted 20-1 with six abstentions ``to deeply
regret the military intervention.''
   The United States cast the sole ``no'' vote. In a Spanish
translation, the resolution used the words ``deplorar
profundamente'' _ profoundly deplore. A resolution to ``condemn''
the invasion was never formally taken up.
   The Pentagon, revising its casualty report, said 20 American
troops and two female dependents were killed in the first two days
of battle, 202 were wounded and two were missing. American military
aircraft were bringing the bodies of the dead back to Dover Air
Force Base in Delaware, their coffins draped with American flags.
   U.S. officials said 122 Panamanian soldiers were killed and 45
wounded. Army Lt. Gen. Tom Kelly said U.S. troops had taken 1,500
prisoners, most of them regulars from the Panamanian Defense Force.
   ``This operation is not over, but it's pretty well wrapped up,''
Bush said Thursday at a news conference that coincided with return
of the first bodies. This morning's report to Congress, ``Our
additional forces will remain in Panama only so long as their
presence is required.''
   Sens. John Warner, R-Va., and Christopher Dodd, D-Conn., called
on other Latin American states to recognize Panama's
newly-installed U.S.-backed president, Guillermo Endara. The OAS
group had not taken up the matter.
   Warner said it was time for ``the hand wringing and second
guessing to stop.''
   The senator in a television interview also said it would be
helpful if Panama's neighbors would ``begin to rally behind him and
perhaps even send in their own police ... so that President Bush
can withdraw our troops as soon as possible.''
   Endara acknowledged in an interview on ABC's ``Good Morning
America'' that he could not safely walk the streets of his country
today _ ``nobody is secure right now,'' he said _ but he claimed
that he was the country's legitimate leader.
   ``I have the wholehearted support of the people right now,''
Endara declared. He said Noriega's capture was ``not absolutely
necessary'' for an Endara government to establish roots.
   If Noriega is caught by Panamanian forces, Endara said, he could
not under Panama's constitution be extradited to the United States,
where he is under indictment on drug trafficking charges, ``so
therefore I'm not looking for him.''
   Following the OAS vote, U.S. representative John Masisto said,
``We're a little disappointed. It certainly wasn't an extreme
resolution but it's a little detached from what is really happening
in Panama.''
   
   MORE
 
</TEXT>

</DOC>