<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0231EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-US-Panama     12-29 0680</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-Panama,680</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Urges Japan To Help Restore Damaged Panamanian Economy</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RUTH SINAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.S. effort to recruit aid for Panama's
damaged economy is targeting Japan, which has a strong vested
interest in the Panama Canal, a Japanese Embassy official says.
   The request, which went out in recent days, is part of a
government-wide mobilization to help Panama rebuild an economy
shattered by two years of U.S. sanctions against deposed dictator
Manuel Antonio Noriega and by last week's invasion by U.S. troops.
   In talks both before and after the invasion, the United States
urged Japan to help Panama regain the economic standing it enjoyed
before Noriega's 1988 indictments in the United States on drug
trafficking charges. The indictments shook investors' confidence in
Panama.
   Japan ships many of its exports to the United States through the
Panama Canal and has provided more than $5 million in annual
technical aid to support the government's stability.
   ``The U.S. expects Japan to play a significant role,'' said a
Japanese Embassy official, who spoke on condition of anonymity.
   Japan stopped its aid to Panama six months ago but expects to
resume and increase the assistance once it recognizes the new
Panamanian government installed with U.S. support last week, said
the official.
   On Thursday, a U.S. State Department team arrived in Panama to
assess the country's immediate needs in providing shelter, food and
medicine to thousands of Panamanians left homeless by the operation
mounted Dec. 20 to remove Noriega from power.
   The team, led by the head of the Office of Foreign Disaster
Assistance, Andrew Natsios, will remain in Panama until Monday.
   An estimated 570 people, including 23 American servicemen, were
killed in five days of fighting against Noriega loyalists,
officials report.
   Alfredo Maduro, president of the Panamanian Chamber of Commerce,
said Thursday that insurance brokers estimate losses from looting
or other damage to businesses in the capital at $750 million to $1
billion.
   Maduro said businessmen planned to ask the United States for
``something like a Marshall Plan for Panama'' to recover.
   To address the country's longer term needs, a task force has
been formed with representatives from the Treasury, State and
Commerce departments. The group has held talks since Tuesday with a
three-man Panamanian delegation and will head for Panama next week
to examine the situation.
   The focus of the Panamanian-American meeting is the transfer of
some $400 million in Panamanian government money frozen last year
in the United States. President Bush last week ordered the funds
released, but the process is expected to take several weeks,
administration officials said.
   The United States already has transferred $5.82 million
confiscated from Noriega to the new government headed by Guillermo
Endara, a U.S. military spokesman in Panama City said Thursday.
   The Bush administration has not yet asked Congress for money for
Panama's rehabilitation, relying for now on the $400 million in
unfrozen Panamanian assets.
   But Rep. Lee Hamilton, D-Ind., chairman of the Joint Economic
Committee of the House and Senate, said that sum would not be
enough.
   ``The Panama economy is in a mess, maybe in a bigger mess than I
think,'' Hamilton said at a news conference.
   Panama's needs must be identified and aid must be provided, he
said. ``You can't promote their democracy unless you help their
economy.''
   Panama, once a thriving banking center with a per capita income
double that of its neighbors, has seen its economy shrink at an
estimated annual rate of 10 percent to 15 percent since 1987,
according to economic analysts.
   Economic sanctions by the United States and a loss of confidence
in Noriega led U.S. firms, including large-scale employers like
Xerox and IBM, to scale down their businesses in Panama.
Unemployment has risen to more than 20 percent.
   In addition, Panama owes at least $5.6 billion to foreign banks,
governments and international lending agencies such as the World
Bank and International Monetary Fund.
   The World Bank is not expected to resume any lending to Panama
unless the country repays some $180 million in arrears on past
loans, bank officials said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>