<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0146 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1907EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Chile     12-21 0445</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chile,0458</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pinochet Refuses to Relinquish Army Command</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SANTIAGO, Chile (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Patricio Aylwin met on Thursday with
Augusto Pinochet, whom he will replace as president in March, and
said the general refused to give up command of the army.
   After the 50-minute meeting, the civilian president-elect told
reporters he asked Pinochet to consider relinquishing the command,
which he cannot be forced to do under the constitution his military
regime wrote in 1980.
   ``I thought it my duty to let him know I considered it
preferable that he not make use'' of the special constitutional
provisions, Aylwin said. ``He told me the opposite.''
   ``The issue was left pending for another conversation,'' Aylwin
said. When asked whether he thought Pinochet would change his mind,
the president-elect said: ``You'll have to ask him.''
   Aylwin, a 71-year-old moderate Christian Democrat supported by a
17-party coalition, won a landslide victory in elections Dec. 14
and will take office March 11th with a new civiilian Congress.
   He said several other issues were discussed in Thursday's
meeting at the presidential palace, including a bill prepared by
the ruling junta that would give the military virtual autonomy
under civilian rule.
   Pinochet, 74, made no immediate comment, but Interior Minister
Carlos Caceres, who was present at the meeting, gave an account
similar to Aylwin's.
   The general seized power in September 1973, overthrowing
President Salvador Allende, an elected Marxist who died in the
coup. He was forced to call elections when voters rejected a
referendum proposal last year that his presidency be extended to
1997.
   According to Aylwin, Pinochet said his remaining as commander
was ``the best guarantee of the army's loyalty to the constitution
and the future government.''
   Thursday's meeting was the first known direct conversation since
the coup between Pinochet and any leading critic of his
authoritarian rule.
   About 2,000 Aylwin supporters waited outside the palace for his
arrival and chanted, ``Give it to him hard!'' as the
president-elect entered the building.
   When some government officials peered through trough gtrgout of
windowsped out palace windows, the crowd waved and shouted, ``Go
away, Pinochet!'' and ``The dictatorship will fall!''
   Aylwin said he and Pinochet they discussed a proposed Armed
Forces Law that would bar the new government from cutting the
defense budget, limit its influence in promotion of officers and
allow the military to decide on arms purchases without government
approval.
   The four-man military junta that acts as a legislature under
Pinochet has yet to approve the legislation.
   Pinochet invited him to prepare written comments on the Armed
Forces Law and other issues, ``then our people and people from the
government would debate their differences and look for reasonable
solutions,'' Aylwin said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>