<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0034EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Romania-TV     12-27 0919</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-TV,0948</SECOND>
<HEAD>Free Romania Television _ Heart of the Revolt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Wednesday AMs report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MORT ROSENBLUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The television station that once
beamed the glory of Nicolae Ceausescu to a numbed nation has become
not only the voice, but the soul of the revolution that toppled his
government and ended his life.
   While everything it broadcast once was suspect, nothing now is
believed until it appears on Free Romania Television, as the
station is calling itself. Although he was reported captured and
executed, it wasn't until television showed Ceausescu in captivity
that the nation sighed in relief.
   The station first broke from the propaganda of the Stalinist
past on Friday morning, when army units joined protesters to drive
Ceausescu from his palace and from power.
   ``We've won. We've won,'' poet Murica Dinescu suddently shouted
into the camera. But those giddy opening moments only were a
prelude to the battles with Ceausescu loyalists that followed.
   The National Salvation Committee clung to the television like a
mantle of power, running the country from a barricaded studio while
Ceausescu's fanatical guard tried to blast it into silence. Sniper
fire smashed windows and heavy shells blew holes in the walls.
   Early Saturday morning, news editor Victor Ionescu announced on
the air: ``We are under attack.'' He urged people to rally outside
the TV station in a masive human shield to protect the building.
Almost immediately, a crowd formed.
   People chanted, ``Freedom! Freedom!'' until gunfire broke out.
Each time, they scattered and regrouped. They shouted, ``We won't
go,'' and they didn't. Outgunned, the attackers pulled back.
   Later that weekend, Ceausescu's guard struck again. Infiltrators
stabbed people in the hallways of the 13-story complex, reportedly
killing three people. For a few hours, TV screens went mysteriously
blank.
   But the interruption was merely a technical problem, it was
explained. Romania was still governed from a hectic studio littered
with empty bottles, cracked coffee mugs and half-eaten sandwiches
and run by people who had not slept in days.
   Television has played a large role in the forces of reform that
swept the East bloc this year. Mass demonstrations were shown live
on TV in Czechoslovakia in the days preceding the Communist
leadership's downfall; East Germans able to watch West German
broadcasts followed closely news of the loosening of travel
restrictions and the rallies that brought down Erich Honecker; a
Solidarity economic minister goes on the air with regular
``fireside chats'' to the people.
   Free Romania Television has become a chaotic reflection of the
country it covers, a jumbled but jubilant mirror of the revolution
it helped orchestrate.
   ``It is madness here, madness,'' said Gratiela Ripeanu. Her
external relations job used to consist mainly of shaking hands with
fraternal Bulgarians.
   Suddenly, she was shepherding countless foreign TV crews all
desperate to relay film back home. Reporters counted on her to find
them National Salvation Committee members to interview.
   One by one, she steered people and their bulky gear through an
obstacle course of gun barrels, locked gates, roiling crowds and
skittish guards who looked for explosives in balpoint pen refills.
Six body searches separated the street from the studio.
   ``We don't know what we are doing anymore, but we're doing it,''
she said.
   Elena Maria Ionescu, a news writer and Victor's wife, helped out
on the studio, partly because her office was a gaping hole in the
eighth floor.
   She smiled broadly when she recognized several reporters who had
sat with her until morning during the first assault.
   They had subsequently stayed in the relative luxury of hotel
rooms, but she was still on the job.
   ``I've slept here, ate here, washed things out here,'' she said.
``My husband is so hoarse he can hardly talk on the air.''
Nevertheless, she seemed ready for another four days.
   Most of the station's 1,300 employees were caught up in the mad
metamorphosis.
   Until the revolution, the station broadcast only two hours
daily, a deadening litany of the heroic and generous qualities of
Ceausescu. Romania's austerity budget left it short of equipment
and supplies.
   Suddenly, it was on the air around the clock, and Romanians who
once scorned television sat glued to their screens.
   Technicians cannibalized old gear and pushed technical
tolerances to the limit.
   Armed soldiers wandered across the set, and overtired officials
reverted to the hated Communist term for comrade, ``Tovarase,''
rather than ``Domnul,'' or mister, but the show went on.
   During the assault, section chiefs and janitors alike beamed
with pride at the unflickering image they broadcast across the
fearful nation. In the face of rumors and threats, the reassuring
voices on television maintained the momentum of the revolt.
   Unlikely heroes emerged in the heat of battle. Marin Constantin,
who edited youth programs, took it upon himself to make sure the
eighth floor occupants made it through the night.
   When the shooting started, he herded eveyone into a central
hallway protected from ricochets by a double layer of walls. When
he found no other way to extinguish the grilled ceiling light, he
deftly smashed it with a chair.
   When the heavy fighting began, his grin broadened, comforting
others whose thoughts were beginning to rattle them. To amuse the
company, he sang an old national hymn that was almost forgotten
during Ceausescu's reign.
   It went, ``Wake up, Romania, from the mortal sleep into which
you have been lulled by the evil tyrant.''
   The song, broadcast earlier in the day over the battered
transmitters, seemed to fit Free Romania Television.
</TEXT>

</DOC>