<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1239EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r k BC-EditorialRdp 1stAdd   12-27 0528</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Editorial Rdp, 1st Add,0545</SECOND>
<HEAD>UNDATED: than Noriega.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Dec. 26
   The Tulsa (Okla.) Tribune on the Panama invasion:
   The Bush administration will make a tactical error if it insists
that Gen. Noriega, now sequestered in the quarters of the Vatican's
apostolic nuncio, be turned directly over to U.S. soldiers
surrounding the property.
   Let us not forget that the No. 1 objective was not to capture a
man wanted on criminal charges but to oust a bloody and corrupt
dictator.
   Noriega is such an opprobrious character that it would be
foolish to give him a chance to play the martyr. By demanding that
the Vatican shove him out the door into the hands of what is, in
fact, an invading army we would raise again all the anger, latent,
at best, in Latin America, over the colossus of the North.
   It would be far better to allow the Vatican, which wants nothing
of this red hot potato, to hand him over to whatever passes for the
military forces in Panama not under control of Noriega officers.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Dec. 26
   Los Angeles Times on the Panama invasion:
   By surrendering to Vatican diplomats on Christmas Eve, former
Panamanian dictator Manuel Noriega saved himself, at least
temporarily, from the U.S. military forces that ousted him. ...
even if Noriega evaded the U.S. government again, he still stands
deposed and discredited _ and that's an important victory.
   ... The Holy See may give him to the new civilian government in
Panama, which also wants to put Noriega on trial. Or it may
negotiate Noriega's departure to a third country like Cuba. But,
frankly, now that Noriega's come to a pathetic end, he's no longer
of any real concern. There are far more important tasks facing the
United States in Panama. ... Getting U.S. forces out of the country
as quickly as possible. ... Helping Panama's new civilian
government build the genuine democracy that has never had a chance
to develop in that country. ... Rebuilding Panama's badly-damaged
economy.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Dec. 22
   The Spokane (Wash.) Chronicle on nuclear plant safety:
   Officials at U.S. nuclear weapons plants say the knowing
disregard for worker safety that prevailed 30 to 40 years ago would
not occur today.
   Americans in general, and weapons plant workers in particular,
can hope that's true. They may never feel completely confident it's
true, though, given the evidence that weapons-production pressures
have taken precedence over worker safety for virtually the entire
history of U.S. nuclear weapons production. ...
   Congress is in the process of providing funds for a new
generation of nuclear weapons plants. So dramatic are the trends in
superpower relations that even the most prudent observers rightly
can ask how much production capacity is required. Some such
capacity, however, will be required _ if only to recycle old
warheads to glean the materials for a much smaller deterrent force.
   Given that need for a new generation of weapons plants, Congress
must see to it that those new plants are operated safely. The means
to that end, not yet achieved, is a management structure severing
safety obligations from production responsibilities and making the
latter subordinate to the former.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>