<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0237 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0156EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-CoalProjects     12-22 0452</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Coal Projects,0463</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Picks 13 Coal Technology Projects in 10 States</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Energy Department says it plans to award
$540 million to 13 companies to help finance ``showcase'' ventures
in 10 states to develop ways of burning U.S. coal with fewer
emissions of harmful gases.
   The proposed awards are part of the department's ``clean coal
technology'' program, a $5 billion, five-year effort to make
coal-burning power plants less polluting and more efficient.
   ``The technologies to be field tested by these flagship projects
represent environmentally superior weays to use U.S. coal,'' Energy
Secretary James D. Watkins said Thursday in announcing the
selections. ``They are this country's best hope for using its most
abundant energy resource, coal, while preserving ... our
environment.''
   The actual awards of federal money for the ventures is subject
to the completion of cooperative agreements with the companies
involved in the projects. Watkins said the negotiations would be
completed by December 1990.
   The 13 projects were selected from among 48 submitted last
August. Twenty-seven other projects already had been selected from
two previous rounds of competition in 1986 and 1988, and two more
rounds are planned for next year and 1991.
   The proposed awards of $540 million in federal money for the 13
projects would be in addition to $777 million to be contributed by
the companies and state governments. Watkins said some of the
private financing would come from foreign companies.
   The largest project, costing $403.6 million and proposed by CRSS
Capital Inc. of Houston and TECO Power Services Corp. of Tampa,
Fla., would use a new technology to convert coal to gas for use in
generating electricity for the city of Tallahassee, Fla.
   Others are headed by AirPol Inc., of Teterboro, N.J., costing
$4.9 million and sited at West Paducah, Ky.; Babcock &amp; Wilcox Co.
of Alliance, Ohio, costing $9.8 million, at Aberdeen, Ohio; Bechtel
Corp. of San Francisco, costing $8.5 million, at Seward, Pa.;
Energy and Environmental Research Corp. of Irvine, Calif., $14.5
million, at Denver, Colo.; and LIFAC North America of Oakland,
Calif., $18.7 million, at Richmond, Ind.
   Also, MK-Ferguson Co., of Cleveland, costing $66.2 million, at
Niles, Ohio; Public Service Co. of Colorado, of Denver, $24.6
million, at Denver, and Alaska Industrial Development and Export
Authority of Anchorage, $191.7 million, at Healy, Alaska; Dairyland
Power Cooperative of La Crosse, Wis., $183.9 million, at Alma,
Wis.; Bethlehem Steel Corp., of Bethlehem, Pa., $104.3 million, at
Burns Harbor, Ind.; and ENCOAL Corp. of Houston, $72.6 million, at
Gillette, Wyo.
   Air Products &amp; Chemicals of Allentown, Pa., and Dakota
Gasification Co. of Beulah, N.D., are jointly heading a project
valued at $213.7 million and sited at Beulah.
</TEXT>

</DOC>