<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1956EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RifleBan     12-17 0387</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rifle Ban,0399</SECOND>
<HEAD>Final Round for Assault Rifle Lovers</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RAINBOW, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Recreational shooting of assault rifles
is going out with a bang in California.
   A state ban on more than 50 varieties of the powerful weapons
takes effect Jan. 1. More than 200 people gathered on a windswept
ridge in this town about 50 miles north of San Diego on Saturday to
get in one last round of gunfire.
   ``I just had to get my hands on an Uzi one more time,'' said
Robert Anderson, a self-described ``gun nut'' who paid a $12
admission fee and up to $1 per round to fire a variety of the
military-style rifles.
   Cathy Tolly, a 26-year-old registered nurse who helped organize
the shoot, called it ``a last hurrah for law-abiding citizens who
happen to like assault-type weapons.''
   ``Once the ban takes place, you won't see events like this
anymore,'' she said.
   The state Legislature enacted the ban after a drifter toting an
AK-47 assault rifle shot and killed five children and wounded 30
other people in Stockton last January.
   Angry gun enthusiasts said the ban would do little to stem such
shootings.
   ``They're kidding themselves if they think taking away assault
weapons is going to lessen the crime problem,'' said Bart Montier,
who brought an antique cannon to the shoot. ``The whole thing's
absurd. You're not going to see gang members turn in their
weapons.''
   Montier said he came to the shoot try out an Israeli Gallil
assault rifle.
   ``Now that's a gun,'' he exclaimed after firing several rounds
into a row of clay pigeons set up against a hillside.
   Nearly 40 high-performance weapons were available for shooting,
including more than two dozen types of assault rifles and an
assortment of pistols and shotguns.
   Elodie McKee of Burbank _ who wore a T-shirt reading, ``Just Say
No to Gun Control _ said the shoot was a way of dressing down
gun-control advocates.
   ``Just by showing up here I think we make a statement,'' said
Ms. McKee.
   ``These guns have gotten such a bad rap that a lot of (gun)
enthusiasts would prefer to just go into hiding and not mention
them,'' said T.J. Johnston, another organizer. ``But I don't feel
that way. That's why we held this thing, to show people what
they're going to be missing.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>