<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1313EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Egypt-Syria 1stLd-Writethru   12-27 0428</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Egypt-Syria, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0509,0442</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Syria and Egypt Restore Relations After 12-Year Rift</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE with relations restored. No pickup.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DAMASCUS, Syria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Syria and Egypt today agreed to restore
diplomatic relations after a 12-year rift, the two governments
announced.
   Syria broke ties with Egypt in late 1977 when then-President
Anwar Sadat opened peace negotiations with Israel.
   A summit between presidents Hafez Assad of Syria and Hosni
Mubarak of Egypt will take place early in January, the prime
ministers of the two countries said in a joint statement released
in Cairo and Damascus.
   ``The governments of the Syrian Arab Republic and the Arab
Republic of Egypt have agreed to resume full diplomatic relations,
effective Wednesday, December 27, 1989,'' the statement in Damascus
said.
   ``This comes to express the determination of the two peoples to
consolidate brotherly relations in all fields,'' it said.
   The breakthrough occurred after a series of meetings this years
between officials of the two Arab countries.
   Earlier today, Egyptian Prime Minister Atef Sedki hinted during
a visit to Damascus that the two countries would resume relations.
   Sedki, the first such high-ranking Egyptian official to visit
Damascus since the rift began, received a warm welcome by his
counterpart, Mahmoud Zoubi, when he arrived at Damascus airport.
   After an official ceremony and a brief meeting in the VIP lounge
at Damascus airport, the two prime ministers drove to the
Muhajereen Presidential Palace for a meeting with Assad, state-run
Damascus radio reported.
   The broadcast quoted Sedki as saying in an arrival statement
that he was ``very pleased'' to visit Syria and that he was
carrying a message to Assad from Mubarak. He did not disclose the
contents of the letter.
   ``Egypt's goal is to unify ranks with Syria and consolidate
cooperation between our two countries,'' Sedki said.
   Zoubi told reporters, ``We are looking forward to more
cooperation and coordination for the benefit of the entire (Arab)
nation.''
   He said restoring ties ``will open a new page in the history of
our common destiny. Developments witnessed by the Arab world
require that Syria and Egypt return to each other on the basis of
their historical and fraternal bonds.''
   Cairo-Damascus relations were severed in December 1977, one
month after Sadat visited Jerusalem to begin a peace process that
led to the signing of the U.S.-sponsored Camp David peace treaty in
March 1979.
   Sixteen other Arab states severed relations with Egypt after the
treaty. All except Syria and Libya had since restored ties with
Cairo.
   Egypt's ties with Libya have improved but have not been restored.
</TEXT>

</DOC>