<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0648EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-TroubledMayor     12-29 0347</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Troubled Mayor,0359</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bradley Admits No Wrong, But Uses Own Money to Settle Ethics Lawsuit</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mayor Tom Bradley admitted no wrongdoing but
agreed to spend $20,000 of his own money to settle an ethics
lawsuit charging he unlawfully failed to disclose personal
financial holdings, a judge said.
   The agreement disclosed Thursday settles a civil lawsuit filed
Sept. 13 by City Attorney James K. Hahn. It charged Bradley with
failing to report personal financial holdings, amounting to roughly
$160,000, on six occasions.
   Typically, politicians have been allowed to use campaign funds
to settle such lawsuits, said Superior Court Judge Robert I. Weil,
who called the Bradley deal ``unique and extraordinary.''
   Nevertheless, Weil said Thursday that Bradley's errors were acts
of negligence, not done with criminal or willful intent. The
settlement, Weil added, ``does not constitute an admission of
liability.''
   Bradley said in a statement: ``Though none of my mistakes was
intentional, I have repeatedly taken public responsibility for the
inadvertent errors.
   ``Therefore, I chose the highly unusual step of resolving this
manner by paying the settlement from my own resources. The decision
to use my personal funds was mine and mine alone.''
   Hahn, however, characterized Bradley's violations as
``significant'' and said the $20,000 Bradley paid personally to
settle the case was unprecedented.
   ``The fact that he is the mayor, the chief executive officer of
the entire municipal corporation of Los Angeles, I think, holds him
to a high degree of requirement to fill out these statements of
economic interest accurately every year,'' Hahn said.
   The lawsuit was filed after the mayor revealed he had made more
than 100 errors and omissions in his statements of economic
interest from 1984 to 1988. At least $222,000 in investments and
income weren't reported; Hahn sued over $160,000 of it.
   The agreement settles only one aspect of Bradley's crisis over
ethics and finances.
   A federal grand jury is investigating the mayor's business ties
to eight banks, savings and loans associations and brokerage firms
for possible insider stock trading or violations of federal laws
aimed at political corruption.
</TEXT>

</DOC>