<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2349EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-China 4thLd-Writethru   12-19 0984</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-China, 4th Ld-Writethru,a0769,980</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Approves China Satellite Deal</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: CORRECTS Eagleburger's first name to Lawrence sted Brent in
5th graf: ``The furor,''</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERENCE HUNT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP White House Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush eased economic sanctions
against China on Tuesday as Secretary of State James A. Baker III
expressed ``regrets'' he may have misled Americans about high-level
U.S. contacts with Beijing.
   The White House announced that Bush had approved the export of
three communications satellites to be launched by China, and had
ended a prohibition on the Export-Import Bank providing help to
companies doing business in China.
   The president's actions came as Baker said through a spokeswoman
he regretted that in a recent television interview, he may have
misled the public about the two trips to China by high-level U.S.
officials.
   Whether the administration was misleading the public prompted
close questioning of White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater, who
mounted a vigorous defense of President Bush's secret contact with
the Chinese leadership.
   The furor erupted after it was learned Monday that national
security adviser Brent Scowcroft and Deputy Secretary of State
Lawrence Eagleburger had visited Beijing in secret in July, in
addition to their previously disclosed trip earlier this month.
   Bush notified Congress that he was exempting the three
communications satellites, which are being built or renovated by
the Hughes Aircraft Co., from economic sanctions imposed on China
after last June's crackdown in Tiananmen Square. Hughes is selling
the satellites to firms in Australia and Hong Kong for launch on a
Chinese rocket.
   ``The sale of these satellites represents approximately $300
million worth of business for U.S. firms,'' said a statement by
Fitzwater.
   The statement said the move was ``consistent with the
president's expressed determination, in imposing sanctions last
June, to maintain commercial relations with China.''
   The July trip came at a time when the administration said
high-level visits to Beijing were banned because of the violent
suppression of pro-democracy demonstrations in June.
   Baker, appearing on ABC-TV Dec. 10, called the December trip by
Scowcroft and Eagleburger ``the first time we've had high-level
U.S. officials go to the People's Republic of China.'' Baker noted
he himself had publicly met high Chinese officials in other
countries.
   Asked about the apparent discrepancy, spokeswoman Margaret D.
Tutwiler said Tuesday that Baker ``felt obligated to protect the
secrecy of a mission that the President wished to have classified.
He regrets that me may have misled some.''
   She added: ``He felt that by acknowledging his own direct
involvement it was sufficient to make the point that this (December
trip) was not the first case of high-level contact.''
   Before that statement, she had said Baker did not feel he had
lied.
   On the satellites, the White House statement said, ``Approval of
these licences is in keeping with the president's policy not to
disrupt normal commercial relations with China.''
   Sen. Albert Gore, D-Tenn., called Bush's approval ``a true
outrage'' and ``another effort to curry favor with the hardliners
in Beijing and an insult to the memory of those who died for
democracy in Tiananmen Square.''
   Gore sponsored the legislation that forbids the launch of
U.S.-manufacturered satellites Chinese rockets unless the president
declares it to be in the U.S. national interest, as Bush has done.
   Before the satellite announcement, Rep. Stephen Solarz, D-N.Y.,
said Bush's sending of high-level emissaries to China after the
violent Chinese crackdown on pro-democracy demonstrators ``makes
the president look like a wimp in Beijing and a hypocrite in
Washington.'' His comments were in a statement issued while he was
traveling in Nepal.
   Facing criticism from members of Congress that the
administration has been too friendly with China in the aftermath of
the June crackdown, the White House issued a separate two-page
``justification'' of the satellite action.
   ``After launch, they will be controlled for civil use,'' the
White House statement said. ``It is in the national interest of the
United States to approve export licernses for the three satellites
currently being prepared for launch in China.''
   Two of the satellites are being built by Hughes Aircraft Co. for
AUSSAT, an Australian company. The other one is being refurbished
by Hughes for AsiaSat, based in Hong Kong.
   The White House also cited ``national interest'' in waiving
restrictions on the Export-Import bank's financing of U.S. business
activities within China.
   The bank is a government agency which helps provide a range of
assistance to U.S. companies, including low-interest loans, to help
them set up overseas operations.
   The White House said the waiver ``preserves a level playing
field for U.S. business. Additional business activity with China
will be considered on a case-by-case basis as part of a continuing
review process.''
   Fitzwater, under close questioning by reporters, declared Bush
had not misled Americans, as critics contended.
   ``It is not misleading to not tell you about everything he's
doing,'' Fitzwater said.
   At the State Department's daily briefing, Tutwiler was asked
whether she felt the American public had been misled on U.S. policy
toward China.
   ``I certainly don't think that I've lied,'' she said. ``I know
Marlin doesn't think that he's lied. Secretary (of State James A.)
Baker doesn't think he's lied and the president doesn't think he's
lied.''
   Fitzwater said he could not comment on whether there had been
other trips to China that still remained secret.
   But he said, ``There have been trips you don't know about. There
will be more.''
   Fitzwater said Bush dispatched Scowcroft and Eagleburger in July
to make sure that China's hard-line leaders knew the seriousness of
U.S. anger over the crushing of the pro-democracy demonstrations.
   He said it was important to keep the trip secret so the Chinese
knew that denunciations of the crackdown were more than public
posturing.
   Denying that the administration had violated its own ban on
exchanges with China, Fitzwater said there never was any intention
to cut off all high-level contact. He said there was a distinction
between high-level ``exchanges'' and high-level ``contacts.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>