<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0166 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 2139EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MaineGov     12-29 0518</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Maine Gov,0537</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rep. Brennan Runs Again for Governor</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DIRK BEVERIDGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rep. Joseph E. Brennan, who left the
governor's mansion in 1987 as he traded jobs with then-Congressman
John R. McKernan, announced Friday he will challenge McKernan for
governor next year.
   Brennan, a Democrat, opened his campaign with an attack on
McKernan, a Republican who has not formally announced he is running
for re-election but makes no secret of his plans to run.
   ``Maine can do better than this,'' Brennan said. ``I think Maine
people deserve a better government than this. These are challenging
times. I want to get Maine moving forward again.''
   McKernan responded with a statement that defended his record and
accused Brennan of being indecisive throughout several months of
speculation about whether he would run.
   ``Clearly, this has not been an easy decision for Congressman
Brennan, as he has agonized publicly over a candidacy for months,''
McKernan responded.
   ``His hesitancy, his delay in reaching a decision until the last
possible moment, his seeming paralysis in addressing the issue of a
gubernatorial candidacy is, I think, revealing.''
   Brennan said he had made up his mind to run on Friday morning,
and he had not yet plotted out his campaign strategy.
   Brennan's statement said a formal announcement of his candidacy
would come later. McKernan promised a formal announcement of his
own candidacy in the ``not-so-distant future.''
   McKernan was making no comment beyond his prepared statement,
according to a spokeswoman in his Augusta office.
   Brennan's announcement Friday drew an immediate endorsement from
Senate Majority Leader George J. Mitchell, D-Maine, who defeated
Brennan in the 1974 Democratic gubernatorial primary.
   That election eventually was won by independent James B. Longley.
   It will be the fourth run for governor for Brennan, 55, who has
been in public life for a quarter of a century. He was a state
legislator when he entered his first primary and lost to Mitchell.
   Brennan went on to capture the Blaine House in 1978, serving the
maximum two terms before running successfully for the U.S. House of
Representatives in 1986. He was re-elected handily two years later.
   Brennan grew up on Portland's Munjoy Hill, the son of a
longshoreman. After Army duty, he went to Boston College on the GI
bill and then entered law school in Maine.
   After three terms in the Maine House, he was elected Cumberland
County district attorney in 1970. Two years later he was elected to
the state Senate and served as Democratic floor leader.
   Following his 1974 primary defeat, Brennan was elected by the
Legislature to serve as attorney general, a post he held until his
1978 election as governor.
   Four years later, Brennan carried all 16 counties as he defeated
Republican nominee Charles L. Cragin.
   Brennan acknowledged at the time that it was uncommon for
governors to go on to the House, giving up the perquisites of a
chief executive to become one vote among 435.
   However, he was assigned to the House Armed Services Committee _
a rarity for a freshman _ as well as Merchant Marine and Fisheries.
</TEXT>

</DOC>