<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0175 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2144EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-UN 1stLd-Writethru a0735 12-21 0647</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-UN, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0735,0669</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S.-Backed Envoy: Noriega Should be Tried in Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS throughout to UPDATE with session ending, council unable
to decide which gov't to recognize, countries denounce U.S. action. No
pickup.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VICTORIA GRAHAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>UNITED NATIONS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The designated U.N. envoy of the
U.S.-installed government in Panama said Thursday that if Gen.
Manuel Antonio Noriega is captured, he should not be extradited to
the United States but tried in Panama.
   Later Thursday, the 15-member Security Council debated the
Panama invasion, with many governments denouncing the United
States. But the council could not decide which government to
recognize _ Noriega's or the U.S.-backed government of Guillermo
Endara _ and no further meeting was scheduled.
   Both sides have sought to have their ambassadors accredited to
the United Nations, which can recognize only one of them.
   Eduardo Vallarino, a self-exiled Panamanian businessman, was
nominated as Panama's U.N. ambassador by Endara's government,
installed by U.S. troops at a military base Wednesday.
   Vallarino told a news conference that Panama's Constitution
prohibits extradition. If Noriega is captured by occupying U.S.
forces, he said, Panama would protest his extradition to face
narcotics charges in the United States.
   ``I would have to say that probably the Panamanian government
would have to protest,'' Vallarino said in answer to a question.
   ``If Noriega is apprehended by the authorities in Panama, he
will have to be duly charged and tried in Panama,'' Vallarino said.
   But he added that the situation is ``irregular.''
   He also said the Endara group had not sought U.S. intervention
in Panama, but welcomed it.
   Secretary-General Javier Perez de Cuellar, in his first comment
on the U.S. intervention, said: ``The position of the U.N. for the
last 45 years is that we always regret the use of force.''
   He added that he hoped the Security Council would reach
agreement ``to restore order in Panama.''
   He spoke before the council reconvened at the request of
Nicaragua, which along with the Soviet Union condemned the U.S.
invasion Wednesday night.
   Nicaragua seeks council condemnation of the U.S. military
action, but the United States and Britain could veto any critical
resolution.
   Discussion of credentials by the Security Council is rare and
has not occurred in recent memory.
   The Noriega government is not represented in the United Nations
because the previous envoy, Leonardo Kam, has been promoted to
foreign minister. That government is trying to accredit as U.N.
envoy its ambassador to the European Community, Mirla Bellavita.
   U.N. diplomats, speaking on condition of anonymity, said they
expected the council would not take up the question of competing
claims. They said the council was likely to ask the
secretary-general for a report. The secretary-general, however, had
said he hoped the council would decide the question.
   The question ultimately could be passed on to the General
Assembly, diplomats said. But according to the U.N. Charter, the
159-nation assembly cannot take up a question while it is under
consideration by the council, without a request by the council.
   The U.N. legal department is studying the question.
   The Organization of American States in Washington declined to
recognize the Endara government Wednesday.
   Vietnam's invasion of Cambodia in late 1978 posed a similar
problem for the General Assembly, which refused to recognize the
Vietnam-installed government and still recocognizes the ousted
Cambodian government in exile, headed by Prince Norodom Sihanouk
and his allies.
   Speakers from 10 countries addressed the council Thursday, and
all except El Salvador denounced the U.S. invasion, although some
also criticized Noriega.
   El Salvador did not specifically endorse the U.S. action, but
criticized Noriega's undermining of democracy and
self-determination in Panama.
   Peru was especially vocal in condemning ``flagrant violation of
Panama's sovereignty'' in what it called ``a grim updating of
imperialist practices.''
   Other speakers included Algeria, Brazil, Cuba, Ethiopia, Finland
and Libya. In the first debate Wednesday night, only Britain
staunchly backed the U.S. action.
</TEXT>

</DOC>