<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0151 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2035EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Judge-Explosion 4thLd-Writethru a0735 12-19 1050</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Judge-Explosion, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0735,1,020</SECOND>
<HEAD>Investigators Looking At Possibility Bombings Were Racially Motivated</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: INSERTS grafs 13-15: ``An anonymous,'' with August anonymous
letter; following graf edited for transition; drops last two grafs to trim</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES ROWLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Federal investigators are concentrating on a
possible racial motivation in the two fatal mail-bombings in the
South over the past four days, the Justice Department said Thursday.
   FBI Director William Sessions indicated that no suspect had been
identified in the bombings. ``As far as I know there's been no
claimant of responsibility at all,'' Sessions said at a news
conference at the Justice Department.
   He said, however, that ``in the back of all of our minds'' is
the possibility that the bombs were the result of racial feelings
over desegregation cases.
   Mail bombs killed 11th Circuit Judge Robert S. Vance at his home
near Birmingham, Ala., on Saturday, and Savannah, Ga., Alderman
Robert E. Robinson on Monday. In addition, authorities removed
bombs from a courthouse in Atlanta on Monday, and from the NAACP
headquarters in Jacksonville, Fla., on Tuesday.
   Vance recently wrote an opinion in a school desegregation case
that was a victory for the Jacksonville NAACP.
   Attorney General Dick Thornburgh called the incidents ``an
affront to our nation's commitment to the rule of law.''
   He said in a statement that the investigation is ``currently
concentrating on a possible racial motivation to the incidents
which have occurred in the past four days.''
   Thornburgh said he had contacted civil rights leaders ``to
assure them that we are fully committed to the vigorous
investigations of these crimes and the apprehension of the person
or persons who perpetuated them.''
   He stressed, however, that ``no firm conclusion'' about
motivation has been reached. And Sessions said, ``I would not rule
out drugs as potentially being involved but that is not a
conclusion'' that can be reached at this time.
   Sessions said the bureau was studying Vance's court docket to
determine if he participated in any cases that might have produced
racial anger.
   In September, Vance wrote the court's unanimous opinion that
ordered the Jacksonville, Fla., schools to continue busing to
achieve racial integration.
   The case was won by the Jacksonville NAACP, which had appealed a
lower court's ruling that busing could stop.
   An anonymous letter was sent from Atlanta to a Jackson, Miss.,
television station in August declaring war on the 11th Circuit, the
station, WAPT-TV, reported Tuesday night.
   ``We turned it right over to the FBI,'' said reporter Deanna Lee
in a telephone interview. Lee said the letter bore an Aug. 21
postmark. The day before that a tear-gas cannister exploded at the
NAACP headquarters in Atlanta, injuring eight people.
   FBI spokesman Charles Steinmetz confirmed that the FBI had
opened an investigation into the letter soon after the television
station had passed it along.
   Sessions said the FBI did not detect any similarity between the
recent bomb incidents and activities of known white supremacist
groups ``but it is something you cannot rule out.''
   ``We would hope the patterns of these types of groups when
studied carefully and compared will yield fruit,'' Sessions said.
   Sessions ticked off a handful of federal agencies at work on the
cases, and offered blunt advice for anyone involved in the criminal
justice system who receives a suspicious package: ``Don't try to
open it.''
   ``I see no reason to panic but I see every reason to be
cautious,'' he said.
   Sessions brushed aside questions on the specifics of the case,
refusing to say whether the bombs were the work of experts, whether
the bomb to Vance bore a postmark of Newnan, Ga., and what
similarities, if any existed among the bombs.
   Asked about the complexity of the bombs, Sessions indicated that
they were not necessarily the work of explosive experts. ``I would
not comment about the specific devices themselves, but laymen have
been knwon to devise those kinds of instruments,'' Sessions said.
   As for a positive racial motivation, Sessions said, ``When the
NAACP headquarters receives a suspicious package, an alderman is
killed, you have to have that in the back of your mind.''
   Asked about a suspect, the FBI director said:
   ``I would not refer to any suspect at all if I had one at this
stage.''
   But he did say he thought it was ``quite possible there is more
than one person'' behind the crimes.
   Sessions said ``every available investigative resource is being
utilized'' to lead authorities to the ``perpetrator or perpetrators
of these horrible crimes.''
   In the meantime, he said the U.S. Marshals Service could keep
judges safe, and he appealed to all to exercise extreme care in
opening suspicious packages _ to the point of advising them to call
the return addressee to make sure a parcel was safe.
   Earlier Tuesday, authorities said the bombs that killed Vance
and Robinson were both packed with nails, suggesting links to the
device sent to the Atlanta courthouse.
   ``There's a strong similarity in the three explosive devices,
and it appears there is a relationship,'' FBI agent Tom Moore said
in Birmingham.
   A government source in Washington said the package containing
the bomb that killed Vance bore the return address of a another
11th Circuit judge, Lewis F. Morgan.
   Morgan, who had previously sent packages to Vance, is not a
suspect but the evidence suggests that the killer was famliar with
the two judges' friendship, said the source, who spoke on condition
of anonymity.
   The bomb contained nails, and injured the judge's wife.
   In Savannah, Mayor John Rousakis said authorities confirmed that
nails also had been packed in the bomb that killed Robinson, who
had represented the NAACP in a long-running desegregation lawsuit
involving Savannah schools.
   The 11th Circuit, which considers federal cases from Georgia,
Florida and Alabama, had last month upheld the Savannah school
board's decision to change its desegregation plan.
   The NAACP had objected to the changes that were also approved by
a federal district judge. Vance did not participate in that case,
according to Julius Chambers, director of the NAACP Legal and
Educational Defense Fund, Inc.
   The nine judges on the 11th Circuit were under round-the-clock
guard, federal marshals said. The bomb removed without incident
from the court's Atlanta headquarters on Monday was addressed to
the ``Clerk of Court 11th Circuit,'' government sources said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>