<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0140 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1737EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Ceausescu     12-18 0571</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ceausescu,0593</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romania's Ceausescu Visits Tehran Amid Turmoil at Home</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto TEH2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANWAR FARUQI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Romanian President Nicolae Ceausescu and
his Iranian counterpart Hashemi Rafsanjani began talks in Tehran on
Monday to cement economic ties amid political turbulence in Romania
stirred by Eastern Europe's reformist wave.
   The Islamic Republic News Agency said the two met shortly after
Ceausescu arrived on a three-day official visit. It said further
meetings were planned to bolster political and economic links.
   Ceausescu told Rafsanjani, ``I am pleased to be the first
president to visit Iran after your election,'' Tehran radio
reported.
   Rafsanjani, elected president in July, assured Ceausescu ``there
are many fields of cooperation in boosting bilateral trade,'' it
added.
   IRNA and the radio were both monitored in Nicosia.
   Referring to Ceausescu's inflexibility while the political
change surged through Eastern Europe, IRNA praised Romania as ``the
sole East European country rigidly adhering to its past
government.''
   Ceausescu, elected Romanian Communist Party chief in 1965, is
the longest-serving leader in the Soviet bloc.
   He has stamped out almost all dissent in Romania. His crash
industrialization program and his frantic efforts to repay all of
Romania's $11 billion debt have led to perennial shortages of
consumer goods and rationing of basic foodstuffs.
   On Monday, Romania sealed its border with Yugoslavia to all but
official traffic after an anti-government demonstration turned
violent in Timisoara, west Romania.
   The Iranian agency said others attending Monday's talks in
Tehran were Foreign Minister Ali Akbar Velayati, Vice President
Masoud Roghani Zanjani and Heavy Industries Minister Hadi
Nejad-Husseinian of Iran, and Deputy Prime Minister Ion Radu,
Foreign Minister Ion Stoian and presidential adviser Constantion
Mitea of Romania.
   Ceausescu's politically powerful wife Elena stayed behind in
Romania, although she usually accompanies her husband on trips
abroad.
   Ceausescu will complete agreements reached by the
Tehran-Bucharest commission that met in Iran last week.
   ``The Iran-Romania summit is an expression of the positive
course of relations between our countries and people,' Ceausescu
was quoted as telling the English-language daily, the Tehran Times.
   Contacts so far were having good results ``especially in
economic and technical-scientific cooperation,'' he said in
excerpts quoted by IRNA. The interview apparently was conducted
earlier in Bucharest.
   Romania is a major trading partner with Iran.
   The agreements Ceausescu is expected to conclude will boost
their volume of trade from about $1.8 billion this year to $3
billion, IRNA said.
   Tehran radio reported Sunday that Iran will export about 1
million barrels of oil and 1 billion cubic meters of natural gas a
year to Romania.
   The agreement was concluded Sunday at a meeting between Iranian
Oil Minister Gholamreza Aqazadeh and Radu.
   Iran earlier this year announced plans to export 5 million
metric tons of crude oil to Romania in return for tractors, oil
drilling equipment and military equipment, including tanks.
   IRNA said that under Sunday's agreement, Romania will supply
equipment for constructing Tehran's subway system.
   Romanian experts are also working with the Iranians on a major
irrigation dam project at Raveh, 20 miles south of Tehran.
   Budapest radio, quoting unidentified witnesses, said security
forces on Monday sealed off Timisoara, which has a population of
350,000 and is the largest city in the ethnically mixed region of
Transylvania.
   Reports of deaths there have surfaced.
   Romanian emigres said thousands of demonstrators battled
security forces over the weekend after ransacking a library and
burning books by Ceausescu.

</TEXT>

</DOC>