<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1302EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Poland     12-23 0574</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland,0590</SECOND>
<HEAD>Poland Signs Agreement to Get Millions in Western Credit</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DRUSILLA MENAKER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Poland has formally agreed to overhaul its
economy in exchange for $700 million in immediate credit from the
International Monetary Fund and the promise of billions more in
Western aid, officials said Saturday.
   Deputy Prime Minister Leszek Balcerowicz and the chairman of the
National Bank of Poland, Wladyslaw Baka signed a letter of intent
that was approved by the IMF executive board in Washington, the
state news agency PAP said.
   The first credit installment could be received as early as next
week, PAP reported.
   Acceptance of the letter also launches a $1 billion fund being
prepared by Western countries to back the Polish currency, PAP said.
   Prime Minister Tadeusz Mazowiecki and his Council of Ministers
met through the night Friday, reviewing the plan in which Poland
vows to choke off 900 percent inflation, cut budget deficits and
weather the unemployment and poverty that the painful economic
reforms are likely to bring.
   The plan, negotiated since Mazowiecki formed the East bloc's
first government led by non-Communists in September, is tied to the
most extensive economic reform legislation ever attempted in the
region.
   Introduced in Parliament a week ago, the program would overhaul
the centralized state-run economy and replace it with a
market-oriented system.
   The IMF agreement will certify to Western leaders that Poland is
making serious efforts to put its economy in order and is expected
to release further loans from the World Bank and other sources. It
is also critical to arranging the rescheduling of payments on
Poland's $40 billion debt to the West.
   ``It was signed during the night. It was important to sign it as
soon as possible because the money could come pretty soon,'' said
Tomasz Drzewosowski, director of the government press office.
   In addition to the $700 million standby loan, the IMF letter of
intent is expected to lead to $300 million in World Bank loans and
about $3 billion in other Western aid.
   The $1 billion currency stabilization fund is expected to be
ready early in 1990.
   Poland is working to make its zloty internally convertible with
the hard currencies of the West, a step important to attracting the
Western business investment badly needed to replace Poland's
outmoded and unproductive industries.
   The government has asked Parliament for speedy approval of the
economic reform legislation so it can be implemented Jan. 1.
   Deputy Finance Minister Janusz Sawicki has said that if the IMF
money were not ready by Jan. 1, several Western countries probably
would offer a bridge loan until the first installment arrives.
   The IMF, one of the biggest lenders to Third World counties, is
owned by 152 governments, with the United States holding the
largest number of votes.
   The economic program anticipates that Poles' real income will
fall 20 percent, there will be a 5 percent decrease in industrial
output, and a 2 percent to 3 percent drop in the gross national
product.
   Price increases of 25 to 50 percent a month during early 1990
are expected as enterprises raise prices to survive after losing
production subsidies that have kept charges artificially low and
maintained unprofitable firms.
   Many bankruptcies are likely. The government is planning the
country's first unemployment benefits and estimates there will be
400,000 workers displaced. Under the communist system, unemployment
and poverty officially did not exist and there has been no welfare
structure.
</TEXT>

</DOC>