<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0050EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama 5thLd-Writethru a0845 12-22 1052</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0845,1088</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>U.S. Planes Bomb Resistance Pocket in Panama City</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS throughout to UPDATE with more fighting, locations, details.
No pickup</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos DOD06,DOD07,FAY1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two U.S. planes late Thursday bombed
a strong pocket of resistance in the capital manned by troops loyal
to fugitive Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega as the second day of the
American invasion ended.
   Flares lighted the moonless sky. Helicopters flew low over parts
of Panama City, shining bright lights.
   On Thursday afternoon, hours before the bombing, U.S. troops on
armored personnel carriers shouted over megaphones for residents
near the Tinajitas garrison in the northeastern San Miguelito
neighborhood to evacuate. Sporadic machine-gun fire could be heard.
   U.S. soldiers throughout Thursday ducked occasional gunfire in
mop-up operations and ringed the Nicaraguan and Cuban embassies
with armored personnel carriers in case the elusive Noriega was
inside.
   Thousands of U.S. servicemen swept into Panama City on the
second day of their huge offensive, trying to wipe out die-hard
resisters and hunting for Noriega, while also searching for missing
Americans believed to be hostages.
   President Bush pledged in Washington Thursday that U.S. forces
would scour Panama ``as long as it takes'' to capture Noriega. He
said the military operation he ordered created stability in Panama
and said ``it's been worth'' the American lives it cost, while
expressing sorrow over the deaths.
   He has ordered a $1 million bounty for the capture of Noriega,
who has been charged in the United States with drugrunning and
money-laundering.
   Looters swarmed the streets of Panama City like locusts
Thursday. Thousands, from children to grandparents, stripped store
shelves down to bare wood on Central Avenue.
   U.S. soldiers were too busy with snipers and small bands of
armed Noriega loyalists to challenge the looters.
   The force in San Miguelito was composed of fighters from the
civilian, paramilitary ``Dignity Battalions'' and other Noriega
loyalists.
   U.S. armored personnel carriers were seen heading Thursday night
toward San Miguelito, a large working-class neighborhood of 340,000
people.
   Residents said people they believed were Panamanian combatants
were fleeing to more secure areas and the poor were being evacuated.
   Elsewhere, machine guns rattled and explosions boomed near Cerro
Patacon hill behind Santa Maria University, close to U.S. Army
communications installations.
   Pentagon officials said U.S. troops had military control of
Panama City. They said most units of Noriega's Defense Forces had
fled into the jungles, and U.S. troops may be ordered in to follow
them.
   They reported 21 Americans killed, 208 wounded and four missing
in two days of fighting.
   Figures for Panamanian casualties were hard to come by.
   An official in the office of Leonardo Diaz, medical director of
the Santo Tomas Hospital, said the hospital had taken in 80 dead
and more than 1,000 wounded.
   ``We have really lost count of the wounded,'' she said, refusing
to give her name. She said many of the wounded were civilians
coming from areas of fighting near Defense Forces barracks.
   ``The morgue is now full. We have no place to put the dead,''
she said.
   She added the hospital was running low on medical supplies.
   Santo Tomas is the hospital nearest the bombed and burned-out
Panamanian Defense Forces headquarters, flattened on the first
night of the invasion.
   An exhausted emergency room doctor at the hospital could give no
breakdown of civilian or military casualties. The Dignity
Battalions and some of Noriega's elite units, such as the Machos de
Monte, wear civilian clothing.
   A Spanish photographer was killed and a French and an English
photographer were wounded Thursday in crossfire between U.S. troops
who mistook each other for Panamanian forces in the Marriott Hotel
parking lot, other journalists said.
   An Associated Press photographer saw flares being fired Thursday
night near Anton, 60 miles southwest of Panama City and a few miles
from the Panamanian Defenese Forces base of Rio Hato. People were
taking refuge in a local school.
   Troops from the 82nd Airborne Division stopped the photographer,
Matias Recart, at Anton and refused to let him continue to Panama
City.
   Residents said Panamanians attacked American positions at Rio
Hato, then apparently went into the mountains.
   Dignity Battalions were seen at several points between Anton and
the western city of David.
   China on Friday came to Noriega's defense, saying U.S. troops
invaded because the Panamanian strongman opposed U.S. attempts to
gain permanent control over the Panama Canal. The official Xinhua
News Agency called it a ``rather novel and sensational'' cliche
that America sent troops to bring to trial ``what it called a `drug
trafficker.''
   In Managua, the Nicaraguan capital, officials ordered troops and
armored vehicles to encircle the U.S. Embassy because of its
embassy in Panama City was surrounded by American forces.
   Defense Secretary Dick Cheney said in a TV interview that
reinforcements sent to aid the troops based in Panama may be able
to leave ``within a few weeks.'' Earlier, officials said they hoped
the action could take three days.
   Looters who capitalized on the chaos set up stands in alleyways
and sidewalks to hawk their wares to jostling hordes of Christmas
buyers.
   Slumdwellers peddled designer brassieres, French champagne and
Gucci watches at bargain prices. Ritzy stores on Avenida Espana,
Panama's main thoroughfare, were stripped of goods.
   ``Look,'' a young man said proudly, showing a gold watch. ``I
bought it for $20, the salesman didn't even realize it is a Gucci.''
   New President Guillermo Endara, sworn in by a Panamanian judge
as U.S. forces invaded at midnight Tuesday, announced an 18-hour
curfew that ends at 6 a.m. Friday. It had no immediate effect on
the crowds.
   Panama's newly installed leaders appeared at the legislative
assembly building under heavy U.S. guard. U.S. soldiers in jeans,
sweatshirts and other civilian clothes were sprinkled throughout
the building.
   Scattered bursts of gunfire came San Miguelito and from a
central hotel district taken over temporarily by armed Noriega
supporters. They did not appear to be seeking confrontation with
U.S. forces, however, but vandalized and looted hotel rooms and
stole cars.
   In Chitre, 100 miles southwest of Panama City, a Panamanian
Defense Forces officer said the garrison of about 200 men had not
been attacked.
   ``We are with ... (Noriega) until the last bullet. We are ready
for the gringos. We are waiting for orders,'' he said.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>