<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0085 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1432EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Poland     12-30 0655</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland,0677</SECOND>
<HEAD>Parliament Approves Sweeping Democratic Reforms; Restores Historic
Name</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH G. SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Parliament on Saturday approved sweeping
democratic reforms that for the first time in 45 years allow the
formation of new political parties, protect private property and
scrap the Communists' guaranteed leading role in society.
   Lawmakers also restored Poland's historic name and national
emblem, both changed after the Soviet-backed Communists took power
in 1944.
   In an emotional end to the session's work, members rose and sang
the national anthem and ``God Who Watches Over Poland.''
   The two houses of Parliament had met in almost constant session
over the past four days, passing the most radical economic reforms
ever attempted in the East bloc and creating a more democratic
constitution.
   ``I am optimistic,'' Solidarity Prime Minister Tadeusz
Mazowiecki told reporters during a reception in Parliament when
asked what he thought the coming year would bring.
   The constitutional amendments give citizens the right to create
independent political parties. Until now, the Communist Party, the
Democratic Party and the Peasant Party were the only legally
recognized parties in Poland. Solidarity, which began as a labor
union, has become a de facto political party.
   The amended constitution also guarantees the protection of
private property, much of which was seized by the Communists at the
end of World War II.
   The Senate approved the changes on a 79-0 vote with two
abstentions. The Sejm, as the lower house of Parliament is called,
adopted the amendments 374-1 with 11 abstentions late Friday, but
Senate approval of Sejm votes is required for bills to become law.
   The amendments drop or modify articles in the constitution
inconsistent with democratic reforms introduced since Solidarity
scored a stunning victory in June elections that led to formation
of the East bloc's first non-Communist government.
   The amendments restored the Republic of Poland as the country's
official name from the People's Republic of Poland, which was
imposed by the Communists four decades ago.
   A smiling announcer on the late afternoon news program
TeleExpress greeted viewers in the ``Republic of Poland.''
   Following similar action in other formerly rigid Communist
countries in Eastern Europe, the Parliament deleted a
constitutional clause that guaranteed the leading role of the
Communist Party in society.
   The amendments also restored democratic language and traditions,
changing a phrase that called Poland a ``socialist society'' to a
``citizens' society.''
   In addition, the pre-war crown that graced the head of the eagle
on the national emblem was restored. The crown symbolizes Polish
sovereignty and unity.
   After the Senate vote, an eagle with a crown, brought two weeks
earlier by a farmer, was hung in the Senate hall.
   The farmer, whose name was not noted when he made the gift to
the Senate's Human Rights Commission, said the eagle was the only
souvenir he had of his father.
   In addition to their legislative sessions, Poland's political
leaders, who less than a year ago were at odds with each other, met
to exchange greetings for the New Year.
   Solidarity leader Lech Walesa met Saturday with Communist Party
leader Mieczyslaw F. Rakowski. Mazowiecki met with Communist
President Wojciech Jaruzelski on Friday after Cardinal Jozef Glemp
made the first postwar visit by a Polish primate to Parliament.
   On Friday, the Senate approved a package of 11 economic laws
backed by the Solidarity-led government to create a market-oriented
economy and reduce inflation.
   If successful, the economic package, which covers credit policy,
joint ventures, foreign capital, hard currency, customs and
taxation, will transform economic life in Poland.
   Two laws on unemployment are designed to protect the 400,000
workers the government estimates could lose their jobs as Poland
makes the difficult transition to a market economy. The plan is
likely to result in the closing of some inefficient enterprises.
   Other laws regulate financing of state enterprises and limit the
growth of wages, a measure designed to hold down inflation now
running at 900 percent.
</TEXT>

</DOC>