<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0272 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2127EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-InsiderTrading     12-21 0353</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Insider Trading,0364</SECOND>
<HEAD>SEC Accuses 2 Connecticut Men of Insider Trading Scheme</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN M. DOYLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two Connecticut men were accused in a civil
complaint Thursday of an insider trading scheme involving Saatchi &amp;
Saatchi's tender offer for Gartner Group Inc., said federal
regulators.
   The Securities and Exchange Commission said it filed a civil
complaint at federal court in Connecticut against Robert Charles
Troup and Helmut August Alpers, both of New Canaan, Conn.
   Troup was accused of making $78,812 in illegal trading profits
with insider information about Gartner Group allegedly supplied by
Alpers, an executive vice president with the Stamford, Conn.,
market research and data processing company.
   Alpers, who was not accused of sharing in the alleged ill gotten
gains, agreed to settle the charges without admitting or denying
wrongdoing, the SEC said.
   Alpers consented to an injunction that bars him from violating
federal securities laws and agreeed to pay $78,812 in penalties
under the Insider Trading Sanctions Act, which requires insiders
who share confidential information top pay a sum equal to alleged
illegal profits even if they did not share in them.
   Troup has not settled the charges, according to the SEC.
   Troup's lawyer in Stamford and Alpers' attorney in Washington
were not in their offices when called for comment Thursday evening.
The SEC complaint did not disclose what Troup did for a living or
how the two men knew each other.
   According to the SEC, Alpers allegedly obtained inside
information in May 1988 that Saatchi &amp; Saatchi, the British
advertising agency, intended to acquire Gartner Group and tipped
Troup to the upcoming deal a month later.
   The SEC complaint alleged that on the morning of June 13, 1988,
Troup bought 22,000 shares of Gartner Group common stock, paid for
in part with an $82,500 loan from Alpers. Later that day Gartner
Group publicly disclosed that it was engaged in sales discussions
with an unidentified company.
   According to the complaint, Troup sold 14,000 Gartner shares on
June 13 and the rest on June 17, after Saatchi &amp; Saatchi publicly
announced its tender offer for Gartner.
</TEXT>

</DOC>