<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0138EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-RetirementHomeFire 6thLd-Writethru a0440 12-25 0479</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Retirement Home Fire, 6th Ld-Writethru, a0440,0491</SECOND>
<HEAD>15 Dead in Retirement Home Fire, Search Continues for More Bodies</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 6 grafs to UPDATE with fire under control, two searches
failing to turn up bodies but search continuing, details, quotes, DELETES
outdated quote; picks up 7th graf, `About 145 ...'.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JOHNSON CITY, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fire swept through a 10-story
retirement home Christmas Eve, killing at least 15 people,
authorities said. At least 26 people were injured.
   Firefighters had the blaze under control early Monday as
rescuers continued to hunt for people who might be trapped in the
John Sevier Retirement Center, city spokeswoman Linda Gordon told a
news conference.
   Fifteen deaths were confirmed late Sunday, and two searches of
the building shortly before midnight failed to turn up any more
bodies, Ms. Gordon said.
   ``Firefighters are still in the building,'' she said early
Monday. ``We'll be searching all night. We've swept the building
completely two times ... The fire chief says we'll go in from top
to bottom at least two more times.''
   A temporary morgue was set up at the Washington County
Courthouse in this eastern Tennessee city in the Appalachian
Mountains, said rescue worker John Charlton.
   Charlton said a few hours after the fire broke out that workers
at the morgue were ``preparing for 50 people at this point. It
could be four more, it could be 40 more. We really don't have a
handle on it.''
   About 145 people were living at the center, but authorities said
they didn't know how many were in the building when the fire broke
out around 5:30 p.m.
   ``But it being Christmas Eve, many residents were out of the
building visiting families and many relatives were visiting at the
center,'' said Ms. Gordon.
   The cause of the fire was not immediately known, but it was
believed to have started on the second floor, officials said.
   The names of the dead were not released pending notification of
relatives.
   Three people were admitted to Northside Hospital, where they
were treated for smoke inhalation, said hospital spokesman Dan
Blevins. At least one person suffered serious burns, he said.
   Two people were admitted to the Veterans Administration hospital
for smoke inhalation, a spokesperson said.
   Twenty-one others were admitted to hospitals for observation,
officials said.
   Firefighters and rescue workers from around the region battled
the blaze in temperatures that only reached the teens.
   ``We've received a tremendous amount of help,'' Charlton said.
   A basement rescue station was set up across the street at Munsey
Memorial United Methodist Church, where medical workers treated
residents initially. The American Red Cross set up an information
center for relatives in the church auditorium.
   The fire is the second at the center within recent weeks. The
earlier fire was contained to one unit, but the building was
evacuated.
   Johnson City is about 100 miles northeast of Knoxville.
</TEXT>

</DOC>