<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0213 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1434EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i AM-FixingtheSphinx Adv25   12-18 0706</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fixing the Sphinx, Adv 25,0725</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv25</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Monday AMs, Dec. 25, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Once Again, Intensive Care Ordered for Ailing Sphinx</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIMI MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GIZA PLATEAU, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tourists can still see the subtle
smile but little else of the Sphinx, the half man, half beast
crouched in the desert sands guarding the pyramids.
   The smile projects above protective scaffolding being erected to
envelop the chest of the ailing 4,600-year-old statue as Egyptian
authorities try yet another remedy for the ills afflicting one of
the world's best-known monuments.
   The effort has surrounded the stoic stone statue with turbaned
workers prying rocks from his massive paws, sticking sensors into
his backside or hammering on the wooden chest girdle.
   Scaffolding first appeared at the Sphinx's right shoulder in the
spring of 1988, shortly after a rock broke off and tumbled to the
ground. More weak spots were discovered, and now the framework is
being extended across the famous frontal view.
   Prime Minister Atef Sedki of Egypt made an official inspection
visit, seeking to determine whether restoration begun in 1982,
which covered the front paws and other portions with concrete
blocks, helped or harmed the Sphinx.
   ``There's no threat to the Sphinx,'' Sedki said after the visit.
But he added: ``Although I'm not a technical man, I can see with my
eyes that former restoration work was wrong.
   ``The government will not deny any financial support that the
new restoration work requires. The important thing is to save the
statue that symbolizes the Egyptian civilization.''
   Sayed Tawfik, chairman of the Egyptian Antiquities Organization,
said the latest effort calls for removing all large restoration
stones attached since 1982.
   Restoration was being done on the Sphinx at least 3,000 years
ago. But Tawfik, climbing atop the front paws, said a key
difference in the current project is that for the first time,
restorers will try to ensure that the repaired Sphinx looks like
the Sphinx.
   Earlier restorations in the 1980s, he said, simply coated
endangered areas without regard to the shape the ancients carved.
   ``There's a 10-centimeter (four-inch) difference in the original
shape of the paws and in restoration stones that cover them,''
Tawfik said. ``You can't even imagine how the Sphinx should look. ''
   He said the Egyptian-born artist and sculptor Adam Henein has
been brought from Paris to help restore the body to its original
form.
   ``We're studying hundreds of pictures taken since the middle of
the last century, even when it was almost totally buried, for clues
to how the Sphinx looked,'' he said.
   Concrete blocks have been numbered and are being carried from
the site as smaller replacement stones from the Giza Plateau are
installed. Greeks and Romans restoring the monument more than 2,000
years ago also used small blocks, and Tawfik said their work is
better than any by modern restorers.
   ``Restoration begun in 1982 proved awfully bad because large
stones were used that completely damaged the Sphinx,'' said Zahi
Hawass, director of the pyramids area.
   ``Also, they used cement and gypsum, so now not only are we
looking at bad rock that has always been in the Sphinx but also at
rock that's been damaged from bad restoration.''
   Criticism of the 1980s restoration has been common for years and
the Sphinx has become a political issue as well as a scientific one.
   The latest controversy began in mid-November with stories in
newspapers speculating that mischief felled the chunk of stone from
the Sphinx's right shoulder on Feb. 7, 1988.
   Tawfik and other experts responded by saying scientists studied
the rockfall for a year before deciding it occurred in a section of
limestone weakened by salt, wind and other natural phenomena. The
dispute raged for weeks.
   The Sphinx is likely to have little peace for quite a while.
   ``The Sphinx is like Lebanon, with militias tearing at each
other,'' said Omar el-Arini, a member of the antiquities
organization's scientific committee and a science officer at the
U.S. Embassy.
   ``He's a 50-million-year-old man, because that's how old the
rock is. How do you restore him? Do you rejuvenate him? Do you
treat his ailments?
   ``What's missing here is a general plan.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Monday AMs, Dec. 25</NOTE>

</DOC>