<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0085 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1436EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-ExecutiveAid Bjt   12-17 0658</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Executive Aid, Bjt,0680</SECOND>
<HEAD>Retired Executives Lend Their Business Savvy to Poles</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JILL ARABAS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>STAMFORD, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For 25 years, Tom Carroll's volunteer
service corps has sent retired executives overseas to lend their
business expertise to foreign companies.
   Now several of his retirees are getting ready to pack their bags
and head for a new frontier: Eastern Europe.
   Carroll's organization, the International Executive Service
Corps, has embarked on an ambitious project to help meat
processors, textile factories and other government-owned businesses
in Poland. The first executive left in October, and others will
head for the airport after the first of the year.
   The projects are a way for Polish operations to learn Western
businesses ways, while giving retired executives an opportunity to
pass along their skills. The government-owned companies pay the
executives' expenses and also provide interpreters.
   The work in Poland comes as Eastern European nations undergo
revolutionary changes in their governments and economies.
   ``This is such a fantastic, magical time in the history of man.
It is a major renaissance of our time, an industrial revolution,''
said Carroll, who keeps miniature flags of several countries in his
ninth floor office in Stamford, overlooking Long Island Sound.
   ``We've got plenty of men we hope will play a major part in the
progress in Hungary and Poland,'' said Carroll, the chief executive
officer of Lever Brothers before becoming president of the corps in
1981. He is one of 50 paid employees.
   The corps, which has 10,700 volunteers, was founded in 1964 by
David Rockefeller and Sol Linowitz, who separately thought up the
idea of sending retired executives overseas. Since then, volunteers
have worked on more than 12,000 projects in 90 countries.
   The projects in the East bloc began in 1986 when a volunteer
went to Hungary to help a meat processing plant.
   ``It was so successful that when the guy went home, they wanted
him back,'' Carroll said.
   The first Polish project began in October when a former
manufacturing executive left his Texas home to advise a synthetic
fiber operation. Another 10 to 25 projects are expected next year,
said vice president Charles Neiswender.
   Pete Moyer, one of 39 executive recruiters, sat in Carroll's
office last week and briefed him on some of the projects, such as
plans to send a former executive with International Harvester to
advise a Polish tractor factory.
   He said a former RCA executive was leaving Jan. 5 to advise the
managers of an old television tube plant. Another retiree will
leave in April to advise a textile manufacturer.
   The corps is still looking for an executive to advise a copper
mining and smelting operation.
   Officials said many Poles already understand the way a
capitalist economy works, partly because of the black market that
has flourished through the 40 years of Communist rule that
officially ended in September.
   But Moyer said the government-owned operations need help in
organization.
   ``This picture tube outfit said they have 5,500 employees and
over 140 organization units, each of which has its own program and
plan, much of the time not being consistent with what top
management sees as the overall plan,'' he said. ``So they need
help.''
   Neiswender said employee motivation is another concern among
workers not used to the incentive system.
   ``Many of these government-owned companies have so many
employees that productive people are unproductive because they have
to trip on and step over the unproductive,'' he said.
   But Moyer, who worked on one of 17 projects in Hungary, said the
Eastern Europeans are eager to learn.
   ``What struck me was the hospitality, and from a philosophical
point of view, the eagerness to learn the know-how of American and
Western European practices, to understand how to run an
organization,'' he said.
   ``These are smart people. They're bright people. They're not
saying, `We're dumb, teach us something we don't know.' They're
saying, `We're coming from a different way, teach us something
different.'''
</TEXT>

</DOC>