<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0214 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1305EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f AM-BusinessMirror Adv21   12-19 0572</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Business Mirror, Adv 21,0590</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv21</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release AMs Thursday, Dec. 21</HEAD>
<HEAD>Shakeout In The Automotive Industry</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN CUNNIFF</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Analyst</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation's car market is so suffused with
lookalike brands and models that competition increasingly will be
forced into pricing, says a professor who has studied the market
for three decades.
   He forecasts competitive pricing over the next few years ``like
we've never seen before'' with potentially severe damage to
products lines and even to entire manufacturing operations.
   ``There'll be a shakeout,'' says Professor Eugene Jennings of
Michigan State University, an adviser to top corporate executives
and an observer of the automotive industry whose opinions are
widely sought.
   ``We go into the 1990s with homogenization of design and style
clear across the board,'' said Jennings, who earlier attributed
some of General Motors' lost market share to a lack of
distinctiveness among its own brands.
   Now, he says, sameness pervades the whole industry to such an
extent that product differences are even too subtle for
advertising, being observable only after salesmen call attention to
them in the showroom.
   But getting buyers into the showrooms, particularly for cars
with little ``curb appeal,'' is more difficult than ever, Jennings
says, especially after two years in which sales were kept strong by
drawing from future markets.
   He says it is unlikely that any one manufacturer intended it
this way, but that they reacted in similar conservative ways to a
fear of overcapacity in the industry, rather than risk losing share
through unacceptable innovations.
   ``The consequences were too great if they guessed wrong,'' said
Jennings in an interview. ``New concepts would have presented too
much risk.'' And yet, he suggested, it might take the assumption of
such risk to make a breakthrough.
   The rare market situation already is reflected in advertising
where, he says, more and more money is spent simply to ``break
through the clutter and confusion,'' and images and themes
substitute for product distinctiveness.
   ``It's almost as if automobiles have become a commodity,'' said
Jennings, a business professor and author of many books about the
inner workings of corporations.
   The pricing problem could hardly be more serious, he says,
observing that prices are following the same conservative trend,
``a bit above or below the category average _ and be prepared to
make a deal.''
   While the sameness syndrome exists, he says, it will be
difficult for many car lines to sustain premium prices, since
customers can easily switch to the ``same'' car made by a different
manufacturer.
   Planning and development also are affected by the syndrome. Big
spending in this area always has been risky, if necessary, since a
new concept or radical style change might not be accepted.
   The failure of Ford's Edsel is a monument to that risk, and more
recently, says Jennings, photographs of General Motors' Saturn car,
a costly effort to rethink the entire production process, were
greeted by yawns.
   In the current market, where sales already have been
``borrowed'' from model years to come, and with large overcapacity
in manufacturing operations, the risk is magnified. ``No one can
afford to have an Edsel,'' says Jennings.
   While assumption of that risk might eventually be the only way
to dissolve the stalemate, Jennings feels for the time being
companies most likely will fight their battle on the pricing front.
   ``Prices will not hold at premium levels,'' he states.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv AMs Thursday, Dec. 21.</NOTE>

</DOC>