<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0153EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-LetterfromBangkok     12-21 0635</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Letter from Bangkok,0653</SECOND>
<HEAD>Letter From Bangkok: Frenzied Pace Replaces City's Old Charm</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Thursday AMs report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DENIS D. GRAY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BANGKOK, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Some say 1989 has been Bangkok's Year
of the Condominium. Others call it the Year of Greed.
   The air of this once languid city of tree-shaded canals and
quiet temples now is filled with the thud of pile drivers and the
thunder of traffic.
   There seems to be no reprieve. Bangkok has become a vast work
site of mushrooming high-rises, its streets choked with traffic and
pollution at dangerously high levels.
   The boom began about three years ago. With annual growth rates
around 9 percent to 10 percent, Thailand is talked about as Asia's
next economic miracle and Bangkok as the dynamic hub of peninsular
Southeast Asia.
   Land prices in the city have soared to as high as $1,115 a
square foot in prime areas. Millions are being made in land
speculation and construction. Rents, not long ago among the most
reasonable in the world, are approaching the levels of New York,
Hong Kong and London.
   In the upper class residential area along Sukhumvit Road, more
than 50 towering condominiums, apartment blocks and office
buildings are rising on what were once leafy family compounds and
peaceful lanes.
   What worries planners and many citizens is that Bangkok is not
only destroying its past, but possibly also its future, with
unplanned growth.
   Forecasts are largely ominous.
   The United Nations predicts Bangkok's population will nearly
double to 12 million by 2000, making it the 10th largest city in
the world.
   The Thailand Development and Research Institute says the city's
mighty Menam Chao Phraya, ``the River of Kings,'' will be devoid of
all aquatic life by the end of the century unless decisive action
is taken immediately. Every day, the institute says, tons of
untreated waste pour into the river from sewers and the
now-befouled canals that earned Bangkok the name ``Venice of the
East.''
   Already serious, pollution is expected to worsen as more
factories sprout around the capital. The main culprit now in air
pollution is the omnipresent motor vehicle and its leaded fuel.
   The National Environment Board recently found lead levels along
Bangkok streets to be up to four times higher than standards in the
United States, and hospitals are reporting children with abnormally
high lead levels in their systems.
   The topic of inordinate greed by the few has become the talk of
the town. A ``me-first'' attitude is often held responsible for
many of Bangkok's woes.
   ``I believe if they could dig up Thailand and put it in a
parcel, they would sell the country, too,'' Bangkok Post columnist
Normita Tongtham wrote recently of what he described as
unscrupulous businessmen.
   Academics, journalists and some technocrats criticize what they
say is blatant pollution by commerical enterprises, disregard for
public well-being by real estate developers, and the quick resort
to bribery to circumvent regulations and laws.
   The critics claim vast economic power _ and behind-the-scenes
decision-making _ is still in the hands of a few Chinese-Thai
families and say it is their ethos that now pervades Bangkok rather
than the traditional Thai one of being satisfied with a modest
lifestyle.
   Standing in stark contrast is Chamlong Srimuang, widely expected
to win re-election in January as Bangkok's mayor.
   A 55-year-old Buddhist, he seems to represent older, rural
values that still attract a large, albeit still largely powerless,
segment of Bangkok's population.
   ``We must not be selfish,'' is one of Chamlong's tenets; another
is, ``Eat less and spend less.''
   He means what he says.
   Chamlong sleeps on a floor mat, eats one meal a day and dresses
in the rough-spun cotton shirts of upcountry farmers. He drives a
battered old car and has donated his salary to the city.
</TEXT>

</DOC>