<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0302EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-FarmSearch     12-29 0346</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Farm Search,0358</SECOND>
<HEAD>Farm Couple Indicted by Grand Jury in Five Murders</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHILLICOTHE, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An elderly farm couple accused of
killing drifters in northwest Missouri to cover up a cattle-theft
scheme was indicted by a grand jury on five counts of murder.
   Ray and Faye Copeland had been charged previously by Livingston
County prosecutors with three counts of first-degree murder. The
indictment handed up Thursday includes those three victims and two
others.
   Officials said they sought indictments by the county grand jury
to avert a costly preliminary hearing. Cases considered by a grand
jury aren't taken to preliminary hearing, in which a judge
determines if the evidence is sufficient to send a case to trial.
   Prosecuting Attorney Doug Roberts said he expected the
Copelands, who are being held in the county jail, to stand trial in
the second half of 1990 at the earliest. Arraignment was scheduled
for Jan. 2.
   Authorities identified the fifth murder victim as the indictment
was filed. He was Wayne Warner, but his hometown and age weren't
immediately known.
   Ray Copeland, 75, and Faye Copeland, 68, have been held since
their arrest in October on charges they conspired to steal cattle.
Those charges have since been dropped.
   Each of the victims had been shot in the head, and the bodies
were found on farms where Ray Copeland had done odd jobs. Four of
the bodies were found in shallow graves and one was found weighted
down in a well.
   The Copelands were charged Oct. 9 with conspiracy to steal
cattle with bad checks from an account set up in August for an
employee.
   Prosecutors allege the couple used the men to write bad checks
in the cattle scheme, then killed them to keep them from talking.
   Prosecutors said previously they would seek the death penalty on
the first three murder charges, and state Attorney General William
Webster said that was still planned.
   Bail had been set at $500,000 each. With the indictment, that
was changed so the couple can't be freed on bail, Webster said in a
news release.
</TEXT>

</DOC>