<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0923EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Mustache-Firings     12-27 0343</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mustache-Firings,0356</SECOND>
<HEAD>Queen Mary Officer May Be Next Fired by Disney for Refusing To Shave</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONG BEACH, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first officer of the Queen Mary
said he'll probably be the next to walk the plank following firings
of two waiters whose mustaches ran afoul of a Walt Disney Co.
grooming code.
   First Officer John Magness said he planned to keep the mustache
he has worn for 42 years while serving on ships around the world.
   ``I'm going to work, punch in as usual, and if they want to fire
me, they can find me and fire me,'' Magness, 65, said Tuesday,
adding that he would fight the anticipated dismissal in court.
   Waiters Reza Nazertehrani and Tom Nicolai were dismissed
Christmas Eve for refusing to shave facial hair forbidden by
Disney, which owns the leaseholds on the permanently docked ocean
liner in Long Beach Harbor.
   ``I got a beautiful present from the Disney corporation _ my
pink slip,'' said Nazertehrani, a 12{-year Queen Mary employee.
   Nicolai, 26, said the 35-year-old Disney policy barring facial
hair is out of date.
   Both men said they would file union grievances protesting their
dismissals.
   The grooming code bans mustaches, beards and long hair on men.
Bright eye shadow, red fingernails or two-toned hair for women are
forbidden.
   Nazertehrani, 43, said the issue involved more than appearance.
   ``I am Iranian,'' he said. ``This mustache is part of my
culture. It is a thing of pride.''
   Five or fewer Queen Mary workers have lost their jobs for
refusing to shave, said Rich Kerlin, a spokesman for the tourist
attraction. He said the firing of Nazertehrani and Nicolai on
Christmas Eve was an accident of scheduling.
   Disney bought rights to the ship a couple years ago, but only
imposed its companywide dress and grooming codes on it recently in
conjunction with a promotional campaign.
   ``I think the initial reluctance people expressed has subsided.
It was controversial for only a week or two,'' Kerlin said.
   The no-facial hair restriction puzzles some who recall that Walt
Disney sported a mustache.
</TEXT>

</DOC>