<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0188 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2220EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Philippines 1stLd-Writethru a0697 12-18 0588</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0697,0601</SECOND>
<HEAD>Aquino Threatens to Close Pro-Rebel Stations, Papers</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: ADDS 4 grafs on Tuesday ambush wounds colonel, kills policeman.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By OLIVER TEVES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Corazon Aquino threatened
Monday to close broadcast stations that air rebel propaganda and to
file charges against newspapers publishing articles that ``incite
rebellion.''
   The Senate and House of Representatives are expected to give
final approval this week to legislation granting Mrs. Aquino
special powers to restore order in the wake of the failed Dec. 1-9
coup by thousands of military mutineers.
   Although the bill does not give Mrs. Aquino additional powers to
clamp down on newspaper and broadcast operations, she told
reporters the government will take action against those spreading
rebel propaganda.
   Mrs. Aquino told reporters broadcasters operate under government
franchise and that the administration will strictly enforce
regulations forbidding ``subversive propaganda.''
   ``If they violate these terms and conditions, they will be
closed, their franchises will be taken away from them,'' Mrs.
Aquino said. ``With regard to print media, it's an entirely
different matter. We will base this on any article that will incite
to rebellion. If such an article does appear in any of the
newspapers, then we will go to court to file charges against the
erring individual or the publication.''
   There was no indication what criteria the government will use to
define inciting to rebellion or subversive propaganda. Since the
launch of the coup attempt, the sixth and worst since Mrs. Aquino
took office in February 1986, two radio stations were closed but
one was allowed back on the air.
   In a front-page editorial Tuesday, the Philippine Daily Inquirer
charged that the Aquino government ``appears to be moving toward
tighter restrictions on the press.''
   Meanwhile Monday, police said the Manila city hall was evacuated
about 9 a.m. after telephone reports that a bomb had been placed
there. No bomb was found, but the incident disrupted court hearings
and other business there for more than two hours.
   Pfc. Edilberto Capacete of the bomb disposal squad said the a
string of recent bomb threats appears part of a rebel plan to raise
tensions in the capital and undermine confidence in the government.
   Last Thursday, suspected mutineers fired two grenades at a U.S.
housing and recreational compound, damaging several cars but
causing no injuries. On Dec. 9, a grenade exploded at the city's
main post office, killing two people and injuring 18.
   Also Monday, four suspected Communist assassins killed a
surburban police chief as he drove to work in suburban Paranaque,
police said.
   In Quezon province, southeast of the capital, government forces
battled Communist rebels for about two hours Monday. Five
government troops and two civilians were wounded, the military
said. There was no report of military casualties but troops
recovered 22 rebel firearms, the report said.
   More than 20 people, including a town mayor, have been killed by
suspected rebels since the nine-day revolt that began Dec. 1,
according to military reports.
   On Tuesday, gunmen wounded the commander of a major military
camp in a daylight ambush and killed a policeman who intervened,
the military reported.
   It said Lt. Col. Eduardo Amoyo, commander of Camp Bagong Diwa,
was hit three times by rifle fire from an auto following his car in
suburban Mandaluyong.
   Amoyo was reported in stable condition after surgery.
   A witness told police the attack car got stuck on a traffic
median and the assailants fled in a commandeered taxi after killing
policeman Mario Hernandez, who tried to stop them.
</TEXT>

</DOC>