<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0546EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BridgeAccident 1stLd-Writethru a0459 12-23 0580</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bridge Accident, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0459,0593</SECOND>
<HEAD>State Officials Recommend Independent Inquiry Into Fatal Bridge Accident</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 4th graf to ADD name of dead woman. Pick up 5th graf pvs:
`Motorist Mark...</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATIA BLACKBURN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A moveable span on a floating bridge opened
unexpectedly during a test, thrusting a steel wall in front of
rush-hour traffic and causing pileups that killed one woman and
injured at least six other people.
   Department of Transportation officials were at a loss to explain
the wreck on the Evergreen Point Floating Bridge across Lake
Washington during a test that has been conducted weekly for 18
years without a hitch. The test of electronic circuits doesn't
involve moving the span.
   But during Friday's test, the span rose 4{ feet without warning
in about three seconds, creating a wall that three vehicles drove
into head-on.
   Raili Korkka, 44, was killed, police said. Three people were
hospitalized in serious but stable condition with a variety of
injuries and three others were either treated at the scene or
briefly hospitalized, according to police and hospital officials.
   Motorist Mark Bauty said his car bounced over the lip of the
drawspan just as it started to open and he could hear tires
screeching and metal crunching behind him.
   ``The bridge was probably six inches high I guess when I hit it
and the car made it over the front end, kept right on going and
flew off the back end when the bridge was probably about a
foot-and-a-half to two feet high,'' Bauty said.
   Several cars were left perched on the elevated section of the
bridge, some with blown tires and mangled metal from hitting the
rising span. No cars went into the water.
   Operator error has been just about ruled out in the 8:50 a.m.
accident, said department spokeswoman Leslie Salisbury, who
explained the bridge-opening sequence requires 18 distinct steps.
   ``When the operator got to the 10th step, for some reason one
part of the drawspan opened up,'' she said.
   Transportation Department crews ran through the procedure three
times Friday afternoon, ``and every time we got to that step the
drawspan opened,'' Salisbury said.
   The step should not have involved the drawspan mechanism at all,
she said. One expert ``likened it to turning on your windshield
wipers and having the radio come on instead,'' Salisbury said.
   The 25-year-old, 2-mile-long bridge is supported for 7,000 feet
on concrete pontoons, making it the world's longest floating
bridge. Two steel-grid spans, each 100 feet long, can be raised
about 7 feet to make room for boats to pass beneath.
   Preliminary inspections didn't turn up any damage, but workers
plan to inspect the bridge further on Tuesday, and to close the
bridge briefly in January for a more detailed look, Salisbury said.
The department also has recommended an independent consultant be
hired to investigate.
   The operator of the bridge has been with the department for 10
years and has run the bridge for one year, following two years of
training, Salisbury said.
   The operator was distraught and was treated by medics 45 minutes
after the accident, said Daryl Rush, district bridge maintenance
superintendent for DOT.
   Opening the drawspan, which creates a 200-foot opening, is
necessary only 30 to 40 times a year because most vessels can pass
under elevated portions of the bridge at each end, Rush said.
   Evergreen Point Bridge, formally known as the Albert D.
Rosellini Bridge, carries an average of 100,000 vehicles daily.
</TEXT>

</DOC>