<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0085 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1004EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Noriega-Indictment     12-20 0308</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Noriega-Indictment,0325</SECOND>
<HEAD>Summary of Charges in Noriega Drug Indictment</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega's capture would enable U.S.
authorities to bring him to trial on drug trafficking charges
brought against him in Miami and Tampa, Fla.
   The indictments against the Panamanian leader were unsealed Feb.
5, 1988, and marked the first time federal charges were filed
against a foreign leader who was not in the United States.
   Fifteen other people also face charges in the case.
   Noriega could receive up to 145 years in prison and more than
$1.1 million in fines if convicted.
   The Miami indictment charges Noriega with conspiracy,
racketeering, importing drugs and traveling to further the
conspiracy. It accuses him of:
   _ Accepting a $4.6 million bribe from Colombia's Medellin drug
cartel to protect s
augment the force.
   Bush said Noriega's ``reckless'' behavior had ``created an
imminent danger to the 35,000 American citizens living in Panama.''
   Fighting also was reported at a Panamanian cavalry unit about
seven miles east of the Defense Forces headquarters; and at the
Panamanian base Fort Cimarron, about 20 miles from the capital.
   Noriega's main bodyguard, Lt. Asuncion Gaitan, spoke on the
national radio network after dawn to say that Noriega was ``well
and in a safe place.''
   ``Don't anyone give up your positions. In the provinces, prepare
to resist. The attacks are going to continue when they find we are
not going to cede,'' he said.
   Gaitan, Noriega's prime bodyguard, then gave a series of
messages using code names and instructions. The codes mentioned
names like ``Alex, Omar,'' or said, ``Alex, take the man to the
hangar and Yeyo.''
   Others were more comprehensible. One was a reference to the
so-called civilian Dignity Battalions of Noriega loyalists.
   ``Dignity Battalions operate in small operations during the day
or look for positions and mix with the people who support you and
at night move and act against the enemy positions in the periphery
of the city,'' ran one.
   Meanwhile, casualty reports were climbing. Dr. Marcel Pena of
the Santo Tomas Hospital in Panama City said wounded had been
coming in all night and the number increased with daybreak.
   ``There are many more than 50 dead and an enormous number of
wounded,'' he said. Earlier, doctors had said there were at least
50 dead at the hospital.
   Hospitals were short of blood, surgical materials and other
supplies and were issuing international appeals for help, he said.
   Fighting after dawn was still continuing in Old Panama, just
east of the Marriott, and in San Miguelito, a poor district hill
district northeast of the city center where some of the strongest
Dignity Battalions are based. U.S. forces were apparently trying to
take the Panama Defense Forces barracks at San Miguelito and
helicopters were buzzing the area.
   In New York, the U.N. Security Council prepared to meet in
emergency session Wednesday morning to debate the U.S. military
attack. Nicaragua requested the emergency meeting.
   On Friday, Noriega's rubber-stamp declared that the country was
in a ``state of war'' with the United States and named the general
head of state to deal with the threat. A day later, a U.S. military
officer was shot to death by Panamanians in what American officials
called an unprovoked attack.
   Pickup a0592, 6th Ld-1st Add.
</TEXT>

</DOC>