<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1346EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-Notebook Bjt   12-24 0492</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Notebook, Bjt,0522</SECOND>
<HEAD>Panama City Celebrates Christmas Amidst the Rubble of War</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOSEPH B. FRAZIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The day before Christmas, Panama City
sits in a pile of its own wreckage. Where a week earlier Christmas
lights glittered, sunlight now shimmers off glass shards in
shattered shop windows.
   More people than usual walk about with bandaged hands. ``Three
more looting days until Christmas,'' one visitor observed.
   Christmas music still filters from a few homes in this mostly
Roman Catholic country, but with shops looted bare and no new
supplies imminent, Monday will be just another hungry day for most
people here.
   At night there is the occasional hollow thump of mortar fire. A
spark ignites against the sky and a flare lights up the tropical
dark, swaying lazily on a parachute invisible from the ground.
   It fades away, leaving a puff of white smoke.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Driving from place to place involves negotiating roadblocks, set
up every few hundred feet in some neighborhoods by armed residents
protecting their property.
   There are piles of tree limbs, old oil barrels, broken furniture
and miscellaneous rubbish and, in several places, Christmas trees.
   There is so much rubbish that driving even short distances
frequently results in a flat.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   There are a few hints of Christmas left in the capital but they
are tattered.
   These days, white flags flutter from antennas of the few
vehicles still on the usually snarled streets.
   At a destroyed police station in the former Panama Canal Zone,
cardboard cutouts of two of the three kings still stand. The third
lies on the lawn, riddled with bullet holes.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   The traditional nine days of ``posadas'' for children,
commemorating Mary and Joseph's trek to Bethlehem, stopped abruptly
Tuesday. Christmas decorations framing windows and nativity scenes
in front of homes were hurriedly taken down.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Looters packed boxes and bags from shops. At one supermarket a
man said he arrived too late for food but had clothes for his
children.
   ``This is their Christmas,'' he said.
   Another toted a case of champagne. ``This is mine,'' he grinned.
   One of the few stations selling gas had been taken over by
neighborhood residents who were filling the tanks and pocketing the
money.
   ``How much to fill the tank?'' asked one driver.
   ``Whatever you want to pay,'' came the reply. ``How about five
dollars?'' Gas sells for about $2 a gallon in Panama.
   ``The owner left in a hurry,'' said the ``attendant.'' ``He
forgot the keys. People here don't have any money. The owner won't
miss it.''
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Men guarding roadblocks with antique shotguns and whatever else
is available mean business but are jovial once they recognize you.
   One helped clear a street so a taxi carrying reporters could
pass.
   ``You have to buy us beer in return for this,'' joked one guard.
   ``Just tell me, where can we get a beer in this country these
days?'' returned the driver.
</TEXT>

</DOC>