<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0247EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-China-Arrests     12-26 0323</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-China-Arrests,0334</SECOND>
<HEAD>China Charges Five With Helping Dissidents Flee</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHY WILHELM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   China says it arrested five Hong Kong and Macao
residents on charges of trying to smuggle dissidents out of the
country and today accused a Hong Kong group of running an
``underground railroad.''
   China said the Hong Kong Alliance for Supporting the Democratic
Movement in China helped dozens of dissidents flee abroad since the
army crackdown on pro-democracy protests in June.
   Police said the arrests ``dealt a major blow to the overseas
reactionary forces who attempted to use Hong Kong and Macao as
sanctuaries for criminals,'' the official Xinhua News Agency said
in a report Monday.
   The five arrests were made over the past three months, and
Xinhua did not say why they were being announced only now. It said
China will ``punish severely those who dare to plot and ship wanted
criminals out of the mainland.''
   China has said repeatedly it will not allow residents of Hong
Kong and Macao to interfere in mainland affairs, but this was the
first time it explicitly accused the Hong Kong alliance of running
the underground railroad.
   The alliance was founded after the June crackdown, which
increased anxiety in British-ruled Hong Kong and Portuguese-ruled
Macao about their return to Chinese rule in the coming decade.
   The official People's Daily defended the arrests in an editorial
in today's editions, saying ``Hong Kong and Macao residents must
obey Chinese laws when on the mainland.''
   In excerpts of the editorial, the paper accused the alliance of
smuggling abroad ``important counter-revolutionary criminals. ...
The Chinese government will never tolerate such activities.''
   China considers ethnic Chinese from the two colonies to be
Chinese citizens and has rejected past efforts by Britain to
intervene on behalf of arrested Hong Kong Chinese.
   The arrests were likely to increase Hong Kong fears about
Chinese rule, which already have sent many in search of haven
elsewhere.
</TEXT>

</DOC>