<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0100 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1349EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Missiles     12-29 0538</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Missiles,0555</SECOND>
<HEAD>North Korean Missile Help Sought by Syria, Egypt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NICOLAS B. TATRO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TEL AVIV, Israel (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Syria is believed to be seeking North
Korea's help in acquiring new surface-to-surface missiles after the
United States pressured China to cancel a reported deal, Israeli
military sources said Friday.
   The sources also said North Korea and Egypt have begun a project
to develop missiles patterned after Soviet-designed Scud missiles.
   The revelation by the sources, who spoke on condition of
anonymity, comes at a time of mounting concern in Israel about an
intensified missile race in the Middle East.
   Fears intensified following Iraq's Dec. 7 launching of the Abed,
a 48-ton, three-stage ballistic missile that Baghdad claimed was
capable of putting satellites into space.
   North Korea has a well-developed arms industry, and the Israeli
sources said it had supplied Iran with Soviet-designed Scud
surface-to-surface missiles during Tehran's war with Iraq.
   The military sources said part of the Egyptian-North Korean
missile project was being developed in Egypt.
   Aharon Levran, a retired brigadier general and an independent
military analyst, said Egypt had an arsenal of aging Scud missiles
provided by the Soviet Union and had apparently turned to North
Korea last year for help in modernizing them.
   ``It's not known exactly what sort of help the North Koreans can
provide, whether it is just to renew the old Soviet missiles and
provide spare parts or maybe install improved components such as
guidance,'' he said.
   He also said published reports indicated North Korea was helping
Iran develop its own surface-to-surface missile and was training
pilots for the Tehran regime.
   The Scud-B, which has a range of 180 miles and poor accuracy,
was introduced into the Middle East in the early 1970s.
   Cairo apparently dropped out of a project with Argentina and
Iraq t develop a more accurate missile called the Condor 2 or Badr
2000. The missile was intended to have a range of about 540 miles
and better accuracy than the Scud.
   Egypt's withdrawal followed political pressure brought by
Washington after the arrest of two Egyptian colonels who were
accused of trying to smuggle technology out of the United States
that could be used to improve missile accuracy.
   President Bush sent National Security Adviser Brent Scowcroft to
Beijing this month to urge the Chinese to cancel a planned sale to
Syria of M-9 surface-to-surface missiles, which have a range of 370
miles and would be capable of hitting targets deep inside Israel.
   The Jerusalem Post reported Syria signed an agreement with China
for 140 M-9 missiles at a cost of $170 million.
   Israeli officials have said Israel was informed that China had
pledged to refrain from such sales, although some doubts still
existed about whether China would go through with the sale.
   Officials in Beijing have denied any sale was in the works.
   Syria has Soviet SS-21 missiles capable of hitting northern
Israel and Scud-B missiles.
   Levran said the Syrians would likely be interested in North
Korean help only if they could improve the range and accuracy of
the Scuds. Unlike the Egyptians, he noted, Syria has close ties
with the Soviet Union and would likely be able to get replacement
missiles without the need for renovation.
</TEXT>

</DOC>