<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0176 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1940EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Iran-Israel     12-20 0433</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iran-Israel,0448</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iran Denies Oil Sold To Israel</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iran's Foreign Ministry on Wednesday
denied a U.S. report that Israel bought oil from Tehran in a bid to
free three military men believed held by pro-Iranian militants in
Lebanon, Iranian TV reported.
   The broadcast, monitored in Cyprus, quoted a Foreign Ministry
statement as saying that ``not even one barrel of oil'' had been
sold to Israel, one of revolutionary Iran's main regional foes.
   ``According to irrevocable, declared principles of the Islamic
Republic, the Oil Ministry has imposed a ban on the sale of oil and
oil-related products to Israel and the racist South African
regime,'' the statement said.
   Tehran has vowed never to establish relations with Israel and
South Africa.
   The statement added that no oil has been sold to those countries
since Iran's 1979 Islamic revolution, which toppled Shah Mohammed
Reza Pahlavi.
   The U.S. State Department on Tuesday confirmed an NBC-TV report
Monday that Israel bought 2 million barrels of oil worth $36
million from Iran in November to help free the three Israelis held
in Lebanon.
   Israeli representatives also have discussed the possibility of
selling Iran spare parts for its U.S.-made military hardware, NBC
said, citing unidentified sources in U.S. and Israeli intelligence.
   In addition to winning Iran's help in releasing the Israelis,
the oil purchases and the potential spare parts deal were intended
to bolster Iran's position against Iraq, their common enemy, NBC
said.
   Spokesmen for Israel's Energy, Foreign and Defense ministries
refused to comment on the report.
   NBC reported that the U.S. government had backed the oil deal in
hopes that it could help the release of eight American hostages in
Lebanon.
   They are among 18 Westerners held in Lebanon by extremist
groups. Most are captives of Iranian-backed Shiite factions.
   Iran's leaders are avowedly anti-Israeli, but the Iranian
economy, battered by 10 years of poor management and 8 years of war
against Iraq, badly needs foreign exchange for post-war
reconstruction.
   President Hashemi Rafsanjani was closely involved in clandestine
arms-for-hostages dealings with the United States and Israel in
1985-86.
   Three American hostages held in Lebanon were freed in exchange
for deliveries of U.S.-made anti-aircraft and anti-tank missile
parts.
   Rafsanjani, leader of Tehran's so-calle pragmatists, is seeking
to rebuild Iran's links with the West to end 10 years of isolation
and seek badly needed investment.
   He generally is considered to be in favor of freeing the
hostages held in Lebanon, but has limited room to maneuver because
of opposition by hard-liners led by former Interior Minister Ali
Akbar Mohtashemi, who has close ties with the Lebanese militants.
</TEXT>

</DOC>