<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0276 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1721EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-CommodityRdp     12-22 0693</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Commodity Rdp,0717</SECOND>
<HEAD>Profit-Taking Cuts Orange Juice Gains in Wild Session</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID DISHNEAU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Orange juice futures prices fell sharply Friday on the New York
Cotton Exchange as skittish players took pre-weekend profits in a
wild session that featured a one-hour trading halt to prevent
mixups in the flood of orders.
   ``We had a really crazy market here,'' said Celeste Georkakis,
an analyst with Cargill Investor Services Inc.
   On other commodity markets, heating oil futures posted fresh
gains as the nation's record-setting cold spell continued; precious
metals advanced; livestock and meat futures were mixed; and grains
and soybeans were mixed.
   Most commodity exchanges held abbreviated trading sessions to
give traders and employees an early start on the long holiday
weekend.
   After rising sharply in the four previous sessions, frozen
concentrated orange juice futures fell 1 cent to 4.7 cents Friday
with the contract for January delivery settling at $1.37 a pound.
   The runup earlier in the week had been fueled by forecasts for a
damaging freeze this weekend in the Central Florida citrus belt,
and those forecasts remained in effect on Friday.
   But many traders fearful of carrying their positions through the
three-day weekend opted to take profits rather than risk a market
dive when trading resumes on Tuesday.
   The lowest temperatures were expected to reach Florida on
Saturday and Sunday, so the threat of damage to Florida fruit will
be long past when the orange juice futures market reopens.
   The market opened with a surge and quickly rose the permitted
5-cents-a-pound limit for daily trading on heavy speculative
buying. But trade selling emerged at mid-morning and speculators
joined in, pushing prices nearly limit-down before the exchange
called a trading halt at 11 a.m. EST. Heavy selling continued when
trading resumed at noon.
   Heating oil for near-term delivery rose sharply for the sixth
straight day and the 17th time in the last 18 trading sessions on
the New York Mercantile Exchange. The buying again was linked to
weather-driven demand for shrinking supplies of home heating oil.
   Dealers have reported spot shortages of fuel oil in the heavily
populated Northeast, where temperatures have been below normal
since late November.
   Heating oil futures settled .83 cent lower to 1.93 cents higher
with January at 81.74 cents a gallon; West Texas Intermediate crude
oil was 23 cents to 27 cents lower with February at $21.29 a
barrel; unleaded gasoline was .18 cent to .65 cent lower with
January at 55.45 cents a gallon.
   Gold and silver futures rose modestly on New York's Commodity
Exchange, reflecting expectations of lower interest rates and a
weaker dollar.
   The Commmerce Department's report of a 5.1 percent rise in
factory orders for durable goods last month also was a supportive
factor, analysts said.
   Gold futures finished $1.20 to $1.30 higher with December at
$413.20 a troy ounce; silver was 1.6 cents to 1.9 cents higher with
silver at $5.56 a troy ounce.
   Most live cattle and hog futures retreated on the Chicago
Mercantile Exchange on expectations that warmer temperatures next
week in the Great Plains and Midwest will lead to increased
livestock marketings.
   Live cattle settled .25 cent lower to .07 cent higher with
February at 76.80 cents a pound; feeder cattle were .08 cent lower
to .13 cent higher wiith January at 84.82 cents a pound; live hogs
were .60 cent lower to .02 cent higher with February at 48.87 cents
a pound; frozen pork bellies were .42 cent lower to .17 cent higher
with February at 49.77 cents a pound.
   Soybean futures settled moderately lower on the Chicago Board of
Trade in quiet, sporadic trading. The grain markets finished nearly
unchanged.
   Analysts said soybeans were pressured by perceptions of improved
growing conditions in soybean-growing areas of South America and
slack export demand.
   Wheat futures settled { cent to 1{ cents lower with the contract
for delivery in March at $4.11} a bushel; corn futures were
unchanged to } cent higher with March at $2.39 a bushel; oats were
\ cent lower to \ cent higher with March at $1.54\ a bushel;
soybeans were 2\ cents to 3 cents lower with January at $5.72\ a
bushel.
</TEXT>

</DOC>