<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0104 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1533EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Poland 1stLd-Writethru a0589 12-27 0370</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0589,0374</SECOND>
<HEAD>Solidarity Caucus to Propose Change of Country's Name</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 1st graf to fix grammar.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Solidarity lawmakers proposed
constitutional amendments Wednesday that include restoring the
country's name to the prewar ``Republic of Poland,'' from the
Communist-imposed ``People's Republic of Poland.''
   Parliament convened Wednesday for a three-day session to
consider sweeping economic legislation that was proposed earlier
this month by the Solidarity-led government to transform the
economy to a market system.
   The government hopes by the end of the session that parliament
will pass wide-ranging laws that aim to reduce the current 900
percent inflation rate, make the zloty a convertible currency and
reform the bloated state sector.
   In addition to the name change, the constitutional amendments
would remove 19 articles, including one saying the Polish People's
Republic is a socialist state and another that mandates the leading
role of the Communist Party in state affairs.
   The prewar Republic of Poland was changed to the People's
Republic of Poland in July 1944 when Soviet-backed Polish
communists entered the country and proclaimed a Communist
government in Poland.
   The package also calls for dropping the phrase that says the
``Polish People's Republic will strengthen friendship with the
Soviet Union and other socialist countries'' as well as removing a
clause which refers to the socialist system in the Polish economy.
   The amendments were presented first to the Solidarity deputies
by caucus leader Bronislaw Geremek who appealed to the union-backed
deputies to be present for the debate in parliament.
   Geremek said an amended Constitution would serve as a temporary
one until a new Constitution could be drafted. The amendments must
receive a two-thirds majority of the Sejm, as the lower house of
parliament is called, to pass.
   The amendments also would create a provision for the formation
of new political parties. As it is now worded, the Constitution
allows only the Communist Party, the Democratic Party and the
Peasants Party to operate legally.
   After the Solidarity-led opposition and Communist authorities
agreed to partially free elections at talks this spring,
union-backed candidates to parliament were forced to organize
themselves as a club rather than a political party because of the
wording in the Constitution.
</TEXT>

</DOC>