<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0116 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1624EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-BushText 1stAdd   12-21 0603</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Bush Text, 1st Add,500</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHN: some questions.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Q: Mr. President, one of your major objectives was to get
Noriega. Are you frustrated that he got away? How long will you
keep on chasing him? And are you confident that you'll get him?
   A: I've been frustrated that he's been in power this long _
extraordinarily frustrated. The good news: He's out of power. The
bad news: He has not yet been brought to justice. So I'd have to
say, Terry, there is a certain level of frustration on that
account. The good news, though, is that the government's beginning
to function, and the man controls no forces, and he's out. But,
yes, I won't be satisfied until we see him come to justice.
   Q: How long will you keep up your full-scale pursuit?
   A: As long as it takes.
   Q: Mr. President, you did mention the casualties. Did you expect
them to be so high on both sides? I mean _
   A: We had some very _
   Q: And also was _ it it really worth it to send people to their
death for this? To get Noriega?
   A: We had some estimates, Helen, on the casualties ahead of
time, but not in numbers. I mean, it was more general; that,
``Look, Mr. President, no way can you do an operation this large
and not have American casualties.'' So the Defense Department was
very up front with us about that. And every human life is precious,
and yet I have to answer, yes, it has been worth it.
   David?
   Q: Mr. President _
   A: No. David, Brit, and Wyatt, and John.
   Q: A few months ago, you said your complaint was not with the
PDF, not with the Panamanian people, but with Noriega only. You
also said only a month ago that you didn't think it would be
prudent to launch a large-scale military operation. What changed
your mind, and particularly why did you opt for the maximum use of
force in this situation?
   A: I think what changed my mind was the events that I cited in
briefing the American people on this yesterday: the death of the
Marine, the brutalizing, really obscene torture of the Navy
lieutenant, and the threat of sexual abuse and the terror inflicted
on that Navy lieutenant's wife, the declaration of war by Noriega,
the fact that our people down there felt that they didn't know
where this was going and they weren't sure what all that meant and
whether that meant we could guarantee the safety of Americans there.
   And so I made a decision to move and to move with enough force _
this was the recommendation of the Pentagon _ to be sure that we
minimized the loss of life on both sides and that we took out the
PDF, which we did, took it out promptly. And so I would like to
think that what I said some time ago still stands.
   I'm not sure what's left on the ground in terms of people, but
what David Hoffman is referring to is that I said our argument was
not with the PDF, but with Noriega, and if they would get rid of
him and recognize a democratically elected government, we could go
back to more normalized relations. We've done that, but we have to
see who emerges in the PDF. But I would like to repeat here that we
have no continuing ax to grind with the institution of the PDF.
Endara's going to need loyal troops who recognize the constitution
and the fairness and the legitimacy of his election.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>