<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0001EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-GalileoManeuver     12-28 0340</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Galileo Maneuver,0350</SECOND>
<HEAD>Galileo Sensors Checked After Course Correction</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   NASA has started testing sensors aboard
Galileo, five days after the spacecraft successfully fired its
thrusters for a second course correction on its journey to Venus
and Jupiter.
   ``We're testing all of the scientific instruments to ensure they
are ready to observe Venus'' when Galileo whizzes past the
cloud-shrouded planet Feb. 9, said Jim Wilson, spokesman for the
National Aeronautics and Space Administration's Jet Propulsion
Laboratory.
   On Friday, Galileo fired its thrusters during a 2{-hour period
so that it will fly about 6,200 miles above the Venusian cloudtops,
Wilson said.
   ``The maneuver went off exactly as planned,'' Galileo mission
director Neal Ausman said.
   Wilson said another maneuver may be needed in late January to
fine-tune the spacecraft's trajectory. The first trajectory
maneuver was performed in November.
   Galileo was launched from the space shuttle Atlantis on Oct. 18.
It will swoop by Venus once and Earth twice so those planets can
act as ``gravity slingshots'' to propel Galileo toward its 1995
encounter with Jupiter, the solar system's largest planet.
   On Wednesday, the spacecraft was 12{ million miles from Earth,
but had traveled almost 105 million miles along its looping
185-million-mile path to Venus, Wilson said.
   The spacecraft still has 2.3 billion miles left out of its
2.4-billion-mile trip to Jupiter.
   After flying past Earth in December 1990 and December 1992,
Galileo will separate into an orbiter and a probe in July 1995.
   The orbiter will circle the giant gas planet for 22 months
starting in December 1995, the same month the probe will parachute
into the Jovian atmosphere, collecting information for 75 minutes
until it is crushed by overwhelming atmospheric pressure.
   Scientific information that Galileo collects during February's
Venus flyby won't be transmitted back to Earth until late October,
after the spacecraft unfurls its umbrella-shaped, high-gain
antenna, Wilson said.
   The antenna would be damaged by heat if it were as deployed near
Venus, the second planet from the sun, he added.
</TEXT>

</DOC>