<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0124 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1346EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel     12-22 0452</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel,0467</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soldiers Kill 3 Palestinians in West Bank</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israeli soldiers shot and killed three
Palestinians in the occupied West Bank on Friday, including the
16-year-old sister of a suspect they sought to apprehend in a
village raid, Arab reports said.
   The army confirmed two deaths from the village raid and said the
suspect was among the seven people wounded in Jaba village. He was
identified by Arab reporters as Mohammed Taysir Alawneh, 22, who
had been sought for anti-Israeli activities in the two-year
Palestinian uprising.
   The deaths came a day after Israeli troops shot and killed two
Palestinians in a similar raid in the nearby village of Beit Furik.
   In a separate incident, soldiers fatally wounded 19-year-old
Yaacoub Ramahi in a clash with stonethrowing youths in the town of
El-Bireh, Arab reporters said.
   Israel radio said the youth was part of a group of masked
Palestinians throwing building blocks and iron bars at a military
patrol.
   An army spokesman said the military was investigating the
incident.
   Also Friday, a 12-year-old Palestinian boy from Bethlehem died
of wounds reportedly suffered when an Israeli civilian fired on him
four months ago.
   The child, who died at Jerusalem's Mukassed Hospital, was
Mohammed Jamil Eid Kamel. He had been paralyzed since Aug. 7, when
Palestinian witnesses reported he was shot in the neck by a passing
Israeli motorist.
   A general strike to mourn Kamel's death closed shops and
businesses Friday in Bethlehem, residents said. Hundreds of
Christian pilgrims are expected in the biblical town starting
Sunday for the Christmas holiday.
   The latest deaths raised to 637 the number of Arabs killed by
Israelis since the Palestinian revolt against Israeli rule began in
the occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip in December 1987.
   At least 161 other Palestinians have been slain by fellow Arabs,
most on suspicion of collaboration with Israel. Forty-three
Israelis also have died in the violence.
   The army said soldiers ``met resistance'' during a Friday raid
in Jaba, six miles north of Nablus.
   As troops were trying to enter the home of a suspect, an officer
fired in self-defense when he was attacked by a Palestinian woman
with a knife, the army said. The woman was killed, and the officer
slightly wounded, it said.
   Arab reports said she was Asmahan Taysir Alawneh, 16, the sister
of the suspect.
   The army quoted hospital officials as saying a Palestinian
teen-ager was fatally shot in a subsequent stone-throwing clash
with troops in Jaba. Arab reports identified him as Iyad Mohammed
Said Hassan, 18.
   Nine Palestinians were shot and wounded in stone-throwing
clashes with Israeli troops in the Gaza Strip on Friday, Arab
reports said. The army said it was checking the reports.
</TEXT>

</DOC>