<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1205EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-ColdRdp 1stLd-Writethru a0494 12-26 0996</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Cold Rdp, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0494,1016</SECOND>
<HEAD>South's Freak Freeze Begins Easing</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 14 grafs to recast and UPDATE with today's conditions,
airports, damages, pick up at 12th graf pvs, bgng `Taps also...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL MOKRZYCKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The Deep South's deep freeze began abating today, melting
Christmas snow that fell as far south as the Gulf Coast, but
thousands of people were without water as frozen, cracked water
pipes and mains thawed and leaked.
   Temperatures stayed below freezing overnight throughout much of
the South. It was 30 degrees in Jacksonville, Fla., at 4 a.m. EST.
But temperatures were expected to reach the 60s in the Carolinas by
the end of the week, the National Weather Service said.
   ``The roads are passable, but it's a sheet of ice in most
places,'' said Larry Dozier of the Dare County, N.C., sheriff's
department.
   A new cold front, not as severe as the one that set hundreds of
low temperature records last week, swung down from Canada and snow
fell today in an arc from Indiana and Kentucky to Maine, the
National Weather Service said.
   West of that air mass, the weather was mild in many places and
Dickinson, N.D., had a reading of 36 above zero at 6 a.m.
   During the weekend, a rare Southern blizzard brought up to 15
inches of snow to Wilmington, N.C., the most ever measured there,
but much of that was expected to melt today with highs in the 40s.
It was the first white Christmas in more than a century in the
coastal city, in Georgia and in Mobile, Ala., on the Gulf Coast.
Snow also dusted northern Florida.
   Citrus growers in Florida and Texas reported extensive crop
damage.
   Officials in Texas estimated 70 percent of the state's citrus
crop and 80 percent of the winter vegetable crop was destroyed when
the temperatures plunged into the low 20s and upper teens as the
holiday weekend began.
   Citrus losses are estimated at $200 million so far and could top
$500 million as trees begin to show effects from the freeze, said
David Galvan, district director of the Texas Department of
Agriculture in Brownsville.
   Florida officials hadn't released citrus loss figures yet today,
but damage is likely to be substantial to the state's $3.5 billion
crop since much of it was still on the trees when freezing
temperatures began Saturday. Strawberry crops suffered less damage.
   In South Carolina, airlines resumed normal schedules at
Charleston today after reducing flights because of the snow, an
airport spokeswoman said. The Myrtle Beach Jetport, closed for a
third straight day Monday, also was expected to resume operations
sometime later today; the jetport can operate only during daylight
because runway lights are covered with snow, said Todd Crawford,
deputy airport director.
   In Florida, Mike Mahoney, spokesman for Tampa Electric Co.,
appealed to families in a six-county area to shut off Christmas
tree lights to save energy. Other Florida utilities imposed
rotating brownouts, and in some caes, blackouts.
   More than 60,000 homes and businesses in Jackson, Miss., were
without water or had greatly reduced pressure because of water-main
breaks and because the Pearl River had frozen around intakes for
the municipal water system. The city government was closed because
of the water problem.
   Texas cities also had broken water pipes, with more than 6,000
leaks reported in Houston, and some people had been without water
since Friday. Hotels in Houston offered discount rates for people
who wanted to take showers.
   Taps also ran dry in the Charleston, S.C., area.
   ``There's got to be thousands of broken lines out there,'' said
Steve Kinard, manager of Charleston's public works department,
which supplies water to 400,000 people.
   ``We've got water mains and pipes bursting all over the city,
everything from hotels to businesses to homes,'' said George A.
Ingram, a fire chief in Norfolk, Va.
   At least 93 deaths from the Plains to the East Coast have been
blamed on the cold since Dec. 15. Victims this weekend included an
18-year-old boy who fell through ice on a lake in DeKalb County,
Ga., and a 7-week-old boy who froze to death in his crib in an
unheated apartment in Miami. Police said they may charge the
parents, who left the baby unattended after an argument.
   The Plains celebrated Christmas with a respite from subzero
temperatures, but a fresh blast of arctic chill blew across the
northern Plains and upper Great Lakes late Monday, dropping as much
as 10 inches of snow in parts of Michigan.
   Christmas Day was the coldest day ever in Wilmington, N.C.,
where it fell to zero degrees. Its previous all-time low was 5
degrees in February 1899. Records also were set Monday for the date
in Florida with lows of 29 in Fort Lauderdale, 30 in Miami and 46
in Key West.
   Farther north, the cold prevented the annual re-enactment of
George Washington's crossing of the Delaware River to capture
British troops at Trenton, N.J. ``We couldn't get our four boats
into the river because it was a sheet of ice,'' said James
Gallagher, who has played the role of Washington since 1985.
   And in Buffalo, N.Y., organizers who struggled for three years
to stage a Winterfest of snow sculpting and ice skating despite
balmy temperatures gave up this year and canceled the festival _
and then the snow began. With nearly 3 feet of snow so far this
season, Buffalo had its first white Christmas since 1985.
   ``Someone just called me and said, `Can't you bring it back?
Then we won't have any snow,''' said Dottie Gallagher, spokeswoman
for Buffalo Place, which had been one of the sponsors.
   It wasn't cold all over the country, though. In Southern
California, surfers got to try out new gift surfboards on Christmas
as temperatures peaked in the low 80s.
   ``All I want to do is swim and enjoy the heat,'' said Linda
Kinsey of Chicago as she stepped off a plane at Los Angeles
International Airport.
</TEXT>

</DOC>