<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0165 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 2030EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WKD--HomeVideo Adv00   12-26 0774</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--Home Video, Adv 00,0810</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv 00</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Anytime</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WEEKEND ENTERTAINMENT AND ARTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Video View: Home Video News and Reviews</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   ``Forbidden Sun'' (Academy Entertainment. VHS-Beta, $79.95.
Rated R)
   
   Lauren Hutton plays a former Olympic athlete who runs a summer
school for girl gymnasts on the island of Crete. Among her pupils
is Jane, a juvenile delinquent who wants to emulate the ancients
Greeks and vault over the horns of a live bull. When one of the
girls is raped, Jane uses a variation of the ``bull dance'' to get
revenge.
   Uh huh, this film is as lame as it sounds.
   The suspense lasts about as long as a skip across the balance
beam. The payoff at the end is meager.
   Filled with references to arson, bulls, rape and young women,
``Forbidden Sun'' undoubtedly has some kind of psychosexual
subtext, but don't waste your time trying to find it.
   By Pete Brown, Associated Press Writer.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   
   ``Great Balls of Fire'' (Orion Home Video. VHS-Beta, $89.98.
Rated PG-13)
   
   Some of the best movie biographies are films such as ``Lawrence
of Arabia,'' ``Gandhi'' and ``Raging Bull,'' all carefully
researched and written and based on a variety of sources.
   And with such standard-bearers, why does Hollywood continue to
seek out books, usually best sellers, that give only a fragmented
(and sometimes biased) account of an event or life, and rush to
make movies of them? Are the creative minds of the film industry
incapable of doing original research and stories?
   These questions come to mind with ``Great Balls of Fire,'' Jim
McBride's movie on the life and times of the piano-pumping rocker
Jerry Lee Lewis, based on the book by Myra Lewis with Murray
Silver. McBride and Jack Baran did the screenplay.
   The movie is a kinetic romp through the early years of rock 'n'
roll, when Elvis was King and pretenders like Jerry Lee threatened
to topple him. The music is non-stop fun, whether songs by Presley
and Lewis, or Gene Autry singing ``Rudolph the Red Nosed Reindeer''
or Dave ``Baby'' Cortez stomping through ``Happy Organ.''
   Dennis Quaid is a treat as Lewis. He's manic, lewd, adorable and
crazy. He swaggers about with childish abandon, and dances with the
piano like a careless lover. At times, though, Quaid becomes almost
cartoonish in his portrayal. But that's OK, because Jerry Lee Lewis
was a walking comic book.
   Myra (Winona Ryder) was Jerry Lee's third wife. She also was his
third cousin and 13 years old when they married. He was 22.
   Ryder (``Heathers'') continues to impress with her film work.
She is a great casting choice for the pubescent, pulchritudinous
bubble gum-chewing Myra. She is wide-eyed and dreamy-eyed, giggly
and pouty, lusty and innocent.
   Their wedding scene is a wonderful slice of life. Ryder stares
blankly at the justice of the peace, mouth ajar like he's the
purple people eater. Later, at the dinner table with her parents,
she bursts into giggles knowing that she's married and they haven't
a clue.
   The year was 1958, and Lewis had already shot to the top of the
charts with ``Whole Lotta Shakin' Goin' On'' and ``Great Balls of
Fire.'' But his marriage to Myra shocked a staid post-war public,
and Lewis' career crumbled.
   The movie is centered on Myra and Jerry Lee's relationship (it
should have been titled ``Jerry and Myra'') and abruptly ends with
the birth of their son, Steve Allen, who drowned in a swimming pool
when he was 3.
   The late Trey Wilson co-stars as Sam Phillips, whose Sun Records
launched Presley and others.Alec Baldwin is deliciously
self-righteous as Lewis' cousin and boyhood buddy, TV evangelist
Jimmy Swaggart.
   ``Great Balls of Fire'' is a harmless piece of entertainment for
a Saturday afternoon. It's fun to watch, especially Quaid's
gymnastics and clownish grimaces.
   But the movie lacks authenticity; it seems to be laughing at
itself and at the era it purports to chronicle. There's also an
element of racism. A scene at a black nightspot, for example,
depicts black patrons as lewd animals doing bumps and grinds, and
crawling over each other in the most suggestive ways.
   By Dolores Barclay, AP Arts Editor.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Motion Picture Association of America rating definitions:
   G _ General audiences. All ages admitted.
   PG _ Parental guidance suggested. Some material may not be
suitable for children.
   PG-13 _ Special parental guidance strongly suggested for
children under 13. Some material may be inappropriate for young
children.
   R _ Restricted. Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult
guardian.
   X _ No one under 17 admitted. Some states may have higher age
restrictions.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Release Anytime</NOTE>

</DOC>