<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0555EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-VerdictOverturned     12-30 0352</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Verdict Overturned,0364</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Trial Ordered for Man Alleging Police Brutality</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Note language in 5th graf may offend some readers.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An appeals court has overturned the murder
conviction of a man who said police beat him and put a plastic bag
over his head to make him confess.
   The court said that when a defendant is injured in custody, the
prosecution must show by ``clear and convincing evidence that the
injuries were not inflicted as a means of producing the
confession.''
   A three-judge panel of the 1st District Illinois Court of
Appeals, ruling Thursday, ordered a new trial for Gregory Banks.
   Banks testified that while police interrogated him in 1983, Sgt.
John Byrne hit him with a flashlight while his hands were
handcuffed behind his back and stuck a pistol in his mouth,
threatening to shoot.
   Banks also said Sgt. Peter Dignan, then a detective, said ``we
have something for niggers,'' then put a plastic bag over his head
for more than a minute while Detective Charles Grunhard kicked him.
Banks said that when Dignan put the bag over his head again about
10 minutes later, he confessed.
   Dignan testified he tackled Banks when he tried to escape while
handcuffed. But the appellate court cited testimony from a doctor
at Cook County Hospital that Banks' injuries weren't of a type that
would be inflicted in a tackle.
   Dignan said people convicted of murder often claim they were
brutalized, and called the allegation that police used a plastic
bag ridiculous.
   ``Banks is a huge fellow, and he's guilty as sin,'' Dignan said.
``He did flee, and I tackled him. I got an elbow in the face and I
punched back.''
   Banks was convicted in 1984 of robbing and killing Leon Barkan
in a drug-related dispute. Cook County Circuit Judge Robert L.
Sklodowski sentenced him to 50 years in prison.
   Sklowodski said that in making his ruling, he had to evaluate
the credibility of the witnesses. He said he took into account the
fact that Banks was appearing in repeat offender's court, were
defendents have two previous felony convictions.
</TEXT>

</DOC>