<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0170 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2121EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Romania 1stLd-Writethru   12-21 0490</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Romania, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0725,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>Reduced Ties with Romania Planned Following Crackdown, Officials
Say</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 4th graf: ``A massacre,'' to give massacre quote</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bush administration is preparing to reduce
U.S. ties with Romania following that country's ``brutal and
violent'' crackdown on anti-government demonstrations, U.S.
officials said Thursday.
   The officials said the cutbacks could affect programs of
economic, scientific and commercial cooperation with Romania and
that an announcement could come as early as Friday.
   State Department spokesman Richard Boucher hinted at the
possibility of sanctions, saying the administration was ``carefully
reviewing'' possible steps against Romania.
   ``A massacre of undetermined proportions is believed to have
taken place'' in Romania over the past several days, Boucher said.
   He said the U.S. Embassy in Bucharest reported that 13 young
people were killed Thursday by automatic weapons fire from
government security forces during a major demonstration. Other
fatalities may have occurred as well, he said.
   ``Anti-regime demonstrations in Timisoara and the government's
brutal and violent crackdown against them continue,'' said Boucher,
who noted that some reports put the death toll since the upheaval
began at several thousand.
   It was not clear whether the United States, as part of a
sanctions program, is planning to reverse a 1988 decision to send
to Romania weapons grade uranium.
   The 16.4 kilograms of uranium are slated to be used at the Triga
reactor near Bucharest, a facility for teaching, basic research and
the production of radioactive isotopes. Such isotopes are commonly
used in medical tests.
   But opponents said the amount of uranium is large enough to make
a bomb.
   U.S. trade with Romania has declined sharply since 1988 when
that country was deprived of the right to sell its exports at the
lowest possible tariff rates under the so-called Most Favored
Nation system.
   Boucher said President Nicolae Ceaucescu has blamed the unrest
on ``fascists and imperialist circles abroad.
   ``In fact, however, the growing anti-government movement
encompasses all of Romania's nationalities, who are showing their
unalterable opposition to Ceausescu and his policies,'' he said.
   Boucher said the U.S. ambassador in Romania, Alan Green, has
been rebuffed in repeated efforts to deliver a strong protest
against the crackdown in Timisoara.
   Deputy Secretary Lawrence Eagleburger attempted to see the
Romanian ambassador in Washington on Wednesday but was told the
ambassador was unavailable.
   ``We have summoned the Romanian ambassador to come to the
Department tomorrow to receive our protest,'' Boucher said.
   Telephone calls to the Romanian Embassy on Thursday were not
answered.
   Protests against the repression in Romania have been made in
statements issued by NATO, the European Community and by the
35-nation Helsinki group.
   Members of the Warsaw Pact, of which Romania is a participant,
have criticized the Romanian actions individually, Boucher said,
adding that the Bush administration has asked the Soviet Union to
use whatever influence it has on Romania. He did not characterize
the Soviet response.
</TEXT>

</DOC>