<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0133EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-FarmScene     12-27 0599</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Farm Scene,570</SECOND>
<HEAD>Modest Consumer Food Price Rise Expected in 1990</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Consumer food prices are still on track to
increase by a modest 3 percent to 5 percent in 1990 despite the
bitter cold that has ravaged citrus and winter vegetable crops,
says an Agriculture Department analyst.
   The food price forecast was made last month, and economist Ralph
Parlett said Tuesday he is sticking by it, at least for now.
   Overall food prices are up an average of about 5.7 percent this
year, the largest annual gain since a 7.8 percent jump in 1981.
Much of this year's increase was due to lingering effects of the
1988 drought and poor weather early in 1989.
   ``I'm not worried about my overall forecast (for 1990) at this
point,'' Parlett said in a telephone interview. ``But there'll be
some impact, and possibly higher prices in the first quarter.''
   Parlett said he and other agency analysts are ``still trying to
assess the damage'' to citrus and vegetable crops in Florida and
elsewhere.
   ``The main thing is oranges,'' he said. ``Vegetables _ tomatoes,
bell peppers, celery _ they're some of the big volume things that
would be coming out of Florida now.''
   Parlett said 90 percent of the Florida oranges are for
processing and that a lot of them can be salvaged for juice. The
main source of ``fresh market'' oranges is California.
   ``There will be some (retail) price impact,'' he said. ``But
since we do have decent supplies in California this year ... the
supply impact will be minimal.''
   With the supply of Florida orange juice reduced by the freezing
weather, Parlett said imports from Brazil will probably rise
sharply.
   ``We've got super supplies in Brazil this year, but the price
has been fairly low because of the higher supplies,'' he said.
``But now that we probably will be importing, that will push the
price up some.''
   Parlett said he had not seen damage reports from Texas, where
state officials have estimated losses of 70 percent of the citrus
and 80 percent of the winter vegetables.
   Vegetable losses are ``a more temporary kind of thing'' because
those crops can be replanted, he said. Growers were just starting
to harvest Florida's main supply of winter vegetables when the cold
weather struck.
   California is still producing vegetables, however, and ``this
time of year we start getting produce out of Mexico, too,'' Parlett
said.
   ``There's no doubt that some of the supplies will be cut short,
and we'll probably see higher prices'' at produce counters, he said.
   In his forecast last month, Parlett said 1990 average retail
prices of all fruits and vegetables might rise only 1 percent to 3
percent, compared with the preliminary 7.8 percent gain registered
this year and 7.6 percent in 1988.
   Parlett said the current freeze damage ``might push us to the
high end'' of the 1990 forecast range _ 1 percent to 3 percent _
and, if conditions worsen, could push it even higher.
   ``Oranges themselves aren't going to do much to hurt that range,
and the vegetables will recover later on,'' he said.
   According to USDA computations based on Bureau of Labor
Statistics price information, prices of fresh fruits and vegetables
last year accounted for 11.4 percent of the BLS consumer price
index for food bought in grocery stores, while processed fruits and
vegetables made up only 6.8 percent of the index.
   Meats, by comparison, accounted for 20.3 percent of the BLS
food-at-home price index, while cereals and bakery products
accounted for 14 percent; and dairy products, 12.3 percent.
</TEXT>

</DOC>