<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0296 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0601EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f BC-Brazil-Hotel Adv25   12-22 0899</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Brazil-Hotel, Adv 25,0926</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv25</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Monday Dec. 25 and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Rio's Most Famous Hotel Sold to American Businessman</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KEN SILVERSTEIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIO DE JANEIRO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Copacabana Palace Hotel, a Rio
landmark that once hosted European royalty and Hollywood movie
stars but fell on hard times, has been taken over by the American
businessman who restored Europe's Orient Express train.
   ``The Copa,'' on Rio's famous Copacabana Beach, on the South
Atlantic coast, has been declining for more than 20 years. But
James Sherwood has pledged to restore the hotel's glory.
   The new general manager, Philip Carruthers, would not say how
much Sherwood paid in September to buy a controlling interest in
the hotel. Local press estimates ran from $70 million to $100
million. But he said no expense would be spared to modernize and
improve the hotel.
   ``The hotel is considered to be part of the country's heritage,
so the facade won't be touched. But the inside will be completely
modernized, so we can make the place successful again,''
Carruthers, a Brazil-reared Englishman, said.
   Sherwood is chairman of the London-based, $2 billion, Sea
Containers Ltd., a leading producer of shipping containers.
   Sea Containers owns 42 percent of Orient Express Hotels, Inc.,
which will run the Copa. The purchase of the hotel is the first
tourism investment in South America by Sherwood, whose firms
already run hotels in the United States, the Bahamas, Italy,
Scotland, England and Portugal.
   Orient Express Hotels refurbished the famous train of the same
name, which during its heyday in the 1920s ran from Istanbul,
Turkey, to London, crossing the English Channel by ferryboat.
   The train, which suspended service in the early 1970s, resumed
operations in 1983 and now makes a twice-weekly run between London
and Venice.
   ``The Orient Express has been re-established as a luxury form of
transport, fully restored in 1920s style,'' said Carruthers, adding
that Sherwood hopes to do the same with the Copa, once considered
one of the world's 20 best hotels.
   ``Mr. Sherwood has always been keen on the hotel. It's an
imposing building on an extraordinary site, with wonderful black
and white pavement,'' said Sea Containers Ltd. spokeswoman Naida
Stancioff in London. She was referring to the wide mosaic sidewalk
that lines the 2{-mile long Copacabana Beach.
   The Copa, inaugurated in 1923, was the creation of Brazil's
then-president Epitacio Pessoa, who lamented Rio's lack of a
first-class luxury hotel to accommodate prominent visitors with the
same pomp with which he was received in Europe.
   Businessman Octavio Guinle, whose family controlled the Copa
until it was bought by Sherwood, told Pessoa he would construct a
hotel to rival Europe's finest if he could install a casino. At the
time, Rio had no large tourist market and Guinle felt gambling was
necesasary to make the hotel profitable.
   Pessoa agreed. Guinle imported cement from Germany, marble from
Italy, crystals from Czechoslovakia and furniture from France.
   The hotel, designed by architect Joseph Gire, contains 223
rooms, including a huge presidential suite overlooking the ocean,
14 party rooms, a theater and the ``Golden Room'' for special
attractions. The facade, inspired by hotels in Cannes and Nice,
France, is a mix of classical styles.
   The hotel always was more famous for social significance _
people here say there was a time when coming to Rio and not staying
at the Copa was like going to Rome and not seeing the Pope.
   Over the years, Maurice Chevalier, Nat King Cole, Edith Piaf and
Ella Fitzgerald performed in the Golden Room.
   The hotel has welcomed world leaders ranging from Dwight
Eisenhower to Eva Peron, Fidel Castro to the Shah of Iran. Animals
were prohibited in the Copa after Magda Lupesco, paramour of King
Carol I of Romania, kept eight Pekinese in her room and they ate
the drapes.
   The most legendary stories concern movie stars.
   Orson Welles, in a drunken stupor, threw a bed into the swimming
pool from his second-floor window after Delores Del Rio broke off
their romance.
   In 1939, Errol Flynn pranced naked through the halls. Nudity
reared its head again in the early 1960s when Jayne Mansfield
nonchalantly sat topless at poolside and made headlines for a week.
   Other famous guests who have stayed at the Copa include Brigitte
Bardot, Joan Crawford, Clark Gable and Tyrone Power.
   In 1946 President Eurico Dutra outlawed gambling, and the Copa
casino closed. But the hotel continued to reign as queen of Rio's
social life until 1960.
   In that year, the national capital was moved from Rio to the
inland city of Brasilia, and the hotel lost the glamour of putting
up visiting VIPs.
   The real crunch came in the 1970s, when several international
firms opened modern five-star hotels in Copacabana. By the early
1980s the number of Copa employees had been cut by two-thirds, and
the hotel was barely breaking even.
   ``The Copa had been resting on its laurels for years. The owners
were so used to being THE hotel in Rio they felt they no longer had
to compete,'' said Carruthers.
   He said current problems range from leaky plumbing to shoddy
interiors.
   But renovations, set to begin by next April, should be completed
by mid-1991. Carruthers said there are even plans to reopen the
Golden Room and bring back world-class performers.
   ``When the work is completed, the Copa will be the best hotel in
Rio again,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>