<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0108 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1557EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-BudgetDeficit     12-21 0421</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Budget Deficit,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>Budget Deficit Increases in November</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN D. McCLAIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The federal budget deficit increased $28.96
billion in November, raising the imbalance during the first two
months of the fiscal year to more than half the ceiling for the
entire year, the Treasury Department said Thursday.
   Combined with the October deficit of $26.09 billion, the
imbalance totaled $55.05 billion. The Gramm-Rudman deficit
reduction law sets a $100 billion ceiling for the fiscal year that
began Oct. 1.
   While the deficit is growing at a slower rate than during the
last fiscal year, it will have to slow substantially in subsequent
months to meet the Gramm-Rudman limit.
   The November deficit was 11 percent more than that posted in
October, but 0.6 percent less than the $29.13 billion November
imbalance a year ago.
   The deficit for the first two months of fiscal 1990 was 1.9
percent less than the $56.14 billion recorded in October-November
of fiscal 1989.
   The deficit for fiscal 1989 totaled $152.1 billion.
   President Bush on Tuesday signed a deficit reduction bill that
would trim spending by $14.7 billion, with a goal of reducing this
year's deficit to about $103 billion, according to supporters of
the measure.
   However, private economists said that estimate was based on
optimistic assumptions and that the actual deficit for the current
budget year is likely to be well above that figure.
   The Congressional Budget Office estimates the deficit actually
will be $128 billion despite the bill signed Tuesday.
   Revenue last month totaled $71.21 billion, 10.7 percent above
the same month of 1989, while spending rose 7.2 percent to $100.17
billion. The deficit is the difference between revenue and spending.
   As usual, the biggest spending categories were for the military,
Social Security and other programs in the Department of Health and
Human Services, and interest on the national debt.
   Military spending totaled $24.57 billion in November and $43.74
billion so far this year. It is projected to total $286.89 billion
for the entire fiscal year.
   Social Security payments amounted to $19.75 billion last month
and $39.61 billion so far this year. It is projected to total
$242.95 billion for the year.
   Other HHS programs, including Medicare and Medicaid, totaled
$14.28 billion in November and $27.63 billion so far this year and
are projected to total $190.17 billion for the year.
   Interest on the national debt amounted to $20.20 billion in
November and $36.66 billion so far this year, and is projected to
total $254.36 billion for the year.
</TEXT>

</DOC>