<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0704EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-HomeworkBusters     12-28 0509</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Homework Busters,0525</SECOND>
<HEAD>Call-In Cable TV Program Offers Help With a National Problem: Homework</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARLENE LEVINSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Students who once turned to the ``boob tube'' to
avoid homework may now seek help from the small screen.
   In a new twist on the TV call-in talk show, Cablevision of
Boston offers youngsters a place to call after school with their
homework questions.
   Begun this fall with Boston teachers who take queries at all
levels of mathematics as well as a preparatory course for the
Scholastic Aptitude Test, ``Extra Help'' will be expanded early
next year with a call-in show for English as a second language, and
reading.
   ``It's not a novel idea,'' said Lisa McNulty, education producer
for Cablevision. She pointed out that similar call-in homework help
has been offered since 1976 on Long Island, N.Y., and elsewhere.
   What is unique about the Boston program is that it's tied to the
curriculum used throughout the Boston system, she said.
   The program is available as part of the basic package offered
the system's 100,000 subscribers in Boston and Brookline.
   The size of the audience isn't known, McNulty said, but a
90-minute installment of the program aired live twice a week
typically gets 20 to 25 calls.
   One regular viewer is Billy Marsden, a 17-year-old senior at
Muriel Snowden High School.
   Marsden said Wednesday the program has helped him climb out of
the depths of a flunking grade in algebra last year to become an A
student.
   ``When you're at home and have no one to turn to, (now) you have
someone there, live, to help with your homework,'' said Marsden,
whose parents both work.
   ``One thing I like about it, the teachers are very personable.
They thank you for calling up the line. They don't have this air
like `You should know this' _ I know of some teachers that have
acted like that.''
   The TV teachers start with a three- to five-minute lesson and
then take phone calls from students who ask questions. The TV
teacher helps by guiding the student callers through the problems.
   Nicholas Rubino, program director of citywide mathematics for
the Boston Public Schools, said ``Extra Help'' is one tool Boston
schools are using to improve education.
   ``A lot of the students in high school don't go home and study
two to three hours at night,'' Rubino said. ``That's all over.
They're going to work or to play sports.''
   This causes particular problems in subjects such as science and
mathematics that require repetition and review, he said. ``Extra
Help,'' which is broadcast on Sundays as well as during the week,
is an effort to get around this, he said.
   It's too soon to tell if the program will improve performance,
Rubino said.
   But the program might also be useful to teachers, Rubino said.
Educators tune in to watch their most imaginative and enthusiastic
colleagues in action.
   ``One of the biggest things we're trying to do is retrain
teachers,'' Rubino said. ``What we're trying to do is make teachers
more sensitive.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>