<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1359EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania-Soviet     12-23 0659</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Soviet,0679</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviets Ready to Aid Romania with Medical Help, But no Soldiers</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAREY GOLDBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soviet officials on Saturday sent medical help and
urged Warsaw Pact allies to support the uprising that ousted
Nicolae Ceausescu in Romania. They all but ruled out military
intervention.
   ``We have to support them from the point of view of medical help
and maybe some other kinds of help, but to bring in forces, I think
that's impermissible,'' Premier Nikolai I. Ryzhkov said.
   ``We mustn't repeat mistakes,'' he told reporters at the
Congress of People's Deputies, the Soviet Parliament. ``Not long
ago we gave our evaluation to 1968 in Czechoslovakia. That was on
Dec. 4, and should we repeat something like that a few days later?''
   Ryzhkov was referring to a Warsaw Pact statement that condemned
the 1968 invasion of Czechoslovakia to crush the ``Prague Spring''
reforms.
   The irony in this instance would be the scenario of Soviet
troops helping to oust the vestiges of a Stalinist regime that, of
all the nations in the Soviet bloc, most resembles the rigid system
prior to the rise of Mikhail S. Gorbachev.
   Romanian TV, in the hands of the opposition, said the Soviet
Embassy had pledged to send personnel and equipment to aid the
uprising.
   The Soviet news agency Tass said Gorbachev told Parliament the
Kremlin ``had decided to appeal to the governments of the Warsaw
Pact states with the aim of coordinated efforts in providing
support to the people of Romania.''
   The Soviet Red Cross, Ministry of Health and other organizations
were working with similar organizations in France and Eastern
Europe to provide medicine and specialists, he said.
   ``The first planes with medicines and urgent supplies have
already arrived in Bucharest,'' Tass quoted Gorbachev as saying.
``But they still are being held up in the Bucharest airport, which
is blockaded.''
   Gorbachev said ``a number of other measures'' were being worked
out with Warsaw Pact allies, and that a special working group was
monitoring events in Romania. He provided no other details.
   Tass issued a government declaration that said ``the Soviet
Union is ready to render rapid and effective humanitarian aid to
the Romanian people and the new leadership of the country to
liquidate the consequences of the tragic events of recent days.''
   Another Tass dispatch said some of the wounded were likely to be
evacuated to Moldavia, a Soviet republic bordering Romania.
Moldavians are ethnically very close to Romanians and speak an
almost identical language. Their region belonged to Romania before
World War II.
   Tass said a building housing families of the Soviet trade
delegation in Bucharest was in the line of fire between pro- and
anti-Ceausescu forces and that fires had started in the building.
   ``Tass was told by the Soviet Embassy in Romania that the
property of many Soviet institutions in Romania has been
considerably damaged, and that there are wounded among their staff
members,'' it said. It gave no details.
   ``The lives of Soviet people, including women and children, are
in serious danger,'' Tass said.
   ``The Soviet Union cannot remain indifferent to the fate of
Soviet citizens and demands that those who have unleashed the above
actions, endangering the lives of Soviet people, should immediately
stop them,'' it said.
   Official Radio Moscow said Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard A.
Shevardnadze met with U.S. Ambassador Jack F. Matlock and told him
the Soviet Union regarded the events in Romania as an ``expression
of will by the Romanian people, seeking to renew society through
democracy.''
   Soviet media have pounced on the uprising in Romania, providing
readers and listeners with startling detail of the battle.
   Ceausescu resisted the kind of reforms the Soviets encouraged in
Eastern Europe.
   Romania remained part of the Soviet bloc, but relations between
Gorbachev and Ceausescu were notably cool. They last met early in
December in Moscow, when Tass described their meeting in terms that
left little doubt of sharp disagreement.
</TEXT>

</DOC>