<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1211EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-TroopReduction     12-17 0329</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Troop Reduction,340</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pentagon Planners Recommend Halving US Troops in Europe</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Top Pentagon officials are recommending to
Defense Secretary Dick Cheney that U.S. troop strength in Europe
eventually be cut in half if Soviet reductions continue for several
years, The Washington Post reported Sunday.
   The newspaper said that according to defense officials familiar
with option papers presented to Cheney, reducing the current force
of 305,000 U.S. air and ground forces to 150,000 would retain a
``political minimum'' to maintain a military presence in Europe.
   That reduced level would enable the United States to meet global
responsibilities in an era of deficit reduction at home, they said.
   The Post said the proposals recommend the United States for the
first time consider reducing its naval commitment to defend North
American sea lanes in order to reinforce Europe from America in
wartime.
   Pentagon planners also have concluded that the Soviet Union no
longer can count on the armies of its East European allies to
support it in any hostilities, the story said.
   Senior defense officials last week presented Cheney with their
views on U.S. armed forces for the next century during the first
two of nine marathon sessions.
   According to The Post, the meetings were attended by Cheney,
Joint Chiefs of Staff Chairman Gen. Colin L. Powell, military
service chiefs and civilian service secretaries. The sessions will
resume Monday and then recess until January.
   One policy paper assessing Germany's future role in Europe
predicted that some form of reunification will occur ``within a few
years.''
   The Post quoted the paper as saying that ``we will likely face
by the next century a Europe shaped as much by German economic
influence and military potential as by Russian military presence.''
   Meetings this week will cover options for reshaping Pacific
Basin forces and strategic nuclear forces. For next month's
sessions, Cheney has requested a senior review of the Strategic
Defense Initiative and space programs, weapons acquisition and the
defense industrial base.
</TEXT>

</DOC>