<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0184 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1823EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-Peru 2ndLd-Writethru a0782 12-22 0590</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Peru, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0782,0605</SECOND>
<HEAD>Peru Suspends Anti-Drug Operations With United States</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 3 grafs to UPDATE with demonstration at U.S. Embassy.
Picks up 3rd, `The announcement...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANDREW SCOTT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LIMA, Peru (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government suspended joint operations with
U.S. drug agents in the coca-growing Huallaga Valley, the U.S.
Embassy said Friday, apparently to protest the U.S. invasion of
Panama.
   Foreign Minister Guillermo Larco Cox said Peru was opening its
embassy in Panama City to people seeking political asylum.
   In Lima, police used tear gas to break up a protest outside the
U.S. Embassy and arrested 10 people. The demonstrators were members
of the governing Aprista Party's youth wing.
   The announcement of the suspension of anti-drug operations came
one day after President Alan Garcia said he would not attend the
Feb. 15 drug summit with President Bush and the leaders of Colombia
and Bolivia.
   ``I cannot meet with the leader of an invading nation,'' Garcia
said Thursday.
   The summit was to be held in Cartagena, Colombia, and include
Presidents Virgilio Barco of Colombia and Jaime Paz Zamora of
Bolivia.
   In an interview published Friday in a Lima newspaper, U.S.
Ambassador Anthony Quainton criticized Garcia's reaction to the
U.S. decision to send troops to Panama.
   Garcia said Thursday that the United States ``could seek to do
the same in Peru if it should think the (Peruvian) government isn't
doing enough to fight drug trafficking in the Huallaga Valley.''
   The Huallaga Valley is the world's single largest source of the
coca leaf, the raw material for making cocaine. The valley is the
focus of the U.S.-sponsored anti-narcotics campaign in Peru.
   U.S. drug agents have been carrying out operations since
September with Peruvian police from a U.S.-built base at Santa
Lucia in the Huallaga Valley. The agents accompany polie on daily
raids against clandestine airstrips and coca-processing
laboratories.
   Between 20 and 40 Americans, including agents, pilots and
mechanics, operate from the $3 million base, which is located in
the jungle about 200 miles northeast of Lima. Eight U.S.
helicopters are based at Santa Lucia for use in interdiction
operations.
   Bush has proposed spending $2.2 billion in the next four years
to combat the drug trade in Colombia, Bolivia and Peru. About $73
million has been earmarked for Peru this year in mostly police and
military assistance.
   Analysts estimate about $1 billion a year comes into Peru from
the drug trade. Garcia recently praised the Bush administration for
offering economic assistance to the Andean nations to offset losses
caused by the cutoff of drug dollars.
   Garcia has been highly critical of the U.S. actions in Panama,
and Wednesday recalled Peru's ambassador in Washington in protest.
   He said the intervention was motivated by the United States'
intention to break the Panama Canal treaties of 1977, which call
for Panama to take control of the waterway at the end of the
century.
   In an interview with the newspaper Expreso, Quainton said, ``I
cannot accept the Peruvian government's argument that says we have
acted in order to break the treaties. We recognize the treaties and
understand that they carry great importance for the whole
hemisphere.''
   Quainton called on Latin American countries to support the
U.S.-installed government of Guillermo Endara, who was elected in
May but was blocked from taking power by Noriega.
   He criticized Garcia's decision to recall his ambassador,
saying, ``If there are differences at this moment concerning
Panama, and obviously Garcia is not very happy, this shouldn't make
us lose sight of the common interests that we have.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>