<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0554EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Romania 4thLd-Writethru a0513 12-22 0442</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Romania, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0513,0454</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Government Declares State of Emergency</HEAD>
<UNK>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE with reports Ceausescu may be leaving the
country, more on protests in Bucharest. No pickup.</UNK>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Romania's embattled leadership declared a
state of emergency Friday as a popular revolt spread throughout the
country, Yugoslavia's official Tanjug news agency reported from
Bucharest.
   Tanjug's report said the situation in the country that President
Nicolae Ceausescu has ruled with an iron fist for 24 years was
``dramatic.''
   Some reports said Ceausescu was preparing to flee the country.
   Troops reportedly killed at least 13 people in Bucharest on
Thursday in a crackdown on thousands of demonstrators who jeered a
speech by Ceausescu.
   Various news agencies said Defense Minister Vasile Milea had
committed suicide. The British Broadcasting Corp. said he had
blamed himself for the nationwide unrest that was touched off by
the weekend massacre of hundreds of protesters in the western city
of Timisoara.
   New protests reportedly occurred in Bucharest Friday morning,
and Tanjug said security forces opened fire. There were no reports
of casualties.
   Tanjug said protesters began gathering at 9:00 a.m. in the
capital, chanting ``join us, join us,'' as they marched through the
streets.
   Later Friday, the Bulgarian state news agency BTA reported from
Bucharest that the army had withdrawn from the streets and that
soldiers were ``fraternizing with the people.'' It said that all
police in front of the Intercontinental Hotel _ the scene of
protests Thursday _ had withdrawn.
   The massive unrest, reported in at least eight cities, indicated
Romanians have been caught up in the pro-democracy movements
sweeping Eastern Europe and are no longer willing to tolerate
Ceausescu's repression and the harships he has forced on them.
   There were reports of a general strike in Timisoara and
similarly unconfirmed reports that a major factory in Bucharest
which employs some 20,000 people had gone on strike on Friday.
   Austrian television quoted Romanian exiles as saying Ceausescu
could possibly be leaving the country and heading for exile in
China.
   Western reports, citing witness accounts, said planes were seen
being loaded at Bucharest airport with goods, indicating Ceausescu
and his family could be preparing to leave.
   Ceausescu declared a state of emergency in the Timisoara region
late Wednesday, but the nationwide declaration indicated the unrest
had spread to other parts of the country.
   Romanian Television announced a special program on Friday and
radio was playing military music, Hungarian Radio said.
   A presidential decree said the state of emergency was necessary
because of ``the serious violation of public order through
terrorist acts, vandalism and destruction of public assets,'' the
BBC said, quoting Hungarian Radio.
</TEXT>

</DOC>