<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0090 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1453EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-China-Lord     12-19 0730</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Lord,720</SECOND>
<HEAD>Breaking with Bush, Ex-Ambassador Condemns Scowcroft Missions</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-US-China Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE FEINSILBER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In a reluctant break with President Bush,
Winston Lord, America's ambassador to China until last April,
denounced the administration's secret diplomatic missions to
Beijing Tuesday as steps that will undercut China's moderates.
   He said the United States was signaling the world ``that the
blood around Tiananmen Square has truly been scrubbed away.''
   The United States would not have reversed course so swiftly if
the killings of pro-democracy demonstrators had occurred in Eastern
Europe, Lord said, contending that the ``pilgrimage'' to China this
month by presidential aide Brent Scowcroft displayed ``cultural, if
not racial bias.''
   In a telephone interview from New York, where he is now a writer
and lecturer, Lord said he had supported Bush's post-Tiananmen
Square policy of seeking to preserve a valued relationship with
China, ``but the Scowcroft trip pushed me over the edge.''
   He made his public break with Bush's policy in a signed article
in The Washington Post _ written, he said, before Monday's
revelation that Scowcroft had also led a mission to Beijing last
July, barely a month after the violent crackdown.
   ``I served briefly in China under President Bush and I have
great respect for him and his knowledge of China,'' Lord said. ``I
would have preferred not to have disagreed, but I felt this trip
was such a mistake that I had no choice.
   ``I felt I could speak with some credibility as one who had
worked on the China issue for 20 years, who had met Chairman Mao
(Tse-tung) five times, spent hundreds of hours with Chou En-lai,
has known Deng Xiaping for 15 years and made 11 trips to China
before becoming ambassador,'' Lord said. He served as U.S. envoy to
Beijing for 3{ years.
   ``One does not shore up the long-term foundations for
Sino-American relations by appearing weak to China's leaders and
callous to the Chinese and American people,'' he wrote.
   ``One does not earn respect abroad by reversing field within
months and practicing double standards,'' he added. ``One cannot
maintain a balanced approach at home by submerging our values and
disdaining congressional and public opinion.''
   If Scowcroft expressed outrage during that first visit, as the
White House says, ``then the Chinese ignored it,'' Lord said.
   On Monday, Bush said any suggestion that his actions amounted to
condoning the repression in China was ``not a good rap, and it's
not true.'' The Scowcroft missions have been condemned by Democrats
as ``kowtowing'' to China's hard-liners; few Republicans have
defended it.
   Lord argued that the approach undermined China's ``closet
moderates.''
   ``Far from strengthening their hand, the administration has
robbed them of the argument that Chinese repression and xenophobia
entail costs,'' he wrote. ``Japan, Europe and others will feel free
to follow the Scowcroft trail.''
   Lord said that while censure from Bush might not influence
China's leaders, acquiescence ``surely reinforces their view that
crushing their populace elicits only fleeting outcries, no lasting
repercussions.''
   Lord was especially critical of the toast offered by Scowcroft
during the Dec. 8 visit. He said whatever business Washington most
conduct with Beijing should be done ``in workmanlike fashion, not
with fawning emissaries.''
   In the toast, he said, Scowcroft ``lined up the administration
with the Beijing regime against the Chinese and American people''
when he said, ``In both our societies there are voices of those who
seek to redirect or frustrate our cooperation. We both must take
bold measures to overcome these negative forces.''
   Lord contrasted those words with what Secretary of State James
Baker said two days later in Berlin: ``True stability requires
governments with legitimacy, governments that are based on the
consent of the governed.''
   By condoning the violent suppression of popular, nonviolent
demonstrations, Lord said, ``the Scowcroft mission sends precisely
the wrong signals'' to Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev.
   ``To be sure, the administration would react strongly over a
sustained period to any massacre of innocents in Europe _ and
Gorbachev probably knows this,'' Lord wrote. ``That is precisely
the point. What we have here is not just a double standard but
cultural, if not racial, bias _ however unintentional and
unconscious.''
   ``Are we to believe that Chinese are not like Europeans, that
they never had freedom and cannot afford it now because China would
be ungovernable and `stability' is crucial to economic reform?''
</TEXT>

</DOC>