<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0708EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-HomelessVeterans     12-28 0579</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Homeless Veterans,0597</SECOND>
<HEAD>Veterans Plead for Respect at Homeless Shelter</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LARRY NEUMEISTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For Ben Colon, Vietnam was the beginning of a
downward spiral that led him to the nation's first homeless shelter
for veterans and now a liquid diet to protest conditions there.
   He said he and other veterans have been fighting for their
dignity since returning to the United States and a public which
viewed them as part of a problem.
   ``They were protesting us, calling us baby killers, throwing
eggs at us,'' he said of protesters who met his plane when it
returned from Vietnam in the early 1970s.
   He went home to Brooklyn, broke up with his girlfriend, jumped
from job to job and ended up homeless a year ago, shortly after
overcoming a drug dependency.
   Now 36, Colon stood Wednesday outside the Salvation Army's
shelter in the New York borough of Queens, with Earl Beddoe, 41.
The two of them have had nothing but juice since Dec. 17.
   The shelter's administrator, Al Peck, said the 400 veterans are
free to go elsewhere if they dislike the rules and conditions.
   ``They know beforehand what the rules and regulations are. There
are 2,000 other guys who want to come in,'' Peck said.
   About 15 veterans joined Beddoe and Colon in 15-degree weather
outside the shelter to push demands for better conditions and a say
in running the shelter, which is run by the Salvation Army
specifically for veterans.
   Homeless veteran Fred Tyus read a statement describing the
Salvation Army's treatment of the veterans as ``arrogant,
dictatorial, unresponsive and iron-fisted.''
   ``The management of this residence uses the homeless veterans as
a superb public relations tool and an excellent conduit for
charitable contributions,'' he said.
   The veterans called for posting of job openings at the shelter,
where two of the 40 workers are homeless veterans; better efforts
to find employment and housing for residents; improved medical
care; observance of religious dietary rules and modification of
curfew policies.
   They also want an end to frisking by security officers;
restoration of laundry service; improved ventilation; a
modification of the system in which three infractions of the rules
are grounds for expulsion; and a change in staff attitude.
   ``This is a veterans residence, not a jail or a concentration
camp,'' homeless veteran Richard Catalano said to applause from the
veterans around him. ``We served our country and should not be
treated as undesirable outcasts or children.
   ``We need compassion, sensitivity and support, not disrespect
and hostility.''
   Colon said the last straw came when veterans were told that if
they went to stay with family during Christmas and missed curfew,
they would lose their beds.
   Peck acknowledged the curfew rule hadn't been altered for the
holidays, and said he didn't expect rules and regulations to change.
   ``They can choose to come here or not to come here. There are 25
other shelters in the city system,'' he said. ``It's a difference
in philosophy. They basically want to run their own shelter.''
   Peck planned to meet with homeless veterans, American Civil
Liberties Union Executive Director Norman Siegel and a
representative of Mayor-elect David Dinkins about the dispute.
   Siegel said he hoped the 1990s would end treatment of ``the
homeless, especially the veterans, as undesirable outcasts or
children or crazies or criminals.''
   Beddoe and Colon both said they were willing to die of
starvation, which Peck called ``an effective tool to get attention
from the press.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>