<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0162 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 2008EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i BC-Symposium-Caribbean Adv31   12-26 0761</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Symposium-Caribbean, Adv 31,0782</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 31, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WORLD SYMPOSIUM '90s: Caribbean _ Trouble on the Horizon</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GLASS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN JUAN, Puerto Rico (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Caribbean, which comprises some
of the world's poorest and most heavily indebted nations, faces the
prospect of increasing economic and social pressures in the 1990s.
   Problems confronting the two dozen island states south of
Florida range from rising unemployment and shrinking markets for
sugar and bananas to the spread of AIDS and drug trafficking.
   Some analysts believe the strain could be severe enough to
produce a resurgence of radical politics and civil unrest.
   ``There is just no way for stable democracy to continue in these
islands unless more jobs and income are generated,'' said John
Collins, adviser on the Caribbean for Gov. Rafael Hernandez Colon
of Puerto Rico.
   While celebrating the 500th anniversary of Colombus' discovery
of the New World in 1992, the Caribbean will likely find itself
still coping with the effects of events dictated far from its
shores.
   Caribbean leaders have expressed concern, for example, that the
Cold War thaw could divert Western investment from their region to
the nations emerging from communist domination in Eastern Europe.
   Likewise, Cuba could be forced to reduce its economic dependence
on the Soviet bloc, said Norman Girvan of Jamaica, president of the
Association of Caribbean Economists.
   ``What's happening in Western Europe is changing our external
environment,'' he said. ``What's happening in Eastern Europe must
change the environment of Cuba.''
   For much of the region, one of the darkest clouds on the horizon
is the proposed single European market after 1992. A unified market
would lift trade barriers within the 12-nation European Economic
Community and harmonize foreign trade agreements.
   Among the nations most at risk are the Windward Islands of
Dominica, St. Lucia, St. Vincent and Grenada, which together ship
240,000 tons of bananas a year to Britain. After 1992, they could
lose preferential access to the British market and face fierce
competition from more efficient banana producers elsewhere.
   Many also fear the loss of benefits as a result of the new
U.S.-Canadian trade accord and proposed changes in the Caribbean
Basin Initiative, the program set up by the Reagan administration
to promote U.S.-oriented economic and political development in the
Caribbean and Central America.
   ``The next decade is going to test the very theory that
microstates can survive in a world increasingly dominated by
massive trading blocs,'' said Larry Birns, director of the
Washington-based Council on Hemispheric Affairs.
   Propects for the sugar industry, meanwhile, are dimmed by years
of sharply declining U.S. import quotas, low world prices and
increasing reliance on corn sweeteners and U.S. and European sugar
beets.
   Compton Bourne, professor of economics at the University of the
West Indies in Trinidad, said he thought pressure would build on
Caribbean governments to follow through on commitments to integrate
their economies and pool limited resources.
   But he said propects for the 1990s largely depended on the
willingness of developed nations to reduce the region's debt burden
and provide sorely needed investment.
   Analysts said the expected loss of revenue from traditional
exports would probably accelerate a move into tourism, already the
No. 1 earner of foreign exchange for several islands, and enhance
such industries as computer data entry that use cheap, semi-skilled
labor.
   Birns said there was a danger that environmental considerations
will be overwhelmed by the rush to exploit the islands' lucrative
tourism potential. Tourism is also regarded as a significant factor
in the rapid spread of AIDS, prostitution and drug use throughout
the Caribbean.
   Although conservative, pro-U.S. governments dominate the region,
Birns said, ``the approaching crisis'' could give rise to radically
leftist leadership and possible destabilization.
   If Western lending institutions such as the International
Monetary Fund and the World Bank force further economic austerity
on such debt-ridden nations as Guyana, Jamaica and Trinidad,
``you're going to see an increasingly dangerous situation,'' Birns
said.
   He added that the Caribbean of the 1990s would figure more
prominently in U.S. policy because of increased immigration and
closer scrutiny of the region's role as a major drug-trafficking
route and source of money-laundering through offshore banks.
   Haiti, the Caribbean's perennial trouble spot, approaches the
new decade at a political crossroads.
   Opinion is divided over whether Haiti's military leader, Lt.
Gen. Prosper Avril, will fulfill his pledge to turn over power to a
civilian government in elections scheduled for the fall of 1990. No
one expects a swift solution to the country's profound economic
problems.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Sunday, Dec. 31</NOTE>

</DOC>