<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0127 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1429EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Cambodia     12-22 0336</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cambodia,0347</SECOND>
<HEAD>Khmer Rouge Claim Major Victory in northern Cambodia</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BANGKOK, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Khmer Rouge guerrillas Friday claimed
to have captured the third district capital since Vietnam's troop
withdrawal from Cambodia three months ago, according to the
guerrilla radio.
   The Voice of the National Army of Democratic Kampuchea said the
guerrillas had been besieging the area around the town of Anlung
Veng since mid-November.
   ``On the 19th and 20th of December, our Cambodian national
resistance forces launched an offensive to destroy and completely
liberate the strategic Anlung Veng position,'' said a transcript of
the radio report seen in Bangkok.
   If true, the seizure of Anlung Veng would one of the most
important Khmer Rouge victories since their seizure of the western
town and district capital of Pailin Oct. 22.
   The Khmer Rouge also say they have taken the district seat of
Samlot.
   The radio said Anlung Veng had protected the entire government
defense network along the Dangrek mountain range, which marks the
border between Cambodia and Thailand.
   ``The attack and liberation of this position ... has basically
dismantled the networks defending the positions of the Vietnamese
enemies and their puppets along the Dangrek mountain range,'' it
said.
   The guerrillas also claimed they had ``attacked and swept''
other positions along route 69 and to the south and east of Anlung
Veng.
   The Communist Khmer Rouge is the strongest of the guerrilla
factions fighting the government Vietnam installed in Phnom Penh
after its late-1978 invasion.
   The invasion ended a 3{-year reign of terror by the Khmer Rouge
in which hundreds of thousands of Cambodians were killed.
   Since Hanoi's avowed late-September troop withdrawal, the
guerrillas have launched big attacks and seized several towns in
the northwestern part of the country. The Khmer Rouge maintain that
Hanoi's withdrawal was a trick and that tens of thousands of
disguised Vietnamese soliders remain in the country.
   The radio report said the area around Anlung Veng was defended
by the Vietnamese 302nd division and government soldiers from the
4th military region.
</TEXT>

</DOC>