<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0144EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-TheSecretiveBush Bjt   12-22 0838</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-The Secretive Bush, Bjt,0866</SECOND>
<HEAD>RETRANSMITTING a0430; inserts budget designator.</HEAD>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON TODAY: He's Talkative But Secretive, Open But Closed</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE FEINSILBER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   George Bush, the most public of presidents, is
surely among the most private of presidents, too. He meets anyone
and travels anywhere yet he acts alone, surprising the world _ and
his own closest advisers.
   He is his own secretary of state, his own director of Central
Intelligence, his own China expert, his own national security
adviser.
   He is such a product of government _ the House, the Republican
National Committee, the CIA, the United Nations, the embassy in
Beijing, the vice presidency _ that he does not need advice from
the professionals who surround him. He was there first.
   ``George Bush is very comfortable with himself,'' says Clemson
University political scientist Charles Dunn, an observer of
presidents. ``He has a good sense of person, of who he is. He is
not awed by the Oval Office or by the press.''
   Moreover, says Dunn, secrecy has worked for Bush. ``He has
thrived by exceeding, at least modestly, the level of expectations
for himself,'' Dunn says.
   Bush says that's the way he is, take it or get someone else.
   ``You've got your job,'' he told reporters Thursday afternoon.
``... But I have mine. And that is to conduct the foreign policy of
this country the way I think best. If the American people don't
like it, I expect they'll get somebody else to take my job.''
   ``Bush doesn't like handlers,'' says Fred Greenstein of
Princeton University. ``He's going to do it his way.''
   Bush's tendency to look inward showed up even before he won
office.
   His most important political decision was the choice of a
running mate. He made the selection of Dan Quayle by himself and
kept it to himself.
   Last June, he decided to propose a summit conference to Mikhail
Gorbachev in December and kept it under his hat.
   He sent Brent Scowcroft off to China and had it announced at 2
a.m. on a Sunday morning, astonishing even the China experts on his
team.
   Later it came out that Scowcroft made a similar trip in July
when Bush was publicly isolating China for the terror at Tiananmen
Square.
   When reporters complained Thursday that he had misled them, Bush
at first fell back on a seeming technicality. ``I said no `high
level exchanges' (had taken place. So please look at it
carefully,'' he told reporters.
   Questioned further about his decision to keep the secret, he
said, ``I have an obligation as president to conduct the foreign
policy of this country the way I see fit.''
   Without asking the CIA for advice, Bush decided in October to
sit out an attempted coup against Panama's Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noriega.
   Then, in maximum possible secrecy, on Sunday afternoon he
decided to commit armed forces to the biggest U.S. military
operation since Vietnam.
   Yet this keep-a-secret president is among the most talkative of
presidents. He conducts so many news conferences that reporters run
out of questions.
   Someone who counted up early this month determined that Bush had
held 105 one-on-one meetings with presidents, prime ministers and
kings. Those he hasn't seen, he's telephoned. If he hasn't, he will.
   Greenstein, chairman of Princeton's politics department, says he
sees another aspect in Bush _ an occasional ``spasm of
impulsiveness.''
   He cites Bush's ``hotdogging at Malta'' _ his decision to ride a
cutter through rough seas _ and his determination to attend a
hemispheric drug summit in Colombia, where drug producers have put
a $30 million price on his head.
   Other presidents have been secretive, and as Bush pointed out
they have to be when planning a military operation. The public
understands.
   Some secrets are political. Harry Truman called a special
session of Congress from the rostrum of the 1948 Democratic
National Convention without telling anyone beforehand. Lyndon
Johnson astonished his closest advisers by tacking his announcement
that he would not seek re-election in 1968 to the end of a Sunday
night television speech on Vietnam.
   Bush, even while flying to the Republican convention in 1988,
didn't tell most of his political advisers that he had chosen a
little-known senator as his running mate. When he made the
announcement upon landing, jaws dropped.
   Presidential secrecy can be risky, says Greenstein, but so can
consultation.
   ``Students of decision making say that solitary decision-makers
are likely to miss some facet of the problem; they're bound to have
some blind spots,'' he says.
   On the other hand, he says, ``like-minded people can become
isolated,'' locking out of the process all who are likely to
disagree while reassuring one another of their astuteness.
   Dunn agrees to this extent: presidents who want support when
their decisions go sour had better confide in advisers in advance.
   He cites an adage: ``If you want me with you on the landing,
make sure I'm with you on the takeoff.''
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   EDITOR'S NOTE: Mike Feinsilber has been covering events in
Washington for 20 years.
</TEXT>

</DOC>