<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0241 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2236EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Panama-USReax 2ndLd-Writethru a0880 12-20 1161</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-US Reax, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0880,1193</SECOND>
<HEAD>Americans Support, Denouce U.S. Action in Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 13 grafs to UPDATE with protests in Boston, Seattle;
quotes from Boston rally, further comment from individuals; picks up 9th
graf pvs: ``This was ...</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Some Americans called it necessary, a professor in California
said it was an overreaction and a Panamanian dissident in
Pennsylvania said U.S. military intervention in his homeland
Wednesday was a ``profound error.''
   In New York City, about 200 people marched through midtown to
protest the invasion, chanting ``U.S. out of Panama!'' and other
slogans. They were jeered by numerous passersby.
   ``Get out of here!'' banker Jay Smith shouted at the protesters.
``You're wrong!''
   About 200 protesters marched in downtown Seattle, and about 100
gathered in freezing temperatures in Boston.
   ``Panama is a sister Caribbean country that has outrageous
conditions of poverty. Military solutions bring nothing,'' Dessima
Williams, a former ambassador to the Organization of American
States from Grenada and a fellowship student at Radcliffe College,
said at the Boston rally.
   ``You need a revolution here in the U.S.,'' she said to cheers
from the crowd.``You need a revolution in foreign policy.''
   While Americans and others had mixed opinions about President
Bush's decision to use U.S. troops in Panama, they expressed little
support for Panama leader Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   ``If I had a Christmas wish it'd be that dictators like that all
die,'' said Karen Romano, a 26-year-old sales assistant in Chicago.
   ``What we're doing here is getting rid of a hooligan that is
causing great turmoil in our hemisphere,'' said Jose Garcia De
Lara, national president of San Antonio-based League of United
Latin American Citizens, which claims 125,00 members nationwide.
   ``I think it's a good move. Manuel Noriega is an international
criminal and should be brought to justice,'' said Bernie Morgan,
62, civil court manager in Rochester, N.Y.
   ``I don't always agree with an eye for an eye, but how much can
you take?'' said Daniel Epps, 35, of Randallstown, Md., referring
to the death of a U.S. Marine lieutenant in Panama on Saturday.
   ``It's not a war on Panama. It's a war on drugs,'' Robert Mauro,
a street vendor in New York City, said in reference to drug charges
against Noriega in the United States. ``The drugs are undermining
our country.''
   Criticism centered on the invasion early Wednesday by American
troops in search of Noriega.
   ``This was a profound error. As a Panamanian and an professor of
international law, I can't agree with the action the U.S. has
taken,'' said Miguel Antonio Bernal, a Fulbright professor at
Lehigh University in Pennsylvania and editor of the Panamanian
opposition newspaper, Alternativa.
   ``The U.S. intervenes with thousands of people just to arrest
one guy. This isn't going to help in the long term of our
relationship,'' he said.
   Terry Karl, an assistant professor of political science at
Stanford University in California and Latin American specialist,
said he thought the attack was an overreaction.
   ``It is particularly unfortunate of the United States to rely on
force to resolve issues at a time when the Soviet Union has
renounced the use of force against countries on its borders,'' Karl
said.
   Thomas W. Walker, director of Ohio University's Latin America
studies program, said Latin America should solve its own problems.
   ``We, just like the Soviets, have to learn to be more relaxed in
dealing with the countries that are essentially under our wing,''
Walker said in a statement.
   The executive secretary of the Quakers' American Friends Service
Committee in Philadelphia condemned the military action.
   ``Shorn of rhetoric, this is another case of the U.S. imposing
its will on another country through direct military intervention, a
clear violation of international law,'' said Asia A. Bennett.
   Brian Becker, who helped organize the New York protest, said the
invasion violated the Constitution. ``Only Congress can declare
war,'' Becker said.
   Another protester, Sharon Ayling, said the invasion was an
attempt to regain control of the Panama Canal. The United States
has agreed to turn the canal over to Panama by the year 2000.
   Condemnation also came from the family of Sarah York, a
12-year-old Michigan girl who struck up a correspondence with
Noriega following his 1988 indictment on U.S. drug charges and
twice has visited the dictator.
   The telephone at the family's home in the Upper Peninsula
community of Negaunee was answered by a recorded message from
Sarah's mother, Pauline York: ``We join the people and the nations
of the world in calling on the president and his military to end
this invasion. To the Panamanian people: Todo por la patria,''
which means ``all for the motherland.''
   Others expressed reservations.
   ``Personally, I don't think it's a great idea. The U.S.S.R.
isn't that happy about it and things were going good with them
prior to this,'' said Kari Schumann, 23, a sales assistant from
Henrietta, N.Y.
   But support came from Bush's predecessor and former public
officials.
   ``President Bush's decision to use U.S. military personnel to
protect the lives of American citizens in Panama and to restore
democracy there was correct and deserves our full support,'' former
President Reagan said in a statement issued from his office in Los
Angeles.
   He said the administration has tried to reach a negotiated
settlement to the problems in Panama, but Noriega rejected all
diplomatic efforts.
   ``There comes a time when a president must take action. That
time has come. I join all Americans in the hope that the people of
Panama will soon know the freedoms to which they are entitled, and
that those who have so abused their power there will be brought to
justice,'' Reagan said.
   Former Sen. Howard Baker, who was Senate minority leader when
the Panama Canal treaty was ratified in 1977, said the assault was
the ``only logical response to the situation.''
   Ambler Moss Jr., former U.S. Ambassador to Panama who negotiated
the Panama Canal Treaty, said public criticism from democratically
elected Latin America leaders is likely.
   ``What Latin American leaders will say publicly and what they
think privately are two different things. But they frankly are very
happy to see Noriega fall,'' Moss said in Coral Gables, Fla.
   ``We should have done it a long time ago,'' said Arnold Hunter,
a Greenville, Tenn., retiree who served in World War II and the
Korean War. ``I'm sorry I'm too old to go ... I don't feel lives
are lost when it's for a good cause.''
   Robert Wesson, Hoover Institution scholar and author of a series
of books on Latin America, said the intervention could be a big
plus for Bush's popularity in the United States.
   `As long as the government is acting on behalf of democratic
institutions, getting rid of a pretty terrible dictator, putting in
power people who were elected, and not putting claims on the
country or the canal, I don't think there will be serious
criticism,'' he said from Hoover, a think tank on the Stanford
campus.
</TEXT>

</DOC>