<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0099 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1455EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-SuspectedBomb 1stLd-Writethru a0518 12-27 0273</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Suspected Bomb, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0518,0275</SECOND>
<HEAD>Precede CHARLOTTE</HEAD>
<HEAD>Suspicious Packages Found at Judge's Home, Federal Building</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to UPDATE with 2nd suspicious package found.
Picks up 4th graf, `Officials were....'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Suspicious packages prompted authorities to seal off the area
around a county judge's home in North Carolina and to evacuate a
federal building in Mississippi today as a bomb scare in the
Southeast widened.
   The package Mecklenburg County District Judge Bill Constangy
found on his porch this morning in Charlotte, N.C., contained only
a doll, Assistant Police Chief D.R. Stone said after authorities
destroyed it.
   An X-ray had revealed some electrical and mechanical
connections, presumably inside the doll, officials said.
   Greenville, Miss., police took a suspicious mailed package found
by a Postal Service worker this morning to an unpopulated area.
Officials said they would wait for a postal inspector to arrive
from Memphis, Tenn., before deciding whether to detonate it.
   ``It hasn't been positively identified as an explosive device,''
Freddy Lee, chief deputy U.S. marshal, said from Oxford.
   The federal building in downtown Greenville, where the Post
Office is located, was evacuated temporarily.
   The package had no return address and officials wouldn't
disclose the addressee.
   Officials were concerned because of recent mail or package bombs
directed against judges or courts in Alabama, Georgia and Maryland.
   Constangy, like other targets, had taken some controversial
stands. He had called himself a pro-life Democrat before hearing a
case involving anti-abortion protesters and, in November, was sued
by the North Carolina Civil Liberties Union and other lawyers over
his practice of opening court with a prayer.
</TEXT>

</DOC>