<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0237 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1026EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Bechtel-Japan     12-21 0278</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bechtel-Japan,0287</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bechtel Wins Piece Of Tokyo Airport Project</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bechtel Group Inc. said it has won its
first construction contract in Japan by landing a ``significant''
role in the building of an $800 million terminal at Tokyo's Haneda
Airport.
   The construction and engineering giant said Wednesday it will
participate with nine Japanese companies in building the
3.1-million-square-foot terminal, which gets under way next month.
The project is scheduled to be finished in late fiscal 1992.
   Bechtel, like other U.S. contractors, has been trying to get a
foothold in the Japanese construction market. It beame the first
American company to receive a construction license in Japan but
until now has been limited to feasibility studies for bridges,
airport terminals, geothermal plants and a golf course.
   Company officials insisted their role in the Haneda Airport
project would be more than a token one, though they did not specify
a dollar figure.
   ``Our role in this important project is a very significant one,
definitely not window dressing,'' said John L. Moore Jr., a member
of the Bechtel Group Inc.'s board of directors. ``We're going to
have to pull our weight alongside our Japanese partners.''
   Haneda Airport, near downtown Tokyo, has been used primarily for
domestic flights since the opening of Narita Airport 11 years ago.
The terminal is being built to handle Japan's fast-growing domestic
air-travel business.
   The project is headed by Taisei Corp. and includes Overseas
Bechtel Inc. as a major shareholder. Other firms in the venture are
Kajima Corp., Shimizu Corp., Takenaka Komuten Co. Ltd., Ohbayayashi
Corp., Tokyo Construction Co. Ltd., Toda Construction Co. Ltd.,
Sato Kogyo Co. Ltd., and JAL Construction Co. Ltd.
</TEXT>

</DOC>