<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0099 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1746EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Panama-Press     12-23 0542</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Press,0561</SECOND>
<HEAD>Concern for Reporters' Safety Clashes with Need To Get The Story</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DOUGLAS GRANT MINE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOWARD AIR BASE, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Journalists itching to get to the
hemisphere's story of the year have sometimes chafed at the
restrictions imposed on them by the U.S. military.
   ``If we had it to do over again, we would never have allowed you
all to come,'' said a harried Air Force Col. Ronald Sconyers,
spokesman for the U.S. Southern Command.
   Reporting has indeed been dangerous _ though not impossible _ in
the days following the U.S. invasion that began Wednesday.
   Snipers, Panamanian Defense Force resisters, Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noriega's Dignity Battalion fighters, looters, and various and
sundry assailants roamed the city with U.S. soldiers searching for
Noriega himself.
   Several reporters, including Candice Hughes of The Associated
Press, were held hostage and threatened with death by Noriega
loyalists before they were set free.
   The U.S. Embassy said Saturday that pro-Noriega forces had
released Jon Meyersohn, a CBS producer seized Wednesday at the
Marriott Hotel, and American businessman Doug Mullen. CBS said
Mullen was an executive with GTE and was taken hostage with
Meyersohn.
   Some journalists were not so lucky. A Spanish photographer was
killed and two foreign journalists were wounded by gunfire.
   Before dawn Friday, about 300 journalists arrived here. But the
Southern Command kept most of them cooped up at Howard Air Base and
on nearby Rodman Naval Station.
   Clad in a helmet and full battle gear, Sconyers briefed a
hungry, tired, unwashed legion of reporters late Friday at Howard,
four miles west of Panama City.
   ``A reporter's job is currently impossible on the streets of
Panama City,'' he said.
   The journalists slept on the floor and lived on hot dogs and
popcorn while waiting for permission to leave. Though mindful of
the danger in Panama City, most of the journalists began to chafe
at the restrictions.
   By Saturday morning, Southern Command authorities had convinced
about a third of the journalists to return home. The command then
``released'' the other reporters.
   ``I can understand why they did it. I don't like it, but I
understand it,'' said one U.S. reporter.
   A handful of journalists was able to get into Panama on small
chartered planes Thursday before two big charters _ one from Miami
and the other from neighboring Costa Rica _ arrived early Friday.
   It was that descent of hundreds of reporters that set off alarms
at the Southern Command.
   One reporter who arrived Thursday, Marjorie Miller of the Los
Angeles Times, said it was dangerous to report from the streets
Friday and that setting loose several hundred reporters _ most with
little or no experience in Panama or in combat _ could have had
grave consequences.
   ``There were a lot of people with guns on the streets,'' said
Ms. Miller, who has worked in Central America for several years
covering war and social upheaval.
   One reporter called the restrictions an attempt to
``breast-feed'' the media with what the Southern Command wanted
reporters to hear and to keep them away from the ugly side of the
invasion.
   He said individual reporters and their organizations should be
allowed to consider the risks and take responsibility for their
coverage.
</TEXT>

</DOC>