<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1220EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Iran-Iraq 1stLd-Writethru a0506 12-25 0393</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iran-Iraq, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0506,0399</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iran Frees 50 Sick, Disabled POWs</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with prisoners reported released.
Pickup 5th pvs, ``It did...''</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iran released 50 ailing or disabled Iraqi
prisoners of war Monday to Red Cross representatives as a gesture
of good will, Tehran radio reported.
   It was not clear whether Iraq would reciprocate and release some
of the Iranian POWs it holds. An earlier attempt to arrange a
formal swap collapsed.
   The radio said the prisoners were released in Tehran to the Red
Cross for eventual repatriation.
   Tehran radio, monitored in Cyprus, quoted a Foreign Ministry
statement as saying the 50 were freed on humanitarian grounds and
in response to a request by U.N. Secretary-General Javier Perez de
Cuellar.
   It did not say when Perez de Cuellar made the appeal. But
Baghdad last week sent a memorandum to the U.N. chief expressing
concern over POWs in Iran after a Red Cross report on Dec. 6 that
22 Iraqis have died in jail.
   The deaths were attributed to ``heart attacks and relevant
diseases,'' but Iraqi media suggested the prisoners might have been
tortured to death.
   The Red Cross has registered 50,000 prisoners held by Iran and
more than 19,200 in Iraqi camps. United Nations officials and
diplomats estimate the two sides hold about 100,000 POWs between
them.
   The Red Cross secured an agreement to repatriate ailing
prisoners immediately after a U.N.-cease-fire halted the war on
Aug.20, 1988. The deal collapsed after the repatriation of only 400
disabled and wounded prisoners, with both sides accusing each other
of falsifying the number of captives seeking asylum.
   Angelo Gnadinger, Middle East chief for the Red Cross, visited
Tehran and Baghdad last week seeking a swap of the remaining 1,000
wounded and disabled POWs held by both sides.
   The mediation collapsed, mainly because Tehran insisted the
exchange be coupled with a withdrawalof Iraqi forces from chunks of
land they occupied in the final weeks of the war.
   U.N.-sponsored peace talks have been deadlocked mainly over the
troop withdrawal issue and Iraq's demand for redrawing the border
to give it full sovereignty over the Shatt-Al-Arab waterway.
   The channel, a confluence of the great Tigris and Euphrates
rivers, is Iraq's sole outlet to the Persian Gulf. Before the war,
the border ran down the middle of Shatt-Al-Arab.
</TEXT>

</DOC>