<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1246EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China-Protests     12-26 0578</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Protests,0595</SECOND>
<HEAD>Poster at University Mocks Ceausescu, Chinese Leaders</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHY WILHELM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An unsigned poster mocking deposed Romanian
leader Nicolae Ceausescu and China's hard-line leaders went up at
Beijing University, birthplace of China's spring democracy
movement, a source confirmed Tuesday.
   ``Lost dog,'' read the poster, which was put up over the weekend
after Ceausescu's flight from his palace in Bucharest and before
his arrest and execution.
   It said the dog, named Ceausescu, might be coming to China to
join four other dogs _ a reference to China's senior leader Deng
Xiaoping, Premier Li Peng, President Yang Shangkun and Communist
Party chief Jiang Zemin.
   The poster, which authorities swiftly took down, violated
martial law regulations in force since May, when Beijing University
students led massive protests for democratic reform in China. Deng
ordered the army into Beijing in June to crush the protests,
leaving hundreds and possibly thousands dead.
   It was the third illegal ``big character poster'' in Beijing
this month, according to Chinese and Western sources. One urging
students to remember those killed in June went up at the Central
Drama Academy in early December, and another appeared briefly
inside the residential compound of the People's Daily, the
Communist Party newspaper.
   That poster read: ``Down with the illegal Li Peng government.''
   At a Dec. 8 dance, students at the drama school also played
songs about the June crackdown from a U.S.-recorded album titled
``China 1989,'' the sources said.
   No arrests have been reported in connection with any of the
incidents. However, at least six and possibly eight people were
arrested Dec. 9 when students from the Beijing College of
Aeronautics unfurled a banner reading: ``Motherland, why are you so
poor?''
   The incidents indicate that anger over June's events has not
subsided, despite intense political education and a scaling down of
the troop presence in Beijing.
   If anything, tensions have increased as authorities have
increased controls. Among other measures, students say the
government appears to be closing the door slowly on study abroad
for all except state-sponsored students by making it impossible for
other students to take the necessary tests or obtain college
transcripts.
   In this atmosphere, news of the democratic changes in East
Europe has been greeted with pleasure but also bitterness by some
Chinese students that their movement did not also succeed.
Romania's uprising has aroused the greatest excitement, because it
was the only other country where hard-line Communist leaders
resorted to violence.
   At one college, some students held a party to celebrate
Ceausescu's ouster.
   The official news media has carried only sparse reports on the
uprising and omitted any explanation of its cause.
   At least one hotel in Beijing stopped selling foreign newspapers
late last week after the uprising began, apparently because of
their reports from Romania. But hotels were not stopped from
showing satellite transmissions of foreign TV networks such as
Cable News Network.
   Chinese workers at one hotel clustered silently around a TV set
Tuesday as CNN showed the bodies of Ceausescu and his wife after
their execution.
   ``North Korea will be next _ that is my prediction,'' said one
Chinese intellectual, who was gleeful over Ceausescu's downfall.
But he did not believe China would follow in the domino-like
toppling of hard-line leaders.
   ``China is too big and poor,'' he said, a widespread sentiment.
   Others speculated it would only make Chinese leaders more
convinced of the correctness of their June crackdown and the need
for tighter surveillance.
</TEXT>

</DOC>