<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0271 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1955EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-PersonalIncome 1stLd-Writethru f0413 12-21 0629</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Personal Income, 1st Ld-Writethru, f0413,0645</SECOND>
<HEAD>Consumer Spending Rose Sharply in November on Higher Incomes</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 4th graf, `The report ...,' to CORRECT last high from March
to April. Also moving on general news wires.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN D. McCLAIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Consumer spending rebounded 0.7 percent in
November from its sharp fall a month earlier, the government
reported Thursday, and analysts said it continues to be one of the
bright spots in a slowing economy.
   ``It suggests that while we have some weak areas in the economy,
particularly in the manufacturing sector, that the consumer has not
turned off completely,'' said David Jones, an economist with Aubrey
G. Lanston &amp; Co. in New York.
   The Commerce Department also reported an 0.8 percent increase in
personal incomes in November, but some analysts questioned whether
income growth will soon begin to weaken and thus cause a decline in
spending.
   The report said consumer spending rose at a seasonally adjusted
annual rate to $3.54 trillion, a 0.7 percent increase and the
steepest gain since a 1 percent jump last April.
   The advance was a rebound from a 0.2 percent decline in October,
which was the first decrease since a 0.1 percent dip in September
1988 and the largest drop since a 1.4 percent fall in January 1987.
   Consumer spending, which has been a major factor for the
economic growth during the first nine months of the year, is
watched closely as a barometer of economic health because it
accounts for about two-thirds of the nation's economic activity.
   Commerce reported last week that retail sales rose 0.8 percent
in November, a rebound from a 1.3 percent decrease in October.
Analysts said it reflected the start of the Christmas buying season
the weekend after Thanksgiving.
   As measured by the gross national product, the economy grew at a
3 percent rate in the third quarter after gains of 3.7 percent in
the first and 2.5 percent in the second, but analysts expect a
sharp decline in the three-month period ending Dec. 31.
   Jones said prospects are good for continued consumer spending,
``particularly in non-durables such as apparel, and in the services
area ... because consumers are still basically optimistic and have
income growth to support that optimism.''
   Personal incomes in November totaled $4.54 trillion at a
seasonally adjusted annual rate, following a similar 0.8 percent
gain to $4.50 trillion in October. It was the largest increase
since a 1 percent gain last March.
   But Lawrence Chimerine, senior economic adviser for the WEFA
Group, a Bala Cynwyd, Pa., forecasting group, said there were a
number of factors that could lead to decreased spending.
   ``The negatives are the high debt loads,'' he said. ``People now
are getting more concerned about the future. You're seeing more
layoffs and, particularly for durables, the pent-up demand we had
in the earlier '80s has just been used up. People just don't have
the same needs.''
   The $26.2 billion increase in personal consumption, which
includes everything except interest payments on debt, contrasted to
a $6.3 billion decrease in October.
   Purchases of durable goods _ big-ticket items expected to last
more than three years _ rose $1.9 billion, while purchases of
non-durable goods jumped $12.4 billion. Spending on services
increased $11.9 billion.
   The November report showed that Americans' incomes after taxes
rose 0.9 percent, up from October's 0.8 percent gain.
   Americans' savings rate _ savings as a percent of disposable
income _ rose to 6.1 percent, up from October's 5.7 percent rate.
   The key component of the income category, wages and salaries,
edged up $1.7 billion in November following a $29.4 billion gain in
October.
   Payrolls at manufacturing companies, hit hardest by the Federal
Reserve's high-interest polices, fell $4.9 billion, after an
October advance of $6.3 billion.
</TEXT>

</DOC>