<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0223 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2207EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SantaCalls     12-20 0391</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Santa Calls,0405</SECOND>
<HEAD>Boeing Engineers Pressed Into Service As Santa's Helpers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM KLAHN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Youngsters calling Santa Claus over the past week
may have been thinking of his sleigh and eight tiny reindeer, but
they got the people who keep 530-mph, four-engine military radar
reconnaissance jets in the air.
   And most of them will never know they got the wrong number.
   The children got connected to technicians at Boeing's support
center for specially equipped military aircraft.
   ``This was quite a surprise when it started out,'' said Duane
Oberg, developer with the Airborne Warning and Control System, or
AWACS, fleet support system.
   ``But after the first several calls we figured out what had
happened, and just started answering phones as if this was Santa's
workshops.''
   Hundreds of children got their lines crossed because of
transposed numbers in a telephone listing in a national magazine,
Boeing Aerospace &amp; Electronics spokesman Elliot Pulham said
Wednesday.
   The aerospace branch of Boeing specializes in missiles,
spacecraft and spy airplanes _ for some, the ultimate toys.
   He said the calls began about Dec. 13 and were winding down by
the middle of this week, after calls for Santa were redirected.
   The first youngsters might have been greeted with, ``Hi. This is
AWACS Fleet Support Central. Can I help you?'' Pulham said. But the
engineers lightened up and played along.
   ``They were putting on their bonnets, and would play Santa
whenever the children would call, but they would give technical
information when customers called,'' he said.
   The normal phone calls to the center are for technical
assistance provided for those who fly, service and repair the AWACS
aircraft, which are loaded with sophisticated radar and other
surveillance equipment.
   There are only 60 such aircraft in operation built by Boeing,
Pulham said, and the toll-free phone line is normally not busy.
   The engineers didn't mind the distractions.
   ``It was actually kind of fun,'' Oberg said. ``Definitely a
break from what we normally do. Although I think some of our
customers were a bit surprised when they called for radar or
computer information and ended up talking to Santa's workshop.''
   Pulham said the situation didn't get out of hand, no matter what
the children might have asked for.
   ``We didn't promise anybody any cruise missiles or anything like
that for Christmas,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>