<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0221EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherWatchers Bjt   12-29 0668</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weather Watchers, Bjt,0686</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rural Observers Scan Skies, Tally Temperatures</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: RETRANSMITTING to restore AP logo.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURA MYERS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RENO, Nev. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eighty-year-old Edna Cooley has been waking up
at 3 a.m. for nearly 22 years to trudge outside in occasionally
bone-chilling cold and record the weather in the sparsely settled
high desert of central Nevada.
   Some 18{ hours later, Mrs. Cooley makes the last of her six
daily weather observations and temperature checks for National
Weather Service records on Austin, population 350, earning $11.10 a
day for her troubles.
   ``Why do I keep doing it? They say you can even get used to
hanging if you hang long enough,'' Mrs. Cooley said. ``I've been
meaning to quit for two years, but can't find anyone else to do
this.''
   She is among the last of a breed of hands-on recorders of the
nation's highs, lows and precipitation amounts. Without the
observers, meteorologists and forecasters would have a more
difficult time predicting the weather.
   ``There's a need for live observation,'' said Gerald Miles, a
meterologist in Elko who supervises the weather watchers.
``Equipment is reliable, but you need good remarks from observers
to go with it. Equipment has its limitations.''
   Bill Davis, the Salt Lake City-based western regional director
of the observation program, said about 50 weather watchers are on
the National Weather Service payroll in his jurisdication.
   Several hundred others, mostly farmers, voluntarily report
climate information to the agency to help keep a historical weather
record.
   Davis said at-home weather observation stations were set up
during World War II ``basically wherever they could find someone
and where we didn't have a government office.'' Meteorology was
rapidly developing, and officials found ``eyeball-type''
information improved their ability to track storms, he said.
   The observers must pass a certification test and use weather
service equipment to take measurements of temperature, winds, dew
point, atmospheric pressure and precipitation. The routine can take
10 to 15 minutes, depending on the weather.
   ``There's no grand plan to get rid of the weather observers,''
Davis said. ``I think they'll be around for the next decade. But
we'll lose some to equipment and because people will retire and the
younger generation doesn't want to work that hard for so little
money.''
   Mrs. Cooley said that when she goes on vacation, ``there's no
weather coming out of Austin. The TV stations just say, `Oh well, I
guess that Edna's out of town again.'''
   Debi Gill, who usually reports Nevada's coldest overnight lows
at Wildhorse Reservoir just south of the Idaho border, has been an
observer for 3{ years.
   ``Sometimes, I wonder why I keep doing it, especially at 5:30 in
the morning,'' she said.
   Mrs. Gill, like other weather observers, gets $2.50 for the
first early morning recording, $1.60 for daytime readings and $1.90
for each night observation.
   She said the most frightening thing about the job is the
late-night readings when near silence fuels the imagination, she
said.
   ``When the lake is frozen over the ice groans and the coyotes
are yipping and howling, I just get all nervous,'' said Mrs. Gill.
``It's silly, but I get scared of the bogyman because that's the
only one who would be out that time of night.''
   The good part of the job is closely watching how nature works
and stopping to enjoy the surrounding weather, sunrises and
sunsets, she said.
   ``Not many people stop and watch the sky,'' she said. ``The
clouds actually grow, puff up right before your eyes. It's
wonderful.''
   Observers must distinguish among three layers of clouds with
nine different basic cloud types possible at each level.
   Susan Deming, who has been observing the weather in Battle
Mountain in north-central Nevada since May, said people sometimes
stop her on the street or telephone her asking what the weather
will be like or with weather-related inquiries, such as whether it
is too soon to plant.
   ``I have to tell them I don't predict the weather; I just
observe it,'' she said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>