<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0111EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CoalFieldChristmas     12-18 0517</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Coal Field Christmas,0532</SECOND>
<HEAD>UMW Hosts Christmas for Striking Miners</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto CN1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KELLY P. KISSEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CORA, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A toy backhoe and tiny bulldozer were perfect
Christmas gifts for 5-year-old twins who want to be just like dad,
a coal miner who has been on strike for eight months.
   Darren and Justin Noe, wearing T-shirts saying ``UWMA On
Strike,'' were among dozens of children who received gifts at a
United Mine Workers of America Christmas party.
   ``They know we're on strike. I've had them up to the picket
line,'' said the father, Larry Noe, a Pittston Coal Group Inc.
striker. ``The backhoe and dozer were good gifts. They look like
they work in the mines.''
   Teen-age children of the miners were given cards with $20
inside. Striking miners who had been receiving $225 a week from the
union's strike fund were given $1,000 bonuses and the union
prepared hundreds of bags of groceries.
   ``Every family will get a bag, every child will get a toy and
every striking miner will get his $1,000 bonus today,'' said Howard
Green, a member of the UMW international board from District 17 in
Charleston.
   The union prepared food for more than 1,500 people for
Saturday's party at what they call Camp Solidarity II, a converted
department store southwest of Logan. Guests braved single-digit
temperatures and icy roads to make an appearance.
   Up many of the hollows, the ice and snow from a storm painted a
picture worthy of Christmas cards, but many prepared for a meager
holiday because of the strike.
   ``There's not much this year,'' said James Justice, a striker
from Dehue. ``It's been pretty tough.''
   A man dressed as Santa Claus visited the camp and handed
presents to the children. He handed out toy construction equipment,
footballs, basketballs, remote control cars and dolls.
   Everett Street, a former Army mess hall sergeant who is in
charge of the kitchen, said he prepared meals for 1,500 to 1,800
people. Families also brought covered dishes.
   ``The people in the county donated food and collections paid for
more of it. It's all coming together,'' Street said.
   Pittston workers in Virginia and West Virginia went on strike
April 5 after working 14 months without a contract. Kentucky's
Pittston employees joined the strike in late June.
   Coal miners from other areas have been invited to both of the
UMW's strike camps to lend support to the strikers, who say
Pittston is trying to break the union. The UMW also is several
smaller operations in West Virginia, including New Beckley Coal,
over separate issues.
   In the Pittston strike, the company said it needs special
concessions from the union, including Sunday workdays and mandatory
overtime and a release from benefits obligations.
   The union has been distributing benefits from the strike fund to
3,700 strikers nationwide, nearly 2,000 of them from Pittston.
   Talks between the union and Pittston have been continuing in
Arlington, Va., but it's unclear whether the dispute is close to
being resolved. Mediator William Usery has limited media access to
the talks in his bid to end the strike.
</TEXT>

</DOC>