<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1224EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-FakeBomb     12-28 0363</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Fake Bomb,0373</SECOND>
<HEAD>Discovery of Fake Bomb Touches Off Investigation</HEAD>
<DATELINE>EL PASO, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A fake bomb discovered on the desk of a
city council member has touched off a police investigation,
authorities said. But the council member says the whole thing was a
joke that was blown out of proportion.
   Police Chief John Scagno said Wednesday officers are
investigating the discovery of a look-alike bomb on Jay J. Armes'
desk Tuesday evening. City Hall was evacuated after a custodian
spotted the device about 6 p.m.
   The realistic-looking bomb had seven sticks of wood wrapped with
waxed paper used on actual sticks of dynamite and a working mercury
switch that caused lights to flash when the thing was tilted, said
Lt. Dave Hamrick, a member of the police's Bomb Squad.
   ``Until we had a chance to check it out, it looked very real,''
Hamrick said.
   But Armes says the ``bomb'' was a gag Christmas gift from his
adult son and that he brought it into his office to use as a clock
Tuesday morning. Armes said his son ordered the device through a
magazine.
   He accused the police of overreacting to the bomb because he has
been feuding with Scagno for months, often questioning the chief's
competence at City Council meetings.
   ``This is the only way they can get back at Jay Armes,'' Armes
said.
   Police deny they are seeking revenge. ``This case is being
handled like any other investigation,'' said Lt. J.R. Grijalva,
police spokesman.
   Earlier this month, bombs killed a federal judge in Alabama and
a city council member in Savannah, Ga., and wounded a state judge
in Maryland. Other bombs were found before they exploded in
Jacksonville, Fla., and Atlanta. El Paso police officials said the
fear created by those incidents was one reason they evacuated City
Hall when the ``bomb'' was found Tuesday.
   In Texas, making or possessing a device that causes somebody to
believe it is an actual bomb or causes emergency officials to
respond is a Class A misdemeanor.
   Scagno said his department will turn over its investigation to
the county attorney's office. Scagno said the attorney's office
will decide if charges should be filed.
</TEXT>

</DOC>