<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1050EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-NoriegaStatement 1stLd-Writethru a0487 12-29 0438</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Noriega Statement, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0487,0443</SECOND>
<HEAD>Panel Suggests Way Out of Noriega Dilemma</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Subs final grafs 10-12, `Anderson said...' to CORRECT spelling
to Andersen.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM F. RAWSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Vatican should put the fate of ousted
Panamanian Gen. Manuel Noriega in the hands of a special public
tribunal, a group of American scholars suggested.
   In a statement transmitted this week to the Vatican, nine U.S.
legal experts and academicians said turning Noriega over to a
``grand-jury-type panel'' would set a positive precedent in
international criminal law for handling deposed dictators accused
of criminal activity.
   The panel should be made up of ``distinguished persons publicly
known to be of high integrity and fair-mindedness, selected by
yourselves and others, including the secretary general of the
United Nations,'' the statement said.
   Noriega has been holed up in the Vatican embassy in Panama City
since Sunday. Both U.S. and Panamanian officials have urged the
Vatican to turn him over for trial on drug-trafficking charges.
   Alfred F. Andersen, a self-described retired philosopher and
author who lives in Tucson, said in a telephone interview Thursday
that he and the eight others who signed the document believe it
would be a mistake for the Vatican simply to hand Noriega over to
the United States.
   ``We, the undersigned, commend your not making a hasty decision
in this matter, and your evidently wanting to be sure that your
ultimate decision will truly serve the cause of justice in this
turbulent world,'' the statement said
   Andersen said the statement was his idea.
   ``I saw the dilemma the Vatican was in,'' Andersen said. ``I
started thinking about how he could be turned over to someone who
would be more objective than the United States or even the
Panamanian government.''
   Andersen said he contacted a friend, Richard A. Falk, a
Princeton University international law professor, and the two of
them worked out the statement.
   Andersen said he and Falk then contacted the others whose names
appear on the document transmitted to the Vatican Wednesday night
and again on Thursday.
   The Vatican has yet to respond, Andersen said.
   In addition to himself and Falk, Andersen said the statement
also was signed by Benjamin B. Ferenca, a prosecutor at the
Nuremberg trials following World War II, who now lives in New
Rochelle, N.Y.; Burns H. Weston, a University of Iowa law
professor; Stephen Cary, retired vice president of Haverford
College, Haverford, Penn.; Hazel Henderson, an author, St.
Augustine, Fla.; Gerald Mische, president of Global Education
Associates, New York; and Saul Mendlovitz, director of World Order
Models Project, New York.
</TEXT>

</DOC>