<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0255EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Romania-Graves     12-27 0451</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Graves,0464</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romanians Bury Their `Heroes Of The Revolution'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BUCH6</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MORT ROSENBLUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At graveside, a yellow bath towel
knotted around a rough pine cross and a spray of white
chrysanthemums scrounged in a city where even bread is scarce were
among tributes to heroes of the revolution.
   A procession of sobbing families Tuesday accompanied makeshift
coffins to a field of 200 freshly dug graves in southern Bucharest.
   One coffin was for 14-year-old Silviu Minca, whose friends said
he was killed when the nation's hated security police called to
them from a window and opened fire when they approached.
   The security police have killed hundreds, perhaps thousands, of
people in in their armed resistance to the uprising that toppled
Nicolae Ceausescu.
   Officials at Belo cemetery believe 300 to 400 people killed in
fighting during the past five days will have to be buried, but
perhaps hundreds more are believed hidden in secret graves dug by
Ceausescu's men before he was overthrown.
   By a pine cross marked ``first hero,'' a veteran gravedigger
named Nicolae Abag wept along with the mourners.
   ``This is so, so much,'' he said. ``I have not cried here since
the earth moved in 1977,'' the year of the earthquake in which
almost 2,000 people were killed.
   At the next grave, people mourned Nicisor Paunoiu, an elevator
mechanic who responded when the radio station appealed for help
because it was attacked by the Securitate, the security police.
   Paunoiu and three friends stormed a Securitate stronghold
unarmed. Three of them were cut down by automatic weapons fire. He
left a son and a daughter who was married three weeks ago.
   Farther down, there was the student Dan Adrian Urucu, who went
to protect the TV station. He joined 3,000 others in a human shield
between harassing Ceausescu loyalists and army men protecting the
13-story TV building. Urucu, 21, was shot in the back.
   ``His death was for all of us, for our freedom,'' student Ileana
Nita said as she stood by Urucu's grave. ``It was a sacrifice we
must appreciate. We have to learn what it means to be free and what
that is worth.''
   Bits of food, round bread rings and bath towels adorned many of
the graves, symbols from an ancient tradition of offering things to
the dead they may need in the afterlife.
   Boughs from Christmas trees with long, yellow candles burning
were left on many graves and there were photographs of smiling
young faces tacked to crosses.
   The Romanian news agency Agerpress said a monument would be
erected at the cemetery to pay tribute the revolution's dead for
``their pure sacrifice for Romania's freedom.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>