<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0150 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1759EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-BushText 2ndAdd a0650-a0657 12-18 0886</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Bush Text, 2nd Add, a0650-a0657,780</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHN: massive cuts.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Q. Mr. President, the issue of China is on a lot of people's
minds. You seem to approach China differently than you approach
some other countries. I know when you talked to Mr. Gorbachev, you
gave him a list of human rights cases you want to resolve. Earlier
in the year, in your Texas A&amp;M speech, you laid out a number of
conditions and challenges to the Soviet Union. With China, you seem
to take almost a kid-glove approach. I mean, do you feel that they
require and demand different treatment or special treatment?
   BUSH: Some think up until recently the approach wasn't kid
glove, it was almost isolation. That's what some felt, Mike, before
I sent a mission over there. Some thought that we were just totally
isolating China. So I don't quite understand your comparison.
   Q: Well, there was a massacre in Tiananmen Square and a few _
   BUSH: And we strongly disapproved of it and spoke out against
it. And I still strongly disapprove of it and I'm delighted to
speak out against it. So, why are you _ what is you _ I missed your
question.
   Q: Well, was there ever any consideration of a more low-key
meeting, for example, without toasts and dinners, which may have
sent some people a signal somewhat different than outrage, but of
the _ let bygones by bygones?
   BUSH: I don't think anyone is sending that kind of _ that
anything should be read into that. I know some of my political
opponents have done that. There's a concerted effort by the
Democratic Party to do that, by their leadership, by the chairman
of the Democratic National Committee. But he is burdened with a
lack of knowledge about China.
   Q: Mr. President, when do you expect Mr. Fang Lizhi will be
allowed to leave the country?
   BUSH: I don't know when that will happen.
   Q: Did you get any concessions?
   BUSH: I won't discuss the specifics.
   Q: Why?
   BUSH: Because I don't believe in doing that, Helen.
   Q: They didn't promise you anything?
   BUSH: I'm more interested in action than I am in premature
speculation. And I notice now that some of the critics who were so
opposed in using this fantastically diabolically anti-me language,
they come up now in saying, well, if you get a, b and c, then it
will be all right, or then we'll understand. Let them just stay
tuned in.
   Q: Well, did you get any concessions? I'm not asking _
   BUSH: I'm not going to discuss what I did or didn't get.
   Q: But there's still plenty _
   BUSH: You see, I still believe that sometimes to effect change
you talk in confidence to people. Now I know that doesn't go _
that's not in keeping with your line of work. You want everything
to be public and I understand it. But I've got to say, I'm very
sorry, I'm not going to discuss it.
   Q: You're out on a limb praising the reforms _ democratic
movement in Eastern Europe and you go and salute a brutal regime.
   BUSH: I don't think it's a salute.
   Q: It seems very _
   BUSH: But I do _ if the question is, do I want to further
isolate a billion-plus people, the answer is no. And if the
question is, do I think we can _ do I think by having certain kinds
of relations with China, not only have we furthered the move more
openness, but can in the future, I think the answer is, yes.
   Q: Well, you're dealing with a country. You're not dealing with
a billion people. You're dealing with a regime that _
   BUSH: Yes, but you're dealing with the aspirations of a billion
people. And I happen to think that some of the contacts that
they've had with the United States have led to a better life for
the billion people.
   Q: Mr. President, there were some _
   BUSH: And I think that's an important point to make. And that
isn't in any way condoning the brutality that everybody in the
world saw in Tiananmen Square. And what I object to is the way
Michael _ some of the people phrase _ put things into him, so that
he phrased his question the way he did. Because that is not a good
rap. And it's not true. And for those who suggest it is, they ought
to just be a little patient and wait and see. And I've noticed a
lot of people that know China best seem to think that maybe this is
the way to effect positive change.
   Q: There were some words of moderation _
   BUSH: So I'm _ you know, I'm just going to stay with my position
and take on a little heat from time to time. And we'll wait and see
what happens.
   Q: Did you expect this kind of heat?
   BUSH: It hadn't been that much.
   Q: Are you kidding?
   BUSH: Well, you think so. I don't think so.
   Q: Well, I can assure you that people out there really _
   BUSH: Out where?
   Q: Out in _ everywhere.
   BUSH: But not after this interview because they'll understand it
more. (Laughter.) They've been dealing with emotion and not facts.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>