<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0269 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1157EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-BoardofTrade Open   12-20 0389</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Board of Trade, Open,0402</SECOND>
<HEAD>Wheat Futures Gain On Export News</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Wheat futures prices were slightly higher in
early trading today on the Chicago Board, reflecting new export
developments, but other grain and soybean futures were narrowly
mixed in listless trading.
   The wheat market got a boost from the Agriculture Department's
announcement late Tuesday that it had targeted the Soviet Union for
sales of another 2 million metric tons of wheat at subsidized
prices in addition to the 14,200 tons remaining under a previous
allocation.
   A new wheat allocation to the Soviets has been expected since
President Bush and Soviet leader Mikhail Gorbachev met earlier this
month.
   ``We knew it was coming; we didn't know when,'' said Susan
Leighty, grain market analyst with Prudential-Bache Securities Inc.
in New York.
   In other export news, the USDA announced sales of wheat to
China, Turkey and Egypt, and Japan was rumored to have bought U.S.
wheat overnight.
   Further support stemmed from Tuesday's USDA announcement that an
additional 3.3 million acres of land had been taken out of
agricultural production and put into a soil conservation program.
Ms. Leighty said about 2 million of those acres were in wheat
country.
   In early trading, wheat futures were 1 cent to 1\ cents higher
with the contract for delivery in March at $4.15{ a bushel; corn
futures were \ cent lower to } cent higher with March at $2.38{ a
bushel; oats were \ cent lower to \ cent higher with March at $1.53
a bushel; soybeans were 1 cent lower to 1\ cents higher with
January at $5.78 a bushel.
   Cattle futures were mixed while pork futures were lower in early
trading on the Chicago Mercantile Exchange. Pork belly futures were
down sharply amid speculation that Thursday's weekly USDA cold
storage report would show a higher-than-normal net increase last
month in supplies of frozen bellies.
   Live cattle futures were .02 cent to .15 cent lower with
December at 78.90 cents a pound; feeder cattle were .10 cent lower
to .20 cent higher with January at 84.52 cents a pound; live hogs
were .10 cent to .50 cent lower with December at 53.35 cents a
pound; frozen pork bellies were .80 cent to 1.25 cent lower with
February at 50.35 cents a pound.
   Livestock and meat futures settled mixed on Tuesday.
</TEXT>

</DOC>