<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1621EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania-Town 1stLd-Writethru   12-24 0742</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Town, 1st Ld - Writethru,a0745,0764</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romanians' Joy At Ceausescu's Fall Tinged With Fear</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with four grafs to CORRECT location of Oradea in relation
to Bucharest; picks up 5th pvs: Thousands of ...</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALEX BANDY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ORADEA, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In this northern city, rejoicing that
``the rat'' Ceausescu had fallen was tinged with fear, rumors of
retribution and an almost crazed desire to talk after 24 years of
dictatorship.
   Oradea, about 10 miles from the Hungarian border, saw no
fighting in the revolution that toppled the country's autocratic
leader, Nicolae Ceausescu.
   Revelers with a foot on the gas pedal and hands on the horn
honked and screamed their joy as they careened down streets in a
wild outburst of euphoria.
   In the local city hall, a group of intellectuals, Communists who
fell from Ceausescu's favor, and students was in session
continuously from Friday, when word of the dictator's fall in
Bucharest reached Oradea, about 300 miles northwest.
   Thousands of people milled outside, listening to speaker after
speaker grab a microphone to repeat how bad the old regime was,
proclaim the new freedom and and urge everyone to remain vigilant.
   But jubilation was tempered with the creeping fear that the
dreaded Securitate secret police forces loyal to Ceausescu would
attack the city of 198,000.
   In Oradea hospital, there were no wounded _ in fact, there
seemed to be no patients at all _ but scores of soldiers
outnumbered hospital staff, manning windows and exits in case the
Securitate arrived.
   A nurse said people were afraid even to enter the hospital after
hearing that Ceausescu forces had entered a hospital in another
city and shot the wounded as they lay in bed.
   Residents throughout the region warned visitors against picking
up hitchhikers. They might be security men dressed in dirty clothes
trying to move west toward the Hungarian border, they claimed. They
will leave unpinned grenades in your car, they warned.
   The fear swirled everywhere amid the small joys, such as eggs
being available for the first time in weeks.
   On the road toward Cluj, a truck driver stopped, his windshield
shot through by a bullet. Don't go on, he warned. There's fighting.
   He heard that a car had sped down a main street in Cluj, with
plainclothes men shooting indiscriminately from its window. Twelve
people died, he heard.
   ``Tyrant'' and ``rat'' were the only words anybody used for
Ceausescu here.
   ``The rat is finished!'' the crowd yelled outside city hall
Saturday. ``Timisoara! Bucharest!'' they chanted, honoring the two
cities where thousands of people died in the revolt.
   ``Toekes! Toekes!'' was another chant, in honor of Laszlo
Toekes, the ethnic Hungarian pastor whose attempted arrest Dec. 15
sparked the revolt.
   The privations Ceausescu imposed on his people while himself
living in opulent homes were evident in Oradea's sparse food stores.
   One large shop Saturday had virtually nothing but shelves and
shelves of jam of uncertain vintage.
   Crowds of ethnic Hungarians gathered around two visitors from
Hungary. After almost 25 years of dictatorship, it was as if the
floodgates had opened for them.
   ``You know they don't let kids speak Hungarian in the schools!''
yelled one man.
   Such discrimination has been well known and publicized for years
in Hungary, but this crowd chronicled it regardless, talking as if
everybody in the outside world knew nothing of Romania because they
themselves had been kept silent for years.
   Only younger ethnic Hungarians voiced any hope that the revolt
would mend torn relations between their community and ethnic
Romanians.
   Dezsoe Kovacs, a man in his 60s, recounted years of humiliation
imposed not only by authorities, but also ordinary Romanians. He
was never promoted from his job as a factory engineer, he said,
while much less qualified Romanians climbed the career ladder.
   The area used to be almost 100 percent ethnic Hungarian. Now, it
is only 33 percent.
   Dozens of people besieged troops and civilian guards protecting
city hall entrances. One, who identified herself as Julia Sz.,
wanted only one thing _ her husband.
   In August, she said, the couple tried to flee across the border
to Hungary with their four children, aged four to 10. They were
caught.
   At Securitate headquarters, she said, she and her husband were
severely beaten as their weeping children watched. Her husband was
hauled off to jail, and she wants him back.
   ``That,'' she said, ``would make this the most beautiful
Christmas ever.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>