<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0343EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CounterfeitShoes Bjt   12-30 0501</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Counterfeit Shoes, Bjt,0520</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sneaker Scam: 18 Charged in Brand-Name Case</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM F. RAWSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Reebok rip-offs? Converse copies? A phony Pony?
   Makers of prestige athletic shoes say counterfeit footwear is
big business and the feds agree, charging 18 people in what
allegedly was a scheme to sneak millions of Korean-made fakes into
the country.
   In unsealing an indictment Friday, U.S. Attorney Stephen McNamee
said investigators had broken up a ``worldwide conspiracy'' to sell
knockoffs of expensive brand-name shoes in the United States and
other countries.
   Eighteen people from three states and several foreign countries
were charged with violating U.S. trademark laws and
money-laundering, McNamee said. At least seven were arrested
Friday, he said, refusing to give names.
   Athletic shoes have become big money-makers, with some models
selling for more than $100 a pair.
   The case involves alleged copying of such popular brands as
Reebok, Converse and Pony.
   The indictment by a grand jury in Tucson names South Korean
businessman Dae Yun Hwang as head of the operation, and three other
South Koreans also are among those indicted.
   The counterfeit shoes were manufactured in Hwang's South Korean
factories and smuggled into the United States and other countries,
McNamee alleged.
   Other brands included Avia, Tiger, Puma, Adidas, L.A. Gear,
Nike, Jordache and Vans.
   The shoes were sold at flea markets and stores unauthorized to
carry those brands.
   The people charged were previously named in two civil lawsuits
by Reebok and Van Doren Rubber Co., the maker of Vans, said Harley
Lewin, a New York lawyer working for the shoemakers.
   The suits in U.S. District Court in San Diego seek a total of
$12 million in damages.
   ``We think that over a period of two years, in excess of two
million pairs of shoes were counterfeited,'' he said.
   The criminal investigation began Aug. 4 when Mexican customs
refused to allow 40 cartons of shoes across the border from
Nogales, Ariz., McNamee said.
   U.S. Customs agents found the shipment contained counterfeit
shoes bearing a number of brand-name labels. The shipment was
seized and a nationwide investigation was launched.
   Federal agents executed arrest and seizure warrants Thursday and
Friday, winding up a 4{-month investigation directed by the Customs
Service, McNamee said. Agents seized $4.5 million cash and other
assets from various defendants, he said.
   Authorities in Chile and Mexico also have made arrests in the
case, McNamee said.
   The case represents ``a notable victory against international
consumer fraud, money laundering and smuggling,'' U.S. Attorney
General Dick Thornburgh said in a news release.
   Besides Hwang, McNamee identified those named in the indictment
as: B.S. Kim, M.K. Kim and H.S. Tae, all of South Korea; San Diego
residents Byron McLaughlin, Debbie Watson, Celeste Cota, Nathan
Betech, Marcos Betech, Abraham Betech, Isaac Paz and Herminia
Ascensio; Glenn McLaughlin of Iquique, Chile; Roman Trenka of San
Juan, Puerto Rico; Dudley W. Miller III of Boston; Sol Weisenberg
of Cincinnati; Natalie Ann Quaratino of Mexico City; and Jorge
Fitch Lazaro of Guaymas, Mexico.
</TEXT>

</DOC>