<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0102 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1808EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Contras-Elections     12-30 0603</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Contras-Elections,0624</SECOND>
<HEAD>Contra Leaders Pledge to Avoid Election Violence</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto MH2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILL LESTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Contra military leaders pledged Saturday to work
with international observers to limit violence as Nicaragua
prepares for elections in February.
   One observer group said the announcement was important because
pre-election violence has been escalating in Nicaragua and talks
between Contra rebels and the ruling Sandinistas have broken off.
   International organizations are working to agree on ground rules
for monitoring and ensuring the fairness of the Feb. 25 elections.
   ``There is not full confidence that there will be a free
election process,'' said Israel Galeano, the Contras' military
chief of staff. ``Our conviction is serious to maintain support for
all observers.''
   He said at a news conference that he has 6,000 fighters in the
countryside, and they will ``take a totally defensive position'' in
the days leading up to the elections.
   But the commander said pulling Contra forces out of Nicaragua or
confining them to isolated areas for the elections would require a
similar commitment to keep Sandinista troops on bases, and that
proposal has been rejected in the past.
   Galeano, whose nom de guerre is Commander Franklin, made the
comments at a session with Contra director Aristides Sanchez and
Osorno Coleman, a Miskito Indian resistance leader known as
Commander Blaz.
   Coleman said he believes the Sandinistas have tried to inhibit
the election process in eastern sections of the country by limiting
registration, but he said the people he represents support the
election process.
   Sanchez predicted victory for the opposition ``because no one in
the world would believe the people are so masochistic that they
would elect this government.''
   Leaders of the Center for Democracy, one of the four groups that
will monitor the elections, arranged the rare appearance by the new
military leaders.
   Center President Allen Weinstein said the Contra military
leaders' pledge to limit violence was a breakthrough that could
resolve an impasse between the Sandinistas, Contras and other
opposition groups.
   ``This is the first statement with a monitoring group (present)
in which they commit themselves fully to the democratic process,''
Weinstein said.
   He said all of the monitoring groups _ the Organization of
American States, the United Nations, the Atlanta-based Carter
Center of former President Carter and the Center for Democracy _
would meet in January.
   ``We hope to (develop) a series of ironclad procedures accepted
by the government, all candidates and the different opposition
groups,'' he said.
   After the observer groups meet, representatives of the
Sandinistas, Contras and civilian opposition groups will be
invited. No specific dates have been set.
   Weinstein's center said the Contras have agreed to help
investigate any violent incidents ``to have been perpetrated by any
of the parties in the Nicaraguan conflict, including their own
fighters.''
   The setting of rules for the election process has become more
urgent because of incidents such as a Dec. 10 confrontation in the
Nicaraguan town of Masatepe between Sandinista and opposition
supporters.
   Election campaign observers said supporters of the leftist
government violently disrupted a rally held by backers of
opposition presidential candidate Violeta Chamorro.
   Sandinista supporters reportedly charged the rally armed with
machetes and clubs. The candidate's motorcade fled town. One man
died of machete wounds, and another half-dozen were hospitalized.
   The Bush administration cited the incident as evidence the
Sandinistas, who lifted a unilaterally declared ceasefire Nov. 1,
will find an excuse to avoid holding fair elections.
   But Weinstein of the Center for Democracy said the new Contra
statement could help bring both sides together for a fair ballot.
   ``There's 60 days. There's plenty of time,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>