<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0093 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1552EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Brazil     12-30 0287</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil,0295</SECOND>
<UNK>Government Officially Names Collor de Mello Brazil's Next President</UNK>
<DATELINE>RIO DE JANEIRO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government Saturday formally
declared Fernando Collor de Mello the winner of Brazil's first free
presidential election in 29 years.
   Collor de Mello, 40, of the rightist National Reconstruction
Party, narrowly defeated socialist Luis Inacio Lula da Silva, 49
percent to 44 percent. The election was held Dec. 17.
   ``I am sure God will give me the strength to govern this country
with open arms, together with the judiciary and the Congress, whose
participation is indispensable,'' said Collor de Mello after
receiving a presidential diploma from the Supreme Electoral Court
during a morning ceremony.
   Collor de Mello had 35,089,998 votes after 100 percent of the
70.26 million ballots cast were tallied, Supreme Electoral Court
President Jose Francisco Rezek said.
   Da Silva, of the radical left Workers Party, received 31,076,364
votes.
   Rezek said 986,446 of the total ballots cast were blank, 3.1
million were annulled and 11.81 million were abstentions. Voting is
mandatory for Brazilians between 18 and 69.
   Collor de Mello is expected to face stiff opposition in
Congress, where his party has only 24 seats, just 3 percent of the
total.
   The president-elect will take over from President Jose Sarney on
Mar. 15, 1990, for a five-year term.
   However, pressure is mounting for Sarney to resign early.
   Several Cabinet ministers have said Collor de Mello should take
office soon to adopt emergency economic measures to bring down
inflation, which ran at 1,765 percent in 1989.
   Sarney, a civilian who took office in 1985 after an electoral
college vote, said he would step down from office early if
Congress, which is now in recess, voted to shorten his mandate.
</TEXT>

</DOC>