<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0102 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1508EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Scene     12-21 0674</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Scene,0694</SECOND>
<HEAD>Unprecedented Interruption of Ceausescu's Speech</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALISON SMALE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For the first time that anybody could
remember, Romanian President Nicolae Ceausescu was interrupted at a
public speech by boos and jeers that began a huge demonstration
against him in Bucharest Thursday.
   Dressed in a black Persian lamb hat with matching coat collar,
Ceausesecu, 71, was about three minutes into one of his typically
rousing speeches when, according to a Yugoslav journalist in
Bucharest, a crowd of young people, quickly joined by hundreds of
sympathizers marched close by.
   All that viewers on state television and listeners on state
radio knew of the demonstration was the muffled sound of boos and
jeers before live broadcast abruptly stopped.
   Ceausescu, Romania's hard-line leader for 24 years, was midway
through a sentence thanking the organizers of his own rally on the
square in front of his official residence, the elegant palace that
until the Communist takeover in 1947 housed the nation's kings.
   Radio and TV quickly switched to stirring patriotic songs. But
Hungarian TV showed more footage of a disconcerted Ceausescu,
clearly aware something was amiss, and a man advising him, ``Come
inside.''
   Three minutes later, the broadcast resumed, again catching
Ceausescu midway through a sentence, this time a stirring appeal to
defend ``the independence, integrity and sovereignty of Romania.''
   Eastern Europe's longest surviving ruler has made many such
appeals in his 24 years as the autocratic boss of Romania.
   The appeals are intended to touch the raw nerve of Romanian
nationalism, long played upon by Ceausescu in his vision of a great
Romania with himself as its undisputed greatest leader ever.
   But the increasing hardships he has imposed on 23 million
people, and the reported massacre of unarmed civilians in the west
Romanian city of Timisoara last weekend, apparently have united
ethnic Hungarians, Germans and Romanians in revolt.
   According to reports from East bloc journalists in Bucharest,
the crowd that interrupted Ceausescu's speech was undeterred by
tear gas grenades.
   About 25 minutes after his mass rally drew to a close, thousands
of mostly young people marched down the nearby central Magheru
boulevard, chanting ``Down with Ceausescu!'' and calling for the
``libertate'' _ or ``freedom'' _ that is coming to their East
European and Soviet neighbors.
   Submachine gunners and tanks tried to push the crowds back, and
bursts of automatic weapons fire were heard as the protesters moved
toward an intersection ringed by the imposing buildings of the
university, the national theater and the 22-story Intercontinental
Hotel.
   There, according to a Yugoslav journalist, the crowd was
encircled by tanks, riot police, troops and special security forces.
   There was a lull in the shooting, during which a Bulgarian
correspondent said elderly people entreated the security forces not
to move against the protesters.
   Shouts of ``The army is with us!'' rang out, a Hungarian
correspondent said.
   But then, according to Yugoslav journalist Petar Tomic of
Tanjug, an armored vehicle ran over two students. Others who went
to help were mown down with gunshots, with about 20 people killed
or wounded.
   A British diplomat told television in London that at least eight
or nine corpses were seen in the streets.
   Elsewhere, the city was quiet, according to a Swiss diplomat
interviewed by Swiss radio. The airport and outskirts, while
heavily patrolled by security forces, seemed untouched by the furor
in the center, he reported.
   Romanians who listened to their own media would have known
nothing. Radio retransmitted Ceausescu's speech, editing out the
offending jeers. Television, which normally transmits only two
hours a night in the shortage-plagued Balkan nation, simply did not
start its usual 8 p.m. broadcast, the Soviet news agency Tass said.
   Radio Free Europe broadcasts in Romanian, and the station is a
lifeline to the rest of the world in a country that now receives
few Western visitors, and sells no foreign newspapers _ not even
those of its allies in the Warsaw Pact.
   Some have adjusted their TV antennas to receive Hungarian,
Yugoslav, Soviet or Bulgarian news.
</TEXT>

</DOC>