<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0160 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1831EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-BushRdp 3rdLd-Writethru a0669 12-18 0993</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush Rdp, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0669,950</SECOND>
<HEAD>Earlier Trip to China by Bush Aide Disclosed</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS graf 7: ``Ron Brown,'' with comment from DNC chairman</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERENCE HUNT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP White House Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush secretly sent high-level
emissaries to Beijing barely a month after the violent crackdown on
pro-democracy demonstrators, the White House said Monday in a
disclosure that sparked new criticism that he had ``misled the
American people.''
   The president, meanwhile, urged critics of his China policy to
``be a little patient.''
   Word of the July trip came as Bush was still defending himself
from criticism for having sent aides to Beijing earlier this month.
Brent Scowcroft, the president's national security adviser, led
both missions, accompanied by Lawrence Eagleburger, the deputy
secretary of state.
   Scowcroft's first trip, kept secret until now, came a month
after Chinese troops crushed a pro-democracy movement, killing
hundreds of demonstrators.
   Rep. Sam Gejdenson, D-Conn., chairman of the Subcommittee on
International Economic Policy and Trade of the House Foreign
Affairs Committee, said Bush had ``misled the American people and
the Congress.''
   ``How does the White House square that (earlier trip) with their
statements at the time that high-level contacts with the Chinese
were cut off,'' Gejdenson said.
   Ron Brown, chairman of the Democratic National Committee, said,
``There has not been a decision so out of touch with American
values since the sale of arms to the Ayatollah. ... President Bush
has demonstrated yet again that he doesn't see the connection
between human lives, human rights and an effectvie foreign policy.''
   A White House statement Monday said the July trip was intended
to underscore U.S. ``shock and concern about the violence in
Tiananmen Square and to impress upon the Chinese government the
seriousness with which this incident was viewed in the United
States.''
   White House press secretary Marlin Fitzwater said he could not
rule out the possibility that Scowcroft or other U.S. officials had
made other trips to China that still remain secret.
   The White House confirmed the July visit only because it was
reported by the Cable News Network, Fitzwater said. The December
visit was disclosed after Scowcroft and Eagleburger had landed in
Beijing.
   Of the July trip, Fitzwater said, ``The president has had years
of experience with China, and he knows that face-to-face
declarations are important to them.''
   Bush, meanwhile, said that criticism ignited by news of the Dec.
8 trip was subsiding and that remaining skeptics should ``be a
little patient and wait and see'' how Beijing responds.
   ``They've been dealing with emotion and not facts. Once they
deal with a full deck, I expect people will understand it,'' Bush
said.
   He refused to say whether China had offered any concessions in
return for his decision to rekindle relations with Beijing in the
aftermath of the June killings.
   Bush said he does not know when Chinese dissident Fang Lizhi
would be able to leave the U.S. Embassy in Beijing, where he has
taken refuge since the crackdown. Fitzwater said Scowcroft had
denied there were any negotiations going on with China about an
acceptable country where Fang might go.
   The president, who has been accused by Democrats of
``kowtowing'' to the Chinese leaders, said, ``I'm just going to
stay with my position and take on a little heat from time to time.''
   Already, Bush said, ``I notice now that some of the critics who
were so opposed and using this fantastically, diabolically anti-me
language, they come up now saying, `Well, if you get a, b and c,
then it will be all right or then we'll understand. Let them just
stay tuned in.''
   Bush made his comments in a year-end interview with The
Associated Press and three other news agencies.
   On other topics, the president:
   _Said a bill he signed to bail out the savings and loan industry
was ``a major accomplishment but I continue to worry about the
S&amp;Ls.'' He did not elaborate.
   _Said his pledge against raising taxes this year was good for
1990 ``as far as I`m concerned.'' He said he had kept his vow in
1989 ``and I want to continue keeping it.''
   _Scoffed at reports that Colombian drug lords had put up a $30
million assassination contract on his life. ``There is nothing to
it,'' Bush said. ``Let me take this opportunity to reassure the
American people that we will not unduly risk anyone's life here and
that ... I feel confident that the security provisions in Cartagena
will guarantee the safety of the president of the United States.''
Bush plans to attend a meeting of Andean leaders in the Colombian
city in February to discuss the drug fight.
   _Said he felt ``enormous frustration'' that Americans are still
held as hostages in Lebanon. ``It's on my mind an awful lot,'' Bush
said, adding that he had written notes recently to families of the
hostages. The president said the tone of moderation in Iran after
the death of the Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini has not been backed up
by action.
   _Said the United States will not compel Israel to deal with the
Palestine Liberation Organization to get peace in the Middle East.
Bush also said he was frustrated by the violence in Lebanon.
   _Declared the United States will play ``an active and
appropriate role'' in encouraging democratic reforms in Eastern
Europe but said those changes will not automatically translate into
huge spending cuts for the Pentagon.
   On another matter, Bush said he felt ``enormous frustration''
that Panamanian leader Manuel Antonio Noriega remained in power
despite U.S. sanctions and support for a failed coup attempt in
October.
   The president said the weekend slaying of an American officer in
Panama was ``an enormous outrage and a matter of enormous concern
to this president.''
   Asked if the United States was powerless to act, Bush said, ``I
think a president, all presidents, have options, but they don't
discuss what they might be.'' He repeated that answer when asked if
military steps were being considered.
</TEXT>

</DOC>