<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0185 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1825EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-EnergyShortages     12-22 0613</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Energy Shortages,0632</SECOND>
<HEAD>New England Energy Officials Meet To Discuss Fuel Shortages</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Cold, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSAN ALLEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MONTPELIER, Vt. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Officials from the Northeast meet
Saturday in Washington to discuss heating fuel shortages amid a
backdrop of record freezing cold and dwindling energy supplies.
   The meeting will bring together representatives of the region's
utilities, pipeline companies, propane distributors, transportation
officials and state energy regulators.
   Assistant U.S. Energy Secretary John Easton said he hopes to
``find out where they (shortages) exist and how serious they are.
   ``We have been receiving a lot of anecdotal data and our
interest is to determine how real the situation is from the
perspective of suppliers and consumers,'' said Easton, who called
the weekend meeting.
   New England is experiencing its coldest December on record,
along with other parts of the country. On Friday, the arctic
temperatures snapped records in more than 125 cities from the
Rockies to the East Coast, making it one of the worst cold spells
on record, the National Weather Service said.
   Forecasters predict moderating weather following the weekend,
but this month's supercold has already drained energy sources.
   ``We've already used as much fuel as we normally would by the
middle of January,'' said Robert Gladden, a spokesman for Bay State
Gas Co., with 250,000 customers in Massachusetts, New Hampshire and
Maine.
   The Energy Department meeting will also include representatives
from the Plains states and as far south as Virginia _ all areas
which are also beginning to feel a fuel pinch due to unseasonably
cold weather.
   But officials said the focus of the meeting will generally
remain on New England, where the problem is considered more serious.
   A severe shortage of propane has prompted some companies to
impose restrictions on deliveries. Vermont Gov. Madeleine Kunin and
propane operators announced this week that deliveries would not be
made until tanks drop to 10 percent capacity and that fill-ups
would be limited to 50 percent of capacity.
   Easton said some help is expected for propane users. The
department has already taken steps to locate additional sources of
the fuel, including contacting the operators of the major propane
gas pipeline that supplies the Northeast.
   Texas Eastern, whose pipeline ends near Albany, N.Y., has
increased the flow of propane through the line by one-third, Easton
said.
   In addition, the high demand for the home heating oil has sent
prices soaring. Oil that was selling for 95 cents a gallon last
week in the region was selling for $1.14 this week.
   ``We are beginning to have some concerns about the supply of
heating oil if this weather continues,'' said Ned Tudi, vice
president of energy relations for Agway Energy Products in
Syracuse, N.Y.
   Electric utilities were also concerned about the cold. A
regionwide appeal was made to cut back usage as utilities predicted
record demand for the weekend.
   On Friday, Rhode Island Gov. Edward DiPrete sent a letter to
Admiral James D. Watkins, the U.S. secretary of energy, urging him
to ``facilitate the transportation of energy supplies to the
Northeast.''
   New Hampshire Gov. Judd Gregg released a letter Friday afternoon
telling the U.S. Customs Service in Washington ``an emergency
situation now exists in that propane supplies to both gas
distribution companies and retail propane dealers in my state are
critically short.''
   ``The situation makes it imperative that all transportation
equipment be used to bring added supplies of propane to my state
and the region,'' Gregg wrote.
   He asked for a waiver to allow the Bay State Gas Co. to charter
a Danish and an Italian ship to transport propane from the Gulf
Coast to terminals in New Hampshire, Rhode Island, New Jersey and
Pennsylvania.
</TEXT>

</DOC>