<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0161 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1856EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RiotTrial-NAACP     12-22 0569</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Riot Trial-NAACP,0587</SECOND>
<HEAD>Black Leaders Want National Guard in Miami</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Black leaders in Miami have asked Gov. Bob Martinez
to send in the National Guard for fear their communities may be
ignored by police loyal to a convicted Hispanic officer.
   Martinez took no action in response to the request received
Friday in a letter from the NAACP but said he has faith in the
local police department, said his press secretary, Jon Peck.
   ``The governor has been fully briefed about security
arrangements in Miami and around the state,'' Peck said. ``He's
comfortable that everything that can be done is being done at this
point.''
   Johnnie McMillian, president of the Miami-Dade chapter of the
National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, wrote
the governor Thursday asking the state to assume responsibilty for
law enforcement in Dade County.
   ``There is an immediate crisis in the ability of the police
department in Dade County to provide protection for their
citzenry,'' her letter said.
   The letter was approved by the NAACP's regional office in
Atlanta and received support from other Miami black leaders,
including two prominent ministers. But the black leaders said they
knew of no specific incidents of lapses in police protection in
black neighborhoods.
   Police Chief Perry Anderson, Mayor Xavier Suarez and spokesmen
for the city's police union and Hispanic Officers Association all
said the letter was unwarranted.
   ``There isn't any reason for any kind of alarm,'' Anderson said
at a news conference. ``We'll continue to perform (our) duties in a
professional manner.''
   He emphasized that no unprofessional behavior would be
tolerated, but added, ``I think the emotion _ pro, con, favorable,
unfavorable _ reaction to the verdict is somewhat understandable.''
   Officer William Lozano was found guilty of two counts of
manslaughter Dec. 7 in the deaths of two black men. Motorcyclist
Clement Lloyd died after being shot by Lozano, and his passenger
Allan Blanchard died from injuries when the vehicle crashed.
   Their deaths Jan. 16 sparked three nights of racial riots.
Lozano's conviction was applauded in the black community, but
police officers viewed the verdict as a restriction of their right
to protect themselves in the line of duty.
   Several officers have worn black bands on their badges or black
wristbands _ normally a symbol of mourning _ to protest the
conviction.
   McMillian said she wants the National Guard to serve as the
local police until the department can prove it isn't divided and
can act impartially.
   The police chief denied that there was significant discord among
officers within the department, noting, however, ``We must all
attempt to work togther to solve our differences.''
   Suarez said the letter shows a lack of confidence in Anderson,
who is black. The mayor held a meeting last week with the leaders
of the city's police union and black and Hispanic associations to
discuss reports of police neglect.
   ``The one thing that came out of the meeting is a commitment
that there would be absolute professionalism,'' Suarez said. ``I am
convinced of that, now more than ever, because there is more
communication between the groups.''
   McMillian said she decided to send the letter after hearing
about a possible work slowdown and an unsubstantiated report of a
Hispanic officer hesitating before responding to a backup call.
   ``If I needed police protection, I would not feel comfortable
calling the police because of the attitude of some of the
officers,'' she said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>