<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0841EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-EndaraProfile     12-20 0616</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Endara Profile,0643</SECOND>
<HEAD>Endara Sworn in Months After Being Declared President</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOSEPH B. FRAZIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For the second time in seven months,
Guillermo Endara has been declared president of Panama, and once
again it comes amid violent clashes between his supporters and
those who back Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   Endara, a portly, affable lawyer and former law professor, was
sworn in as president today after U.S. troops, in a bid to oust
Noriega, launched an assault on the country.
   His opposition activities date back more than two decades, to
when he served in the National Assembly under Arnulfo Arias Madrid,
Panama's grand old man of the opposition.
   Endara was Arias' spokesman in Panama until Arias died in Miami
in 1988 in self-imposed exile. He used to speak, amost dreamily, of
the day when Arias would return ``as a sign of providence'' to lead
the country.
   In May, Endara himself was chosen to lead the country in a
presidential election. Exit polls showed Endara and his two
vice-presidential candidates with an edge of about 3-1, but Noriega
nullified the results, ignoring the outcry at home and abroad.
   Three days after the vote, men wearing T-shirts of Noriega's
``Dignity Battalions'' battered Endara and his two
vice-presidential candidates in a bloody street scene captured by
foreign cameras.
   Endara spent his 53rd birthday in a hospital bed, recovering
from the attack.
   ``They were not battalions and they have no dignity,'' Endara
said in a hospital interview as supporters held up his bloodied
guayabera, a short- sleeved, smock-type shirt favored by many
Latins.
   He staged a hunger strike to press Noriega to accept his victory
and urged his supporters not to accept the military man as their
leader.
   Endara, a veteran member of the Panamanista Party, ran very much
in the shadow of Arias.
   Endara lost control of the party in December to Hildebrando
Nicosia, who ran as a third-party candidate in May and finished
third.
   The opposition Liberal Authentic Party adopted Endara, and the
coalition Democratic Opposition Alliance ran him for president.
   Endara served twice in the National Assembly and was Arias'
minister of planning and economic policy in 1968 when Arias was
thrown out of office for the third time after only serving 11 days
as president.
   Endara went into hiding, was jailed for a time and eventually
fled to exile.
   When Arias reorganized his party as the Authentic Panamanist
Party in 1983 after a long ban on political activity in Panama,
Endara helped.
   Endara, who studied at the University of Panama, in Argentina
and in New York, lacked Arias' charisma and spent most of his time
behind the scenes of the opposition's seemingly endless attempts to
replace the de facto military power that began its iron-fisted rule
21 years ago.
   In a pre-election interview he put faith in the hope that the
democratic process in Panama would prevail, electoral fraud or not.
   He said if he won Noriega would be given a chance to leave
gracefully and be fired if he refused.
   
   Noriega hired and fired presidents pretty much at will after
taking over the military in 1983.
   His last victim was Eric Delvalle, who tried to fire Noriega
after the general was indicted on drug charges last year in the
United States. Even so, Endara said he trusted the democratic
process.
   ``Remember Delvalle was in very different circumstances,'' he
said. ``He was a puppet of the military by the fraud of 1984.
That's the price you pay for not being a democratically elected
person. You are subject to the decisions of the military.''
   He and his wife, Marcella, have one daughter, also named
Marcella.
</TEXT>

</DOC>