<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1335EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Vatican-Panama     12-26 0736</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Vatican-Panama,0758</SECOND>
<HEAD>Exile in Third Country Appears Likely Solution to Noriega Case</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>By STEPHEN R. WILSON</HEAD>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VATICAN CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Vatican likely will allow Gen. Manuel
Antonio Noriega to go into exile in another country rather than
turn him over to the United States to face drug trafficking
charges, sources said Tuesday.
   Vatican and U.S. diplomats were at work Tuesday to resolve the
diplomatic stalemate involving Noriega, who took refuge in the
Vatican Embassy in Panama City on Sunday after four days of eluding
American invasion troops.
   An embassy spokesman said the U.S. ambassador to the Holy See,
Thomas P. Melady, has been discussing the case with high-ranking
Vatican officials but gave no details.
   The Vatican's deputy spokesman, Monsignor Piero Pennacchini,
said contacts were under way between the concerned parties,
including the newly installed Panamian government, the United
States and the Vatican.
   ``It's very delicate situation,'' Pennacchini said. ``It has to
be treated with much discretion to find the best solution for all
of the parties.''
   A State Department source in Washington said Monday the United
States had demanded ``in extraordinarily tough terms'' that the
Vatican turn Noriega over to U.S. custody for trial on drug charges.
   But church authorities had rebuffed the request and were trying,
so far unsuccessfully, to find another country to take Noriega, the
Washington official said.
   ``We want him alive to stand trial in the United States,'' the
U.S. Embassy spokesman in Panama City, Terrence Kneebone, said.
``We see this as a criminal matter. This is not a case of
poltitical or religious persecution.''
   But a Rome diplomatic source, who is close to those involved in
negotiations, on Tuesday said the possibility of the Vatican
handing over Noriega to U.S. authorities was ``very dim'' and he
would more likely go to another country.
   Spain, Cuba and the Dominican Republic have been mentioned as
possible refuges.
   A senior Vatican official, who is not directly involved in the
case but follows foreign policy issues, said ``no rules of any
kind'' would permit the Vatican to turn over Noriega to U.S.
invasion forces.
   ``They could only hand him over to the country where he's held
or arrange safe passage to another country,'' said the official,
adding that exile in a third country was the more likely solution
of the two.
   He noted that the issue of granting asylum for Noriega is not
new.
   Noriega's representatives had negotiated with the United States
in the past and again this year about the possibility of stepping
down and taking up exile in another country.
   The official also wondered how eager Washington is to bring
Noriega to the United States for trial, referring to published
reports that he might reveal embarrassing details of former links
with the CIA.
   On Monday, chief Vatican spokesman Joaquin Navarro said ``I
don't think so'' when asked if the Vatican would simply turn over
Noriega to the Americans, noting the Holy See does not have an
extradition treaty with the United States.
   There were reports from Washington and Panama that the Vatican
was having trouble finding another country to accept Noriega.
   Spanish newspapers Tuesday quoted the Spanish ambassador in
Panama, Tomas Lozano Escribano, as saying Spain has formally denied
Noriega political asylum. Foreign Minister Francisco Fernandez
Ordonez told the national news agency EFE on Monday that Spain was
not the ideal country for Noriega because of its extradition treaty
with the United States.
   Sources indicated it was likely a deal was struck between
Noriega and the Vatican Ebassy before he took refuge there. Under
this scenario, Noriega sought guarantees that he would not be
turned over to the Americans, while the Vatican demanded that he
renounce the conflict in Panama.
   In fact, Navarro said Noriega sought refuge at the Vatican
mission ``after having expressed his will to end the conflict.''
The spokesman indicated the Vatican knew of Noriega's position
before he showed up at the embassy.
   Analysts noted that it was unlikely Noriega would have gone to
the embassy if there was any chance he would be turned over the
Americans.
   The Vatican stressed that Noriega's move marked an opportunity
to bring peace to Panama.
   ``The legal aspect is certainly interesting,'' Navarro said on
Monday. ``But more important is the announcement that now, with his
(Noriega's) declared intention to contribute to the pacification of
the whole country, one can bring an end to the violence.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>