<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1107EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-OccupiedCity Bjt   12-30 0913</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Occupied City, Bjt,0944</SECOND>
<HEAD>Occupied City: Picking Up the Pieces</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CANDICE HUGHES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>COLON, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A babble of voices rose from the filthy
streets as hands dipped into crushed cartons of cigarettes and
shoes, bags of bras. Golden bracelets dangled from eager fingers,
on display for shoppers in the impromptu looters' market.
   ``One dollar! One dollar!'' a man cried, flicking his wrist at a
pile of pastel polo shirts.
   Four thieves surrounded a shopper. A knife glittered. A wallet
vanished into the hands of a skinny boy who ran and dodged like an
all-star wide receiver.
   A U.S. soldier rounded the corner. ``He was robbed! He was
robbed!'' excited voices cried, gesturing at the victim. The
soldier listened to the tale and shrugged.
   ``It's returning to normal,'' he said.
   The slums of Colon are glutted, sated with booty from the
frenzied looting sparked by the U.S. invasion of Panama on Dec. 20.
   ``People don't want any more TVs. They don't want any more
Betamaxes. Now they want money,'' said the new provincial governor,
Leopoldo Benedetti.
   Reality is beginning to dawn. You can't eat televisions; stereos
are indigestible. Colon is in shambles.
   ``There is going to be unemployment. And when you have hunger,
you have social unrest. Life could become unbearable,'' said
Alfonso Esquivel, the Colombian consul and one of the city's senior
diplomats.
   While U.S. troops ringed Colon last week, looters gutted its
shops and stores and cracked open the warehouses and dockside
terminal where goods from the Colon Free Zone, the world's
second-largest duty free port, are stored.
   Colon is an occupied city that put out the welcome mat. Its
merchants begged U.S. troops to enter to save their city from
chaos, and the city's new leaders are in no hurry for the
occupation to end.
   They need help picking up the debris from the fall of Gen.
Manuel Antonio Noriega's dictatorship.
   ``They have a moral obligation to help us get back to normal,''
said businessman Rafael Arosemena, vice chairman of the joint
council set up to get Colon back on its feet.
   This rough-and-tumble port city on the Atlantic end of the
Panama Canal unraveled with the sudden intensity of a tropical
storm.
   The U.S. troops landed, attacked several Defense Forces
installations and sealed off the city in the predawn hours of
Wednesday, Dec. 20.
   When dawn broke, Colon was a city without law. Noriega's Defense
Forces, which includes the local police, had fled, flinging open
the jailhouse doors as they went.
   The looting cut across class barriers in this city of about
60,000, known for some of the meanest slums and most predatory
street thieves in Latin America.
   ``I saw a doctor I know drive by with his BMW stuffed with
loot,'' Esquivel said.
   The rampage lasted two days.
   ``They were coming in by the hundreds,'' Bruce Motta Jr., whose
family trades watches and whiskey in the Free Zone, said as he
surveyed the debris-littered streets of the zone's auxiliary
warehouse area at France Field.
   ``They were running with televisions. They were running toward
the jungle. But they wouldn't put those televisions down,'' he said.
   In the main part of the Free Zone, about 150 plucky Arab traders
and their sons fought off looters for days, killing at least three
people and wounding several more.
   ``My luck was I had guys who knew how to use guns from the
invasion of Lebanon,'' one prominent merchant said, asking that his
name not be used.
   By the time U.S. forces entered the Free Zone on the afternoon
of Dec. 22, the looting was almost over and Colon was a wreck.
   Benedetti and several Defense Forces officers who had been
trying to fend off looters began gathering up arms from the
townspeople and the Defense Forces troops in hiding. Within two
hours, they had arranged a surrender, delivering several truckloads
of arms.
   The commander of the U.S. forces, Col. John Brooks, and his
staff took one look around and realized they had to change gears.
Within hours, they had come up with Project Cooperation, a plan for
the rebirth of Colon.
   The occupation force began arranging relief supplies, medical
care, health and sanitation services. They set up a joint council
with the officials President Guillermo Endara appointed to replace
the old Noriega regime.
   ``They're super people. They are very self reliant,'' Brooks
said of Colon's new leaders. ``The thing they want is security.''
   Within a week, more than 300 of the former Defense Forces
personnel had been signed up for a new security force. About a 100
were put on active, but unarmed duty, and began joint patrols with
U.S. troops.
   Details of the corruption that flourished under Noriega began
shaking loose as the dictator's allies rushed to align themselves
with the new order.
   The manager of a trading company that served as a slush fund for
Noriega turned himself in, professing his eagerness to cooperate
with the new government.
   As a semblance of order returned, Colon woke up like a drunk
after a binge. Benedetti and others began to realize how profound
the damage has been.
   Crucial government offices like customs houses had been
destroyed, normal commerce had come to a halt, merchants were faced
with huge, uninsured losses, the port was shut down, banks were
closed.
   The prospects for even deeper poverty and unemployment were grim.
   ``Colon is a city with too many problems,'' Benedetti said.
``There are 60,000 people; 40,000 of them have problems.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>