<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 2310EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People-ZsaZsa     12-17 0416</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People-Zsa Zsa,0426</SECOND>
<HEAD>Zsa Zsa Fired from Film Role in Dispute with Sheik</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI BEACH, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It seemed an unlikely role _ Zsa Zsa
Gabor as Saudi Arabian royalty _ and the sharp-tongued Hungarian
lost the job Sunday because of a tiff with the sheik who's
bankrolling the movie.
   Sheik Mohammad al-Fassi fired Miss Gabor before the pair even
met because of disparaging remarks she made about him in a dispute
over travel expenses, said Chris Christenson, producer of the
planned epic on Saudi history.
   The dispute began Saturday, when Miss Gabor canceled an
appearance with the sheik to promote the project, Christenson said
Sunday.
   The actress-socialite _ recently in the news for slapping a
police officer _ demanded travel expenses and in the course of
discussions with an aide, said she had reservations about the
sheik's character, Christenson said.
   ``She said `I don't trust him. I've heard bad things,' and he
went and told the prince,'' Christenson said. ``And the prince came
to me and said why would we use (her) if she doesn't trust me. ...
He said `I will not have anything to do with that.' ''
   Miss Gabor, believed to be in her late 60s or early 70s, denied
making disparaging remarks.
   ``How can I say something about someone I don't even know?'' she
asked. ``I was supposed to go there and read a script. I think this
was a publicity stunt to get the press over there. ...
   ``I don't know him, I don't wish to ever meet him,'' she said of
the sheik. ``This man didn't come down for half an hour and I said
thank you and I left. No one takes advantage of me,'' she said in a
telephone interview from the Polo Club in Palm Beach County.
   The sheik and producer say they will spend $50 million on the
movie chronicling Saudi Arabia from the time of King Abdel-Aziz ibn
Saud to the present. Their attention was drawn by Miss Gabor's
trial for slapping the officer, and they cast her as the king's
mother.
   After the dispute, Miss Gabor left the sheik's estate, presently
populated by dozens of cats in connection with his $2.5 million
project to save the nation's stray felines.
   Miss Gabor was sentenced to 72 hours in jail fined $2,937 for
her Sept. 29 misdemeanor conviction for slapping a Beverly Hills
policeman.
   Her movie roles include ``Moulin Rouge'' in 1953, ``Picture
Mommy Dead'' in 1966 and ``Up the Front'' in 1972.
</TEXT>

</DOC>