<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0653EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-WashingtonInBrief     12-21 0501</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Washington In Brief,500</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pentagon: No Major Withdrawal from Pacific Bases Planned</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. military officials say they are not
actively considering a major military withdrawal from East Asia,
although Pentagon planners recently drafted a memorandum outlining
such a possibility.
   The Asahi Shimbun and Washington Post reported this week that
Pentagon officials were considering closing U.S. bases in the
Philippines and withdrawing forces from South Korea and Japan.
   That policy was outlined in a paper discussed at a meeting
Monday involving Defense Secretary Dick Cheney and Gen. Colin
Powell, chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, but many other
options also were discussed, Pentagon officials said Wednesday.
   One source said that no such withdrawal was being considered for
the next two or three years.
   U.S. Pacific forces include 222,238 personnel _ 50,000 in Japan,
45,000 in Hawaii, 32,000 in South Korea, and 34,000 at sea,
according to Pentagon statistics. Additionally, the United States
operates two important bases in the Philippines.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Concern Over Polluted Parks Hoped to Help Clean Air Act</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Air pollution is taking its toll on national
parks and wilderness areas, says a lawmaker who expects that
concern over removing the dangerous haze will produce bipartisan
support for strengthening the Clean Air Act.
   ``I believe that when the public learns the extent of the damage
to our natural and cultural heritage, there will be strong
bipartisan support for our efforts,'' Rep. Ron Wyden, D-Ore., said
Wednesday at a news conference.
   Wyden is a member of the House Energy and Commerce Committee,
which early next year will take up clean air legislation. The full
Senate is also expected to take up such legislation soon after it
reconvenes in late January.
   Wyden said he wants to amend the act to strengthen the
protections for the national parks and other public treasures.
Although the 1977 Clean Air Act contains such an amendment, the
Environmental Protection Agency has not enforced it fully, he said.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Cajun Food Recalled by Producer</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 1,000 pounds of a frozen pork and rice
product is being recalled by a Louisiana processor because it might
be contaminated with a food-poisoning organism, Listeria
monocytogenes, according to the Agriculture Department.
   Bodin Foods Inc. of New Iberia, La., sells the product through
small distributors in Arizona, California, Florida, Louisiana and
Texas.
   It is sold frozen in vacuum-sealed plastic packages with the
name ``Boo Dan (Boudin Link) Traditional Cajun Pudding'' on the
label, and ``Est. 8214'' printed inside the USDA inspection seal on
the label.
   A USDA spokesman said Wednesday the product is cooked pork and
rice wrapped in a sausage casing, or link.
   Listeriosis was described as ``a rare but potentially serious''
disease. Most vulnerable are those with weakened immune systems,
including infants, the elderly and the chronically ill.
   Symptoms in adults include the sudden onset of flu-like symptoms
such as fever, chills, headache, backache, and sometimes abdominal
pain and diarrhea. In newborns, symptoms include respiratory
distress, refusal to drink and vomiting.
</TEXT>

</DOC>