<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0105 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1833EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-Embassy     12-30 0688</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Embassy,0713</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nicaraguan Ambassador Says Troops Knew Home Had Immunity</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOSEPH B. FRAZIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nicaragua's ambassador said Saturday
that he tried for an hour to convince U.S. troops his home was a
diplomatic residence before 60 troops entered, walking under a
large Nicaraguan emblem.
   A U.S. Embassy official said the soldiers didn't know the
residence was diplomatic quarters, and the United States later
apologized for the entry.
   Nicaragua's Sandinista government retaliated against the U.S.
action by expelling 20 American diplomats and ordering the U.S.
Embassy in Managua to reduce its support staff from 320 to 100. The
State Department called that an ``irresponsible overreaction.''
   U.S. troops have been posted around the embassies of Cuba,
Nicaragua and Libya since soon after the invasion to capture Gen.
Manuel Antonio Noriega began Dec. 20.
   On Saturday, Noriega remained at the Vatican mission, which was
surrounded by American troops.
   A U.S. official, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said
troops entered the house to search for weapons.
   ``(The troops) had no orders to do that if they knew it was the
ambassador's residence,'' a senior U.S. Embassy official said.
   Nicaraguan Ambassador Antenor Ferrey said he argued with the
troops for more than an hour and asked them to call American
diplomatic and military officials before they entered the house
about 6 p.m. Friday.
   The estimated 60 troops who searched the house in the four-hour
operation had to walk under the seal.
   The embassy official, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said
soldiers apparently did not see the emblem. However, a military
spokesman said that while they may have seen it, it was not a
sufficient indication of diplomatic immunity.
   Ferrey moved to the house more than a year ago.
   President Bush said the United States had apologized for the
incident.
   ``It's a screw-up and they (U.S. military officials in Panama)
have expressed their regrets that it happened,'' Bush said after a
golf game at the Houston Country Club.
   But he questioned why there were large amounts of weapons in the
residence.
   Six rocket-propelled grenade lauchers were among the weapons
found, the State Department said in Washington. The cache also
included four Uzi machine guns, 12 AK-47s, three hand grenades, 10
FEN rifles, 17 bayonets, one M-1 carbine, one shotgun, four
rocket-propelled grenade sights, one light anti-tank weapon, 27
rocket-propelled grenade rounds and approximately 1,300 rounds of
ammunition of various caliber.
   A communique from the Southern Command said the soldiers entered
``with good cause'' after receiving a tip from a Panamanian citizen
that there were weapons in ``what is now claimed to be the alleged
home of the Nicaraguan ambassador to Panama.''
   According to the military account:
   Ferrey drove up after troops had ordered people in the house to
evacuate and fired warning shots into the air. He provided an
identity card, but indicated he had left his red diplomatic
identity card at the embassy, it said.
   Troops at the residence checked with their superiors and were
told the ambassador's residence was in an apartment building at
another location.
   Based on the information that the house was not covered by
diplomatic immunity, the commander on the scene informed Mr. Ferrey
he had received authorization to search the house and intended to
do so.
   The residents and weapons were released afterwards.
   The embassy official said he understood the search stopped as
soon as people at the house produced diplomatic credentials, ``and
if that isn't the case we have a double apology to make.''
   He said the action was not a mistake until the house was
identified as one with diplomatic immunity.
   He rejected the possibility that the raid was intended to be a
signal to Noriega, hiding out in the embassy of the Vatican since
Christmas Eve, that diplomatic immunity there might not protect him
indefinitely.
   Nicaragua claimed the U.S. soldiers stole more than $2,000 and
took some clothes from the residence.
   In Nicaragua, the government gave the American diplomats 72
hours to leave, leaving 15 in the country, the minimum set by
international agreement. Most of the support staff is Nicaraguan.
</TEXT>

</DOC>