<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0120 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1926EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Secession     12-28 0482</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Secession,0497</SECOND>
<HEAD>Koch Vows to Fight Staten Island Secession in Court</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN SHANAHAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vowing ``Not now, not ever!'' outgoing Mayor
Edward I. Koch said Thursday the city is challenging a new law that
permits the borough of Staten Island to vote on secession.
   He said the bill signed Dec. 15 by Gov. Mario Cuomo could
``dismember this, the world's greatest city.''
   The bill violates the state and federal constitutions because it
was passed by the state Legislature without the consent of the City
Council or the mayor, Koch said, and would allow only the residents
of Staten Island to vote on a matter that directly affects citizens
of the city's other four boroughs.
   ``New York City is and should continue to be one city _ not two,
not five, just one,'' he said at a news conference in City Hall.
``Secession _ not now, not ever!''
   Koch, who leaves office Jan. 1, said the city filed a lawsuit
challenging the law in state Supreme Court on Thursday.
   The bill was sponsored by state Sen. John Marchi, a Staten
Islander who said his borough would lose its political clout in the
city under a reorganization that eliminated the powerful Board of
Estimate. Marchi did not immediately return a telephone call to his
office Thursday.
   The U.S. Supreme Court ruled last spring that the Board of
Estimate, which has broad authority over contracts and planning and
approves the city's annual budget, violated the one man-one vote
principle because it gave equal voting power to the boroughs
despite vastly different populations.
   Staten Island has fewer than 400,000 residents while Brooklyn
has about 2.6 million.
   Koch said secession would have an enormous impact on the
property, affairs and government of the city.
   ``Would the residents of New York state stand silently by if the
City of Buffalo were to annex itself to Canada?'' he asked. ``I
don't think so. They would put up a fight.''
   ``We too will put up a fight to make sure that one of the five
jewels in our city's crown _ the Borough of Staten Island _ remains
a shining, vital part of our community,'' Koch said.
   He said when Cuomo signed the bill he ``plunged a dagger into
the heart of New York.''
   Koch said secession would remove substantial housing resources
from the city. Staten Island has the largest share of single and
two-family dwellings as well as the most available land for future
housing development, he said.
   ``The city also owns buildings and other properties on Staten
Island worth billions of dollars. There are sewer lines, water
mains, over 50 schools, over 25 parks, police precincts,
firehouses, a ferry terminal, streets and bridges and cultural
facilities,'' he said.
   ``The citizens of all five boroughs have contributed financially
to the construction and the operation of all of these facilities,''
Koch said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>