<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0161 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1607EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-Symposium-SouthAmerica Adv31   12-26 0744</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Symposium-South America, Adv 31,0764</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 31, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WORLD SYMPOSIUM '90s: South America _ Outlook Still Bleak</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KEVIN NOBLET</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SANTIAGO, Chile (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Having struggled through ``a lost
decade'' of crushing debt and economic stagnation, South America
limps into the 1990s with the grim prospect of more tough times.
   Its many young democracies still fight to establish firm roots
in troubled societies, inherited in many cases from now-retired
military governments.
   At the same time, they face the daunting challenge of halting a
continental slide deeper into underdevelopment.
   The 1980s began with what is now generically known as ``the
crisis'' _ plunging prices for South America's products accompanied
by skyrocketing foreign debts.
   The decade ended with those debts approaching $300 billion
overall, with surreal inflation averaging nearly 1,000 percent a
year, with spreading poverty and with widespread social unrest. At
the close of the decade, per capita production was 8 percent less
than it was at the start.
   The troubles struck not only in countries with a tradition of
political and social commotion such as Peru and Argentina. Even
long-steady Venezuela was jolted by price riots in 1989. Colombia,
another economic and political stalwart, waged bloody war with a
billion-dollar cocaine underworld that was deeply entrenched in
several other South American countries.
   The experts see few signs of a better decade ahead.
   ``As far as perspectives for the 1990s, there is a certain
temptation to predict that the crisis will continue,'' said Gert
Rosenthal, director of the United Nation's Economic Commission for
Latin America and the Caribbean.
   In an interview in Santiago, Rosenthal said there were grounds
for pessimism in the inertia of Latin America's deep and
long-lasting recession, which has prompted him to call the 1980s
``a lost decade.''
   He said he also harbored ``the suspicion that the prolonged
expansion of world development can't last much longer, and any
recession in the international economy surely will hit Latin
America very hard.''
   In addition, he noted, there's little prospect of badly needed
fresh credit for the debtor countries trying to refinance loans
that drain the region each year of $30 billion, money that could be
put to use at home.
   Nonetheless, Rosenthal cited several positive developments that
could help in coping with the future.
   He said South America learned a hard lesson in the 1980s: Its
archaic economies, run by creaky state bureaucracies, must be
overhauled if it is to compete in the world marketplace. Also, he
said, both creditor banks and debtor countries were adopting
ever-more flexible positions on foreign debts.
   He also cited a certain ``revitalization'' of the old, battered
concept of Latin American cooperation and integration.
   The 1980s began with nine of the continent's 12 countries
controlled by authoritarian military governments. The decade ends
with elected leaders governing all but in Chile, where elections in
December set the stage for the first civilian government since 1973.
   Few of those new civilian governments have shown any success in
solving economic problems, but none has yet to fall. Indeed, while
particular governments have sometimes suffered from slumping
popular support, surveys indicate little inclination for the return
of military rule. Periodic uprisings at Argentine garrisons have
been quickly snuffed.
   ``Despite the entire decade's critical economic situation, it
appears clear that the democratic regimes are becoming consolidated
in the principal countries,'' said Jose Joaquin Brunner, director
of the independent Latin American Faculty of Social Sciences.
   ``There is no reason to believe the (democratic) processes will
be interrupted in the foreseeable future,'' Brunner said. ``Even
where the situation is most precarious, such as Peru, the
institutional machine keeps working despite everything.''
   The wave of democracy has produced a spirit of fellowship and
cooperation reflected in numerous summit meetings among South
American nations, involving as many as a half-dozen presidents.
Brunner said a new political and economic coherence is emerging.
   ``Everyone sees the need for relatively pragmatic programs,
aimed at economic restructuring,'' he said. ``No one is turning to
ideological alternatives. There is no South American wave in favor
of socialism, for instance.''
   In deeply indebted Brazil, a pro-business conservative, Fernando
Collor de Mello, edged out a socialist, Luis Inacio Lula da Silva,
in presidential elections Dec. 17.
   Brunner said deep ideological divisions and animosities that
often fractured South American societies are being erased.
   ``The range of possibilities has become so narrow, it's obliging
everyone to be pragmatic,'' he said.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Sunday, Dec. 31</NOTE>

</DOC>