<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0220 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0217EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-PhoneFight     12-21 0449</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Phone Fight,0463</SECOND>
<HEAD>Wampanoags Gain `Millions' in Phone Bidding Settlement</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DIAMOND</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Wampanoag Indians of Gay Head, Mass., have
dropped a bid to run a Cape Cod cellular phone service in exchange
for ``millions of dollars'' in a settlement with a competing
telephone company.
   NYNEX Mobile Communications, a subsidiary of NYNEX Corp., agreed
to the settlement Wednesday, which clears an obstacle for it to run
a cellular phone servce on the Cape.
   The tribal president said the money will go toward other
economic development programs for the Wampanoags, possibly
including a resort complex on Martha's Vineyard island.
   ``We both got what we wanted, actually,'' said Donald Widdiss,
president of the Wampanoag Tribal Council of Gay Head Inc. ``We
feel we can leverage the money we have to go into other ventures.''
   Those include setting up a museum and cultural center in Gay
Head, a town on Martha's Vineyard and the tribe's home base,
establishing a performing arts center, and possibly developing a
resort hotel complex.
   Neither Widdiss nor NYNEX officials would disclose the exact
amount of the settlement but Widdiss said, ``It's in the millions
of dollars.''
   The Wampanoags began looking at the possibility of running a
cellular phone service in 1987 as a way to generate revenue for the
tribe. While the tribe itself has no equipment or particular
expertise in the field, the Wampanoags had agreed to work with a
cellular phone company based in Hartford, Conn., Message Center
Management. The Hartford firm also got an undisclosed percentage of
the settlement, Widdiss said.
   Permits to operate cellular phone service are awarded by the
Federal Communications Commission. Each region of the country is
divided into service areas and the FCC awards a license to one
company for each area.
   Wednesday's announced settlement came just before the FCC was to
conduct a lottery in which one of the competing companies would be
chosen. Once selected, a company would still have to pass further
government hurdles before winning a license.
   With the announcement of the settlement, the drawing for the
Cape Cod region was canceled.
   NYNEX is the largest cellular phone service provider in New
England, operating in regions extending from southern New Hampshire
to Worcester, Mass., and Rhode Island.
   Widdiss said the possibility of winning a cash settlement from a
competitor ``was part of the strategy'' from the beginning when the
tribe first sought to run the cellular service.
   About 280 Wampanoag Indians live on Martha's Vineyard and the
tribe is renting office space in the town of Gay Head. About 250
acres of land have been put into federal trust for a reservation
where the Indians can build homes.
</TEXT>

</DOC>