<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0649EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     12-21 0515</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0530</SECOND>
<HEAD>Snow, Bitter Cold in Midwest</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Winter officially began this afternoon, but it seems like it's
already been here for a while for much of the nation already
shivering under frigid temperatures.
   Temperatures dropped to well below zero from Wyoming to
Michigan, and wind chills were expected today to be as low as 80
below in North Dakota, 75 below in Minnesota and 65 below in
Missouri.
   Snow fell early today throughout the Midwest, blanketing parts
of Missouri, Michigan, Illinois, Ohio and Indiana.
   A cold front continued to move south across the nation's
midsection Wednesday afternoon. The southern edge of the cold air
extended across western New York, central Ohio, southwest Indiana,
northeast Missouri, southwest Iowa, north-central Kansas, northeast
Colorado, northwest Wyoming and north-central Montana.
   The cold air was expected to reach northern Texas and northern
Louisiana today, and to invade North Carolina and northern Georgia
by Friday. A ``major freeze'' was predicted across the lower Rio
Grande Valley of Texas from tonight until Saturday.
   Winter storm warnings for heavy snow and wind were posted today
for much of Michigan and northwest Pennsylvania. About a foot of
snow was forecast for northwest upper Michigan. Snow also fell
early today over Pittsburgh.
   Winter officially arrived at 4:22 p.m. EST today.
   Snow showers were scattered in central New England Wednesday
evening. Snow also fell in western New York, northwest
Pennsylvania, northeast Ohio, Michigan, northern Indiana, northern
Illinois, Wisconsin, southern Minnesota, Iowa, northern Missouri,
southern and western South Dakota, eastern and northern Nebraska,
northeast Kansas, and parts of Wyoming, Montana and Washington
state.
   The high temperature for the Lower 48 states Wednesday was 84
degrees in Florida at Hollywood, Homestead and Miami.
   Other reports at 3 a.m. EST:
   _East: Atlanta 29 foggy; Boston 14 fair; Charleston, S.C. 30
fair; Chattanooga 21 fair; Cincinnati 9 partly cloudy; Cleveland 8
snow; Detroit 7 snow; Hatteras 32 fair; Jacksonville 44 cloudy; Key
West 73 partly cloudy; Knoxville 19 foggy; Macon 27 foggy; Miami 71
cloudy; New York 19 fair; Philadelphia 14 fair; Pittsburgh 8 snow;
Portland, Maine 11 fair; Richmond 15 fair; Tampa 53 foggy;
Washington, D.C. 20 fair.
   _Central: Bismarck 27 partly cloudy; Chicago 4 fair; Denver 2
cloudy; Des Moines 13 snow; Indianapolis 8 snow; Kansas City 1
windy; Little Rock 21 fair; Louisville 10 fair; Memphis 21 fair;
Nashville 13 foggy; New Orleans 41 foggy; North Platte 4 snow;
Oklahoma City 19 windy; Omaha 10 windy; Rapid City 10 snow; St.
Louis 9 snow; Minneapolis-St. Paul 21 fair; Sault Ste. Marie 4
snow; San Antonio 34 fair.
   _West: Anchorage 21 snow; Boise 28 smoke; Casper 7 snow;
Fairbanks 17 fair; Great Falls 13 snow; Honolulu 72 cloudy; Las
Vegas 36 partly cloudy; Los Angeles 54 hazey; Medford 29 foggy;
Pendleton 40 fair; Phoenix 49 fair; Portland, Ore. 33 foggy; Reno
29 partly cloudy; Salt Lake City 30 fair; San Diego 51 fair; San
Francisco 47 foggy; Seattle 45 cloudy; Spokane 28 foggy.
   _International: Montreal 0 fair; Ottawa 1 fair; Regina 34 fair;
Toronto 7 cloudy; Winnipeg 28 fair; Merida 75 fair.
</TEXT>

</DOC>