<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1046EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CraneShutdowns     12-28 0369</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Crane Shutdowns,0380</SECOND>
<HEAD>Safety Inspectors Shut Down Five SF High-Rise Cranes</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Angry officials say inspectors have found
safety violations in half the high-rise construction cranes
operating in the city a month after a crane collapse killed five
people.
   Inspectors ordered two more cranes shut down Wednesday, bringing
to five the number of cranes ordered to stop work by the California
Occupational Safety and Health Administration. In most cases, the
cranes were allowed to go back into operation after violations were
corrected.
   Two other construction cranes were found to be in proper order,
while the other three cranes in use at high-rise construction sites
around the city have not yet been inspected, officials said.
   Mayor Art Agnos, who requested Cal-OSHA to do the inspections
after the Nov. 28 disaster, promised to seek stricter supervision
of the machines, warning careless operators that ``we're coming
after you.''
   He said he would tell other mayors throughout the state of the
result of the inspections and hoped that together they could
pressure the state Legislature for stricted regulation.
   Cal-OSHA inspectors on Wednesday shut down a skyscraper crane at
a construction site because the operator lacked equipment to test
for unsafe loads. They shut down another crane because of
improperly set safety devices, said Cal-OSHA spokesman Rick Rice.
   ``Our feeling is one of being upset and very surprised,'' Rice
said.
   On Tuesday, Cal-OSHA shut down a crane because it lacked a
required warning light and bell to tell workers of dangerously
heavy loads. Inspectors, citing similar problems, earlier shut down
two other cranes.
   A huge tower crane was being raised from the 16th to the 20th
floor of a Financial District skyscraper on Nov. 28 when it fell to
the pavement, killing the operator and four other people. The
accident is still under investigation.
   State inspectors do not regularly examine tower cranes,
generally relying on the owners and operators of the equipment to
certify them as safe.
   Agnos, at a news conference, criciticized the practice as
``unacceptable'' and comparing it to ``a system that allows the fox
to guard the chickens.''
   Both the state Legislature and the San Francisco city government
are considering measures to tighten regulation of crane operators.
</TEXT>

</DOC>