<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0246 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0909EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-Boeing-Shrontz     12-22 0562</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Boeing-Shrontz,0584</SECOND>
<HEAD>Boeing Chairman Confirms Layoffs Planned</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Boeing Co. plans to lay off about 1,200 employees
in the first half of 1990, with most of the cuts to be made among
production workers at Everett, Chairman Frank Shrontz said.
   Shrontz's comment, in interviews with the Seattle Times and the
Morning News Tribune of Tacoma, confirmed recent speculation that
jobs would be cut.
   The exact size of the layoffs or where they might occur has not
yet been determined, but it will likely be in the general range of
1,200 employees, Shrontz said.
   The company is studying how it can transfer rather than lay off
workers, he said. That study should be completed by early next year.
   ``The continued impact of the defense budget on some of our
programs has made it now look like we can't hold the decline to
just attirition and there will be layoffs in the first half'' of
next year, he said. aIn the early 1970s as many as 60,000 workers
lost their jobs in a two-year period.
   Boeing employs about 165,000 people worldwide.
   Shrontz said the company anticipated a reduction in production
workers who were needed for startup work on the 747-400 jetliner,
but had not thought layoffs would be necessary.
   Increased experience and productivity on the assembly lines is
lessening the need for more workers, Shrontz said, even though the
company is experiencing a record surge in orders _ 888 jets worth
$46.7 billion this year. There is also an $85 billion backlog of
more than 1,700 planes.
   Shrontz said he had hoped excess workers could have been
transferred to work on the B-2 Stealth bomber, but B2 work was
slowed as part of defense-budget cutbacks, leaving the extra
commercial jet workers nowhere to go. Boeing, a subcontractor to
the Northrop Corp. on the new bomber, has had nearly 10,000 working
on the B2.
   Layoffs here will most affect production workers, Shrontz said,
but some engineers in Wichita, Kan., may also lose their jobs.
   A 48-day machinists' strike that ended last month ``clearly hurt
our profitability,'' Shrontz said, but he declined to be specific.
   Boeing had been expected to deliver 94 jets during the fourth
quarter but now may deliver less than half that number.
   ``We hope to get (the factories) back up to speed in the first
quarter,'' he said.
   Boeing ``clearly has been hurt in image'' but a flurry of
federal investigations and charges filed this year, he conceded.
   ``The defense business is very difficult,'' he said. ``There is
still a significant resentment against defense contractors by the
public and I foresee this climate will continue.''
   Richard Fowler, a former Boeing Aerospace employee, was recently
convicted of 39 counts of document trafficking and fraud in federal
court in Alexandria, Va. Boeing agreed to pay a $5.2 million fine
and pleaded guilty to two counts of illegally receiving secret
government documents in the case.
   ``What's so frustrating about this is that it occurred in the
early 1980s,'' said Shrontz. ``I think we've gained substantially
in ethics since then.''
   He said the company has found no further evidence of fraud or
misconduct in federal investigations of project billings. The
government continues to investigate the overbilling allegations.
   On other topics, Shrontz said while Boeing is reorganizing its
defense business divisions, the company will stay in defense work.
   ``We'll find our niche,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>