<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0164 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1200EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--GeneEditing Adv01   12-28 1074</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Gene Editing, Adv 01,1103</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv01</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Monday, Jan. 1, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Discovery Of `Editing' Of Genetic Messages Offers Hope Against Diseases</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RAEBURN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Editor</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Researchers have made the startling discovery
that some chemical messages sent by genes are changed before they
arrive at their destinations, a finding that challenges a central
tenet of genetics.
   ``It's an absolutely astounding concept,'' said Olke Uhlenbeck
of the University of Colorado in Boulder, a biochemist familiar
with the research. ``Nobody has the foggiest idea how it works.''
   The phenomenon is called ``RNA editing.'' One of its
discoverers, Larry Simpson of the University of California, Los
Angeles, said the discovery could lead to new treatments for
African sleeping sickness, a similar South American ailment called
Chagas' disease, and leishmaniasis, a disfiguring skin disease.
   Those diseases are all caused by the group of parasites called
trypanosomes. The first evidence for RNA editing was found in
trypanosomes by Rob Benne of the University of Amsterdam, who
reported the discovery in 1986.
   RNA editing has since been found in a slightly different form in
a slime mold called physarum, in measles virus, and in the human
gene for the protein called apolipoprotein B, associated with heart
disease.
   Most recently, independent teams in France and Canada reported
in Nature magazine in October that they had discovered RNA editing
in wheat plants.
   Researchers do not yet know how widespread RNA editing is or why
it evolved, but it appears to be a normal part of the functioning
of some genes. In trypanosomes, for example, researchers found that
certain genes were missing crucial elements. Yet the elements were
present in the genetic messenger chemicals associated with those
genes.
   ``RNA editing'' is the name that researchers gave to the process
by which the missing elements were restored.
   Although the initial discovery was made in 1986, the existence
of the phenomenon has not been widely accepted until now, says
another discoverer, Kenneth Stuart of the Seattle Institute for
Biomedical Research.
   ``It was initially met with extreme skepticism,'' said Stuart,
who has occasionally collaborated with Simpson. When Stuart
presented some findings to biologists last year, they were ``met
with disbelief,'' he said.
   Now, he said, other research groups have confirmed the findings
and more clear-cut examples of RNA editing have been found. ``We
now have three examples in which more than 50 percent of the gene
has been edited,'' Stuart said.
   ``It's been found by too many people in too many places now,''
said Uhlenbeck, who studies interactions between RNA and proteins.
``The reason I like it is that RNA has consistently been putting
out surprises for the last couple of years, and this seems to be
the next one.''
   Earlier work on RNA splicing, a different process in which RNA
is altered in accord with genetic instructions, earned a Nobel
Prize last year for Thomas Cech of the University of Colorado in
Boulder and Sidney Altman of Yale University in New Haven, Conn.
   RNA editing differs in an important way from RNA splicing and
other forms of RNA processing that were known previously, Stuart
said. RNA editing is the only process that appears to require the
addition of information not provided by the genes.
   ``It means that the genetic system has more capability than we
had previously recognized,'' he said. ``People who think about
things like this would not have predicted that such a complex
mechanism for changing information even existed.''
   The reason for the initial skepticism was that RNA editing
seemed to violate what biologists call the central dogma of
genetics, which holds that genetic information contained in the
genes passes from the genes, by way of a messenger chemical, to
proteins.
   The genes, made of DNA, or deoxyribonucleic acid, direct the
manufacture of messenger RNA, made of ribonucleic acid. The
messenger RNA travels from the cell nucleus to protein factories
called ribosomes, where the RNA directs the manufacture of the
myriad proteins the cell needs to survive and reproduce.
   In RNA editing, changes are made in the RNA after it is produced
by the genes but before it arrives at the ribosomes.
   ``Imagine a book that has less than half its pages,'' Stuart
said, ``and somehow, upon reading it, all the missing pages get
magically put back in. Or you type it into your computer and all
the vowels are missing, and when you send it to the printer all the
vowels somehow get put back in.''
   The discovery of RNA editing poses a difficult question. Where
are the missing pages _ or the missing vowels _ coming from? Where
does the cell get the information to restore or delete parts of the
messenger RNA?
   If the information is not coming from the genes, the central
dogma of genetics has been violated.
   ``What I hypothesize is that the genetic information actually
resides in the genes in encrypted form _ in an abbreviated or
compact form,'' said Stuart. If that is the case, then the central
dogma would not be violated; the editing information would be
coming from the genes.
   Simpson, who calls the edited genes ``cryptogenes,'' also
believes that the information added by the editing is somehow
hidden in the genetic code.
   The discovery of RNA editing in trypanosomes could lead to the
development of a drug that would kill them without harming human
cells, Simpson said.
   ``These are very important human and animal parasites,'' he
said. If RNA editing is found to be widespread in human cells, it
is likely to occur in a different form; drugs that attack
trypanosomes by interfering with RNA editing might, therefore, have
no ill effects in humans.
   ``We could kill the parasite and not harm the host,'' he said.
``Any time you find something that's unique to a parasite, it's
incredibly significant.''
   Simpson said there are similarities in the RNA editing in the
trypanosomes and in physarum, the slime mold. In both organisms,
the RNA editing occurs in the cells' energy-producing structures,
called mitochondria.
   ``What gets me excited is if the trypanosome type and the
physarum type are the same, which we don't know yet, then that
implies there was a common ancestor that had RNA editing in its
mitochondria.''
   If RNA editing was present in the ancient ancestor of
trypanosomes and physarum, then it must have developed early in
evolution and could have by now spread to many other organisms,
Simpson said.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Jan. 1</NOTE>

</DOC>