<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0092 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1548EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Boy-CrackArrest     12-30 0507</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Boy-Crack Arrest,0519</SECOND>
<HEAD>9-Year-Old Boy Accused Of Selling Crack To Undercover Agents</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 9-year-old boy accused of offering crack cocaine
to an undercover police officer was released to his grandmother and
police searched for the teen-ager who allegedly supplied drugs to
the youngster.
   ``With all the shootings and terrible things we see, this has
affected us the most because he is supposed to be innocent,'' said
Deputy Superintendent Robert Hayden. ``He is supposed to be worried
about what he got for Christmas, how he is going to set up his
Nintendo game.''
   The 3-feet-11 boy weighing 95 pounds, had $68 in his pockets at
the time of his arrest, police said. Police said he offered an
officer a bag thought to be crack.
   Among other youngsters arrested around the country on crack
charges this year have been a 10-year-old Detroit boy in August and
a 10-year-old boy on Long Island in New York in January. Last year,
Boston police arrested an 8-year-old boy who allegedly was holding
drugs for a dealer.
   The Boston boy was arraigned Friday in Roxbury District Court on
juvenile delinquency charges and released to the custody of his
grandmother, with whom he has been living while his mother is in
prison, police said.
   Hayden said the boy was scared and crying when he was taken into
custody Thursday and police tried to make him comfortable during
his jail stay. They sent out for a chicken dinner and an officer
sat with him all night.
   ``It was a very sad and traumatic thing to see a little
9-year-old boy sitting in the station arrested for drugs,'' Hayden
said. ``I saw some veteran officers with tears in their eyes over
this incident.''
   An arrest warrant has been issued based on information provided
by the 9-year-old, police spokeswoman Mardi Sullivan said Saturday.
   The youngster reportedly gave the first name and described a
teen-ager believed to be between 16 and 18 years old, as his
supplier.
   ``The little boy would go out and sell until the end of the
night when he would reach the older person who would give him
money'' for the sales work, said Hayden. The boy told police he had
been selling for about two weeks.
   Charles Dickerson, a juvenile officer at the Area B station,
said the youngster needs better supervision than his grandmother
can provide and police will ask Tuesday to have him turned over to
the Department of Social Services.
   ``He's used to getting out there and staying with the older
kids,'' Dickerson said. ``He's been seen at 11 p.m. with older
kids.''
   Hayden said three undercover officers went Thursday night to
Warren and Copeland Streets where there had been reports of heavy
drug activity. One officer was approached by the boy who said,
``What's up?''
   ``What do you got?'' asked the officer.
   The boy reached into his pocket and handed the officer what is
believed to be crack, the highly addictive form of cocaine. After
the arrest, officers found 80 small bags of crack nearby.
</TEXT>

</DOC>