<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0524EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-VampireRapist     12-28 0382</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Vampire Rapist,0393</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Try to Link Admitted Rapist to Unsolved Murders</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MELBOURNE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man dubbed the ``vampire rapist'' and
now serving a 25-year prison sentence may be released by 1992
unless police succeed in linking him to six unsolved slayings, a
prosecutor says.
   ``We will continue to work these cases as hard as we can'' in
hopes of bringing murder charges against prison inmate John
Crutchley, said State Attorney Norm Wolfinger.
   Crutchley pleaded guilty in 1986 to kidnapping and raping a
19-year-old woman who said her assailant called himself a vampire
and drained blood from her arms and legs through needles, drinking
some of it.
   In exchange for his guilty plea, prosecutors dropped several
charges, including the unusual count of robbery for taking nearly
half the woman's blood.
   Doctors said the woman would have died if she hadn't escaped
through a window in a locked bathroom while Crutchley, a former
Harris Corp. engineer, was at work.
   Wolfinger commented on the six unsolved murder cases this week
after Crutchley's former lawyer, Joe Mitchell, disclosed that he
tried to begin plea negotiations on the deaths in 1986.
   Crutchley would have admitted to some of the 1985 slayings and
taken investigators the victims' burial sites, Mitchell said. But
the negotiations fell through because prosecutors lacked evidence
linking him to any of the killings.
   ``He was going to admit to from three to six murders, but the
negotiations never got off the ground,'' Mitchell said.
   Crutchley, who blamed pornography for his obsession with bizarre
sexual rituals, refused through prison officials to be interviewed.
   Wolfinger said Tuesday that ``very informal'' negotiations never
reached a point at which Crutchley would have pleaded guilty to
murder.
   ``There comes a point in the negotiations when the state has to
show something,'' the prosecutor said. ``If we had had anything to
tie a charge to, we would have done it. But we had nothing.''
   Police said they have long suspected Crutchley in the unsolved
deaths in Brevard County. Although he is serving a long sentence,
he may be eligible for early release within three years because of
time earned behind bars, officials said.
   Investigators are looking for evidence in the deaths of five
victims whose bodies were discovered in 1985 and the disappearance
of another woman.
</TEXT>

</DOC>