<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0623EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-PanamaCasualties     12-22 0346</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama Casualties,0356</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bodies of Servicemen Returned from Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto XDV3</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-US-Panama</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By THERESA HUMPHREY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DOVER AIR FORCE BASE, Del., (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Drum rolls echoed through the
frigid night air as 14 flag-draped caskets were carried slowly from
a cargo jet and loaded into waiting hearses.
   The remains of U.S. servicemen killed in Panama were brought
home early today in the second such ceremony in less than 24 hours.
   On Thursday, the remains of four Navy men arrived to a solemn
runway ceremony at this base, which houses the Defense Department's
largest mortuary.
   Just after midnight this morning, military officials and the
family of one of the dead men braved 7-degree temperatures and wind
that made it feel like 25 below to honor 13 Army soldiers and one
Marine killed in the U.S. invasion of Panama this week.
   U.S. Army Secretary Michael P.W. Stone said the men died
defending freedom.
   ``We honor now the men whose lives represent our country's
latest losses in that long-lasting vigil ... We honor your courage,
your devotion and your loss. The nation honors your memory,'' Stone
said.
   Marine Lt. Gen. Norman Smith said Cpl. Garreth C. Isaak, 22, of
Greenville, S.C., ``paid the ultimate in carrying out his mission
to help preserve human dignity and freedom.''
   The parents and two brothers of Army Staff Sgt. Larry R. Barnard
of Hallstead, Pa., attended the ceremony. The Rev. Marilyn Barnard,
her husband, Raymond, and their two sons declined to talk to
reporters.
   Friends said Larry Barnard married his high-school sweetheart,
Tammy, and they had a 10-year-old daughter and a younger set of
twins.
   Ten evacuees from Panama, all of them believed to be civilians,
also arrived at the base Thursday night, according to base
spokesman Capt. Walter Thorp. They refused to comment to reporters.
   The Navy divers were killed leading the assault on Paitilla Air
Field, where deposed Panamanian strongman Manuel Noriega kept
aircraft, said Cmdr. Bob Prucha Prucha, a Navy spokesman.
   The remains will be prepared for burial and then transferred to
their next of kin.
</TEXT>

</DOC>