<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0115 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1432EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-EastGermany     12-29 0543</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany,0560</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rift Develops in Main Opposition Group</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NESHA STARCEVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   One branch of East Germany's biggest
opposition movement defied the coalition's leaders Friday and said
it would form a political party to challenge the Communists in
parliamentary elections.
   The military announced it was replacing its top-ranking officers
and said it had abolished the section in which the Communist Party
ensured obedience from the military.
   Sen. Carl Levin, D-Mich., said Friday that he was told that East
Germany is considering reducing its defense spending by 20 percent
next year.
   The main body of New Forum, which claims membership of 200,000,
decided earlier this week to remain a citizens' group rather than
found a formal political party.
   New Forum activists from five East German cities, however, met
in Karl-Marx-Stadt and said they set up a committee to form the
German Forum Party, the official news agency ADN said. The new
party will hold its founding convention on Jan. 27 and run
candidates in the May elections, ADN said.
   There has been friction between New Forum founders, who are
mainly based in East Berlin, and the more radical members of the
group in the provinces.
   New Forum was formed as a loose group of opposition activists
just over two months ago, when the pro-democracy movement began
challenging the hard-line Communist leadership.
   The protests grew into massive street demonstrations that forced
the ouster of hard-line Communist leader Erich Honecker, democratic
reforms and the resignation of the entire Communist leadership Dec.
3.
   In less the two months, East Germany opened the Berlin Wall and
other borders and embarked on the path of democratic reforms that
will culminate in the free elections.
   Late Thursday, New Forum's national council issued a platform
for the elections, but said it still considered itself only a
nationwide citizens' movement.
   The group said it was ready to assume political responsibility,
strived for a ``mixed economy,'' and supported ''a special
relationship'' with West Germany.
   New Forum said it will offer an alternative for citizens who did
not trust other established parties and their willingness to carry
out deep reforms. It said it supported a confederation with West
Germany.
   The East German offer to trim 20 percent of its defense budget
``could be very significant'' if it turns out to be true, said Sen.
Levin. Levin said the figure came out during a meeting with Defense
Minister Theodor Hoffmann.
   ``It adds evidence that there is a very significant reduction in
the threat from the East,'' said the senator, who added that lower
U.S. defense spending could be justified by the reforms being
introduced in Eastern Europe.
   East German officials had previously said the 1990 defense
budget would be at least 10 percent lower than the $13 billion
reported for this year.
   The Defense Ministry announced a series of new appointments that
take effect Monday.
   Ministry spokesman Uwe Hempel told ADN that Gen. Horst Bruenner
was retiring after the abolition of the political administration
department. The office dealt with ideological matters and ensured
Communist policies and ideology were observed in the military.
   The military also replaced the chief of staff and commanders of
the navy, air force and land forces.
   ADN gave no reason for the changes.
</TEXT>

</DOC>