<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0093 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1200EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-Noriega-Holdings 315   12-22 0325</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Noriega-Holdings, 315</SECOND>
<HEAD>Noriega Records May Help Trace Drug Money</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES ROWLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Financial records found in Manuel Antonio
Noriega's offices may help investigators trace money the deposed
Panamanian leader earned from drug trafficking, the Justice
Department said today.
   Department spokesman David Runkel said U.S. investigators are
reviewing the records seized in Noriega's offices at the Panamanian
Defense Forces headquarters.
   ``We believe there are assets and we are checking records to
determine where those assets are currently located,'' Runkel said.
   ``We have been in contact with foreign governments and financial
institutions as well as people here'' to trace the cash and other
holdings that Noriega is believed to have amassed from his
involvement in drug trafficking, Runkel said.
   Runkel said he had no information to specifically identify any
assets either in this country or abroad.
   But the spokesman said two foreign governments, which he would
not name, are currently assisting the Justice Department's efforts
to trace and freeze Noriega's holdings.
   The Treasury Department also was participating in the effort to
trace the assets, Runkel said.
   The records seized during the U.S. invasion might contain
evidence that Noriega looted the Panamanian treasury too, he said.
The records will be studied in Panama by officials of the new
Panamanian government installed after the U.S. invasion, he said.
   If useful, the records would be turned over to federal
prosecutors in Miami and Tampa, Fla., where Noriega faces drug
trafficking charges. He is accused of pocketing $10 million by
allowing Colombian drug lords to smuggle cocaine and marijuana
through Panama to the United States.
   The search for Noriega's assets was stepped up as the White
House announced that U.S. troops in Panama had found about 110
pounds of cocaine worth $1.25 million in the Panama City building
where Noriega had an office.
   The cocaine was found during a ``floor-by-floor'' search of the
building at Fort Amador, said White House spokesman Marlin
Fitzwater.
</TEXT>

</DOC>