<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0522EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Obit-Morial     12-25 0697</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Obit-Morial,0719</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ernest Morial, New Orleans' First Black Mayor, Dies At 60</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LINDA ASHTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ernest Morial, New Orleans' first black mayor
who spent a lifetime breaking down racial barriers, has died from
an apparent heart attack after leaving a Christmas party. He was 60.
   Morial was found slumped over the steering wheel of his car at
11 p.m. Saturday after leaving a party, said Jinx Broussard, a
spokeswoman for Mayor Sidney Barthelemy. Morial apparently had
suffered a heart attack.
   He was taken to Mercy Hospital where efforts to revive him
failed, and was pronounced dead at 1:30 a.m. Sunday, Broussard said.
   The feisty attorney became the city's first black mayor in 1978
at a ceremony loaded with symbols of black-white unity and tough
promises.
   He served two terms, leaving office in 1986 after an
unsuccessful attempt to persuade voters to amend the city charter
to allow him a third consecutive term. He then practiced law.
   Becoming mayor wasn't the only time he achieved a first for
blacks.
   He was the first black graduate from Louisiana State University
law school in 1954. He was the first black assistant U.S. attorney
in Louisiana, serving from 1965 to 1967. He became the first black
Louisiana legislator in modern times, serving in the House from
1967 to 1970, when he was appointed to a juvenile court judgeship.
In 1973, he was the first black elected to the Louisiana 4th
Circuit Court of Appeal.
   He also was a president of the National Conference of Mayors, a
Democratic National Committee member, and an adviser to Democratic
presidential candidate Michael Dukakis in 1988.
   Moon Landrieu, who was mayor from 1970 to 1978, said Sunday that
Morial was a formidable leader who left his mark on city, state and
national politics.
   ``I'm satisfied that when you're the first of anything, you're
long remembered for that. `Dutch' was the first black individual to
achieve high public office in this state. ... That alone I think is
a very significant achievement,'' Landrieu said.
   ``I think he will also be remembered for his tenacity and
pugnaciousness. He was certainly controversial, and I think will be
remembered for that also, and very fondly by some.''
   Morial was born Ernest Nathan Morial on Oct. 9, 1929, a son of a
New Orleans cigar maker. Morial later had his name changed to make
his nickname, Dutch, his second middle name.
   ``He was really an extraordinary individual,'' said Arnold
Hirsch, a professor of history and urban studies at the University
of New Orleans.
   ``If there's one thing that constantly comes to mind about
Morial, it was his dogged refusal to accept any of the barriers
that were laid in his way.''
   Morial's public service career was launched in the 1960s when he
became president of the local chapter of the National Association
for the Advancement of Colored People.
   ``He had his signature on almost every case that began to
dismantle the edifice of Jim Crow here, brick by brick,'' Hirsch
said.
   At a speech in 1967, Morial said: ``New Orleans won't have the
kind of political climate it takes to elect a Negro mayor for eight
or 10 years.'' He was elected 10 years later.
   As mayor, Morial dealt with floods in 1978, a city police strike
in 1979 that effectively shut down Mardi Gras, and the 1984
Louisiana World Exposition that was a financial disaster.
   When voters rejected a charter change that would have allowed
him to run for a third term, Morial backed Sen. Bill Jefferson to
succeed him. But Jefferson was defeated by Sidney Barthelemy, a
former state legislator and councilman. Barthelemy is up for
re-election in February 1990.
   Morial had been considering running against Barthelemy and
challenger Donald Mintz. But two weeks ago, he said the demands on
his family would be too great.
   Survivors include his wife, Sybil, and five children.
   Morial will lie in state Wednesday at Gallier Hall in New
Orleans. A prayer service is scheduled that evening in Municipal
Auditorium.
   A funeral Mass will be said Thursday at historic St. Louis
Cathedral in the French Quarter. Burial will be in St. Louis
Cemetery No. 1.
</TEXT>

</DOC>