<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0191 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0105EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-TradeDebate     12-19 0582</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Trade Debate,0596</SECOND>
<HEAD>Trade Experts Fail To Reach Consensus</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN CRUTSINGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Economics Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A panel of experts called in by a research
organization to make recommendations on U.S. trade policy failed to
reach a consensus and instead was forced to issue two separate
reports mirroring the deep divisions in the current debate over
trade issues.
   Officials of the Twentieth Century Fund said Monday it was the
first time that a panel of experts convened by the nonprofit
research organization had failed to reach enough agreement to issue
a single report.
   Instead, the panel split 7-5 with seven experts advocating free
trade and five other panel members supporting what some have called
a ``managed trade'' approach to the nation's huge trade deficits.
   The depth of feeling on both sides emerged during a sometimes
heated news conference the panel held to unveil their separate
reports.
   Those arguing for free trade asserted that the trade policies
established by the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade, the
Geneva-based organization which governs world trade, should not be
tampered with because they had served the global economy well for
almost four decades.
   ``We are the world's leading exponent of the free-market system
whose triumph we are now celebrating,'' said Herbert Stein, former
chairman of the Council of Economic Advisers in the Nixon
administration. ``We should not retreat into fearful isolationism.''
   The minority group on the panel argued that the huge trade
deficits during the 1980s and the United States' new status as the
world's largest debtor country showed that more must be done to
attack the huge trade imbalances.
   Clyde Prestowitz, a former Commerce Department trade official in
the Reagan administration, argued that free-trade advocates were
ignoring the fact that trade to a large extent was being managed at
the present time. He said much of the Japanese success stemmed from
that government's active involvement in assisting emerging
technologies.
   ``Traditional free-traders argue that it is not important
whether your industry makes computer chips or wood chips, but we
believe that the composition of industry in a country is
important,'' said Prestowitz, now a senior associate at the
Carnegie Endowment.
   Advocates of a more aggressive trade policy argued that the
United States should establish a goal of erasing the country's
annual trade deficit by 1993. The broadest measure of trade, the
current account, was last in surplus in 1981. The deficits have
been stuck above $100 billion for the past five years.
   Stein said efforts to protect certain U.S. industries against
trade competition would end up costing consumers who must pay
higher prices for products. He said proposals for the government to
pursue an industrial policy by picking winners and losers in
emerging technologies was also ill-conceived.
   ``The notion of turning the United States economy over to a
government agency is ludicrous,'' he said.
   The members of the task force who signed the free-trade report
were Stein; Anne Krueger, economics professor at Duke University;
Lawrence J. Brainard, senior vice president at Bankers Trust Co.;
Harry L. Freeman, executive vice president, American Express Co.;
Paul Krugman, economics professor at the Massachusetts Institute of
Technology, Robert Z. Lawrence, senior fellow at the Brookings
Institution, and Gary Hufbauer, professor at Georgetown University.
   Joining with Prestowitz in the opposing report were Patrick D.
Choate, vice president for policy analysis at TRW Inc.; Robert
Kuttner, economics editor at ``The New Republic;'' Howard D. Samuel
with the industrial union department at the AFL-CIO, and Alan
Wolff, a Washington attorney.
</TEXT>

</DOC>