<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0284 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1810EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-BankofNewEngland     12-22 0307</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bank of New England,0316</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bank of New England Rescinds Stock Dividend</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JONATHAN YENKIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bank of New England Corp., which expects heavy
losses due to bad real estate loans, on Friday rescinded a common
stock dividend it had declared last month.
   The announcement came one week after Bank of New England said it
would boost its loan reserves above $1 billion and that it expected
a ``substantial'' loss for the year.
   At the time, the bank also said it was exploring the sale or
merger of its assets and was considering rescinding a 34 cents per
share dividend for the fourth quarter ending Dec. 31.
   In a brief statement late Friday, the bank said its board of
directors had agreed to rescind the dividend.
   Analysts said such action is highly unusual but reflects the
serious trouble Bank of New England faces due to a real estate
slump that has battered many of the region's banks.
   ``We're looking at a real estate market that is deteriorating
very rapidly and very dramatically, and Bank of New England is a
major real estate player,'' said James Moynihan, senior vice
president of Advest Inc. in Boston.
   While 28 banks in New England have eliminated or cut dividends
since April, Moynihan said: ``I've never seen a cash dividend
declared, then rescinded.''
   Bank of New England, the region's second largest bank, has come
under increased scrutiny by regulators, and analysts predict
changes could be forthcoming in the company's management. The bank
last week reassigned a senior executive overseeing its real estate
group.
   Moynihan also said the possibility is growing the bank could be
acquired by an another bank or outside investor.
   ``One of the things you have to address is customer
confidence,'' he said, noting the bank could have trouble restoring
credibility without outside help.
</TEXT>

</DOC>