<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0200 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1906EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-Panama-KellyText 2ndAdd   12-20 0802</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Panama-Kelly Text, 2nd Add,a0844 et. seq.,660</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHN: of MPs.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   And then the command-and-control capability that the brigade
headquarters gives us should give us an ability to thicken the
forces in the vicinity of Panama City, and to get in there tomorrow
and do some good work.
   I would point out to you that most of the paratroopers, and most
of the soldiers and the Rangers who went into Panama, have at this
point been awake for three days, and they're pretty tired. You
know, they marshal the troops a good 18 hours before they get on
the airplane.
   They fly down, which is not a lot of fun because we tend to
fully book the aircraft, and then the most comfortable thing they
do is to step out the back door. And when they get on the ground,
of course, they're using up their adrenalin and they're nervous.
And so, they're just flat tired. We will be doing some work tonight
and we will be doing some work every night every night. But I think
that the progress has been reasonable, understanding that the
operation has not been going on yet for a full day.
   The command and control, in my own opinion, has been excellent.
The chain of command is short and effective from the Secretary of
Defense through the Chairman (of the Joint Chiefs of Staff) to the
Commander-in-Chief in Panama to the field commander, who is also
the Commander of the 18th Airborne Corps. And everybody in the
country who carries a gun works for him.
   I'd be happy to address some of your questions now.
   Q: General, how _ the Rio Hato situation _ how many troops in _
that's the Montes _ de los Machos?
   GEN. KELLY: The Men of the Mountain are the 7th Infantry Company.
   Q: Yes _ how many of them escaped? I mean, what kind of forces _
   GEN. KELLY: Hard to say, because we think only about a half of
them were there in the first place. They had some of these folks _
and Ted's the expert on that _ but they were at the Comandancia.
They had a real mixed bag of people at the Comandancia, protecting
it. It seemed that Noriega, in his latter days as dictator, liked
to keep moving people around to keep them loose. Ted, do you want
to add to that?
   ADM. SHEAFER: Half the 7th Company was up at the Comandancia.
   Q: At the Comandancia down at Rio Hato?
   ADM. SHEAFER: At the Comandancia. You've got 250 at Rio Hato _
is that right?
   GEN. KELLY: 250 detainees _ yes. And if that was half the 7th
Company _ excuse me _ most of the 6th Company, we got a pretty good
slug of them, I would think, and I wouldn't think more than about
75 _
   ADM. SHEAFER: We haven't had a chance to go through all of the
detainees yet, and get an order _
   Q: Good intelligence _ but you think you got a number of them at
the Comandancia?
   ADM. SHEAFER: Yes.
   Q: General, what can you tell us about the hostage situations?
What can you tell us about the different hotels that house
Americans that apparently the troops have had trouble getting to?
What is the situation, and why have the troops had trouble getting
to these hotels?
   GEN. KELLY: We now have a clear understanding of the importance
of getting to the hotels. We don't plan to tell you how we're going
to do that, because we don't want to help those who are possibly
around the hotels.
   Incidentally, in some cases people are isolated in hotels, but
they're not hostages because they're not being held by anybody.
   Our original strategy was to attack the PDF and to break its
structure down. I think we've pretty much done that. Now, we'll
move in with much greater force into the built-up areas of Panama
City in order to be able to protect the Americans and other people
who are there.
   Incidentally, we don't have an effective police force in Panama
City either _ a Panamanian police force _ one of the things we
would hope to get re-established fairly quicky.
   Just let me add one thing. We know of no Americans who've been
killed as the result of any of this.
   Q: General _
   Q: General, can you tell us, is there an ongoing hostage
situation there? Are you aware of hostages? How many do there
appear to be? How much of a problem is it for you?
   GEN. KELLY: We have reports of hostages. Some of those reports
seem credible. None of those reports have been verified by our
military. And I think I'll ask Ted to add anything to that that you
would choose.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>