<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 2240EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Brazil 3rdLd-Writethru a0750 12-17 1001</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0750,1034</SECOND>
<HEAD>Brazilians Choose Collor de Mello as President, Polls Say</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 20 grafs to UPDATE with more initial returns; pickup
graf 20 pvs `Some 82...' ^LaserPhotos MA1, SAO2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TODD LEWAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRASILIA, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Exit polls showed free-market champion
Fernando Collor de Mello had defeated his socialist adversary by a
narrow margin Sunday in Brazil's first free presidential election
since 1960.
   Initial returns late Sunday showed Collor de Mello running neck
and neck with Luis Inacio da Silva.
   Many of the millions who turned out waved campaign flags and
sported candidates' buttons in a climate that appeared totally free
of political or military intimidation.
   Unofficial results gave Collor de Mello 14.1 million votes with
37 percent counted. Leftist Luis Inacio Lula da Silva had 14
million, Globo TV, the nation's largest network said.
   The Superior Electoral Court's official count _ far behind with
just 1.2 percent of the vote tallied _ gave da Silva 452,780 votes,
or 44 percent, and Collor de Mello 408,061, or 39 percent. The rest
of the votes were blank, nullified or abstentions.
   Election officials said final results would be known in three
days.
   Collor de Mello, a member of one of Brazil's wealthiest families
and former governor, and Rep. da Silva , a former lathe worker and
union chief, appeared to be in a dead heat when the polls opened.
   But one survey, by the Brazilian Institute of Public Opinion and
Statistics, gave Collor de Mello, of the rightist National
Reconstruction Party, 52 percent of the vote in an exit poll. The
institute interviewed 1,218 Brazilians after they voted in 95
cities between 10 a.m. and 4 p.m.
   Da Silva, of the radical left Workers Party, had 48 percent of
the vote, according to the institute.
   ``We are predicting a victory for Collor de Mello by 2.5 million
to 4 million votes,'' Carlos Augusto Montenegro, director of the
polling company, said in a live televised interview.
   A second exit poll, by the DataFolha polling institute, gave
51.5 percent to Collor de Mello and 48.5 percent to da Silva after
11,995 people were questioned in 223 cities nationwide between 8
a.m. and 4 p.m., DataFolha said.
   The exit polls buoyed officials in the Collor de Mello camp.
   ``We are not celebrating yet, but we are relieved because the
polls are confirming our expectations of victory,'' said Claudio
Humberto Rosa e Silva, Collor de Mello's chief spokesman.
   Officials of da Silva's party said it was too early to concede.
   ``We need to get the end of the vote counting before conceding
anything,'' Eduardo Suplicy, a member of the Workers Party's board
of directors, said in a televised interview.
   From the Amazon rain forest to the concrete sprawl of Brazil's
southeastern cities, lines of voters began forming before sunrise.
   Polls opened at 8 a.m. and closed at 5 p.m. (2 P.M. EST),
although voters in line then were allowed to cast ballots.
Unofficial reports from polling stations in several major cities
showed turnout lower than anticipated.
   Election officials attributed this in part to heavy rains in
central, northeastern and far southern Brazil.
   Rain also caused the deaths of four people in northern Brazil
when two trucks carrying voters to polling stations overturned on
slippery roads.
   The Workers Party complained that in some cities, da Silva
voters couldn't get to the polls because private bus companies
idled their vehicles. It asked federal election officials to
investigate.
   Some 82 million voters across Latin America's biggest nation
were registered for the election, seen as a huge step toward the
return of full democracy after a rightist military regime ruled
from 1964 to 1985.
   The new president takes office March 15 for a five-year term.
The current president, Jose Sarney, took office in 1985 after he
was picked by an electoral college controlled by the military
regime.
   The election also was seen as a referendum on the past two
decades, which have been marked by 1,500 percent annual inflation,
sinking real wages and corruption.
   Despite wild street rallies that capped a week of mudslinging by
both candidates, voting was peaceful across the country.
   Da Silva supporters jammed Brasilia's confetti-littered business
district in cars, honking horns and waving huge red-and-white flags.
   Collor de Mello, 40, voted in his home district of Maceio, the
capital of Alagoas state on Brazil's northeastern Atlantic tip.
   ``I am confident in the grand victory the Brazilian people will
obtain with our proposal of rebuilding this country,'' he said. He
later flew to Brasilia to follow the vote count.
   The burly da Silva, 44, kissed his ballot as he cast it in the
southeastern industrial city of Sao Bernardo do Campo, on the
outskirts of Sao Paulo, Brazil's biggest city.
   ``Today is the happiest day of my life,'' said the former
factory worker, dressed in a red T-shirt and jeans. He drove to a
friend's ranch to await the final results.
   Collor de Mello and da Silva were the top vote-getters in a
field of 21 candidates in balloting Nov. 15. Neither obtained the
majority needed to win, and Sunday's runoff was scheduled.
   Collor de Mello campaigned for a free-market economy and an end
to government corruption. He was backed by business leaders, the
military and the media.
   He tried to portray his adversary as a radical who favored
violent, Marxist revolution.
   Da Silva also had the support of the Brazil Popular Front, a
coalition that includes Marxists, unionists and the dominant
liberal wing of Brazil's powerful Roman Catholic Church.
   Da Silva said he supports redistribution of land and wealth,
reforms in education and health care and a moratorium on Brazil's
$110 billion foreign debt.
   He criticized his opponent as a media creation with ties to the
``ruling class'' and the former military regime.
   The last popularly elected president of Brazil was Janio
Quadros. He resigned in 1961 after seven months in office citing
``occult forces.''
   A right-wing military regime overthrew Quadros' successor, Joao
Goulart, and ruled from 1964-1985.
</TEXT>

</DOC>