<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0217 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0212EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Korea-Jet Bjt   12-21 0676</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Korea-Jet, Bjt,0698</SECOND>
<HEAD>South Korea Picks McDonnell Douglas FA-18 as Main Warplane</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By M.H. AHN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   South Korea has chosen the FA-18
Hornet produced by McDonnell Douglas Corp. as its main jet fighter,
a decision worth an estimated $4.4 billion to the U.S. defense
contractor.
   The Hornet won out over another U.S. competitor, General
Dynamics Corp.'s F-16 Falcon, after a lengthy contest.
   The announcement Wednesday came as a surprise. Widespread
reports said the nod would go to the far less expensive F-16. South
Korea already has dozens of F-16s. In the early 1980's, it
purchased 36 of them.
   McDonnell Douglas, based in St. Louis, said in a statement
released in Seoul, ``The Korean decision reaffirms America's
worldwide leadership in the aerospace industry.''
   It estimated the contract would mean more than 20 million man
hours of labor for U.S. workers and $3 billion worth of exports
over the next eight years.
   Defense Minister Lee Sang-hoon told a news conference, ``We have
chosen the FA-18s after considering all factors, including safety,
national interest and operational advantage that can help us to
effectively cope with North Korea's fast developing air
capability.''
   The announcement gave no price tag for the project, but industry
officials estimated it was worth at least $4.4 billion. They said
the same number of Falcons would have cost $2.8 billion.
   The deal calls for South Korea to buy or co-produce 120 FA-18s
under its fighter program from 1992-98. Korea plans to buy 12
finished FA-18s, assemble 36 from U.S.-supplied kits, and
co-produce 72 in Korean factories with the help of its U.S.
contractor.
   The Hornet is a single-seat twin-engine jet first produced in
1978. It is used by 30 squadrons in the U.S. Navy and Marine Corps,
and 842 planes have been sold to Canada, Australia, Spain, Kuwait
and Switzerland.
   Its standard combat arms include two heat-seeking Sidewinder
missiles on the wingtips, two radar-guided advanced Sparrow
missiles on fuselage stations and an internally mounted 20mm
machine gun with 570 rounds of ammunition.
   The cockpit is entirely digital, with three color monitors and a
new navigational and radar system for night attacks.
   Some civilian officials supported choosing the cheaper F-16 but
the air force preferred the FA-18s, which it believes can
technically match North Korea's newly introduced Soviet-made
MIG-29s and Su-25s, government sources said, speaking on condition
of anonymity.
   Defense Ministry spokesman Brig. Gen. Kim Ji-wook said McDonnell
Douglas offered a better deal, including a promise to
electronically upgrade aging Phantom jet fighters now in operation.
   Industry officials expressed hope the plane purchase would help
develop South Korea's civilian aerospace industry. Samsung
Aerospace Industries, an arm of the giant Samsung Group, will be
the main Korean contractor for the military deal, and companies in
the Daewoo and Hanjin groups will participate.
   Under American law, the U.S. Congress will have 50 days to
approve or reject the sale from the time it is formally notified of
the agreement.
   The U.S. government, under congressional pressure, had asked
South Korea to purchase more finished aircraft to help reduce South
Korea's trade surplus with the United States, expected to reach
$4.5 billion in 1989.
   South Korea, bowing to U.S. pressure, also had to lower from 50
percent to 30 percent the portion of the so-called off-set program,
under which the U.S. contractor would buy Korean-made aircraft
parts in return for selling the American aircraft.
   Some U.S. legislators expressed concern over technology transfer
to a nation which can develop its own aviation industry to compete
with American firms.
   McDonnell Douglas officials in Seoul said South Korean air force
people visited the United States twice this year to try out the
airplane, once for six weeks. The company shipped more than a ton
of paper evaluations on the plane to Seoul in September.
   They said delivery of the first planes will depend on how
quickly Congress approves the contract.
   The FA-18 was approved for overseas sales 3{ years ago and is
the top U.S. military plane that can be offered for sale to foreign
nations.
</TEXT>

</DOC>