<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0192 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0833EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a PM-ReligionintheNews Adv22   12-21 0783</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Religion in the News, Adv 22,0808</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv22</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Fri PMs Dec. 22, or thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Hanukkah Marks Trimuph Of Religious Rights Over Despotism</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE W. CORNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Religion Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The abused and trampled can win. That's the legacy of Hanukkah.
It was demonstrated in the origins of that Jewish holiday and also
resonates in present surges toward religious freedom in communist
lands.
   The point _ that the weak but principled can triumph over the
mighty _ was etched in that ancient Jewish victory which preserved
the ``mother faith'' and also the roots of Christianity and Islam.
   Their rise hinged on the heritage of Hanukkah, whose eight-day
observance begins at sundown Friday. It commemorates the amazing
feat of the Maccabee-led insurgents in overthrowing a
religion-crushing totalitarianism.
   All three major monotheistic faiths _ Judaism, Christianity and
Islam _ ``owe an enormous debt to the Maccabees,'' said Rabbi A.
James Rudin, interreligious affairs director of the American Jewish
Committee.
   ``If that victory had not occurred, the ruthlessness of imperial
power likely would have washed out and eliminated Jewish life as
Jesus knew it,'' Rudin added.
   But in that first war for religious freedom, the groundwork
endured not only for Judaism but also for its two offspring faiths.
   The successful outcome in 165 B.C. came after a lopsided,
three-year war in which relatively small, tattered bands of Jewish
guerrillas finally beat off the world's then mightiest military
power, the Syrian empire.
   ``The courage and faith of the few prevailed over overwhelming
odds,'' said Rabbi Henry Michelman, executive vice president of the
Synagogue Council of America, embracing all three wings of Judaism.
   ``It was the miracle of freedom over tyranny,'' he said, citing
parallels between that event and the emergence of persisting
freedom movements in Eastern Europe.
   ``The whole history of activism and dissent is of minuscule
handfuls of people, through stubbornness and conviction, being able
to resist the mighty empires,'' he added.
   ``The lonely, suppressed voices ultimately are sustained.''
   Rudin said that ``more and more we're seeing the weak overcoming
the strong, the power of an idea. We see it in Czechoslovakia, in
East Germany, Poland and elsewhere. It's the theme of Hanukkah.
   ``Over and over again, the folly of the world is that if
military power is sufficient, it is controlling. But monotheism,
freedom, democracy, have their own greater strength.''
   In the ancient, epic struggle, Syria's despotic Antiochus had
conquered most of the Middle East. He ordered all subjects to
worship the state pantheon of gods, and the destruction of all
vestiges of Judaism.
   Scripture scrolls were burned, synagogues razed, Sabbath
services forbidden. A defiling statute to the pagan Jupiter was
erected in the Jerusalem Temple. Thousands of Jews were slain,
though most complied.
   Pagan altars were erected throughout Israel, and patrols
deployed to force villagers to bow and make offerings to the new
``gods.''
   But revolt broke out when the aging Maccabee, father of five
sons, refused and killed a Syrian officer.
   The Maccabees fled to the hills and gradually gathered a scanty,
ill-equipped but growing army of resistance fighters _ a few
against the Syrian many. But their leader, Judas Maccabee, the
``hammerer,'' said:
   ``In the sight of heaven there is no difference between
deliverance by many or by few. So do not be afraid of them.''
   The long, relentless struggle marked the first successful use of
guerrilla tactics _ lightning strikes and retreats, surprise
attacks, ambushes, night raids and harassment.
   In the final decisive battle, the overwhelmingly outnumbered
Maccabee force of only 3,000 routed a Syrian army of 47,000,
including horsemen, foot soldiers and spearmen mounted on elephants.
   It was a turning point for civilization in the preservation of a
monotheistic religious heritage that has spread around the earth
through its descendant faiths.
   ``In successfully throwing off the yoke of religious
suppression, Judaism was able to go on, and many years later, from
its womb came the other monotheistic faiths,'' Michelman said.
   Those successive events had a ``direct historical correlation,''
he said.'
   After the Maccabean victory, the Jerusalem Temple was cleansed
and rededicated.
   Legend says that there was only enough oil for the Temple lamps
to burn one day but miraculously they burned eight days until more
oil could be made.
   In celebrating the event, Jewish families light an additional
candle each night beginning with the first this Friday evening
until on the final evening the following Friday, eight candles
shine from the menorah.
   Called the ``festival of lights,'' it is not directly related to
Christmas, but they have similar merry traditions of decorative
lights, games and gift-giving.
   They also share that Hanukkah gift that produced them both _ the
perpetuation of religious rights.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Fri PMs Dec. 22.</NOTE>

</DOC>