<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0094 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1559EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MailBombs-NAACP     12-30 0473</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mail Bombs-NAACP,0487</SECOND>
<HEAD>NAACP Figure Tries To Keep Normal Pace in Face of Death Threat</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Mail Bombs, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SONYA ROSS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When a group that claimed responsibility for two
mail bomb assassinations made a blanket death threat against NAACP
officials, that blanket might well have been dropped over Earl
Shinhoster's head.
   Shinhoster, Southeastern regional director for the NAACP, has
emerged as a potential target of someone's apparent grudge against
his group and the 11th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals.
   ``I've always understood very clearly the security implications
for what I do,'' Shinhoster said Friday night.
   ``These folks are deadly serious, whether this is isolated,
whether it's one or two issues involved,'' Shinhoster said. ``I'm
less concerned about reasons here as I am about how to deal with
it.''
   ``I'm really concerned for Shinhoster and others with the
NAACP,'' said Charles King, an Atlanta civil rights activist.
``This is very serious for them, but the rest of us ... I don't
think we're that much at risk.''
   Shinhoster's jurisdiction in the National Association for the
Advancement of Colored People includes Georgia, Alabama and
Florida, the three states that make up the 11th Circuit of the
federal appeals court.
   Package bombs killed 11th U.S. Circuit Judge Robert Vance on
Dec. 16, and Savannah, Ga., lawyer and civil rights activist Robert
Robinson two days later. Two others were intercepted at the 11th
Circuit building in Atlanta and the Jacksonville, Fla., NAACP
office.
   In August, a mailed tear-gas bomb went off in Shinhoster's
office, injuring eight people _ at about the time letters declaring
war against the 11th Circuit popped up at several television
stations.
   And a threatening letter _ much like the one in which
``Americans for a Competent Federal Judicial System'' claimed
responsibility for the bombs that killed Vance and Robinson _
arrived at Shinhoster's office shortly after the tear-gas did.
   ``I think it was very specific and targeted,'' Shinhoster said.
``I don't think it was happenstance.''
   Authorities have confirmed that the letters appear to come from
someone involved in the mail bombings.
   Shinhoster said that link means he probably will be greeted by
guards, police and FBI agents wherever he goes, at least in the
immediate future. On Friday, he said, police officers met him at
the airport in Savannah, where he went for a funeral.
   ``When I got back on the plane, they put me on the plane,'' he
said.
   James D. Williams, national spokesman for the Baltimore-based
NAACP, said the organization has taken extra security precautions
he would not specify.
   ``We believe that this latest incident is an effort to
intimidate our association, to strike fear in our hearts,'' said
NAACP executive director Benjamin Hooks. ``It will not succeed. We
intend to go about our business, but we will most certainly be
taking precautions.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>