<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0118EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Senators-Ethics Bjt   12-23 0524</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Senators-Ethics, Bjt,510</SECOND>
<HEAD>RETRANSMITTING a0421 to restore bjt designator</HEAD>
<HEAD>Ethics Committee Starts Probe of Keating Five and D'Amato</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LARRY MARGASAK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Senate ethics committee says it's formally
investigating five senators who intervened with regulators for a
troubled savings and loan, and a sixth accused of influence
peddling.
   The lawmakers are using the announcement to again proclaim their
innocence.
   The committee said Friday it has begun preliminary inquiries of
the six _ the first of three possible investigative steps _ but
emphasized in a statement it ``has taken no position as to the
merits of the allegations or the weight of the evidence.''
   In the savings and loan case, the ethics panel will probe the
activities of Majority Whip Alan Cranston, D-Calif.; Banking
Committee Chairman Donald W. Riegle, Jr., D-Mich.; John McCain,
R-Ariz.; Dennis DeConcini, D-Ariz., and John Glenn, D-Ohio.
Congressional watchdog Common Cause asked for the investigation.
   Sen. Alfonse D'Amato, R-N.Y. will be the subject of the
influence-peddling inquiry, expected to focus in part on the award
of federal housing money to the senator's political contributors. A
complaint was filed by a political opponent of the senator.
   ``It's a good move,'' said Murray Flander, press secretary to
Cranston in a comment that echoed the sentiments expressed by the
other five lawmakers.
   ``The fact that they are conducting a full preliminary
investigation and the fact that he will be cleared, this will
obviate any charges of whitewash afterwards,'' he said.
   A preliminary inquiry determines whether there is reason to
believe Senate rules were broken. An affirmative finding is needed
before the committee would proceed to the next level.
   Cranston, Riegle, McCain, DeConcini and Glenn received a
combined $1.3 million for their campaigns and causes from Charles
H. Keating Jr., who headed Lincoln Savings and Loan of Irvine,
Calif. The senators met with regulators on Keating's behalf in 1987.
   The government didn't seize control of Lincoln until last April
14, and the eventual cost to taxpayers is expected to reach a
record level _ for a thrift failure _ of more than $2 billion.
   The ethics committee, headed by Sens. Howell Heflin, D-Ala., and
Warren Rudman, R-N.H., had hired an outside counsel, Robert Bennett
of Washington, to determine whether a formal probe should begin in
the Lincoln case. Another Washington attorney, Henry Schuelke,
performed the same role in the D'Amato case. The panel said both
counsels had recommended the preliminary inquiries.
   McCain spokesman Scott Selley said, ``The senator has cooperated
fully with the committee and will continue to do so. Frankly we
think they'll find there was nothing wrong with what Senator McCain
did.''
   DeConcini commented, `I welcome a thorough evaluation of the
facts and feel confident that I will be exnerated.''
   Glenn was out of town and not available, said assistant press
secretary Paul Brinkman.
   D'Amato said he was delighted with the announcement and
predicted, ``My actions are going to be proven to be correct,
responsible, and the work appropriate in every matter.''
   Riegle's office issued a statement that the senator ``strongly
supports this review and knows it will determine his conduct to
have been entirely proper.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>