<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1324EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-UN-Panama 2ndLd-Writethru   12-21 0652</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-UN-Panama, 2nd Ld - Writethru,a0572,0672</SECOND>
<HEAD>Security Council Confronts Two Competing Panamanian Governments</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 10 grafs to ADD Perez de Cuellar comments. Pickup
9th pvs, `Endara won...</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY12</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER JAMES SPIELMANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>UNITED NATIONS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As the Security Council convened for an
emergency debate on the U.S. invasion of Panama, the question that
immediately arose was: who speaks for Panama?
   The council was expected to recognize a new Panamanian
ambassador today, said diplomats and U.N. officials speaking
privately.
   At issue was which government was legitimate: that of strongman
Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega or Guillermo Endara's, which was
installed by the U.S. troops that invaded Panama early Wednesday
and smashed Noriega's forces.
   The United States, with help from other Western members, pressed
Wednesday for recognition of a new ambassador appointed by Endara's
government.
   Diplomats said Endara had appointed Eduardo Vallarino, a
Panamanian businessman in self-imposed exile in the United States.
   U.N. Secretary-General Javier Perez de Cuellar said today the
council was faced with an unprecedented situation because the
upheaval occurred when Panama had no accredited U.N. ambassador to
argue a case.
   The previous permanent representative, Leonardo Kam, was
promoted to foreign minister, and no one took his place.
   Noriega's government is trying to have its ambassador to the
European Community, Mirla Bellavita, accredited as U.N. ambassador.
   Perez de Cuellar said of the U.S. invasion that ``the position
of the United Nations for the last 45 years is that we always
regret the use of force.''
   ``At the same time, I think I shouldn't forget to say that what
is important as well for the United Nations is the preservation of
democracy,'' he added.
   Endara won the presidency in Panama's national elections May
7-9. But the Noriega-controlled government nullified the results
before they were announced.
   During Wednesday's debate, U.S. Ambassador Thomas R. Pickering
said his country had exercised its right to self-defense under
international law and the U.N. Charter ``in response to armed
attacks by forces under the direction of Manuel Noriega.''
   Panamanian soldiers shot and killed a U.S. Marine officer at a
roadblock Saturday night, one day after Noriega declared ``a state
of war'' existed between his country and the United States.
   American officials said the Marine, a lieutenant, was unarmed
and that the attack on him and three fellow Americans was
unprovoked.
   Pickering said the incident capped two years of harassment of
U.S. military personnel and workers at the Panama Canal Commission.
He said more than 400 U.S. personnel had been detained and 140
endangered.
   Pickering noted that Noriega's 1988 indictment in the United
States on drug-trafficking and money-laundering charges.
   ``Gen. Noriega could not be permitted falsely to wrap himself in
the flag of Panamanian sovereignty while the (Colombian) drug
cartels with which he is allied intervene throughout this
hemisphere,'' the ambassador said.
   ``That is aggression. It is aggression against us all, and now
it is being brought to an end,'' Pickering said.
   ``His ruthless cabal repeatedly obstructed the will of the
Panamanian people which has been expressed in (the May) free
elections,'' which Noriega's candidate lost, Pickering said.
   The ambassadors of Nicaragua, China and the Soviet Union
criticized the invasion and said U.S. troops should be withdrawn
immediately.
   Britain and Canada's ambassadors defended the intervention,
saying Noriega had provoked it.
   Ambassador Pierre-Louis Blanc of France agreed that the United
States had been provoked, but said, ``For us, use of outside force
is deplorable, whatever the circumstances.''
   Panama has repeatedly come before the council to complain about
allegedly provocative U.S. military maneuvers it said were intended
to lay the groundwork for an invasion to topple Noriega.
   During council debates in April and August, Panama claimed the
United States was trying to provoke confrontations in order to keep
control of the Panama Canal.
   Under 1977 treaties, the United States will cede control of the
canal to Panama at the end of 1999.
</TEXT>

</DOC>