<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0636EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DrugDecriminalization     12-18 0348</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Drug Decriminalization,0359</SECOND>
<HEAD>Michigan Congressman Calls for Drug Decriminalization</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. Rep. George Crockett joined a small group of
public officials endorsing decriminalization of drugs, saying money
now being spent on enforcing drug laws should be shifted to social
programs.
   Federal drug czar William Bennett reacted angrily to the
suggestion, saying Crockett and the others are undermining the Bush
administration's anti-drug efforts.
   ``Decriminalization is the only solution,'' Crockett, D-Mich,
told The Detroit News in an interview published Sunday. ``Our
courts are burdened down with these drug cases and there is nothing
they can do about it. And here we are talking about spending
additional billions to build jails and prisons to send people to.''
   Money spent on enforcement should be shifted to job training for
the urban poor, education, health care and day care, said Crockett,
whose 13th District includes Detroit's economically depressed east
side.
   Crockett said he didn't have plans to immediately introduce
legislation decriminalizing drugs because Congress would reject
such a move.
   Last week, U.S. District Judge Robert Sweet of New York became
the first federal judge to publicly support decriminalization. Also
favoring decriminalization are Baltimore Mayor Kurt L. Schmoke and
economist Milton Friedman.
   Bennett, director of the Office of National Drug Control Policy,
cursed when told of Crockett's position, the newspaper said.
   ``Here we go. We were wondering who was going to be the first''
in Congress to endorse decriminalization, Bennett said.
   Giving drugs the same legal status as alcohol could cause even
greater social and economic problems, Bennett said.
   ``Alcohol has done quite enough damage, thank you,'' he said.
``And if you want to see people using crack go from 1 (million) or
2 million to 10 million, make it as available as alcohol.''
   U.S. District Judge James Churchill, chief federal judge of
Michigan's Eastern District, said the idea at least should be
debated.
   ``Decriminalization is not a good answer,'' Churchill said.
``But it is an answer. ... What are we going to do once we get our
prisons full and we still have as many drug dealers on the street?''
</TEXT>

</DOC>