<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0137 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1452EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-RomanianDissidents     12-22 0411</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romanian Dissidents</SECOND>
<HEAD>Exiles See Brighter Future for Romania</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-US-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RUTH SINAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   One exiled Romanian dissident said Friday that
Nicolae Ceausescu had ``lost touch with reality,'' while another
said he was ready to return to help shape his country's future.
   ``I am ready to assume my responsibility and to save my
people,'' Mihai Botez said in an interview from New York City.
   Botez, a mathematician and economic planner exiled by Ceausescu
in 1987, said all political scenarios are open for Romania's
future, but one model is ``over, and that's Stalinism.
   A former economic adviser to the Romanian government before he
fell out of favor 10 years before his exile, Botez said he would
like to see the country develop a strong private sector, ``although
some socialist, nationalized enterprises will remain at first.''
   Vladimir Tismaneanu, a resident scholar at the Foreign Policy
Research Institute in Philadelphia, said that when Ceausescu
ordered troops to fire on anti-government protesters last week, it
was ``a clear indication that Ceausescu had completely lost touch
with reality.''
   Ceausescu's cult of personality and ``megalomania'' during his
24-year reign were compounded by his wife Elena's
``idiosyncracies,'' Tismaneanu said.
   Corneliu Manescu, the 73-year-old former foreign minister who
assumed leadership of a provisional government in Romania after
Ceausescu fled, is ill and will probably only serve as a
transitional leader until free elections are held, Tismaneanu said.
   But Ion Iliescu, a former Central Committee secretary ousted by
Ceausescu in 1971, would likely play a major role in the new order
in Romania, he said.
   Iliescu, who announced Friday that a ``National Salvation
Front'' had been set up to rule the country, was a classmate of
Soviet leader Mikhail Gorbachev at Moscow State University in the
1950s, Tismaneanu said.
   Botez, who has been a guest scholar at several U.S. think tanks
and universities since his departure from Romania was achieved with
the help of the State Department, says he has not been able to
contact his wife since he left Romania.
   His wife, also a prominent dissident, has been under house
arrest, as he was for several months before leaving Romania.
   The first priority, Botez said, is to supply food and clothing
to Romanians ``and stop the desperate suffering.''
   The foreign ministers of the European Community pledged
immediate aid to Romania on Friday and the International Committee
for the Red Cross dispatched two planes carrying 4 tons of medical
supplies to Bucharest.
</TEXT>

</DOC>