<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0090 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1417EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Panama 6thLd-Writethru   12-21 1243</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama, 6th Ld-Writethru,a0602,1282</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cuban, Nicarguan Embassies Surrounded in Search for Noriega</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Subs 1 graf after 8th, `The Nicaragua...' to UPDATE with State
Department confirmation of action in Managua. Pickup 9th, `Heavy fighting...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. troops today surrounded the
Nicaraguan and Cuban embassies after rumors spread that Gen. Manuel
Antonio Noriega may have fled there during the U.S. military
invasion that toppled his regime.
   The Nicaraguan government immediately ordered its army to
surround the U.S. Embassy in Managua until the siege on its embassy
ended.
   U.S. troops hunting for Noriega gained control of all major
Panamanian military bases after sporadic fighting late Wednesday
and early today.
   On Wednesday night, Noriega tried to rally his supporters by
making a brief radio address in which he vowed to ``win or die.''
   The general's loyalists apparently still held at least a dozen
Americans hostage. Armed thugs roamed through the capital today,
one day after the U.S. attack on Panama in which at least 18
Americans died.
   After rumors spread that Noriega or other members of the
Panamanian Defense Forces high command were in the Nicaraguan and
Cuban embassies, U.S. troops in armored personnel carriers
surrounded the two missions.
   One armored personnel carrier driver had to ask a reporter for
directions, and a soldier laying concertina wire at the Nicaraguan
Embassy said, ``We're just securing exits.''
   The Nicaragua government, which has fought the U.S.-supported
Contra rebels for eight years, ordered its troops to surround the
U.S. Embassy in Managua until U.S. troops withdrew from the
perimeter of its embassy in Panama City.
   Several hours later, State Department spokesman Richard Boucher
said that ``tanks or armored vehicles'' were surrounding the U.S.
Embassy in Managua. ``There is some sort of activity like that
going on,'' he said in Washington.
   Heavy fighting raged in the middle-class suburb of San Miguelito
just before dawn, marked by machine-gun fire, grenade explosions
and light artillery fire. U.S. aircraft and helicopters flew
overhead and drew ground fire.
   By daybreak today, the fighting had ceased, and U.S. Army troops
patrolled the streets as many Panamanians began looting shops once
more. There was no evidence U.S. troops were trying to halt the
looting.
   U.S. military officials said most of the fighting between
pro-Noriega forces and American troops has subsided and that little
real threat remains.
   Col. Ronald Sconyers, spokesman for the U.S. Southern Command,
told a pool of Pentagon reporters Wednesday that much of the
gunfire still being heard around the country is from roving bands
of Noriega's civilian ``Dignity Battalions'' who were ``just
getting their last licks in.''
   Meanwhile, the Panama Canal opened today after closing
Wednesday, the first time anything other than a landslide has
forced the 75-year-old canal to close. The 43-mile-long waterway
will be open only during daytime until at least the weekend, the
Panama Canal Commission said in a statement from Washington.
   Shortly before midnight Wednesday, a day of terror ended for 29
Americans and other foreigners at the Marriott hotel when about 90
paratroopers from the U.S. 82nd Airborne Division secured the
building after firefight.
   Armed Panamanians had raided the hotel periodically and abducted
guests, eventually freeing all but two, the hotel's manager and a
CBS news producer.
   The hotel was cleared of guests today, and there were reports
that U.S. soldiers were exchanging gunfire with Noriega loyalists,
a Marriott spokesman in Washington said.
   In addition, the Smithsonian Institution said 11 scientists and
technicians were missing from a research institute and believed
taken hostage.
   Pentagon officials said finding American hostages is a ``primary
concern.''
   Noriega surfaced with an ominous message. He said on a
government-run FM radio station that he will now lead a guerrilla
war against the United States.
   ``We're in trench warfare now and we will maintain the
resistance,'' he said. ``We ask the world for help, with men,
dignity and strength. Our slogan is to win or die, not one step
back.''
   The general's whereabouts could not be determined, and it was
unclear whether he had substantial forces under his command.
Journalists recognized the voice on the radio Wednesday night as
Noriega's.
   In Washington, Pentagon officials said troops may have to head
into the jungle to pursue Noriega units.
   The United States was offering a $1 million reward for Noriega
and $150 for each firearm surrendered.
   American forces appealed today in radio broadcasts for members
of Noriega's Panamanian Defense Forces to surrender.
   ``Do not fight for a small group of drug traffickers. Remember
the oath you took when you joined such an honorable institution as
the Defense Forces,'' one broadcast said in Spanish. ``Your fellow
citizens are asking your help to restore democracy.''
   Pentagon officials said about 1,500 U.S.-based reinforcements
were flown into the country late Wednesday to assist an exhausted
attack force and prepare to flush Noriega loyalists out of Panama
City.
   That effectively doubled to 24,000 the number of U.S. troops
that had been in the country before President Bush ordered
``Operation Just Cause'' in a bid to topple the general who has
been a thorn in the side of two U.S. presidents.
   Bush initially ordered 9,500 troops to Panama to augment 13,000
at bases along the Panama Canal.
   The Bush administration declared the operation a military
success. At least 18 Americans were dead, 117 wounded and one
missing. Also, one American female dependent was killed.
   Noriega's president, Francisco Rodriguez, said more than 60
Panamanians had been killed and hundreds were wounded, many of them
civilians.
   By late Wednesday, U.S. troops controlled most Panamanian bases
and the government television station. They had also knocked out a
radio tower, silencing the national network that had broadcast
appeals for resistance and military messages.
   Bush said in a speech Wednesday morning that he ordered the
invasion to bring Noriega to trial in the United States on 1988
cocaine-trafficking charges, to protect the 35,000 Americans in
Panama and to restore democracy.
   Opposition leader Guillermo Endara, winner of the May 7
elections that were voided by the Noriega-controlled government,
was sworn in as president. Also sworn in were First Vice President
Ricardo Arias Calderon and Second Vice President Guillermo
``Billy'' Ford.
   None surfaced by late Wednesday, however, and a call for public
demonstrations of support drew no visible reaction.
   Noriega declared Friday that Panama was in a ``state of war''
with Washington and a U.S. Marine lieutenant was killed the next
day in what American officials called an unprovoked shooting.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III claimed the administration
had received unconfirmed reportes that Noriega planned to order an
attack on an American residential neighborhood in Panama.
   U.S. forces began the attack by pounding Panamanian military
bases in and around the capital with mortar, cannon and machine-gun
fire. Noriega's headquarters in the densely populated neighborhood
of Chorillo was gutted.
   U.S. troops took 150 Panamanians prisoner and were holding them
in an automobile storage lot, a report from Pentagon pool reporters
said.
   The U.S. invasion was the biggest chapter in Washington's long
war with Noriega, a career soldier who had a strong core of support
among working-class people and who seemed to delight in defying the
mighty United States.
   Noriega survived two coup attempts from within his Defense
Forces and Washington's best non-military efforts to oust him,
including harsh economic sanctions that severely depressed the
economy.
   Bush ordered the sanctions lifted Wednesday and said he intended
to turn over the Panama Canal as required under existing treaties.
</TEXT>

</DOC>