<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 1831EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Egypt-Sudan     12-31 0285</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Egypt-Sudan,0292</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mubarak Says He'll Mediate in Sudan</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KHARTOUM, Sudan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Visiting President Hosni Mubarak of Egypt
pledged his help Sunday in mediating a settlement of the civil war
in southern Sudan.
   Mubarak, in an apparent attempt to make himself acceptable to
the rebels, seemed to pour cold water on an attempt by his host,
military ruler Lt. Gen. Omar Hassan el-Bashir, to reactivate a 1976
defense treaty with Egypt.
   El-Bashir has asked Mubarak, as a friend of Sudan and chairman
of the Organization of African Unity, to mediate a settlement of
the war that is crippling this East African country's economy.
   However, the leader of the rebel Sudan People's Liberation Army,
Col. John Garang, has demanded the scrapping of Sudan's military
agreements with Egypt and Libya as one condition for making peace.
   The former civilian prime minister, Sadek el-Mahdi, whom
el-Bashir toppled in a coup on June 30, said the agreements were
canceled. But El-Bashir told the official Sudan News Agency
Saturday that Sudan and Egypt are ``consulting on the procedures to
reactivate these agreements.''
   Asked about the treaty Sunday, Mubarak, with el-Bashir standing
by his side, said, ``Sudan and Egypt are one country, and they do
not need defense agreements.''
   Mubarak spoke to reporters at Khartoum airport after arriving
for a one-day visit to celebrate the 34th anniversary of Sudan's
independence.
   ``We have contacts with the Garang movement, and our relations
with the north are strong,'' Mubarak said. ``We are doing our
utmost to solve the problem.''
   Fighting between the southern rebels and the government has
escalated yiice peace talks in Kenya collapsed Dec. 5 after five
days of negotiations. Former President Jimmy Carter acted as
unofficial observer at those talks.
</TEXT>

</DOC>