<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0111 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1522EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     12-18 0642</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0674</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Apryl is CQ</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PALMER, Neb. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four entrepreneurs are leaving no stone
unturned in their first business venture.
   Rocks of all shapes, sizes and colors are on sale _ when the
weather's nice and not during cartoons _ in this east central
Nebraska community of 480. It's 25 cents for the small ones and 50
cents for the big ones.
   ``We're going to make money to buy Christmas presents,'' said
Greg Bader, 7.
   Greg and his sister, Steph, 8, and neighbors Apryl and Daniel
Gay, were ``digging for gold'' in the the Gays' backyard one day
this fall, but they found no gold, no dinosaur bones _ only rocks,
he said.
   ``Then we decided to sell the rocks,'' said Steph, a
third-grader.
   The four children have what looks to Greg like ``a thousand
billion'' rocks for sale.
   ``Some are so very, very clear that you can see through them,''
said 8-year-old Apryl with one rock up to her eye.
   ``Some look like bubble gum,'' said Daniel, 6, of the ones
painted pink.
   When the weather isn't too cold, the four sit at a table made
from an electrical wire spool in the Gay's front yard, displaying
the loot.
   After gathering the inventory, the children decided it was time
to advertise.
   Palmer Journal Publisher Dale Kirkpatrick said all four of the
young entrepreneurs paid him a visit to ask if they could place an
ad.
   ``They were very businesslike, very serious,'' he said.
   That businesslike demeanor inspired Kirkpatrick to offer a
four-column ad free of charge.
   ``He just told us he'd try and get some customers for us,''
Steph said.
   ``All they knew was that they had to put an ad in the paper in
order to sell their rocks,'' Kirkpatrick said. ``They had no idea
they would normally have to pay for it.''
   When Peg Gay, Apryl and Daniel's mother, heard the children had
tried to place an ad, she thought it would be a good lesson in
economics.
   ``I was going to teach them a lesson,'' Mrs. Gay said. ``I was
going to show them that it costs to put an ad in the paper and that
people don't buy rocks. I suppose they are learning a lesson, but
not the one I intended.''
   Placing the ad has spurred the children to dwell on what they'll
do with the profits, even though they've sold just two rocks in two
weeks.
   ``We might have to get more jars for our money,'' Steph said,
explaining that the blue plastic bear might not be sufficient.
   ``We might have the whole house full of money and have to get a
bigger one,'' Greg said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>MALIBU, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   One of Santa's better kept secrets is that
he and his elves surf on Christmas Day when they can get the beach
to themselves.
   Joe Klein's catchy holiday song ``Christmas in Malibu'' about a
forlorn, board-less surfer who gets an unexpected Christmas visit
from the surfing Santa has become the rage along the
celebrity-laden Malibu shores.
   ``Beaches are bare, Ain't no one there,'' begins the Beach
Boys-flavored rendition of the Christmas Day visit of the surfing
Old St. Nick, who proclaims with a hearty ho-ho-ho, ``Surf's up,
Dudes!''
   Klein shipped 7,000 audio cassette tapes to radio stations and
local record stores. The response was phenomenal, said Klein, who
hurriedly produced a video when cable's music channel MTV inquired.
   The lyrics include:
   Then, out of the northern sky comes a sled
   It lands on a swell, guess who's inside?
   St. Nick and his elves
   Wet suits off the shelves
   It's the one day of year
   They get the waves to themselves
   After Santa leaves with a wink and his board washes ashore, the
surfer gets the best waves he's ever seen: ``A gift just for me
from St. Nick.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>