<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0119 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 2003EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-DefiantCeausescus     12-26 0785</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Defiant Ceausescus,0818</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ceausescus Unrepentant in TV Footage of Trial</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DUSAN STOJANOVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Romanian TV on Tuesday broadcast
footage of the secret trial of Nicolae and Elena Ceausescu, showing
the dictator and his wife defiant, unrepentant and dismissive of
the tribunal that sentenced them to death.
   Ceausescu, gaunt and looking his 71 years, repeatedly told the
court he would answer only to the country's rubber-stamp parliament
``and the working-class'' for his actions.
   His wife, restrained from speaking several times when her
husband put his hand on her arm or leg, blasted back at unseen
prosecutors accusing the family of stashing cash in Swiss banks.
   ``Prove it,'' she retorted. ``This is a base provocation.''
   Ceausescu alternately remained silent after questions about his
24 years of dictatorial policy, or shouted replies in the raised
voice he used in his most strident speeches.
   ``Everything that was said here was false, and I don't want to
talk any more,'' he said.
   ``This was a coup d'etat and I don't answer your questions,'' he
proclaimed at another point.
   The couple sat silently as the indictment was read, charging
them with genocide of more than 60,000 people, the undermining of
the state and the economy, the destruction of historic monuments
and attempting to flee by hiding more than $1 billion in foreign
banks.
   Ceausescu refused to answer key questions about who ordered the
Dec. 17 shooting of unarmed civilians in the western city of
Timisoara that precipated the popular rage that drove him from
power.
   Elena Ceausescu, who was effectively in charge of Romania Dec.
18-20 while her husband was in Iran, acted unconcerned when asked
if she knew of the shooting in Timsisoara.
   ``What are you talking about?'' she demanded.
   ``Who ordered the shooting in Bucharest?'' a voice asked,
referring to the shooting of protesters in Bucharest last Thursday,
a day before the army backed the revolt and the Ceausescus were
forced to flee.
   ``Nobody was shot in the Palace Square,'' Ceausescu said. He was
referring to the square where he addressed a pro-government rally
Thursday that backfired and turned into a demonstration against him.
   The Ceausescus were captured Saturday in an underground bunker
at an undisclosed location. They were tried, sentenced and shot to
death by firing squad on Monday.
   Earlier Tuesday, the television broadcast scenes of their
bullet-ridden bodies slumped against a wall. A close-up showed
Ceausescu's face, his eyes open and blood on the right side.
   It has not been disclosed where and exactly when they were tried
and shot after the secret trial.
   ``Do you know what's happening now? Why are these people
fighting in the street?'' the prosecutor demanded, referring to
street battles between security troops loyal to Ceausescu and the
army, which backs the revolutionaries.
   ``The people are fighting the gangs of traitors who in collusion
with foreign forces organized this coup d'etat,'' Ceausescu
answered.
   ``Do you know that you were sacked as a president and a supreme
commander of the army?'' the prosecutor asked.
   ``No, I do not recognize this. I am the President of the
Socialist Republic of Romania,'' Ceausescu replied.
   Asked why he exported food grown in the country and left his own
people scraping by on meager rations, Ceausescu characteristically
cited the inflated statistics he loved to use to justify his
Stalinist policies.
   ``It's a lie that the people are hungry,'' he said.
   ``Why were the peasants going to Bucharest to buy bread?''
retorted the prosecutor. Ceausescu was silent.
   At another point in the 40-minute broadcast, he defended his
hated plan to ``systemize'' the countryside by moving peasants from
villages to shoddy new housing in agro-industrial centers. He
claimed the plan would bring more civilization to Romania's
tradition-rich peasantry.
   ``I didn't want to destroy the villages, on the contrary it was
a buildup of villages, they were supposed to get doctors,
schools,'' he said.
   ``It was an improvement, not a destruction. They were to be the
best villages in the world.''
   The couple also was asked about the luxurious lifestyle of their
daughter Zoia-Elena, captured by soldiers on Sunday.
   Television has shown footage of her opulent villa, containing
jewels and other artifacts from national museums and her two
lapdogs, said to have been fed with imported meat weighed on golden
scales.
   ``We don't have any villa,'' Ceausescu defiantly replied. Both
he and his wife laughed when asked about the imported meat for pets.
   ``We lived like normal citizens. It's incredible what you are
accusing us of,'' Ceausescu said.
   ``Did you ever suffer from any mental disorder?'' Elena was
asked at one point.
   ``Oh, what a base provocation,'' answered the woman who only a
week ago reigned supreme in Romania.
</TEXT>

</DOC>