<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0145EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BatteredWife     12-27 0874</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Battered Wife,0899</SECOND>
<HEAD>Attorneys Say Wife's Murder Acquittal a Victory for Battered Wife
Defense</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONG BEACH, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When they first dated in 1982, Jack
Elson opened doors for his future wife, Robin, cooked romantic
dinners and lit her cigarettes.
   ``I figured my knight in shining armor had finally come,'' said
Robin Elson, who has an 11th-grade education and was selling Avon
products when she met the 188-pound, 5-foot-8 auto mechanic.
   What he didn't tell her was that he had been married four times,
that one previous wife was hiding from him and another got a
restraining order against him when he beat her for slicing onions
too big.
   They married after a two-month courtship. He showed up 45
minutes late and drunk for the wedding.
   Six months later, when Robin objected to Jack going on a
Saturday fishing trip, he asked his friend to wait outside, went in
the house and blackened both her eyes.
   It was the opening of a brutal reign that left the two children
he and Robin had together, sons Camrin, 4, and Brock 2, and a
daughter from Robin's previous marriage, Renee, 11, living in
terror.
   Robin and the children were not only beaten, but Jack also left
her lists of chores to be completed, limited her nail polish colors
to pale pink and peach, forbade her to wear makeup, told her what
food to buy and checked her change against grocery receipts.
   Last December, Robin picked up a rifle as her husband lay in his
recliner chair after a morning of drinking and beating his family
and their pet dog. The 4-foot-9, 70-pound woman braced herself
against a wall and fired three times, killing him.
   A jury in Long Beach last month acquitted the 28-year-old woman
of murder after hearing a wide range of testimony about a married
life filled with terror and abuse.
   He beat her because the pork chops she cooked were too dry. He
slugged her in the stomach while she was pregnant because she
burned the toast, then apologized with flowers.
   Neighbors said they watched _ horrified but too terrified of
Jack to call police _ as he ordered one pleading child to do 100
push-ups on hot cement and shoved a running garden hose down the
throat of another.
   ``If he told me I was stupid, I believed it. If he told me he
would kill me, I believed it. If he opened the door and said `Go,'
I wouldn't, for fear he'd stab me in the back on my way out,''
Robin said in an interview published in Tuesday's Los Angeles
Times. ``I was a robot.''
   Prosecutors were appalled by the jury's vote, but defense
attorneys hailed the decision, saying jurors are ready to accept
the battered wife defense.
   ``Is this a signal that men who get frustrated by the actions of
their wives can kill them? That whenever we get frustrated with
someone we are entitled to exact the ultimate sentence _ death?''
asked Denis Petty, deputy district attorney.
   The law requires an ``imminent danger'' to justify a killing in
self-defense. Prosecutors insist that was not the case when Robin
shot and killed her husband.
   ``She could have left the state, gone to a neighbor, called the
police. He was asleep when the first shot was fired. He wasn't
posing any threat. And when we start allowing citizens to take
matters into their own hands, we are back to the law of the
jungle,'' Petty said.
   Robin tried twice to escape, and both times Jack found her.
   After the second time he found her, he promised to reform. But
when they returned home, he took away her check-cashing card and
house key, quit his job, and never left the house without one of
the children. He often took the telephone with him.
   ``It's like the scientific experiment where they shocked dogs to
the point that even when the gate was left open, the dogs never
left,'' defense attorney Lynda Vitale said. ``The dogs saw the open
gate not as a means of escape, but an invitation to more
punishment.''
   Neighbors said Jack and his little sister were raised in the
house that he later inherited from his two alcoholic parents. While
they were growing up, Jack and his sister were often thrown against
the wall by their parents, or left alone at night while they went
out for a night of drinking.
   When Jack got big enough, he began beating his mother. Sounds of
violence from the house were common. The sounds continued after
Robin moved in.
   Neighbors reported hearing the children shouting, ``Please,
Daddy, don't.''
   ``I knew what he was like. I tried not to irritate him. I was
scared to death of that man,'' said longtime neighbor Nola De
Martino, 74.
   Robin and her family now live in a two-bedroom apartment in Long
Beach. She has put on 25 pounds and is trying to stop smoking. The
entire family is undergoing extensive therapy, the Times said.
   De Martino can see the Elson house from her kitchen window.
   ``I cry about it and I pray about it,'' she said. ``I even
prayed for Jack that he wouldn't go to hell. But I don't know how
he couldn't.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>