<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1051EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SomaliaCameras     12-30 0280</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Somalia Cameras,0289</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cameras Unwelcome in Somalia</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Somalia, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOGADISHU, Somalia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   This Horn of Africa nation, one of the
poorest in the world, is not a great place for tourists. Especially
those with cameras.
   Take a snapshot on a Mogadishu street and there's a good chance
your camera and film will be confiscated by police.
   It is all part of the elaborate security system established by
President Mohammed Siad Barre in his 20 years of authoritarian rule.
   An Associated Press reporter who recently interviewed the
president inside his walled, heavily guarded compound in Mogadishu
asked aides if he could be accompanied by a local photographer.
   ``Well, it's all highly complicated,'' said one. ``We'd have to
get clearance from the Board of Censors and that could take some
time. Maybe we can get the presidential press unit to take a
picture.''
   The presidential press unit didn't, although it taped the
interview on a high-quality, reel-to-reel recording machine,
apparently to be sure the quotes were accurate.
   At another interview with a lesser government official, an
unidentified man seated himself next to the reporter, took notes
and disputed the journalist's use of certain words in framing his
questions.
   He was from state security, the reporter was told later. Seems
the official being interviewed had spoken too frankly to a West
German television crew a few months earlier and was now being
monitored.
   A visiting Yugoslav journalist, Rosa Grce of the Zagreb
newspaper Vjesnik, complained to an Information Ministry official
that she couldn't even find postcards depicting Mogadishu scenes.
   ``All I find are pictures that could have been taken anywhere in
Africa,'' she said.
   ``This is Africa,'' said the official.
</TEXT>

</DOC>