<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0247 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2223EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s f BC-Eastern-Thumbnails Adv24   12-21 0423</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Eastern-Thumbnails, Adv 24,0436</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv24</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Sunday, Dec. 24</HEAD>
<HEAD>With BC-Eastern-Then and Now</HEAD>
<HEAD>Major Players in the Eastern Airlines Drama</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are brief profiles of some of the major
players in the Eastern Airlines strike and bankruptcy proceeding,
which began in early March:
   _FRANK LORENZO: Powerful chairman of Texas Air Corp., owner of
Eastern and Continental Airlines, denounced as a ``robber baron''
by unions and considered an airline industry pioneer by some.
   _PHIL BAKES: President of Miami-based Eastern, reporting to
Lorenzo. A former attorney for the Civil Aeronautics Board, he was
influential in drawing up the 1978 law deregulating the U.S.
airline industry.
   _CHARLES BRYAN: Leader of the Machinists union at Eastern, known
before the strike for his fiery temper and fierce opposition to
management, who adopted a low public profile after the walkout
began.
   _JACK BAVIS: Former head of Eastern pilots union, thrown out by
the membership in September for proposing that they consider ending
their strike. He was replaced by Skip Copeland, a hard-liner on the
strike.
   The pilots reversed their position shortly before Thanksgiving
and voted to call off their walkout, which had been in sympathy
with the Machinists' wage dispute. The Eastern flight attendants
union, headed by MARY JANE BARRY, quickly followed suit.
   _BURTON R. LIFLAND: The U.S. bankruptcy judge overseeing
Eastern's Chapter 11 proceeding that began March 9 in federal court
in New York. A powerful judge known for biting sarcasm, he took an
aggressive approach to his goal of getting Eastern flying again.
   _DAVID I. SHAPIRO: The special bankruptcy examiner appointed by
Lifland to mediate between Eastern management and unions and to
investigate the financial history of Eastern, its sister carrier
Continental and their parent Texas Air. A street-smart Washington
attorney, he has participated in cases ranging from prostitution to
freedom of speech.
   _PETER V. UEBERROTH: Former baseball commissioner, who made a
$464 million bid to buy Eastern from Lorenzo in April. He had
extensive negotiations with Eastern's unions, which agreed to labor
concessions in exchange for a 30 percent share in the airline. But
the deal collapsed when the unions insisted on a trustee to replace
Lorenzo before Ueberroth took over, and Lorenzo refused.
   _JOSEPH RITCHIE: Chicago businessman and quixotic bidder for
Eastern, who made a bid in early May in alliance with the unions.
Lifland removed the buyout plan from consideration and Lorenzo
dismissed it as a ``joke''.
   _JOEL ZWEIBEL: Lead attorney for the committee representing
Eastern's major unsecured creditors, such as aircraft manufacturers.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Sunday, Dec. 24</NOTE>

</DOC>