<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0233 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1838EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-MergerActivity 1stLd-Writethru   12-29 0585</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Merger Activity, 1st Ld-Writethru,0601</SECOND>
<HEAD>Once-Booming Takeover Business Ends the Decade Quietly</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf, to CORRECT one less deal to two fewer deals.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOYCE M. ROSENBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The once-raucous takeover business ended the
1980s subdued and humbled as the value of corporate acquisitions
plunged more than 60 percent in the fourth quarter from the
stratospheric levels of a year earlier.
   There were 935 acquisitions valued at $72.2 billion announced
during the last quarter of 1989. A year earlier, when the merger
business reached its zenith with the record $24.53 billion buyout
of RJR Nabisco Inc., there were two fewer deals, 933, but the
acquisitions totaled a record $183.1 billion.
   Leveraged buyouts, the debt-financed deals so popular a year
ago, dropped even more sharply. There were 22 LBOs announced during
the fourth quarter of 1989, totaling $15.5 billion _ down 85
percent from the 49 deals worth $102.2 billion in the last quarter
of 1988.
   The figures, compiled by the financial research firm Securities
Data Corp., were unsurprising. The takeover business has been
devastated over the past year by the failure of Campeau Corp.'s
$6.6 billion buyout of Federated Department Stores Inc. and the
subsequent collapse of the market in junk bonds, the high-interest
securities used to finance many buyouts.
   The enthusiasm that takeover strategists and their bankers once
displayed was replaced by caution in 1989. Over the year, 1,447
purchases of U.S. businesses worth a total of $362.7 billion were
announced, down 29 percent in value from the 1,543 acquisitions
worth $511.5 billion in 1988.
   Securities Data considered transactions worth $10 million or
more in compiling its figures.
   The 1989 record of Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Co., the company
that bought RJR Nabisco, is an illustration of how times have
changed.
   In 1988, Kohlberg Kravis, considered the leader among leveraged
buyout firms, announced four transactions worth $27.88 billion.
Excluding RJR Nabisco, the company's other deals totaled $3.35
billion.
   But in 1989, Kohlberg Kravis participated in one deal worth just
$310 million, the buyout of several small divisions of Macmillan
Inc.
   Kohlberg Kravis likely adopted the same cautious stance that
other prospective acquirers have had to take.
   Ruth Pachman, a spokeswoman for the firm, declined to say that
Kohlberg Kravis had become more conservative. However, she said,
``They're not going to do a deal for the sake of doing a deal.''
   Kohlberg Kravis, although buoyed by the stellar performance of
RJR Nabisco this year, has had to contend with financial problems
at some of its smaller units that may have put a crimp into some of
its acquisition plans.
   Earlier this week, Hillsborough Holdings Corp., formed as part
of Kohlberg Kravis' takeover of homebuilder Jim Walter Corp., filed
for federal bankruptcy court protection.
   Another Kohlberg Kravis company, Seaman Furniture Co. has been
forced to reschedule its debt payments, and a third company, SCI
Television Inc. also is trying to renegotiate its debt.
   The slowdown in takeovers also was evident in financing of deals
and merchant banking activity, Securities Data said.
   There were 67 junk bond offerings raising a total of $14.1
billion in 1989, with $4 billion of that amount attributable to
just one deal, the RJR Nabisco buyout. In 1988, there were 90 junk
bond offerings that raised $16.4 billion, Securities Data said.
   Meanwhile, major investment banks participated directly in 82
deals worth $24.8 billion this past year. In 1988, there were 83
such transactions, but they totaled $95.5 billion, far
outdistancing the 1989 total.
</TEXT>

</DOC>