<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0148 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1946EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Salvador-Senators     12-18 0344</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Salvador-Senators,0353</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Senators Believe Government is Seeking Jesuit Killers</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Salvador-Christmas</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN SALVADOR, El Salvador (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two U.S. senators met rightist
President Alfredo Cristiani on Monday and asserted that his
government is committed to finding out who massacred six Jesuit
priests.
   Dennis DeConcini of Arizona and Bob Graham of Florida, both
Democrats, told a news conference they expected continued U.S.
support for El Salvador. However, DeConcini said it was possible
aid would be cut off if the investigation shows military
involvement in the Nov. 16 killings.
   The slayings of the leadership of the Jesuit-run Central
American University prompted some U.S. legislators to call for
reappraisal of the $1.5 million in aid that Washington provides
daily to El Salvador.
   The Roman Catholic Church and the Jesuits have concluded
military men were almost certainly responsible for the massacre of
the Jesuits, their housekeeper and her daughter. A witness has
testified she saw men in army uniforms near the priests' on-campus
residence shortly before the fatal shots were heard.
   ``We believe President Cristiani and military leaders are
prepared to have any and all outside assistance to certify the
exhaustiveness and thoroughness of the investigtion wherever it
leads, including if it leads to the military,'' said DeConcini.
   FBI and Scotland Yard investigators, as well as detectives from
Spain, are collaborating in the inquiry.
   DeConcini said he would be ``flabbergasted'' if the
investigation found high-level military responsibility. He said if
such involvement were proven, a cutoff in U.S. aid ``would
certainly be a possibility.''
   If a small armed forces contingent acting on its own is found to
be responsible, an aid cutoff ``would still be a possibility, but
not very likely,'' he said.
   ``If the government continues its forceful and aggressive
investigation, support in Congress will be maintained,'' DeConcini
said.
   The Salvadoran government has offered a reward of $250,000 for
information leading to the prosecution of those responsible for the
massacre.
   The Jesuits were killed during a renewed offensive by leftist
guerrillas trying to overthrow the government. Right-wing forces
often view church people as guerrilla allies.
</TEXT>

</DOC>