<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1200EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Philippines     12-24 0309</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines,0319</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shots Fired at U.S. Library in Philippines</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three armed men opened fire on the
U.S. Information Service library in Davao City on Sunday,
shattering windows but causing no injuries, police reported.
   Sgt. Rommel Moya said the gunmen escaped after shooting from a
speeding car about 1:15 p.m. The library was closed at the time,
Moya said.
   There was no indication who was responsible for the shooting.
Communist rebels operate in Davao City, 600 miles southeast of
Manila.
   But government troops have been on alert in the Davao area
because of reports that military mutineers who tried to topple
President Corazon Aquino earlier this month were planning attacks
in the Davao area.
   The mutineers were angered when U.S. warplanes flew air cover
missions to support government forces Dec. 1, the first day of the
failed coup. Although they did not fire, the U.S. jets helped turn
the tide in the battle.
   The military said Saturday that five private shooting clubs
associated with the son of Sen. Juan Ponce Enrile, were involved in
the failed coup.
   The Philippine Constabulary said about 100 civilian members of
the clubs were identified through photographs and videotapes as
having fought alongside military mutineers who launched the coup
attempt.
   The shooting clubs are part of the Philippine Tactical Shooting
Association, an umbrella organization headed by Juan ``Jackie''
Ponce Enrile Jr., son of the former defense minister and lone
opposition member of the Senate, the constabulary said.
   The statement did not specifically name the younger Enrile as
among those members taking part in the coup attempt.
   The elder Enrile has denied involvement in the coup attempt,
believed to have been led by a clique of officers associated with
him when he served as Mrs. Aquino's defense chief.
   Enrile was fired in November 1986 after a failed coup by his
followers.
</TEXT>

</DOC>