<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0137 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1921EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Rushdie     12-18 0524</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rushdie,0543</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lawyer Says Four Iranians Suspected of Being Rushdie `Hit Squad'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MANCHESTER, England (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four Iranians being held by police
under the Prevention of Terrorism Act believe they are suspected of
plotting to kill author Salman Rushdie, their lawyer said Monday.
   The three students and a disabled father of four were arrested
Friday at their homes in Manchester, police said. Under the act,
suspects can be held seven days without charge.
   ``The police have told me very little, but the men are under the
impression they have been arrested because they are suspected of
being a hit squad to kill Salman Rushdie,'' attorney Zahir Aziz
said.
   Moslems worldwide have mounted protests against the British
author and his novel, ``The Satanic Verses.'' The Indian-born
Rushdie was condemned to death Feb. 14 by the late Iranian leader
Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini, who accused him of blaspheming Islam
in his novel.
   Rushdie has been in hiding ever since under police protection.
   Friday's arrests put in jeopardy tentative steps to improve
Anglo-Iranian relations and restore diplomatic links severed over
the Rushdie affair.
   The detainees' lawyer identified the students as Karen Abrinia,
32; Mehrdad Kokabi, 33; and Hussein Gharibi. No age was immediately
available for Gharibi.
   The attorney asked that the fourth man, 40-year-old Javad
Mousavi, who suffers from multiple sclerosis, be moved from his
police cell to a hospital.
   A Manchester police spokeswoman, who spoke on condition of
anonymity, refused to say why the suspects were detained.
   However, she said the detentions were not connected to the U.S.
State Department's warning last week of a possible terrorist attack
on a U.S. target in Western Europe or West Africa.
   Patrick Stephenson, registrar at the University of Manchester
Institute of Science and Technology, said Kokabi and Abrinia were
engineering students who had completed their course work for doctor
of philosophy degrees and were writing dissertations. It was not
known where Gharibi studies.
   Iran's official Islamic Republic News Agency on Friday quoted
the Iranian newspaper Kayhan as saying the arrests followed
demonstrations by Moslems in more than 1,000 mosques throughout
Britain against Rushdie.
   Press Association, Britain's domestic news agency, said police
activity in Manchester is believed to have intensified following a
stormy meeting there on Oct. 21 to celebrate the birthday of the
Islamic prophet Mohammed. At that session, hard-line Moslems voted
overwhelmingly to support the call for Rushdie's execution.
   Kayhan was quoted as saying police broke into the homes of the
four Iranians ``without producing any legal warrants, and, after
the unauthorized search of their homes, forcibly took them into
custody.''
   The Manchester police spokeswoman refused to comment when asked
about the warrants.
   English-born Dawn Mousavi said police came to the family's home
in Manchester on Friday afternoon and arrested her husband.
   ``We were kept in the kitchen for two hours while the police
searched the house. They took away personal papers like letters and
even bank books. They turned everything upside down and took the
floorboards up,'' she said.
   ``Javad is innocent. I don't know why he is detained. He is not
a politically active person _ although we both support the Iranian
government,'' Mrs. Mousavi said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>