<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0109 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1559EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania 1stLd-Writethru 0598 12-27 1209</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania, 1st Ld - Writethru, 0598, </SECOND>
<HEAD>Officials Declare Romania No Longer Communist</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: UPDATES throughout with report on eagerness of firing squad;
raises Mazilu quotes, minor editing.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos BUC1,2; PAR6</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MORT ROSENBLUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A top official declared Wednesday that
Romania is no longer a Communist country, and revolutionary leaders
tried to stop citizens from waging a ``witch hunt'' of revenge
against supporters of the old regime.
   Security police still loyal to executed leader Nicolae Ceausescu
attacked the television building in the capital early Wednesday but
were repulsed in a half-hour firefight, news reports said.
   The television building is the headquarters of the provisional
government headed by new President Ion Iliescu, who on Wednesday
spoke with Mikhail S. Gorbachev and expressed his thanks for the
Soviet leader's support. The men are friends from their college
days in Moscow.
   Dumitru Mazilu, vice chairman of the National Salvation
Committee provisional government, reaffirmed that the new leaders
are devoted to replacing Ceausescu's 24-year Stalinist despotism
with democracy.
   The government has said free elections will be held in April.
   ``We want Romania to become a member of the free civilized
world,'' Mazilu said. ``Romania is no longer a Communist country.
Romania is a free land, and we will create a real democracy.''
   But the revolutionary government still is fighting a guerrilla
war with Ceausescu loyalists, although the battles are waning.
   Romanian news reports said security police were holding out in
``isolated positions'' in other parts of the country, but army
forces backing the revolt were for the most part in control.
   Trying to heal the wounds of Romania's revolution, the interim
leadership offered the possibility of lenient penalties to
Ceausescu's security forces if they surrendered.
   But there were suggestions those who did not give up could face
the same fate as the Ceausescus, who were reported executed by
firing squad on Monday.
   According to a communique read on Bucharest Radio, security
police members have until Thursday afternoon to surrender or
they'll be ``tried and condemned'' by special tribunals.
   ``If they surrender voluntarily, with their weapons, they will
be tried and the death penalty will not be applied,'' the
communique said.
   Loyalist Ceausescu forces have been launching their attacks in
Bucharest from a maze of tunnels built by the dictator for the
feared security police.
   On Wednesday night, Romanian TV showed nervous soldiers combing
the tunnels in search of members of the security police, known as
the Securitate.
   The soldiers found bottles of whiskey, radio equipment, food and
weapons caches, and at least one gas mask _ but no security police.
The army troops kicked open doors leading to small rooms in the
tunnels.
   At one point, a young soldier tipped back his helmet and wiped
his brow after forcing his way into one of the rooms. His
frightened expression reflected Romanians' fear of the Securitate.
   Unconfirmed reports have said Ceausescu's police have walked
into hospitals hiding knives to carry out acts of terrorism, and
poisoned village wells.
   There have been reports that Securitate forces have been
surrendering en masse after battling army units backing the
revolution and armed citizens. However, there have been no figures
on how many Ceausescu loyalists have given up.
   Elsewhere, Romanian TV on Wednesday showed workers taking down
Communist Party signs and slogans from buildings in Bucharest.
   Corneliu Bogdan, Romania's new deputy foreign minister, said
that while bureaucrats who worked for years under Ceausescu still
are in positions of power, the new government wants a clean,
peaceful break with the past.
   ``They are not all criminals, they were at the most too servile
and obedient. We must try to avoid a witch hunt at any costs,'' he
said.
   The governing committee headed by Iliescu, a former Communist
Party secretary ousted for challenging Ceausescu, is made up of
dissidents, intellectuals and disaffected army commanders and
former government officials.
   In their conversation, Iliescu told Gorbachev the situation in
Romania was returning to normal and that 90 percent of the
factories were back at work, the Soviet news agency Tass said. It
said Iliescu thanked Gorbachev for a resolution passed by Soviet
lawmakers expressing support for the revolution at a time when its
outcome was in doubt.
   The National Salvation Committee named a new foreign minister,
university professor Sergiu Celac, 58. His predecessor, Ion Stoian,
has been ousted with Ceausescu's ruling cabal.
   Relief flights were arriving in Romania as the country struggled
to recover from nearly two weeks of upheaval. At Bucharest airport,
more than 40 relief aircraft had arrived by Wednesday.
   ``There is even too much aid,'' said Bernard Kouchner, French
minister for humanitarian affairs. ``We have to decide what is
needed and then coordinate.''
   The revolution began with a protest in the western town of
Timisoara on Dec. 15, and escalated into huge demonstrations in
which thousands are believed to have been slain.
   Thousands were reported massacred by troops in Timisoara and
dumped into mass graves. During his trial, Ceausescu was accused of
being responsible for the killing of 60,000 people during his
24-year reign.
   Ceausescu fled his palace Friday after army units joined the
revolt. Since then, the revolutionary government has been fighting
urban guerrilla attacks by secret police. He was captured Saturday.
   President Bush said he was ``amazed'' at the changes that have
taken place in Romania. ``We did say we were concerned that the
trial of Ceausescu should have been more open, but that's their
matter,'' he said.
   Petre Roman, the country's new interim prime minister, defended
the secret trial and quick executions of Ceausescu and his wife,
Elena.
   ``We were in circumstances which did not permit us to wait
longer in a situation of instability. There were pressures. We had
information concerning possible attacks on the place where he
was,'' Roman told French TV.
   Roman previously has said there had been indications secret
police were making plans to try to free Ceausescu.
   At the once-prestigious university library, 500,000 volumes,
including some precious manuscripts, were burned in a fire sparked
by the fighting.
   But at the National Library, the only books destroyed were six
long shelves of the works of Ceausescu: pages upon pages of his
revised Stalinist socialism.
   From the first signs of Ceausescu's forced departure Friday,
staff members began baling the dusty volumes to be destroyed.
   ``No one ever read this stuff, no one,'' said Virgil Tiberiu
Spanu, director of acquisitions. ``Never.''
   Romanians were exultant Wednesday after state TV showed the
Ceausescus being tried, as well as photos of the couple lying dead
next to a bullet-riddled wall.
   The firing squad was eager to execute the couple, according to a
man who said he was on the tribunal that tried the Ceausescus.
   ``We weren't even able to film (the execution) because the
soldiers lost control, they could no longer wait to fire,'' the man
told the network FR3 in from Bucharest. He declined to give his
name but who appeared to be the same man who was shown on Romanian
TV with Iliescu last week.
   Bogdan Lazaraen, a 21-year-old engineering student, shook his
head when asked about the executions.
   ``A week ago he was screaming at us and calling us fascists and
terrorists,'' he said. ``And now to see him lying in some obscure
place, shot.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>