<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0216 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1326EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--Millennium Adv31-2Takes   12-18 1153</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Millennium, Adv 31-2 Takes,1184</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 31</HEAD>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<HEAD>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 2 b&amp;w photos,
1 graphic. ColorFoto subscribers get 1 35mm slide.)</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Tomorrow, for most Christians, becomes Jan. 1,
1900, the end of a decade. Ten years hence marks the end of the
millennium. But hold on a second. Says who? One man's millennium is
another man's humdrum day. The way years get numbered, you see,
depends on who's counting, when they began counting and what
they're counting.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By SID MOODY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Newsfeatures Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Repent, brothers and sisters, repent! The millennium is coming.
   Kind of.
   Kind of because this small planet does not, most decidedly, spin
to the same calendar. Worldwide there are at least 40 of them, each
marching to its own drummer.
   But just 10 years from New Year's Day, Christians will rip a
page off the calendar and Saturday 12-31-1999 will become Sunday
1-1-2000, the zeros lined up like cherries in a slot machine, like
a milestone 100,000 miles on the family clunker. (Killjoys say the
millennium really is 1-1-2001 because we count from one, not zero,
so 2000 is really the 10th year of the 1990s. Disregard them).
   But one man's millennium is another's numberless day at the
office. Moslems will uncelebrate the middle of 1420 A.H., Jews 5761
A.M. Ancient Greeks will observe the 694th Olympiad.
   Olympiad?
   The way years get numbered, you see, depends on who's counting,
when they began counting and WHAT they're counting. If you count by
the moon _ Moslems do _ a year is 12 lunar months based on 29 days,
12 hours, 44 minutes and 2.8 seconds from new moon to new moon. The
solar year is about 11 days longer, the 365 days, 5 hours, 48
minutes and 46 seconds it takes Earth to circle the sun. Eventually
by the Moslem calendar it's June in January. But who decided it's
January in January anyway?
   To begin with, the calendar is a convenience to mark the passage
of time. It tells you when it's time to move the sheep into the
hills, when to report for spring training, when to plant cotton,
when to pay bills, when to get married next Saturday and celebrate
the anniversary of such 10 years hence.
   Ancients just chased mastodons whenever they could find them and
didn't worry about dates until they settled down and began planting
crops. For that you had to know seasons. The clock of the heavenly
bodies in their unalterable cycles told them.
   The Egyptians knew the Nile was about to flood when Sirius, the
Dog Star, was on the horizon at sunrise. Plant. Australian
aborigines know it's time to hunt termites when Arcturus is on the
horizon at dawn. Eat.
   The Sumerians and Babylonians, first-rate farmers and no
dummies, had a good calendar. But it was based on the moon and
pretty soon you're planting wheat in December with predictable
results.
   ``The year hath a deficiency,'' would declare Hammurabi, the
great lawgiver, as he threw in an extra month. We call such
doctoring intercalation.
   The Babylonians also invented the week, maybe because seven was
their lucky number, maybe because it conveniently divided the
lunation into quarters. The Jews later reinvented the week based on
the seven days of Creation.
   Somewhere along the line Sunday became the first day because the
sun gave life. Saturday, at week's end, comes from the Roman god
Saturn who presided over old age. Old-time Teutons also named days
for gods such as Wodan, Thor and Fria. Guess what became of them.
   In Yemen the day begins when you can tell a white goat hair from
a black one. Moslems begin a month when holy men first report a
sighting of the new crescent moon. If it's overcast, they wait a
day and start counting again.
   ``The Mursi in southwest Ethiopia spend most of the month
arguing about what day it is. They spend the rest arguing about
what month it is,'' says LeRoy Doggett, editor of the Nautical
Almanac in Washington, D.C.
   ``If you don't have to catch a plane, the date may not really
matter.''
   The Soviets, in the flush of communist creation, tried a
five-day week in 1919, went to six days in 1932 and returned to
tradition in 1941. They also celebrate the October Revolution in
November, which we'll get to.
   The ancient Egyptians switched from the Babylonian moon to a
12-month solar calendar of 30 days each and tagged on five holidays
at year's end. In 238 B.C., Ptolemy III, also no dummy, put in a
leap day after checking with Sirius to make up for the fraction of
a day left over from 365 days in orbit.
   Meanwhile, in Rome, the Romans did as the Romans. Romulus,
co-founder of the city, devised a 10-month calendar of 304 days.
Winter months were ``useless'' and not counted. The year began in
Aprilis, from Latin ``to open,'' at the time of the equinox of
equal night and day.
   Romulus's successor, King Numa, added Januarius and Februarius
and came up with a 12-month calendar of 365 days. Not bad, but
still out of tune, made more so by high priests who were not above
subtracting a month to collect taxes sooner or adding some to
extend friends' terms of office.
   What with one thing or another, by the time of Julius Caesar the
calendar was three months out of phase with the sun. Caesar hired
the Egyptian astronomer Sosigenes. He added three months, just like
that, to 46 B.C. producing a year of 445 days and what justly
became known as ``the year of confusion.''
   This Julian calendar had the requisite 365 days, plus a leap
every third year. Caesar's birth month of Quintilis was renamed in
his honor. Guess where July comes from. Augustus Caesar fine-tuned
things by making leap year every fourth year. In HIS honor the
month of Sextilils was named for him _ by now you must know where
August comes from _ and a day was added to it to make 31 and not be
outshone by 31-day Julius. The Julian calendar was OK but lagged 14
seconds a year or one day every 128 years.
   But which year was it?
   The Romans started counting from Romulus and Remus, year one
being 753 A.U.C. _ anno urbis conditae, the year the city was
founded. The Jews toted up the begats and counted from Creation,
3761 B.C., before Christ to Christians, A.M. _ anno mundi, year of
the world _ to Jews. The Greeks counted in four-year periods _
Olympiads _ starting with 776 B.C. when Coraebus won the first
Olympic foot race. The Japanese counted from the first emperor _
660 B.C. _ and the Chinese from the first year of whatever dynasty
they were in. The Mohammadans weren't there yet.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>