<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0243EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-PanamaPrisoners     12-21 0319</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama Prisoners,250</SECOND>
<HEAD>Most Captured Panamanians Cooperating</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The following was compiled from pool reports
filed from Panama City by Steven Komarow of The Associated Press,
Robert Kearns of Reuters, Dick Thompson of Time Magazine, Kevin
Merida of The Dallas Morning News; Kathy Lewis of The Houston Post
and Bill Clayton of the Houston Chronicle.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Most of the 150 captured Panamanians
being held in an automobile storage lot were cooperating as U.S.
military officers tried to determine which of them were civilians
caught up in combat and which were POWs.
   The prisoners made a forlorn-looking group Wednesday as they
stood in the lot under a broiling sun. Some prisoners wore military
fatigues; others wore casual civilian clothes such as T-shirts and
shorts. Most were shirtless.
   Staff Sgt. Phillip Salcido of Las Cruces, N.M., said some were
in fact civilians caught up in combat, and officers were
questioning them to determine who could be released.
   The lot, holding brand-new Japanese and Korean cars, was
surrounded by razor-sharp concertina wire.
   Though Salcido said most prisoners were cooperating, some
squabbled over cooperating with their questioners. An MP broke up
one apparent fight that Salcido said might have been planned as a
diversion for an attack on guards.
   In a remark he took back immediately, Salcido quipped that a
prisoner cooperates or ``accidents happen.''
   One prisoner called out to another, in Spanish, ``Speak Spanish
to them.''
   ``All of them are being given every right under the Geneva
convention,'' said a military police captain.
   Officers said refugees from the fighting were being taken to
Balboa Stadium, the city's largest sports complex. ``The POWs,
though, they will remain with us,'' said one officer.
   Reporters were not permitted to talk with the prisoners, nor
were they flown over the city or permitted to go to one of the
objectives of the attack because of concern over sniper fire.
</TEXT>

</DOC>