<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0223 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0232EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-KodakRebates Bjt   12-21 0608</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Kodak Rebates, Bjt,0629</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kodak Makes Last Payments for Instant Camera Rebates</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HILARY APPELMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ROCHESTER, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As Eastman Kodak Co. waits to hear how
much it will be penalized for violating Polaroid Corp.'s instant
camera patents 13 years ago, the company is making its last
payments to customers who bought Kodak's instant models.
   Kodak was forced to stop making and selling instant cameras and
film in 1986 after a federal judge ruled that the Rochester-based
photographic company infringed on seven Polaroid patents.
   Since then, Kodak has paid about $108 million in cash to 3.5
million consumers who bought the company's instant cameras from
1976 to 1986, plus issued them $89 million worth of rebate coupons
on other Kodak products.
   ``It is probably the most successful outreach program to
consumers ever,'' said Chicago attorney Burton I. Weinstein, who
represented camera owners in a class action lawsuit against Kodak.
   ``That's the best return that I've ever heard of,'' said Beverly
Moore, editor of Class Action Reports in Washington, D.C.
   Kodak had sold 16.5 million instant cameras in the United States
by the time Polaroid won its suit. The courts have not yet ruled
how much Kodak will have to pay Polaroid, which is based in
Cambridge, Mass., but stock analysts predict it will be in the $1
billion to $2 billion range.
   Kodak has insisted it should pay only $177 million, or 5 percent
royalties on the instant cameras and film it sold.
   Final arguments in the penalty phase of the trial were filed
Wednesday in U.S. District Court in Boston.
   Camera owners filed a class action suit against Kodak after the
company proposed a settlement with them that did not include cash.
   Attorneys for Kodak and the claimants worked out a settlement
that instead gave each camera owner a cash refund of $19 to $52,
plus rebate coupons worth $18 to $30 for use on Kodak products. The
coupons must be used by Dec. 31 and submitted to Kodak by Jan. 31,
1990.
   Both sides say the settlement process has gone extremely
smoothly.
   ``It's incredible what was accomplished by the efforts of people
who were literally at each other's throats _ Kodak and us,''
Weinstein said. ``Once there was a settlement, Kodak worked
extremely hard to make sure people got compensated.''
   Of the possible claimants, 3.8 million filed claims, 3.4 million
of which were approved, said William J. Campbell, who represented
Kodak in the settlement.
   ``My client spent a heck of a lot of money'' to advertise the
settlement nationwide, he said. ``They went more than the
distance.''
   Weinstein estimated that Kodak spent about $200 million overall
on the settlement, including advertising and attorneys' fees.
Administrative and legal costs were less than 10 percent of the
total, he said.
   Moore called it ``extraordinary'' that nearly 25 percent of the
possible claimants filed claims, particularly since as long as 10
years had elapsed since some people bought their cameras.
   Kodak could not say how many of the coupons have been used.
Spokesman Paul Allen said the company estimated it would spend $42
million to redeem the coupons.
   Kodak expects many of the rebate coupons will be used during the
Christmas season.
   Claimants were divided into four groups according to how much
their cameras cost. People in all but the group that owned the most
expensive instant cameras got back more cash than they originally
spent to buy the camera, Campbell said. All the claimants got more
than the resale value of their used cameras, he said.
   Even if the claimants didn't use their rebate coupons, Weinstein
said, ``they're way ahead of the game.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>