<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0161 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 2007EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e AM-APArts:Mehta Adv01   12-27 0743</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-AP Arts: Mehta, Adv 01,0772</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv 01</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Mon AMs, Jan 1 and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Strauss Meets Buffalo Bill</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY CAMPBELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Brahms loved Buffalo Bill's Wild West shows when
they played in Vienna and so, presumes conductor Zubin Mehta, did
Johann Strauss Sr. At any rate, Strauss composed ``Indian Maidens
Galop'' and Mehta will conduct the work with the Vienna
Philharmonic on New Year's Day.
   ``From Vienna: the New Year's Celebration 1990,'' Vienna's
traditional New Year's concert of effervescent Strauss music, will
be televised on Jan. 1 at 2:30 p.m. EST by PBS.
   ``There is such an output by the Strauss family, taking Johann
Strauss Jr. and Sr., cousins and uncles, we can go on for 10 years
of concerts without repeating a single piece,'' said Mehta, who was
born in India.
   However ``The Blue Danube Waltz'' and ``Radetzky March'' will be
repeated. They're played every year.
   ``The accent is on Vienna in this year's program,'' said Mehta,
who has never conducted a New Year's concert in Vienna. ``I'm doing
an overture, by Franz von Suppe, to `Morning, Noon and Night in
Vienna.''' Also on the program is Mehta's favorite by Strauss,
``Vienna Blood,'' which he has often presented as an encore when he
conducted the Vienna Philharmonic.
   ``They used to ask the music director of the opera to do it.
They have come to another sort of a plan now; each year they want
to ask another one of their regular conductors to take over. Next
year will be somebody else.''
   In an interview at his office in Avery Fisher Hall, Mehta said
he has watched the concert on TV in the past and will in the
future. ``I think Johann Strauss is as classical as Mozart is. The
pieces are played too much and without the right style, which tends
to diminish the quality of this music. When played in the right
style, it is sheer pleasure. It is the kind of music, like Mozart,
that one feels there's not an extra note.
   ``This music reflects an age before the turn of the century when
Vienna was the cultural center of the world. It's the height of the
Hapsburg monarchy that it reflects.''
   Mehta, 53-year-old artistic director of both the New York
Philharmonic and Israel Philharmonic, conducted the Vienna
Philharmonic last year in Amsterdam but hasn't toured with it. ``I
can't be music director to two orchestras and tour with a third
one. That wouldn't be fair to any side.''
   Last year, Mehta told the New York Philharmonic that when his
contract expires in 1991, he won't renew, even though he believes
the New York Philharmonic is one of the greatest orchestras around
today.
   ``I feel after 13 years of my contributions here, somebody else
should take over now,'' he said. ``New York takes its toll on your
spirit. Nobody can work harder than I can. But 13 years of playing
20 programs a season takes its toll on your inner person.
   ``And one has to be honest with oneself and say, I like to be
free. I'm going to do a lot but I'm going to do what I want. I'm
planning my freedom. I'm planning more free time and I'm also
planning projects. The next person waiting to meet me now is the
director of the Chicago Lyric Opera. From 1993 I'll be doing a new
Ring cycle in Chicago.''
   He also plans to record more operas.
   The physical part of conducting doesn't tire Mehta. ``It is that
inexplicable love and drive that you have from within for the music
that makes you supersede all these material discomforts.''
   In Florence, when he conducted ``Gotterdammerung,'' the fourth
and last opera in Wagner's Ring cycle, he said, ``You come out of
the pit after conducting two hours. The longest Mahler symphony is
an hour and a half. You've got the second and third acts to look
forward to. And I can't wait for the second act to begin! For me
these Wagner pauses are necessary because of stage changes and the
singers have to rest. But I can't wait to go back.''
   Mehta planned to fly to Vienna the Wednesday before New Year's.
   ``This concert is carefully prepared,'' he said. ``Though it's
music that comes out of their blood, there are four rehearsals and
two previous concerts, one for the Army, one for the public, to
prepare for it.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv</NOTE>

</DOC>