<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1229EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Syria-Egypt     12-17 0446</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Syria-Egypt,0460</SECOND>
<HEAD>Egypt and Syria Try to Settle Rift</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DAMASCUS, Syria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Hafez Assad met Sunday with an
Egyptian government minister for the latest in a series of talks
aimed at ending a 10-year-old rift between the two major Arab
powers.
   Egyptian Information Minister Safwat al-Sharif was sent by
Egypt's president, Hosni Mubarak.
   Al-Sharif became the first Egyptian presidential emissary to
visit Demascus since Syria broke relations with Cairo in 1979 to
protest the late President Anwar Sadat's peace treaty with Israel.
The rift between the two Arab states has been a major stumbling
block to Arab unity.
   Assad's spokesman, Jibran Kourieh, said the Syrian president
will dispatch a personal envoy to Mubarak within the next few days.
   He said that during the meeting with al-Sharif, Assad
``expressed Syria's keenness to strengthen cooperation with Egypt
in various fields.''
   The Egyptian envoy, accompanied by senior officials of Cairo's
Foreign Ministry, delivered a letter from Mubarak to Assad, who in
turn gave Sharif a letter to deliver to Mubarak.
   The contents were not disclosed. But Sharif said when he arrived
at Damascus airport that the rapprochement that was started ``when
the two leaders met in Casablanca is continuing permanently, and we
are all witnessing the positive developments between the two
countries.''
   Assad and Mubarak met in the Moroccan city in May during an Arab
summit conference. They met twice in October and agreed to build
economic ties in agriculture, oil and industry.
   Sharif said, ``God willing, we hope to proceed forward on the
road of common Arab action and joint struggle through the mutual
understanding between presidents Mubarak and Assad.''
   Egypt was returned to the Arab fold after an Arab summit in 1987
gave the green light to restoring relations with Cairo. Since then
most of the Arab states that severed links in 1979 have resumed
them. Only radical Syria and Libya have yet to do so formally, but
both are now moving down that road.
   Last week, Mubarak and Assad agreed during a telephone
conversation to resume direct flights between Cairo and Damascus by
their national airlines.
   The first Egypt Air jetliner to touch down in Damascus in a
decade landed Tuesday, carrying Maj. Gen. Samir Rashad, Egypt's
deputy transport minister.
   Egypt and Libya restored air links in June and reopened their
border, closed since 1977 when they fought a five-day war.
   Mubarak has lately been acting as a key mediator between Israel,
the Palestine Liberation Organization and other Arab states in
trying to forge a Middle East peace settlement.
   Syria also is at odds with PLO Chairman Yasser Arafat and has
rejected his peace initiative toward Israel, a move strongly backed
by Egypt.
</TEXT>

</DOC>