<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0145 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1452EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-HospitalMortality Bjt   12-20 0784</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hospital Mortality, Bjt,790</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Reports Hospital Mortality Rates</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Mortality-List</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH MESCE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Death rates for Medicare patients were higher
in 1988 than federal projections at 3.4 percent of the nation's
nearly 6,000 hospitals, the government said Wednesday.
   Thirty-two hospitals, including six public hospitals in Puerto
Rico, have had higher-than-projected rates for three consecutive
years. Four had fewer deaths than projected during the same period,
officials said.
   However, federal health officials cautioned that the report ``is
not a direct measure of the quality of care'' and should not be
used to judge hospitals as good or bad.
   The report said 196 hospitals, or 3.4 percent of U.S. hospitals,
had higher-than-expected death rates in 1988.
   That compares with 194 such hospitals in 1987 and 187 in 1986,
according to revised figures. Data for those years were recomputed
to account for different risk factors added to the calculations of
the 1988 projections.
   At the other end of the scale, 51 hospitals, or 0.9 percent,
were found to have Medicare death rates lower than projected.
Applying the revised calculations, such hospitals numbered 48 in
1987 and 40 in 1986.
   Although the statistics were based solely on admissions of
Medicare patients, officials said they believe the rates are
reflective of the general population.
   The information in the third annual report on Medicare hospital
patient death rates was compiled by the Health Care Financing
Administration.
   Thomas Morford, director of the agency's health standards and
quality bureau, said it would be unfair and inaccurate to label the
facilities whose death rates were outside the projected ranges as
the nation's best or worst hospitals.
   ``This is not a one-to-one measure of quality of care,'' he said.
   Rather, the information is intended to be one indicator of
quality of care and consumers should use it to ask more informed
questions when assessing a hospital's strengths and weaknesses, he
said.
   The names of the 32 hospitals with repeatedly
higher-than-expected death rates were released with the caveat that
it ``does not necessarily mean that the care at these hospitals was
substandard nor that these hospitals are the poorest performing
acute care hospitals in the United States.''
   Twenty of the hospitals are public facilities, five are private
non-profit hospitals, three are private for-profit and four are run
by churches.
   The four hospitals with repeatedly lower rates included two
public hospitals and two private facilities, one for-profit and one
non-profit.
   Asked about the significance that six Puerto Rican hospitals,
more than any one state, have had repeatedly higher rates, Morford
said: ``At this point, I'm not drawing anything from anything. ...
Obviously we are going to make some inquiries as to the care at
(all 32) hospitals.''
   Morford said Martin Luther King Jr. General Hospital in Los
Angeles is an example of a hospital that consistently exceeded
projected death rates for Medicare patients but recently improved
conditions remarkably. The hospital was told last year that it
would no longer receive Medicare reimbursement unless improvements
were made.
   Though the Los Angeles hospital is on the list of 32, ``over the
past three months they have done extraordinary things to bring
themselves into compliance,'' Morford said.
   In comments included in the report, some hospitals took
exception to the agency's projected ranges, some noted data errors
and others said the ranges don't adequately reflect that many of
their patients are sicker when they arrive at the hospital and more
likely to die.
   For some hospitals, death rates were less than 1 percentage
point over the upper bound of the projected range.
   The financing agency, a unit of the Department of Health and
Human Services, said one of the studies it conducted using the
report's data indicates that large urban hospitals and publicly
owned hospitals are more likely to have quality problems and higher
death rates than other hospitals.
   As another measure of quality, officials said a study by agency
staff and researchers at the Medical Colleges of Wisconsin shows
that hospitals with a larger percentage of board-certified
physicians, registered nurses, higher payroll expenses and more
access to high-technology facilities are more likely to have lower
mortality rates.
   The hospital mortality report calculates the rates for all
causes of Medicare deaths as well as for each of 16 diagnostic
categories, including cancer, heart disease and stroke. It provides
such general information as the number of beds, interns, residents
and registered nurses, as well as the types of specialty services
offered.
   Medicare pays hospital and doctor bills for about 33 million
Americans who are over 65, blind or disabled.
  
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Eds: Copies of the report may be ordered from the Health Care
Financing Administration's health standards and quality bureau by
calling (301) 966-1133.
</TEXT>

</DOC>