<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1049EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Czechoslovakia-Havel     12-29 0742</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Czechoslovakia-Havel,0767</SECOND>
<HEAD>Czechoslovakia's Best-Known `Dissident' Elected President</HEAD>
<HEAD>With Czechoslovakia, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SYDNEY RUBIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vaclav Havel, the passionate
defender of human rights and eloquent philosopher of moral
resistance, was in jail just nine months ago for challenging the
Communist masters.
   On Friday, he was elected president of Czechoslovakia.
   The spontaneous revolution that carried Havel to the highest
post in the land could not have been more perfectly scripted if it
had been plotted by the 53-year-old playwright himself.
   One year to the day from Czechoslovakia's first legal
demonstration for human rights, the Communists lost their monopoly
on power.
   The appointment of the new reform government on Dec. 10 and the
simultaneous resignation of hard-line Communist President Gustav
Husak followed four weeks of mass pro-democracy protests and days
of negotiations between the Communists and the opposition, led by
Havel.
   Although sparked by the violent police crackdown on peaceful
student demonstrators Nov. 17, the revolution that toppled the
Communists was achieved without violence. Its weapon was the
enormous moral force which Havel has come to symbolize.
   The upheaval cast Havel into the leading role as head of the
opposition Civic Forum. But long before, he embodied for many
Czechoslovaks the individual's struggle for human dignity under
Communism.
   His trouble with authorities began in the Stalinist 1950s when
he was declared too bourgeois to attend high school because he came
from a family of well-known architects and entrepreneurs in
pre-Communist Czechoslovakia.
   He went to work in the theater where his play ``The Garden
Party'' brought him instant success in 1963.
   His essays, letters and manifestoes were a relentless attack
against tyranny. In his 1978 essay, ``The Power and The
Powerless,'' Havel powerfully describes how the Communist regimes
of the Soviet bloc sought to strangle independent thought.
   His unbending defense of liberty, which included signing the
human rights manifesto Charter 77, earned him a four-year jail
sentence in 1979.
   Even after release Havel was hounded, interrogated and followed
by secret police. His works were published and performed to wide
acclaim in the West and despite an official ban, his ideas
circulated at home through smuggled books and underground journals
and his popularity grew.
   Havel's work, especially the rich, poetic philosophical
meditations of his political essays, made him one of the leading
spokesmen for East European intellectuals.
   In an interview published in May by The Observer in London,
Havel reflected on the unique role of the writer under
totalitarianism.
   ``Where society cannot organize itself naturally and where
politics in the original sense of the word have been abolished,
everything becomes crypto-political or semi-political. Politics are
thrown out the door only to come back through the window,'' he said.
   ``Abolished as a specific form of activity, politics spread to
encompass a wide range of other pursuits.
   ``Everything from a rock group to a concert to a religious Mass
can become political. If a writer attempts to speak the truth all
his life, he too becomes a political phenomenon,'' he said.
   Havel's election _ becoming the first non-Communist president in
41 years _ revives Czechoslovakia's tradition of the philosopher
president dating to Tomas Garrigue Masaryk, the professor and
author who built the nation from the rubble of the Austro-Hungarian
empire in 1918.
   His countrymen look to Havel to create stability after the
recent upheaval and to encourage investment from the West.
   Havel sees his role as director, guiding the nation toward its
first free elections in 41 years.
   He has said he envisions a ``modern contemporary system which
would return to people their honor and freedom.''
   ``Politics really should be ethics put into practice,'' he has
said.
   After the first free multi-party parliamentary elections next
year, he would like to return to writing, leaving the nation in the
hands of a president elected by a new Parliament to serve a full
five-year term.
   In a letter written from his cell to Olga, his wife of 30 years,
and published in the collected ``Letters to Olga,'' he described
with his usual clarity the motivation which drives him today.
   ``There are times,'' he wrote, ``when an artist must put his art
aside in order to do something positive in life, something modest
that may not earn him a place in history but which is the
expression of a moral imperative or simply a love for people.''
   Czechoslovaks standing beneath the balcony of the presidential
castle looked up to Havel Friday and returned that love.
</TEXT>

</DOC>