<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 2334EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Romania-USReax     12-22 0544</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-US Reax,0560</SECOND>
<BYLINE>Apprehension Tempers Celebration by Romanians in U.S. ^By JOSEPH
NEFF</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 400 Romanian-Americans sipped champagne in
a rally to celebrate the downfall Friday of Romanian President
Nicolae Ceausescu, but their joy was tempered by continued
bloodshed in their homeland.
   ``I have mixed feelings about the overthrow,'' said Lumi Sava, a
rally organizer. ``It's extremely sad that so much innocent blood
was spilled _ women and children. It's a high price for freedom,
but's it's worth it.''
   Thousands of civilians have been reported killed in Romania
since the revolt against the last Soviet bloc dictator began Dec.
15 in the western city of Timisoara. Hundreds more reportedly died
Friday in the uprising that sent Ceausescu fleeing from the
presidential palace.
   In New York, demonstrators gathered in 12-degree cold across the
street from the Romanian mission to the United Nations, the same
spot where many of them have held nightly protests against
Ceausescu since the upheaval in their homeland began.
   The ralliers sipped champagne from plastic cups, waved red, blue
and yellow Romanian flags _ minus the socialist symbol _ and
chanted ``Victory, Victory.''
   Speakers addressed the crowd in Romanian and English, presenting
their demands for a completely new Romanian government. Sava called
on the U.S. government to send emergency medical and food aid to
Romania.
   ``Blood is especially needed _ we have heard that Ceausescu
bombed the blood bank and main hospital in Bucharest,'' she said.
   Sava said the coalition Romania 21 would ask the U.S. government
to seize the assets of the Romanian government in this country, to
set up a congressional observation team to report on what happened
in Romania, and to bring Ceausescu to trial in the U.N. Security
Council.
   Some members of the crowd were able to reach friends and
relatives in Romania by telephone Friday.
   ``My mother was crying _ all she could say was `I'm free',''
said Horia Dugala, 26, who spoke with his mother in Brasov on
Friday afternoon.
   After hours of trying to contact his family by phone, Radu
Tuian, 32, reached a friend in Bucharest.
   ``The most important thing was that he could speak freely for
the first time,'' Tuian said. ``After 45 years of darkness, they
came out into the light.''
   Mircea Ionescu, a playwright who fled his country after his
works were banned by the Ceausescu regime, said Romanians will be
able to celebrate Christmas openly for the first time since the end
of World War II,
   ``But it's not Christmas _ it's bloody Christmas,'' said
Ionescu, editor of the Romanian-language weekly Lumea Noastra.
Still, he added, ``Now I'm proud of being Romanian.''
   A demonstration celebrating the revolt also is planned Sunday at
Chicago's City Hall. An estimated 20,000 Romanian emigres live in
the Chicago area.
   ``For us this is really the biggest day of our lives,'' said
Rodica Perciali, director of the Romanian Folk Art Museum in
suburban Evanston, Ill. But she too expressed remorse at the loss
of life in the upheaval.
   Mrs. Perciali said Romanians had felt ashamed as the rest of
Eastern Europe enacted sweeping reforms of their communist
governments.
   ``We felt guilty and also powerless _ we almost lost hope to see
any change in Romania,'' she said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>