<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1734EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MissingPlane 1stLd-Writethru a0753 12-17 0288</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Missing Plane, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0753,0289</SECOND>
<HEAD>Searchers Still Have No Sign Of Missing Airplane</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS new 3rd graf, `Darkness forced ...' to UPDATE with search
called off for night. Phegn in penultimate graf is cq.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Blustery winds and fresh snow frustrated
rescue workers searching for a twin-engine airplane that
disappeared during a snowstorm with six people aboard, authorities
said Sunday.
   About 20 airplanes and helicopters were searching a four-county
area of the Catskill Mountains for the Piper Navajo that apparently
crashed Friday night, state police Sgt. John Vansteenburg said in
Catskill.
   Darkness forced rescuers to call off the search until Monday
morning, trooper Robert Carl said.
   ``We've found no sign,'' said Lt. George Ezzo, who is heading a
team of forest rangers in the search. Rescuers gave up searching on
foot because the plane ``could be anywhere along a 100-mile line,''
he said.
   The airplane took off Friday afternoon from Warren County
Airport, 50 miles north of Albany, bound for Orange County Airport
just north of New York City, said Civil Air Patrol spokeswoman Ann
MacMillan. It was reported about 30 miles south of Albany when it
disappeared, she said.
   The plane took off in blustery weather, and as much as 7 inches
of snow fell in the area. Although skies were clear Sunday, snow
that has fallen since Friday may have buried the plane,
Vansteenburg said.
   Salvatore Arlotta, a vice president of the Middletown-based
environmental consulting firm Wehran Engineering, and Peter Lovi, a
scientist for the company, were returning from a trip to a landfill
project northeast of Glens Falls, said Wehran spokeswoman Phyllis
Phegn.
   Authorities have not released the names of the pilot or the
other three passengers.
</TEXT>

</DOC>