<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0609EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Britain-Panama 1stLd-Writethru   12-20 0381</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Britain-Panama, 1st Ld - Writethru,a0513,0386</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Telephones Thatcher, She Gives Him Full Backing</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 6 grafs to UPDATE with Thatcher quotes. Picks up
8th pvs, `Mrs. Thatcher's ...</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher on Wednesday
hailed as courageous the U.S. invasion of Panama and declared ``the
rule of democracy must be upheld.''
   Mrs. Thatcher spoke to reporters on the steps of her Downing
Street office after President Bush telephoned her at 7 a.m. (2 a.m.
EST) to tell her he had sent in U.S. troops to seize Panamanian
Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega, wanted on U.S. drug charges.
   ``I said we would fully support him in the action he was taking
to bring an end to this rule of terror,'' said Mrs. Thatcher. ``I
believe he was right to do so. I believe this is what friends are
for to give support at this time. It was a courageous decision.'
   Mrs. Thatcher called on other world leaders to declare support
for Bush, saying ``Every action has a risk and it is important that
it be successful.''
   ``Gen. Noriega is wanted on drugs allegations in the United
States. We are fighting terror and the battle against drugs as
well. The rule of democracy should be upheld,'' she added.
   A government spokesman said Bush told Mrs. Thatcher she was the
first foreign head of the government he had called with the news.
They talked for 10 minutes.
   Mrs. Thatcher's warm response contrasted with her public
criticism of the U.S.-led invasion of Grenada in 1983 to overthrow
a leftist administration that had seized power in the Caribbean
island. Grenada is a former British colony that regards Britain's
Queen Elizabeth II as its titular head of state.
   Britain's opposition Labor Party criticized the Panama invasion,
saying it had ``nothing to do with democracy in Panama and
everything to do with protecting the American interests in the
Canal Zone.''
   ``I think everyone agrees that Noriega is a nasty dictator but
that's not the reason for the intervention,'' Labor's foreign
affairs spokesman George Foulkes said in a British Broadcasting
Corp. radio interview.
   ``The main reason is that the Americans have got a key interest
in the Panama Canal Zone ... They have therefore decided to take
the law into their own hands.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>