<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0111EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Reporter'sNotebook     12-26 0705</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Reporter's Notebook,690</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Pool Reporters in Panama: Late for the Story</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEVEN KOMAROW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>COLON, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Under cloak of darkness, the U.S. army
helicopter flew the length of the Panama Canal taking a pair of
reporters, a photographer and a television crew to this port city.
   But soon after they arrived, members of the group realized that
they'd missed the story. Again.
   Soldiers told of entering the city on Friday afternoon to the
cheers of citizens who draped American flags from their balconies.
They told how the local groups helped the U.S. soldiers round up
Noriega loyalists, and how deeply moving the scene had been.
   But more than two days after the invasion began, the U.S.
military still was keeping the media away from its operations until
they were over.
   The Pentagon news pool, created to cover American military
actions in a way that would protect important operational secrecy,
was still on its way to Panama last Wednesday when the invasion
began.
   Arriving in the country, the pool had to cool its heels for
hours inside a U.S. army base and found out the details of the
attack the same way everyone else in America did _ on television,
based on reports from other news people already in the city.
   The group arrived at the battle area around Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noriega's headquarters after the battle was over. They viewed
Noriega's private retreats after they'd been disturbed by military
investigators, and saw people who had been rescued, but not the
rescue itself.
   After a while, the pool members decided their motto should be
``semper tardis,'' or ``always late.''
   The U.S. Southern Command showed reporters the spoils of war but
not the war itself, which was, of course, the reason for the pool
in the first place.
   Exposure to ongoing events was almost an accident for the pool,
but it happened. For example:
   _An alert photographer yelling ``Whoa!'' got the press bus to
stop at a makeshift prisoner-of-war camp.
   _Reporters heading to a pre-set downtown site received an
extraordinary view of looting and mayhem when their driver got lost.
   _The press corps couldn't help but witness a surprise attack on
Southern Command headquarters, the site of the press center.
   _On a trip to interview U.S. commanders west of the city,
reporters happened upon an extraordinary scene: more than a
thousand people cheering wildly as Noriega loyalists surrendered
their weapons to U.S. soldiers.
   All around the country, American GIs and local citizens were
more than happy to tell their stories. But, not being witnesses
themselves, reporters were forced to piece things together and deal
with difficult contradictions.
   At Rio Hato, a Panamanian army base west of Panama City, Army
rangers fresh from their first real combat told of parachuting into
an intense firefight. Several U.S. lives were lost, and one
paratrooper was shot in the doorway of his C-130 aircraft as he
prepared to jump, they said. His Ranger comrades had to pull him
back to save his life.
   But back in Washington, the brass was saying how the attack on
Rio Hato had been cleared of resistance thanks to new Stealth
fighter planes which evaded radar for a bombing run which
distracted the defenders.
   At Fort Amador near Panama City was the ``Witch House,'' a
modest residence where Noriega was said to have kept his four
Brazilian voodoo witches.
   Reporters were shown the evidence of strange ritual: a bucket of
blood, animal entrails, and a variety of religious artifacts
carefully arranged on a desk that apparently served as an altar.
   But before reporters were allowed in, the military removed what
soldiers said were packets of cocaine wrapped in tropical leaves.
   Soldiers who confiscated the stockpile described their haul as
about 50 pounds of cocaine. At headquarters and in Washington, the
generals said it was 50 kilograms, which, at 2.2 pounds per kilo,
would better back up the U.S. claim that Noriega was involved
heavily in the drug trade.
   It was possible the generals were referring to cocaine also
recovered elsewhere, but reporters never were able to reconcile the
figures.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Steven Komarow was a member of the Pentagon
press pool in Panama during the U.S. invasion.
</TEXT>

</DOC>