<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0096 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1603EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania-Tunnels     12-30 0659</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Tunnels,0682</SECOND>
<HEAD>Elaborate Tunnel Network Under Bucharest Protected Ceausescu's Forces</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania-Revolution, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERRY LEONARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A steep staircase off Palace Square
descends into a black labyrinth of dank, narrow tunnels, the secret
passages of a paranoid state.
   The dark underground corridors were dug clandestinely on the
orders of Nicolae Ceausescu, the Communist dictator who apparently
grew to fear the consequences of his increasingly repressive
24-year rule.
   A week ago, when the army moved against Ceausescu, the
dictator's dreaded special police used the tunnels to move freely
under the withering machine-gun fire in the square above.
   Soldiers and civilians armed with AK-47 assault rifles guard the
entrances now. Nervous army patrols comb the tunnels, fearful they
will find ``terrorists,'' as they call Ceausescu's police, lurking
in unknown passages.
   ``It is still dangerous,'' said one soldier, who carefully
examined the passports of three Western journalists at the entrance
to a tunnel.
   Officials of the provisional government say the tunnels near
Palace Square are only part of a vast network that extends for
miles beneath the capital.
   The passages connect major government buildings and lead to
communications bunkers or to underground stores of food, weapons
and ammunition.
   ``This tunnel was used by terrorists. The ones for the president
are much wider,'' said a provisional government official who, along
with an armed escort of four men, took the reporters on a brief
tour.
   The brick-lined tunnel used by the police was about a yard wide
and less than two yards high.
   It stretched out beyond the range of his fading flashlight to an
intersection with another that also vanished into darkness toward
the royal palace.
   ``The tunnels for the president are about 5 meters wide and they
are lined with marble,'' said the official, who didn't want to give
his name after giving the reporters the unauthorized tour.
   ``Oh, no. You cannot go there,'' he said to reporters who
inquired about Ceausescu's tunnels. ``They are still too dangerous.
We are conducting demolitions,'' he said in halting English,
declining to elaborate.
   The secret passages are dark and ominous symbols of a paranoid
state that hardened itself against its people. There are others.
When soldiers shot away the windows on the top floor of the royal
palace, they exposed concrete walls built to withstand the heavy
machine-gun fire.
   Liviu Axente, a photojournalist from Focsani, showed two Western
reporters pictures of a huge underground bunker in that city 125
miles north of the capital.
   ``They (security forces) have bunkers like this in every
district,'' he said. ``They intercepted every telephone call, read
everyone's mail.''
   ``There are hidden microphones in my house,'' he said. He showed
reporters pictures of the munitions, including sophisticated
automatic weapons, he said were found in the bunker and given to
the army.
   He also had pictures of the electronic eavesdropping equipment
and of a vast collection of security files, placed in boxes stacked
to the ceiling.
   Photographs of the inside of the files showed photocopies of
intercepted letters and postcards and of reports on monitored
telephone calls.
   It has been just a week since the popular revolt ousted, seized
and executed Ceausescu. Outraged Romanians are still struggling to
uncover the extent of the madness of Ceausescu's ``golden era.''
   Ceausescu lived in an opulent villa, with gold leaf and marble
floors in the entrance way and golden fixtures in the bathrooms.
Tapestries and paintings in gilted frames adorn the walls and
crystal chandeliers hang from the ceiling.
   He dined extravagantly by the light of candles burning in golden
candelabras.
   His people had to wait in long lines with their ration cards to
buy substandard food in an agriculturally rich country.
   When the people protested, demanding bread and reform, his
special police opened fire. The tunnels, underground bunkers and
windows reinforced with concrete, suggest Ceausescu knew one day
the people might say enough.
   ``He was a monster,'' one young soldier said near the tunnel
entrance.
</TEXT>

</DOC>