<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0181 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2011EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DonorSuicide     12-20 0530</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Donor Suicide,0544</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Takes Own Life in Attempt to Save Brother's</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TAMARAC, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   With the squeeze of a trigger, Gerald Olson
thought he could give his ailing brother the most precious
Christmas gift: a chance at good health.
   But Olson's suicide wish to offer his heart to his 56-year-old
brother could not be granted. Even if the organ were suitable,
doctors said a transplant was impossible because the heart had
stopped pumping.
   ``If it fits, and I'm pretty sure it will, as one last wish I'd
like to offer him mine, so please do your best. Thanks and Merry
Christmas,'' Olson wrote in a seven-page suicide letter found near
his body.
   Authorities say Olson, 46, drove his van Monday evening to
University Community Hospital in Tamarac, about 25 miles north of
Miami. He parked the vehicle outside the emergency room entrance
and shot himself in the mouth with a .25-caliber pistol.
   No one heard the shot, but minutes later a nurse saw Olson
slumped inside the van. A medical team tried to revive him, but he
was declared dead 19 minutes later.
   ``You can't take a non-beating heart out of a dead body and use
it,'' said hospital spokeswoman Lynne Farber. ``Heart transplants
have to be a little bit more well-planned. His brother wasn't even
in the state of Florida.''
   Olson's brother Bob is being treated with medication for an
enlarged heart and has been waiting for a transplant for three
years.
   ``Bob's got everything to live for,'' his brother wrote. ``I
figure I can do more good for him than myself.''
   Bob Olson said he was shocked by his brother's suicide.
   ``He thought of me in his last thoughts. He wanted somebody
benefiting from his death,'' he said from his home in Belvedere,
Ill. ``If he had been killed accidentally, I could have accepted
this. But to take his own life, something that is so precious to
me, I can't deal with.''
   Family members say Gerald Olson moved to Florida from Illinois
about eight years ago to stay with his sister after her husband
died of a heart attack.
   In addition to his job at a Pompano Beach tavern, Gerald Olson
helped organize fund-raising events for his brother, who made
regular trips to the Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minn.
   The tavern went out of business last year, and Gerald Olson left
his sister's apartment last month after an argument. For the past
month he had been living in his van, which was cluttered with
fund-raising posters for his brother.
   In a passage of the suicide letter addressed to his daughter,
Lisa Marie, he wrote: ``I'm so sorry it had to come to this, Honey,
but lately there's been too many downs and no ups for me on this
roller coaster of life.''
   He also requested that his family be together for his funeral
and that the Mass include a tape recording of him singing ``I'll Be
Home For Christmas.''
   ``He was close to everybody, not only his family, but other
people, too,'' said another brother, Ronald Olson, 58, of Rockford,
Ill. ``Gerry's business was to like people. And if he liked you, he
loved you.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>