<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0119 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2009EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Democrats-States     12-19 0536</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Democrats-States,510</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dems Target 18 State Legislatures</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM M. WELCH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Democratic Party announced plans Tuesday
to target statehouse elections in 18 states next year in the hope
of controlling state legislatures when congressional districts are
redrawn for the 1990s.
   The Democrats hope to raise $3 million to help candidates for
the legislatures in those states next year, said Tim Dickson, who
heads the party's Project 500 program.
   The program's aim is to expand Democratic control of state
legislatures before they begin congressional and state legislative
reapportionment in 1992.
   Democrats are particularly concerned with states likely to gain
or lose congressional districts as a result of population shifts
that will come to light in the 1990 census. They are also focusing
on states where the majority's grip in the state legislature is
tenuous.
   ``We believe fair lines will be drawn, but we prefer to be the
ones drawing them,'' Dickson told a news conference. ``Since 1980,
individual elections have been battles, but control of
redistricting is the war.''
   The targeted states are Arizona, California, Colorado,
Connecticut, Florida, Illinois, Indiana, Iowa, Michigan, New
Jersey, New York, Ohio, Oregon, Pennsylvania, Texas, Virginia,
Washington and Wisconsin.
   Democrats now control 36 state Houses and 32 state Senates,
while Republicans control 12 Houses and 17 Senates. They share
power in Indiana's House; Nebraska has a nonpartisan bicameral
legislature.
   Dickson said that the $3 million would be more than three times
what the national party spent toward state legislative races in
1988, and that his group has raised $650,000 toward the goal.
   The party will give money to Democratic legislative campaign
organizations in each of the states, which will decide how to
divide it among individual candidates. Some of the money may go to
gubernatorial candidates, although the party has another fund for
those campaigns.
   Of the targeted states, five are exected to gain congressional
seats because of population shifts: one or two seats in Arizona;
five or six seats in California; three or four seats in Florida and
Texas, and one seat in Virginia.
   Six other states are expected to lose seats due to
reapportionment, with New York projected to lose three seats and
Ohio and Pennsylvania each expected to lose two and possibly three.
Illinois is projected to lose two seats, according to the
Democrats; Iowa, one seat, and Wisconsin, perhaps one.
   The Republican National Committee also has a program to target
state legislative races and governors' races. Leslie Goodman, a
spokeswoman for the Republicans, said the party would not reveal
its spending plans or list its targeted states.
   ``It makes no sense to lay out a political game plan,'' she said.
   But, Goodman said, the Republicans will be focusing on states
where redistricting will mean a gain or loss of congressional
seats, and what she said were 14 states where Republicans are
within striking distance of winning control of at least one
legislative chamber now held by the Democrats.
   ``Ultimately we have to do better in redistricting than we did
in '81,'' she said. ``We consistently get gerrymandered out of our
fair share. ... We're never going to have a shot if we don't get
the lines drawn fairly and properly.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>