<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1131EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-Romania     12-21 0281</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Romania,0287</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romania Condemns U.S. Invasion of Panama as `Brutal'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt, PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Romania today condemned the U.S. invasion
of Panama as ``brutal aggression'' as its own security forces
reportedly shot to death several civilians protesting the hard-line
Communist regime.
   A commentary in the Communist Party daily Scinteia and all other
state-run media carried an article headlined, ``An inadmissible act
of outstanding international gravity _ the U.S. aggression against
the republic of Panana.''
   The commentary expressing the official view said Romania had
repeatedly called for ``renunciation of measures of force and
threat of force'' and for resolving interstate disputes ``by
peaceful means only.''
   ``All the much more reprehensible are the U.S. actions of brutal
aggression as they were taken against a small state which defends
its independence and freedom violated by a superpower,'' the
Romanian statement said.
   It added, ``It is the sacred right of each people to decide its
own way of life, its political regime, according to its aspirations
and traditions.''
   ``By stating its solidarity with the Panamanian people's fight
for the independence of its country, the Romanian people firmly
condemns the U.S. armed intervention ... and asks that an end be
put forever to the colonialist, imperialist policy of domination
and dictate, of interference in the home afairs of peoples,'' the
commentary said.
   The criticism came on the same day a wave of unrest hit the
Romanian capital, Bucharest. The Soviet news agency Tass and a
reporter for the Yugoslav news agency Tanjug said security forces
fired on protesters in Bucharest today.
   The Yugoslav reporter said several people were killed and
wounded, and military tanks were reported rolling through the city.
</TEXT>

</DOC>