<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0271 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1633EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-GreetingCards Bjt   12-22 0512</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Greeting Cards, Bjt,0528</SECOND>
<HEAD>Baby Boomers Like Humor For Christmas Cards But Tradition Prevails</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DWIGHT WOODWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   'Tis the season to be traditional, but silly
Santas, laughing reindeer and teddy bears are arriving in mailboxes
nationwide this year as Christmas card makers appeal to a trend in
card buying that transcends race, religion and sex _ humor.
   Those who like the offbeat can send a card showing cow udders
singing a Christmas carol or Santa kicking a football through the
antlers of a laughing reindeer.
   While the majority of the 2.3 billion Christmas cards sent this
year will reflect more customary symbols of the holiday, humor is
where the growth is, said Terry Carney, spokeswoman for American
Greetings Corp., the largest publicly owned greeting card company
with $1.2 billion in annual sales.
   ``But it's not usually the kind of humor that is nasty, rude or
sarcastic,'' said Ms. Carney.
   About 500 members of the creative staff at American, based in
suburban Cleveland, produce about 2,300 designs a year of which
about one-third are Christmas cards, Ms. Carney said.
   In addition to laughs, specialty cards with a regional flavor _
cactus for the Southwest, for instance _ or messages aimed at
particular occupations are popular.
   As with most consumer tastes, the explanation is demographic.
   ``The bulk of the cards purchased are by people between 35 and
59,'' said E. Gray Glass III, a New York stock market analyst with
Prudential-Bache Inc. Glass. ``These are people that move around a
lot and they want to keep in contact with their friends.''
   Barbara Miller, spokeswoman for Hallmark Cards Inc., agreed that
humor is in this year, but she said tradition dies hard.
   ``Wreaths, holly trees, bells, fireplace and sleigh scenes _
these are the symbols people see as Christmas,'' she said.
   That doesn't mean the giant Hallmark hasn't cultivated a Yuppie
sense of humor. One Hallmark offering shows a dazed cat with a
stocking cap swinging on an ornament attached to Christmas tree
lights. Inside, the caption reads, ``In the air there's a feline of
Christmas.''
   Among the specialty cards designed to suit distinctive tastes
are ones ``for the barber, the teacher, bus driver or the
mailman,'' Ms. Miller said.
   With annual sales of more than $3.5 billion, the privately held
Hallmark, based in Kansas City, Mo., has the biggest single share
of the greeting card market, producing 2,700 card designs for
over-the-counter sales and another 400 different boxed sets of
multiple cards, Ms. Miller said.
   Glass said Hallmark produces about 44 percent of U.S. Christmas
cards, followed by American with 32 percent and Cincinnati-based
Gibson Greetings Inc. about 10 percent.
   Another 700 to 800 U.S. companies produce the remainder of U.S.
Christmas cards with a negligible portion coming from foreign
manufacturers, Glass said.
   Among the strangest, if not funniest, cards to emerge are
pet-to-pet missives.
   ``From our cat to your cat, from our dog to your dog _ people
consider their pets part of the family,'' Ms. Miller said. ``They
are cute cards, not drippy or sentimental.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>