<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0088 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1723EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     12-25 0359</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0369</SECOND>
<HEAD>Snow and Record Cold for Christmas in the Southeast</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Record lows were confined to the Southeast on Monday as a major
cold wave dwindled, but more cool air began moving into northern
Minnesota and heavy snow fell around Lake Superior.
   Monday's low of zero degrees at Wilmington, N.C., broke the
city's previous all-time record of 5 above, which had stood since
February 1899.
   The low of 33 degrees at Miami Beach, Fla., equalled that city's
record for all of December, established just the day before.
   Other record lows Monday, all in Florida, were 29 at Fort
Lauderdale, 46 at Key West, and 30 at Miami, the National Weather
Service reported, a far cry from last week when temperatures hit
record lows in more than 100 cities a day.
   A cold front nosed into the northern Plains region and the upper
Mississippi Valley during the afternoon, kicking up snow and gusty
wind that sharply reducing visibility in some areas.
   Squalls associated with the cold front produced heavy snow along
the shoreline of Lake Superior, and up to 12 inches of new snow was
possible by Tuesday in parts of western and central Upper Michigan
near the lakeshore, the weather service said.
   A weak storm system brought light snow to the Tennessee Valley
early Monday and snow flurries were reported as far south as the
central Gulf Coast. Mobile, Ala., reported snow on Christmas for
the first time since record-keeping began in 1871.
   Snow showers were scattered from Missouri and Tennessee to the
Great Lakes and western New England.
   Freezing drizzle was reported in northern Illinois during the
morning.
   Temperatures dropped below freezing early Monday across most of
the nation, with sub-zero readings reported across New England and
eastern New York state, and parts of West Virginia and coastal
North Carolina.
   Monday's low for the Lower 48 states was 17 degrees below zero
at Houlton, Maine.
   A warm front crossing the Great Lakes region, middle Mississippi
Valley and southern Plains spread more seasonable temperatures
eastward. Afternoon readings were in the 40s in the central Plains
and in the 50s across the southern Plains.
</TEXT>

</DOC>