<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1401EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Jordan     12-30 0529</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jordan,0544</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lawmakers Demand Faster Liberalization</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMAL HALABY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AMMAN, Jordan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Parliament deputies on Saturday demanded
more democracy and improvements in the economy as they debated
whether to give a vote of confidence to the new government of Prime
Minister Mudar Badran.
   Lawmakers predicted that approval of Badran's 25-member Cabinet
was likely in the vote Sunday, despite the tough attacks on his
government.
   The debate caps a revival of life in the Parliament. Last month,
Jordan held its first general elections in 22 years.
   King Hussein on Dec. 4 named Badran to form a new government.
The Cabinet he formed will have the task of negotiating with
Parliament on new legislation, but first it must win a vote of
confidence from Parliament.
   Twenty members of the Moslem Brotherhood, the largest bloc in
the 80-man Parliament, said in a joint statement they would abstain
unless the government agreed to stricter Islamic laws, quick repeal
of martial law, reinstatement of public officials fired for
security reasons and a ban on liquor sales in public places,
including aboard Royal Jordanian airline flights.
   The large number of deputies rising to address Parliament forced
Speaker Suleiman Arar to postpone a vote on the question until
Sunday.
   Abdullatif Arabiyyat, delivering the Brotherhood's joint
statement, said Brotherhood deputies had told Badran earlier that
they would cooperate ``with a strong, clean government,'' although
efforts to agree on ministerial seats for the Brotherhood collapsed.
   ``And then we were faced with a surprise ... a government that
was much below the level of our aspirations and the aspirations of
the people,'' he said.
   Hundreds of people jammed the public galleries for the debate,
sometimes applauding deputies below. About 100 others demonstrated
in front of the building to demand immediate freedom for political
prisoners.
   Even some steadfast loyalists of the king said they would vote
against the new government, despite a series of measures by Badran
to loosen martial law, restrict the security forces and free the
press.
   Former Royal Court Chief Thouqan Hindawi accused Badran of
helping create the kingdom's debt crisis during earlier terms as
prime minister from 1979 to 1983, and he said it was difficult to
determine how the money was spent.
   ``Where is the rest of the money, Mr. Badran?'' asked Hindawi,
who resigned as King Hussein's chief aide to run for Parliament in
November during Jordan's first nationwide election since 1967.
   Economic problems caused by the debt crisis led to four days of
rioting in April that toppled the government of then-Prime Minister
Zaid Rifai and led Hussein to launch a series of liberalizing
measures.
   Many Jordanians allege that government corruption caused much of
the economic problems.
   Since taking office, Badran's government has eliminated some of
the security checks for passports and work permits and has stripped
most of the work from martial law courts, as well as liberalizing
the press.
   But many of the deputies speaking Saturday demanded full repeal
of martial law, imposed during the 1967 war with Israel, and
legalization of political parties banned more than 30 years ago.
   Some also called for investigations into the country's economic
distress and trials of those deemed responsible.
</TEXT>

</DOC>