<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0733EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CrackArrest     12-30 0425</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Crack Arrest,0441</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Disclose Arrest Of 9-Year-Old Boy</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police had tears in their eyes when they booked a
9-year-old boy who allegedly sold crack cocaine to an undercover
officer, an official said.
   The 3-foot-11, 95-pound youngster was arraigned Friday in
Roxbury District Court on juvenile delinquency charges. He was
released to the custody of his grandmother, with whom he has been
living because his mother is in prison, police said.
   The boy's name was not released.
   ``It was a very sad and traumatic thing to see a little
9-year-old boy sitting in the station arrested for drugs,'' Deputy
Superintendent Robert Hayden said. ``I saw some veteran officers
with tears in their eyes over this incident.''
   Among the youngest children arrested around the country on crack
charges have been a 10-year-old Detroit boy in August and a
10-year-old boy on Long Island in New York in January.
   Boston police said they sought an arrest warrant for the
teen-ager whom the 9-year-old identified as the supplier of the
crack.
   ``The little boy would go out and sell until the end of the
night when he would reach the older person who would give him
money'' for the sales work, Hayden said. The boy told police he had
been selling for about two weeks.
   The 9-year-old had $68 in his pockets, probably from drug sales,
when he was arrested Thursday night, police said.
   ``He was kind of scared,'' Hayden said. ``He was crying.''
   Police said they will ask to have the boy turned over to the
Department of Social Services. Charles Dickerson, a police juvenile
officer, said the youngster needs better supervision than he gets
from his grandmother.
   ``He's used to getting out there and staying with the older
kids,'' Dickerson said. ``He's been seen at 11 p.m. with older
kids.''
   Hayden said three undercover officers went Thursday night to a
corner in Boston's Roxbury section where there had been reports of
heavy drug activity. Hayden said one officer was approached by the
boy, who said, ``What's up?''
   ``What do you got?'' asked the officer.
   The boy reached into his pocket and handed the officer what is
believed to be crack, the highly addictive, form of cocaine. After
the arrest, officers found 80 small bags of crack near the
intersection.
   Hayden said, ``The feeling we were left with was, with all the
shootings and terrible things we see, this has affected us the most
because he is supposed to be innocent.
   ``He is supposed to be worried about what he got for Christmas.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>