<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0112 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1654EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Judge-Explosion 4thLd-Writethru a0597 12-19 1217</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Judge-Explosion, 4th Ld - Writethru, a0597,1246</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Police Disarm Bomb at Jacksonville, Fla., NAACP Office</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with eight grafs to UPDATE with police disarming Jacksonville
bomb, Sessions comments in Washington; picks up 3rd graf, `In Alabama ...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos AX1,AX2,WX7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURAN NEERGAARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAVANNAH, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A police bomb squad today disarmed a parcel
bomb found at the Jacksonville, Fla., office of the NAACP, the
latest discovery in a rash of mail bombings in the South that have
claimed two lives, authorities said.
   ``It was designed to kill the individual that opened this
package or anyone else standing in the area,'' said Jacksonville
Sheriff Jim McMillan.
   The building was evacuated and the bomb, which arrived in the
mail Monday but was left unopened, was disarmed by disconnecting
the battery from the explosive, officials said.
   ``It had a great similarity in the packaging to the other
bombs,'' said Willi Ellison of the U.S. Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco
and Firearms. ``It was addressed to no one specifically, but to the
legal staff of the NAACP.''
   The bomb was to be taken to an FBI laboratory in Washington and
compared with the other devices, he said.
   FBI Director William Sessions said in Washington that
investigators were looking into race as a possible motive, noting
that the incidents involved ``federal judges who have heard cases
involving racial matters,'' the NAACP and a black civil rights
activist.
   Under questioning, Sessions told a Justice Department news
conference that more than one person might be involved in the
bombings, which have killed a federal judge and a civil rights
lawyer.
   The parcel bomb that killed the lawyer in Savannah had been
packed with nails, suggesting another link to the bomb that killed
the judge and another bomb, authorities said.
   In Alabama, police X-rayed a package left on the doorstep of a
Birmingham city councilman who was friends with the slain judge,
but concluded it was probably an innocent mailing. ``This is one of
many screening processes we'll probably be going through because of
the situation,'' said FBI agent Allen Whitaker.
   The FBI, meanwhile, warned judges, lawyers and NAACP activists
to beware of strange packages, saying white supremacists might be
behind the attacks.
   Robert Robinson, a 42-year-old black lawyer and city alderman,
was fatally injured in his law office Monday night, hours after
police removed an explosive device delivered to the 11th U.S.
Circuit Court of Appeals in Atlanta and two days after a mail bomb
killed 11th Circuit Judge Robert S. Vance.
   ``There's a strong similarity in the three explosive devices,
and it appears there is a relationship,'' FBI agent Tom Moore said
in Birmingham, Ala.
   Officials said the bomb that killed Vance on Saturday hurled
nails when it exploded. The Atlanta Constitution today quoted
unidentified authorities as saying the Atlanta bomb contained nails
as well, and Savannah Mayor John Rousakis said today: ``We believed
nails were part of this bomb also, and that has been confirmed.''
   Robinson represented the NAACP in a long-running desegregation
lawsuit involving Savannah schools, and the 11th Circuit, which
handles appeals for Georgia, Alabama and Florida, had recently
ruled in that case.
   Federal marshals said the nine judges in the 11th Circuit were
being given round-the-clock protection.
   In Washington, a government source, who spoke on condition of
anonymity, said the bomb that killed Vance bore the return address
of a second judge who regularly sent Vance packages. The second
judge, Lewis F. Morgan, also of the 11th Circuit, is not a suspect
in the case. But the discovery means the killer knew a great deal
about Vance's personal habits and friendships, the source added.
   FBI agent Bob DeLoach said Monday that authorities were
following several leads but that it was possible white supremacists
sent the bomb that killed Robinson.
   ``I've been here three years and can't recall white
supremacists, but who knows what goes on in people's minds and why
they'd start now?'' DeLoach asked. ``We're definitely looking into
that, but everything else, too.''
   Former Alabama Ku Klux Klan leader Don Black, who now lives in
South Florida, said there are disgruntled members of the white
supremacist movement who believe the legal system works against the
white majority.
   ``They believe the only solution is direct attacks, illegal
acts, on the system,'' Black said. ``When that first bombing
happened Saturday, it occurred to me it might not be Colombian drug
smugglers.''
   DeLoach and FBI agent William Henshaw said the FBI was warning
lawyers, judges and activists with the National Association for the
Advancement of Colored People to look over their mail carefully.
   Henshaw said the NAACP Southeast regional headquarters in
Atlanta also had been warned because the bombs appeared to be
related to a Aug. 22, 1989 tear-gas mail bomb that exploded at the
Atlanta office, injuring eight people. That case is still being
investigated.
   Earl Shinhoster, the NAACP regional director, said he had talked
with the FBI and ``needless to say, it was a wide-ranging
discussion.''
   Shinhoster also said he hadn't ruled out the possibility that
white supremacists were responsible for the bombings ``especially
now, since various groups ... are much more zealous in their
particular ideological pursuits.''
   Morris Dees, head of the Southern Poverty Law Center, said the
FBI had warned him to take precautions.
   ``The FBI contacted me as a routine matter (because) they
suspect it was a possibility that white supremacists were involved
in the bombings,'' he said. ``And, as a precautionary measure
because of my past involvement, wanted to warn me.''
   On Sunday, authorities warned the nation's 1,500 federal judges
to be careful with their mail.
   ``We have pretty good security here,'' said U.S. Circuit Judge
William W. Wilkins of Greenville, S.C. ``But I've of course asked
my family not to open any packages mailed to the home unless I've
had a chance to take a look at them.''
   ``It's a tough business,'' said Judge Daniel A. Manion of South
Bend, Ind. Manion sits on a three-judge panel of the 7th U.S.
Circuit Court of Appeals in Chicago.
   Robinson represented the NAACP in its challenge to a plan to
settle a 25-year-old desegregation lawsuit against the Savannah
School system, said State Rep. Jim Pannell of Savannah, who
attended the University of Georgia Law school with Robinson.
   The 11th Circuit in September upheld the plan that relied
heavily on magnet schools to draw more whites into predominantly
black schools and voluntary ``majority to minority'' transfers.
   The NAACP and U.S. Department of Justice had objected to the
plan, which was put into place voluntarily by the school system
last fall.
   Vance, 58, was not on the three-judge panel that ruled in the
case but did serve on a panel that had cleared the way for
prosecution of a case against the Ku Klux Klan.
   The panel, in a June 1985 decision, had overturned a lower court
ruling that had thrown out evidence critical to the prosecution of
10 Klansmen in a bloody May 1979 confrontation with black civil
rights marchers in Decatur, Ala., that wounded four people.
   Authorities said the Atlanta bomb was in a mailed package
addressed to the 11th Circuit courthouse _ but not to a specific
individual, unlike the bomb that killed Vance. Employees were
evacuated from the five-story downtown building Monday morning.
Police safely disarmed the bomb.
</TEXT>

</DOC>