<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1307EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Panama 4thLd-Writethru a0500 12-30 1108</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0500,1141</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>U.S. Embassy Official Says Search of Nicaraguan Residence Was a Mistake</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE with U.S. Embassy saying the raid was
a mistake, State Department criticizing Nicaraguan `overreaction, CORRECTS
Sconyers to Air Force, sted Army. TRIMS to tighten. No pickup.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY10, 11, 12</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. military authorities today
defended their search of the Nicaraguan ambassador's residence, but
a senior U.S. Embassy official said it was a mistake and that steps
were being taken to apologize.
   Nicaraguan President Daniel Ortega retaliated for the search of
the ambassador's residence Friday by ordering the expulsion of 20
U.S. diplomats.
   In Washington, the State Department said today that the soldiers
who searched the home found a large cache of weapons but returned
them when they realized the residence was occupied by a Nicaraguan
diplomat.
   The State Department said Nicaragua's response was ``an
irresponsible overreaction'' intended to reduce the U.S. Embassy's
ability to monitor the fairness of general elections scheduled in
Nicaragua on Feb. 25.
   In another development, the Vatican promised to work toward
resolving the crisis over ousted leader Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   In Rome, the Vatican today declared it did not intend to ``block
the course of justice'' by giving refuge to Noriega, who is wanted
in the United States on drug trafficking charges. He has been in
the Vatican's Panama City embassy since Sunday, four days after the
United States invaded Panama.
   The Vatican Secretariat of State also said in a communique that
it was continuing to examine the case with U.S. authorities ``in a
spirit of serene collaboration'' in hopes of finding a mutually
acceptable solution.
   Vatican spokesman Joaquin Navarro said on Friday the Vatican
could not hand over Noriega to the Americans but was urging him to
leave its embassy in Panama City on his own. The Vatican also
demanded that U.S. troops stop harassing the Vatican mission with
loud music. Navarro warned that ``further steps will be taken'' by
the Vatican if the harassment continued.
   The rap and rock music, which has included numerous taunting
songs, seemed intended to torment Noriega. U.S. troops turned down
the volume late Friday afternoon, and it stopped this morning.
   Nicaraguan Ambassador Antenor Ferrey said about 60 U.S. troops
ordered him, seven Nicaraguan staff members and two Panamanians to
leave his residence on Friday while American soldiers searched the
house for two hours.
   Neighbors of the residence in northeastern Panama City said
soldiers fired shots in the air. A U.S. C-130 transport plane and a
helicopter flew overhead.
   ``This violates the principal foundations of the
extraterritoriality of diplomatic missions,'' Ferrey told a news
conference. ``The North Americans are going to pay for it.''
   ``They acted arrogantly, like Rambos!'' Ortega said in Managua.
   Ortega announced late Friday in Managua that his government was
ordering 20 U.S. diplomats to leave Nicaragua within 72 hours and
reduce its support staff from 320 employees to 100. It was unclear
whether any of the support staff were Americans and whether they
also would have to leave the country. Many members of the support
staff are Nicaraguans.
   The United States does not have an ambassador in Managua, and it
was not also immediately known whether U.S. charge d'affaires John
Leonard, the top U.S. diplomat, would be expelled.
   American troops have been surrounding Nicaragua's Embassy, but
not the residence, since the Dec. 20 U.S. invasion. The troops have
also ringed the Cuban and Libyan embassies on a hunch Noriega
associates might seek refuge.
   U.S. Air Force Col. Ronald Sconyers, a Southern Command
spokesman, said today that the search of the house Friday was based
on ``reliable information'' from a Panamanian citizen that it
countained a large arms cache.
   Reading from a statement, he said the search was made ``with
good cause'' and said the official Nicaraguan Embassy residence was
listed as being an apartment in another part of the city, thus it
was the position of the United States that the house searched did
not have diplomatic immunity.
   Ferrey told reporters that he moved more than a year ago and
that he argued for 75 minutes with the commander of the operation,
asking him to double-check his information but that the commander
refused.
   The front wall of the house bears a large Nicaraguan seal.
   A senior U.S. Embassy official said at a press briefing today:
   ``It was a mistake. We do not go into diplomatic residences.''
   Speaking on condition that his name not be used, the official
said the troops did not know it was a diplomatic residence until
the search was well under way and that when they realized it they
apologized and left.
   ``The had no orders to search if they knew it was the
ambassador's residence,'' the official said.
   He said the United States would take ``appropriate steps'' in
terms of an official apology, but he did not say what those steps
might be.
   He said the Nicaraguan response of expelling U.S. diplomats from
Managua was ``disproportionate.''
   Ferrey said the troops seized five rifles that were for
self-defense, then returned the arms with apologies. However, a
watch and $1,000 in cash appeared to be missing, he said.
   Sconyers said there were many more weapons there, including four
Uzi machine guns, 11 AK-47 rifles, grenades and anti-tank weapons.
   The State Department statement said the cache included four
Uzis, six rocket-propelled grenade launchers, 12 AK-47s, three hand
grenades, 10 FEN rifles, 17 bayonets, 1 M-1 carbine, one shotgun,
four rocket-propelled grenade sights, one light anti-tank weapon,
27 rocket-propelled grenade rounds, approximately 1,300 rounds of
ammunition of various caliber.
   The State Department said the soldiers entered the residence
after receiving a tip that arms were hidden there and that the
weapons they found were clearly ``in excess of normal requirements
for defending the residence.''
   ``When it was determined that the residence was that of a
Nicaraguan diplomat, the weapons were returned. The Nicaraguan
government claims that the Nicaraguans were mistreated during the
search are not accurate. There was no damage to the house or
injuries to the occupants,'' the State Department said.
   ``Despite the fact that we expressed our regrets about the
incident, which involved a substantial weapons cache, the
Nicaraguan government has taken the decision to expel the majority
of U.S. personnel assigned to our embassy in Managua and to reduce
drastically the number of Nicaraguan employees.
   ``This is an irresponsible overreaction and clearly motivated by
Nicaraguan desires to reduce the size of our mission... By reducing
our mission drastically, the Nicaraguan government hopes to curtail
severely our ability to monitor the fairness and openness of the
elections.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>