<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0237 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2159EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Panama-Canal     12-20 0703</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Panama-Canal,0721</SECOND>
<HEAD>Panama &amp; Its Canal: A Boon to World Trade, Headache for Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BALBOA HEIGHTS, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Panama Canal, a crowning
achievement of U.S. industry and energy, has been a boon for world
trade, a symbol of achievement for Americans and a source of dismay
for many Panamanians.
   ``The canal has been good and bad for us,'' said historian
Carlos Bolivar Pedreschi in an interview with The Associated Press
earlier this year.
   ``It helped us attain independence and created an efficient
class of administrators. But then the United States also created
and supported a Panamanian military class that, claiming it must
prepare to protect the canal, has suppressed the democratic
forces,'' Pedreschi said.
   The canal was closed for the first time in many years on
Wednesday after the beginning of the U.S. attack that ousted the
most recent representative of that military class, Gen. Manuel
Antonio Noriega.
   It had been closed before, but only because of landslides in the
narrow Gaillaird Cut. The Canal Commission, headquartered at Balboa
Heights above the southern end of the canal, hoped to have the
canal open for business on Thursday, but it wasn't clear if it
would be safe.
   The United States helped Panama secede from Colombia in 1903,
with President Theodore Roosevelt serving as godfather, and paid
the French, who started work on the canal, $40 million for rights
and properties, then spent $387 million and ten years building it.
   Linking the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans and cutting sailing time
around Cape Horn by more than half, the waterway was a marvel of
engineering from the start. Nearly 262 million cubic yards of dirt
and rock were removed, enough to fill a train circling Earth four
times.
   Since then, dredges have dug out nearly 400 million more cubic
yards to widen it and keep the 51-mile-long waterway in running
condition.
   An estimated 36,000 workers were employed at the peak of the
enterprise, and they built dams and locks, conquered yellow fever
and malaria and sawed through Gold Hill, now the peak of Culebra
Cut, also known as the Gailliard Cut for its chief engineer.
   In order to negotiate the waterway, ships are lifted 85 feet
from one ocean and deposited again in the other through the locks,
whose level rises or descads depending on the ship's direction.
   The cuts the route from, for example, Peru to the East Coast by
6,200 miles, and the cost is not exhorbitant: $1.83 per cargo ton
in 1989; $1.46 per ton unloaded. Adventurer Richard Halliburton,
weighing 140 pounds, paid 36 cents to swim it in the 1920s.
   But adventure and commerce were not the only meaning of the
canal. It had quite another meaning to men like Noriega's mentor,
the late dictator Omar Torrijos, who made it their historic project
to recover the Canal Zone.
   The zone was an affluent little America, 10 miles on each side
of the waterway, replete with manicured lawns, its own courts,
police, stamps, stores and lifestyle.
   The treaty that created the Zone, a 10-mile wide domain of U.S.
sovereignty that cut Panama in two, was considered unfair even by
John Hay, the U.S. Secretary of State who arranged it, but it
helped convince Congress to spend the money to build the canal.
   Over the years, highly paid American canal employees and
military personnel living caused increasing resentment among poorly
paid Panamanians _ especially blacks, who faced Southern-style
segregation.
   In 1964, riots over what flags should fly at Balboa High School
left four U.S. soldiers and 22 Panamanians dead.
   The Panama Canal Treaties, signed in 1977 by President Jimmy
Carter and Torrijos, eliminated the Canal Zone and called for the
United States to give up all rights to the canal it built and
maintained at noon on Dec. 31, 1999.
   When Torrijos died in a plane accident in 1981, an obscure
military intelligence officer whom he had befriended began to work
himself up the ladder of power. In 1983, he became head of the
Defense Forces.
   The treaty, the Canal and compliance became one of many bones of
contention between the United States and Panama during Noriega's
stint as leader of Panama.
</TEXT>

</DOC>