<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0103 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 2017EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-WorldChristmas 2ndLd-Writethru a0577 12-25 1086</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-World Christmas, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0577,1110</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eastern Europe Gets New Freedom For Christmas; Pope Prays For Peace</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERT 2 grafs after 25th graf, `In Bethlehem ...' to INCLUDE
hostages' Christmas. Picks up 26th graf, `South African .. .'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos ROM1,8</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LARRY RYCKMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Millions of Eastern Europeans celebrated their first free
Christmas in four decades: political prisoners rejoined their
families, East Germans and Czechoslovaks watched Mass on TV, and
Romanians listened to carols long-banned on state radio.
   Pope John Paul II prayed for Romanians ``celebrating this
Christmas in fear and trembling,'' mourned the thousands killed
overthrowing their Communist leaders, and praised the democratic
reforms remaking his native Eastern Europe.
   The Soviet Union's Baltic republics enjoyed the first official
Christmas holiday allowed by the Communists.
   Panamanians and U.S. soldiers spent Christmas on the lookout for
snipers.
   Church bells pealed across Czechoslovakia to mark the new
freedoms won in a pro-democracy movement that toppled Communist
leaders, created a free press and brought promises of free
elections.
   ``I feel like this is a miracle,'' said Ivan Martin Jirous, who
was reunited with his family after being released from prison one
month ago. Jirous, 45, was imprisoned more than eight years for
``subversive'' acts such as unauthorized lecturing and publishing.
   ``Everybody is so happy, so cheerful. It is euphoric with
everybody chatting about the future,'' said Dagmar Vogel, 22, home
for Christmas for the first time since her family fled their
homeland when she was 15 months old.
   On Prague's 15th century Charles Bridge, young carolers sang
haunting, traditional Christmas melodies. In previous years, police
chased carolers from the broad, cobbled King's Road.
   Millions attended Mass or watched an unprecedented live TV
broadcast of one in Prague's 13th century Strahov Monastery. It was
said by Vaclav Maly, a dissident priest who was banned for 11 years
for his human rights activities.
   In Berlin, people from both sides of the divided city mingled
freely, attending joint church services for the first time since
the Berlin Wall was built 28 years ago. East Germany on Sunday
began allowing visa-free travel by West Germans and thousands used
the opportunity to cross to East Berlin to join relatives for a
Christmas service.
   East Germans also watched their first Mass on television, as the
pope delivered his traditional Christmas message in 53 languages
from St. Peter's Square in Rome. Many of his remarks were aimed at
Eastern Europe.
   ``May this Europe open her doors and her heart to understand and
receive the anxieties, the fears and the problems of the nations
which seek her help,'' he prayed.
   ``May she respond with the strength and the generosity of her
Christian roots to this very special moment of history ... which
the world is now experiencing as if awakened from a nightmare and
opened up to a better hope.''
   ``In particular, bless at this hour, O Lord, the noble land of
Romania, which is celebrating this Christmas in fear and trembling,
with sorrow for the many human lives tragically lost and in the joy
of having taken once more the path of freedom,'' the pope said.
   Amid the sounds of gunfire on the streets of Bucharest were the
sounds of Christmas songs and carols, broadcast by Radio Bucharest
for the first time since the Communist takeover in December 1947.
   Yugoslav and Finnish journalists brought Christmas presents for
children in the western Romanian town of Timisoara, provided by a
Yugoslav candy company, the state news agency Tanjug reported.
   Also for the first time in four decades, Bulgarian radio and TV
broadcast the speech of Christmas and New Year by the head of the
Bulgarian Orthodox Church, Patriarch Maxim.
   It was a working day in Bulgaria, ``but people are wishing merry
Christmas to each other, maybe for the first time without fear that
they would be accused of being `religious,''' the state news agency
BTA reported.
   In the Baltics, which have large populations of Roman Catholics
and Protestants, all offices were closed for the first official
Dec. 25 holiday in the four decades of Soviet rule there.
   In Vilnius, the capital of Lithuania, Roman Catholic activist
Antanas Terleskas said many people attended church on Christmas
Eve. But he said people were not especially happy, because ``the
freedom of expressing religious beliefs is just an illusion we are
permitted to toy with.''
   Estonians watched religious programs with Christmas carols on
TV, as well as the pope's Mass. It also was seen in Latvia, where
all TV and radio programs were religious oriented.
   Christmas in most of the vast Soviet Union will be celebrated
Jan. 7, according to the Russian Orthodox calendar.
   In London, Queen Elizabeth II spoke in her annual Christmas
broadcast about ``the exciting news'' that the barriers were coming
down in Europe and people in the East and West were beginning to
think about their future as neighbors.
   ``It would be splendid to think that in the last years of the
20th century Christ's message about loving our neighbors as
ourselves might at last be heeded,'' she said.
   In Bethlehem, Christians from around the world prayed at the
site of Jesus' birth, but it was a subdued Christmas overshadowed
by the Palestinian uprising in the Israeli-occupied West Bank.
   In Lebanon, newspapers, radio and TV stations released
morale-boosting messages to eight American hostages, but there was
no way of knowing if the messages reached them. Terry Anderson,
chief Middle East correspondent of The Associated Press, and
educator Thomas Sutherland marked their fifth Christmas in
captivity.
   The Americans are among 18 foreign hostages in Lebanon, most
believed held by Shiite Moslem extremists. Anderson was abducted
March 16, 1985.
   South African Archbishop Desmond Tutu worshiped at the Anglican
St. George's church in Jerusalem's Arab sector. He was criticized
by Christian and Jewish leaders for supporting the creation of a
Palestinian state.
   ``But we say also, dear brothers and sisters, the Jews have a
right to their independent state as well,'' Tutu said.
   Philippine President Corazon Aquino urged her countrymen to
``regain the momentum'' lost in the recent coup attempt, as
thousands of candles flickered in front of homes, businesses and
military camps in a Christmas Day plea for peace.
   About 200 Cambodian refugees prayed for peace in their village
of exile in Thailand, Site B, exactly 11 years after Vietnam
invaded their homeland and started the continuing civil war.
   ``I pray to God that I can go back to my country,'' said Sau
Rany, 22, a religion teacher who wants to be a nun.
</TEXT>

</DOC>