<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0025EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     12-27 0353</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0367</SECOND>
<HEAD>On the Light Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Caesar glowered amid the holiday cheer.
   The gorilla clambered up the rocks and squatted, turning out his
lower lip in displeasure as the family ate its presents and a few
trees on Tuesday.
   Caesar's gloom was probably caused by a cold, but if the illness
was catching, his disposition wasn't. The rest of the gorilla
family and the family in the compound next door smelled the roses
and promptly ate them.
   The two families of gorillas at the Los Angeles Zoo were
released from their quarters at midmorning to find their compounds
were strewn with popcorn balls, cranberries, bougainvilleas,
rawhide chews and fruit.
   Banana trees decorated with purple, orange and yellow roses and
sprinkled with coconut snow stood outside the grottos, with boxed
presents all around.
   Burlap stockings were placed by the rocks with care, filled with
nuts and squash and all sorts of goodies.
   The holiday party was the work of volunteers from the Gorilla
Garden, which grows supplemental foods for the zoo's dozen gorillas.
   ``They enjoy it because a lot of their really special favorite
treats are out there,'' said Jennifer Chatfield, the gorillas'
keeper. ``They also have some things they don't usually get _ like
a whole banana tree.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NANAIMO, British Columbia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dave Lebiuk says he swims only
once a year _ the day after Christmas _ so he likes to make it last.
   That's why he was the last person out of the water Tuesday
during the annual ``polar bear'' swim at this Vancouver Island
city. The 35-year-old spent 30 minutes in the 50-degree waters of
Departure Bay.
   ``I started four years ago or more and I just keep doing it,''
he said as he dried off before heading for a hot tub set up on the
beach.
   The 196 participants who braved the chilly waters ranged in age
from 2-year-old Mary Rice to 76-year-old Patrick O'Rooney.
   Swimmers receive a silver dollar and polar bear pin for their
efforts.
   ``It's fun, but I think they're crazy,'' said 12-year-old Esther
McDonnall, who was visiting from Australia.
</TEXT>

</DOC>