<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1546EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BeckettAppreciation     12-26 0658</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Beckett Appreciation,0667</SECOND>
<HEAD>An Enigmatic Playwright of Dark Despair</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Obit-Beckett, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL KUCHWARA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Drama Critic</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Samuel Beckett repeatedly refused to explain his
own work, leaving it to critics and audiences to interpret, puzzle
over and argue about the writings of one of the 20th century's
greatest playwrights.
   ``I meant what I said,'' was all he would ever offer about a
body of work that encompassed the darkest of despair about the
human condition in scores of plays, novels and poems that defied
convention.
   He didn't write plots. He didn't construct plays with stories to
tell. His masterpiece was ``Waiting for Godot,'' the tale of two
tramp-like figures, Estragon and Vladimir, waiting for the
mysterious Godot, who never arrives. It had no beginning and no
end. Futility and funny business exist side by side. When asked for
a summary of the play, the great clown Bert Lahr, who played
Estragon on Broadway, said simply, ``It's about two bums.''
   The play's history in the United States mirrors Beckett's
gradual acceptance by American critics and audiences. In early
1956, it had a disastrous tryout in Florida where two-thirds of the
opening-night audience walked out after the first act. ``Playing
`Waiting for Godot' in Miami was like doing `Giselle' at
Roseland,'' Lahr said later.
   Partially recast and with a new director, the play opened on
Broadway to widely divergent reaction. Columnist Walter Winchell
vilified it. Audiences were mystified, and so were many of the
reviewers. Critic Brooks Atkinson called it ``a mystery wrapped in
an enigma,'' adding that ``Theatergoers can rail at it, but they
cannot ignore it.'' But ``Waiting for Godot'' folded after a run of
only 59 performances.
   ``It has taken the world a little while to catch up with Sam
Beckett,'' said Alvin Epstein, who was in the original Broadway
production of ``Godot.'' ``The source of his greatness is that he
tapped into the universal unconscious of Western society in the
20th century. He expressed something so deeply felt by people who
were shook up by war, destruction and technology. He was not really
a writer, he was a visionary.''
   Thirty-two years later, there were no quibbles about ``Waiting
for Godot'' when Mike Nichols directed an all-star version starring
Steve Martin and Robin Williams at New York's Lincoln Center.
Whatever their thoughts about the particular production, critics
and audiences embraced the play as a modern masterpiece.
   Beckett's influence on other playwrights was enormous. Edward
Albee, Harold Pinter, David Mamet and particularly Tom Stoppard, in
his ``Rosencrantz and Guildenstern are Dead,'' acknowledged
Beckett's hold over them in his use of language, time and images.
   Beckett's plays are filled with indelible images, most of them
of people trapped, unable to move or even sometimes to speak. In
``Endgame,'' one character cannot sit, another cannot stand, while
two more are encased in trashcans. In ``Rockaby,'' an old woman,
rocking slowly in a chair, confronts death. In ``Play,'' three
voices are imprisoned in large earthen jars. In ``Happy Days,'' a
woman is buried up to her neck in sand.
   As he grew older, his plays became more minimalistic _ and more
nihilistic. In ``Acts Without Words,'' he wrote a play with no
dialogue, only sounds. In ``Not I,'' a one-character play he wrote
for actress Billie Whitelaw, only the outline of the draped
performer is visible with a spotlight focused on her mouth.
   ``He was to playwriting what Einstein was to physics in the 20th
century,'' said Gregory Mosher, artistic director of the Lincoln
Center Theater. ``After he figured out what he did, which seems so
simple and obvious because it was so true, nothing ever was the
same afterwards. It's the idea that all that's left to us is trying
to live a decent life in a world that has gone completely nuts.
Take Woody Allen's great joke: `90 percent of life is just showing
up.' That's a line straight out of Samuel Beckett.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>