<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0216 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1948EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-PhysicianKickbacks     12-28 0519</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Physician Kickbacks,1st Ld-Writethru, f0283,0533</SECOND>
<HEAD>SmithKline Agrees to Pay $1.5 Million to Settle Kickback Investigation</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: ADDS 2 grafs to UPDATE with comment from labs; ``Patric'' in
penultimate graf is cq.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL PAGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   SmithKline Beecham Clinical Laboratories Inc.
has agreed to pay $1.5 million to settle a federal investigation of
alleged kickbacks for physicians who referred Medicare and Medicaid
business to the company, the government said Thursday.
   The Department of Health and Human Services' inspector general
found that more than 100 physicians were investors in three
California laboratories managed by the company.
   The inspector general's office said the arrangement under which
doctors were recruited as investors and lab profits were
distributed to those same doctors violated a federal law
prohibiting payments intended to induce referrals of Medicaid and
Medicare patients.
   The $1.5 million settlement was the largest ever made under the
law, the inspector general's office said.
   SmithKline spokeswoman Tobey Dichter said the settlement ``is an
agreement that was reached to avoid costly litigation and
disruption to our business.
   ``It is not an admission of liability in any way. We say there
was no wrongdoing. We believe it is an ambiguous statute,'' she
said.
   The inspector general proposed the three laboratories be barred
permanently from participating in Medicare, Medicaid, Social
Security and California health care programs and that some
individuals and companies linked to the labs be barred for several
years.
   The inspector general's office said the arrangement cost the
federal health care programs an unspecified amount of money.
   ``Our studies have shown that with this type of arrangement
there is a significant amount of overutilization by those
doctors,'' said D. McCarty Thornton, chief of litigation in the
inspector general's office. Doctors ordering unecessary tests
``does cost the program significant amounts of money,'' he said.
   The company agreed to cooperate in the continuing investigation.
The inspector general's office said documents on agreements the
company has with 56 other physician-owned laboratories indicate
there may be other illegal arrangements.
   ``Physicians referring (business) to entities in which they have
an ownership interest and contractual arrangements such as those
involved here are very common in the industry,'' the inspector
general's office said in a statement.
   The labs covered in the settlement were established by the
Hanlester Network of Santa Ana, Calif. SmithKline Beecham Clinical
Laboratories Inc., based in King of Prussia, Pa., contracted to
manage the facilities.
   Under the inspector general's recommendation, the Pacific
Physicians Clinical Laboratory Ltd. of Santa Ana, the Omni
Physicians Clinical Laboratory Ltd. of Pasadena and the Placer
Physicians Clinical Laboratory Ltd. of Sacramento would be barred
from the various government health care programs.
   Patric Hooper, a Los Angeles lawyer representing the three labs,
said they will challenge the HHS attempt to bar them from the
programs on the ground that the department lacks authority to take
the action.
   He added that payments to the physician-investors were based on
amount of ownership, not on referrals, and that the investment was
marketed to physicians because they ``have an interest in
maintaining the quality of the laboratory to which they send a
specimen.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>