<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0135 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 2027EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NoriegaAttorney     12-28 0356</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Noriega Attorney,0366</SECOND>
<HEAD>Member of Noriega Defense Team Says He Wants Out</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILL LESTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An attorney representing Manuel Antonio Noriega on
federal drug charges said Thursday he is unhappy with public
discussions of the case by other members of the defense team and
has asked to withdraw from the case.
   Neal Sonnett of Miami said one of the reasons for his request is
his disagreement with the other attorneys ``over some of the
statements to the media.'' He said he would prefer not to go into
detail or discuss the other reasons.
   ``It was a question of drawing the line between function as a
lawyer and a general spokesperson,'' he told The Associated Press.
``I didn't really want to create a firestorm. There have been other
conflicts between me and co-counsel but nothing I feel is
appropriate to discuss.
   ``I have consistently refused to comment on Panamanian affairs _
they are outside my responsibility. It's important for me to
practice law.''
   Sonnett made the announcement official Wednesday in a five-page
motion asking the U.S. District Court here to allow him to quit the
case.
   Two of the three other Noriega attorneys reacted with surprise
to Sonnett's motion. Both Frank Rubino and Raymond Takiff said they
had experienced no conflict. Attorney Steve Kollin said he had no
comment.
   ``We've had no problems whatsoever, just general differences of
opinion,'' Takiff said.
   He said he found it puzzling, especially after Sonnett recently
appeared on CNN to talk about Noriega.
   ``It's just too hot in the kitchen,'' Takiff said.
   Sonnett denied he had talked about the deposed Panamanian
dictator on the news show. He said he appeared as president of the
National Association of Criminal Defense Lawyers to talk about
forfeiture of attorney's fees.
   A February 1988 indictment accuses Noriega and 14 others of
running drugs into the United States and using Panama as a safe
haven.
   Noriega, driven from power in a U.S. invasion of Panama last
week, is currently seeking asylum at the papal embassy in Panama
City while the U.S. government attempts to negotiate his
extradition.
</TEXT>

</DOC>