<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0138EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-RogerPorter     12-27 0774</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Roger Porter,760</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Domestic Policy Adviser Takes `Honest Broker' Approach</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RITA BEAMISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   He is President Bush's top adviser on domestic
issues _ from gun control to clean air _ a veteran of three
presidencies who knows government inside out and is such a
workaholic he sometimes sleeps in his White House office.
   From Roger Porter's arrival at the White House on the same day
Richard Nixon left office in scandal, through every Republican
administration since, he has had a hand in crafting policies that
affect millions of Americans.
   Today as Bush's domestic policy adviser, he is the presidential
assistant who reigns over issues such as child care, the drug war,
education and auto pollution.
   But Porter's is a name little known to most Americans.
   ``He doesn't like to hog attention,'' says White House legal
counsel C. Boyden Gray, adding, ``Don't mistake that for lack of
influence or lack of force.''
   The president typically consults with Porter on a daily basis
for what some describe as Porter's ``honest broker'' approach to
sifting through competing policy options.
   He is Bush's intermediary to interest groups, members of
Congress and government agencies that want to sell their side of a
given issue.
   He also gives speeches on administration policy, with a
methodical style recalling his days as a Rhodes scholar and
professor of government and politics at Harvard and Oxford.
   But his low-key image belies a tough-minded dealer who is
fiercely protective of Bush's interests, associates say.
   ``I found Roger to be cautious. He likes you to verify
everything,'' said Dewey Stokes, head of the Fraternal Order of
Police, who sought Bush's support for a waiting period and
background check for gun purchasers.
   That idea was rejected. And under Porter's guidance, other ideas
for Bush's much-proclaimed ``kinder, gentler'' America have been
muted along the way.
   As the administration point man at the education summit with
Bush and the nation's governors, Porter ensured joint endorsement
of results-oriented education without committing Washington to
specific spending.
   While he led the administration's drive for a new clean air
package that went well beyond President Reagan's stringency, it
didn't quite measure up to the aspirations of environmental groups.
   Perhaps because he tries to give Bush a balanced view of all
viable policy options, Porter is seen by some as a weaker adviser
than might be expected of his position.
   One White House colleague said Porter's effectiveness is
dampened by White House Chief of Staff John Sununu's unquestioned
dominance, making it impossible for Porter to assume a larger role.
   Asked if that is true, Porter says he is ``quite happy to be
part of a collegial effort.''
   ``I don't go out and do things that I'm not going to discuss
with him, but he gives me a lot of latitude,'' he said, referring
to Sununu.
   Porter, who often spends the night in his White House office,
admits to being a workaholic and ``a bit of a perfectionist.''
   ``I have never regretted the extra effort. ... I know I'm not
going to be doing this for the rest of my life,'' he said. ``I view
it as a rare opportunity.''
   His introduction to the White House came Aug. 9, 1974. Arriving
from Harvard to start work as a White House fellow, Porter recalls,
he ran into his new boss, then-Vice President Ford, at the elevator.
   Ford greeted him somewhat distractedly and headed off to his
historic final Oval Office meeting with Nixon, Porter recalled.
   Later that day, a Ford aide assigned Porter to be the secretary
of Ford's transition team. He helped write a report based on
interviews with all the Cabinet members and senior players in
government.
   Under Ford, Porter had a variety of jobs including special
assistant to the president and executive secretary to the Economic
Policy Board. During the Reagan administration he also held several
White House jobs, including director of the Office of Policy
Development.
   Porter me Bush over tennis, a game for which both share a
passion and considerable skill. Ford had just named Bush to be his
CIA director and invited both men to play on the White House courts.
   Porter says he can tell a lot about a person from his tennis
game. About Bush, he said: ``One thing I look for is how they call
the lines ... In all the time I've played with Bush over a 15-year
period, I have never once had occasion to question his line calls.
He is scrupulously honest.''
   Other Bush tennis traits, Porter said, are patience, persistence
and strategy, reflecting a methodical approach in how he approaches
other things as well.
</TEXT>

</DOC>