<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0440EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-PanamaReax 1stLd-Writethru a0498 12-20 0429</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama Reax, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0498,420</SECOND>
<HEAD>EDS: Adds additional quotes throughout; no pickup</HEAD>
<HEAD>Dole, Helms, Dodd React To Panama Military Operation</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DIANE DUSTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As first word circulated concerning the
American military against Panama's Manuel Noriega, Senate
Republican leader Robert Dole said early Wednesday he expects
bipartisan support for President Bush's commitment of troops in
Panama City.
   ``We need to see how it plays out,'' said Dole in a telephone
interview with The Associated Press. ``I would guess there would be
widespread bipartisan support for the president.''
   Said Sen. Jesse Helms, R-N.C., ranking Republican on the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee, ``The majority of the Senate will feel
good by this turn of events. Certainly I feel a lot better.''
   ``I called to tell the president, `my complements to the
chef,''' he said in a telephone interview from his home in Raleigh,
N.C. He said he had been briefed on the operation just prior to the
White House news conference announcing the military mission.
   Immediate congressional reaction was limited because Congress is
in recess and the White House announced its action at 1 a.m.
   Dole said Bush called him shortly before the early morning White
House news conference announcing the military mission.
   He said the White House also was trying to reach Senate Majority
Leader George Mitchell, D-Maine, who was in Mexico meeting with
President Carlos Salinas de Gortari, but Dole did not know if
they'd gotten to him before the public announcment.
   Sen. Christopher Dodd, D-Conn., chairman of the Senate Foreign
Relations subcommittee on the Western Hemisphere, also was briefed
about the operation.
   ``We don't believe it would be appropriate to comment at this
point,'' he said through his aide Jason Isaacson.
   Issacson said Dodd spoke to Secretary of State James Baker and
``is monitoring these events very closely. He is also making calls
to other people in the region.''
   Dodd has been generally supportive of President Bush actions
concerning Noriega.
   Dole said he met with the elected Panamanian officials Dec. 10
and ``they were in effect pleading with us to do something'' about
Noriega.
   Helms said he has confidence in the leaders of Panama sworn in
Tuesday night under American auspices, and said he has no plans to
bring up measures in the Senate calling for the abdication of the
Canal Treaties negotiated by former President Jimmy Carter, even
though he contines to oppose the treaties.
   ``I believe them to be sensible, rational people and some of my
concern about the United States surrendering the canal has been
diminished,'' said Helms.
</TEXT>

</DOC>