<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0104 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1831EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WeatherpageWeather     12-30 0389</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0403</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rain From Texas to Mid-Atlantic Coast, Snow Further North</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Rain fell from Texas to the Middle Atlantic coast Saturday while
freezing rain and snow stretched further north from New England to
the Plains and parts of the Rockies.
   A flash flood watch was posted over a portion of east-central
Texas. Almost 4 inches of rain fell overnight at Broaddus, and rain
continued to fall Saturday morning.
   Nearly an inch of rain fell at Monroe, La., in the six hours
ended at 1 p.m. EST, while two-thirds of an inch and more fell at
Little Rock and Jonesboro, Ark.
   Flash flood watches also were posted through the night for
Kentucky and much of West Virginia.
   Snowfall amounts were modest in most places, although Hartford,
Conn., and parts of northern Pennsylvania received about 4 inches
overnight and up to 5 inches fell Saturday morning near New
Mexico's Red River.
   A winter storm watch was posted into Sunday for the Texas Big
Bend region.
   Late in the morning, snow was falling in central and southern
New England, southeast New York state, northwest Iowa, western
Wisconsin, much of Minnesota, eastern North Dakota, eastern and
central South Dakota, south-central Kansas, southeast Colorado,
southern Wyoming and north-central Utah.
   Freezing rain, often mixed with snow, fell in parts of
Pennsylvania, northern Illinois, southeast Wisconsin, southern
Minnesota, Iowa, northwest Missouri, eastern and north-central
Kansas, eastern Nebraska and northwest Texas.
   Rain was falling in north-central Texas, northern Alabama,
northern Georgia, western South Carolina, northern North Carolina,
Virginia, Delaware, Maryland, New Jersey, West Virginia, Kentucky,
northwest Indiana, the rest of Illinois and southeast Missouri.
   Rain and occasional thunderstorms were scattered over Arkansas,
western Mississippi, northern Louisiana and east-central Texas.
   Caribou, Maine, had its coldest December reading on record with
an early morning low of 31 degrees below zero. That shattered the
old record of 26 below in 1975.
   Bakersfield, Calif., had a morning low of 28 degrees. It was the
18th day this month with a low below the freezing point, exceeding
the previous record of 13 December days with freezing temperatures
in 1949.
   The low temperature for the Lower 48 states Saturday morning was
34 degrees below zero at Houlton, Maine.
   Temperatures at 3 p.m. EST ranged from 2 degrees at Massena,
N.Y., to 81 degrees at Fort Myers, Fla.
</TEXT>

</DOC>