<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1041EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-MailBombs 1stLd-Writethru a0474 12-29 0739</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mail Bombs, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0474,0755</SECOND>
<HEAD>Responsibility Claimed in Mail Bombings; More Killing Threatened</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS grafs 6-7 with 4 grafs to UPDATE with newspaper reporting
that new letter contains same identifying codes as other letters, other
details. Picks up 8th graf, `In its evening...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SONYA ROSS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A group claiming responsibility for bombs that
killed a federal judge and a civil rights lawyer threatened in a
letter full of racial invective to assassinate two NAACP officials
``as part of the same reprisal.''
   In a letter to WAGA-TV, an organization calling itself Americans
for a Competent Federal Judicial System also threatened to kill
lawyers, judges and members of the National Association for the
Advancement of Colored People ``any time a black man rapes a white
woman.''
   The threatened reprisals led black leaders to bolster security
plans for the Jan. 15 celebration of slain civil rights leader
Martin Luther King Jr.'s birthday.
   Precautions were being taken at the 600 southeastern branches of
the NAACP, said Earl Shinhoster, the organization's regional
director. He declined to say what those precautions were.
   An FBI official said he believed the letter was authentic
because it contained information available only to someone closely
associated with the construction and mailing of the bombs that
killed 11th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals Judge Robert S. Vance at
his home near Birmingham, Ala., on Dec. 16 and Savannah attorney
Robert Robinson two days later.
   William L. Hinshaw, agent in charge of the FBI investigation,
would not specify what that information is.
   ``It opens a new door, and we hope through that door will pass
information from the public,'' he said.
   Authorities are unfamiliar with the group, Hinshaw said.
   The Atlanta Constitution, in today's editions, quoted
unidentified sources as saying the letter contained the same
identifying code as the previous letters and that physical evidence
links all of the letters to the bombs. The newspaper did not
elaborate.
   In its evening broadcasts Thursday, WAGA-TV released excerpts of
the letter, which said the group held a secret meeting Dec. 19 in
Montgomery, Ala., after the two fatal bombings.
   According to the station, the letter said group members from
Georgia, Florida and Alabama gathered ``to draft new orders'' and
to go public with their mission.
   The group claimed it ``assassinated Judge Robert S. Vance and
attorney Robert Robinson in reprisal for atrocities committed on
Julie Love,'' a white woman who was robbed, raped and murdered in
Atlanta in 1988.
   The letter also said: ``Two more prominent members of the NAACP
shall be assassinated, using more sophisticated means, as part of
the same reprisal.''
   The letter expressed anger over school desegregation cases,
apparently referring to a long-running battle over the DeKalb
County, Ga., schools in which the slain judge was involved.
   ``Protecting the innocent warrants a higher court priority than
granting the blacks' demand for white teachers for their
children,'' the letter said.
   Vance was on the 11th U.S. Circuit Court panel that directed
DeKalb schools to transfer about 120 veteran teachers from
predominantly white schools to predominantly black ones in an
effort to balance teacher experience in the system.
   Robinson handled a desegregation case in Savannah, and another
school desegregation case came out of Jacksonville, Fla., where a
bomb was delivered to NAACP headquarters. That bomb and one sent to
the 11th Circuit building in Atlanta were safely removed.
   ``Anytime a black man rapes a white woman in Alabama, Florida or
Georgia in the future, Americans for a Competent Federal Judicial
System shall assassinate one federal judge, one attorney and one
officer of the NAACP,'' the letter said.
   It cited the slaying of Ms. Love, 27, who disappeared July 11,
1988, after her car ran out of gas. Her remains were found a little
more than a year later, in a wooded lot near an inner-city
neighborhood.
   Two young black men _ Emmanuel Fitzgerald Hammond, 24, and
William Maurice Porter, 20 _ have been charged in the slaying.
Porter pleaded guilty in November and is expected to testify
against Hammond.
   ``It's very difficult to react,'' the NAACP's Shinhoster said.
``The threats against the NAACP and others contained in that
communication must be taken seriously. We've already had two
decent, fine individuals murdered by that group.''
   Walter Morrison, a spokesman at the NAACP's Baltimore
headquarters, said the group wasn't intimidated by the action.
   ``We've indicated that we will not be deterred,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>