<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1015EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Romania-Reax 1stLd-Writethru a0501 12-26 0569</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Reax, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0501,0578</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Leaders Backed, But Some Say Mistake Not To Publicly Try Ceausescus</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 12 grafs to UPDATE with British recognition, Iran
dismissing ambassador, Soviets calling execution an internal affair; picks
up 12th pvs, `On Monday...'; Minor editing thereafter to CONFORM</HEAD>
<BYLINE>With PM-Romania, Bjt ^By MICHAEL WEST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   China and Iran, which had cordial ties with
Romanian dictator Nicolae Ceausescu, today joined countries
including the United States and Soviet Union that have pledged
support for Romania's new leadership.
   But the United States and some other governments regretted that
Ceausescu and his wife, Elena, who were executed in Romania on
Monday after a secret military trial, were not tried publicly.
   The Soviet Foreign Ministry called the executions an internal
affair. Spokesman Vadim Perfiliev said the decision ``has probably
been made taking into account the aspirations and will of the
Romanian people.''
   The Dutch government said it was ``concerned'' that the
Ceausescus had been executed after a secret trial and expressed
hope that ``the high principles of the rule of law will find their
place in the new Romania for which so many have fought to the
utmost.''
   In Britain, a Foreign Office spokesman said normal accepted
standards were difficult during ``a civil war situation.''
``Although one may regret a secret trial, at the time it was not
really surprising,'' said a Foreign Office spokesman, who by custom
was not identified.
   ``Dracula Executed,'' blared the banner headline in Britain's
Daily Mirror. ``Tyrants are Executed,'' said the rival Daily
Express.
   Britain, China, Greece and Iran today joined at least 13 other
nations in pledging support for Romania's provisional government,
which took over after Ceausescu fled the capital in a helicopter on
Friday.
   The Beijing government also said the Red Cross Society of China
would provide immediate humanitarian aid, but it did not elaborate.
   Ceausescu was esteemed by Chinese leaders for maintaining good
relations with Beijing over the decades when China and the rest of
the Soviet bloc viewed each other with hostility.
   Ceausescu was one of the few socialist leaders to praise the
Chinese leadership's crackdown of the student-led pro-democracy
movement in June, when hundreds, perhaps thousands were killed by
troops in the streets of Beijing.
   Iran said today it recognized the Romanian government and Tehran
Radio said Iran's Red Crescent Society was ready to send medical
aid. But it dismissed its ambassador to Bucharest for failing to
inform Tehran of growing opposition to Ceausescu before the
Romanian leader visited Iran last week.
   The United States and France said Saturday they would not oppose
Soviet bloc intervention to support Romanians fighting against
police units loyal to Ceausescu, but the Soviet Foreign Ministry
spokesman said Monday the provisional government had not for Soviet
support.
   On Monday, food and medical aid began to flow into the hard-hit
country.
   French education minister Lionel Jospin said on French
television Monday night: ``Perhaps one would have wished that
Ceausescu could have been judged and said what he had to say.
Naturally we prefer public trials, but these are tragic and at the
same time very hopeful events we are seeing now in Romania.''
   Philippine President Corazon Aquino said: ``The staggeringly
high number of casualties reported in Romania is truly shocking and
deplorable. We join the rest of the world in wishing that country
and its people the blessings of peace, freedom and well-being.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>