<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0020EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-SellingVanGogh     12-18 0767</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Selling Van Gogh,0793</SECOND>
<HEAD>Entrepreneurs Cash In On Van Gogh Centennial</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ABNER KATZMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AMSTERDAM, Netherlands (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   If Vincent van Gogh had the
marketing pizazz of the entrepreneurs cashing in on his centennial,
he probably wouldn't have died a penniless suicide.
   As the Van Gogh 1990 Foundation prepares a multi-media
extravaganza here marking the 100th anniversary of the artist's
death, merchandisers are capitalizing on the event with everything
from wine to ties bearing his name or image.
   The commercialization has not pleased either the foundation or
Van Gogh's family.
   ``It is not to our taste,'' grandnephew Johan van Gogh told The
Associated Press.
   The government-backed foundation is preparing the biggest-ever
van Gogh show, with almost 200 works loaned from more than 50
countries for an exhibition opening on his birthday, March 30.
   The official commemoration has the support of the van Gogh
family.
   ``We are going to give Vincent van Gogh a high quality
commemoration,'' said foundation spokeswoman Madeleine A.
Wardenaar. ``We want him to be respected as a Dutch artist.''
   ``We're not doing this as a business,'' added foundation
financial advisor J. Rooyackers.
   But many others are.
   Chief among them is Amsterdam dentist Jacob G. Dekker, whose Van
Gogh International has registered the name Vincent van Gogh as a
trademark ``in just about every country you can think of except
Timbuktu'' for a variety of products.
   His flagship line of ``Vincent van Gogh'' perfumes and colognes
has a floral fragrance to remind buyers of works like the
``Sunflowers'' series and ``Irises,'' which holds the art auction
record of $53 million.
   Other commemmorative products Dekker has licensed include pen
sets, watches, compact discs of music composed by van Gogh
contemporaries Debussy, Ravel and Chausson, and T-shirts, scarves
and ties decorated with van Gogh scenes.
   Dekker projects total centennial year sales of about $75 million
worldwide. He says he registered the trademark five years ago,
without a thought to the centennial.
   ``The idea was to find a (product) name that everyone knows
worldwide, so you don't have to spend millions establishing a
name,'' Dekker told the AP.
   For those who take van Gogh slightly more seriously than to dab
him behind their ears or tie him around their necks, the U.S.-based
Franklin Mint is issuing a ``limited edition'' bronze commemorative
medallion for $150.
   American Express Netherlands is offering an 8-inch bronze bust
of van Gogh for $488. Its manufacturer, Barcelona-based Vincent
Fine Art, is also hawking van Gogh reproductions and commemorative
bottles of Spanish champagn.
   The commercial hoopla has created frictions between the
entrepreneurs and organizations like the centennial foundation,
which see themselves as trying in vain to shield an artistic giant
from crass commercialism.
   ``When I offered my products to the gift shop of the Van Gogh
Museum, they treated me like a stray dog,'' said Dekker.
   The foundation has, for example, refused endorsements such as
one for a line of curtains embossed with van Gogh sunflowers.
   ``We try to discourage people. We don't like the publicity it
gets, but we cannot control it,'' said Ms. Wardenaar, since both
the artist's name and his works are in the public domain.
   ``They can do what they like. We have not much to say about
it,'' said Johan van Gogh, grandson of the artist's brother Theo.
   Johan chairs the family-run Vincent van Gogh Foundation, which
owns more than one hundred works on permanent loan to the Van Gogh
museum here, the world's largest single collection.
   At issue is one of this nation's greatest cultural icons, a
minister's son whose early works reflected the grinding poverty of
19th century rural Dutch life. Foremost among them is ``The Potato
Eaters,'' depicting a farming family with grotesquely pinched
features gathered around their meager supper.
   It was only during his later French period that Van Gogh bloomed
with the vibrant colors that have gilded the auction gavel.
   The irony is that the world's best-selling artist sold only one
single painting himself.
   After his descent into mental illness, Van Gogh fatally shot
himself in July 1890 at the age of 37.
   The centennial foundation is pushing ahead with events it claims
will nurture interest in the artist without exploiting him.
   A van Gogh opera will premiere in Amsterdam, a commemorative
medal will be issued, a film festival screened, and a poetry book
published with the poems of 20 Dutch and Belgian poets commissioned
in his honor.
   Commemorative posters by 20 contemporary artists, including
Czechoslovak Jiri Kolar, Dutchman Willem de Kooning and American
Roy Lichtenstein have been run off to help offset the $11.5 million
exhibition cost.
</TEXT>

</DOC>