<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1335EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-US-Romania     12-19 0305</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-Romania,300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Administration Condemns Use of Police Force in Romania</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERENCE HUNT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bush administration today condemned the
``brutal use of police force'' in Romania and said the United
States was consulting with allies about the possibility of sending
independent observers to see what was happening.
   ``The repressive measures undertaken by the Romanian government
are totally unjustified and stand in stark contrast to the positive
changes taking place elsewhere in Eastern Europe,'' said White
House press secretary Marlin Fitzwater.
   ``The United States condemns the brutal use of police force by
the Romanian government,'' Fitzwater said.
   Romania has virtually sealed off its borders, but witnesses say
security forces have shot and killed dozens of people in
anti-government rioting that began over the weekend.
   Unconfirmed reports have put the death toll at up to 400 and one
witness was quoted as saying he saw helicopters fire on crowds in
the city of Timisoara.
   ``The demonstrations in Timisoara and elsewhere were a result of
the systematic denial of human rights to the people of Romania,
particularly to members of the Hungarian minority,'' Fitzwater said.
   He said the United States was calling on the government ``to
cease this brutal repression, open its borders and respect the
human rights commitments of the Helsinki Final Act.''
   Moreover, he said the United States was urging Romania to allow
international observers to visit Timisoara and other cities where
violence has been reported. On that point, Fitzwater said the
United States was consulting with allies in hopes of getting an
independent verfication of what was transpiring.
   Fitzwater said there is a provision under the 35-nation
Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe that allows member
countries to verify independently events in other participating
states. Both Romania and the United States are members of the
conference.
</TEXT>

</DOC>