<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0277 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 2138EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f BC-WeeklyCommodities Adv23-24   12-22 0895</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Weekly Commodities, Adv 23-24,0923</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv23</HEAD>
<HEAD>$adv24</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Weekend Editions Dec. 23-24</HEAD>
<HEAD>Orange Juice and Heating Oil Jump Because of Cold Wave</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID DISHNEAU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Speculators in orange juice and heating oil futures are having
an especially merry Christmas because of a record-busting cold
front that prompted fears of a Florida freeze and created spot
shortages of fuel.
   Most other commodity markets were fairly quiet ahead of the long
holiday weekend.
   Frozen concentrated orange juice for delivery in January settled
at $1.37 a pound Friday on the New York Cotton Exchange, about a 9
percent increase from $1.26 a pound a week earlier. The contract
traded as high as $1.4225 on Friday but finished the day with a
steep loss as traders took pre-weekend profits.
   On the New York Mercantile Exchange, heating oil for January
delivery rose 16 percent to 81.74 cents a gallon from 70.42 cents.
   The dramatic rise in both markets was almost entirely due to the
relentless southerly advance of a cold air mass that meteorologists
rated as one of the most intense of this decade.
   The leading edge of the chill that hit North Florida early
Friday was expected to bring near-record lows to the entire state,
including the citrus-growing region in the middle of the Florida
peninsula.
   About 85 percent of Florida's $1 billion-plus citrus crop is
still on the trees. The last major killing frost, on Christmas Day
1983, damaged at least 30 percent of the orange crop.
   Citrus specialists estimated less than 5 percent of the state's
700,000 acres of trees were protected by costly heaters or wind
blowers.
   But the 1983 freeze and another in 1985 prompted citrus growers
to shift production further south. So while the projected lows of
15 to 29 degrees in the citrus belt would be enough to damage
fruit, analysts said the damage would probably be less severe than
six years ago.
   ``The situation was quite different in 1983,'' said Celeste
Georkakis, an analyst with Cargill Investor Services Inc. ``If the
groves were where they were then, we'd have the same effect, but
they aren't.''
   This year's Florida orange crop is projected at 133 million
boxes vs. 170 million in 1983. But Brazil has since become a major
producer of orange juice and is expected to harvest a record large
crop this year.
   Therefore, Ms. Georkakis said, any frost-damage shortfall in
U.S. production can be made up with Brazilian imports, reducing
excess supplies on the world market.
   Some heating oil suppliers in the Northeast reported temporary
outages in the past week as the region counted its 24th straight
day Friday of below-normal temperatures.
   Star Enterprise, a Texaco Inc. affiliate, said sales of home
heating oil were running 50 percent above projections for the month
of December. Exxon USA said it had limited oil customers to amounts
specified in purchase contracts.
   The extraordinary domestic demand extended to six weeks a
heating-oil price rally that ran its first leg on concerns about
supplies of fuel oil in Europe.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Precious metals</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Gold and silver futures fell slightly in a week of lackluster
trading on New York's Commodity Exchange. Even the U.S. invastion
of Panama failed to create much excitement in the gold market,
which usually advances when international tensions rise. After
climbing sharply last month, gold appeared stuck in a trading range
between $400 and $420 an ounce.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Grains and soybeans</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Soybean futures sank on the Chicago Board of Trade as growing
conditions improved in Brazil, a leading soybean producer. Almost
all of the Brazilian soybean crop has been sown. Corn futures rose
slightly as foreign demand picked up. Wheat was little changed.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Livestock and meat</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Livestock futures were little changed but the pork belly market
retreated for the fourth straight week amid continuing
disappointment over the government's slower-than-expected pace in
buying bellies to donate to Poland.
   Here are commodity price trends during the past week:
   Most grain and soybean futures retreated on the Chicago Board of
Trade.
   Wheat for delivery in March settled Friday at $4.11} a bushel,
unchanged from a week earlier; March corn slipped to $2.39 a bushel
from $2.40}; March oats slipped to $1.54\ a bushel from $1.55{;
January soybeans dropped to $5.72\ a bushel from $5.83\.
   Cattle futures rose on the Chicago Mercantile Exchange while
pork futures retreated.
   December live cattle rose for the third straight week, ending
Friday at 76.80 cents a pound compared with 76.07 cents; January
feeder cattle rose to 84.82 cents a pound from 84.27 cents;
February hogs dropped to 48.87 cents a pound from 49.17 cents;
February frozen pork bellies fell to 49.77 cents a pound from 51.42
cents, the fourth straight weekly decline for that market.
   Gold and silver futures retreated on New York's Commodity
Exchange.
   December gold fell to $413.20 a troy ounce from $413.90;
December silver fell for the fourth straight week, to $5.56 a troy
ounce from $5.607.
   Energy futures rose across the board on the New York Mercantile
Exchange, gasoline for the third week, crude oil for the fourth and
heating oil for the sixth week in a row.
   West Texas Intermediate crude oil for February delivery climbed
to $21.29 a barrel from $20.67; January heating oil surged to 81.74
cents a gallon from 70.42 cents; January unleaded gasoline rallied
to 55.45 cents a gallon from 52.80 cents.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End adv for weekend editions Dec. 23-24</NOTE>

</DOC>