<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0010EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Romania-Text     12-25 0601</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Text,0617</SECOND>
<HEAD>Text of National Salvation Committee Statement</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here, as carried by the Romanian news
agency Agerpres in its own translation, is the text of the
communique issued Sunday by the National Salvation Committee and
read by member Virgil Magureanu:
   The collapse of the hideous dictatorship of the Ceausescu clique
has added the last page to the bloodstained chronicle of the
suffering-filled years the Romanian people had to live. Declasse
and irresponsible elements still loyal to the tyrant have sought to
continue the terrorist practice of the old regime, resorting to
provocations, armed attacks on the civilian population, killing
indiscriminately unarmed people, attacking public institutions,
industrial enterprises, military objectives, trading units,
hospitals and dwellings.
   The Romanian people have once more proved their huge moral
power, released by their liberating will.
   The army have done their duty as have a large part of the staff
of the Ministry of the Interior.
   The revolution has triumphed.
   To the end of bringing the situation back to complete normalcy
and securing our free society, the Council of the Front of National
Salvation has decided to take exceptional measures, imperatively
demanded by the present moment:
   1. Total and immediate cessation of fire throughout the
country's territory. Whoever violates this order is guilty of
crimes against the Romanian people and is liable to be given the
... most merciless punishment. No drop of blood shall be shed any
longer.
   At the same time, any act of vandalism and destruction as well
as personal revenge are illegal and can only impair the nobleness
of our revolution.
   The guilt of the dictator and his former flunkies toward history
and law shall be decided by the court which will pass with all
strictness the punishments deserved for their action of destroying
the country.
   2. The army is the only possessor of weapons, the firm arm
defending the people's interests. All those who in the course of
these days have come into the possession of weapons and ammunition,
irrespective of circumstances, should urgently give them back, the
deadline for this action being Monday, Dec. 25, 5 p.m. All those
failing to comply with this are guilty of serious violation of
legality and shall be punished with utmost harshness.
   3. The units of the Ministry of the Interior shall be integrated
in the Ministry of National Defense which takes over the single
command of all the country's troops and combat means.
   The militia and firemen bodies preserve all their specific
duties which they should exercise with all firmness.
   4. Executives and all working people are called to secure the
protection of economic, commercial, health care, education, science
and cultural units. Romanian society should function normally by
the dedicated contribution of us.
   Likewise, we call on all our country fellows to support the
public order bodies in securing the integrity of the embassy
buildings and the immunity of diplomats.
   5. The bodies of the new structures of democracy should urgently
begin their activity for the country's reconstruction, establishing
themselves with firmness, immediately subordinating themselves to
the council and adopting together with it the political, social,
administrative and economic measures absolutely necessary for the
first stages of reconstruction.
   May the first free New Year bring to Romania, together with the
joy of liberation, the quiet and calm enabling us to assume all
responsibilities of a people asserting its dignity.
   The national consensus, the cooperation of the country's
creative forces, of all the social categories irrespective of
nationality, offer the vital condition and guarantee for the
attainment of the fundamental goals of the revolutionary process in
Romania.
</TEXT>

</DOC>