<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0121EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-RiotTrial-Police Bjt   12-26 0764</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Riot Trial-Police, Bjt,0791</SECOND>
<HEAD>Officer's Conviction Drives Ethnic Wedge Into Police Force</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: McMillian cq.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD COLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The manslaughter conviction of a Hispanic officer
in the deaths of two blacks had raised hopes for healing a decade
of racial tension. Instead, the verdict has spread tensions within
police ranks.
   Talk of a work slowdown by the police and an allegation that a
Hispanic policeman hesitated before responding to a backup request
from a black officer have embroiled the force in recent weeks.
   The local branch of the National Association for the Advancement
of Colored People even asked Gov. Bob Martinez on Friday to have
National Guardsmen patrol Miami's black neighborhoods.
   ``If I needed police protection, I would not feel comfortable
calling the police because of the attitude of some of the
officers,'' said the NAACP's Johnnie McMillian.
   Martinez rejected McMillian's request, and Mayor Xavier Suarez
and Police Chief Perry Anderson assured the community that officers
of all races would act professionally.
   Tensions have been evident since a jury found Colombian-born
officer William Lozano guilty Dec. 7 in the deaths of black
motorcyclist Clement Lloyd and his passenger, Allan Blanchard.
   During the past two weeks, an Hispanic Miami officer and a white
Metro-Dade policeman have been suspended for wearing black tape on
their badges or black wristbands to protest the verdict.
   The Police Benevolent Association has raised funds and presented
Lozano with a ``Brotherhood in Blue'' T-shirt _ a mocking reference
to the term prosecutors used during the trial to accuse officers of
protecting each other.
   Many black officers, however, agreed with the verdict and see
fund-raising, wristbands and clemency petitions as a slap in the
face.
   ``For the very people who uphold law and order, to take
exception in such a blatant manner, is extremely insensitive,''
said Officer Sam Harlan, head of the Black Officers Association.
   But to many other officers, Lozano is seen as a martyr to the
community's desperation to avoid a fifth race riot in the 1980s.
   Two previous disturbances followed acquittals of officers
charged with killing blacks, and the Jan. 16 deaths of Lloyd and
Blanchard ignited three days of riots.
   ``It wouldn't have made a difference whether he was Hispanic or
black _ he didn't receive a fair trial,'' said Martin Garcia, head
of the Hispanic Officer's Association.
   Garcia defended officers' action in support of Lozano. He said
some black officers cheered and gave each other high-fives when the
conviction was announced.
   ``If the blacks were permitted to celebrate, then we have the
right to protest,'' Garcia said.
   Some community leaders have blamed past racial violence on a
feeling by blacks that they are being left behind while the
Hispanic population grows in size, wealth and influence.
   Hispanic gains in the community have been reflected in the Miami
police force during the past decade. Today, 44 percent of the
force's 1,100 officers are Hispanic, 19 percent are black and 37
percent non-Hispanic white. The changes have created divisions that
didn't exist before, when Hispanics joined blacks in challenging
``Anglos'' for jobs and promotions, Garcia said.
   ``Before, we probably had better working relations with black
officers than we did with Anglo officers _ but not now,'' Garcia
said.
   In the week following Lozano's conviction, a Hispanic officer
was accused of stalling on the way to the aid of a black officer
who had called for assistance. The incident prompted a meeting of
the Hispanic and black officers associations with police officials
to soothe the tension.
   ``This used to be a war between the police and the criminal,''
said Hialeah Police Chief Rolando Bolanos, who mediated the
meeting. ``We do not need to have a war between police and police.''
   The mayor also met with Garcia and police unions. ``They showed
a lot of sensitivity,'' Suarez said.
   Nevertheless, police unions continue to fight the suspensions of
the two officers punished for the black bands and raise money for
Lozano's appeal. Members of the Fraternal Order of Police each have
agreed to donate $260 to defray Lozano's legal expenses.
   The Hispanic Officers Association is selling its own T-shirts
and distributing black wristbands to departments around the state,
said Garcia. Although police chiefs have banned in-uniform displays
of support, many Miami-area officers wear black wristbands off-duty.
   Roy Black, Lozano's defense attorney, said he hasn't been
surprised by the support.
   ``A lot of people didn't take it seriously until he was
convicted,'' Black said. ``I get more calls all the time from
people, many of them police officers, who want to know what they
can do.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>