<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0189 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0647EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DigestBriefs     12-21 0739</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Digest Briefs,0765</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After another huge demonstration,
Romanian President Nicolae Ceausescu declared a state of emergency
in the city where witnesses say his security forces killed hundreds
of anti-government protesters last weekend.
   Tens of thousands of enraged people had filled the streets of
Timisoara Wednesday night, chanting ``Give us our dead!'' There
were reports that the unrest had spread to at least eight other
cities.
   Breaking his silence on the unrest, Ceausescu on Wednesday
blamed the weekend protests on ``hooligans'' incited by ``a brazen
campaign of slander and lies'' from abroad, especially Hungary.
   He has been accused by Budapest of persecuting ethnic
Hungarians, who are concentrated in the Transylvanian region that
includes Timisoara.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United States has plenty of plutonium for
future use in nuclear weapons, and the Bush administration should
drop plans to spend $1 billion to expand supplies of the material,
a government advisory panel concludes.
   The conclusion published Wednesday by a special committee of the
National Research Council contradicts the administration's repeated
assertions to Congress that additional capacity to make
weapon-grade plutonium is vital to national security.
   The Energy Department, which owns the nation's defense nuclear
materials plants, declined to comment on the report, which the
department requested in February 1988.
   Former Energy Secretary John Herrington said during the Reagan
administration that the nation is ``awash in plutonium,'' but his
successor, James D. Watkins, had disavowed the statement. Watkins
contends that while current plutonium supplies are adequate, more
capacity will be needed in the coming decade.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The State Department, citing ``changing
conditions'' in the Soviet Union, is giving high priority to
constructing a new U.S. Embassy in Moscow to replace the one to be
razed after years of indecision.
   The job could cost up to $500 million. Nicholas Salgo, a former
U.S. ambassador to Hungary, was assigned Wednesday to hold formal
negotiations with the Kremlin. In the meantime, the Soviets will
continue to be shut out of their new embassy in the Mt. Alto
section of Washington and relegated to an older mansion near the
White House.
   Ever since U.S. intelligence 10 years ago detected what was said
to be a network of sophisticated listening devices in the Moscow
embassy, U.S. officials have pondered what to do with the $95
million building.
   Finally, on Wednesday, Secretary of State James A. Baker III
notified key members of Congress the embassy will be torn down and
a new one constructed in its place.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>ALTON, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The ice block on the Mississippi River has
created a traffic jam of 1,000 barges, giving some pilots time to
catch up on their reading.
   ``Right now, it's `Southern Outdoors,''' Roy East said by CB
radio Wednesday from his tugboat, tied up with 22 barges on an
island in the icy river just north of Alton. ``Mostly it's just sit
up here, and hurry up and wait.''
   A 200-mile stretch of the Mississippi, from Alton, just north of
St. Louis, down to Cairo in southern Illinois, was closed
indefinitely to barge traffic Monday night by the Coast Guard
because ice and low water had combined to make navigation unsafe.
   The shutdown comes at the slowest time of year for barge traffic
on the river, but it still worries shipping officials who fear
damage to barges stuck in and around the ice and mounting costs of
idled towboats.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>MOUNTAIN BROOK, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The federal judge who died after
opening a mail bomb was eulogized as a strong believer in the law
and a man ``who stood up for the underdog and the oppressed.''
   National and local judicial figures were among more than 700
mourners at Judge Robert S. Vance's funeral on Wednesday in a
church guarded by dozens of police officers and sniffed by dogs
trained to smell for bombs.
   The FBI said its probe of a wave of recent mail bombs in the
South remained open-ended, with authorities giving close attention
to whether the explosives were tied to a racist group such as the
Ku Klux Klan or the work of an individual.
   Vance, a member of the 11th U.S. Circuit Court and a former
chairman of the Alabama Democratic Party, was killed instantly
Saturday in his home when he opened a package and the bomb
exploded, sending 16-penny finishing nails into his lower abdomen.
The bomb also wounded his wife.
</TEXT>

</DOC>