<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1342EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SovietProgram     12-30 0519</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet Program,0531</SECOND>
<HEAD>Popular TV Program Disappears From Screen</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK J. PORUBCANSKY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   State-run radio and TV dropped without explanation
last week's broadcast of the country's most popular program, whose
controversial and free-wheeling shows have been a lightning rod for
conservative criticism.
   One youth newspaper, Moskovsky Komsomolets, complained Saturday
that the decision to pull the two-hour ``Vzglad'' program from the
Friday night schedule smacked of the heavy-handed pre-glasnost
censorship of the media _ ``in a word, to spit on public opinion
and forget about it.''
   Alexander Lyubimov, one of the creators of ``Vzglad,'' or View,
said by telephone that the ``directors of Gostelradio made a
decision to reduce the amount of political programming on the eve
of the New Year.''
   He refused to comment further on the decision.
   ``Vzglad'' has used the freer atmosphere of glasnost to tackle
touchy subjects. In spring, members of the Communist Party Central
Committee expressed outrage when stage director Mark Zakharov
suggested on the program that Lenin's body be removed from display
in a mausoleum on Red Square and buried.
   Since then, the idea has gained some public support among Soviet
intellectuals.
   Boris Nepomnyashchy, director of the nationwide radio network
Mayak that is another branch of the state radio and TV complex,
told listeners during a live call-in program Saturday that the
``Vzglad'' program for Friday was not ready and would be shown
shortly after the New Year's holiday, his secretary said.
   Instead of ``Vzglad,'' viewers were shown a program dedicated to
the work of Leningrad theater director Igor Vladimirov. Television
sources said the decision to pull the Friday edition of ``Vzglad''
was made Thursday. Only the Communist Party daily Pravda was able
to make a last-minute change in its program listing.
   Sources close to ``Vzglad'' said the program would be back on
the air Jan. 5 but that TV schedules in the future would list only
``youth program'' in their late evening time slot, allowing
different programming to be substituted at the last minute.
   They denied Moskovsky Komsomolets' report that plainclothes men
had entered the program's studios and seized all copies of the
intended program, which the newspaper reported was to be a parody
of the stodgy nightly TV news program ``Vremya.''
   The sources, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said the
program was to air a piece on human rights activist Andrei D.
Sakharov who died Dec. 14, and a historical review of Soviet
President Mikhail S. Gorbachev's reform effort.
   Soviet media have come under pressure lately from Gorbachev and
other officials to narrow the scope of the public debate about the
Soviet past and instead try to build a consensus on how to solve
difficult social and economic problems.
   But one ``Vzglad'' source speculated that the cancellation of
the program was instigated by Gorbachev's conservative foes to make
the Soviet leader look bad before a public that would assume the
program only could be canceled on his authority.
   Moskovsky Komsomolets also claimed that a ``black list'' of rock
groups that should not be shown on Soviet TV was circulating at the
state television studios.
</TEXT>

</DOC>