<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0262 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1436EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Bonds     12-22 0549</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bonds,0575</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bond Prices Down</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bond prices fell Friday in abbreviated
pre-holiday trading on a lower dollar overseas, concerns over
Japanese interest rates and a buoyant report on U.S. durable goods
orders.
   The Treasury's benchmark 30-year bond declined 5-16 point, or
$3.13 per $1,000 in face amount. Its yield, which rises when prices
fall, jumped to 7.88 percent from 7.85 percent late Thursday.
   The credit markets shut down at 1 p.m. EST in advance of the
Christmas and Hanukkah holidays.
   William V. Sullivan, director of money-market research for Dean
Witter Reynolds Inc., said dealers sold bonds in an effort to
reduce their portfolios before the end of the year.
   He said a drop in the dollar in overseas trading also spurred
some selling, as did concern that Japan may raise its key lending
rate by half a percentage point over the long holiday weekend.
   The U.S. financial markets are closed Monday for Christmas.
   Economists said Friday's report showing orders for durable goods
_ costly items expected to last more than three years _ up 5.1
percent in November caused an immediate selloff. The increase was
the biggest in a year and averted the first three-month drop since
mid-1986.
   The November durable goods gain was an exception to recent
evidence that the U.S. manufacturing sector is in a severe slowdown.
   `It seemed to suggest that although there are pockets of
weakness in the economy, we're not in a position that would
indicate that a recession is at hand,'' Sullivan said.
   An economic slowdown generally boosts demand for long-term
fixed-income investments such as bonds, which are seen as a hedge
against hard times.
   Kathleen Camilli, a money-market economist with Drexel Burnham
Lambert Inc., said the increase in durable goods orders was sharply
higher than economists' projections ranging from no increase to up
0.5 percent.
   In the secondary market for Treasury securities, prices of
short-term government issues fell 7-32 point to \ point,
intermediate maturities were down 5-16 point to 13-32 point, and
long-term issues were 9-32 point lower, according to Telerate Inc.,
a financial information service.
   The movement of a point is equivalent to a change of $10 in the
price of a bond with a $1,000 face value.
   The Shearson Lehman Hutton Daily Treasury Bond Index, which
measures price movements on all outstanding Treasury issues with
maturities of a year or longer, fell 3.36 to 1,194.16.
   Yields on three-month Treasury bills rose to 7.82 percent as the
discount gained 3 basis points to 7.58 percent. Yields on six-month
bills rose to 7.83 percent as the discount increased 7 basis points
to 7.44 percent. Yields on one-year bills jumped to 7.69 percent as
the discount rose 5 basis points to 7.16 percent.
   A basis point is one-hundredth of a percentage point. The yield
is the annualized return on an investment in a Treasury bill. The
discount is the percentage that bills are selling below the face
value, which is paid at maturity.
   The federal funds rate, the interest on overnight loans between
banks, was quoted at 8 3-16 percent, down from 8\ percent late
Thursday.
   In the tax-exempt market, the Bond Buyer index of 40 actively
traded municipal bonds closed at 93}, down 1-32 point. The average
yield to maturity held at 7.22 percent late Thursday.
</TEXT>

</DOC>