<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0231 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0137EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-HeatingOil Bjt   12-22 0611</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Heating Oil, Bjt,0630</SECOND>
<HEAD>Heating Oil Supplies Declining Along With the Temperature</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: ``Top'' in 6th graf is cq.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOYCE M. ROSENBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The cold snap gripping much of the nation has
drained heating oil supplies, causing temporary shortages in some
areas and driving the price of the fuel sharply higher, industry
officials said.
   Oil companies said Thursday they're taking steps to ensure there
is enough heating oil for all their customers. But the increased
demand has sent the price consumers pay for oil as high as $1 a
gallon.
   Exxon USA, Mobil Corp. and Star Enterprise, a Texaco Inc.
affiliate, reported that some of their Northeastern terminals
suffered temporary oil depletions and that customers have been sent
to other facilities or forced to wait for new supplies to arrive.
   ``These outages ... have been maybe for a few hours,'' said
Exxon spokesman Jim Davis, who said customers at the company's
Everett, Mass., terminal were directed to nearby Waltham, where
supplies were more plentiful.
   At Mobil, spokesman John Lord estimated that some customers in
the Northeast were kept waiting an hour for heating oil to arrive
by barge or pipeline, but ``that is not the norm. The norm is no
outages.''
   The wait was longer at Star Enterprise's East Hartford, Conn.,
terminal, which ran out of oil Thursday and was hoping for a
delivery today or Saturday, said Texaco spokesman Top Ingram.
   The companies placed the blame for the shortages squarely on the
weather, as customers burned more oil or tried to stock up on extra
fuel. Bad weather has also made it hard for oil barges to unload
their cargoes in some East Coast harbors.
   A series of arctic air blasts has chilled the eastern half of
the United States for 10 days, and cold weather in Europe has
placed a further strain on inventories.
   Because of the increased demand, Amoco Corp. is producing about
1 million barrels of oil a month above its usual 8 million, said
spokesman Richard Judy. Amoco has not reported any shortages at its
terminals.
   Exxon is limiting its customers to the amounts of oil specified
in their purchase contracts, Davis said, adding, ``We believe that
our heating oil inventories should be adequate to meet our monthly
contract volume.''
   At Star Enterprise, where heating oil sales are running 50
percent above projections for December, the company also is
``trying to figure out a way to distribute it on an equitable
basis,'' Ingram said.
   Oil prices have climbed steadily as temperatures have dropped.
On the New York Mercantile Exchange, a gallon of home heating oil
for delivery in January cost 79.81 cents Thursday, compared with
62.71 cents on Nov. 30.
   Heating oil prices normally rise and fall by fractions of a
cent, but Thursday's price was up more than 4 cents a gallon from
Wednesday, a further reflection of the increased demand.
   Mobil's Lord said prices the oil company has paid on the open
market have shot up 25 cents over the last three weeks and
distributors in New Jersey reported a similar increase.
   Homeowners and businesses are already paying higher prices.
Platt's Oilgram News, an oil industry newsletter, said some
consumers are paying $1 a gallon in the New York City area, where
heating costs are the highest in the nation, and about 10 cents
less in the Midwest.
   The National Weather Service was predicting some relief might
arrive by Christmas. The oil companies said that as long as the
cold abates, they should have enough supplies.
   But officials were still a little uneasy.
   ``It's keeping your fingers crossed that you don't run out,''
said Texaco's Ingram.
</TEXT>

</DOC>