<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 1930EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania 1stLd-Writethru a0696 12-31 0960</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0696,0991</SECOND>
<HEAD>Official Declares Communist Party `Dead' ^LaserPhotos BUC1,9</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with interim president abolishing death
penalty, reaffirming pluralism, re-introducing private ownership. Edits
to trim. No pickup.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERRY LEONARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An official in the new government
declared Sunday that the Communist Party is dead and will not be
allowed to take control as the country moves toward democracy in
the new year.
   Also Sunday Romania's interim president, Ion Iliescu, abolished
the death penalty, saying that the late Nicolae Ceausescu and his
wife were ``the last persons that deserved this fate.'' The couple
was executed a week ago.
   Iliescu, in a New Year's address, also reaffirmed the nation's
commitment to political pluralism and re-introduced the concept of
private ownership.
   In other developments, the Agerpres news agency reported that
the former head of the dreaded Securitate secret police had been
detained, and army units continued to search for Securitate
holdouts loyal to Ceausescu.
   But there were no reports of major clashes as Romanians
celebrated their first free New Year's Eve in decades.
   One newspaper carried a warning from police asking holiday
merrymakers not to use fireworks and noisemakers in the capital,
where the streets were filled with nervous soldiers armed with
automatic weapons.
   Hungarian television reported that an assailant it did not
identify stabbed Ceausescu's son, Nicu, immediately after he was
shown on Romanian television Dec. 22.
   The assailant was arrested while the younger Ceausescu underwent
an operation for his stomach wound ``which was successful,''
Hungarian TV said.
   Nicu Ceausescu was the Communist Party chief in the Transylvania
town of Sibiu until the revolution that ousted his father. He was
one of dozens of Ceausescu family members who were given positions
of power.
   Deputy Foreign Minister Corneliu Bogdan, one of the members of
the government that took over after Ceausescu's overthrow Dec. 22,
told reporters Sunday there is no danger of Communists gaining the
upper hand again.
   ``The Communist Party is dead,'' Bogdan said, adding that party
members are a minority in the current government, which will run
the country until elections planned in April.
   Bogdan did not say how many Communists were in the temporary
leadership. But he said their expertise was needed.
   ``I was deceived,'' Bogdan said of his own membership in the
party. ``I will pay for it,'' he added without elaboration.
   He said said Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard Shevardnadze would
visit Jan. 5 or 6, and said ``all possibilities are alive'' for
cooperation with the Soviet Union.
   Iliescu, in comments carried by all state media, told the
nation's 23 million people that despite stubborn resistance by
pro-Ceausescu forces, ``the revolution has triumphed and will
remain unvanquishable.''
   The interim govermnent seeks ``a large, novel political
pluralism,'' he declared.
   Iliescu also:
   _promised a moratorium on expensive construction projects
undertaken by Ceausescu despite wide-spread privation at home.
These include the Danube-Bucharest Canal, with a projected cost of
$2.5 billion; and Ceausescu's pet project, the nearly completed
Palace of the Republic, which has consumed $600 million.
   _declared land on which farmers live and surrounding plots
private property, re-establishing a concept banned for decades, and
also announced that farmers would again be allowed to sell produce
and animals raised on leased land, as long as they did not demand
``mercurial prices.''
   Agerpres reported the signing of a decree by Iliescu providing
the legal basis for creation of new political parties _ an
important step toward free elections.
   The decree bans fascist parties and others that ``propagate
ideas at variance to the state and law and order,'' Agerpres said.
   At least six new political parties have emerged since
Ceausescu's overthrow.
   The decree also states that officials of the defense and
interior ministries, judges, prosecutors, members of state radio
and television cannot join political parties, to ensure their
impartiality.
   Ceausescu ruled for 24 years and refused to accept the reforms
orchestrated by Soviet leader Mikhail S. Gorbachev. The revolt
against him began Dec. 15 and climaxed Dec. 22 when Ceausescu and
his wife, Elena, fled.
   Agerpres said former Securitate chief Iulian Vlad was arrested
Sunday along with former deputy interior ministers Giani Bucurescu
and Aristotel Stamatoiu, and Vasile Gheorghe, another senior
Interior Ministry offical.
   The four have been removed from active duty and were being held
for questioning, the report said. Vlad is a colonel general, while
the other three are lieutenant generals.
   The Agerpres report did not specify what charges, if any, the
four faced.
   Prime Minister Petre Roman, meanwhile, defended the decision to
execute Ceausescu and his wife after a hasty military trial.
   ``There were great risks in guarding him,'' Roman was quoted as
saying by the Bucharest newspaper Adevarul. ``We had secure
information that (Securitate) paratroopers were prepared to attack
the place where Ceausescu was, and the place was not well guarded.''
   Adevarul _ the former Communist Party daily that now appears as
a non-affiliated daily _ and other newspapers reserved much of
their space for rejoicing over the first New Year's Eve without
Ceausescu.
   Romanians on the street greeted each other and foreigners with
cheerful shouts of ``Multi Ani,'' which means Happy New Year, as
they trudged through the snow and slush or stood in long lines to
buy food for their holiday dinners.
   Many walked up the hill above the broad street Ceausescu named
The Avenue of Socialist Victory, to the 17th century Patriarchal
Church,@Uhere they offered prayers for the dead and asked for
peace, prosperity and freedom in the new year.
   There is no firm figure of how many people died in the Romanian
revolution, but the death toll is believed to be in the thousands.
   Romanian television broadcast a special Romanian Orthodox New
Year's Mass, celebrated by Patriarch Theocrist, to the entire
country.
</TEXT>

</DOC>