<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0086 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1445EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     12-30 0531</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0549</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CORINTH, Miss. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dancing and drinking to strains of ``Auld
Lang Syne'' will be limited strictly to homegrown parties this
year, since a city ordinance forbids dancing on Sundays at places
where beer is being served.
   It's OK to drink on Sunday, but you can't do both.
   Leading at least one local restaurant and lounge to advertise
its New Year's Eve bash for Saturday night, a day early.
   The mayor said folks began worrying about it too late for him to
do anything. And even if the city board had tried to vote an
exemption, they'd still have to check with the attorney general.
   ``I don't think I'd have the executive power to say go ahead and
open up for your New Year's party,'' Mayor E.S. Bishop said last
week. ``I don't think it would be legitimate for me to say that.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>OXFORD, Ohio (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bible from start to finish is on the
reading list this weekend for members of a local church.
   ``When we finish early Sunday, we will have read for 54
consecutive hours, and will have read all 1,159 chapters and all
773,746 words of the Bible,'' said Mark Taylor, minister of the
University Church of Christ.
   The Bible marathon began at 6 p.m. Friday and was to end at
midnight Sunday. Some of the congregation's 70 members and other
volunteers began reading from the book of Genesis at the church,
while another group in Oxford's town square began reading from the
middle of the Bible.
   ``Two groups is the only way we can get through the entire Bible
over the weekend,'' said church deacon Carl Martin. Officials said
they hope the marathon will encourage folks to read the Bible more
on their own.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>ONEIDA N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   What may be the smallest chapel in the world
has been dedicated on an artificial island in the middle of a
2-acre pond here.
   Chandler Mason of Oneida erected an 8-foot lighted cross in the
pond three years ago, and later decided to go a step further and
build a church there. It church was dedicated Friday.
   The chapel was framed with 2-by-4s, and has white aluminum
siding and a shingled roof. A friend cut three cathedral-shaped
windows, and others are building the 5-foot steeple and stained
glass windows.
   The 1989 edition of the Guinness Book of World Records lists
Union Church in Wiscasset, Maine, as the world's smallest, with a
floor area of 4{ by 7 feet.
   Mason's ``Cross Island Chapel'' is one inch smaller in both
dimensions. When Mason and his family finished the church's parts,
they built a small sled and dragged the parts to the middle of the
pond and erected the chapel. It now sits on a foundation of five
tons of gravel and cement that Mason had poured earlier into the
pond _ wheelbarrow-load by wheelbarrow-load.
   Mason says that by summer, he plans to install two custom-made
pews, a tiny pulpit and an altar. Already, couples have contacted
him about using the church for wedding ceremonies, he said.
   ``That's fine with me, but guests will have to bring their own
boats,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>