<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0170 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1922EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-LaughingTrial     12-18 0475</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Laughing Trial,0488</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mohawk Casino Owner Pleads Guilty to Federal Gambling Charges</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM KATES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SYRACUSE, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The owner of an illegal casino on a Mohawk
Indian reservation pleaded guilty to gambling charges on the first
day of his federal trial Monday, saying he made the plea so he
could appeal.
   ``In order to take this case to the next level, I had to make a
plea, no matter how much I feel I'm innocent,'' Anthony Laughing
said outside the courtroom.
   Laughing, a 42-year-old Mohawk, pleaded guilty to single counts
of possession of slot machines, operating an illegal gambling
business and resisting arrest. Under a plea bargain, prosecutors
dropped six other counts.
   The plea came after a 90-minute conference that followed
Assistant U.S. Attorney John Brunetti's opening argument in the
trial.
   Laughing is to be sentenced Feb. 27. He faces up to 10 years in
prison if given the maximum penalties for each of the three counts.
   He entered conditional pleas to the gambling charges, reserving
the right to appeal the charges on the basis of Indian sovereignty
issues.
   Laughing and 12 other Mohawks who were arrested in a July 20
raid by state and federal law enforcement officers contend the St.
Regis Indian Reservation is a sovereign nation and that state and
federal laws do not apply there.
   Laughing said he wanted to get his case to the next federal
level more quickly rather than endure an extended trial. ``I am
innocent and if I have to appeal this all the way to the Supreme
Court, I will,'' he said.
   His attorney, Michael Vavonese, said an appeal would be filed
with the 2nd U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals in New York City after
sentencing.
   Laughing also said he did not believe he would receive a fair
trial before U.S. District Judge Neal McCurn because McCurn has
ruled repeatedly in the government's favor.
   McCurn earlier this year rejected the sovereignty argument in
pretrial motions, citing other Indian cases where courts have ruled
that federal and state governments have jurisdiction on Indian
reservations.
   McCurn allowed Laughing to remain free on $300,000 bail, but
continued a U.S. magistrate's order that he report to authorities
twice daily and be at home overnight to receive a call from them.
   Laughing owns Tony's Vegas International, the largest of seven
high-stakes casinos on the reservation, which straddles the
U.S.-Canadian border in northern New York.
   He avoided arrest in the July 20 raid, and was a fugitive for
two months until being caught Sept. 21 after a chase by state
troopers.
   Laughing's case is the fifth to be resolved. Three other Mohawks
have either been convicted or pleaded guilty to gambling charges. A
fifth Mohawk was acquitted when prosecutors failed to prove he was
the owner of a truck stop where state police seized slot machines.
</TEXT>

</DOC>