<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0117 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1824EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Bulgaria     12-27 0503</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bulgaria,0519</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bulgarian Communists to Hold Talks With Opposition</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SOFIA, Bulgaria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The ruling Communists and an opposition
coalition agreed Wednesday to hold wide-ranging talks on Bulgaria's
future government. Some workers staged brief strikes as a warning
to the Communists.
   Following the agreement, an independent trade union called off a
general strike scheduled for Thursday. The union demands the
resignation of the government, the Parliament and the Communist
Party's Central Committee.
   In other developments Wednesday, the government fired Interior
Minister Georgi Tanev following criticism of police violence
against demonstrators in October. The official BTA news agency gave
no reason for his ouster.
   The announcements are the latest in a series of changes since
Bulgaria's longtime hard-line Communist leader, Todor Zhivkov, was
ousted Nov. 10.
   Since then, amid a wave of democratic reform that has swept
Eastern Europe, leaders have scrapped a law forbidding dissent,
proposed free elections in May and granted amnesty to political
prisoners.
   The ruling party reached agreement with the opposition
coalition, the Union of Democratic Forces, ``toward holding
consultations'' beginning Tuesday or Wednesday, said Ivan Angelov,
a spokesman for the Central Committee.
   The talks were characterized as being similar to those in
Czechoslovakia that led to a government dominated by non-Communists.
   For the first time in Bulgaria, strikes were held throughout the
country Wednesday, but only small groups of workers took part. The
two-hour strikes were intended as a warning to Communist leaders.
   The independent union Support withdrew its Thursday strike call
following the agreement, said chairman Konstantin Trenchev.
   Support's job action was not backed by most of the independent
organizations in the Union of Democratic Forces, which said workers
should strike only after all other forms of a dialogue are
exhausted.
   Plamen Darakchiev, a secretary of Support, said the trade union
``will not relinquish its demands but make them in a categoric
way'' at the talks with the Communists.
   BTA said Tanev was replaced as Interior Minister by Gen. Atanas
Semerdzhiev, the army's chief of staff. BTA said the deputy foreign
minister, Lyuben Gotsev, would move to the No. 2 position at the
Interior Ministry, which is responsible for the East bloc country's
police and internal security.
   Tanev, 48, was blamed for the Oct. 26 crackdown on demonstrators
of the then-banned Eco-Glasnost environmental group. The government
said at least 22 people protesting in Sofia against a government
hydroelectric project were beaten and kicked by police, and Western
diplomats said from 30 to 40 were detained.
   The police action embarrassed the Bulgarian leadership because
it drew sharp criticism from delegates to a 35-nation ecological
forum in Sofia taking place at the time. The group was later
legalized.
   At the last session of the Parliament on Dec. 14, Tanev read a
long statement on the incident, rejecting all responsibility. He
said he had only learned of the police action afterward.
   Under Tanev, a police squad that cracked down on human rights
activists and political opponents was in operation. Under new
Communist leader Petar Mladenov, it was disbanded Nov. 25.
</TEXT>

</DOC>