<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0195 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1947EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Panama-Military 3rdLd-Writethru a0801 12-22 0781</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Military, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0801,830</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Troops Find Weapons Caches, Aim to Control Panama City</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 2nd graf to update with additional troops
being sent; SUBS 15th graf pvs, bgng: Late Friday xxx to include that two
U.S. civilians have been killed.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSANNE M. SCHAFER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Military Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pentagon officials said Friday that American
troops had seized 10,000 weapons in three separate caches in their
sweep through Panama City and were trying to move out ``looting
sniping'' remnants of Manuel Antonio Noriega's forces.
   ``The primary endeavor of the movement is to clear Panama City
and assist the government in restoring law and order,'' said Lt.
Gen. Tom Kelly, the director of operations for the Joint Chiefs of
Staff.
   Meanwhile, a Pentagon source said Friday night an additional
2,000 Army soldiers were being flown to Panama ``in the near
future.''
   Earlier Kelly was asked about reports of a mortar round being
fired at U.S. military headquarters at Quarry Heights.
   ``Things like that can happen,'' he said. ``Popping off a mortar
round is a fairly easy thing to do.''
   Kelly called the weapons discovery ``little short of
astonishing.''
   ``One wonders what the intentions of Noriega were,'' the general
said, adding that the arms cache was composed primarily of Eastern
bloc weapons.
   Kelly, who raised the prospect that additional U.S. troops might
be brought to Panama, acknowledged that Noriega's defense forces
had put up a tougher battle than expected and that the ``mopping
up'' process would take longer than first thought.
   ``It's simply a difficult operation ... There are a lot of
places to hide (in Panama City),'' Kelly said. He said military
commanders' estimates for ``clearing the city range from five to 10
days.''
   The general also suggested a new direction for the U.S. troops,
saying ``we plan to move out to the west of Panama City,'' but he
declined to discuss what the target of the operation might be.
   While officials said Noriega remained at large, Kelly said, ``I
don't think he has a very long half-life. ... He sure is out of
power.''
   Kelly said that U.S. forces were encountering the remnants of
Noriega's armed civilian battalions.
   ``They are looting, sniping, they are lawless,'' he said. But he
said U.S. forces have been able to make some progress, including
taking the legislative building, the presidential palace, central
bank, and several ministries.
   ``I'm satisfied it's under control,'' Kelly said of the
military's urban operation. ``We're not getting anything we can't
handle.''
   In a pincer movement, Kelly said the 193rd Infantry _ which is
permanently based in Panama _ and the forces of the 82nd Airborne
were moving through the city from opposite points and hoped to link
up.
   Late Friday, the Pentagon updated its report of U.S. soldiers
killed in action, saying that 21 had been killed and 221 wounded
with two missing. In addition two civilian U.S. dependents were
killed.
   The Pentagon added that 127 members of the Panamanian Defense
Forces had been killed, 66 wounded and 1,663 were being detained.
   Rear Adm. Ted Sheafer, who joined Kelly at the briefing, said
there were still reports of three hostages cases that were ``not
resolved. There may be others,'' he said.
   The admiral, the intelligence chief for the Joint Chiefs, said
the administration was sending a team of experts to Panama from the
various intelligence agencies and departments to go through a
``treasure trove'' of documents that had been discovered in
Noriega's military headquarters.
   Kelly, asked whether he had enough military force to keep peace
in the city, said, ``We are looking to bring more troops in. We are
also looking at re-establishing the police force.''
   The general said that since the new government was offering to
pay the police, ``that may be an incentive for them to come back.''
   ``We would like to be able to put Panamanian police and U.S.
military police out in pairs _ one Panamanian, one U.S. military _
and in that way begin to restore law and order,'' he said.
   Later, the general said that two companies of U.S. military
police had been brought into Panama on Thursday and that ``they are
the ones we want in the street with the police, because they have
the training to do it.''
   Pentagon spokeswoman Maj. Kathy Wood said that Panamanian police
and U.S. military police have performed security duties at all U.S.
military installations in Panama since the inception of the Panama
Canal treaties, so the concept of dual patrols is not a new one to
the area.
   She pointed out that the Panamanian police, while part of the
PDF, are not soldiers and are considered public servants.
</TEXT>

</DOC>