<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0822EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-SuicideDonor     12-20 0533</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Suicide Donor,0546</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Kills Self, Trying to Donate Heart to Ill Brother; Fails</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TAMARAC, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man who felt he was a failure committed
suicide outside a hospital in an effort to save a brother with
heart disease. But the body was found too late, and his heart could
not be used for a transplant.
   Gerald Olson, 46, drove his van Monday evening to University
Community Hospital in Tamarac and parked outside the emergency
room, authorities said Tuesday. Then he put a gun into his mouth
and pulled the trigger.
   Ten minutes passed before a nurse on her way home noticed Olson
slumped over the steering wheel. An emergency medical crew
administered heart massage, but he died less than an hour later.
   Police found suicide notes in the van in which Olson complained
of ``too many downs and no ups for me on this roller coaster ride
of life.'' Olson wrote that he wanted his heart donated to his
56-year-old brother, Bob Olson, who has been on a waiting list for
a heart transplant for nearly three years.
   ``His main purpose for (committing suicide) at the hospital was
to make his heart available for his brother,'' said Sheriff's
Detective Steve Wiley. ``Unfortunately, he failed.''
   ``It made me feel like someone special,'' Bob Olson said from
his home in Belvedere, Ill. ``He thought of me in his last
thoughts. He wanted somebody benefiting from his death.
   ``I love my brother,'' Olson added, sobbing. ``I'm going to miss
him.''
   The elder Olson, who was diagnosed as having cardiomyopathy,
which causes an enlarged heart, and other relatives said they
recognized Jerry Olson did not succeed in life as he might have
wished, but they said they had no idea he might be suicidal.
   ``I think he probably was capable of doing anything he wanted to
do. If he'd only gone and done it,'' said Roland Olson, 58, who
lives in Rockford, said of his younger brother.
   Instead, Jerry Olson worked in lounges and sold bar supplies. He
was unemployed in recent months. Jerry moved to Tamarac about eight
years ago to help a sister after her husband died of a heart
attack, Roland said.
   But three weeks ago, she asked her brother to move out,
according to Wiley. ``She thought it was time for him to stand on
his own two feet,'' the detective said. Since then, Jerry Olson had
lived in his van, Wiley said.
   On Sunday, Jerry Olson recorded a tape. An Elvis Presley fan who
named his daughter Lisa Marie, same as the singer's daughter, he
sang ``I'll be Home for Christmas,'' and in two letters asked that
the song be played at his funeral.
   To his daughter, Jerry Olson wrote: ``I'm so sorry it had to
come to this Honey, but lately there's been too many downs and no
ups for me on this roller coaster ride of life!
   ``I'm tired of everyone saying how much talent I've got. Uncle
Bob's got everything to live for! And if they find out he can use
it and Uncle Bob wants it, I'm going to be his donor Lisa! I figure
I could do more good for him than myself!''
</TEXT>

</DOC>