<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0119 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1559EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Sakharov Bjt   12-18 0873</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sakharov, Bjt,0900</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gorbachev, Thousands Bid Farewell to Sakharov</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos MOSB5,6; MOS5,14</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN-THOR DAHLBURG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After a kiss from his widow, Andrei D. Sakharov
was buried Monday in a snowy cemetery where Kremlin elite joined
with common people in mourning the human rights advocate once
treated as an outlaw.
   To the baleful strains of Robert Schumann's ``Traumerai,''
Sakharov's coffin was carried along a path strewn with evergreen
boughs to the freshly dug grave at Vostryakovskoye Cemetery.
   ``It's over,'' Sakharov's wife and dissident comrade-in-arms,
Yelena Bonner, said as she turned to a companion during the
twilight burial under pines dripping with rain.
   Sakharov died Thursday of an apparent heart attack at the age of
68. He was buried alongside Bonner's mother, Ruth, a Stalin-era
political prisoner who died in 1987 at age 87.
   Before the crimson- and black-trimmed coffin was lowered into
the cold land Sakharov tried so hard to change, its lid was removed
to allow Bonner a last farewell. She took the shroud from his face
and bent to kiss him on the forehead.
   As the procession wound its way through Moscow, some mourners
marched alongside with signs demanding democratic elections, one of
Sakharov's final causes.
   Others hoisted the blue, red, and white flag of czarist Russia,
now the symbol of the grassroots pro-democracy Russian People's
Front.
   Top Communist Party brass riding sleek black limousines and tens
of thousands of common people trudging through the slush joined in
paying their last respects to the Nobel Peace laureate, who once
was pilloried as an ignoramus and dupe of the West.
   In the morning, President Mikhail S. Gorbachev and other members
of the ruling Politburo stood in the rain to view the body outside
the Academy of Sciences. Sakharov, a creator of the Soviet hydrogen
bomb, was a member of the academy.
   Gorbachev spoke at length there with Bonner and later told
reporters: ``Now it is clear that he deserved the Nobel Prize.''
   Sakharov won the prize in 1975 for his human rights campaign,
but the Soviet leadership at the time refused to let him go to
Norway to accept it. He was hounded for years and finally sent into
internal exile in Gorky for nearly seven years.
   An open-ended bus followed by thousands of mourners carried
Sakharov's body and Bonner along Lenin Prospekt to outdoor funeral
ceremonies in the parking lot of the Luzhniki sports complex, a
favorite site for rallies by human rights activists.
   More than 30,000 people surged forward toward Sakharov's
carnation-bedecked coffin, and Bonner had to plead for order.
   Sakharov ``did all he could,'' Ilya Zaslavsky, a Moscow member
of the Congress of People's Deputies, told the crowd. ``Now only
his ideas can change things, and only we can fulfill his ideas.''
   ``The Academy of Sciences is guilty before him; we were passive
in our defense of him,'' Sakharov's fellow academician and Congress
member, Dmitri Likhachev, said in a quavering voice. ``Now we say:
Andrei Dmitrievich, forgive us!''
   State-run TV showed excerpts of the Luzhniki services in a
special broadcast of the kind usually reserved for the deaths of
major government figures. The evening news program ``Vremya'' led
off with an eight-minute report on Sakharov's last rites,
accompanied by a sorrowful dirge.
   The 2,250-member Congress, or parliament, to which Sakharov
belonged adjourned at midday so its members could attend the
funeral ceremonies.
   From Luzhniki, the coffin was transported nine miles in a bus to
the cemetery along slush-filled streets.
   In addition to Gorbachev, Politburo members and other Soviet
leaders gathered at the Academy of Sciences to view Sakharov's body.
   From another direction, buses escorted by police cars arrived.
Some 20 people carried the casket on their shoulders from a bus and
placed it on a bier in front of the academy. Bonner also emerged,
accompanied by her son, Alexei Semenov.
   The coffin was opened in the frigid rain, and an umbrella opened
to shield Sakharov's face.
   A bareheaded and somber Gorbachev walked to the foot of the
casket and stood for awhile in silence. He bowed twice, and the
huddle of people around the casket broke up.
   Gorbachev and Bonner spoke animatedly, with Bonner smiling at
one point. Gorbachev and his entourage entered the academy
Presidium building to sign an official book of condolences. He
wrote simply, ``M.S. Gorbachev.''
   He emerged and talked briefly with reporters. ``The relations
between myself and Sakharov were always those of mutual respect,''
Gorbachev said. ``Now it is clear that he deserved the Nobel
Prize.''
   It was Gorbachev who allowed Sakharov to return to Moscow in
December 1986 after the years of exile in Gorky. The two men had
clashed, however, over the speed and sweep of Gorbachev's political
reform program, with Sakharov demanding the Communist Party that
Gorbachev heads renounce its constitutional monopoly on power.
   Some parliamentarians Monday pledged to heed Sakharov's call to
create a full-fledged opposition in the Congress and to push for
victory for progressives in nationwide local elections that began
this month.
   Lech Walesa, the leader of Poland's Solidarity movement and
winner of the 1983 Nobel Peace Prize, had been expected to attend
the service, but Poland's official PAP news agency reported his
plane had to land in Leningrad because of bad weather.
</TEXT>

</DOC>