<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0446EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-MedflyWeapon     12-19 0459</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Medfly Weapon,0473</SECOND>
<HEAD>Researcher Announces New Weapon in War on Medflies</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEVE ELLIOTT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HONOLULU (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An expert on the Mediterranean fruit fly has
developed a poison bait for the crop-destroying pest that he says
might enable California to end aerial spraying in a few years.
   Roy T. Cunningham, a U.S. Department of Agriculture entomologist
based in Hilo, said Monday he plans to begin tests early next year
on a compound that's a mix of a new, long-lasting chemical
attractant and pesticide. It is designed to be sprayed on trees and
utility poles.
   The bait, called Ceralure, is mixed with malathion, the same
pesticide California authorities have in recent weeks been spraying
from helicopters over wide stretches of the Los Angeles suburbs to
control a Medfly outbreak.
   Though scientists insist the pesticide is safe in the minute
quantities used, spraying is the focus of emotional debate in
California, where the flies threaten a $16 billion farm industry.
Residents and some environmental groups oppose each new round of
spraying as unsafe, while farmers and government agriculture
experts insist it's necessary and harmless.
   California officials have spent $10 million battling 13
outbreaks this year. A 1980-82 infestation cost California
taxpayers $100 million for eradication and cost growers about $100
million in lost sales.
   The Medfly, one of the most damaging fruit flies, attacks more
than 250 fruits and vegetables. Most of the damage is done when
females deposit their eggs in crops, making them unmarketable.
   Medflies get into California as eggs or larvae in fruit and
produce, usually illegally imported or mailed from Hawaii or
Central America.
   The Ceralure gel is ``a much simpler and a much less costly
system than we presently have,'' said Cunningham, who chairs a
committee that advises California officials on fighting Medfly
outbreaks.
   It could eventually replace aerial spraying, but it will take
two to three years of testing to determine if the substance is an
effective and safe option, Cunningham said.
   California's Department of Food and Agriculture has agreed to
help fund the study of Ceralure's effectiveness, providing $83,600
during the next three years, said Isi A. Siddiqui, the agency's
assistant director.
   Blobs of the Ceralure gel shot from trucks onto trees and
utility poles would attract male Medflies, whihch would be killed
by the pesticide, Cunningham said.
   The key to the new system is that Ceralure appears to stay
effective for two weeks. If that proves the case, it may be
cost-effective to use the substance to fight fly outbreaks in
California, reapplying the Ceralure every two weeks, Cunningham
said.
   The gel technique has already been used in California to fight
the Medfly's cousin, the Oriental fruit fly.
   Cunningham said researchers don't understand how Ceralure
attracts the male Medflies.
</TEXT>

</DOC>