<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0538EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Eastern     12-29 0514</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Eastern,0531</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eastern Cuts 600 Jobs, Trims 10,000 Salaries</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD COLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eastern Airlines plans 600 more layoffs along with
salary cuts for half its employees under measures to stem the flood
of red ink that has swamped the airline for a decade.
   About 10,000 workers will have wages temporarily slashed from 10
percent to 20 percent, although some of those cuts must be
negotiated with the Air Line Pilots Association and the flight
attendants union.
   The principal cause of the cuts _ which were announced Thursday
_ is the sale of Eastern's Latin American routes to American
Airlines.
   But Tom Matthews, Eastern's senior vice president for human
resources, also cited ``the softness in the economy ... the
increase in fuel prices, the extensive competition in the Miami
hub,'' particularly from Pan American World Airways.
   The package is expected to save $100 million next year for
Eastern, which reported a $185.2 million loss in this year's third
quarter.
   Eastern President Phil Bakes said pay and benefit reductions
were ``something we wanted to avoid,'' but that large losses are
expected to continue in the first half of the new year.
   The cuts are also part of Eastern's bankruptcy court plan for
financial reorganization that stemmed from the March 4 strike that
virtually idled the Miami-based carrier for weeks. Eastern claimed
it was losing $1 million a day prior to the strike.
   The majority of the layoffs will involve administrative and
airport service personnel, and will not include the unionized
pilots, flight attendants or mechanics.
   Attrition and early retirement will blunt the effects of the
cutbacks, but a number of operations-related employees will be out
of work Jan. 31 as Miami operations fall from 75 to 50 daily
flights.
   Job cuts also will come July 1 when American Airlines is
scheduled to assume the Latin routes.
   Meanwhile, half of Eastern's 20,000 employees _ including
management, pilots and flight attendants working at the older,
higher wage levels _ will have their wages cut by 10 percent to 20
percent for a year, beginning Jan. 16.
   About 850 pilots will see their $72,000 salaries slashed by 20
percent for six months. Half of the cut will be restored after six
months, and wages are scheduled to return to normal after a year.
About 950 newly hired pilots are working for $27,500 a year and
will not be affected.
   Flight attendants earning a pre-strike salary of $30,000 a year
will take a 15 percent initial cut, but those hired under the new
wage levels of $15,000 will not.
   Machinists, who had cuts imposed when the strike began, aren't
affected. Machinists remain the only group that hasn't gone back to
work.
   Mary Jane Barry, head of Eastern's flight attendants union,
refused to comment on the proposal, saying negotiations were
continuing. Calls to ALPA were not returned.
   Eastern employed 32,000 before the strike began, and the airline
filed for bankruptcy protection five days later.
   Eastern, a Texas Air Corp. subsidiary, plans to reshape itself
with about 75 percent of its operations centered at Atlanta.
</TEXT>

</DOC>