<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0101 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1456EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Flight103-US 1stLd-Writethru a0574 12-21 0652</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Flight 103-US, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0574,0664</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bells Peal for Victims of Flight 103</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 11 grafs to UPDATE with church bells pealing for
victims; PICKS UP 11th graf pvs, `I don't ...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Flight 103</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GENEVA COLLINS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Church bells pealed today at the precise moment one year ago
that a bomb blew Pan Am Flight 103 out of the sky, and the airline
took out full-page ads urging the public to remember the 270
victims on the anniversary of their death.
   Several U.S. towns scheduled memorial services for those who
lost loved ones in the terror attack on the Boeing 747 over
Lockiebie, Scotland. The unsolved bombing killed 259 passengers and
11 people on the ground.
   In Washington, more than 20 members of victims' families planned
to take part in a 90-minute candlelight memorial service at Holy
Trinity Church. Guests were to include Sir Antony Acland, Britian's
ambassador to the United States.
   ``One year a today, 270 lives were lost in one senseless,
barbaric act. At 2:02 p.m. (EST) today, we ask you to join us in
pausing for a moment of prayer for these and all other victims of
terrorism all over the world,'' Pan Am said in full-page ads placed
in nine newspapers, including The New York Times, USA Today and The
Annandale (Scotland) Herald.
   Pan Am spokeswoman Pamela Hanlon said memorial services would be
held today at New York's Kennedy Airport, in London and in
Frankfurt, West Germany. The jet was en route to New York from
London; Flight 103 originated in Frankfurt.
   In Ramsey, N.J., where people gathered at an elementary school
to commemorate New Jersey's 38 victims, church bells pealed at 2:02
p.m, the exact time locally that the jet blew up. Bells were to
ring for 270 seconds, one second for each victim.
   In Pennsylvania, Blessed Sacrament Cathedral in Greensburg rang
its bells at 2:02 p.m. for 270 seconds as well. Two students at
Greensburg's Seton Hill College were among the victims of the
bombing.
   ``In memory of all those people who we knew or were in some way
connected with the parish, we felt this was a fitting memorial on
this day,'' said the Rev. Donald Mondello, rector of the Roman
Catholic cathedral.
   Bells pealed also at Syracuse University, and handful of people
attended a university chapel service for the 35 Syracuse students
killed in the bombing. University chaplain Paul Kowalewski read
aloud the names of the students.
   ``It was very quiet and meditative,'' Kowalewski said. ``People
there were in a somber mood.''
   University spokesman Darryl Geddes said Hendricks Chapel would
be open for silent prayer all day, with a brief service at 5 p.m.
He said most students have gone home for the Christmas break and
few people are expected to attend. About 550 people attended
memorial services Dec. 13 for the Flight 103 victims at the chapel.
   ``I don't think for any of us Christmas will ever be the same,''
Bert Ammerman of River Vale, N.J., whose brother Tom perished in
the tragedy, said Sunday. He is a founding member of the support
group Families of Victims of Pan Am Flight 103.
   At least 20 American relatives crossed the Atlantic to mourn
with the 3,500 residents of Lockerbie. Organizers planned two
simple remembrance services. Pan Am offered to fly families of the
victims to the memorials.
   The wife of Pan Am 103 pilot James MacQuarry said today she is
not yet ready to visit the crash site.
   ``Some other time, but not now,'' said Janet MacQuarry, who
planned a quiet gathering of friends and family at her house in
Kensington, N.H., tonight.
   Investigators say the bomb that brought down the plane was made
of powerful plastic explosives concealed in a radio-cassette
player. Police have said one focus of their investigation is the
Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine-General Command, a
radical Syria-based faction.
</TEXT>

</DOC>