<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0096 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1444EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-US-Romania 3rdLd-Writethru a0531-571 12-27 0819</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-Romania, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0531-571,750</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush `Amazed' by Sweeping Changes</HEAD>
<UNK>Eds: SUBS grafs 5-6 pvs, The United, with 8 new grafs on Bush message,
State Department comment, picking up, 7th graf, `Concerned citizens.'</UNK>
<DATELINE>CORPUS CHRISTI, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush said today he is
``amazed and respectful'' of the changes that have taken place in
Romania and that he hopes now for ``tranquility and freedom'' in
the East Bloc country.
   Bush told reporters he was concerned that the trial of Romania's
deposed dictator Nicolae Ceausescu was held in secret, ``but that's
their matter,'' he said.
   ``I'm just amazed and respectful of the change that has taken
place,'' he said as arrived here for six days of hunting and
fishing.
   The task ahead for Romanians is ``to bring the remaining holdout
forces to bay,'' Bush said. ``The army seems to be doing that, and
my concern is for tranquility and freedom in Romania.''
   The president sent a congratulatory message to Romania's new
head of state, President Ion Iliescu.
   ``The president expressed his sympathy over the tragic bloodshed
over the past two weeks and his hope that Romania will now move
along on a peaceful path of democratic change,'' the White House
said in a statement issued in Corpus Christi.
   The administration was sending a C-141 cargo plane loaded with
medical supplies to Romania on Thursday, the Agency for
International Development (AID) announced.
   The cost of the flight and supplies, about $250,000, was in
addition to the $500,000 in cash the administration was giving to
the International Red Cross for medical supplies, along with
$25,000 from an embassy contingency fund in Romania.
   In Washington, State Department spokesman Mark Dillen said that
the U.S. ambassador to Bucharest, Alan Green, had requested an
appointment with the provisional president, Ion Iliescu, but no
appointment had been scheduled.
   Commenting on reports of an anti-Communist rally in the Romanian
capital, Dillen said the embassy had reported the demonstration was
attended by 500 to 1,000 students, and that a student leader had
appeared on Romanian television.
   ``We encourage the government of Romania to allow all voices to
be heard as the process of reform and the transition to a new
government progress,'' said Dillen, reading a prepared statement.
   On Tuesday, Andrew Natsios, director of the U.S. AID Office for
Foreign Disaster Assistance, said that private citizens were
welcome to help, but that ``the best way to get assistance to
Romania is through cash donations.''
   ``Concerned citizens are urged not to donate goods or supplies,
which are sometimes inappropriate and tend to clog relief supply
lines,'' Natsios said on Tuesday.
   U.S. officials, who recognized the new government on Monday,
expressed regret that Romanian revolutionaries did not hold an open
trial for Ceausescu and his wife, Elena, who were executed on
Christmas day.
   ``We would have preferred it if there had been a public trial,''
White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said.
   State Department officials said they had been in contact with
Romanian Ambassador Ion Stoichici, who announced over Christmas
weekend that the embassy staff had switched allegiances to the new
government.
   Stoichici kept the doors of the embassy closed Tuesday but said
he was helping Romanians who wanted to return home.
   ``We have the same feelings as other Romanians,'' said
Stoichici, who declared his loyalty to the new government on
Saturday, before the outcome of the fighting was clear.
   Another embassy officer, Vasile Leca, said ``all the staff ...
condemn the crimes that were done to the Romanian people by Nicolae
and Elena Ceausescu.''
   Stoichici and Leca refused to allow a reporter inside the
embassy, speaking instead through iron bars on a window.
   Splattered, frozen eggs coated the white brick walls of the
embassy, a turn-of-century mansion on Sheridan Circle along Embassy
Row.
   Wooden police barricades and yellow plastic tape stretched
alongside the sidewalk where over the weekend scores of Romanians
vented their rage against Ceausescu's 24-year rule.
   The ambassador said his first order of business was to ``work to
improve relations with the United States,'' which had grown
increasingly critical of Ceausescu's human rights policies.
   ``Las evening, the State Department informed us that they
recognized the staff of the Romanian Embassy'' as representative of
the new government, said Stoichici. He said he was in telephone
contact with U.S. authorities.
   A State Department official said no meetings were scheduled
between Stoichici and U.S. diplomats.
   ``They are in telephone contact with us, but when we call them,
they don't answer,'' said the source, who spoke on condition of
anonymity. Press calls to the embassy were not answered, either.
   Romanian consular officials were accepting, through the barred
window, visa applications from Romanian-Americans who wanted to
return home.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>___</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   AID said the address for those wishing to send donations to
Romania is: American Red Cross; PO Box 37243, Washington D.C.
20013. The telephone number for those wishing to help is: (703)
276-1914, which is Volunteers In Technical Assistance or VITA.
</TEXT>

</DOC>