<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0113 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1526EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-FlaGov-Security     12-18 0322</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fla Gov-Security,0331</SECOND>
<HEAD>Martinez May Increase Protection; Miami Mayor Under Watch</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Judge-Execution Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CURT ANDERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TALLAHASSEE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gov. Bob Martinez, whose life has been
threatened by Colombian drug barons, said Monday he will consider
wearing a bulletproof vest following the assassination of an
Alabama federal judge.
   The Florida Department of Law Enforcement has urged the governor
to wear a vest during some public appearances, but Martinez said he
has never felt comfortable in one.
   The governor said he would re-evaluate that stance because of
the weekend mail bombing that killed Robert Vance, an 11th U.S.
Circuit Court of Appeals judge, in his home outside Birmingham, Ala.
   Brian Ballard, Martinez's director of operations, said the
governor probably would wear a bulletproof vest ``as a last
resort.''
   ``If there was a specific threat, I think maybe he'd put one
on,'' Ballard said. ``He doesn't feel comfortable that the governor
of the state of Florida should have to wear one of those things.''
   Martinez has taken a leading anti-drug role in organizations
such as the National Governors Association.
   Authorities have not linked drug dealers or the Colombian
cocaine cartels to Vance's killing Saturday. But Martinez has been
threatened previously by drug lords and the bombing drew attention
to the governor's security precautions.
   ``We take into account events like that which just occurred in
Birmingham,'' said FDLE spokesman Mike McHargue. ``We're interested
in this incident.''
   Earlier, authorities disclosed that Miami Mayor Xavier Suarez is
under round-the-clock police protection because of threats
attributed to factions of the Colombia cartel.
   ``We're received information indicating there might be a threat
to several individuals, including the mayor and governor,'' said
Lew Wilson, agent in charge of the Miami FDLE office.
   Security for the governor has been increased twice in recent
months because of the threats and the August arrest of a Miami man
suspected of involvement in a plot to assassinate Martinez.
</TEXT>

</DOC>