<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0013EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Salvador-Witness     12-18 0725</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Salvador-Witness,0746</SECOND>
<HEAD>Witness to Priest Killings Says FBI Mistreated Her</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A woman who says she witnessed Salvadoran
soldiers moving towards the residence where six Jesuit priests were
murdered was so intimidated by FBI agents and a Salvadoran colonel
that she recanted her story, a human rights official said Sunday.
   From Nov. 27 to Nov. 30, Lucia Barrera de Cerna, a cleaning
woman at the Jesuit University in San Salvador, and her husband,
Jorge Cerna, were repeatedly asked by the agents and the colonel
what they saw the night of the killings, said Martha Doggett of the
Lawyers Committee for Human Rights.
   When they told of having seen Salvadoran soldiers moving to and
from the priests' residences, they were accused of lying and asked,
``Who put you up to this?'' Ms. Doggett said.
   Ms. Barrera was also told, ``Depending on what you say, you may
or may not have to go back to El Salvador,'' said Ms. Doggett, who
coordinates Latin American and Caribbean affairs for the Lawyers
Committee and was one of two representatives from the organization
to interview Ms. Barrera recently.
   The Salvadoran, Lt. Col. Manuel Antonio Rivas, also yelled at
Ms. Barrera: ``I'm ashamed of you! You're a Salvadoran! You're a
liar!'' said Ms. Doggett.
   Rivas is head of the U.S.-trained Special Investigative Unit,
which was designed to handle human rights cases.
   After three days of interrogation, Ms. Barrera ``couldn't take
it anymore. She wanted to be left in peace,'' said Ms. Doggett.
   On Nov. 30, when she was asked by Rivas to ``tell us again what
you saw from the window,'' Ms. Barrera replied: ``I didn't see
anything from the window,'' Ms. Doggett said.
   That night, she told her husband what she had done and the next
day he too recanted.
   Both of them failed lie detector tests when they repeated their
story that they had not seen the soldiers.
   The State Department then turned them over to the custody of the
Association of Jesuit Colleges and Universities, which contacted
the Lawyers Committee for Human Rights.
   ``It's a mystery to me why they would treat her this way,'' said
Ms. Doggett. ``She was treated as one would streat a suspect in a
crime and not a witness. She was already terrified. She'd lost some
of the people she was most close to (the priests) and then she was
uprooted from her home.''
   She added, ``These hostile people, they sort of ensured that she
wouldn't cooperate.''
   Duty officers at the FBI and the State Department in Washington
said there was no one available to comment on the matter Sunday
night. However, The New York Times reported in its Monday editions
that officials with the FBI and State Department had said there was
no evidence to support the Cernas' allegations.
   Ms. Barrera told Ms. Doggett she was awakened some time after
midnight Nov. 16 by the sound of gunfire and from a window saw five
men _ two wearing camouflage uniforms with visored caps and guns _
walking toward a passageway leading to the priests' residence.
   According to Ms. Doggett, she heard a priest whom she was very
close to _ Father Martin-Baro _ say, ``This is an injustice!'' A
short time later, she and her husband heard gunfire constantly.
   The next morning, with security guards who worked for the
Jesuits, Ms. Barrera and her husband found the bodies of two
housekeepers who had worked for the priests. She also saw the body
of Martin-Baro, and her husband saw the bodies of four of the six
priests who had been murdered.
   A human rights official of the Archdiocese learned what they had
witnessed and told them to take sanctuary in a foreign embassy.
They first went to the Spanish Embassy, where a Salvadoran judge
took a statement from them, then to the French Embassy, and then
they were brought by a U.S. Embassy official and an FBI agent to a
Miami hotel on Nov. 23.
   Ms. Barrera and her family lived in a suburb of San Salvador,
but had spent the night the priests were killed in a cottage near
the priests' residence because of heavy fighting in their own
neighborhood.
   She told Ms. Doggett she was sure the soldiers who came to the
priests' residence were government soldiers because the entire area
was held by the government forces.
</TEXT>

</DOC>