<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0218 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 2056EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f BC-Bourbon Adv31   12-28 0776</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Bourbon, Adv 31,0801</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sun., Dec. 31, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Bourbon Closes 200th Year With Battle Against Declining Consumption</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserGraphic under ``Bourbon''</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN A. BOLT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The revelry of the New Year's weekend marks the
end of bourbon's 200th year, but the only truly American liquor
faces declining consumption as drinkers turn to sipping cordials
and gulping vodka.
   Outside the United States, especially in Japan, ``bourbon is
accepted as a very sophisticated, very American, very high price,
very quality spirit,'' said Barry Berish, president of Jim Beam
Brands Co., which makes the best-selling U.S. bourbon.
   But that's at odds with bourbon's image back home, where it's
considered an everyday kind of liquor, summoning images of
two-fisted drinkers throwing back shots of bourbon or patrician
Southerners sipping bourbon in the form of mint juleps.
   Bourbon has only half the share of the U.S. distilled spirits
market it had 20 years ago, falling from 20.7 percent in 1970 to
about 10 percent in 1988, the last year for which numbers were
available.
   After hitting a high of 25.5 million cases in 1973, U.S. bourbon
consumption has fallen to 15.3 million cases in 1988, according to
Jobson's Liquor Handbook, an industry guide.
   ``Basically, it's the white goods _ the vodkas, gins, tequilas,
rums and cordials'' that are gaining, said Jobson's Editor Nicholas
Furlotte. Vodka's now the most popular stiff drink in America, with
30.2 million cases sold in 1988.
   Bourbon is generally considered to be the legacy of a pioneer
Baptist minister living in the wilds of what was then Bourbon
County, Va., a region that's now part of Kentucky.
   Sometime in 1789 _ probably September, according to the
Dallas-based Bourbon Information Bureau _ the Rev. Elijah Craig
mixed spring water, corn, rye, barley malt and who knows what else
to concoct bourbon.
   Within 21 years, the region had 2,000 stills and bourbon had
even become an unofficial currency.
   Today, Kentucky is home to 14 bourbon distilleries and produces
80 percent of the world's bourbon supply.
   The liquor Craig devised was clear, however, not the amber
bourbon we know today. The reason, according to even less provable
lore, has to do with a barrel maker's mistake.
   ``According to legend, a 19th century barrel maker was steaming
and bending barrel staves over an open fire,'' the Bourbon
Information Bureau says. ``He didn't watch the staves carefully
enough and they soon began to char. Being a frugal fellow, he went
ahead and used them anyway, not bothering to tell the distiller.
   ``However, the distiller who used the barrel found that his
whiskey had improved in flavor and picked up a rich color. Needless
to say, he insisted that all of his barrels in the future have
charred staves.''
   And now, according to a federal law passed in 1964, a liquor can
only be called bourbon if it contains more than 51 percent corn in
the mash, and is aged in ``new charred oak containers'' for at
least two years. Some bourbons, however, contain more corn and are
aged longer.
   The holidays are an especially important time in the liquor
business. In 1988, 13.7 percent of bourbon sales were in December,
according to Jobson's, and Furlotte estimates that 25 percent to 35
percent of sales come between Thanksgiving and New Year's.
   Bourbon apparently is most popular in Washington, D.C., which
leads the per capita rankings for bourbon consumption.
Washingtonians drink up 161.3 cases per thousand people _ almost
three times the national average of 62.2 cases.
   Kentucky is second at 139.5 cases per thousand residents.
   While consumption of bourbon and other distilled spirits has
been declining, Jobson's says the fall seems to have slowed, and
``people want the best, but they don't want to feel as if they're
being taken.''
   The Bourbon Information Bureau, a promotional office funded by
the Schenley American Whiskey Group, says ``a shakeout is taking
place among marginal and less-profitable brands,'' leaving the
market open for the biggest bourbon producers.
   Jim Beam's Berish agrees, sayings his brands' market share and
volume are increasing in the United States, where the company is
using a ``back-to-basics'' advertising campaign to capitalize on
bourbon's history and tradition.
   In addition, ``We see a marvelous potential to sell and promote
what is the American spirit throughout the world,'' Berish said.
   Industry officials aren't sure how much bourbon is sold in
Japan, but Berish said Jim Beam's international sales are up 11
percent to 15 percent.
   ``The Japanese love American products,'' he said. ``They like
our food, they like our music, they like our clothes and they like
our bourbon.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, Dec. 31</NOTE>

</DOC>