<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0114 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0925EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a w PM-WalterMears ADV26   12-25 0855</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Walter Mears, ADV 26,0874</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv 26</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release PMs Dec 26 and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Credibility Gap Looms Due to Bush Administration Gestures Toward
China</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WALTER R. MEARS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The ingredients of a credibility gap are
showing in the tortuous White House explanations of administration
missions and gestures toward China, a private easing of publicly
declared sanctions. It is an account heavy with fine print and fine
distinctions as President Bush and his spokesmen argue that
Americans were not misled by secret diplomacy.
   Administrations that offered hairsplitting definitions in
defense of their actions have had trouble before. Lyndon B.
Johnson's credibility problems began when he shaded meanings to
create impressions that would build support for his policies.
   The controversy over the Bush administration's secret and
secretive China overtures is not ended, only on hold because of
U.S. intervention in Panama. It will be revived, with an effort to
override a Bush veto of a bill extending visas for Chinese students
due soon after Congress reconvenes Jan. 23.
   The administration's sanctions were imposed June 20, after the
massacre in Tiananmen Square that began China's repression of
democracy demonstrators. Bush was said to have suspended ``all
high-level exchanges of government officials'' while halting
military exchanges and postponing international loans to Beijing.
   But within two weeks of that decree, Bush secretly sent two top
officials to Beijing on a mission disclosed Dec. 18 after it had
been reported by Cable News Network. The same two men, Brent
Scowcroft, the national security adviser, and Lawrence S.
Eagleburger, the deputy secretary of state, went to China on Dec. 2
and 3; that trip was announced at 2 o'clock on a Saturday morning,
after they had arrived. Bush's spokesman said the Chinese wanted it
done that way.
   The second trip had stirred sharp criticism from congressional
Democrats who said the Chinese hadn't done anything to warrant an
easing of the sanctions, which some critics had said were too tame
in the first place.
   Bush said he ordered those contacts with China because improved
relations serve U.S. interests, and because a nation of more than 1
billion people should not be isolated.
   The initial, secret trip came to light a day after the
administration sent Eagleburger to brief a top congressional
Democrat on the December mission to Beijing _ while withholding
word of the one in July. Senate Majority Leader George Mitchell,
D-Maine, said he was astonished to learn of the July mission. The
White House said Bush sent Scowcroft on that one to tell the
Chinese of his shock and concern at the Tiananmen killings.
   Bush by then had ordered the sanctions. He and Scowcroft had
confronted the Chinese ambassador with the same message at a White
House meeting.
   Press Secretary Marlin Fitzwater said Scowcroft was sent to
Beijing ``to make sure that the Chinese did not think this was just
a public statement.''
   He said Bush considered it important that the July contact be
kept secret from Congress as well as from the public. To the
suggestion that the Scowcroft message might have been reinforced
had Congress been advised and joined in the reproof, Fitzwater
replied:
   ``It might carry more weight in the American way of thinking,
but not in the China way of thinking.''
   And Bush on Thursday said people should pay close attention to
the words he uses, insisting that he never precluded high-level
contacts with the Chinese. ``I said `no high-level exchanges,''' he
clarified. ``So please look at it carefully.''
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III wasn't careful enough _ he
said in a Dec. 10 television interview that the latest
Scowcroft-Eagleburger visit was ``the first time we've had
high-level U.S. officials go to the People's Republic of China''
since the sanctions. After the secret trip was disclosed, the State
Department said Baker ``regrets that he may have misled'' some
people.
   There was a further easing of the sanctions Dec. 19, when Bush
lifted a ban on loans that promote U.S. business in China, and
approved the export of three communications satellites that are to
be launched into orbit by the Chinese.
   Bush insisted Thursday that his policies were the right ones.
``I know how China works,'' he said, ``see what we can do, make a
representation of how strongly we feel against human rights abuse,
but see what it's going to take to go forward.''
   He also has said that reciprocal Chinese actions would silence
some of his critics. ``I notice now that some of the critics who
were so opposed, using this fantastically, diabolically anti-me
language, they come up now and say well, if you get A, B and C,
then it would be all right.''
   That may be so. But the Chinese haven't offered any of the above.
   On Thursday, Beijing condemned the U.S. move into Panama as a
shocking violation of international law and demanded immediate
withdrawal.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Walter R. Mears, vice president and columnist
for The Associated Press, has reported on Washington and national
politics for more than 25 years.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>For Release Tues PMs Dec. 26 and Thereafter</NOTE>

</DOC>