<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0925EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ColdRdp 1stLd-Writethru a0465 12-28 0769</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Cold Rdp, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0465,0787</SECOND>
<HEAD>Water-Short South Reckons Damage in Lost Crops, Tourism</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 2 grafs after 8th, `Governments hoping...' to UPDATE
with water problems in Louisiana caused by cold. Picks up 9th graf pvs,
`If we have...'.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GARTIES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Southerners just beginning to thaw out after four days of record
cold struggled to patch water systems, reckoned their losses from
crop damage and missed tourism in a normally busy resort week.
   Consumers in the East and Midwest will soon be feeling the
effects of the South's Christmas chill as the devastation on
Florida's vegetable farms drives up prices in the grocery stores,
agriculture experts said.
   Meanwhile, the early winter cold wave continued to make itself
felt farther north today, with barge traffic on Pittsburgh's three
rivers slowed to a near standstill by ice.
   The long, cold weekend gave way to mostly clear skies and
temperatures in the 40s, 50s, even 60s in much of the Deep South on
Wednesday, and most of the region will get highs in the 60s today,
forecasters said.
   Highs in the teens and 20s were forecast from the Northeast to
the Rockies today, with milder temperatures elsewhere.
   More than 100 deaths nationwide have been blamed on the cold
since Dec. 15.
   In communities from Houston to James Island, S.C., plumbers
worked overtime Wednesday to repair water pipes that split in the
freeze, and homeowners faced another day of dry faucets or low
water pressure.
   Governments hoping to restore water pressure begged people to
conserve and to shut taps they left trickling to prevent freezing.
   In central Louisiana, residents of Boyce were without water for
two hours Wednesday afternoon and again for five hours overnight as
the town's wells were shut off to allow water levels to rise. In
Pollock, residents will have only limited water service at least
until the weekend, because the town's three wells failed on
Christmas Day.
   In New Orleans, firefighters pumped water from a bayou to fight
an eight-alarm fire at an abandoned cannery after leaks in pipes
reduced water pressure throughout the city. And the same problem
loomed elsewhere.
   ``If we have a fire, we're in trouble,'' said Mayor George Sides
of Dora, Ala., where volunteers helped look for broken pipes. ``You
can only put so many bricks on the wagon before it breaks.''
   Shortages were reported in five Alabama counties, and in Mobile,
pressure wasn't expected to return to normal for 93,000 customers
for two more days.
   Wilmington, N.C., declared two days of emergency conservation,
cutting off water to non-essential businesses. Leaks were forcing
the city to pump more than 18 million gallons of water a day,
almost double the normal 10 million gallons.
   Thousands of acres of produce froze in the fields of Florida
over the long weekend, and experts said wholesale prices began
climbing Wednesday because of the short supply of tomatoes, bell
peppers, lettuce, cucumbers and other vegetables.
   ``Everything has just tripled in price. Green cabbage was doing
about $8.75 (a box) and they're asking over $20 for it now,'' said
Paul Graff, manager of the Len Strom brokerage in Miami. ``Zucchini
is way up in the $25 range, which was between $11 and $12 before,
and so it goes.''
   Prices will begin climbing in the markets of the Midwest and
Northeast within a week, said Reggie Brown, spokesman for the
Florida Fruit and Vegetable Association in Orlando.
   Production in California and Mexico should ease the shortages
somewhat, he said, but prices are likely to remain high for three
months, until Florida farmers can replant.
   The weather put a damper on tourism around Orlando, Fla., in
what is normally one of the busiest weeks of the year, but resort
operators around Walt Disney World and elsewhere hoped the return
of 60- and 70-degree sunshine would turn that around by year's end.
   Hotel occupancy and attendance at attractions began picking up
rapidly Wednesday.
   ``Between Christmas and New Year's, it's usually a bonanza. But
this year, no,'' said Ron Caimano, general manager of the Embassy
Suites hotel in Orlando, where occupancy Tuesday was just 75
percent.
   The big chill wasn't all bad news, though.
   While it was bringing the rare thrill of a white Christmas to
some, it may have been killing off millions of fleas, ticks, gnats,
mosquitoes and flies, said Frank Funderburk, an extension agent in
Bibb County, Ga.
   ``It's hard to say what nature is going to do,'' Funderburk
said, ``but the insects that bother man should be less in number
early in the summer.''
   Unfortunately, household pests like cockroaches probably
survived, he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>