<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0175 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1956EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DurenbergerDealings     12-20 0385</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Durenberger Dealings,0393</SECOND>
<HEAD>Durenberger: Had `Lapses in Judgment' Over Financial Dealings</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GENE LAHAMMER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MINNEAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. Sen. Dave Durenberger said Wednesday his
financial dealings did not violate Senate rules, but he apologized
for mistakes he made and said he would work to restore public
confidence.
   ``In retrospect, it is clear that I made mistakes and had lapses
in judgment on these matters,'' he said at the first of four news
conferences planned throughout the state Wednesday. ``I apologize
this morning to the people of Minnesota.''
   Durenberger, a Republican, said he did not intend to circumvent
Senate rules on outside income when he signed a book deal with a
Minneapolis publisher, which resulted in his earning $100,000 in
outside income over two years.
   The Senate Ethics Committee is trying to determine whether
Durenberger used the book deal to circumvent limits on senators'
income from speaking fees. The limit in 1985 was about $22,500; in
1986 it was about $30,000.
   Durenberger earlier said his appearances were to promote his two
books, ``Neither Madmen Nor Messiahs'' and ``Prescription for
Change,'' and that he cleared his activity with the Federal
Election Commission, which ruled it was allowable compensation.
   The book deal was one of three plans Durenberger had for
boosting his income when he was having financial difficulties. Two
of the arrangements are being looked at by the Ethics Committee _
the book matter and allegations that he scheduled speeches in 1985
and 1986 to coincide with appointments he and his wife had with a
marriage counselor in Boston.
   In addition, the Senate Rules Committee is looking into
Durenberger charging the Senate for rent at a Minneapolis
condominium in which he had a financial interest. Committee aides
have said their tentative conclusion was that the matter belonged
before the Ethics Committee.
   Durenberger charged the Senate for rent whenever he stayed at
the condo and collected at least $9,947 in expense payments from
the Senate for time he spent in Minnesota from July 1983 to June
1987.
   Durenberger said Wednesday he relied on advice from legal
counsel and tax experts, but said he should have paid more
attention to the details.
   The senator also said he has no intention of resigning from the
Senate and pledged to work to restore public confidence in him.
</TEXT>

</DOC>