<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0147 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1422EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--EmbassyBugs Adv07-1stAdd   12-26 1000</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Embassy Bugs, Adv 07-1st Add,1028</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv07</HEAD>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Sunday, Jan. 7</HEAD>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON: constant attendance.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Across the street is an old Russian church no longer used as
such. Among American intelligence people, who say the place is
loaded with electronic equipment for monitoring its neighbors, the
old church is now known as ``Our Lady of Telemetry.''
   Such was their mutual distrust, the superpowers needed 10 years
to agree on an exchange of sites to be used free of charge for 85
years. The United States got 11.9473 acres in Moscow. The U.S.S.R.
got 12.5258 acres in Washington.
   It took three more years to agree on ``conditions of
construction'' in two stages, each using local labor and materials
in stage one and each using a mutually agreed maximum number of
their own specialists imported for the second, or finishing stage.
   The original agreements stipulated simultaneous exchange of
sites, simultaneous completion of construction, simultaneous
occupancy of the chanceries. They also agreed to exchange
architects' drawings and each would have veto power over the other.
And, since the Soviet Union had no market economy on which to base
costs, they agreed that cost calculation for the Moscow
construction would be based on Washington prices.
   Congress originally appropriated $192 million for the whole
project. Now, says a State Department official, it will be asked to
come up with $270 million more for the new chancery. It will cost
that much because, to play safe, all the labor will have to be
brought in from the United States at American scale to build a
building free of Soviet ears.
   Time schedules meticulously negotiated by the superpowers bent
in the fluctuating heat of their Cold War and the numbing pace of
Soviet labor.
   It took two years to finish most of the embassy in Washington;
the Soviets moved into the residential and support quarters in
1979. It took seven years to complete the equivalent in Moscow, and
the Americans moved into those in 1986.
   All work had stopped. The United States had ``locked out'' all
Soviet employees the year before for building an office building
abounding in ``intentional defects.''
   The invisible presence in the woodwork should have surprised no
one. In Moscow, spying on visitors was older than borscht. The
czars kept informers busy, and their proletarian heirs bugged the
American embassy for years.
   So regularly that guests at Spasso House, the ambassador's
residence, were given cards welcoming and warning them:
   ``Every room is monitored by the KGB and all of the staff are
employees of the KGB. We believe the garden also may be monitored.
Your luggage may be searched two or three times a day. Nothing is
ever stolen and they hardly disturb things. ... If you have
anything sensitive to talk about, please call and make an
appointment with the ambassador to discuss it in his office.''
   The Soviets liked Ambassador W. Averill Harriman so much that
they gave him a handsome replica of the Great Seal of the United
States. It was years before the next ambassador found a tiny
microphone nestled in the carved wooden eagle.
   Americans have also found, they said, more than 40 mikes in the
walls of the old chancery, bugs in electronic typewriters, signs of
microwave assaults on the building, wires leading to a tunnel
between the embassy and a nearby Soviet apartment building, and
traces of a ``spy dust'' called nitrophenylpentadienal by which the
movements of people and objects could be tracked.
   Unintentional defects were equally hard on the psyche of
Americans trying to get a new embassy built in the land of Lenin.
Which brings us to a tale of bricks told with a lingering shudder
by Charles Bassett, chief architect.
   The plans called for the eight-story chancery to be faced in
brick. No problem, said the Soviets. Bassett quickly found
problems. Available Soviet bricks were rough and unattractive.
Lithuania looked promising but that didn't pan out. Likewise the
kilns of Western Europe.
   Finally, the right bricks were produced in Augusta, Ga., and
more than a million were carefully strapped and packaged on pallets
and shipped by boat to Helsinki and by train to Moscow, tenderly
chaperoned all the way by Americans. There, the Soviets had to be
stopped from ruining the bricks by heaving them into dump trucks
for delivery.
   Then, Bassett watched with horror as Soviet bricklayers went to
work using no strings or levels and setting bricks from inside a
wall on irregular lines. ``Among Soviet workers, meeting quotas was
all-important; it didn't matter if the wall fell down the next
day.''
   All work was stopped until master masons with proper tools could
be flown in from the United States to teach and supervise. And it
was stopped again with the discovery of the bugs, before the
building was closed in properly and the well-traveled bricks could
be protected from the weather.
   In their original negotiations in what seems like another age of
man, the two parties set up a cumbersome process to arbitrate
disputes. The United States has since claimed $29.9 million in
damages resulting from Soviet delays and defective work. It has
also given notice of intention to claim an undetermined amount for
``intentional defects.'' The U.S.S.R. struck back with damage
claims for $18 million resulting from U.S. delays. Settlement is
not just around the corner.
   Proving he was no imprudent country bumpkin, Uncle Sam took out
a $42 million policy with the Granite State Insurance Co. 20 years
ago. This was to insure the government ``against unforeseen and
sudden physical loss or damage during construction.''
   When last heard from, the State Department had collected $14,287
from Granite State to cover the theft of construction materials
from the construction site on Konyushkovskaya Ulitsa.
   Among the exclusionary clauses of the policy, the complex is not
insured against damage from defects, intentional or unintentional.
And should the United States embassy in Moscow be destroyed by
nuclear war, Granite State makes clear it will not pay.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>

</DOC>