<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0153 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2136EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Cyprus-Communists     12-19 0304</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cyprus-Communists,0316</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cyprus Party Chief Denies More Resignations Imminent</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALEX EFTY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The secretary-general of the powerful
Cyprus Communist Party denied Tuesday that the party is opposed to
perestroika and said none of its hard-line old guard intends to
resign.
   The statement came one day after the resignation of Michael
Papapetrou, a leading reformer in the party, which is known as
Akel. Papapetrou, 42, also resigned from Parliament, where he had
been a member since 1985.
   Papapetrou complained that most of Akel's Central Committee did
not support perestroika _ the political and economic restructuring
sought by Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev. His statement came
at the end of a five-day Central Committee meeting.
   Dissenters have accused the party of sticking to discredited
Stalinist methods.
   Papapetrou said the discussion ``indicated that the Central
Committee does not have the slightest intention to compromise ...
opening the way for reform and perestroika.''
   Demetris Christofias, 43, Akel's secretary-general, told a news
conference Papapetrou's resignation saddened him and the two would
meet to discuss the issues Papapetrou raised.
   ``We will proceed with the renewal of the party as decided by
the Central Committee meeting and will implement the message of
perestroika and new thinking...,'' he added.
   A statement issued after the Central Committee meeting condemned
the 1968 Soviet-led invasion of Czechoslovakia, falling in line
with East bloc parties.
   Papapetrou and other reformers had publicly criticized the party
for stalling on such a denunciation.
   Christofias reacted angrily when asked if any old-guard members
of the 75-member committee, aged over 70, would resign in
recognition of past mistakes.
   ``We are proud and honor and respect the older members of our
committee who have spent a lifetime in the service of the working
class and who have nothing to be ashamed of,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>