<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1109EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Ambassador-China     12-19 0483</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Ambassador-China,440</SECOND>
<HEAD>With PM-US-China Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Reagan Ambassador to Beijing Condemns Scowcroft Mission</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE FEINSILBER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Winston Lord, a career diplomat who served as
President Reagan's ambassador to China, today denounced President
Bush's decision to send emissaries to Beijing as a ``severely
misguided'' step that will make the United States appear weak to
China's leaders.
   ``One does not shore up the long-term foundations for
Sino-American relations by appearing weak to China's leaders and
callous to the Chinese and American people,'' Lord said in a signed
column in today's Washington Post.
   ``One does not earn respect abroad by reversing field within
months and practicing double standards,'' he said.
   Lord's piece was written before the White House's disclosure on
Monday that Brent Scowcroft, Bush's national security adviser, and
Lawrence Eagleburger, the deputy secretary of state, secretly
visited Beijing on Bush's orders in July.
   Scowcroft and Eagleburger also visited China earlier this month.
The White House announced that visit after they arrived in Beijing.
   Lord served in Beijing as U.S. ambassador from 1985 to 1989. He
was a special assistant to Henry Kissinger when Kissinger first
visited China in 1971 and served as a special assistant to the
president for national security affairs in the Nixon White House.
   Bush has come under criticism from Democrats and Republicans
alike for the Scowcroft mission, which was undertaken despite the
president's pledge to break off high-level contacts until China's
leaders acted to repair the damage done in the Tiananmen Square
massacre of pro-democracy demonstrators last June.
   In an interview Monday, Bush said any suggestion that his
actions amounted to condoning the repression in China was ``not a
good rap, and it's not true.''
   Lord said in seeking improved ties with China the administration
forfeited the right to censure it on moral grounds. ``But even on
its own terms the Scowcroft mission was severely misguided,'' he
said, arguing it undermined China's ``closet modererates.''
   ``Far from strengthening their hand, the admninistration has
robbed them of the argument that Chinese repression and xenophobia
entail costs,'' he wrote. ``Japan, Europe and others will feel free
to follow the Scowcroft trail.''
   The former ambassador said that while censure might not
influence China's hard-line leaders, ``international acquiescence''
in the Tiananmen shootings ``surely reinforces their view that
crushing their populace elicits only fleeting outcries, no lasting
repercussions.''
   Lord was especially critical of Scowcroft's toast during the
Dec. 8 visit. He said Scowcroft ``lined up the administration with
the Beijing regime against the Chinese and American people'' when
he said, ``In both our societies there are voices of those who seek
to redirect or frustrate our cooperation. We both must take bold
measures to overcome these negative forces.''
   Lord contrasted those words with what Secretary of State James
Baker said two days later in Berlin: ``True stability requires
governments with legitimacy, governments that are based on the
consent of the governed.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>