<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0209 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1652EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Heck'sSale 1stLd-Writethru f0159 12-29 0489</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Heck's Sale, 1st Ld-Writethru, f0159,0501</SECOND>
<HEAD>Heck's Selling Retail Operations in Six States</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: New throughout with comments from Heck's official.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK PAXTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Association Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Heck's Inc., unable to turn a profit
despite emerging from federal bankruptcy court protection,
announced plans Friday to sell its retail operations, including 55
discount stores in six states, to New York-based Jordache
Enterprises Inc.
   Faced with mounting debts that totaled $9 million since
February, Heck's essentially decided to give away its retailers to
a subsidiary of Jordache which in return will assume the chain's
debts and longterm obligations, said Maartan Hemsley, Heck's chief
operating officer.
   Heck's said in a statement it would receive ``nominal
consideration'' in exchange for the Take 10 Discount Club stores in
West Virginia, Virginia, Ohio, Kentucky, Pennsylvania and
Tennessee, plus its headquarters building in Nitro, W.Va. and
warehouses in Nitro and Poca, W.Va.
   Retail Acquisition Corp., the Jordache subsidiary, will assume
all debts associated with the retail operations, including $22
million in mortgages and $3.5 million in annual rent, Heck's said.
The deal is scheduled to be completed by spring.
   Hemsley said the company will move its headquarters to
Pittsburgh and concentrate on its wholesale operation, which
distributes automotive merchandise through its Steel City Products
division.
   He said no more than one or two Heck's employees will be
transferred to Pittsburgh. The fate of the remaining 2,000 Heck's
employees won't be known until a definitive sale agreement is
completed next month, he said.
   Heck's Chairman John Isaac Jr. said in a prepared statement that
slow sales during the Christmas shopping season proved that the
chain could not make enough money to keep the stores open.
Operating losses for the quarter ended Nov. 25 were about $8
million, Issac said.
   Heck's, which once operated stores throughout the Southeast and
Midwest, cut its employment from 5,900 to 2,000 and closed more
than 100 stores from 1987 to 1989.
   When the company emerged from bankruptcy protection on Sept. 25,
it changed the name of its stores to Take 10 Discount Club and
instituted a ``membership'' program for additional discounts in an
effort to attract customers.
   Heck's stock was traded on the New York Stock Exchange before
its bankruptcy filing, and it once owned a discount shoe retailer,
a string of women's apparel shops and a furniture store.
   Under the agreement announced Friday, Retail Acquisition Corp.
will lease all Heck's retail properties from Jan. 31 to March 15,
after which the sale will be completed, subject to approval by
Heck's stockholders.
   As part of the agreement, Retail Acquisition agreed to buy all
automotive merchandise for the former Heck's stores from the Steel
City division for at least three years.
   This will be Jordache's entry into the discount retail market,
Hemsley said.
   ``This is their first retail operation,'' he said. ``They had
some prior involvement. But they haven't been in this kind of
business at this time.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>