<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1251EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-EmuFarm     12-27 0683</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Emu Farm,0701</SECOND>
<HEAD>Emu Ranchers _ Their Heads Aren't Buried in the Sand</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Retransmitting a0547, which had incorrect cycle designator.
Originally transmitted for Wednesday PMs; also moved on financial wire.
Now available for Thursday AMs.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto HT2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL GRACZYK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOVELADY, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   There's oil in them thar birds, and two
entrepreneurs are cashing in on the animal that's so despised in
its native land that the government once paid people to kill the
varmints.
   On a 65-acre tract in the East Texas Piney Woods, Mark Solomon
and Dusty Driskell are entering their second year as a new breed of
Texas oilmen _ raising emus.
   ``It's just been unbelievable for us, beyond our wildest
dreams,'' said Solomon, 27, whose full-time job with the Texas
Department of Criminal Justice is designing furniture manufactured
for the state by inmates.
   ``We have to pinch ourselves to see if we're awake. It's still
hard to believe and we have to tell ourselves it's really
happening,'' added Driskell, 29, a tax consultant.
   Last October, the lifelong friends purchased a pair of emus for
$1,800. The Australian birds, which resemble ostriches, now fetch
more than $12,000 per pair.
   They now have 31 birds, including 12 breeding pair. And profits
from sales of birds to people who buy them as an investment have
enabled Solomon and Driskell to purchase the 65-acre spread in
Houston County.
   ``People don't know what they are, but they've been good for
us,'' Solomon said.
   Emus can grow to about 5{ feet tall and can weigh up to 120
pounds. The only bigger bird is the ostrich. Emus have
brownish-black feathers, long neck and long legs that can propel
them about 30 mph.
   The bird's meat, leather and feathers are marketable, but what
makes emus valuable is the oil they secrete.
   The oil _ about 5 quarts per processed bird _ is used as a
pharmaceutical for people suffering from arthritis. In cosmetics,
the oil is used in production of wrinkle-retarding emollient.
   Driskell and Solomon say the meat, although not readily
available, tastes like beef and has less cholesterol and fewer
calories. The leather is used like ostrich leather and the feathers
are used for fishing lures and feather dusters. Even the large
toenails _ three per foot _ are used for jewelry.
   ``Right now it's strictly a breeders' market,'' Solomon said
recently. ``That's why prices are so high because there are not so
many around. But it's getting more common.''
   Emu prices are on the rise because of speculation about placing
a processing plant in the United States, according to the American
Emu Association, based in Harper. One plant already operates in
Europe and another in Australia, where thousands were killed and
bounties were placed on the emu because the bird trampled sheep
fences and ate crops.
   The association estimates about 1,500 breeding pair were in the
United States as of last year, with the largest concentration in
Texas. Driskell and Solomon have driven as far as Washington state
and Minnesota to purchase birds.
   ``Whenever the processing stage comes into play we're going to
get less per bird,'' Driskell said. ``But I'll be tickled to death
when it happens because you'll be looking at a definite place to
sell the bird and a definite income coming in.''
   Their first breeding pair, named Bonnie and Clyde, laid 36 eggs
the first year. The eggs, which are dark green and resemble
avocados, hatch in 48 to 52 days. And once the birds get into a
cycle, they'll lay eggs every three days.
   Driskell and Solomon are expanding their farm and hope to
eventually have 90 pens in operation.
   Some people will purchase chicks at $1,000 to $1,500 apiece,
keep them for three or four months and then sell for as much as
$3,000 each. Feed costs are minimal, ranging from $150 to $180 per
year for each bird.
   Neighbors who raise cattle like to joke that Texas is a land for
moo-moo, not emu.
   ``They are an ugly bird,'' Driskell acknowledged. ``But when
they sell for $12,000, they look pretty good.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>