<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0205 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0831EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv28   12-18 0473</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv28,0494</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv28</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Thursday, Dec. 28</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is Thursday, Dec. 28, the 362nd day of 1989. There are
three days left in the year.
   Today's Highlight in History:
   On Dec. 28, 1917, the New York Evening Mail published ``A
Neglected Anniversary,'' a facetious essay by H.L. Mencken on the
history of bathtubs in America which asserted, among other things,
that Millard Fillmore was the first president to have a bathtub
installed in the White House. Much to Mencken's disbelief, many
readers regarded his spoof as the truth.
   On this date:
   In 1694, Queen Mary II of England died after five years of joint
rule with her husband, King William III.
   In 1832, John C. Calhoun became the first vice president of the
United States to resign, stepping down over differences with
President Andrew Jackson.
   In 1846, Iowa became the 29th state to be admitted to the Union.
   In 1856, the 28th president of the United States, Thomas Woodrow
Wilson, was born in Staunton, Va.
   In 1869, William Finley Semple of Mount Vernon, Ohio, patented
chewing gum.
   In 1937, composer Maurice Ravel died in Paris.
   In 1945, Congress officially recognized the Pledge of Allegiance.
   In 1945, author Theodore Dreiser died in Hollywood.
   In 1973, Alexander Solzhenitsyn published ``Gulag Archipelago,''
an expose of the Soviet prison system that led to his expulsion
from the Soviet Union.
   In 1977, in a surprise move, President Carter announced he was
replacing Arthur F. Burns as chairman of the Federal Reserve Board
with Textron Inc. Chairman G. William Miller.
   In 1982, Nevell Johnson Jr. a black man, was fatally wounded by
a police officer in a Miami video arcade, setting off three days of
racial disturbances that left another man dead.
   In 1987, the bodies of 14 relatives of R. Gene Simmons were
found at his home near Dover, Ark., after Simmons went on a
shooting spree in Russellville that claimed two other lives.
Simmons has been sentenced to die in all of the killings.
   Ten years ago: President Carter withdrew from participating in a
forum in Iowa with other Democratic presidential contenders, citing
the Iranian hostage crisis.
   Five years ago: Vote-counting continued in India, where Prime
Minister Rajiv Gandhi and his Congress Party went on to win a
majority of seats in Parliament.
   One year ago: British authorities investigating the explosion
that destroyed Pan Am Flight 103 over Lockerbie, Scotland,
concluded that the blast had been caused by a bomb on board the
jumbo jet.
   Today's Birthdays: Actor Lew Ayres is 81. Actor Lou Jacobi is
76. United Auto Workers union president Owen Bieber is 60. Actress
Maggie Smith is 55. Pianist Richard Clayderman is 36.
   Thought for Today: ``A big lie is more plausible than truth.'' _
Ernest Hemingway (1899-1961).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Advance for Thursday, Dec. 28</NOTE>

</DOC>