<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0600EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-Cheney     12-26 0480</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Cheney,0494</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cheney Confirms `Stealth' Planes Dropped Bombs On Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DORALISA PILARTE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>QUARRY HEIGHTS, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Advanced-technology ``stealth''
jets slipped through Panamanian air defenses and dropped two
2,000-pound bombs on a military base in the early hours of the U.S.
invasion, said Defense Secretary Dick Cheney.
   Cheney told a Monday news conference in Panama that the raid
before dawn Wednesday was intended to ``stun and disorient'' the
Panamanian Defense Forces at Rio Hato before airborne troops were
dropped there.
   The troops attacked an officers' school and base of the Machos
de Monte battalion, one of deposed Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega's
crack units.
   The raid, first reported by a Pentagon spokesman on Saturday,
was the first combat use of the F-117A fighter jet that employs
``stealth'' technology designed to elude radar. To date, the
super-secret fighter built by the Lockheed Corp. has been kept from
public viewing, with a squadron based in Nevada.
   A photograph of the plane released by the Pentagon last year
depicts a relatively small swept-wing plane with a flat underbelly.
From some angles it looks like a stingray. Stealth technology makes
extensive use of exotic composite materials, some of which absorb
rather than reflect radar waves, and avoids sharp surface angles.
   Cheney refused to elaborate on negotiations over Noriega, who is
wanted in the United States on drug trafficking charges. Noriega
sought refuge Sunday in the Vatican Embassy.
   ``It is U.S. policy that we would like to see Noriega brought
for trial,'' he said, adding that the military's role in the hunt
for the general had ended and ``now it is up to diplomats and
lawyers.''
   Cheney said he met with President Guillermo Endara and vice
presidents Ricardo Arias Calderon and Guillermo Ford and was
``tremendously impressed with their determination to get the
government of Panama back on its feet.''
   He would not say what they talked about.
   Cheney also said U.S. troops had discovered a larger supply of
Cuban weapons in Panama than they did during the American invasion
of Grenada six years ago.
   ``It is sure far more weaponry was found than Mr. Noriega could
conceivably use even if he armed his forces several times over,''
Cheney said. ``I'm not sure what the purpose of this is.''
   Cheney said additional troops sent for the invasion ``will stay
as long as they are needed. ... We don't want to leave too soon
before the objective has been achieved.''
   Cheney noted that the United States does not turn over the
Panama Canal for 10 more years and said, ``There were troops here
before so there will continue to be a U.S. military presence for
the near future.
   The defense secretary visited troops earlier Monday and called
the invasion ``the most surgical operation of its size ever carried
out, not only by our forces but by anybody else's forces.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>