<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0161 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 2028EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Panama-Duran     12-29 0390</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Duran,0402</SECOND>
<HEAD>Duran Hopes Use of Apartment by U.S. Soldiers Will Help Court Case</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DOUGLAS GRANT MINE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Panamanian boxing champion Roberto
Duran said Friday he hopes the use of his luxurious apartment by
U.S. troops will count toward the community service he has been
sentenced to in a Florida court for driving while intoxicated.
   Duran said he is letting his penthouse apartment be used by the
soldiers so they can keep an eye on the Vatican Embassy, where
deposed ruler Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega has taken refuge.
   But mostly, he hopes it will get him off the hook.
   ``I want a letter of recommendation, a certificate of good
conduct, from American authorities here to show the judge in Miami.
That should compensate for the community service,'' he said.
   Early this week, U.S. forces broke down the door of Duran's home
on the 22nd floor of a highrise beside the embassy compound. The
soldiers have since maintained a constant presence there.
   ``If I were anybody else, I would be charging them or throw them
out,'' Duran said in an interview. ``They're taking showers,
sleeping there. The house is suffering some wear and tear. I give
them food, too. And I'm not charging them a cent.''
   Duran and his wife, Felicidad, were not living in the penthouse
when Noriega fled to the embassy Sunday and U.S. forces descended
on the exclusive seaside neighborhood of Punta Paitilla.
   The middleweight fighter, who earlier this month lost a
much-heralded but lackluster title bout to Sugar Ray Leonard, owns
several homes in Panama.
   More than 100 U.S. soldiers have sealed off the streets around
the embassy with wire, roadblocks, tanks, armored cars and
sandbagged machine-gun nests. Entrance and exit from Duran's
building is strictly controlled.
   Duran was arrested Jan. 14 in Miami for driving while
intoxicated. He pleaded no contest in county court five months
later.
   The judge gave him six months probation, suspended his license,
fined him $250 and ordered him to do 50 hours of community service
by giving boxing instruction to Miami children.
   But Duran thinks his cooperation with the American forces should
suffice as payment of the debt he owes to U.S. society.
   U.S. military authorities said Friday they were considering
Duran's request for written acknowledgement of his cooperation.
</TEXT>

</DOC>