<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0193 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1716EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-WallStreet 1stLd-Writethru   12-27 0475</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Wall Street, 1st Ld-Writethru,0495</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eds: Updates with closing prices throughout.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHET CURRIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The stock market gained ground in a quiet
session Wednesday, bidding again to mount a yearend rally.
   The Dow Jones average of 30 industrials, down 2.13 on Tuesday,
climbed 15.14 to 2,724.40.
   Advancing issues outnumbered declines by about 5 to 3 in
nationwide trading of New York Stock Exchange-listed stocks, with
928 up, 560 down and 476 unchanged.
   Volume on the floor of the Big Board came to 133.73 million
shares, up from 77.61 million in the previous session. Nationwide,
consolidated volume in NYSE-listed issues, including trades in
those stocks on regional exchanges and in the over-the-counter
market, totaled 176.89 million shares.
   Analysts found little in the economic news to stir the market
out of its recent lethargy. Interest rates were narrowly mixed in
the credit markets.
   But traders still appeared to be hopeful that stocks might
gather strength in early 1990, once yearend maneuvering by
investors for tax and portfolio reporting purposes is out of the
way.
   Worries persist on Wall Street that the economy will encounter
rocky going in the early stages of the new year.
   However, some analysts are predicting a relatively quick
recovery in business activity, given encouragement from a continued
easing of the Federal Reserve's credit policy.
   Germany Fund jumped 2] to 17\ in active trading as the West
German stock market soared to new highs, propelled by enthusiasm
over the ascendance of democracy in Eastern Europe.
   Other single-country and regional investment companies reaching
new peaks for the year included Austria Fund, up | at 17; Thai
Fund, up 2| at 32}, and Scudder New Asia Fund, up } at 16].
   Scudder New Asia declared dividend and capital gains
distributions totaling $1.38 a share to holders of record Friday.
   Gainers among the blue chips included Philip Morris, up \ at
40\; Sears Roebuck, up { at 37~; International Business Machines,
up \ at 94}; Ford Motor, up \ at 43\, and General Electric, up ] at
63}.
   Hilton Hotels fell 6~ to 82~ on a report that efforts to sell
the company had attracted lower bids than had been predicted.
   Rexene Corp. tumbled 1~ to 4\. The company, whose stock traded
as high as 22] earlier this year, suspended its dividend, citing a
variety of reasons.
   As measured by Wilshire Associates' index of more than 5,000
actively traded stocks, the market increased $17.79 billion, or
0.53 percent, in value.
   The NYSE's composite index of all its listed common stocks
gained .97 to 192.69.
   Standard &amp; Poor's industrial index rose 2.51 to 398.16, and
S&amp;P's 500-stock composite index was up 2.00 at 348.81.
   The NASDAQ composite index for the over-the-counter market added
3.55 to 448.81. At the American Stock Exchange, the market value
index closed at 372.96, up 2.16.
</TEXT>

</DOC>