<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1249EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ChristmasMovies 1stLd-Writethru a0443 12-18 0819</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Christmas Movies, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0443,0837</SECOND>
<HEAD>Holiday Movies Lack a Lot of Christmas Cheer</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Subs 13th graf, ``One very ...,'' to CORRECT that Kovic did
not lose his legs, but the use of his legs.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LINDA DEUTSCH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOLLYWOOD (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In a season when too many smiling cherubs and
sugar plum fairies can make your teeth ache, movie makers are
offering a respite from cheerfulness with the most serious batch of
Christmas films in recent memory.
   Holocaust survivors, a paraplegic Vietnam war veteran and a
platoon of black Civil War soldiers are arriving at theaters for
the holidays.
   Some observers see the blitz of ``message'' films as contrary to
conventional Hollywood wisdom.
   ``It used to be: `You don't open Hamlet at Christmas,' just as
you don't open heavy drama in the summer,'' said Art Murphy, who
follows the industry for the trade paper Daily Variety.
   ``I remember 20 years ago when Columbia opened `In Cold Blood'
at Christmas. It was a great movie. But did people really want to
say `Merry Christmas, let's go see the family get slaughtered?'''
   Others see the season differently.
   Paul Mazursky, whose ``Enemies _ A Love Story'' has been touted
as the movie to watch at Oscar time, says his interpretation of an
Isaac Bashevis Singer story about Holocaust survivors in Coney
Island was planned for a Christmas release from the outset.
   ``You can't expect movies like `Enemies' to open like, `Back to
the Future,''' he said. ``But it's having very emotional responses
and there's no reason it won't be popular.'''
   ``Enemies'' isn't the only Christmas film with a
Holocaust-related theme. ``Triumph of the Spirit,'' in which Willem
Dafoe survives Auschwitz by boxing to entertain his Nazi
tormentors, has opened to plaudits. And ``Music Box,'' starring
Jessica Lange as an attorney who defends her father against war
crimes allegations, opens in selected theaters on Christmas Day
with wide distribution in January.
   ``You find there is a much more mature audience going to films
now than three or four years ago,'' said Irwin Winkler, who
produced ``Music Box.'' ``They don't want to see `Breakfast Club'
or all those teen-age movies. ... I don't know why that's
happening, but I'm grateful.''
   There is a limited range of lighter fare available _ films like
``We're No Angels'' starring Robert DiNiro and Sean Penn
masquerading as priests, and ``Back to the Future II,'' a
continuation of Michael J. Fox's fantasy adventure. For kids young
and old, there's ``All Dogs Go to Heaven,'' ``The Little Mermaid''
and ``Wizard.''
   Hovering over all Christmas releases is the specter of Oscar.
Many films are ``platformed'' this time of year, meaning they are
released briefly in a few theaters for Oscar consideration.
   ``If you look at the history of films that got nominated, many
of them came out at Christmas,'' said Winkler, who points to his
own ``Raging Bull'' as an example.
   One very tough movie that made it at Christmas was the
Oscar-winning Vietnam War saga ``Platoon.'' The same
producing-directing team of Alex Kitman Ho and Oliver Stone brings
us this season's ``Born On The Fourth of July,'' possibly the
toughest movie of this year. Tom Cruise stars as a decorated
veteran who lost the use of his legs and came home to lead the
anti-Vietnam War movement as well as the crusade for veterans'
rights.
   Ho said a newly grown-up audience helps such films succeed.
   ``The baby-boom generation has matured. They are the core
audience,'' said Ho, citing the success of ``Field of Dreams'' and
``Dead Poets Society'' as a harbinger of the changing American
appetite for films.
   ``Serious movies do very well with the baby boomers. They have
grown up and they have more time to go to the movies.''
   Even satires such as ``War of the Roses'' and ``She-Devil'' have
a hard edge this season. They are black comedies about bitter
divorce and revenge.
   Perhaps the hardest sell of any Christmas movie was ``Driving
Miss Daisy,'' the adaptation of a Pulitzer Prize-winning play with
Jessica Tandy as a Jewish Southern matron and Morgan Freeman as her
black chauffeur.
   ``Nobody wanted to make this movie,'' said Lili Zanuck, who
produced it with her husband, Richard. ``We were turned down by
everybody.'' Even Warner Bros., which eventually took it on, turned
it down twice, she said.
   Early reviews were positive, and the National Board of Review, a
15-member organization of the nation's leading film critics, named
it best film of 1989.
   ``Glory,'' the story of the first platoon of black Civil War
soldiers, is being released on a limited basis with a larger run
planned in January.
   ``Audiences now are more inclined to spend their time in a
theater thinking rather than watching bubble gum movies,'' said its
producer, Freddie Fields. ``They are more sophisticated and they're
getting their fill of fluff. You can only have so many cupcakes
before you don't want another cupcake.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>