<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 0206EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Hijacking 1stLd-Writethru   12-17 0567</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hijacking, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0581,0582</SECOND>
<HEAD>PRECEDE Tokyo</HEAD>
<HEAD>Hijacked Plane Returns to China With Wife, Child of Hijacker on Board</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 11 grafs to UPDATE with plane returning to Beijing,
wife, child aboard; picks up 9th pvs, `South Korean...'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Chinese airliner hijacked to Japan was flown
back to Beijing on Sunday, with the hijacker's wife and 10-year-old
son on board.
   The Air China Boeing 747 was heading from Beijing to New York on
Saturday when a knife-wielding man ordered the pilot to fly to
South Korea. South Korea refused permission to land, and the pilot
diverted to Fukuoka, 560 miles southwest of Tokyo.
   President Yang Shangkun, at a brief news conference before
setting out on an 11-day trip to the Middle East, thanked Japanese
authorities for their cooperation in ending the hijacking.
   The hijacker, who was hospitalized, was not on the return flight.
   Police and airline officials said they did not know the status
of the returning wife and child, but foreign reporters saw her led
from the plane in handcuffs.
   The hijacker told police he had participated in China's
pro-democracy protests in June and decided to flee his homeland
after the violent crackdown on the movement, the Japan Broadcasting
Corp. reported.
   The father, who was identified by police as cotton factory
foreman Zhang Zhenhai, 35, is being treated at a hospital for
injuries suffered after he was shoved out the back door of the
plane by a crew member after arriving in Fukuoka, 560 miles
southwest of Tokyo.
   Japanese police said Zhang's wife, whose name has not been
released, said she wanted to return to China. They quoted Zhang as
saying she and the child did not know about his hijacking plans.
   An official at the Civil Aviation Administration of China, in
charge of all airlines, said 185 of the 200 passengers on Air China
Flight 981 flew back with the plane and would re-start their
journey. He said the others planned to continue their trip from
Japan.
   CAAC said most of the passengers were Chinese. Japanese police
said there were 19 non-Chinese, including 12 Americans.
   Flight 981 was on a flight from Beijing to New York via Shanghai
and San Francisco when Zhang ordered the plane to fly to South
Korea.
   South Korean authorities refused to allow the plane to land, and
the plane changed course and landed at Fukuoka at 2:52 p.m., nearly
four hours after taking off from Beijing, a Japanese Transport
Ministry said.
   After the plane landed, purser Wei Li opened a rear door and
told Zhang, ``Look, this is Seoul,'' an official of the Fukuoka
prefectural police said.
   When Zhang peered out the door, Wei pushed him out and he fell
to the ground, said the official, who would not give his name. He
said he did not know if Wei was a man or woman.
   Television footage showed Zhang lying face down on the airport
tarmac and later being rushed into a local hospital.
   Zhang suffered injuries that officials said require up to six
months' treatment. A woman companion whom Zhang described to police
as his wife was overpowered, along with a 10-year-old boy.
   Zhang told Japanese police he intended to bring aboard a bomb
but instead left it at a hotel in Beijing, the Japan Broadcasting
Corp. reported.
   Air China is the international division of the Civil Aviation
Administration of China, China's state airline.
</TEXT>

</DOC>