<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0119 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 2153EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-CoalStrike 3rdLd-Writethru a0637 12-23 0616</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Coal Strike, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0637,630</SECOND>
<HEAD>Talks Recess Until After Christmas</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 3 grafs after 4th graf pvs, `A settlement ...,</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   to
UPDATE with striker's comment; picks up 5th graf pvs, `Usery,
hoping...
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By JOHN KING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Labor Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United Mine Workers and Pittston Co.
failed Saturday in a last-ditch effort to reach a pre-Christmas
settlement in a bitter, nearly 9-month-old strike by 1,700 coal
miners in three states.
   Negotiations recessed Saturday evening with an agreement that
both sides would return to the bargaining table Wednesday.
   Government-appointed mediator W.J. Usery, who had said he wanted
to end the strike by Christmas, told both sides he expected to
settle the dispute by next Friday, according to sources familiar
with the talks. Because of a gag order imposed by Usery, the
sources would talk only on the condition of anonymity.
   A settlement by the end of next week would allow the Virginia,
West Virginia and Kentucky miners to return to work after the
traditional holiday shutdown of mining operations.
   Striking mine workers in Castlewood, Va., said they were not
surprised that contract talks were called off.
   ``I wasn't expecting too much,'' said Bob Dixon, a UMW local
president from St. Paul, Va. ``We did not want to get our hopes up,
that way they don't get shot down.''
   Miners pulling the late shift at the picket shack in McClure,
Va., agreed with Dixon. ``It's kind of what I expected,'' said a
miner who did not want to be identified. ``It was not realistic to
expect so much so soon.''
   Usery, hoping to meet his goal, had the two sides at the table
virtually around the clock all week, taking a break at midnight
Friday but calling negotiators back to the table Saturday morning.
   Considerable progress was made in the past few days but Usery
decided to recess the bargaining until next week because it was
clear that an agreement could not be reached, drafted and approved
in time for the bargainers to make it home for Christmas.
   The possibility of a settlement kept Labor Secretary Elizabeth
Dole, who appointed Usery, in Washington _ delaying a trip she
planned to North Carolina for Christmas.
   The nearly 1,700 miners struck Pittston's coal subsidiary on
April 5, walking off the job at mines in Virginia, West Virginia
and Kentucky after working 14 months without a contract.
   Wages never have been a major sticking point. Instead, the
walkout was prompted by Pittston's refusal to participate in an
industry agreement on how to fund costly miners retirement and
health plans.
   The talks are being closely followed throughout the coal
industry because of the implications a settlement might have on
future discussions about the benefit plans.
   The strike has been costly for both sides.
   The union has paid the strikers about $200 a week in benefits
and is facing fines totallying $63.5 million for violating court
orders limiting picketing and other strike activities. Last week
the union said it would give striker a $1,250 Christmas bonus.
   Although Pittston hired replacement workers, production has been
well below pre-strike levels. The company reported that its coal
operations lost $3.6 million in the second quarter of 1989 and $9.8
million in the third quarter, compared to profits of $9 million and
$7.4 million in the respective quarters of 1988.
   The company has said special security requirements to protect
replacement workers and equipment has cost more than $10 million.
   At times, the strike has turned violent.
   Thousands of striking miners were arrested as a result of
demonstrations in the early months of the strike. Several strikers
also have been arrested in connection with violence against
replacement workers at some of the mines.
</TEXT>

</DOC>