<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1141EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Lucas     12-23 0309</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Lucas,0319</SECOND>
<HEAD>Last Full-Blooded Kwaaymii Indian, Teller Of Tribal Lore, Dead at
87</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tomas Lucas, the last full-blooded Kwaaymii
Indian, has died at age 87 in the Laguna Mountains area that was
home to his ancestors for centuries.
   Lucas, who eagerly retold his tribe's history and described its
cultural traditions for audiences ranging from anthropologists to
elementary school children, died Thursday, said his daughter Carmen
Lucas.
   In his final days, Lucas contracted pneumonia, she said.
   ``He knew he was dying. He told us so,'' she said. ``He told us
of his disturbing dreams where he was surrounded by angels, but
when he reached out to touch them, their wings turned to paper.''
   Because Lucas was the last full-blooded member of the dwindling
tribe, Kwaaymii elders had forced him to learn and repeat the
tribal history.
   Anthropologists and archaeologists came to hear his recounting
of tribal history and many hours of his monologues were recorded on
videotape during talks with children from a nearby school.
   ``I guess that I'm the only one today that remembers the past,''
he told a reporter last year. ``I was the only child and no kids to
play with.
   ``At night, I was bound to listen. Listen to stories, listen to
prayers. ``By keeping my ears open, as I most generally have, I
picked up quite a few things. Some things I wasn't supposed to know
I heard anyway.''
   During World War II, Lucas moved to San Diego where he worked
until he retired at age 70. He returned to the former Kwaaymii
reservation land where he was raised about five years ago.
   Beside Carmen, Lucas is survived by a second daughter, Jacquelyn
Pfingst of San Diego, and three grandchildren.
   An all-night wake was scheduled to begin at sunset Wednesday,
followed by burial Thursday at the former reservation burial
grounds.
</TEXT>

</DOC>