<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0108 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1223EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r k BC-EditorialRdp 2ndAdd   12-20 0944</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Editorial Rdp, 2nd Add,0981</SECOND>
<HEAD>UNDATED: anti-drug commitment.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Dec. 18
   The Columbus (Ohio) Dispatch on fighting drugs:
   Georgette Watson was not afraid to get involved. In Boston, she
founded Drop-A-Dime, a hot line that acts as a conduit for tips on
drug pushers.
   That's terrific. She deserves the whole community's respect and
admiration. There should be more people like her. Not only in
Boston, but in any city in any country that has a drug problem. ...
   In the motion picture Network, the hero defiantly yelled from a
window that he was ``mad as hell and wasn't going to take it
anymore.'' People like Georgette Watson are fed up, too.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Dec. 19
   The Pittsburgh Press on personal saving habits:
   One discouraging aspect of the remarkable U.S. economic boom of
the 1980s was the decline of personal saving among wage earners.
Fortunately, that trend is slowly being reversed.
   As a percentage of gross national product, the personal savings
rate in the United States has risen from less than 4 percent in the
mid-1980s to 5.4 percent this year.
   But Americans still lag behind other industrialized nations in
their saving habits. During the presidential campaign, George Bush
promised to encourage saving, and now his administration is
considering a number of proposals to fulfill the pledge. They may
be onto something.
   The proposal currently floating around the White House and
Treasury Department, for inclusion in the 1991 budget, is
tentatively called the Family Savings Account. It would allow
people of all incomes to contribute as much as $5,000 a year to
their account; after 10 years, the interest and dividends would be
tax-exempt, although the money could be ... withdrawn. ...
   The plan should be attractive to policy-makers. Because
exemptions wouldn't begin for 10 years, loss of revenues to the
government would be incremental and more easily predictable. The
$5,000 ceiling would draw more money into the savings pool than
other plans, including the IRA, which sets a $2,000 limit per year.
And unlike IRAs, in which savings aren't released until retirement,
the family accounts would allow acxcess to savings much sooner.
   If the plan has a fault, it's that it doesn't go far enough. ...
   We know how Washington hates to lose money. But if greater
personal saving is the goal _ and it's a good one _ bolder ideas
may be in order.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Dec. 15
   Hobbs (N.M.) Daily News-Sun on handgun control:
   James Brady is right: Congress is gutless on handgun control.
   Speaking before a Senate committee, President Reagan's former
press secretary, who was shot and permanently injured during John
Hinckley's 1981 assassination attempt on Reagan, charged that
Congress is cowed by the National Rifle Association from passing
reasonable gun control laws.
   One proposal, which is named after Brady, would require a
nationwide seven-day waiting period and a police background check
for all handgun purchases to make sure the buyer had no criminal
record or was not mentally ill. A week's delay in picking up a
handgun is not unreasonable.
   The NRA and its allies on Capitol Hill argue that such a law
would ``victimize innocent sports people.'' Nonsense. The
inconvenience would be minimal and the benefit could be the saving
of hundreds of lives.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Dec. 13
   The Greenville (S.C.) News on the Philippines:
   The serious domestic problems in the Philippines have raised
questions about continued American support for (President Corazon)
Aquino. In the midst of the coup, the Bush administration provided
limited military support for her beleaguered government. Since then
questions have been raised about whether it's wise for the United
States to strongly ally itself with Aquino's troubled
administration.
   It should be noted that there is a difference between support
for Aquino and support for democracy. The point of American aid to
the Aquino government is that it backs a popularly elected
government in the face of an attempt to overthrow it by military
force.
   If democracy survives in the Philippines, the people will have
an opportunity to turn out Corazon Aquino and her government at the
polls. American policy is quite properly based on helping to ensure
the Philippine people have that chance.
   After decades of repression under the dictatorship of Ferdinand
Marcos, freedom in the Philippines is especially fragile. The
United States, in keeping with its long and close relationship with
the Philippines, has an obligation to aid the continued development
of democracy in that country.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Dec. 18
   Argus Leader, Sioux Falls, S.D., on Leona Helmsley:
   As Newsweek magazine once told the story, after Leona Helmsley's
only son died, she sued his poor widow to get a ring returned.
   Reportedly, the billionaire hotel queen also would secretly drop
bread crumbs on the dining room floor of her mansion to test the
efficiency of the cleaning staff. And she would fire other workers
with little provocation or sympathy.
   Most notoriously of all, she once told an employee: ``We don't
pay taxes. Only little people pay taxes.''
   It's easy to see why the self-anointed hotel queen of New York
has developed into such a despised person across the United States.
   Last week in New York, she finally got what she deserved. U.S.
District Judge John Walker sentenced Helmsley to four years in
prison and to 750 hours of communited their blood ties, yet spontaneously
saw something else in
him, calling him ``Lamb of God'' who atones for human wrongs.
   Although protesting his unworthiness for it, John baptized
Jesus, who insisted on it.
   As he emerged dripping from the water, a heavenly glow ``like a
dove'' descended on him, the account says, and a voice sounded,
``This is my beloved Son, with whom I am well pleased.''
   Eventually, as Jesus' ministry began, agents of Galilee's King
Herod Antipas seized John the Baptist, imprisoned him in a dungeon,
and finally beheaded him at the coaxing of the king's dancing
step-daughter.
   Gospel accounts say the imprisonment resulted from John's
attacks on Herod switching wives in a bigamous marriage, but
ancient Jewish historian Josephus says John also was suspected of
inciting insurrection.
   While in prison, John had begun to wonder about Jesus' ministry
and sent followers to ask, ``Are you he who is to come or shall we
look for another?''
   Jesus responded, ``Go and tell John what you hear and see; the
blind receive their sight and the lame walk, lepers are cleansed
and the deaf hear ... and the poor have good news preached to them.
And blessed is he who takes no offense at me.''
   This hinted at possible rivalry between them, but Jesus went on
to extol the baptizer.
   While Christianity generally has minimized John as simply a
forerunner of Jesus, the record shows lingering ties between them.
John's influence lasted long afterward in many places as related by
the missionary-apostle Paul.
   Jesus, in his preaching, often referred to John, asking
challenging questions about him to stump critics. Some
contemporaries saw Jesus as John's successor, thinking Jesus was
the baptizer raised from the dead.
   Indicating the bracketing of their work, Jesus' apostles once
asked, ``Lord, teach us to pray as John taught his disciples.''
   Jesus then recited _ under pressure of John's example _ that
famous prayer known to all Christianity as the ``Lord's prayer.''
   Yet there was a poignant note as John watched his own star
fading and that of Jesus brightening. ``He must increase, but I
must decrease,'' John told his followers. Yet ``this joy of mine in
now full.''
   Grasping the ``historical solidarity between John and Jesus,''
writes New Testament scholar W.R. Farmer, ``has become an essential
first step toward an understanding of the mission and message of
Jesus.''
   The baptizer, says the fourth gospel, ``was not the light, but
came to bear witness to the light.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Tomorrow: The Galilean Clan</NOTE>

</DOC>