<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0086 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1621EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Jordan     12-26 0298</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jordan,0306</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government of King Hussein Loosens Martial Law Restrictions</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AMMAN, Jordan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government of King Hussein on Tuesday
removed most categories of crimes from the military courts,
significantly easing Jordan's 22-year-old martial law.
   State Jordan Television said the cabinet, acting on the wishes
of Hussein, gave civil courts jurisdiction over cases ranging from
political offenses to price hike violations and homicide.
   The action is the last in a series of liberalizing measures in
the kingdom, which this year held its first general elections in
more than two decades and reversed a controversial 1988 law that
nationalized all daily newspapers.
   The changes were sparked by four days of rioting in April in
which at least 10 people died following price hikes of many
subsidized goods and services and the appearance of government
indifference to the economic situation of many Jordanians.
   The cabinet said civil courts will immediately start handling
cases involving firearms, gunplay at weddings, homicide, price
gouging, forgery, assaults on officials, violations of martial law
orders and the ban on membership in political parties, as well as
the law against communism.
   Military courts have handled such cases since martial law was
imposed during the 1967 Arab-Israeli war, in which Jordan lost the
West Bank _ with much of its economy and population _ to Israel.
   The cabinet also said that a ministerial committee will study
whether to remove economic and security offenses from martial law
jurisdiction, and will report its findings within two months.
   The action comes the same week that the newly appointed
government of Prime Minister Mudar Badran must by law seek a vote
of confidence from the recently elected parliament, most of whose
members campaigned for an end to martial law.
   The king earlier this year promised to limit martial law.
</TEXT>

</DOC>