<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0337EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ShootingVictims Bjt   12-28 0666</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Shooting Victims, Bjt,0684</SECOND>
<HEAD>Random Killings Are Latest Weapon in Crack War</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Lysa cq</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIRGINIA BYRNE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lysa Biffle was nine months pregnant and hoping
for a boy. Ebony Williams was looking forward to college.
   Their fates became linked in the final moments of Christmas
night, when both women were shot and mortally wounded by random
shots apparently fired by drug dealers in a turf battle over a
housing project's cocaine trade.
   ``These people happened to be in the wrong spot,'' said police
Lt. Eugene Dunbar.
   But the randomness of the shootings has shocked residents of the
Queens housing project. They now must fear being the target of drug
dealers who Dunbar believes had no other purpose than ``flexing
their muscles'' in the neighborhood.
   ``That's the horror of the whole thing,'' said state
Assemblywoman Barbara Clark, whose district includes the South
Jamaica Houses project. ``I'm ready to call out the National Guard
to stand around the project and defend people against these
drive-by shootings.''
   Miss Williams, 18, who planned to attend nearby York College
next fall, lived with her mother in another section of the
neighborhood. She had eaten Christmas dinner at her grandmother's
house and was meeting friends who lived at the project. The friends
had planned to see a movie.
   The teen-ager and a friend were making a call at a corner pay
phone when the bullets struck her twice in the head at 11:50 p.m.
Monday, killing her instantly.
   Witnesses told police three or four men in a Toyota Camry then
coasted about 200 feet and pulled up next to Mrs. Biffle, her
husband, Dwayne, 25, and his brother, Vincent, as they were getting
into their car after visiting a relative.
   The gunmen fired several shots into the Biffles' car before
speeding off.
   Mrs. Biffle, 26, was shot once in the back, with the bullet
striking her aorta, spleen, pancreas and colon, but missing the
fetus. Her husband was shot once in the left foot, police and
hospital officials said.
   The Biffles were taken to a hospital where doctors delivered a
healthy 6-pound, 7-ounce son by Caesarean section.
   Mrs. Biffle died Tuesday. Her husband and son were reported in
good condition at the hospital.
   ``This is a tragedy compounded to an infinite degree,'' said
Benjamin Suckewer, a partner at the Manhattan law firm of Dreyer &amp;
Traub, where Mrs. Biffle worked as his secretary. ``Along with her
love of her family there always shined through an incredible
faith.''
   He said that when she had a spare moment she would study
Scriptures at her desk.
   Her co-workers, who gave the expectant mother a baby shower last
week, were waiting for her funeral plans to be announced. The law
firm is helping co-workers set up a fund for her son.
   The South Jamaica neighborhood that surrounds the
1,047-apartment project has been the scene of violent clashes by
gangs fighting to gain control of the drug turf left by the 1988
arrests of Howard ``Pappy'' Mason and Lorenzo ``Fat Cat'' Nichols.
   Mason was convicted of racketeering, as well as ordering the
February 1988 murder of Police Officer Edward Byrne. The rookie
officer was fatally shot as he sat in a marked patrol car guarding
the home of a witness in a drug case. Nichols also is imprisoned on
murder and drug charges.
   Dunbar said it is not unusual for drug dealers in the area to
fire at people ``to get a message across to other drug dealers that
someone else is moving in.'' He said during the past year there
have been three other similar shootings in the South Jamaica area.
   ``In the last couple of months there have been at least six
murders in and around the project,'' Ms. Clark said. ``It's just
become unreal.''
   The assemblywoman said she met with Mayor-elect David Dinkins on
Wednesday to demand ``the same kind of response we had when Officer
Byrne was killed, because so far, nothing has happened.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>