<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0014EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ChristmasMiracle     12-26 0347</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Christmas Miracle,0359</SECOND>
<HEAD>Teen-ager Emerges From Coma in Time For Christmas</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SPOKANE, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Just last week, doctors thought
18-year-old Melissa ``Missy'' Goebel would remain in a coma for
years.
   On Christmas Day, the Mead High School honors student was
talking and watching as family members opened presents for her at
Sacred Heart Medical Center.
   ``I thought the very best Christmas present I could ever get was
to hear my daughter talk again,'' said Missy's father, Steve. ``She
gave me that gift with a week to spare. And each day she gets a
little bit better.''
   Missy was injured Nov. 25 in a head-on collision on Interstate
90, just west of Coeur d'Alene, Idaho.
   Ms. Goebel and her 16-year-old boyfriend were in her car when
they collided with a pickup truck traveling the wrong way. Ian
McElfish, the boyfriend, was treated and released. The 79-year-old
driver of the pickup is now in a nursing home.
   A month ago, doctors, family members and friends thought Melissa
would die.
   Missy was in a coma, largely unresponsive to talking and
touching by family members. On Day 19, doctors said Goebel most
likely would be comatose for years.
   But just a few hours after doctors left her room that day, Missy
spoke to her mother. Then, she asked to telephone her brother,
despite her head injuries and a broken neck, clavicle, right arm
and left leg.
   ``She's a little miracle,'' said Victoria Goebel, Missy's
mother. ``She's quite an amazing girl.''
   Mrs. Goebel said she welcomed the sound of Missy bickering with
her younger brother, Brian.
   ``She calls her brother a dweeb a lot,'' the mother said, adding
that the siblings were close friends. ``I couldn't believe it when
they were in there arguing the other day. It was great.''
   Missy's struggle is far from over. The left side of her body
remains paralyzed.
   Goebel said his daughter often slips into a ``kind of dream
state'' and gets confused easily.
   ``She's pretty much like a rag doll,'' he said. ``But she's
further along than anyone ever thought she would be.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>