<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0123EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-CivilRights Bjt   12-26 0869</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Civil Rights, Bjt,860</SECOND>
<HEAD>Employment Rights Bill Tops Civil Rights Shopping List on Capitol
Hill</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE ROBINSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Civil rights forces, stunned by what they see
as a wave of setbacks in the Supreme Court last June, are putting a
congressional agenda forward for next year.
   ``We'll have a fight but we'll win because civil rights is
looked upon with favor these days,'' declares Rep. Don Edwards,
D-Calif.
   A civil rights bill, set to be unveiled soon after lawmakers
return from the holidays, could focus political pressure on the
Bush administration. Opposition would risk alienating the black
community while support would mean repudiation of court decisions
that have found favor among conservatives.
   The sponsors, Sen. Edward M. Kennedy, D-Mass., Rep. Augustus F.
Hawkins, D-Calif., and bipartisan coalitions in both houses are
expected to introduce the bill soon after the 1990 congressional
session gets under way.
   Thus far, Justice Department officials have been saying they see
no problem with recent rulings on the employment discrimination
front. They have said they would monitor the results to determine
whether legislation is needed.
   Civil rights forces say it is needed now. While details are not
available, proponents say the measure will be designed in large
part to counter three decisions by the Supreme Court last June:
   _The court held in a June 5 decision involving two salmon
canneries that plaintiffs in hiring bias suits have the burden of
proving the practices at issue have no legitimate business purpose.
Prior to the so-called Wards Cove decision _ named for a packing
company that figured in the case _ it was the employer who had to
prove that there was a legitimate business reason.
   _The justices on June 12 cleared the way for challenges to
longstanding, court-approved agreements giving minorities and women
preference in hiring for government jobs. The Martin vs. Wilke
case, involving Birmingham, Ala., firefighters, was viewed as a
sharp setback for affirmative action plans.
   _The court ruled June 15 that a civil rights law does not bar
racial harassment in the workplace. The Patterson case was brought
by a black woman from North Carolina who said she was mistreated on
the job because of her race.
   In each case, the court was divided 5-4.
   ``What has happened is that the Supreme Court, in its
mischievousness, in the past year has actually gutted title 7 of
the 1964 Civil Rights Act,'' said Althea Simmons, lobbyist for the
National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. Title 7
is the job bias portion of the 1964 Civil Rights Act.
   Legislation to counter the decisions ``has to pass _ we have no
choice but to pass it,'' she said. ``If you ask, `Is it going to be
smooth sailing?,' I think we have to work hard to pass it, but I
think it's going to pass.''
   Actually, winning approval for the measure might not turn out to
be such a formidable task. No longer the embattled underdogs of
yesteryear, civil rights forces have been getting most of what they
want from Congress, often by margins as wide as 70 percent in each
house.
   ``We expect very substantial bipartisan majorities in both
houses of Congress to support this vital legislation,'' said Ralph
Neas, executive director of the Leadership Conference on Civil
Rights, an umbrella group that includes virtually every civil
rights organization active in Washington.
   Both Ms. Simmons and Neas described the employment rights
measure as far and away the top item on the civil rights agenda for
the year ahead. But civil rights forces are pressing for a wide
array of other items.
   They are hoping for legislation to counter a Supreme Court
decision in a Richmond, Va., case that struck a severe blow at
set-asides that reserve a portion of government contracts for
minority-owned business. Rep. John Conyers, D-Mich., is planning
hearings.
   Legislation to guarantee civil rights for Americans with
disabilities already has been passed by the Senate following a
compromise agreement with the Bush administration. Action in three
House committees is expected when Congress returns from its break.
   Pending in the Senate Judiciary Committee is House-passed
legislation that would order the government to gather statistics on
so-called hate crimes, directed against racial, religious and
ethnic minorities.
   Committees in both houses have approved legislation that would
guarantee employee rights to medical leave in cases involving
birth, adoption and serious illness.
   A conference committee currently is attempting to resolve
differences between House and Senate versions of legislation to
provide federal aid for child care, either through grants to states
or tax credits. Leaders in both houses have said the measure will
get high priority.
   Incorporated into legislation to reestablish the death penalty
now pending in the Senate is an amendment to bar racial
discrimination in imposing it.
   Civil rights forces also are pressing the House to attach
anti-discrimination provisions to pending legislation that would
allow voter registration through the mail, provide automatic
registration for anyone with a driver's license and require
government agencies to register voters.
   Also pending is Senate-passed legislation that would reauthorize
through 1994 discretionary programs to aid handicapped students.
Civil rights forces plan to press Congress again for legislation
that would guarantee Americans affordable housing.
</TEXT>

</DOC>