<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0210 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 2258EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-NKorea-Socialism     12-22 0411</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-NKorea-Socialism,0421</SECOND>
<HEAD>North Korea Says Socialism in Danger</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By K.P. HONG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   North Korea launched a campaign Friday to promote
socialism, warning that it could be destroyed by political reform
and a multiparty system.
   Radio Press, a private Japanese news agency that monitors
Communist news reports, said the campaign suggests that North Korea
is watching the recent reforms in East Europe with ``a strong sense
of crisis.''
   ``If political pluralism and the multiparty system were allowed
in socialist society, they would bring grave consequences.
Anti-socialist forces may come to the fore and destroy the
political unity of the popular masses and fundamentally demolish
the socialist system,'' ruling Communist officials of North Korea
said.
   Official Radio Pyongyang broadcast news of the campaign in a
50-minute report from the Communists' Workers Party organ, Rodong
Sinmun. The Korean Central News Agency carried a full text of the
Rodong Sinmun article as well as eight other related stories.
   North Korean media have remained silent on the dramatic changes
in Eastern Europe, and the reports Friday did not mention them.
   However, an article carried by the Korean Central News Agency's
English service said socialism ``is facing a grave challenge.''
   The article asserted that the socialist system was bound to win
out. ``Socialism tomorrow which withstood challenge of the
imperialists today is sure to be crowned with the honor of final
victory,'' it said.
   North Korea, one of the most isolated countries in the world,
has been making a timid attempt to emulate the policies of openness
and economic reform undertaken by China and the Soviet Union.
   However, the hard-line state remains firmly under the grip of
President Kim Il Sung, who has been ruling it since 1945. Neither
he nor his heir-designate son, Kim Jong Il, has shown signs of a
desire for major reform.
   The party article said, ``The capitalists not only oppose the
socialist, communist idea _ a great ideology which indicates the
path of a worthy life of man _ but also spread reactionary
bourgeois ideology and culture ....
   The article went on to say: ``If there is a crisis in socialist
countries, it is not a crisis resulting from `lack' of commodities,
but a crisis resulting from lack of communist ideology.''
   ``The only effective prescription to cure the fatal disease of
the capitalist society and achieve world peace and common
prosperity of mankind is to liquidate the capitalist exploiting
system and advance toward socialism,'' it said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>