<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0117 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1340EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RudolphStickers     12-22 0309</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rudolph Stickers,0320</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Postal Service Cancels Rudolph Stickers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MITCH WEISS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RUDOLPH, Ohio (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.S Post Office's refusal to let the
post office in this village put Rudolph the Red-Nosed Reindeer
stickers on holiday mail has some people seeing red.
   The Postal Service, citing cost and time, told Rudolph
Postmaster Joanne Patton she couldn't add stickers bearing the face
of Santa Claus' most famous aides to envelopes this holiday season.
   ``I think it stinks,'' said Paul Davidson.
   Each year, the small post office is swamped with cards from
people who want the village's postmark on their mail. Last year,
Mrs. Patton decided to add putting stickers on each piece of mail.
   More holiday mail than ever came through Rudolph.
   ``We had a lot of fun with it,'' Mrs. Patton said. ``People told
us how wonderful it was and it put everyone in the holiday spirit.''
   The sectional postal center in Toledo, however, decided the
stickers were taking up too much time and money, and ordered Mrs.
Patton not to use them this year. Last year's batch of stickers
cost several hundred dollars.
   Bob Hill, director of Postal Service field operations in Toledo,
said the response to the stickers overwhelmed the small post
office. The village has 500 residents.
   Since each letter had to be handled by employees, it interfered
with automation, Hill said.
   Mrs. Patton said mail dropped off at the post office after the
decison to drop the stickers. The Rudolph branch will handle 4,000
letters and cards this holiday season compared with 7,000 in 1988.
   ``I hate to have the Postal Service coming off sounding like
Scrooges,'' Mrs. Patton said. ``I understand their concerns. It
took a lot of time for us to put them on and it did get rather
expensive. But it was fun and people liked them.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>