<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0119 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1454EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Britain-Honors     12-29 0611</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Honors,0627</SECOND>
<HEAD>Honors for V.S. Naipaul, Maggie Smith, and Heroes of Lockerbie</HEAD>
<HEAD>Embargoed For Release 7:01 p.m. EST _ Time Set By Source</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By AUDREY WOODS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Britain on Saturday gave author V.S. Naipaul a
knighthood, made actress Maggie Smith a dame and honored police and
rescue workers in the search for victims of bombed Pan Am Flight
103.
   The colony of Hong Kong, to return to Chinese sovereignty in
1997, also was heavily represented on Queen Elizabeth II's
semiannual honors list, which is compiled by the government. The
queen carries out the investiture of the honors at a later ceremony.
   Former New Zealand Prime Minister David Lange, whose
anti-nuclear stance put him at odds with Prime Minister Margaret
Thatcher, was made a companion of honor, a prestigious order headed
by the queen and never numbering more than 65 members.
   Lange, 47, resigned in August after five years as head of a
Labor government, citing health reasons.
   Naipaul, 57, a Trinidad-born writer, was made a Knight Bachelor.
The author of ``In a Free State,'' ``A Bend in the River'' and
``Enigma of Arrival'' came to Britain at age 17 on a scholarship to
Oxford University and has become one of this country's most
important writers.
   The honor entitles him to call himself Sir Vidiadhar, but his
work always appears with his initials.
   Descended from an Indian family that emigrated to Trinidad as
indentured laborers, Naipaul grew up in a tightly knit Hindu
family. This background is reflected in his writing about
rootlessness and being an alien, even when visiting his ancestral
home in India, which he described in ``An Area of Darkness.''
   Maggie Smith, 55, one of Britain's finest stage actresses and an
Oscar-winner for ``The Prime of Miss Jean Brodie,'' was made a Dame
Commander of the Order of British Empire, the equivalent of a
knighthood for a woman.
   Another actor honored was actor Michael Gambon, most widely
known to television audiences for his lead role in the mini-series
``The Singing Detective.'' Gambon, 49, was made a CBE, or Commander
of the British Empire.
   Many of the 947 awards made in the New Year list went to
emergency service staff who worked at Lockerbie, Scotland, after a
bomb exploded on Flight 103 and the plane crashed Dec. 21, 1988,
killing 270 people.
   A Queen's Police Medal went to Inspector George Stobbs, a local
policeman who consoled many of the American relatives who arrived
at the remote Scottish village.
   John Boyd, the former chief constable of the Dumfries and
Galloway Constabulary, was made a CBE.
   A Queen's Police Medal went to Superintendent Angus Kennedy of
Strathclyde police, responsible for relations between the police
and the news media the night of the disaster, who was honored for
``his calm and immensely professional manner ... under the quite
exceptional pressures from the media on that night.''
   Kennedy heard of his honor after a 70-year-old neighbor cycled
two miles in a gale to his vacation cottage on the Hebridean island
of Coll to summon him the phone.
   ``This comes as a surprise and a very great honor,'' Kennedy
said.
   More than 20 honors went to Hong Kong residents, topped by a
knighthood for Justice Derek Cons of the Hong Kong court of Appeal.
There was a CBE for Li Kwan-ha, the colony's police commissioner
and nine awards for public and community service.
   The issue of British residence rights for Hong Kong citizens
worried by the prospect of Chinese rule, is becoming a very sore
point for the government. Many feel Britain's limited immigration
policy is elitist, but many in Mrs. Thatcher's own party feel it is
too liberal.
</TEXT>

</DOC>