<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0187 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1735EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Opposition     12-20 0753</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Opposition,0780</SECOND>
<HEAD>Transylvania, Romanian Moldavia Lead Opposition to Ceausescu</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIOREL URMA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Opposition to President Nicolae Ceausescu
is centered in ethnically diverse Transylvania and in the northern
part of Moldavia, both of which have stronger historical links to
the West than the Romanian heartland that is Ceausescu's home.
   Periodic outbreaks of unrest have shaken Romania over the years,
triggered by harsh living conditions in the Balkan nation.
   In 1977, about 30,000 coal miners went on strike in the Jiu
Valley to protest Ceausescu's iron-fisted domestic policies _
policies that put an early chill on any form of organized
opposition.
   The valley is Romania's leading coal basin in rugged western
Transylvania.
   The miners demanded pay raises, more food on the shelves and
improved working conditions.
   Faced with the first big wave of opposition since he became
Communist Party leader in 1965, Ceausescu gave in to the strikers'
demands.
   Police, however, subsequently arrested and harassed hundreds of
people who took part in that work action.
   Protest leaders disappeared under mysterious circumstances in
traffic accidents.
   In November 1987, at least 10,000 workers demonstrated in Brasov
in southern Transylvania, demanding freedom, more food and
Ceausescu's ouster. The uprising was brutally put down by police
and the army.
   In the most dramatic protest faced by the 71-year-old Marxist
autocrat, hundreds _ perhaps thousands _ of demonstrators were
reported to have died last weekend in unrest in Timisoara, also
part of Transylvania and 500 miles from the capital Bucharest.
Security forces randomly shot into crowds of protesters there.
   Scenic Timisoara, the city of flowers, noted for its many parks
and trees, is the capital of the Banat, a region of mixed
population containing Romanians, Hungarians, Serbs and Germans.
   It was on Timisoara's main Liberty Square that the protesters
were killed by Ceausescu's security forces.
   It was also on that square that Gheorghe Doja, leader of a
peasant uprising in 1514 and a national symbol against oppression,
died under torture.
   Like the peasants the protesters last weekend demanded freedom.
They shouted: ``Down with Ceausescu!'' ``Down with the dictator!''
and ``Today in Timisoara, tomorrow in the whole country!'' in
allusion to the spreading revolt that apparently has gripped the
country, according to witnesses.
   In the other corner of Romania, in Iasi, close to the Soviet
border, people on Wednesday were burning books by Ceausescu, Mihai
Munteanu, a member of the Soviet Congress of People's Deputies,
said in Moscow.
   Ceausescu's writings had been prominently displayed in bookstore
windows there.
   Iasi is an old cultural and historical center. French influence
was dominant there, starting in the 18th century. Many sons from
well-off families traveled to Paris to complete their education.
   They gradually formed the nucleus of an intellectual class,
which favored French philosophy and thought and became receptive to
the liberal ideas of the French Revolution and later trends.
   Hundreds of Romanian students marched in Iasi in January 1987
demanding better food and more heat in their cold dormitories.
Industrial workers held several strikes there.
   Munteanu, an ethnic Romanian who lives in Soviet Moldavia, a
former Romanian region annexed by Moscow in 1940, said he spoke
with acquaintances in Romania and was told that pro-democracy
demonstrations were going on in several cities.
   Southern Romania, historically known as Walachia, lived for five
centuries under the Ottoman Turks and has little democratic
tradition.
   The historic development of Transylvania was substantially
different and more complex.
   The province benefited from comparatively higher cultural and
political standards under the Austro-Hungarian Empire until the
empire collapsed in 1918, when Transylvania was united with the
Romanian kingdom.
   During its long experience under the Hapsburgs and Hungarians,
Transylvania became intimately associated with the events in
Central and Western Europe.
   Opportunities for travel to Vienna and cultural contacts that
developed shaped the people's political awareness.
   As Ceausescu stubbornly rejected reforms under way in the Warsaw
Pact countries, the opposition found it could now learn something
from its Marxist neighbors. By way of special TV antennas, it could
pick up Soviet, Hungarian and Yugoslav programs.
   Even in Bucharest, about 35 miles north of the Bulgarian border,
the 2 million residents can watch Bulgarian television apparently
unhindered.
   ``You can't keep Romanians isolated from the outside world, as
Ceausescu would like,'' a woman living in Iasi, six miles from the
Soviet border, said. ``It's enough to have a TV or a radio set to
be kept abreast of developments in the world.''
   ``The virus of freedom is spreading anyway,'' she told The
Associated Press.
</TEXT>

</DOC>