<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0097 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1614EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NuclearWasteDump     12-30 0536</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nuclear Waste Dump,0549</SECOND>
<HEAD>Opponents Say Fight Has Just Begun While Supporters Welcome Waste
Dump</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By J.L. SCHMIDT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUTTE, Neb. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Opponents of plans to put a $40 million
low-level radioactive waste dump near this farming community say
they have just begun to fight, while others see the project as an
``economic shot-in-the-arm.''
   ``We'll fight this _ technically, politically and legally,''
opponent Lowell Fisher said Saturday.
   Fisher, the leader of a group called Save Boyd County, said it
felt like ``a death in the family'' Friday when a developer, US
Ecology, announced it had selected a 320-acre site about two miles
west of this community of about 580 residents for construction of
the dump.
   The above-ground system of concrete vaults would store low-level
radioactive waste, such as contaminated gloves and equipment from
nuclear power plants and hospitals, from Nebraska, Kansas,
Oklahoma, Arkansas and Louisiana.
   Many had figured the site would be ruled out for its location,
five miles from South Dakota and therefore remote from the other
four states in the Central Interstate Low-Level Radioactive Waste
Compact.
   Sen. Tom Daschle, D-S.D., called the decision unsound and said
he would fight it.
   But Ken Reiser, one of the leaders of the proponent People for
Progress, said he was elated at the prospect of economic
development and the estimated 30 to 40 jobs the facility could
bring to the area.
   ``This is one of the best things since electricity came into
this county or the day my dad changed from using a horse to using a
tractor to farm,'' Reiser said Saturday.
   US Ecology officials said they chose the Boyd County location
over two others in southern Nebraska because it was the best choice
geologically. The company already has options on the land.
Opponents say the tract contains wetlands and any leaks could
contaminate Nebraska's groundwater.
   Since Boyd County was named as a finalist site, opponents have
boycotted businesses owned by supporters, sought to recall a county
supervisor and posted ``no-hunting'' signs on their land in an
attempt to get hunters to protest consideration of the site.
   At the US Ecology office in Butte manager Bob Wittry handed out
job applications Saturday even though the company won't even submit
its license application to the state until July.
   Lavaun Johnson said that the office on Butte's main street was
the first to open in nearly a decade. Butte once boasted five
grocery stores and several car dealerships, she said.
   ``Today it's mostly two bars, a lumber company, a village-owned
restaurant and the post office,'' she said.
   Her husband, Owen Johnson, called the announcement an ``economic
shot-in-the-arm'' to the mostly farming community.
   ``It might bring some of our native sons and daughters back home
to work,'' he said. ``We've seen nothing but `ag' up here for
years, and bad times on the farm have taken their toll.''
   US Ecology has promised that the five states and their utilities
and other companies that generate waste will pay $300,000 a year to
Butte and Boyd County until the facility is built and up to $2
million each year the facility is used. That money is in addition
to tax revenue and economic benefits produced by the facility.
</TEXT>

</DOC>