<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0152 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0934EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APArts:Britain-Theater Adv04   12-28 0591</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP Arts: Britain-Theater, Adv 04,0604</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv 05</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Thurs PMs, Jan 4 and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>New Plays Taking Center-Stage in London</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MATT WOLF</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   New plays are about to take center-stage in London
as the theater capital moves away from the star-filled revivals and
classic productions that have dominated recent seasons.
   Alan Ayckbourn, Michael Frayn and Simon Gray are just three of
the well-known English dramatists who will open new plays on
London's commercial West End in the first six months of 1990.
   Howard Barker and David Hare, two well-known leftist
playwrights, will premiere three plays between them in London's
government-subsidized theaters.
   Barker kicks off the activity with two plays starting
performances Jan. 4: ``Seven Lears,'' at the Royal Court, which
takes its title from Shakespeare's ``King Lear''; and ``Scenes From
an Execution,'' at the Almeida.
   The latter brings two-time Academy Award-winner Glenda Jackson
back to the London stage following her performance this fall in a
Los Angeles stage revival of Edward Albee's ``Who's Afraid of
Virginia Woolf?''
   The new play casts her as a painter in Renaissance Venice.
   Feb. 8 sees the bow at the Royal National Theater of ``Racing
Demon,'' David Hare's play about four south London clergymen. The
show marks Hare's first play since his 1988 ``The Secret Rapture,''
which had a long run at the National but flopped quickly this fall
on Broadway.
   Alan Ayckbourn's ``Man of the Moment,'' the prolific author's
36th play, opens Feb. 14, with Michael Gambon (TV's ``The Singing
Detective'') heading the cast.
   ``It's my play with a swimming pool,'' Ayckbourn, 50, said in an
interview, referring to the setting for one of the scenes. The
play's theme, he added, was ``what the media selects from people.''
   ``I'm always amazed that it picks out the people it likes, and
the people who might be nicer it leaves alone,'' he said. ``Some of
the nicest people on TV are the nastiest people in real life.''
   ``Look Look,'' Michael Frayn's first completely new play since
his 1984 ``Benefactors,'' opens April 17 at the Aldwych. The
dramatist has been busy lately translating and adapting the plays
of Anton Chekhov and writing for television. Frayn, who had
Broadway successes with both ``Benefactors'' and ``Noises Off,''
was reluctant to discuss his new play's plot.
   ``Silence is what one had better preserve at this point,'' he
said. The play stars Stephen Fry and Serena Gordon, and is directed
by Mike Ockrent (``Me and My Girl'').
   Simon Gray, who wrote ``Butley'' and ``The Common Pursuit,'' is
expected to have a new play on the West End by the summer, and John
Osborne and Christopher Hampton are two other noted playwrights
readying new works.
   The flurry of new writing contrasts with 1988 and 1989, when the
primary theatrical excitement came from seeing stars do the
classics _ Vanessa Redgrave in ``Orpheus Descending'' and Dustin
Hoffman in ``The Merchant of Venice,'' to name two London
productions that traveled to Broadway.
   This past year's most revelatory staging was Trevor Nunn's
tightly focused revival of William Shakespeare's ``Othello'' for
the Royal Shakespeare Company. The production paired Tony-winning
actor Ian McKellen and opera singer Willard White as Iago and the
jealous Moor.
   Unlike recent years, there are few new musicals to whet
theatergoers' appetites. By far the most eagerly awaited are the
British debuts of two shows by Stephen Sondheim: ``Sunday in the
Park With George,'' opening March 15 at the Royal National; and
``Into the Woods,'' which bows next fall on the West End.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv</NOTE>

</DOC>