<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0189 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2224EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Unrest 1stLd-Writethru a0689 12-18 0526</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Unrest, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0689,0538</SECOND>
<HEAD>13 Arabs Wounded During Protest Against Jewish Vandals</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: ADDS three grafs with battle in Lebanon</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israeli soldiers Monday shot and wounded 13
Palestinians during a stone-throwing protest against vandalism by
Jewish settlers at a Gaza Strip building site planned to house
Palestinian refugees, Arab reporters said.
   Hospital officials said 18 other people were shot and wounded in
other clashes with Israeli troops in the occupied Gaza Strip.
   The 13 wounded in Rafah included a 10-year-old boy seriously
wounded in the head with rubber bullets and another 10-year-old
shot in the hand, hospital officials said.
   The army confirmed 10 wounded in another clash in Gaza's Shati
refugee camp and said it was checking the reports of wounded in
Rafah.
   An army spokeswoman said settlers attacked the construction site
in Rafah's Tel Sultan section on Sunday night, overturning a
foundation, slashing cement bags and sawing down a utility pole.
   The 5,800 Palestinian refugees are being settled in Rafah, on
the Egyptian border, as part of a family reunification program
under the 1979 Egypt-Israel peace treaty. They were cut off from
families in Gaza when Israel returned the Sinai Desert to Egypt as
part of the treaty.
   The reunification is expected to take more than a year, and
several families from Egypt laid the foundations of homes two weeks
as a first step.
   After the vandalism, the Committee for Gaza Settlements, which
represents the almost 2,500 Jewish settlers in the area, released a
statement to the press threatening more action if the resettlement
effort continues.
   ``The settler's committee promises that it will not rest and
will not be silent until the decision is changed regarding the
resettlement of refugees in Tel Sultan,'' the statement said.
   Committee member Yigal Kirshinzaft said on Israel radio, ``We
won't leave one stone on top of another in this place. Terrorists
will not be allowed in the borders of this state.''
   The army spokeswoman said the military is prepared to take
measures to protect the building site but would not say what
actions have been taken.
   At least 631 Palestinians and 43 Israelis have been killed
during the two-year-old uprising against Israeli occupation.
Palestinians also have killed 161 fellow Arabs, mostly on suspicion
of collaborating.
   The latest victim was a 30-year-old woman, Suad Abu Hadrus, who
died on Monday. She was beaten by masked youths Sunday in the Askar
refugee camp near Nablus in the West Bank, Israel radio said. It
said she was killed on ``morality grounds.''
   Some Arabs have been killed for ``moral offenses'' against the
Palestinian revolt, such as prostitution or drug-dealing.
   In Israel's self-proclaimed security zone in south Lebanon,
Israeli-backed Lebanese militiamen killed two Arab guerrillas in a
gunbattle Monday, Israeli military officials said. One militiaman
was also killed, they said.
   The clash between the guerrillas and the Israeli-backed South
Lebanon Army occurred in the eastern sector of the zone near Ayn
Habbariyah, a village five miles north of the Israeli border. The
guerrilla group was not identified.
   The zone is patrolled by Israeli soldiers and the 3,000-member
South Lebanon Army, a mostly Christian force trained and financed
by Israel.
</TEXT>

</DOC>