<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0122 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1335EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i USTroopsThinkTheyAlmostGotNoriegaFirstDay     12-22 0519</FIRST>
<SECOND>US Troops Think They Almost Got Noriega First Day</SECOND>
<HEAD>EDITOR'S NOTE: The following is based on a pool dispatch from Panama
by Steven Komarow of The Associated Press and Robert Kearns of Reuters.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEVEN KOMAROW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. troops think they almost got
Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega on the first day of the intervention
when they broke into a fortified house, finding signs of panicky
flight and, by one account, ``vats of blood'' and animal entrails.
   The abandoned office and house, on the seacoast near here and
close to several U.S. military bases, was stormed by U.S. soldiers
on Tuesday, about six hours after the U.S. invasion began.
   ``The cigarettes were still smoking in the ashtray and the women
left their purses, which no woman would ever usually do,'' a
soldier familiar with the house said Thursday.
   But Noriega was not to be found in the retreat that had been
specially built for him, and soldiers continued scouring the
countryside Friday for the deposed leader wanted in the United
States on drug charges.
   The American soldier, who would not give his name, said troops
who saw the house spread the word that one room was apparently
devoted to the occult, with blood and entrails.
   Military officials could not immediately confirm the soldier's
account.
   Saying the house might have been booby-trapped, officers would
not allow reporters and photographers inside, Gen. John Huston said.
   Another soldier, Sgt. 1st Class Joseph Torregrossa, said there
were bizarre trappings in another of Noriega's quarters, his
private office in Panama's military barracks at Fort Amadar.
   ``When we went inside, there were all of these expensive prints,
but he also had a portrait of Adolf Hitler and a lot of expensive
weapons, mostly automatic,'' Torregrossa said. ``He had German
Lugers, Israeli Uzis, all sorts of real sophisticated stuff.''
   Travel restrictions, including a nighttime curfew, were still in
effect Friday, and new fighting was reported with men loyal to
Noriega attacking the headquarters of the U.S. Southern Command.
   A two-hour tour through a bombed-out shopping district that once
was a Noriega stronghold showed scenes of near chaos as thousands
of looters seized refrigerators, microwaves, automobile tires,
gasoline and other goods.
   They cheerfully stopped, however, to shout ``Viva Bush, Viva
Bush'' or ``Bush, Bush, Bush'' as they waved to soldiers and
journalists. One held up a knife sharpener and joked, ``It's a
present from Bush.''
   Noriega's nine-building headquarters was a smouldering hulk, its
windows blown out by tank and artillery fire. It was closely
guarded by dozens of U.S. troops.
   Less than a mile away, the body of a man, face down and
shirtless, lay trapped in the crushed wreckage of a sedan. A U.S.
infantry sergeant said an armored personnel carrier rolled over the
car after the driver was seen passing out AK-47 rifles.
   An old section of the city around Noriega headquarters contained
many of Panama City's poor and homeless, but they had largely
abandoned it, taking refuge in quarters provided by U.S. military
at the American-owned Balboa High School in the suburbs, U.S.
officials said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>