<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1417EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Panama-Neighborhood     12-23 0442</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Neighborhood,0455</SECOND>
<HEAD>Neighborhood That Was Home To 28,000 Burned To Ground</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two weeks ago hundreds of people
gathered around a large TV to watch their neighborhood hero,
Roberto Duran, fight American boxer Sugar Ray Leonard and make the
kind of money they cannot even dream of.
   Last week, they watched another fight on the streets of El
Chorrillo as the invading Americans attacked Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noriega's headquarters nearby. Many were killed or wounded;
thousands lost their homes.
   On Dec. 7 they sat on the ground to watch the match on a large
screen set up on a flatbed truck provided by Gustavo Torreclosa, El
Chorrillo's representative to Noriega's rump national legislature.
   ``Stonehands'' Duran lost, but the people of El Chorrillo were
philosophical about it. Leonard dominated the fight, but their El
Chorrillo-born hero had held several world championships. He'd had
his day.
   El Chorrillo had 28,000 residents, mostly black and poor. Every
Friday night was an outdoor party of music and dancing, with fresh
fried fish and beer sold on the sidewalk. The beer was cheap _ it
usually ``fell off a truck'' down at the Balboa docks.
   Petty crime was a danger, and there were plenty of
``maleantes,'' or hoods, and those who tried to act like hoods.
   The barrio was right next to Noriega's headquarters. Wednesday
morning, U.S. cannon fire and swept across the neighborhood for
hours as troops moved in to try to capture the general.
   The general is gone, but so is El Chorrillo.
   The wooden structures, dating back to the late 1800s and early
1900s, burned like tinder under the shattering cannonade. The fire
lit the sky through the night and sent a pall of smoke across the
city throughout the next day.
   Buildings that were home to thousands were reduced to a frieze
of charred sticks.
   Hundreds were wounded and more than a hundred were dead,
according to doctors at Santo Tomas Hospital, a mile down the
shore. Torreclosa was among the first victims. Everyone who was not
wounded or killed left. Many were dazed, many were unable to take
out even a single possession.
   ``We tried to avoid civilian casualties,'' said a U.S. soldier
who had been there the night of the attack. He refused to give his
name.
   On Saturday, the area was still off limits. U.S. tanks and
soldiers patrolled the streets with loudspeakers warning everyone
to stay away.
   ``Why did they do this?'' a resident asked, looking at the
rubble that had been his building 200 yards away. ``Just because
they wanted to get Noriega?''
</TEXT>

</DOC>