<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 2242EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Colombia     12-31 0463</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia,0482</SECOND>
<HEAD>Suspected Leader of Drug Death Squads Arrested</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM WELLS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The chief of the death squads organized
by the Medellin cocaine cartel was arrested at a police roadblock
in central Colombia, authorities said Sunday.
   Elsewhere, battles between leftist guerrillas and security
forces left eight rebels and four soldiers dead, radio reports said.
   In other violence, a bomb exploded early Sunday in Bogota,
destroying two cars, the national police said in a statement. No
one claimed responsibility for the attack.
   The latest drug-trafficking suspect to be arrested was Jose
Manuel Cruz Aguirre, chief of the Medellin cartel's right-wing
death squads, who is wanted in Peru, the Administrative Security
police said in a separate communique.
   Aguirre was arrested Friday night on a highway about 35 miles
south of Bogota, the security police said. There were no immediate
details on what charges he faces.
   Death squads financed by drug traffickers have killed scores of
peasants suspected of sympathizing with leftist guerrillas, who
have tried to extort cattle ranchers in areas where traffickers
hold property.
   The death squads also have killed about 740 members of the
country's biggest leftist political party, the Patriotic Union,
presumably because the party has the support of the country's
estimated 10,000 leftist guerrillas.
   Aguirre also was part owner of one of Colombia's professional
soccer teams, Deportes Tolima, the security police said. Colombian
authorities have claimed for years that drug bosses are among
owners of several professional soccer teams in Colombia.
   Aguirre was the third purported member of the Medellin cartel
arrested in four days. The others were Jose Antonio Ocampo Obando
and Camilo Antonio Ruiz Vega.
   Ocampo Obando, arrested Friday, is considered by Colombian
authorities to be the fifth most important member of the Medellin
cartel. He is wanted for extradition by the United States, police
said last week.
   Ruiz Vega was a top confidant of Gonzalo Rodriguez Gacha, the
No. 2 leader of the Medellin Cartel who was killed by police Dec.
15.
   On Saturday, police confiscated a 25,000-acre ranch belonging to
Rodriguez Gacha in the central state of Tolima, the security police
also said in their communique Sunday.
   The biggest battle between guerrillas and the army was Saturday
near the Caribbean coastal town of Turbo, the Defense Ministry said.
   Six guerrillas of the Popular Liberation Army and two soldiers
were killed, the Colombian radio networks RCN and Caracol quoted
the military command as saying.
   Also Saturday, guerrillas from the same group ambushed an army
patrol in northeastern Colombia, the radio networks quoted the
army's 5th Brigade headquarters in Bucaramanga as saying.
   They said two guerillas and two soldiers were killed.
   The People's Liberation Army is one of six guerrilla groups in
Colombia and claims it adheres to Maoist Chinese doctrine.
</TEXT>

</DOC>