<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0104 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1549EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Czechoslovakia-Dubcek 1stLd-Writethru a0540 12-28 0509</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Czechoslovakia-Dubcek, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0540,0520</SECOND>
<HEAD>Czechoslovakia's Tragic Hero Emerges Triumphant</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 11th graf ``He was ...'' to DELETE reference to Kremlin-installed
government at the time.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SYDNEY RUBIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Alexander Dubcek suffered two
decades of humiliation at the hands of hard-line Communists who
ousted and banished him for trying to humanize socialism and
increase freedom for his people.
   But with his stunning return to power Thursday as leader of
parliament, the man once considered by many as Czechoslovakia's
tragic hero may be remembered as one who fought the noble fight and
won.
   ``This is a moral satisfaction to the hundreds of thousands ot
people who have upheld the ideals of the `Prague Spring,''' Dubcek
said Thursday in his acceptance speech before the Federal Assembly.
   Elected to replace Antonin Novotny as head of the Communist
Party in January 1968, Dubcek led a courageous band of reformers
who dreamed of a ``socialism with a human face.'' For an
exhilarating eight months, Czechoslovaks felt new personal freedoms
and saw the emergence of political pluralism and economic reforms.
   Intellectuals, straining at the leash of Communist control,
provided ideological ammunition for Dubcek as he argued with Moscow
for the abolition of censorship and the curbing of police, all in
the name of a rejuvenated Party.
   The radical novelty of the ``Prague Spring'' was the realization
that economic reform was impossible without political
decentralization, an idea proposed nearly 20 years later by Soviet
President Mikhail S. Gorbachev.
   But under Soviet leader Leonid Brezhnev in 1968, the ideas
Dubcek championed were considered dangerous.
   At the head of a column of Warsaw Pact troops, Soviet tanks
rolled into Prague's broad Wenceslas Square on Aug. 20, 1968, to
crush the liberal reforms. It was a dramatic and enduring message
to the world that the Soviet Union would not refrain from using
force if its imperial position was threatened.
   The Soviet invasion became a watershed in Eastern European
history and Dubcek came to personify all those who challenged
Communist tyranny.
   Like thousands of Czechoslovak intellectuals and reformist
politicians, Dubcek was the target of repression after the invasion.
   He was flown to Moscow and forced to sign an agreement
sanctioning the invasion and allowing 80,000 Soviet troops to
remain inside Czechoslovakia.
   By May 1970, Dubcek had been ousted from parliament, his last
public position, and stripped of his party membership.
   His name was removed from history books and his picture
airbrushed out of official photos, leaving an empty space where the
popular leader once appeared.
   He was sent with his wife and three sons to work as a forestry
manager in Bratislava, the capital of his native Slovakia, and was
kept under constant police surveillance.
   Dubcek, while not actively involved in dissident human rights
activities throughout the 1970s, was embraced by the opposition
during November's peaceful revolution.
   The dramatic photo of a triumphant Dubcek, 68, waving to
hundreds of thousands of pro-democracy supporters and admirers from
the balcony over Wenceslas Square on Nov. 24 made front pages
around the world.
</TEXT>

</DOC>