<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0216 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1142EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APArts:Frisch Adv27   12-22 0582</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP Arts: Frisch, Adv 27,0596</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv 27</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Wed PMs, Dec 27 and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Book on Swiss Army Hits Best-Seller Lists</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HANNS NEUERBOURG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ZURICH, Switzerland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It doesn't compare with his
``Stiller'' or other works that won worldwide attention. But at 78,
novelist-playwright Max Frisch has broken eight years of literary
silence and has returned to Swiss best-seller lists.
   The subject of his new book is Switzerland's militia army, which
has not fought a foreign war in five centuries. The army has
fascinated him since he boarded a train on Sept. 1, 1939 to join an
artillery unit based in the Alps. At that time he was convinced he
would help defend the neutral country against an invasion by the
Nazis. His concern focused on a German Jewish resident of Basel,
who was then his girlfriend.
   Two of his books, published in 1940 and 1974, deal with his
wartime experience, marking his conversion to increasingly radical
pacificism. The third was jotted down in barely two months last
spring.
   It was timed to add fuel to a nationwide debate on a recent
proposal that sought the abolition of the 625,000-man Swiss army.
   Frisch's new ``Switzerland Without an Army?'' features a
sparsely worded dialogue between a ``grandfather,'' easily
identifiable as the author himself, and his ``grandson,'' Jonas.
   Subtitled ``A Palaver,'' it is actually a collection of pros and
cons in the debate, though Frisch makes no secret of his opinion.
   ``We need the army, seriously,'' the grandfather at one point
tells a doubting Jonas, who is thinking of possibly emigrating to
the United States. The grandfather lists the well-worn whys _
``school of life, school of men, school of the nation'' _ before
adding what to him is the principal reason, ``the bodyguard of the
reign of the wealthy.''
   Once more, Frisch shows himself as a disillusioned critic of the
Swiss system.
   ``Their misery is the purchasing power without any great hope,''
the grandfather says of his compatriots. ``They spend their
vacations in the service of economic growth.''
   The army is not ``our army,'' Jonas is told, but an ``army that
is maneuvering on our territory as the army of the Swiss society of
finance and officers.''
   The book went into its fifth edition three months after
publication, and has been translated into four languages.
   A dramatized version, ``Jonas and His Veteran,'' premiered at
Zurich's prestigious Schauspielhaus theater Oct. 20, directed by
Benno Besson, a Swiss disciple of Bertolt Brecht. A French language
version went on stage one day later at Lausanne. The performances
drew rounds of applause, but reviewers were mixed.
   ``It is a convincing text,'' said the Zurich weekly
Sonntagszeitung, praising Frisch's ``subtle argumentation, (and)
his stylistic elegance.'' The reasons presented are of such
``cogent logic that the question ought to be on the mind of
everyone leaving the theater: How could one ever believe in the
institution of the army?''
   For the Berner Zeitung of Bern, the play showed that the idea of
a Switzerland without an army can be the subject of a ``spirited
discussion.''
   Another Bern newspaper, Der Bund, said the play ``lacked the
stylistic power, the poetic weight and dramaturgic logic of
`Triptych,''' the last work Frisch wrote exclusively for the stage
in 1978.
   Frisch's ``grandfather'' is sure the Swiss army is sure to stay.
``If the Swiss army is ever be disbanded, it will not be by a
referendum but by a war.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv PM Wed Dec.9 27</NOTE>

</DOC>