<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0259 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1026EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-WallStreet10am     12-18 0345</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Wall Street 10am,0363</SECOND>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The stock market was little changed today,
steadying after Friday's decline.
   The Dow Jones average of 30 industrials edged up 2.98 to
2,742.53 in the first half hour of trading.
   Losers outnumbered gainers by about 5 to 4 in nationwide trading
of New York Stock Exchange-listed issues, with 417 up, 510 down and
557 unchanged.
   Volume on the Big Board came to 20.95 million shares as of 10
a.m. on Wall Street.
   Brokers said traders remained uneasy about the outlook for
real-estate finance and regional bank stocks after the Bank of New
England on Friday announced projected increases in its loan-loss
reserve and non-performing assets.
   In the past couple of weeks, Wall Street has been devoting
increased concern to the soft real estate market in many parts of
the country and the problems real-estate debt might pose should
prices of properties lag for an extended period.
   Bank of New England shares led the active list, unchanged at 9
on the heels of a 3]-point drop Friday.
   Among other actively traded banking and mortgage issues, Bank of
Boston lost | to 16{ and Federal National Mortgage was down \ at
33{.
   Otherwise, analysts said hopes persisted that stocks could
overcome their recent hesitancy and gain ground in the next few
weeks, aided by the lifting of pressures from yearend tax selling.
   Marriott rose \ to 34~. The company announced a restructuring
plan that calls for its departure from the fast-food and family
restaurant business and the buyback of an additional 10 million of
its shares.
   The NYSE's composite index of all its listed common stocks rose
.12 to 193.57. At the American Stock Exchange, the market value
index was off .52 at 374.98.
   On Friday the Dow Jones industrial average dropped 14.08 to
2,739.55, reducing its gain for the week to 8.11 points.
   Declining issues outnumbered advances by nearly 3 to 2 on the
NYSE, with 616 up, 897 down and 481 unchanged.
   Big Board volume totaled 240.39 million shares, against 178.70
million in the previous session.
</TEXT>

</DOC>