<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0853EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-PoliceProbe     12-21 0290</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Police Probe,0299</SECOND>
<HEAD>Target of Missing Police Funds Probe Arrested on Fraud Charge</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAN DESMOND</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A former police official suspected in the
disappearance of money from a secret $1.4 million Police Department
fund was arrested on fraud charges today.
   Kenneth Weiner, a former civilian deputy chief who resigned in
1986 amid allegations of a pyramid scheme, was arrested as he
stepped off a flight from Los Angeles about 12:15 a.m., the FBI
said. He awaited a bail hearing today.
   The FBI charged Weiner with wire fraud in a 1986 precious metals
investment scheme in which Detroit investors lost thousands of
dollars. Officials refused to say how they learned of his travel
plans.
   Weiner had dropped from sight in recent weeks as the FBI and
city officials looked into the $1.4 million fund used for
undercover narcotics operations. Weiner had access to the fund from
1980 to 1986 while deputy chief.
   Police Chief William Hart has accused Weiner of diverting
hundreds of thousands of dollars from the fund and funneling money
into phony corporations in California. Records also show a phony
California corporation connected to Weiner paid $72,000 rent on a
Beverly Hills home occupied by Hart's daughter and her husband.
   Weiner has not been charged in the disappearance of the money.
   Hart has said he was unaware of problems with the fund,
including the rent payments for his daughter, until recently.
   Mayor Coleman Young reluctantly turned records of the fund over
to city auditors this week, but some documents needed to trace
money were missing.
   Young initially maintained that turning over the records could
jeopardize undercover operations.
   Last week, the FBI raided Weiner's apartment in Ann Arbor and
seized boxes of documents.
</TEXT>

</DOC>