<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1313EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-EastGermany 1stLd-Writethru a0556 12-27 0695</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0556,0710</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gorbachev Visit Triggered Honecker's Ouster, Former Aid Says</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 11th graf, ``Describing a ...'' with 1 graf to fix wording
of perestroika definition.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NESHA STARCEVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev's
attempts in October to convince Erich Honecker to abandon Stalinism
helped topple the East Germany leader, a former Honecker aide was
quoted as saying Wednesday.
   Gorbachev visited Honecker in East Berlin on Oct. 7-8 for
celebrations marking East Germany's 40th anniversary of statehood.
His visit came as a fledgling pro-democracy movement was growing in
strength.
   In an interview with the newspaper Junge Welt, former Parliament
speaker Horst Sindermann said that Gorbachev tried to convince the
Communist Party chief to pursue reform, and that Honecker resisted.
   ``The realization that Honecker must go was growing all the
time. The last push came from Gorbachev's visit for the 40th
anniversary,'' Sindermann was quoted as saying.
   Sindermann's interview was the first insight into the power
struggle that preceded Honecker's last days in office and the
pivotal role played by Gorbachev's visit.
   Honecker, a hard-liner who ruled East Germany for 18 years, was
ousted Oct. 18 and replaced as party leader by Egon Krenz. Growing
pressure from the pro-democracy movement and dissent in party ranks
forced Krenz and the entire Communist party leadership to step down
Dec. 3.
   A new Communist-led reformist coalition took its place and has
agreed with the pro-democracy opposition to hold free elections on
May 6, 1990.
   The 77-year-old Honecker and 11 of his former aides _ including
Sindermann _have been expelled from the party. Honecker has been
placed under house arrest and he and other leaders are accused of
profiting financially from their positions of power.
   Gorbachev's visit came during a mass exodus of East Germans to
the West. The official celebrations of East German statehood were
marked by anti-government demonstrations, which included clashes
between activists and security police.
   Sindermann, one of Honecker's closest aides in the ruling
Politburo, said differences between Honecker and other Politburo
members had been growing for some time.
   Describing a meeting between Gorbachev and the Politburo during
the Soviet leader's visit, Sindermann said Gorbachev urged the
leaders to pursue perestroika, the Soviet leader's system of social
and economic reforms.
   ``He told us we would have a much easier time with perestroika
because we have a much higher level of economic development,''
Sindermann said.
   ``But Honecker kept on pulling out a U.N. statistic that showed
that we had a higher productivity than the Soviet Union. And he
used it to argue that we must stay true to the old course,''
Sindermann was quoted as saying. ``He told this to Gorbachev, too.
That gave the impulse. We came out of the meeting and we were
united. Now is the end.
   ``The next day we went to the Politburo and (former premier
Willi) Stoph made the motion to remove Honecker. And that's how it
happened,'' Sindermann was quoted as saying.
   He said the Politburo voted unanimously to oust Honecker. ``He
was fighting against it.''
   Meanwhile, talks between the Communist-led coalition government
and the opposition resumed in controversy Wednesday when the
chairman of Democratic Awakening, one of the new political parties,
withdrew from the forum.
   Wolfgang Schnur denied newspaper allegations that he had abused
his position to obtain a large apartment. But Schnur said he was
withdrawing from the talks until the matter is clarified.
   The fourth session of the discussions on the future of the
country ended Wednesday with opposition calls for more say in the
day-to-day running of the country.
   Several opposition leaders called on Communist Premier Hans
Modrow to attend all the sessions and to consult more with the
participants over important government decisions.
   The talks involve 37 representatives from five established
political parties, including the Communists, and 16 opposition
groups.
   The forum is acting as a watchdog group on Modrow's government
until the elections.
   The official news agency ADN published results of a survey
carried out last week in Leipzig, the cradle of East Germany's
pro-democracy movement, that gave Modrow a 66 percent approval
rating, up from 58 percent a week earlier.
</TEXT>

</DOC>