<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1418EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     12-19 0595</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0619</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JACKSONVILLE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The elves looked like sailors, Santa's
sleigh looked like a string of trucks and Mrs. Claus resembled
Dorcas Drake, a woman putting together her 32nd annual Christmas
party for needy children.
   ``Hurry up and take you time,'' Mrs. Drake told Navy volunteers
Monday as they left for lunch after a morning of loading the first
of 100,000 toys into seven semi-trailer trucks.
   The toys will be given out Wednesday at Mrs. Drake's all-day
fest at the Jacksonville Coliseum. Each child attending the party
will receive a bagful of toys from a small army of volunteers.
   As usual, Mrs. Drake, a former justice of the peace, fretted
earlier that she wouldn't collect enough toys for the children. As
usual, her worrying has come to another happy end.
   ``We got enough. I'll just say a quiet `Thank the Lord,''' she
said.
   The warehouse at 1 Santa Claus Lane was a whirlwind of activity
as volunteers sorted the toys. Most of the toys were donated by
their original owners and those that can't be fixed are discarded.
   Last year, an estimated 50,000 children attended the party.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>MICHIGAN CITY, Ind. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Christmas dinner with all the
trimmings is no small feat under any circumstances, but John
Fegaras is expecting at least 1,800 guests.
   The open house at one of his restaurants is becoming a Christmas
tradition, now six years old, for Fegaras who owns four restaurants
in this lakefront community.
   Three hundred people attended the first dinner, but this year
Fegaras expects more than 1,800 people, many of whom have nowhere
else to go for Christmas.
   As in past years, volunteers ranging from Mayor Robert Behler to
city bus drivers will help cook and serve the food and transport
residents to the restaurant.
   Behler and his family spent a good part of their Christmas Day
helping at the restaurant last year, and he recalls a lot of happy
and surprised people.
   ``I had a hard time convincing a family that drove in from
Interstate 94 that there was no charge for dinner,'' Behler said.
   This year's menu again will feature turkey and ham with all the
trimmings. Limited delivery service will be offered to those living
within the city who are unable to leave their homes.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Those into the car culture have been busy
this Christmas season decking the grills with boughs of jolly.
   Car wreaths are the seasonal rage, dangling from hood ornaments
or tied to the grills of vehicles of every shape and size, from
Rolls-Royce, Mercedes-Benz and Range Rover to Chevrolet, Ford and
big-rig Peterbilt.
   ``I figure I spend so much time in my car I should decorate it
for Christmas. I think it's great because everybody is so intense
right now with he hassle of Christmas,'' said Timi Krissman
Freshman.
   She paid $18.50 for her car's plastic, snow-covered pine ring,
complete with fake miniature apples and a red velvet bow.
   ``The wreath just gives everybody a little lift,'' the
48-year-old real estate agent said.
   ``It's like (being in) your own personal sleigh,'' Jeep driver
Healy Cosay said of the wreath transformation.
   Jim Morris, who stuck a wreath on his Mercedes, said fellow
motorists look and grin, adding: ``People think I'm Santa. They
smile and honk and wave.''
   Geary's of Beverly Hills has sold more than 2,000 car wreaths
this season, said wreath designer Bruce Meyer.
   ``They're just a very friendly gesture for the season,'' he
said. ``I guess you could say we're driving motorists crazy with
Christmas cheer.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>