<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0158 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1822EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-EastGermany 1stLd-Writethru a0593 12-18 0924</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0593,0951</SECOND>
<HEAD>Opposition in Both Germanys Fight Reunification</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs to include Leipzig march; picks up 8th `The
broad'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAROL J. WILLIAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Both East German reformers and West Germany's
opposition Social Democrats said Monday the sovereignty of both
Germanys must be protected at Tuesday's summit, where the issue of
reunification will be raised.
   Representatives of 16 East German political parties,
pro-democracy groups and social organizations holding their second
session on the nation's future said Monday the summit was a sign of
both hope and a possible danger.
   Chancellor Helmut Kohl of West Germany and Hans Modrow, the
Communist premier of East Germany, are to meet in Dresden on
Tuesday and Wednesday.
   Kohl has made clear that his government seeks eventual
reunification of Germany, which has been divided since 1945.
   Modrow and many other East Germans, however, feel joining the
two states would threaten the stability of Europe and result in a
``sellout'' of East German land and industry.
   Monday night in Leipzig, about 200 pro-reunification activists
tried to disrupt a silent procession of about 200,000 people
bearing candles to commemorate victims of past intolerance. They
were hushed quickly.
   Delegates to the East German talks said the Kohl-Modrow meetings
``express the expectation that the visit will contribute to the
building of relations between East Germany and West Germany.''
   They alwo warned, however, that Kohl's visit ``may in no case
put the sovereignty or state identity of either German nation in
question.''
   The broad forum includes Communist Party chief Gregor Gysi, as
well as Interim President Manfred Gerlach of the Liberal Democrats
and pairs of representatives from the Neues Forum opposition group
and more than a dozen others.
   Many of the small parties and citizens' movements are
positioning themselves for the forthcoming election campaign for
parliamentary seats, as well as airing their views on how the
nation should be reformed after four decades of Communist
domination.
   East Germany's first free elections are set for May 6, a result
of the first forum held Dec. 7.
   Under pressure from mass pro-democracy protests, East Germany in
the past two months also has ousted its hard-line leaders, opened
the Berlin Wall and other borders, and ushered in reforms.
   In West Berlin, the opposition Social Democratic Party opened
its national convention Monday, focusing on how the two German
nations should be brought together in the new age of open borders.
   Party leader Hans-Jochen Vogel, who is likely to challenge Kohl
in federal elections for the West German leadership a year from
now, said East Germany must be allowed to find its own path.
   Vogel appealed for a ``border-transcending solidarity'' to
prevent further mass emigration from East Germany.
   More than 300,000 East Germans have fled to West Germany in
1989, many giving up hope that their state could rectify its
daunting economic problems or institute democracy in the place of
Stalinism.
   The westward tide has ebbed somewhat since the borders were
opened Nov. 9 and East Germans were allowed to come and go as they
pleased.
   But Germans on both sides of the border fear that if visible
improvement in the lives of East Germans is not achieved soon, the
exodus will increase.
   Gerlach, who was named interim president Dec. 6 after former
leader Egon Krenz was forced to resign, said the situation is
``already critical.''
   Gerlach said the basic supply of goods and services to the
public is threatened after Jan. 1 if labor and distribution are not
improved by then.
   An East German newspaper disclosed Monday that a new law on
trade unions to be presented to parliament will include a right to
strike.
   Neues Forum on Monday urged both German states to ``recognize
the current borders in Europe.'' The appeal aims to fix the postwar
territorial order in Europe, thereby preventing formal
reunification.
   ``The major problems facing our world _ securing peace,
improving the environment, social and economic issues _ are not
solvable by single states,'' the leading opposition group contended.
   Gerlach conceded that despite resistance by both unofficial
citizens' groups and the parties represented in Parliament,
reunification is forcing itself into negotiations.
   ``There may be no formal negotiations, but in reality it is
being discussed in both states,'' said Gerlach, who opposes any
union with West Germany that would result in loss of East German
sovereignty.
   The talks got off to a disorderly start, with hundreds of angry
demonstrators shouting outside the ground-floor conference room
where the party and citizen group representatives were assembled.
Speakers inside couldn't be heard above the noise of protesters
chanting through bullhorns that they wanted to be included at the
talks.
   ``Anyone who tries to push his participation in this way is not
acting in the interests of democracy,'' Gerlach said.
   The participants agreed to include nine other groups at the
talks as representatives or observers.
   Discussion of proposals for a new constitution and laws on the
media, political groups, campaign funding and other issues
connected with the reform movement will be carried on state radio
and TV, they decided.
   They agreed to hold regular meetings Mondays through the interim
period before elections. But the next regular session was set for
Dec. 27 in view of the Christmas holiday.
   They also decided to meet Friday to discuss economic problems
with Deputy Premier Christa Luft.
   Another new political party was founded Monday, adding to the
dozens already in existence. The new group named itself Nelken, or
``The Cloves,'' and said it would adhere to traditional Marxist
principles.
</TEXT>

</DOC>