<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0162 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1945EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-MailBombs     12-21 0642</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mail Bombs,0659</SECOND>
<HEAD>Threatening Letters Sent to Two Mail Bomb Targets</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BYRD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At least two of the four targets of mailed bombs
have been sent follow-up letters, apparently from the same person,
threatening further action, federal investigators said Thursday.
   Officials would not reveal where the letters were sent or their
contents.
   The four targets of the bombs were federal Judge Robert S.
Vance; his court, the 11th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals in
Atlanta; Savannah attorney Robert Robinson; and the Jacksonville,
Fla., NAACP.
   Vance was killed in his suburban Birminham, Ala., home Saturday
when a nail-studded bomb exploded; Robinson was killed in his
office by a bomb Monday. The packages sent to the court and the
NAACP office were defused safely.
   ``There have been follow-up letters sent since receipt of the
bomb parcels,'' said Leo Shatzel, a postal inspector in Atlanta.
``It appears they may have been sent by the individual who sent the
parcels.''
   Shatzel said the letters ``were threatening additional mailings
to other individuals.'' But asked if the letters specifically
threatened further bombings, he replied simply, ``No.''
   Shatzel and FBI officials said a number of letters have come to
their attention in the wake of the bombings, including the two sent
to targets.
   William Hinshaw, head of the FBI's Atlanta agency, said none of
the letters specifically claim responsibility for the bombings on
behalf of a person or group, or describe exactly the details of the
four bombing attempts.
   Hinshaw said the letters were not sent before the bombings,
which might corroborate a link between the letter-senders and the
bombings.
   Shatzel said investigators ``have to assume there may be a
relationship'' between this week's letters and letters sent in
August, to a Jackson, Miss., TV station and other parties,
threatening the 11th Circuit Court _ which, as Hinshaw noted
Thursday, does not handle Mississippi cases.
   The latest letters ``may be a hoax. They may be from other
persons,'' Shatzel said. But ``they may be from an individual who
did send a bomb.''
   All four packages have been linked to civil rights court cases:
Vance and other 11th Circuit judges have handled school
desegregation and other civil rights cases from Georgia, Alabama
and Florida; the Jacksonville NAACP recently won a school
desegregation case in the Atlanta court; and Robinson had
represented the Savannah NAACP in a school desegregation case.
   Hinshaw said that while no bombs have been discovered in the
past two days, investigators dare not assume the attacks are over.
A bomb threat was called in Thursday to a Birmingham, Ala.,
building housing two bankruptcy judges and the Internal Revenue
Service but no explosive was found.
   ``We're fortunate today we didn't turn up any more bombs _ knock
on wood,'' he said, speaking with reporters at a news conference
with postal authorities and Georgia law enforcement officials.
``But we can't say this person's stopped.''
   FBI spokesman Diader Rosario in Atlanta said agents have
interviewed everyone whose name appeared on the four parcels, but
``we do not consider them suspects or involved in any way, shape or
form.''
   FBI officials have said at least three of the bombs were mailed
in Georgia _ in Newnan, Atlanta and Macon _ and all four had
Georgia return addresses. The package to Robinson may have been
mailed in Macon as well, but officials said the postmark on that
bomb was damaged or blurred.
   A Macon attorney, Charles A. Mathis, said Wednesday the FBI had
questioned one of his associates about a 14-year-old racial
discrimination case against the Air Force as part of the bombing
investigation.
   Mathis declined to name the associate or detail what he was
asked. The Macon firm's clients won a $3.75 million settlement in
the case, which involved Robins Air Force Base in Warner Robins and
had been before the 11th Circuit.
</TEXT>

</DOC>