<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0268 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1209EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f PM-OntheMoney Adv21   12-20 0595</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-On the Money, Adv 21,0609</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv21</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release PMs Thurs Dec 21</HEAD>
<HEAD>Mutual Funds: Don't Rule Out the New</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHET CURRIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In trying to evaluate a mutual fund as a
prospective investment for the 1990s, anyone might naturally start
by asking, ``how has it done in the '80s?''
   Steeped as they may be in the old doctrine that past performance
is no guarantee of future results, experienced investors
nevertheless want to see what a fund's managers have demonstrated
they can accomplish.
   Ten-year periods, furthermore, provide a convenient reference
point for people who are pursuing long-term financial goals. Any
fund that can turn in good results over such a protracted span
presumably has something going for it beyond luck or a fleeting hot
streak.
   Conversely, experts on the subject say, a fund that couldn't
flourish in the lush financial climate of the 1980s ought to have
some explaining to do before you entrust your money to it for the
years ahead.
   But with all that, some advisers say, you can go astray by
putting too much reliance on long-term past performance in the
process of picking a fund.
   For one thing, notes Sheldon Jacobs, publisher of the advisory
letter The No-Load Fund Investor in Hastings-on-Hudson, N.Y., if
you insist on a 10-year record these days you are going to
eliminate a great many possibilities right off the bat.
   Among the 241 diversified stock funds he follows, Jacobs says,
more than half didn't start operating until 1980 or later, and
nearly a third have gone into the business since 1985. ``That's a
lot of potentially outstanding funds to ignore,'' he observes.
   In the mutual fund game, many analysts say, young up-and-comers
often enjoy a special edge on their older competition.
   While they are still small to medium-sized, they tend to be lean
operations that can enhance the results they achieve with a
relatively small number of well-timed investments.
Long-established, popular funds can become encumbered by their own
sheer size.
   In recognition of this problem, several of the industry's stars
closed their doors to new investors for lengthy intervals in the
'80s, striving to keep their growth at a manageable pace.
   Some big funds that have kept on scoring top marks, such as the
eminently successful Fidelity Magellan Fund, have been widely
publicized. But industry commentators often cite them as the
exception that proves the rule.
   On top of that, Jacobs suggests, the outstanding years in a
fund's past may have been the work of a manager or managers who
have since moved on to other endeavors. ``It's not uncommon for old
funds to have new managers,'' he says. ``The manager is the key,
not the fund.''
   In the universe of the funds he follows, only one in five has
been operating with the same people at the helm for 10 years or
more.
   For a final test of his argument, Jacobs checked actual
performance records of new vs. older funds for various periods in
more recent times through the third quarter of this year.
   On the list of the top 25 performers since the beginning of
1986, 56 percent were funds organized in 1980 or later. For the
period since the lows after the 1987 market crash, the newcomers'
share swelled to 80 percent. Over the most recent 12 months, it
stood at 60 percent.
   Jacobs's conclusion: Age discrimination is unwarranted when
shopping for a mutual fund. ``Young funds are no problem,'' he
says, ``as long as they are performing well.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv PMs Thurs Dec 21</NOTE>

</DOC>