<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0205 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 2332EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Hilton     12-27 0327</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Hilton,0338</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report That Bids Are Low Causes Hilton Stock Price To Fall</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEVERLY HILLS, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hilton Hotels Corp. stock plunged
Wednesday on a report that offers for the hotel-casino company are
in the $90 range instead of the $120 some analysts had believed
Hilton would fetch.
   Hilton, which was put up for sale last summer after the
settlement of a dispute over the estate of founder Conrad Hilton,
fell $6.87{ to close at $82.87{ a share on the New York Stock
Exchange.
   The Wall Street Journal reported that JMB Realty Corp., a
Chicago-based pension fund manager, had offered about $90 a share
for Hilton, which would bring the total offer to $4.3 billion.
Hilton general counsel William Lebo declined to comment on the
report.
   Another of the bidders for Hilton is Miller-Klutznick-Davis-Gray
Co., billionaire investor Marvin Davis' Denver-based real estate
vehicle. The Journal reported that Miller-Klutznick was bidding
about the market price for the stock, which was about $90 before
the Journal report Wednesday.
   Calls to Miller-Klutznick and JMB were not returned.
   Hilton stock was trading at $63 per share when Conrad Hilton's
son, Barron Hilton, settled the estate dispute in May.
   In August, Hilton stock soared to $112 a share on reports that
the company would consider at least two formal buyout bids. At that
time, some analysts were estimating that shareholders were likely
to get $120 per share if Hilton was sold and possibly as much as
$140.
   But the collapse of the junk bond market and fears of a
recession have made it much harder to complete takeovers recently,
and the stock price has gradually fallen as no deal was announced.
   Hilton had its best year ever in 1987, when profits rose 43
percent and earnings were $5.59 per share. Earnings fell to $2.72
per share last year and have remained relatively flat this year,
rising 2 percent in the July-September quarter to $28.1 million, or
57 cents a share.
</TEXT>

</DOC>