<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0543EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-US-ChristmasRdp     12-26 0678</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-Christmas Rdp,0706</SECOND>
<HEAD>Americans Share Holiday Cheer With Those in Need</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Americans took time out from family celebrations to bring
Christmas cheer to the unfortunate, sorting cards for GIs in
Panama, staffing soup kitchens and even giving up their own feasts
when thieves took food destined for the needy.
   In military towns such as Ft. Bragg, N.C., families prayed for
loved ones fighting in the U.S. invasion of Panama.
   Shirley Kinney and her two teen-age children celebrated almost
as usual _ but left unopened under the tree presents for Master
Sgt. Walter Kinney, an intelligence officer among the 4,000-person
contingent sent from Ft. Bragg.
   ``I just hope and pray he'll be safe over there,'' said Mrs.
Kinney, 40, who wore a symbolic yellow ribbon on her lapel next to
the Santa Claus pin.
   Wounded soldiers at Wilford Hall Medical Center in San Antonio
exchanged presents with relatives in special visiting rooms, said
Staff Sgt. Rey Adame, a hospital spokesman. Residents volunteered
to help sort gifts, cards and letters sent to the GIs injured in
Panama.
   For many Americans, it was a day for church services or quiet
personal celebration of the birth of Jesus. But many extended
gift-giving beyond their families, sharing with the less fortunate.
   In Atlanta, some homeless people dined on pizza instead of
turkey and ham after thieves stole 400 turkeys and thousands of
dollars worth of food and toys collected for a Christmas meal.
   Then, when word got out of the theft, Atlantans nearly
overwhelmed the Georgia World Congress Center with traditional
holiday fare, much of it apparently destined for their own tables,
said attorney Neal Boortz, one of the organizers.
   ``We told the people that we needed some more turkey, some more
ham, and people at home today are taking the turkey and the ham
they were going to eat and were putting it in boxes and bags and
bringing it to us,'' Boortz said. ``They were looking in their
cabinets for some canned goods and were making themselves some
spaghetti or something.''
   Organizers estimated that 20,000 people showed up.
   ``This is the helping spirit of Kwanzaa, Christmas and Hanukkah
all wrapped into one,'' said Dr. James Scott, a volunteer on the
food line. Kwanzaa is an African-American celebration.
   Chicago's Paul Hall Center, also hit by theft of thousands of
dollars worth of food intended for Christmas Eve dinner for 1,500
needy people, was back in business Christmas Day, bolstered by
donations from city residents.
   About 100 volunteers turned up at the Midnight Mission on Skid
Row in Los Angeles to help serve meals of turkey, yams and pumpkin
pie to the homeless.
   ``This gives me perspective,'' Clint Hodges, a 52-year-old
attorney, wearing a white cap and apron.
   President and Mrs. Bush spent the holiday with their five
children and 11 grandchildren at Camp David, in Maryland's
snow-covered Catoctin mountains, but weren't out of reach of the
day's events.
   Bush invited National Security Adviser Brent Scowcroft to brief
him on the situations in Panama and Romania.
   In Manhattan Beach, Calif., 19-year-old Ryan Flaherty made it
home for Christmas with a present from his doctors _ a transplanted
heart that saved his life.
   Flaherty, who suffered from a congenital heart defect, had the
transplant Dec. 14 at the University of California, Los Angeles,
Medical Center.
   His second-biggest present was a bass guitar, said his mother,
Karen.
   For the 10th year, Merrill Lynch &amp; Co. invited about 900 senior
citizens invited to its headquarters in New York to make free
long-distance telephone calls to loved ones.
   One family in Lake Bluff, Ill., celebrated an anniversary as
well as a holiday.
   The children of the advertising copywriter who created Rudolph
the Red-Nosed Reindeer 50 years ago for a Montgomery Ward's
promotion booklet said they are grateful year-round for the
residual payments from the mythical sleigh-puller.
   The writer's daughter, Elizabeth Decker of Lake Bluff, Ill.,
says that every Christmas season her late father, Robert May, used
to look out the window at a statue of the reindeer and say ``Thank
you, Rudolph.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>