<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0638EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Dollar-Gold     12-29 0300</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Dollar-Gold,0317</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar, Gold Higher</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dollar was higher in quiet European trading
late this morning. Gold prices also moved up.
   In the foreign exchange markets, the few remaining market
participants were covering short positions on the last business day
of 1989, dealers said. That meant they were buying dollars to
fulfill agreements to sell them.
   Traders said activity was reduced to a minimum as most players
already have closed their books for the year.
   ``The market is very restricted, but after it (the dollar)
touched bottom at 1.6650 (West German) marks, some banks started to
cover short positions,'' one Milan trader said.
   He said he didn't expect any major moves in the dollar for the
rest of the day, as most banks were closing early today ahead of a
three-day New Year's weekend.
   In Tokyo, the dollar rose 1.25 yen to a closing 143.40 yen.
Later, in London, it was quoted at 143.80 yen.
   Other dollar rates at midmorning compared with late Thursday:
   _1.6965 West German marks, up from 1.6905
   _1.5490 Swiss francs, up from 1.5385
   _5.8055 French francs, up from 5.7665
   _1.9170 Dutch guilders, up from 1.9000
   _1,273.50 Italian lire, up from 1,264.50
   _1.1585 Canadian dollars, up from 1.1563
   In London, the dollar gained against the British pound. It cost
$1.6043 to buy one pound, compared with $1.6137 late Thursday.
   Gold opened in London at a bid price of $400.25 a troy ounce, up
from $399.50 bid late Thursday. At midmorning, the city's five
major bullion dealers fixed a recommended price of $401.00.
   In Zurich, the bid price was $401.00, up from $400.00 bid late
Thursday.
   Gold in Hong Kong fell $1.72 to close at a bid $399.89.
   Silver rose in London to a bid price of $5.18 a troy ounce from
Thursday's $5.15.
</TEXT>

</DOC>