<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0344EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-WashingtonInBrief     12-20 0441</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Washington In Brief,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eighteen State Legislatures Targeted by Democrats</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Statehouse races in 18 states will be targeted
next year by Democrats who hope to control state legislatures when
congressional districts are redrawn for the 1990s.
   Democrats will try to raise $3 million to help candidates for
the legislatures in those states next year, Tim Dickson, who heads
the party's Project 500 program, said Tuesday.
   Democrats are particularly concerned with states likely to gain
or lose congressional districts as a result of population shifts
that will come to light in the 1990 census. They are also focusing
on states where the majority's grip in the state legislature is
tenuous.
   The targeted states are Arizona, California, Colorado,
Connecticut, Florida, Illinois, Indiana, Iowa, Michigan, New
Jersey, New York, Ohio, Oregon, Pennsylvania, Texas, Virginia,
Washington and Wisconsin.
   Democrats now control 36 state Houses and 32 state Senates,
while Republicans control 12 Houses and 17 Senates. They share
power in Indiana's House; Nebraska has a nonpartisan bicameral
legislature.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Sears, Government Settle Insulation Ads Complaint</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sears, Roebuck &amp; Co. has agreed to pay a
$100,000 civil penalty to settle a dispute with the government over
insulation ads, the Federal Trade Commission said.
   The FTC said Sears or its representatives had failed to include
details on the insulation's heat resistance when it promoted the
thickness and price of the product.
   The ads ran within the last five years.
   Chicago-based Sears has agreed to create an advertisement
designed to educate consumers about home insulation, especially the
importance of having heat-resistance information when making a
purchase, the FTC said Tuesday.
   ``The violations were technical in nature and did not result in
any consumer complaints,'' Sears spokesman Gordon Jones said.
``There was no misrepresentation or deception involved.''
   The settlement must be approved by a federal judge in
Washington. The FTC said the consent decree does not constitute
admission of a law violation. The penalty is paid to the
government, not consumers.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Government Upgrades Beretta Investigation</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The National Highway Traffic Safety
Administration says it's upgrading an investigation of a possible
steering deficiency in the 1988 Chevrolet Beretta.
   The agency also said Tuesday it was beginning probes of reported
explosions in the heating systems of Coachmen Industries
recreational vehicles and of cruise control failures in the Ford
Taurus and Mercury Sable.
   The agency said it was stepping up its Beretta probe from a
preliminary evaluation, which involves mostly paperwork, to an
engineering analysis, in which the possibly defective parts are
examined.
   Such investigations can lead to recalls or can be dismissed if
engineers decide there is no widespread safety problem.
</TEXT>

</DOC>