<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0245 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0506EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-SPE--Bride&amp;Groom:LookingGood     12-18 0457</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-SPE--Bride &amp; Groom: Looking Good,0464</SECOND>
<HEAD>SPECIAL EDITION</HEAD>
<HEAD>Bride &amp; Groom: Looking Good</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   You want to look terrific at your wedding, not just because it's
your day in the spotlight, but because the pictures made will be
among the most tangible mementos of the event.
   But just like every other detail of the celebration, getting
your hair, makeup and skin ready takes planning and care.
   ``Hair and makeup are the keys to a bride's beauty, and she
should devote as much care and attention to them as she does to the
selection of her dress,'' says Denise O'Donoghue, Bride's magazine
beauty editor.
   Along with Prell, the shampoo maker, she advises getting hair
into shape early. If you plan to color, highlight or permanent your
hair, do it well enough in advance to fine tune the result.
Preliminary shaping should be done about three or four months in
advance and a fresh cut done about three weeks before the wedding.
Freshly washed and conditioned hair will look fullest and best in
the photographs. Smooth wispy flyaway strands with hairspray, but
be sure to do so before stepping into your gown to avoid staining
or spotting on light-colored, delicate fabrics.
   Also plan your makeup, which may be different from your daily
wear. ``Remember, you will be wearing white from head to toe. Since
the only color will be on your face, your palette has to be just
right,'' says O'Donoghue.
   She recommends experimenting ahead of time, using a white sheet
to simulate the effect of the gown. This will help you discover
whether you'll look better in peach- or pink-tinted makeup. She
advises forgoing frosted or pearlized makeup items, since the
resulting iridescence reflects too much and will make your skin
photograph unnaturally.
   Choose a light foundation toned to your skin and soften blusher
and eyeshadow by blending the edges. Soft black or brown mascara
should be lightly applied, since the white of the gown will
intensify its impact. And, of course, the mascara should be
waterproof to avoid streaking from tears.
   Then, have a friend make test pictures to see how the makeup
choices do on film.
   Nails should be professionally manicured every three or four
weeks, with the last session the day before the wedding. Choose
pastel pink or peach shades consistent with your makeup.
   Part of the preparation is getting skin into shape, according to
L'Oreal Cosmetics, which recently introduced a top French skincare
collection called Plenitude. According to Linda Harris, vice
president of product development, the key to healthy skin is
cleansing and moisturizing. Bar soaps are too harsh and strip
natural oils, she says, so the job should be done with gels (for
oily skin) or creams (dry skin).
</TEXT>

</DOC>