<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0188 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0006EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AtkinsParole     12-21 0449</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Atkins Parole,0463</SECOND>
<HEAD>Manson Follower Susan Atkins Denied Parole</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FRONTERA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Susan Atkins, who fatally stabbed
pregnant actress Sharon Tate during the Charles Manson ``family''
killings 20 years ago, was denied parole for a ninth time Wednesday.
   In rejecting her bid for release, the state parole board noted
that Atkins was involved in three incidents resulting in the
premeditated murder of eight people ``for the bizarre motive of
starting a race war.''
   Atkins, 41, who is serving a life sentence on eight murder
convictions that included the 1969 Tate-LaBianca slayings, won't
get another parole hearing until December 1992, the three-member
board decided.
   Atkins, with other Manson followers, was convicted of murder and
conspiracy in 1971 for the murders of Miss Tate and four others at
the actress' home, and of for slayuing grocer Leno LaBianca and his
wife at their home the next night.
   Prosecutors argued during the Manson family trial that the
killings were part of Manson's plot to incite chaos, or ``Helter
Skelter,'' that would result in a black vs. white civil war.
   Manson, who expected ultimately to take control of the country
when the fighting ended, is serving a life prison sentence and has
repeatedly been denied parole.
   Miss Tate, who was 8{ months pregnant, was stabbed 16 times by
Atkins and Charles ``Tex'' Watson, who is serving a life sentence
in the California Men's Colony in San Luis Obispo.
   Presiding Commissioner Rudolph Castro called the crimes among
``the most heinous and callous ever committed in California, if not
in the nation.''
   The actress' mother, Doris Tate, addressed the board.
   ``Anyone has an alternative to do right. I don't understand why
anyone would murder an innocent pregnant woman,'' she said. ``The
thing that goes continually through my mind is the lack of
compassion Susan had for Sharon.
   ``When Sharon begged for her life, Susan said, `Shut up, bitch.
You're going to die.' And after they stabbed her 16 times they hung
her. I have nothing but contempt for this individual.''
   Prosecutor Stephen Kay, a Los Angeles County deputy district
attorney, told the board the release of Atkins would be ``one of
the most dangerous things this board can do.''
   Atkins said she realized she might spend the rest of her life
behind bars for acts she called ``unforgivable.''
   ``I take the blame,'' Atkins told the board. ``Not only am I
being punished, but I deserve to be punished for what I did.''
   Atkins' attorney, Deborah Fraser, said although her client's
crimes should not be excused, the board should put aside political
considerations and offer her a release date. She cited a 1989
psychiatrist's report that found Atkins ``less dangerous than the
average inmate.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>