<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0549EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     12-29 0641</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0662</SECOND>
<HEAD>Threats and Promises of More Snow</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The Lake Superior snowbelt, Montana and the mountains of the
desert Southwest braced for snow today as sleet and freezing rain
left an icy swath from South Dakota to northern West Virginia.
   A cold front in southern Wisconsin was expected to sink into
southern Iowa by Friday morning, continuing south into Missouri
later in the day. Temperatures in the region should cool gradually
cool as the weather becomes more unsettled.
   High pressure should move away from the area around the nation's
capital today, making way for the front now in the Upper Midwest.
Clouds and precipitation were expected to return to the region for
the weekend.
   A winter storm watch was posted through today in northern
Arizona's higher elevations. Up to 4 inches of snow was expected in
elevations above 6,000 feet.
   Wintry weather may return to New Mexico for the weekend, as a
developing storm system could bring new snow to the northern
mountains.
   Light snow or freezing drizzle was forecast today across South
Dakota, Minnesota and Wisconsin.
   A snow squall advisory was extended in Wisconsin along Lake
Superior, where up to 4 inches of snow fell Thursday. An additional
3 to 6 inches was expected today.
   Snow across north-central Montana Thursday left 3 inches at
Havre, 4 inches at Great Falls and more in the mountains.
   Snow mixed with sleet and freezing rain was forecast for
Illinois and northern Ohio today, and was expected later in western
Pennsylvania and northern West Virginia.
   Snow was falling today in northern Maine, central New Hampshire
and New York state, northwest Pennsylvania, Upper Michigan,
northern Lower Michigan and northern Wisconsin and Minnesota.
   Rain was scattered across Texas and southwest Louisiana.
   Over 8 inches of snow fell in Syracuse, N.Y., between midnight
and 3 p.m. EST Thursday, making this the city's snowiest December
on record with 57 inches. Syracuse's total snowfall this season is
73.2 inches, another record.
   Newark, N.J., is shivering through its coldest December on
record, according to the National Weather Service.
   The average temperature in Newark in December 1989 was 25.1
degrees. December 1945, which had an average temperature of 29
degrees, was the previous coldest December on record.
   Thursday's high temperature in the nation was 79 at McAllen, Tex.
   At 4 a.m. EST today, Sault Ste. Marie, Mich., reported a reading
of 3 below.
   Other reports at 3 a.m. EST today:
   _East: Albany, N.Y. 15 cloudy; Atlanta 38 fair; Boston 17 fair;
Buffalo 21; Charleston, S.C. 37 fair; Chattanooga 28 partly cloudy;
Cincinnati 28 partly cloudy; Cleveland 25 cloudy; Detroit 30
cloudy; Hatteras 28 fair; Jacksonville 38 foggy; Key West 62 fair;
Knoxville 28 fair; Macon 33 fair; Miami 55 fair; New York 28 fair;
Philadelphia 22 fair; Pittsburgh 23 cloudy; Portland, Maine 5 fair;
Richmond 28 fair; Tampa 50 fair; Washington, D.C. 28 partly cloudy.
   _Central: Birmingham 51 cloudy; Bismarck 10; Denver 33 cloudy;
Des Moines 34 fair; Fort Worth 59; Indianapolis 31 partly cloudy;
Kansas City 48 cloudy; Little Rock 48 rain; Louisville 30 foggy;
Memphis 54 cloudy; Nashville 36 partly cloudy; New Orleans 57
partly cloudy; North Platte 28 snow; Oklahoma City 54 windy; Omaha
34 cloudy; Rapid City 26 freezing drizzle; St. Louis 42 cloudy;
Minneapolis-St. Paul 23 windy; San Antonio 56 foggy.
   _West: Albuquerque 32 fair; Anchorage 21 cloudy; Boise 17 foggy;
Casper 27 snow; Fairbanks 6 snow; Great Falls 28 snow; Honolulu 70
partly cloudy; Las Vegas 48 cloudy; Los Angeles 54 fair; Medford 29
fair; Pendleton 27 foggy; Phoenix 57 partly cloudy; Portland, Ore.
36 foggy; Reno 36 cloudy; Salt Lake City 29 foggy; San Diego 52
fair; San Francisco 45 fair; Seattle 39 foggy; Spokane 27 cloudy.
   _International: Calgary 23 fair; Montreal -5 fair; Ottawa -5
fair; Regina 14 cloudy; Toronto 18 snow; Winnipeg -17 fair; Merida
64.
</TEXT>

</DOC>