<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0159 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1826EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-Bush-Text 3rdAdd a0650-a0657-a0666 12-18 0719</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Bush-Text, 3rd Add, a0650-a0657-a0666,630</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHN: not facts.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Q. Well, isn't that what life is all about?
   BUSH: Once they deal with a full deck, I expect people will
understand it. But there are some times in this job, you've got to
do something like that. And you just have to worry about it. You've
got to, you know, have the conviction that you're doing what you
think is correct. That's what the people elected me to do. This
gets way over any other issue, incidentally. And so I can't worry.
If you'd asked me 10 years ago so and so criticized you _ all the
people out there are criticizing you; doesn't this concern you? And
you'd have gotten an honest answer out of me, I'd probably have
said, yeah. But not any more. Because in this job, you don't do
that. You do what you think is correct. If you screw something up,
you say, hey, I was wrong. But if you're right, you don't need to
get instant credit for it. So you just try to do your best.
   Q: Can we move beyond China, and let me ask you about another
part of the world. There were some words of moderation out of Iran
after the death of Ayatollah Khomeini, but nothing concrete seems
to have happened since then. Are we missing anything?
   BUSH: I don't think we're missing anything, but I think your
predicate is correct there.
   Q: Well, but has there _ my predicate that there has been no
concrete action?
   BUSH: Yes.
   Q: There hasn't been?
   BUSH: I haven't seen anything that I can consider particularly
hopeful, but we'll continue to be alert for anything that the
Iranians decide to do.
   Q: So it's a year later for the hostages in Iran _
   BUSH: Exactly.
   Q: _ in Lebanon.
   BUSH: And that's an enormous frustration to me. I wrote notes to
the families the other day, and I just _ at the end of the year,
you count your own blessings, and you have to go through your mind
the concerns you feel about others. And this one I feel very
strongly about. And I feel a regret that I haven't been able to
facilitate the release of these hostages.
   On the other side of the world, I feel pleased that, thanks to
the good work of General Vessey, we've been able to further account
for Americans missing. And I'm talking, obviously, about Vietnam.
But in this one, I feel a personal frustration about it. It's on my
mind an awful lot. And if we want to talk about frustrations, I
feel that about the lack of peace and tranquility in Lebanon. I
feel _ we could go around the world, because I've tried to
highlight positive things here. But there's been some like this
one, Terry, that I feel frustrated about at year's end. The holding
of these kinds, the young people _
   Q: Mitterrand said that you couldn't have a Palestinian solution
without the Palestinian participation _
   BUSH: Yes, that's right.
   Q: _ in the transcript. Do you agree?
   BUSH: Well, I think what Jim Baker is trying to work out is to
have a voice of Palestinians at the talks. And it's a very
difficult process. But Mubarak tried to do the same thing.
   Q: Why is it difficult?
   BUSH: Simply because it is difficult, and the discussions
compelling Israel to negotiate with a particular Palestinian entity
is impossible. So find a way to get talks going. And that's what I
would like to see us do. And that's what we're trying hard to do.
   Q: Can you have any kind of real or meaningful peace settlement
in that region without the PLO participating, which is the entity
you no doubt were referring to?
   BUSH: You crawl before you walk. And we're not _ there's no
intention on our part to compel Israel or anybody else to deal with
any specific entity. We are trying to be a catalyst for peace in
the area. And it's plagued administrations in the past, it's gone
back over hundreds of years _ differences that exist on these
questions. So find some common ground and try to move the process
forward, and then cross each bridge as you come to it.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>