<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0238EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-HaitianChildren Bjt   12-19 0696</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Haitian Children, Bjt,0714</SECOND>
<HEAD>Missionary Couple Arrives with Foster Family of 28 Haitian Kids</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NA5</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BETH HARRIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>INDIANAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Don and Kathy Blackburn began taking in sick
and abandoned children while serving as missionaries in Haiti, and
came to love them so much they've brought all 28 home to adopt.
   ``It turned into a family and snowballed,'' Blackburn said as
the couple arrived to a rousing welcome Monday night at
Indianapolis International Airport. The Blackburns and their
children _ ages 3 to 14 _ headed for a church camp where they'll
stay in a dormitory until they find a home.
   The arrival of the Christian Evangelical missionaries and the
children culminated two years of efforts by Christian groups in
this country to bring the family to the Blackburns' home state.
   The Blackburns fled Haiti for the neighboring Dominican Republic
in 1987 during the turbulence that followed the 1986 ouster of
dictator Jean Claude Duvalier. This month, they won special holiday
parole status from the Immigration and Naturalization Service to
bring the children to the United States.
   ``This is one of the most fantastic things that ever happened,''
a tearful Mrs. Blackburn said at the airport, where she and her
husband were greeted by friends and relatives who hadn't seen them
since they left for Haiti 13 years ago.
   Dressed in sweaters and brightly colored sneakers, the children
lugged handmade cloth bags containing a change of clothing. Their
only other possessions were two dogs and two cats that also made
the trip.
   The children _ who glimpsed snow for the first time during a
stop in Chicago _ chased each other through the terminal, ate candy
and examined the equipment of television news crews.
   ``We thought we could sneak through without any notice,'' Mrs.
Blackburn, 42, said. ``We didn't think anybody would care if we had
28 kids. We take it for granted.''
   The group left by bus for the campground in the town of Letts,
30 miles southeast of Indianapolis, where they will live in a
dormitory with nine bedrooms and eight bathrooms. Mrs. Blackburn's
sister, Marianne Lortz, will help care for the brood.
   The children were granted humanitarian parole by INS
Commissioner Gene McNary in Miami because they were ineligible for
entry under any other category. Under immigration law, the
commissioner may allow an otherwise inadmissible alien to enter the
country temporarily for humanitarian reasons, or when such entry is
considered in the national interest.
   After granting parole, the INS worked with the State Department
to speed paperwork so the family could be home together by
Christmas, McNary said.
   The Blackburns, with their two sons, started a ministry in the
small mountain village of Maissade in 1976. After they had lived
there about 18 months, they began caring for sick or abandoned
children who were brought to their home.
   All but two of the children came to the Blackburns as babies,
including the youngest, who was just 6 hours old. All speak English.
   The couple brought the children to this country seeking a more
stable environment, and because they believe it will be easier to
adopt them here. Adoption efforts were blocked in Haiti and the
Dominican Republic because the children's biological parents are
dead, unknown or untraceable.
   The Blackburns, whose own children are in their 20s and living
on their own, are supported in the venture by churches and
organizations that have sponsored them for 14 years.
   ``We feel like the Lord was guiding and working to bring us
here,'' said Mrs. Blackburn.
   Eventually the family will find somewhere other than the church
camp to live or build a home large enough to accommodate the family.
   ``We'll home-school them for now,'' said Blackburn, 45.
``Everything is so new to them.''
   Asked how she and her husband managed to keep track of 28
children, Mrs. Blackburn said: ``Jesus Christ. There is no other
secret. Jesus has always taken care of us.''
   Planning, however, is important in managing such a large group.
   ``You just organize a little bit more. You don't go off and
leave them for two or three hours,'' she said. ``Nobody babysits
for crowds like that.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>