<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0137EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-TaxMailout Bjt   12-26 0691</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Tax Mailout, Bjt,660</SECOND>
<HEAD>Federal Tax Forms in the Mail Today</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN CRUTSINGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Economics Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Taxpayers receive their annual holiday
greetings from Uncle Sam starting today, as the Internal Revenue
Service mails out more than 107 million tax forms and instruction
packages.
   The forms, which have been waiting at post offices across the
nation for weeks, should be in most taxpayers' hands before Jan. 1.
   The IRS always times the mailing, which costs $26 million for
postage and printing, to come right after the crush of Christmas
mail but soon enough to give taxpayers as much time as possible to
complete their returns before the filing deadline, which falls this
year on April 16.
   For taxpayers still reeling from the sweeping changes wrought by
the 1986 Tax Reform Act, the IRS has reassuring words: the new
forms look very much like last year's forms.
   But to the chagrin of IRS officials, one of the few changes
should not have been made, and it could confuse millions of elderly
Americans.
   The IRS is trying to get the word out to taxpayers eligible for
Medicare that they should ignore the lines on the tax form covering
the supplemental Medicare premium. Congress did away with the
premium along with the catastrophic health program it was designed
to fund.
   But Congress did not vote to repeal the controversial program
until late November, long after the IRS forms had gone to the
printers.
   The IRS hopes to keep confusion to a minimum through a publicity
campaign to get word to the 12 million elderly taxpayers who could
be affected. In addition, IRS officials note that the form
taxpayers would need to compute their Medicare premium tax
liability, Form 8808, does not exist.
   ``We believe that taxpayers will not want to pay taxes that they
don't have to pay,'' said IRS official Arthur Altman.
   But Altman said that if taxpayers still include an amount on the
Medicare premium line, the IRS will refund the money.
   This year's returns are accompanied by a special pitch from new
IRS Commissioner Fred T. Goldberg Jr., who urges taxpayers to
consider filing their returns electronically to cut down on the
time it takes to process their refund checks.
   The IRS is providing a special toll-free telephone number,
1-800-424-1040, for people to call for a list of tax preparers in
their area who can file returns electronically.
   In 1988, two-thirds of all taxpayers qualified for a refund,
with the average refund totaling $875.
   All of the changes in this year's forms are explained in the
accompanying instruction booklets, which also include a list of
other IRS publications that offer further help in preparing taxes.
To request additional tax forms and the tax information
publications, taxpayers can call the IRS at 1-800-424-3676.
   Among the changes featured in this year's forms:
   _The personal exemption, the amount you may exempt from taxation
for yourself, your spouse and each dependent, increases to $2,000
per person, up from $1,950 last year.
   _The standard deduction, claimed by people who do not itemize,
rises to $3,100 for a single person, up from $3,000 last year. The
exemption for a couple increases to $5,200, up from $5,000 last
year.
   _Tax rates remain the same at 15 percent, 28 percent and 33
percent with about four of every five taxpayers paying only the
lowest rate. While the rates stay the same, the tax brackets have
been widened so that more income will be taxed at lower rates in
order to compensate for inflation.
   _For the first time, the IRS will include two name lines,
instead of one, in recognition that more married couples have
different last names.
   The IRS is looking for 111.2 million individual tax returns to
be filed this year with 65 percent expected to opt for the
comprehensive Form 1040, designed for taxpayers who itemize or who
have incomes above $50,000 annually.
   Two shorter forms, Form 1040A and the brief nine-line Form
1040EZ, are available for taxpayers who do not itemize and can meet
other qualifications.
   The IRS form each taxpayer receives is based on the form that
taxpayer used last year.
</TEXT>

</DOC>