<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0168 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 2032EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WKD--Lange Adv05-07   12-26 0836</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--Lange, Adv 05-07,0853</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv 05-07</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Weekend Editions, Jan 5-7, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WEEKEND ENTERTAINMENT AND ARTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Star Watch: Jessica Lange Meets Costa-Gavras</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: ``The Music Box'' opened in New York and Los Angeles on Dec.
22.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BOB THOMAS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The combination of a volatile star and a
director of international renown might seem potentially explosive.
But Jessica Lange and Constantin Costa-Gavras claim the expected
fireworks didn't happen in their collaboration on ``Music Box.''
   After her disastrous debut in ``King Kong,'' Lange began taking
charge of her career. She has reportedly clashed with directors
over interpretations of her film roles and has developed and
produced her own projects, such as ``Country.''
   Costa-Gavras is known as the uncompromising, Greek-born director
of such politically-themed films as ``Z,'' ``Missing'' and
``Betrayed.'' ``Music Box'' deals with guilt from the Holocaust.
   ``I had input as far as the development of the character,'' says
the actress, who plays a Chicago lawyer defending her father
against charges he murdered Jews in his native Hungary.
   ``I wasn't involved at a production level. I had such respect
and confidence in Costa that I didn't feel the need to get in there
and make my opinions known. I agreed with what he was doing, which
made the filmmaking much easier for me. It's difficult when you're
not in agreement with how the film is being made. You have to
expend a lot of energy arguing or opposing the way things are
happening.
   ``In this case, everybody was in sync. But it's rare.''
   ``She is strong, and extremely nice,'' Costa-Gavras said about
his star. ``It was a big pleasure, because the relationship
(developed) little by little, getting very close as we spoke about
the character in a very intimate way. I think it was quite a unique
experience to me. She looks a little distant, but she's absolutely
not.''
   In one of her infrequent interviews, Lange was asked if she
encountered any resentment because a star insisted on making her
opinions known.
   She laughed and replied, ``I suppose there was some of that. I'm
certainly not the first person to do that, and I won't be the last.
Sometimes you're just an actress for hire: You go in and do your
part and that's it. At other times your commitment is deeper than
that.''
   Lange approached her ``Music Box'' role with her usual
thoroughness, hanging out in courtrooms and reading endless legal
briefs. ``Ultimately, you can observe behavior,'' she said, ``but
when you get down to playing it, it all has to come from the
character.
   ``But I learned a lot about legal proceedings. It's a very
tricky business. ... One thing I learned about law is that it's not
synonymous with truth. They do not exist side-by-side, which is too
bad, because originally I think that's what it was meant to be. Now
so much of it is rhetoric, tricks and manipulation.''
   The 40-year-old Lange reigns as one of the five most-in-demand
film actresses, a position no one would have predicted 10 years
ago. After repeating the Fay Wray role in ``King Kong,'' she didn't
work for two years. Finally, Bob Fosse gave her a small part as an
angel in ``All That Jazz.'' Although the remake of ``The Postman
Always Rings Twice'' with Jack Nicholson was a failure, Lange was
impressive as a dramatic actress.
   That promise was fulfilled in ``Tootsie,'' ``Frances,'' ``Sweet
Dreams'' and ``Country,'' all resulting in Academy nominations. She
won the 1982 Oscar as supporting actress for ``Tootsie.''
   Her acting dreams began as a child in rural Minnesota, where she
fell in love with ``Gone With the Wind'' and played Melanie's death
scene with every sickness.
   ``From the time I was 9, I was obsessed with `Gone With the
Wind,''' she confessed. ``It was an obsession that lasted until I
saw the French film, `Children of Paradise.' Then my obsession
switched. These two films got me through childhood and adolescence,
all the way up into my 20s.''
   Lange is intensely private, but she has provided the gossip
writers with plenty of copy. Her liaison with dancer Mikhail
Baryshnikov produced a daughter, Alexandra, 7. She and
playwright-actor Sam Shepard are parents of Hannah Jane, born in
1986, and Samuel Walker Shepard, born in 1987. She and Shepard, who
are not married, make their home in rural Virginia.
   ``The farm is great, but every once in a while you want the
bright lights, big city,'' she remarked. ``The trick is to find an
equilibrium.''
   ``Music Box'' was partly filmed in Hungary before the recent
political upheavals.
   ``You could feel there was something in the air when we were
there in the spring,'' the actress said. ``There was definitely a
change beginning to happen; you could tell from the spirit of the
people. I had never been to an Eastern bloc country before, so it
was real interesting to me. I was real relieved to get home,
though.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Weekend Editions, Jan. 5-7</NOTE>

</DOC>