<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0109EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-BiologicalWeapons Bjt   12-26 0641</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Biological Weapons, Bjt,630</SECOND>
<HEAD>Anti-Biological Weapons Legislation Making Progress</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DONNA CASSATA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Twenty years after President Nixon ordered the
destruction of the U.S. stockpile of biological weapons, the
federal government is on the verge of making development and
possession of the weapons illegal.
   Although Nixon's directive met with little resistance and the
United States joined the Soviet Union and 109 other countries in
signing a 1972 pact to prohibit production and possession of the
weapons, efforts to incorporate the treaty's provisions into U.S.
law have failed _ until this year.
   Scientists, defense analysts and lawmakers credit the Bush
administration, the changing atmosphere for arms control agreements
and the work of a freshman senator from Wisconsin who has little
foreign policy background.
   ``If I had to pick any of the 100 senators, it would not be him,
even the top 80,'' John Isaacs of the liberal Council for a Livable
World said in a recent interview. ``He was the new kid on the
block.''
   The kid is Democratic Sen. Herbert Kohl, who with the help of a
longtime opponent of biological and chemical weapons, Sen. David
Pryor, D-Ark., convinced the Justice Department and the full Senate
to support the Biological Weapons Anti-Terrorism Act of 1989.
   In the waning hours of the congressional session on Nov. 21, the
Senate approved the legislatio by voice vote. House passage and
presidential approval appear likely early next year.
   ``By approving the legislation, the Senate has signaled the
world that the United States is serious about controlling these
abominable creations,'' Kohl said on the Senate floor.
   By definition, biological weapons are a form of bacteria, virus,
fungus or naturally occurring toxin. A biological weapon could be
unleashed on an unsuspecting public by using it in a liquid to
contaminate water or in an aerosol that is dropped by bomb.
   In 1925, the Geneva Protocol banned the first use in war of
biological and chemical weapons, but did not address the
development, production, possession or transfer of the weapons.
   Forty-four years later, Nixon ordered the Defense Department to
destroy its arsenal of biological weapons. The United States then
spearheaded the fight for an international ban on production and
possession of the weapons. On April 10, 1972, in Washington, Moscow
and London, 111 countries signed the Biological Weapons Convention.
   The Senate ratified the treaty two years later.
   According to the pact, each nation must take ``any necessary
measures'' to prohibit biological weapons at home. Legislation was
introduced in Congress over the years to include the prohibition in
U.S. law, but the measures never got far.
   Among the problems during the 1980s, according to the
legislation's House sponsor, Rep. Robert Kastenmeier, D-Wis., was
the view of the Reagan administration.
   ``This administration is somewhat different,'' Kastenmeier said
in an interview. ``During eight years of the Reagan administration,
candidly speaking, they were not really for this legislation. ...
They felt we didn't need this.''
   But with the Bush administration's support for the bill and the
``tenor of the times'' for arms control legislation, said Kohl, the
biological weapons bill won easy Senate approval after just a
handful of hearings.
   ``It was the right time, the right place, the right bill,'' Kohl
said.
   The measure's purpose is twofold. It implements the 1972
Biological Weapons Convention and seeks to protect the United
States against the threat of biological terrorism.
   ``The legislation would prohibit the possession or development
of germ warfare devices and authorize the punishment of those who
attempt to help foreign nations acquire such weapons,'' the bill
says.
   Kohl believes final congressional approval and Bush's signature
would strengthen the United States' hand in demanding that all
countries comply with the 1972 treaty.
   The administration is concerned about countries with the
capability to produce biological weapons, including Iran, Iraq,
Syria and Israel. The official list remains classified.
</TEXT>

</DOC>