<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1048EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Soviet-Romania 4thLd-Writethru a0501 12-23 0682</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Soviet-Romania, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0501,0700</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviets Offer Help, Urge Warsaw Pact to Support Romanian Revolt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 11 grafs to UPDATE with Soviets urging Warsaw Pact
allies to aid uprising, supply planes blockaded in Bucharest; Picks up
13th graf, `Gorbachev indicated ...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAREY GOLDBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Soviet Union today sent medical supplies to
Romania and appealed to its Warsaw Pact allies to help support the
uprising against Nicolae Ceausescu, but it appeared to rule out
military intervention.
   The Soviet news agency Tass said wounded Romanians likely will
be flown to the Soviet Union for treatment, and it warned that the
fighting in Bucharest had endangered the lives of Soviets living in
the Romanian capital.
   ``The first planes with medicines and urgent supplies have
already arrived in Bucharest,'' President Mikhail S. Gorbachev
said. ``But they still are being held up in the Bucharest airport,
which is blockaded.''
   Tass said Gorbachev told the Soviet Parliament that the Soviet
government ``had decided to appeal to the governments of the Warsaw
Pact states with the aim of coordinated efforts in providing
support to the people of Romania.''
   The Soviet Red Cross, Ministry of Health and other organizations
were working with similar organizations in France and Eastern
Europe to provide medicine and specialists, he said.
   Gorbachev said ``a number of other measures'' were being worked
out with Warsaw Pact allies, and that a special working group was
monitoring events in Romania. He provided no other details.
   Premier Nikolai I. Ryzhkov dismissed talk of sending Soviet
troops to Romania to aid the provisional Romanian government that,
backed by the army, declared itself in control after Ceausescu fled
Bucharest on Friday.
   ``We have to support them from the point of view of medical help
and maybe some other kinds of help, but to bring in forces, I think
that's impermissible,'' Ryzhkov said.
   ``We mustn't repeat mistakes,'' the head of the Soviet
government told reporters. ``Not long ago, we re-evaluated the
Warsaw Pact invasion of Czechoslovakia in 1968. That
reconsideration was made on Dec. 4, and should we repeat something
like that a few days later?''
   Romanian TV, in the hands of the rebels, said earlier today that
the Soviet Embassy had pledged to send personnel and equipment to
aid the uprising.
   The announcement followed an appeal broadcast by the television
from an unidentified army general who urged Moscow to step in
because ``terrorist units'' loyal to Ceausescu had sent
reinforcements to the capital.
   Gorbachev indicated his country was just as confused as the rest
of the world about the whereabouts of Ceausescu, who had ruled the
allied country of 23 million people for nearly a quarter century.
   Tass said the fighting had put Soviet trade officials and their
families living in Bucharest in ``serious danger.
   ``The Soviet Union cannot remain indifferent to the fate of
Soviet citizens and demands that those who have unleashed the above
actions, endangering the life of the Soviet people, should
immediately stop them,'' Tass said.
   On Friday, the Soviet Parliament passed a resolution offering
``decisive support for the just cause of the people of Romania.''
   Hundreds of people were killed in clashes in Bucharest between
the army and police forces that included Ceausescu's personal
anti-terrorist squad.
   Soviet media have aggressively covered the uprising in Romania,
providing readers and listeners with startling details of the
battle for power.
   Correspondents of the official Tass news agency have provided
vivid eyewitness accounts of the battle between army units
supporting the uprising and guard units loyal to Ceausescu.
   Official television on Friday night showed film of hundreds of
thousands of Romanians packed into the squares of downtown
Bucharest.
   Gorbachev has given his blessing to the political reforms
sweeping Eastern Europe, where one after another old-style
Communist regimes have fallen this year to the forces of democracy.
   While Ceausescu's Romania remained a part of the Soviet bloc,
relations between Gorbachev and Ceausescu were notably cool.
   They last met early in December in Moscow, when Tass described
their meeting in terms that left little doubt about their sharp
disagreements.
</TEXT>

</DOC>