<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0170 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0209EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-FrozenCrops Bjt   12-27 0699</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Frozen Crops, Bjt,0718</SECOND>
<HEAD>Temperatures Plunge; Futures Prices Jump, but Consumers May be Spared</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also on general news wires.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY5</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By IKE FLORES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ORLANDO, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Orange juice prices leaped on the futures
market after a weekend freeze overwhelmed Florida and Texas citrus
groves, but experts said consumers may escape big price increases
because of a bumper crop in Brazil.
   However, Big Chill '89 likely will drive up vegetable prices in
the Northeast because the cold wiped out thousands of acres of
carrots, cauliflower, broccoli and other crops in Florida,
agriculture officials said.
   Experts assessing the damage Tuesday said it was too early for
definite predictions about prices. U.S. Agriculture Department
economist Ralph Parlett in Washington said price increases were
likely, but he hadn't changed his earlier forecast of a 3 percent
to 5 percent overall rise in food prices in 1990.
   In Florida, where the citrus industry is worth an estimated $3.5
billion a year, the Christmas cold wave struck with about 80
percent of the citrus crop still on the trees, and there was heavy
icing of oranges and grapefruit. In Texas, an estimated 65 percent
of the crop _ or $55 million worth wholesale _ was still on the
trees, according to growers and farm officials.
   Fruit frozen on the trees can still be used for juice, as long
as it's picked and processed before the weather warms too much, and
crews raced through groves salvaging what they could.
   A large juice reserve in Florida, booming citrus production in
Brazil and swift processing of iced oranges should stabilize juice
prices somewhat, said Dan Gunter, executive director of the Florida
Department of Citrus.
   ``Because of that, there might be a more moderate impact than we
might expect for a freeze year,'' Gunter said.
   Ever-jumpy commodities traders ran up the price of frozen orange
juice futures _ in effect a contract to buy a set amount of juice
on a specified date.
   The contract for January delivery of frozen concentrated orange
juice jumped 16.1 cents to $1.531 a pound Tuesday on the New York
Cotton Exchange, an 11.8 percent gain. The contracts for March and
May delivery rose their permitted daily limits of 5 cents a pound.
   The freeze didn't affect California and Arizona citrus, which
generally is sold fresh rather than frozen for juice. Florida
farmers use about 90 percent of their oranges for juice and about
50 percent of the grapefruit.
   Consumers' biggest worry from the freeze appeared to be
vegetable prices. Florida farmers reported widespread damage to
vegetable crops from one end of the peninsula to the other, said
state Agriculture Commissioner Doyle Conner.
   Much of the winter vegetable crop was destined for the
northeastern United States, and central and south Florida growers
said thousands of acres of carrots, radishes, cauliflower and
broccoli were destroyed and that little would be salvageable.
   Near-total losses were reported in winter vegetables in large
areas of the state, and heavy losses of beans, squash, corn,
tomatoes and watermelons. Strawberries, ornamental plants and other
crops also were hard hit.
   ``With shortages, naturally prices will go up,'' Conner said.
   Vegetable losses are ``a more temporary kind of thing'' because
those crops can be replanted, noted the USDA's Parlett. Continued
production from California and Mexico could also cushion the blow,
he said.
   ``There's no doubt that some of the supplies will be cut short,
and we'll probably see higher prices'' at produce counters, Parlett
said.
   Florida growers were optimistic that trees throughout the
700,000-acre citrus belt had been spared extensive damage.
Nevertheless, losses to the industry _ just starting to recover
from disastrous freezes in 1983 and 1985 _ were expected to be
heavy.
   ``Growers are concerned about their trees,'' said Bobby McKown,
executive vice president of Lakeland-based Florida Citrus Mutual, a
trade association of more than 12,000 growers. ``But right now, we
don't see the black leaves that we had in 1983.''
   Freeze fallout could include unemployment for thousands of
migrant farm workers. Once the rush to save the oranges subsides
and the crops disappear, those workers workers could lose their
jobs, said Charles Esposito, program manager for the Beth-El
Mission in Plant City.
</TEXT>

</DOC>