<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1405EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Lebanon     12-23 0379</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon,0392</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fighting Rages Between Shiite Militias in South Lebanon</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By AHMED MANTASH</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SIDON, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rival Shiite Moslem militias backed by
Syria and Iran fought daylong tank and artillery battles in south
Lebanon on Saturday, killing at least 17 people and wounding 45,
police said.
   Most of the casualties reported were from the Syrian-backed Amal
movement, but police could not give a specific breakdown. Amal's
rival, the pro-Iranian fundamentalist Hezbollah, or Party of God,
appeared to have the upper hand in the fighting that began north of
Sidon, 25 miles south of Beirut.
   At least six Shiite civilians, two of them children, were taken
to Beirut's American University Hospital with serious wounds, radio
stations reported.
   Iran's Islamic Republic News Agency, monitored in Cyprus, said
First Deputy Foreign Minister Ali Mohammad Besharati left for
Damascus ``to settle the differences'' between Hezbollah and Amal.
   Meetings between representatives of both sides were held in
Sidon ``in a bid to stop the fighting and prevent more bloodshed,''
official sources said.
   It was the latest eruption in a 2-year-old power struggle
between Amal and Hezbollah for control of Lebanon's 1.2 million
Shiites, the country's largest sect.
   Police were unsure what sparked the fighting, which torpedoed a
truce mediated by Syria and Iran that halted fighting between the
Shiite rivals last month.
   By police count, 588 people have been killed and 1,624 wounded
in Amal-Hezbollah battles that have raged intermittently since May
1987.
   An Amal official conceded that his movement's fighters had been
driven out of four villages in a surprise pre-dawn Hezbollah
assault.
   The official, who identified himself by his nom de guerre of Abu
Hassan Qobeissi, told The Associated Press at Amal's forward
command post outside the village of Kfar Hatta that the Hezbollah
forces attacked from their hill stronghold around the villages of
Jbaa and Ein Bouswar.
   The attackers overran four Amal-held villages, Kfar Hatta,
Mjaidel, Kfar Kila and Kfar Milki, he said.
   ``We were taken by surprise, but we're now counterattacking to
try to recapture the four villages,'' Qobeissi said as smoke from
burning buildings billowed into the sky.
   Police reported heavy fighting, with both sides using tanks,
mortars and rocket-propelled grenades around the contested villages.
   Hundreds of villagers fled toward Sidon, the provincial capital
of south Lebanon.
</TEXT>

</DOC>