<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0648EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Lithuania     12-27 0663</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lithuania,0684</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gorbachev to Visit Lithuania to Try to Mend Party Rift</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAREY GOLDBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Mikhail S. Gorbachev will travel to
Lithuania in coming days to try to persuade the republic's defiant
Communist Party to reaffirm its allegiance to the national party,
officials say.
   When it declared itself independent on Dec. 20 the Lithuanian
Communist Party created the first major crack in the political
monopoly forged by Vladimir Lenin after the 1917 Bolshevik
Revolution.
   Gorbachev attacked the Lithuanian party leadership at a meeting
of the Soviet party's Central Committee held Monday and Tuesday to
consider the Lithuanian break with Moscow.
   He accused the Lithuanians of allowing themselves to become
``hostages to separatists.''
   But, in a report published Tuesday in the party newspaper
Pravda, he also urged ``maximum restraint'' to allow emotions to
cool. The 250-member Central Committee unanimously approved the
report.
   The committee decided to send Gorbachev and other top party
officials to Lithuania ``to explain our position and at the same
time to get a better sense of the situation there,'' Vadim A.
Medvedev, a Politburo member and the party's chief ideologist, told
a news conference afterward.
   Medvedev said some officials at the Central Committee meeting
proposed ousting the Lithuanians from the national party or
annulling the Lithuanian decision, but others pushed more moderate
measures.
   All were united, however, in their disapproval of the Lithuanian
move, Mededev said. ``Most agreed that this was a blow to
perestroika,'' he said, referring to Gorbachev's program to
restructure the Soviet economy and to a certain extent the
political system.
   Medvedev said the trip to Lithuania would take place ``in not
very many days'' and that the Central Committee will make a firm
decision on the dispute in January.
   The Lithuanian Communist leader, Algirdas Brazauskas, said in an
interview that the party officials' visit would be ``good and
helpful,'' an editor at Lithuanian Radio said.
   Despite the postponement of a full decision, the Central
Committee's stand as stated Tuesday refused to recognize the
Lithuanian party's self-proclaimed independent status.
   ``No part of the Soviet Communist Party has the right to decide
the question about its independent existence with its own program
and rules, not taking into account the position of the Soviet
Communist Party as a whole,'' Gorbachev said in the report approved
by the plenum. ``And this means that the Communist Party of
Lithuania was and remains a part of the united Soviet Communist
Party.''
   Gorbachev tried for several months to head off the Lithuanian
split.
   At the Congress of People's Deputies meeting in Moscow on
Saturday he lashed out at separatists: ``Today, to realize the
right to self-determination through secession means to blow up the
union, set the people against each other and sow conflict and blood
and death.''
   Gorbachev told the Central Committee meeting the Soviet
government should consider the legal status of movements that are
``carrying out separatist activities and whipping up nationalist
terror.''
   He did not identify any such organizations, but in the context
of the debate he likely was referring to Lithuania's people's
front, known as Sajudis, and other groups pushing for independence
from the Soviet Union.
   Medvedev said the fight against separatist groups would not
involve the use of force by Moscow. ``We're against application of
the military or other such methods,'' he said.
   Thousands of people gathered Tuesday in Vilnius, Lithuania's
capital, for a rally in support of the regional party's move, said
Lithuanian Radio editor Eduardas Potasinskas.
   Brazauskas, in an interview with the Interfax news service
published Tuesday, defended his party's decision as a ``step toward
renewal of the party.''
   ``The idea is to make sure that the public perceives it as a new
political force with a new message,'' he said.
   Medvedev, however, said the Lithuanian party would end up
``crushed by separatist and nationalist forces'' without Moscow's
support.
   Despite Gorbachev's bluster, Brazauskas and other Lithuanian
party leaders maintain that the Soviet leader has shown
understanding of their move.
</TEXT>

</DOC>