<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0192 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0105EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-EC-US    12-19 0416</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-EC-US, </SECOND>
<HEAD>EC Angry Over U.S. Action in Hormone Ban</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SALLY JACOBSEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRUSSELS, Belgium (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The European Community, angered by U.S.
efforts to circumvent a ban on hormone-treated beef, has asked the
United States to slash retaliatory duties imposed in the trade
dispute, an official said.
   The official said Monday that the 12-nation trading bloc wants
the tariffs reduced because of legislation requiring U.S.
commissaries in Europe to buy their beef from American _ not
European _ producers. Commissaries are stores for U.S. military and
other personnel.
   The official, who demanded anonymity, said the purchases plus
transportation costs were expected to amount to about $55 million,
which he described as an ``extra penalty'' applied by the Americans
in the dispute.
   The United States slapped duties of about $100 million on a
variety of European products to retaliate for the ban on imports of
meat from cattle treated with growth hormones. Some of the duties
have been eased slightly since the prohibition went into effect
last Jan. 1.
   Frans Andriessen, the EC's top trading official, and Ray
MacSharry, its agriculture chief, requested the tariffs be lifted
in a Dec. 1 letter to U.S. Agriculture Secretary Clayton Yeutter
and U.S. Trade Representative Carla Hills. No response has yet been
received.
   Foreign ministers of the 12 community nations discussed the
dispute at a meeting Monday and asked to be kept informed of the
American reaction, the official said.
   The banned meat affects only a tiny part of the $166 billion in
1988 trade between the trading partners.
   The community official also said the trading bloc was
considering accepting the conclusions but not critical findings of
an international trade panel that ruled in favor of the United
States in a dispute over soybean subsidies.
   The official said the community would be willing to do so
provided that the United States refrained from imposing unilateral
trade measures violating international trade rules.
   Last week, a panel of the 97-nation General Agreement on Tariffs
and Trade, found that community subsidies to processors and
producers of soybeans hurt trade. Details of the soybean decision
have not been released.
   U.S. soybean producers complained in December 1987 that
community subsidies had cut into American exports to Europe. The
American Soybean Association argued that the payments encouraged
farmers to grow oilseeds, which then reduced the demand for
American imports.
   The community argued the erosion of the European market was
largely due to increases in cheaper imports from Brazil and
Argentina.
</TEXT>

</DOC>