<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0177 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0749EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-NordstromLawsuit     12-28 0440</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Nordstrom Lawsuit,0457</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nordstrom Headed For Court In Personal-Injury Suit</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Detectives at the downtown Nordstrom store who
chased a shoplifter now find their employer embroiled in a personal
injury lawsuit.
   Two men who were run over by the shoplifter claim the detectives
were negligent and have filed suit against the national retail
chain.
   Nordstrom lawyers say the store sympathizes with Alexander
Passovoy, 63, of Lake Oswego, Ore., and William Pack, 64, of
Britain, but feels their legal recourse should be aimed at the
shoplifter.
   Pack suffered cracked ribs and Passovoy said he will need
surgery to repair torn leg ligaments caused by the Sept. 20, 1985
incident. Passovoy said he fell to the bottom of some stairs with
his leg twisted under him.
   ``There was a sort of heavy pounding behind us and we were
knocked sideways,'' said Pack.
   Pack and Passovoy, longtime friends, contend the store and its
lawyers have been anything but sensitive about the case, scheduled
for trial June 25.
   Three years ago, King County Superior Court Judge Susan Agid
threw out their suit. She said Nordstrom could not be held
accountable for the actions of a fleeing criminal.
   Last year, the state Court of Appeals reinstated the suit,
saying a jury should decide whether the detectives' failure to
shout a warning for customers in the store amounted to negligence.
   To concede responsibility would be to restrict store workers
from doing their jobs, Nordstrom lawyers have said.
   ``Nordstrom is not taking care of a prison,'' Michael Reilly,
Nordstrom lawyer, told The Seattle Times. ``They're not prison
wardens. They're merchants. Merchants shouldn't be required to walk
around with balls and chains,'' he added.
   He said the Nordstrom store detectives exercised reasonable care
in the crowded store and ``did exactly what they should have done.''
   The shoplifter who was the object of the chase was eventually
grabbed near the downtown Monorail by a couple of Bon Marche
department store security officers who heard shouts from Nordstrom
store detective David Siler.
   Siler gave chase after he saw two men stuffing suits into bags.
One shoplifter was tackled in the store. The other was pursued
through the store and onto the sidewalks of downtown Seattle.
   ``I'm not looking for the moon here,'' said Passovoy. ``We just
want some equity. But they claim they weren't responsible.''
   Nordstrom and the National Retail Merchants Association were
upset by the appeals court ruling. The association represents 4,500
retailers nationally.
   ``No appellate court in the United States has ever gone so far
as to impose a duty to warn customers of the possible dangers
caused by a fleeing shoplifter,'' the association said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>