<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1233EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Security     12-18 0432</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Security,0445</SECOND>
<HEAD>Big Airport Delays Reported at Heathrow</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The pre-Christmas travel rush caused long lines
and delays at Heathrow Airport, where security has been tightened
in the last six weeks, an airport spokeswoman said Monday.
   The operators of Heathrow and six other British airports
appealed to passengers to leave Christmas gifts unwrapped, minimize
electronic items they pack and limit themselves to one piece of
hand baggage to speed up security checks.
   ``There was a lot of congestion this morning due to heavy
Christmas traffic,'' the Heathrow spokeswoman said, speaking
anonymously in keeping with British custom.
   More than 250,000 passengers passed through Heathrow, the
world's busiest international airport, during the weekend, she said.
   Tighter security measures ordered by the Transport Department in
October did not contribute to the delays of up to two hours for
check-ins, she said.
   However, some travel agents were issuing airplane tickets
stamped with the warning to check in early ``in view of the
increased security precautions at British airports.''
   Those measures include the hiring of 350 additional security
staff and stricter checks on airport staff with access to aircraft.
   The Heathrow spokeswoman said the tightened security was not
related to Friday's warning by the U.S. State Department about a
possible terrorist attack on a U.S. target in Western Europe or
West Africa.
   Heathrow is spending $8 million to upgrade security following
the bombing of Pan Am Flight 103 one year ago Thursday. The flight
originated in Frankfurt, but baggage and passengers were
transferred to a larger plane during a stop at Heathrow. All 259
people on board died, and 11 people on the ground in Lockerbie,
Scotland, were killed by the falling wreckage.
   ``Staff are aware that the spotlight will be on us this week and
everyone is anxious that there should be no slip-ups,'' said one
Pan Am worker at Heathrow, requesting anonymity.
   Transport Secretary Cecil Parkinson described airport security
as ``satisfactory for the perceived level of threat.'' He said
airports are more secure now than a year ago, particularly for U.S.
aircraft, ``which are regarded as a higher risk than ours.''
   Heathrow's managing director, Alan Proctor, said: ``Particular
attention will be given to the examination of electronic goods
including radios, computers, cameras and battery powered equipment
and this will take longer.''
   The bomb that brought down Flight 103 was made of plastic
explosives concealed in a radio-cassette player.
   ``To avoid queues and congestion at security checkpoints, I urge
all departing passengers to help us to help them by traveling with
a minimum of electronic items and hand baggage this Christmas,''
Proctor said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>