<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0415EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Japan-Markets     12-19 0448</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Japan-Markets,0462</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar Edges Down, Stocks Lose</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Tokyo Stock Exchange's key index ended seven
days of gains and the dollar edged down against the Japanese yen
today, as markets were stirred by rumors of an impending discount
rate increase.
   The dollar ended trading at 143.80 yen, down 0.42 yen from
Monday's 144.22-yen close. It opened at 143.55 yen and ranged
between 143.15 and 143.97 yen.
   ``Trading was hectic because of the rumor,'' said Minori
Takeuchi, a trader with Chemical Bank in Tokyo.
   In spot active trading in which an estimated $10.8 billion
traded hands, Japanese investors sold the dollar and the West
German mark to buy the yen during morning trading. In the afternoon
they bought the currencies back after Finance Minister Ryutaro
Hashimoto denied the reports of an interest rate increase.
   Hashimoto said the current Japanese economic situation did not
require another discount rate hike because of stable prices, but
that exchange rate levels required watching.
   The Bank of Japan has raised its discount rate twice this year
to the current 3.75 percent.
   Following Hashimoto's remarks, Bank of Japan official Tatsuya
Tamura said in a statement that government interest rate policy was
``a blank slate.''
   The Yomiuri Shimbun and the Asahi Shimbun, Japan's two largest
newspapers, reported today that the Bank of Japan would hike its
official discount rate by 0.5 percentage points to 4.25 percent by
this weekend.
   Ms. Takeuchi said the government's denial made the market
players shift their attention from domestic to U.S. monetary
policy, ``because the market now expects the hike will be postponed
at least until after February, when (Japanese) national elections
are expected.''
   The official discount rate is the rate the central bank charges
on its loans to commercial banks, which often influences other
interest rates. Higher interest rates make a country's currency
more attractive to currency investors, but discourages stock
investors.
   On the Tokyo Stock Exchange, the 225-issue Nikkei Stock Average
lost 147.08 points, or 0.38 percent, closing at 38,489.10. It had
gained 315.14 points to a record-high close of 38,586.18 on Monday.
   Dealers attributed the loss to the discount rate rumors.
   ``Until the bank actually raises the rate, the market will move
nervously every time somebody spreads the rumor in the market,''
said Kazuyuki Suzuki, a Daiwa Securities dealer.
   ``Since the market already has begun reacting to the rumors, the
impact will be minimal if and when the central bank actually
announces a hike,'' said Masahiro Umemori, an analyst with Nomura
Securities.
   ``We consider today's decline small, considering the negative
impact of the rumor,'' he said.
   Volume on the market's first section was an estimated 900
million shares, up from Monday's 850 million shares.
</TEXT>

</DOC>