<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0824EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Buchwald-Paramount     12-20 0399</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Buchwald-Paramount,0410</SECOND>
<HEAD>Buchwald Says His Movie Idea `Stolen, Raped' by Studio</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LINDA DEUTSCH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Art Buchwald amused court spectators with his
wry humor but said there was nothing funny about what he called
Paramount Pictures' theft of his idea for the film ``Coming to
America.''
   ``It's very hard for a humorist to be taken seriously in
something like this,'' the Pulitzer Prize-winning columnist
testified Tuesday in his $5 million lawsuit against Paramount. ``I
feel this is a very serious matter. I feel my property has been
stolen, raped, whatever you want to call it.''
   Paramount contends there are no similarities between Buchwald's
idea and the hit movie starring Eddie Murphy. The trial was to
continue today.
   Asked by Paramount attorney Robert Draper if the studio's
chairman, Martin Davis, is a good friend of Buchwald, the humorist
said, ``He used to be.''
   Buchwald said Davis did not seem to know about the
breach-of-contract suit until the two encountered each other at a
party last year.
   ``The next thing I know a bottle of Dom Perignon arrives at my
desk with a copy of a recording called `Sue Me,''' Buchwald
recalled. ``I sent him back a note that said, `Anyone who sends a
bottle of Dom Perignon is guilty.'''
   Buchwald said Paramount optioned his story, ``It's a Crude,
Crude World'' in 1982, then changed its title to ``King for a Day''
and spent nearly $500,000 trying to develop it as a movie for
Murphy.
   Paramount abruptly dropped its option in 1985 and Buchwald and
his co-plaintiff, producer Alain Bernheim, took the idea to Warner
Bros., Buchwald told Superior Court Judge Harvey Schneider on
Tuesday, his second day of testimony in the non-jury trial.
   But Buchwald said that Warner Bros. dropped the idea in 1987
when word spread that Paramount was producing a similar story.
   Draper said he has decided against calling Murphy as a witness
in the case because of the ``circus atmosphere'' that accompanied
the appearance Monday of late-night talk show host Arsenio Hall.
   Hall testified that he and Murphy conceived the idea for
``Coming to America,'' in which Hall also starred. Murphy testified
likewise in a deposition.
   Buchwald's 2{-page script idea and ``Coming to America'' were
about an African prince who comes to the United States, lives in
the ghetto, falls in love and takes a bride back to his country.
</TEXT>

</DOC>