<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 1222EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania-Deaths     12-31 0472</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Deaths,0487</SECOND>
<HEAD>As Shooting Dies Down, Revolution Death Toll Still Unknown</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two weeks after the revolution broke
out, there still is no official word on how many people died in
street fighting throughout Romania. Estimates range from hundreds
to several tens of thousands.
   As the first sketchy witness accounts began to trickle out of
the western city of Timisoara where the uprising began, the death
toll was first estimated at hundreds, then thousands.
   Then the revolution spread to other areas in Transylvania and
finally to the capital, Bucharest. As fighting escalated in the
streets with security forces loyal to Nicolae Ceausescu battling
the army and young revolutionaries, the estimates of dead rose. At
one point a report set the number at up to 70,000.
   But only days later, French health officials were told about 700
had died.
   Initial reports from witnesses and citizens in Timisoara, where
security forces opened fire on unarmed demonstrators Dec. 17, set
the death toll in the hundreds, then appeared to concur in
estimates of between 2,000 and 4,500.
   At one point, there were estimates that 12,000 people were
killed in Timisoara, more than 7,000 of them reportedly executed by
the security forces after being detained.
   But Western journalists returning from Timisoara and other
cities in the region where heavy fighting had been reported said
they doubted those figures, and thought the total likely would turn
out to be much lower.
   On Dec. 22, the day Ceausescu was toppled and tried to escape
the capital by helicopter from the roof of his palace, U.S.
diplomats said they saw 13 killed in Bucharest.
   But East European news agencies reporting out of Bucharest
before Western reporters were able to enter the country said
hundreds had died.
   The following day, Dr. Marian Palaschivescu said he alone had
counted 54 bodies, and an Austrian pilot said he counted 30 bodies
at the airport after fierce fighting on Dec. 24.
   Ninety bodies were counted that day at only one of many morgues
in the city.
   The East German news agency ADN reported that the National
Salvation Committee seeking to run the country estimated that 5,000
were killed in only two days of fighting.
   On Christmas day, Hungarian radio cited ``authoritative
sources'' as saying some 70,000 had died and 300,000 were injured.
   But Victor Ciobanu, the health minister under Ceausescu now
supporting the provisional government, said that day that 500 had
died in Bucharest over the previous four days of fighting.
   The day after Christmas, Romanians in Bucharest began preparing
to bury their dead, and 200 freshly dug graves were counted in one
cemetery.
   French health officials were told this week that 746 people had
died in the revolution, but Western diplomats estimated from
witness accounts and their own assessments that some 10,000 people
had died.
</TEXT>

</DOC>