<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0218 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1703EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Dollar-Gold 1stLd-Writethru   12-29 0486</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dollar-Gold, 1st Ld-Writethru,0499</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar, Gold Rise</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: SUBS 7-9 grafs to ADD rates at beginning of year; uppicks 9th
graf pvs: Other late ...</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dollar closed higher on world currency
markets Friday in light dealings ahead of the New Year's holiday.
   Gold prices rose in European and domestic trading after falling
in the Far East. On the Commodity Exchange in New York, gold
bullion for current delivery settled at $402.50 a troy ounce, up
$3.90 from Thursday. Republic National Bank in New York quoted a
late bid for gold at $402.50 an ounce, up $3.50.
   Dealers said the currency market lacked direction on the last
trading day of 1989, and many trading operations closed early.
   ``There was end-of-the-year position squaring,'' said Ron
Holzer, chief dealer at Harris Trust and Savings Bank in Chicago.
But by midday, activity was ``virtually at a standstill,'' he said.
   Traders predicted the dollar will begin 1990 on a weak note,
continuing the trend that reflects the strength of the West German
mark.
   ``There's no reason for the trend of a strong mark to change
yet, although we still expect a correction,'' said a corporate
adviser for a U.S. bank in London.
   In Tokyo, the dollar rose to a closing 143.40 Japanese yen, from
142.15 yen at Thursday's close. Later in London, it rose to 143.80
yen. In New York, the dollar ended the year at 143.85 yen, up from
143.55 on Thursday. The dollar ended 1988 at 122.00 yen.
   In London, the British pound fell to $1.6115, from $1.6137 late
Thursday. In New York, one British pound cost $1.6105, more
expensive than Thursday's $1.6045. The pound began the year at
$1.8850.
   The dollar closed in New York at 1.6950 West German marks, up
from 1.6875 on Thursday and up from 1.5815 at the beginning of the
year.
   Other late dollar rates in New York, compared with late Thursday
included: 1.5420 Swiss francs, up from 1.5390; 5.7805 French
francs, up from 5.7675; 1,267.00 Italian lire, up from 1,264.13,
and 1.1588 Canadian dollars, up from 1.1568.
   Other late dollar rates in Europe, compared with late Thursday
included: 1.6923 West German marks, up from 1.6905; 1.5430 Swiss
francs, up from 1.5385; 5.7860 French francs, up from 5.7665;
1.9100 Dutch guilders, up from 1.9000; 1,270.00 Italian lire, up
from 1,264.50, and 1.1587 Canadian dollars, up from 1.1563.
   Gold rose in London to a late bid price of $401.00 a troy ounce,
from $399.50 bid late Thursday. In Zurich, the metal rose to a
closing bid of $401.00, from $400.00 bid late Thursday. Earlier in
Hong Kong, gold fell $1.72 to close at a bid $399.89.
   Silver prices rose. On New York's Comex, silver bullion for
current delivery closed at $5.208 a troy ounce, up from $5.150 on
Thursday. In London the metal rose to a late bid price of $5.18 a
troy ounce, from $5.15 bid late Thursday.
</TEXT>

</DOC>