<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0199 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2118EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-ArabLeague     12-20 0441</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Arab League,0454</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two-day Arab, EC Meeting Opens Thursday</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL GOLDSMITH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A two-day conference of foreign ministers of the
European Community and the Arab League gets underway Thursday
despite misgivings discreetly expressed by the United States.
   The initiative for the unprecedented meeting came from French
President Francois Mitterrand, current chairman of the 12-nation
European Community, to give a new impetus to the EC's exchanges
with the Arab world.
   But the United States has taken a critical view of the idea,
conference sources reported, because it would exaggerate the
importance of the EC, which is preparing to create a single
European market among the 12 by 1992.
   Furthermore, the Americans dislike the idea of Libya, Syria and
the Palestine Liberation Organization _ with which the United
States has no trade relations _ participating fully and dealing on
equal basis with the members of the European Community, said the
sources, who asked to remain anonymous.
   They said Britain and some Arab countries close to the United
States _notably Saudi Arabia _ dragged their feet on taking part in
the meeting because of the American misgivings.
   But all 12 members of the Community and the 22 members of the
Arab League finally decided to participate for fear of being
isolated within their groups.
   In Washington, the State Department had no immediate comment on
the conference, said spokesman Adam Shubb.
   Libya was seen as the most reluctant Arab participant because of
France's military intervention on behalf of the government of Chad
against Libyan-backed rebels, as well as the French decision to
renew the ban on shipment of French-made arms to Libya.
   The government of Col. Moammar Gadhafi decided to participate
``only at the urgent request of its Arab brothers,'' Libya's
official JANA news agency said.
   The first steps to creating an ``Arab-European dialogue'' were
taken in 1973 when the oil crisis had brought the Arab states to
the high point of their power. The earlier attempt collapsed
largely because of political problems, including accusations of
terrorism against Libya and Syria.
   For the current conference, the French government has reoriented
the agenda more toward economic matters.
   France is concentrating on a selected list of specific to avoid
getting bogged down in political subjects, such as the PLO's
decision to challenge the export of citrus fruit from the
Israeli-occupied territories to Europe.
   The agenda includes such items as agreements on trade in
petrochemicals, the exchange of consulting engineers, an
Arab-European financial convention, European aid to the North
African railroad network and preparatory work for the proposed
fixed link _ by tunnel or bridge _ across the Strait of Gibraltar.
</TEXT>

</DOC>