<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0278 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1941EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-MobilDismissal     12-22 0343</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mobil Dismissal,0357</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge Unseals Mobil Documents in Wrongful Firing Case</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DANIEL J. WAKIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEWARK, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal judge Friday unsealed confidential
corporate documents in a lawsuit against Mobil Oil Corp. but
withheld the order when lawyers for the oil giant said they would
appeal.
   The company is fighting to prevent the disclosure of the
documents _ reports on environmental conditions at its chemical
division plants _ because it says they are self-critical
evaluations.
   Disclosing such reports would have a chilling effect on a
company's efforts to be candid about its operations, Mobil argued.
   But U.S. District Judge Harold A. Ackerman, ruling in favor of
The Associated Press and a former Mobil employee suing over his
firing, said the public's right to know was paramount.
   ``Public access to civil judicial proceedings is of vast
importance,'' Ackerman said. Such access ensures justice and
contributes to the public's understanding of government and the
legal system, he said.
   Ackerman dismissed the company's argument that its candor would
be chilled if the public were able to see self-criticism. He also
noted that Mobil didn't object to disclosure of the documents until
Ackerman ruled Dec. 11 that the case should be heard by a jury.
   Mobil said it would appeal Ackerman's order to the 3rd U.S.
Circuit Court of Appeals in Philadelphia.
   The judge also said he was baffled by Mobil attorney Richard
Reibstein's efforts to keep the documents from coming to light and
to keep the news media from covering the case.
   Ackerman on Friday admitted the AP into the courtroom over
Mobil's objections.
   Valcar Bowman Jr. claims he was fired as Mobil Chemical Co.'s
environmental affairs manager for refusing to go along with changes
ordered by company lawyers in the reports.
   He claims revisions were imposed to minimize pollution problems.
   Mobil says the changes were innocuous and that it was committed
to environmentally sound practices. Mobil says that Bowman, 47, of
Riverdale, Ga., was let go in an economic cutback.
   Bowman had worked at the division's Princeton, N.J. office.
</TEXT>

</DOC>