<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0156EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Schools-Television     12-19 0617</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Schools-Television,610</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ted Turner Gets Educational Organization Support</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By W. DALE NELSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   National educational organizations are lining
up behind broadcaster Ted Turner in a campaign to put his
commercial-free news into high school classrooms instead of
commercially sponsored Channel One.
   Associations representing administrators, principals, teachers,
parents and school board members appeared at a news conference
Monday with Turner to promote use of CNN Newsroom, the daily
15-minute program produced by Turner Broadcasting System of Atlanta.
   Spokesmen for several groups coupled their endorsement with
charges that Channel One, a daily 12-minute program produced by
Whittle Communications of Knoxville, Tenn., amounts to commercial
exploitation of students.
   Jeremiah Floyd, associate executive director of the National
School Boards Association, although reaffirming his group's
previous support for the Turner show, did not criticize Channel One.
   ``It is a local proposition and if that's the only game in town
and the local people decide they want to go with that game, then
that's their prerogative,'' Floyd said.
   Channel One also was criticized for offering to install
television sets, video recorders and satellite dishes at
participating schools.
   ``Exploitation of a captive audience in the classroom, using the
classroom and the curriculum as a marketplace for products rather
than a marketplace for ideas, and selling or trading students in a
classroom for a satellite dish or a television monitor are
outrageous breaches of ethical practice,'' said Gary Marx,
associate executive director of the American Association of School
Administrators.
   A spokesman for Whittle Communications, David Gerard,
interviewed by telephone at his office in Nashville, Tenn.,
defended the use of commercial sponsors.
   ``We are not introducing advertising to schools,'' Gerard said,
arguing that newspapers and magazines with advertising have long
been used as teaching tools.
   He said the company will have sold about $200 million worth of
advertising on Channel One by the end of the year. Whittle tested
its program in six schools for seven weeks last spring and plans to
begin national broadcasting in March.
   Scott Thompson, executive director of the National Association
of Secondary School Principals, said the organization has written
to all of the companies that advertise on Channel One explaining
his group's objections.
   ``I am delighted that a number of these companies, for their own
reasons, have decided not to continue sponsoring Channel One,''
Thompson said.
   He said no company had written back to say that it planned to
continue its sponsorship, although he understood that the M&amp;M Mars
candy company, one of the sponsors during the spring test, intended
to do so.
   Contacted at the company's headquarters in Hackensack, N.J.,
Hans Fiuczynski, director of external relations for M&amp;M Mars, said
the company received such a letter from the association during the
spring test of Channel One.
   He said M&amp;M Mars replied that it was aware that the program was
controversial but understood that it had been approved by local
school boards in the test communities. As to whether the candy
company would be a sponsor of the national news program, Fiuczynski
said it was against the company's policy to disclose future
marketing plans.
   Turner, president of Turner Broadcasting, said CNN Newsroom had
an enrollment of 1,000 schools when it was launched in August and
now has 5,000. He said he expects to reach 10,000 by the start of
the next school year in September.
   Whittle Communications said in November that it had 1,050
schools lined up. The company has said it hopes to expand this to
8,000 schools by the end of 1990.
   With Turner at the news conference were Thompson, Marx, Floyd
and Keith Geiger, president of the National Education Association,
and Tari Marshall, director of public relations for the National
Parent-Teacher Association.
</TEXT>

</DOC>