<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0150 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1917EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Reax     12-21 0816</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Reax,0845</SECOND>
<HEAD>Condemnation of Romanian Repression Grows</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 6 grafs to add Britain to list asking for Security
Council meeting, add quote; picks up 5th `Demonstrations against'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROLAND PRINZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   European governments issued new
condemnations Thursday of the bloody repression in Romania and
President Francois Mitterrand of France said the Stalinist regime's
``days are numbered.''
   China said the events in Romania were an internal affair. In
Beijing, the China-Romania Friendship Association opened a
laudatory photographic exhibit called ``Romania in Socialist
Construction.''
   West Germany, Austria, Britain and Hungary requested an urgent
meeting of the U.N. Security Council.
   Javier Perez de Cuellar, the U.N. secretary-general, expressed
``profound anxiety'' about developments in Romania.
   ``It is essential that this situation be handled with scrupulous
respect for the universal Declaration of Human Rights and in
accordance with the U.N. Charter,'' Perez de Cuellar said.
   Britain urged ``all nations'' to condemn ``this behavior, which
is an affront to all internationally accepted norms.''
   Demonstrations against President Nicolae Ceausescu's government
began last weekend in Timisoara, a city in western Romania, and
have spread to other parts of the country, including Bucharest.
   Estimates by witnesses of the number of people killed in
Timisoara range from hundreds to 4,000. Reports from Bucharest said
security forces fired into crowds of protesters in the capital
Thursday, but no precise casualty reports were available.
   In Washington, State Department deputy spokesman Richard Boucher
said the U.S. Embassy in Buchrest reported that 13 young people
were killed by automatic weapons fire from government security
forces during the demonstration. He said other fatalities may have
occurred as well.
   Romania's conduct has isolated it from Warsaw Pact allies, where
the trend is toward democracy and economic reform.
   Thousands of people chanting anti-Ceausescu slogans and waving
banners for freedom gathered outside Romanian embassies in Prague,
Budapest and Belgrade, the capitals of Czechoslovakia, Hungary and
Yugoslavia. Demonstrators burned an effigy of Ceauesescu outside
the Romanian Embassy in Vienna, Austria.
   In Paris, Federico Mayor, the head of the U.N. Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization, summoned Romanian
representative Petre Gigea and reminded him Romania had promised to
uphold human dignity before it was allowed to join UNESCO.
   At the end of the current round of the East-West conventional
arms talks in Vienna, a diplomat expressed concern that the trouble
in Romania could jeopardize negotiations on reducing military
forces in Europe.
   ``It's feared that Hungary and Romania will no longer sit on the
same side of the negotiation table,'' the diplomat said privately.
   Official Soviet reaction was cautious, but coverage of Romania
by the state news agency Tass gave vivid accounts of violence
against demonstrators.
   ``If we do receive information on victims among people we, of
course, will be extremely sorry about them,'' said Vadim Perfiliev,
a spokesman for the Soviet Foreign Ministry.
   ``We should emphasize that we do have opinions on what is
happening, but ... I cannot go into comments without having
all-inclusive information and orders in that regard.''
   On a visit to East Berlin, Mitterrand was more direct.
   ``It is a regime of personal, family power that has no honest
reason to remain,'' he said. ``I think that the days of this
regime, in a Europe in full movement, are numbered.''
   He ruled out foreign intervention amd said: ``The response has
to come from Romania.''
   In Bonn, Helmut Kohl's chief spokesman, Hans Klein, said the
chancellor was ``deeply shocked by the brutal repression of the
justified and peaceful protests. He strongly condemns the massive
use of weapons and the reprehensible attempts by the Romanian
leadership to suppress the efforts for freedom and democracy.''
   Klein said Kohl ``appeals to those responsible at all levels in
Romania to halt repression by the military and security police, and
to open a dialogue on the justified demands of people.''
   In London, the Foreign Office said withdrawing their ambassadors
from Romania was one of several options being considered by the 12
European Community members.
   Italy announced it had recalled its ambassador, Luigi Amaduzzi,
for consultations.
   East Germany condemned the ``brutal action of the Romanian state
power against peaceful citizens demonstrating to assert their
elementary human rights.''
   It urged the Romanian government stop the violence and recalled
Ambassador Herbert Plaschke for consultations.
   Czechoslovakia summoned a senior Romanian diplomat to receive a
protest from the Foreign Ministry in Prague.
   Government and other protests continued in Hungary, which has
tense relations with Ceausescu's regime because of alleged
harassment of the 1.7 million ethnic Hungarians in Romania.
   ``There exists or has developed in Romania a serious political
movement,'' said Foreign Minister Gyula Horn. ``It is an
anti-Ceausescu movement. There is no accurate information on its
strength, or the extent to which it has spread.''
   Greece condemned the suppression and the Athens Academy of
Sciences canceled the membership awarded in 1976 to Ceausescu's
wife, Elena, the second most powerful person in Romania.
</TEXT>

</DOC>