<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0204 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 2238EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Chevron-Pennzoil     12-27 0355</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Chevron-Pennzoil,0370</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge Lifts Ban on Pennzoil Suits</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BOB EGELKO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal judge in Chevron Corp.'s suit
over Pennzoil Co.'s alleged clandestine takeover attempt lifted
restrictions Wednesday on Pennzoil's ability to file countersuits
in other courts.
   U.S. District Judge Thelton Henderson refused to extend an order
imposed by another federal judge Dec. 7 that prohibited Pennzoil
from suing anywhere on related issues without approval of the San
Francisco federal court.
   Henderson noted that Pennzoil had denied any intention of suing,
said Chevron's claims to the contrary were based on speculation,
and added that the local court had the power to prevent
inconsistent rulings even if other suits were filed elsewhere.
   The decision was a skirmish in Chevron's battle to force
Pennzoil to sell its newly acquired $2.1 billion, 8.8 percent share
of Chevron's stock and prohibit it from buying more stock without
court approval.
   San Francisco-based Chevron also is seeking to validate the
anti-takeover measures its directors took around the time of the
disclosure of Pennzoil's purchases three weeks ago.
   Pennzoil, based in Houston, said it was using $2.1 billion of
its $2.6 billion net proceeds from a settlement of its suit with
Texaco as a long-term investment in Chevron for tax purposes.
Pennzoil said it might invest the other $500 million in Chevron
stock but denied any intention of a takeover of the nation's
fourth-largest oil company.
   But Chevron, citing Pennzoil's past attempts to acquire oil
property, contended the rival firm intended a hostile merger or a
forced restructuring.
   Chevron's suit accuses Pennzoil of violating federal laws
requiring advance notice and a 30-day waiting period before major
stock purchases by anyone but a passive long-term investor.
   Pennzoil, saying Chevron's suit is based on unfounded
suspicions, has asked Henderson to dismiss the case. A ruling is
pending.
   Wednesday's decision involved an order Chevron obtained Dec. 7
from Chief U.S. District Judge William Ingram forbidding suits by
Pennzoil without approval from the local court.
   Chevron said Pennzoil would inevitably sue to challenge the
restrictions on takeovers, and argued that restrictions were needed
to avoid inconsistent decisions.
</TEXT>

</DOC>