<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0157 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1738EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-USInterventions     12-20 0935</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US Interventions,890</SECOND>
<HEAD>Panama Invasion Follows Long History of Intervention</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-US-Panama Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN KING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The invasion of Panama by American troops is
the latest in nearly 20 episodes over the past 150 years in which
the United States has used its military might in Latin America and
the Caribbean.
   Prior to the action in Panama, the most recent outright use of
U.S. force in the region was six years ago, on Oct. 25, 1983, when
U.S. forces led an invasion of the island of Grenada.
Then-President Reagan said his aim was to rescue American students
and to end Cuban use of the Caribbean nation as a training ground
for terrorists.
   In April 1965, President Johnson sent U.S. troops to the
Dominican Republic after rebels tried to seize power. Johnson said
he was acting to protect U.S. citizens and to prevent Communists
from taking power. Some members of the Organization of American
States also sent troops. A truce was signed a month after the U.S.
forces arrived and all were withdrawn by September 1966.
   U.S. Marines also had occupied the Dominican Republic from
1916-1924 to keep order among rival political factions.
   Short of combat, troops in recent years were stationed at the
Panama Canal and military advisers were sent to Honduras and El
Salvador to train the military forces of friendly Central American
governments. The United States has also supported the Contra rebels
seeking to oust the Sandinista government in Nicaragua.
   Support for the Contras is the latest phase in a long saga of
U.S. involvement in Nicaragua. About 2,500 Marines were sent in
1912 to protect the government and about 100 of them remained for
13 years.
   The United States also sent gunboats and troops to Nicaragua in
1926 to help the government during a rebellion led by Gen. Augusto
Cesar Sandino. U.S. planes bombed guerilla strongholds, eventually
forcing Sandino to flee to Mexico. The U.S. troops withdrew in
early 1933.
   Further back in history, two episodes helped make the
reputations of future U.S. presidents: Gen. Zachary Taylor's
capture of Buena Vista in the Mexican War and Theodore Roosevelt's
charge up San Juan Hill in the Spanish-American War. In 1961,
President John F. Kennedy's administration would be shaken after
U.S. failure to deliver military backing to Cuban exiles seeking to
foster revolution in their homeland.
   It was more than 80 years ago when U.S. troops first landed in
Panama.
   Then, the troops were deployed to support a fledgling Panamanian
government that had revolted against Colombian rule in late 1903.
The United States had failed to convince Colombia to support the
Panama Canal project but the new Panamanian government endorsed it,
beginning the U.S. presence in the southernmost country of Central
America.
   That first use of American military power in Panama came nearly
50 years after U.S. troops ventured onto Latin American soil in a
war with Mexico.
   A decade after Texans revolted against the Mexican government,
U.S. soldiers crossed into Mexico in 1846, beginning a war that
gave the United States land that is now California, Nevada, Utah
and parts of Arizona and New Mexico.
   Americans ultimately occupied much of Mexico and the war brought
fame to Zachary Taylor, whose forces won the battle of Buena Vista
in 1847. That victory catapulted Taylor to the presidency, and the
war ended in 1848.
   It would be 67 years before U.S. troops again invaded Mexico,
this time to seize the shipping port Veracruz after U.S. sailors
were arrested in Tampico. President Woodrow Wilson ordered the 1914
seizure to block arms shipments to Mexican forces.
   In 1916, Gen. John J. Pershing was sent into Mexico in an
unsuccessful bid to capture revolutionary leader Francisco Pancho
Villa, blamed for the deaths of 16 Americans during an incursion
into Columbus, N.M.
   Wilson also set U.S. Marines to quell political unrest in Haiti
in 1915. They remained until 1934.
   It was the Spanish-American War of 1898 that brought U.S. forces
to Cuba and Puerto Rico.
   The U.S. battleship Maine was off the coast of Cuba when it
mysteriously exploded in February 1898. President William McKinley,
who had sent the ship there to protect U.S. interests in Cuba
during an uprising against Spanish rule, blamed Spain for the
explosion and declared war.
   Five months later, U.S troops landed in Puerto Rico, then
controlled by Spain. Theodore Roosevelt's exploits at San Juan Hill
helped set him on the road to the presidency.
   Puerto Rico would later become a U.S. commonwealth. Cuba would
experience a period of turmoil that intermittently involved U.S.
forces.
   Most American troops left Cuba in 1902 after elections and an
agreement with the Cuban government for a lease for a U.S. naval
base at Guantanamo Bay. The U.S. forces would return four years
later because opposition to the elected government had turned into
open rebellion.
   American troops left Cuba again in 1909 after a new government
was elected, but returned in 1917 to protect American companies and
citizens during yet another uprising.
   Cuba's turmoil would continue through dictatorships and the rise
to power of Fidel Castro in January 1959.
   Two years later, President John F. Kennedy refused to commit
U.S. assistance to a group of Cuban exiles seeking to oust Castro
by invading at the Bay of Pigs on Cuba's south coast. The exiles
had been promised U.S. assistance and the episode proved a major
embarrassment for the Kennedy administration.
   Nineteen months later, Kennedy imposed a naval blockade of Cuba
during the 1962 missile crisis, stationing U.S. vessels off Cuba
until the Soviet Union agreed to withdraw its missiles from Cuba.
</TEXT>

</DOC>