<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0842EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Sears-RocketBooster     12-21 0288</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Sears-Rocket Booster,0298</SECOND>
<HEAD>Retailer Takes Toy Off Market</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOISE, Idaho (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sears, Roebuck and Co. says it is
immediately pulling off the market a toy that simulates a rocket
booster blowing up.
   Four Boise children had complained the toy represented ``sick
humor'' after the 1986 explosion of the space shuttle Challenger.
   Sears spokesman Gordon Jones said Wednesday in an interview from
Chicago that the Building Blaster toy is ``removed from sale. We
will not fill orders.''
   Jones said the toy was pulled ``out of concern that we may have
offended some customers.'' He said the company had as many as 100
complaints.
   The sons of Christa and Gary Sanders _ Jared, 13, Seth, 9,
Spencer, 5, and Cody, 3 _ spotted the toy in the Sears holiday
Wishbook catalog and wrote Sears and President Bush to complain.
   ``We don't want children learning to blow up space shuttles!''
they wrote.
   The National Aeronautics and Space Administration got the
Sanders' letter to Bush and submitted a complaint of its own to
Sears.
   Jared praised the withdrawal of the product, but said, ``That's
something they should have thought of earlier.''
   The toy, available only through the toy catalog, was advertised
in the Wishbook as ``simulating a countdown gone awry. Construct
the rocket pad and prepare missile for launch. Ticking timer
detonation device destroys the entire structure.''
   John Bohach, a vice president of the manufacturer, Kenner
Products Inc., said from Cincinnati that the company had no
intention of equating the toy with the Challenger. He said the
company found that ``kids like to build things and like to knock
them down.''
   Jones said two other toys in the Building Blaster series, a
communications tower and a bridge, also are withdrawn.
</TEXT>

</DOC>