<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0131 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 2212EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Reax 2ndLd-Writethru a0629 12-26 0981</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Reax, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0629,1009</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Romanian Gov't Gains Support but Executions Criticized</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf, By late ... and INSERTS 2 grafs after 23rd graf,
`Britain, Chile ... to UPDATE with North Korean recognition.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EDITH M. LEDERER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Several nations and the human rights group Amnesty
International criticized Romania's new leaders Tuesday for
executing dictator Nicolae Ceausescu and his wife without a public
trial, saying a free Romania should live by the rule of law.
   But there also were expressions of understanding of the
treatment meted out to the Ceausescus, and the country's new
government gained increasing international support.
   By Wednesday, at least 18 countries _ including such past
Ceausescu supporters as China, North Korea and Iran _ had
recognized Romania's National Salvation Committee, which overthrew
Ceausescu Friday following a popular uprising.
   Tons of international aid streamed into Romania.
   Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev sent a message to
Romania's leader of the new provisional government, Ion Iliescu,
noting that he ``took charge of the country at a difficult moment
when Romanian patriots resolutely came out to save the nation from
forces of despotism and terror.''
   In the message, carried by the official news agency Tass,
Gorbachev assured the new government of Soviet support.
   The Soviet Foreign Ministry called the executions of the
Ceausescus an internal affair. Spokesman Vadim Perfiliev said the
decision ``has probably been made taking into account the
aspirations and will of the Romanian people.''
   The United States joined several nations in criticizing the
secret trial, and the Italian office of Amnesty International
deplored the executions.
   ``The idea that the use of the death penalty can survive during
the passage from the old regime to a democratic system provokes
worry,'' the human rights group said.
   The Dutch government said it was ``concerned'' and expressed
hope that ``the high principles of the rule of law will find their
place in the new Romania for which so many have fought to the
utmost.''
   The Dutch said, however, that Ceausescu was responsible ``for
the inhuman suffering inflicted on the Romanian people'' and said
they were ``willing to take into account the possible connection''
between his death and efforts to quickly end ``the senseless
bloodshed'' caused by elite police units loyal to the dictator.
   In Britain, a Foreign Office spokesman said normal accepted
standards were difficult during ``a civil war situation.''
   ``Although one may regret a secret trial, at the time it was not
really surprising,'' said a Foreign Office spokesman, who by custom
was not identified.
   But George Robertson of the opposition Labor Party called the
secret trial ``a sad birth to the new nation.''
   Iolanda Stranescu, president of the British Romanian
Association, echoed his assessment, saying: ``Our feeling is
Ceausescu should have had a public trial. It is not an excellent
start for the new government.''
   Fund-raising for Romania gained momentum worldwide.
   Two West German military planes carrying medical supplies and
other relief equipment landed in Bucharest Tuesday and the German
Red Cross prepared a convoy to leave by land.
   The British Red Cross, which launched an appeal Saturday, said
Tuesday that it had received as many as 12,000 callers an hour and
had raised more than $700,000. It said it had sent 30 tons of drugs
and medical supplies to Romania.
   Libya's official news agency JANA said Libya was sending a
planeload of medicine. Libya again denied that Libyans were
participating in events in Romania on the side of the pro-Ceausescu
forces, JANA said.
   Czechoslovakia sent two cargo planes with medical aid and food
to Bucharest, following two trains and ambulance convoys sent over
the weekend, the official CTK news agency said.
   In Israel, where 400,000 Romanian immigrants and their
descendants live, a two-hour radio show was held Tuesday to seek
donations and pass on information about Jews in Romania.
   Israel's Foreign Ministry planned to send a six-ton shipment of
medical supplies to Bucharest. Israel Radio said two
Romanian-speaking doctors would accompany the supplies.
   Britain, Chile, China, Colombia, Greece, Hungary, Spain and Iran
on Tuesday joined the United States, the Soviet Union and at least
nine other nations in pledging support for the National Salvation
Committee.
   On Wednesday, the official (North) Korean Central News Agency
said communist North Korea recognized the new government. KCNA was
monitored in Tokyo.
   ``We respect the road chosen by the Romanian people and
recognize the Council of the Romanian National Salvation Front as
the representative of the Romanian people,'' read a statement of
the North Korean Foreign Ministry, quoted by the agency.
   Hungarian Foreign Minister Gyula Horn said in a statement that
hostilities between Hungary and Romania were at an end, and pledged
his government's support for the new leadership.
   Relations between the two countries were traditionally strained
over Hungary's claims that the ethnic Hungarian minority in Romania
was discriminated against under Ceausescu.
   Tensions aggravated as Hungary increasingly embraced democratic
reforms while Ceausescu remained staunchly opposed to such reforms.
   Iran announced its recognition hours after dismissing its
ambassador to Bucharest for failing to inform Tehran of growing
opposition to Ceausescu before he visited Iran last week.
Parliament demanded that Foreign Minister Ali Akbar Velayati
explain why Ceausescu was warmly received by Iranian officials.
   The Foreign Ministry, announcing recognition of the new
government, said relations between the two countries ``will
expand.'' Romania was Iran's second-biggest trading partner in
Eastern Europe and during Ceausescu's visit he signed an agreement
to buy 1 million barrels of oil and 1 billion cubic meters of gas a
year.
   The Chinese Foreign Ministry said Tuesday it was ``ready to
continue to maintain and develop its friendly relations with
Romania.''
   Ceausescu maintained good relations with Beijing over decades of
hostility between China and the rest of the Soviet bloc and was one
of the few socialist leaders to praise the Chinese leadership's
crackdown of the student-led pro-democracy movement in June.
</TEXT>

</DOC>