<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1045EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Panama-USText     12-30 0398</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Panama-US Text,0413</SECOND>
<HEAD>Text Of Southern Command Statement</HEAD>
<DATELINE>QUARRY HEIGHTS, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is the text of a statement
the U.S. Southern Command issued Saturday concerning an incident
involving the Nicaraguan ambassador to Panama:
   With good cause U.S. soldiers entered and searched what is now
claimed to be the alleged home of the Nicaraguan ambassador to
Panama in the El Dorado section of Panama City around 6 p.m. last
night.
   Acting on reliable information from a Panamanian citizen that
the house contained a large arms cache, soldiers from the JTF-South
(Joint Task Force-South) moved to the location and surrounded it.
Occupants of the house were notified by loudspeaker to evacuate the
building.
   After the request was ignored, warning shots were fired into the
air. At this point a man identifying himself as the Nicaraguan
ambassador, Mr. Antenor Ferrey, drove up. He stated tht the
building was his quarters and had diplomatic immunity.
   When asked for credentials, the man provided a blue identity
card, indicating that he had left his red diplomatic identity card
at the embassy. The unit continued to secure the area and requested
guidance from higher headquarters.
   Information provided by the American Embassy indicated that the
residence of the Nicaraguan ambassador was located in a high-rise
apartment building, Edificio Villa Magna, at Punta Paitilla rather
than the building surrounded by U.S. forces.
   Based on this information that the house was not covered by
diplomatic immunity, the commander on the scene informed Mr. Ferrey
he had received authorization to search the house and intended to
do so.
   Mr. Ferrey instructed the occupants, four men and three women,
to come out of the house. Mr. Ferrey also stated that there were a
few weapons in the house. Asked if these men were his personal
security force, Mr. Ferrey responded that they were members of his
family. The commander of U.S. forces at he scene was directed to
confiscate all weapons.
   At 7:10 p.m. all individuals and confiscated weapons were
released and U.S. forces left the premises.
   There was no damage to the house or injury to the occupants. It
should be pointed out that the weapons and munitions found were in
fact an arsenal far in excess of `a few' weapons we were told were
in the house.
   It is obvious that Mr. Ferrey was less than candid with us
regarding the quantity of weapons present.
  
</TEXT>

</DOC>