<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0111EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Eastern     12-23 0377</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Eastern,0391</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eastern Airline Reduces Schedule</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAN SEWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eastern Airlines announced its first cut in
scheduled daily flights since it began its reorganization last
March at the outset of a long strike, and said it might lay off
some employees.
   The carrier, which earlier in the week sold its Latin American
routes to American Airlines, announced Friday it was cutting daily
flights from 830 to 802 effective Jan. 31.
   Eliminated flights include some nonstop service from Miami to
Boston, Philadelphia, Orlando, Tampa, and runs to several Caribbean
cities. More flight cutbacks are to follow once the deal with
American has been completed.
   Eastern told employees this week that ``some furloughs may be
necessary as we reduce operations.''
   But the airline doesn't anticipate ayoffs of pilots, flight
attendants or mechanics, Eastern spokesman Robin Matell said Friday.
   Eastern, which had more than 30,000 employees and 1,040 daily
flights before the strike began March 4, now employs about 20,000
workers, most of them non-union.
   The flight reduction was prompted by economic priorities, Matell
said.
   ``We're trying to develop the best possible schedule that opens
the most potential for profitability,'' he said.
   Eastern filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection from
creditors five days after its three unions struck last March. In
April, the carrier announced plans to rebuild to about two-thirds
its pre-strike size.
   In August, negotiations over the sale of Eastern's Central and
South American routes to American stalled, and Eastern officials
said they would keep those routes and build back to 90 percent of
their airline's pre-strike size.
   But Eastern creditors reportedly were displeased over projected
cash shortfalls, prompting the sale this week of the Latin American
service and other assets by Eastern's parent, Texas Air Corp.
   Approval of the sale to American by the U.S. Department of
Transportation and the U.S. bankruptcy court is expected to take up
to six months, and Eastern will continue to fly the routes until
approval has been granted.
   Officials of the Machinists union, the only union still on
strike, said Eastern's planes are flying at less than half capacity
in spite of the airline's sharp discounting to boost business.
   Eastern flights averaged about 50 percent occupancy during the
first half of December, Matell said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>