<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0108 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1456EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CCCProjects     12-18 0389</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-CCC Projects,0401</SECOND>
<HEAD>Alumni of Depression-Era Organization Compiling Book of CCC Projects</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JACKSONVILLE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Local alumni of the Depression-era
Civilian Conservation Corps are working to preserve the history of
the group that built roads, bridges, dams and parks across the
nation.
   ``We want the nation to know from now to eternity what was done
and show what a mark we made,'' said James Lynn of Jacksonville. He
worked with the CCC in the Ocala National Forest and at Fort Clinch
State Park in Fernandina Beach from 1933 to 1938.
   To make sure Americans remember the work of the 3 million CCC
members, the local chapter of the CCC alumni will spend the next
year compiling material for a book that will list and describe the
work done by the organization.
   The CCC, formed by President Franklin Roosevelt, directed an
army of previously unemployed people who built parks, roads, dams
and sewers, and brought electricity and telephone service to
millions.
   Kark Busch, program director of the local CCC alumni, said no
one has ever produced a complete listing of the corps' works,
although various state and federal agencies have tried.
   It will be a monumental task, he said, noting that in Florida
alone CCC members planted more than 18 million trees and built an
estimated 2,700 bridges.
   The CCC did soil erosion control work on 23 million acres and
strung 89,000 miles of telephone line, developed 80 parks and
contributed 12 million man-days of work in fighting forest fires,
Busch said.
   ``It may take two books because we did so much,'' he said.
   Making the task even more difficult, Busch said, was that
information on obscure projects may have to come from the people
who worked on them.
   Lynn was a farm boy of 17 when he joined the CCC from the
Gainesville area. Busch, then a 16-year-old in New York City, was
sent to Washington state for his CCC work.
   ``It gave many boys a new start and changed their way of
living,'' said Lynn, 74, who became a diesel mechanic after leaving
the CCC. ``I wouldn't trade anything for my experiences in the CCC.
   ``I'd give $1,000 cash to work for a month and be back with the
boys.''
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Eds: Address is: Operation CCC, Jacksonville, Fla. No ZIP
necessary by arrangement with Post Office.
</TEXT>

</DOC>