<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0630EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Flight103-Memorial     12-18 0455</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Flight 103-Memorial,0471</SECOND>
<HEAD>Families of Passengers Hold Service</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE P. BAYLISS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RAMSEY, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Relatives of the passengers who died in the
crash of Pan American Flight 103 gathered to support one another in
a season of painful reminders.
   ``I don't think for any of us Christmas will ever be the same,''
said Bert Ammerman, whose brother, Thomas, died on the flight.
Ammerman, of nearby River Vale, is the head of one group of
relatives, The Victims of Pan Am Flight 103.
   Surrounded by Christmas wreaths, Advent candles and a manger,
members of 22 families of the victims attended a service Sunday at
the Ramsey Presbyterian Church.
   The first anniversary of the crash is Thursday. On Dec. 21,
1988, a bomb blew the the Boeing 747 apart, killing 259 passengers
and crew. Another 11 people died on the ground in Lockerbie,
Scotland.
   Joan Dater, a member of the northern New Jersey congregation
whose daughter, Gretchen, died in the bombing, said she and her
family planned to spend Christmas together.
   ``It's painful because Gretchen won't be there, of course, but
Gretchen loved Christmas,'' Mrs. Dater said.
   She called the service a ``gift from the church.''
   The Rev. Robert A. Colman, minister at Ramsey First
Presbyterian, said the congregation wanted to mark the anniversary
of the bombing and discussed it with the Daters. ``We wanted to
keep it simple,'' he said.
   ``Blessed are those who mourn, for you shall be comforted,''
Colman told the congregation of about 70, which included the family
of a former church elder, James Fuller, who died on the flight.
   Colman urged the families to grieve and remember their relatives.
   The family of college student Alexia Tsairis has established a
foundation in her memory to promote conflict resolution.
   Her father, Peter Tsairis, said the family was talking with
Syracuse University, where she studied, to establish such a program.
   ``We need to stop terrorism, and the way to do that is through
education,'' he said.
   Peter Lowenstein, whose son Alexander died on the flight, said
he questioned why there were 168 empty seats on flight 103. He said
there was evidence some passengers had canceled their reservations
at the last minute and called for somebody to ``come forward and
tell us that actually occurred.''
   Ammerman said some relatives of the victims planned to attend a
public memorial service set for Thursday in Washington, while
others plan to go into seclusion.
   Mrs. Dater said another service was planned in Ramsey on
Thursday at the John Y. Dater Elementary school, named after
Gretchen Dater's great-grandfather.
   At 2:02 p.m., church bells in the community will ring for 270
seconds, she said.
   ``It's going to be a very difficult week,'' Ammerman said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>