<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0229 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0818EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-UAL     12-21 0576</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-UAL,0596</SECOND>
<HEAD>Coniston's UAL Ultimatum: OK Buyout by Jan. 8 or Prepare for Recap</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Coniston Partners investment group has
threatened to press for a recapitalization of UAL Corp. unless
United Airlines employees come up with a buyout plan for their
parent company early next month.
   But the leader of at least one airline union said Wednesday that
her group won't be rushed into anything by the ultimatum.
   In a brief statement issued after the stock market closed,
Coniston said it favored a sale of the company to one or more
employee stock ownership plans and that it has considered becoming
a long-term equity investor in such a transaction.
   But the investment group, which owns 11.8 percent of UAL's
stock, also said that if no acceptable proposal was put forward by
Jan. 8, it ``intends to work with the company's board of directors
and their financial and legal advisors to develop and promptly
implement'' a recapitalization plan.
   ``A lot of time has passed since the pilots initiated their
original offer to buy the company,'' said Paul Tierney, one of
Coniston's principals. ``We don't think what's required is much
more time to understand it. What's necessary is a decision.''
   The ultimatum increases the pressure on United's pilots, UAL
management and the UAL board of directors to come up with a new
buyout plan after a pilot-management attempt to buy the company for
$6.75 billion failed two months ago.
   Coniston said it had met with representatives of UAL's board and
unions and acknowledged that progress had been made toward a new
deal.
   But, the partnership said, ``progress has been slow.''
   Patricia Friend, president of the United flight attendants, said
the union is reviewing a preliminary buyout plan proposed by UAL
management on Dec. 6.
   She said Coniston's comments Wednesday aren't likely to change
her union's strategy, which is ``to take this thing nice and
slowly, one day at a time.
   ``No one will stampede us into anything that is ill-advised or
ill-conceived,'' she said, adding that her union has no meetings
scheduled this month with UAL management.
   If Coniston and the UAL board cannot agree on a recapitalization
plan, Coniston said it might proceed with a threatened drive to
solicit shareholder consent to oust 13 of UAL's 15 directors and
create a five-member board that would include Coniston principals
Tierney, Keith Gollust and Augustus Oliver.
   A recapitalization could involve selling assets, such as planes
or routes, or borrowing money to make a payout to shareholders.
United has one of the highest percentages of company-owned planes
in the industry and could raise money by selling some of them and
leasing them back.
   UAL spokesman Joe Hopkins said he had not seen Coniston's
statement and could not comment. Kathie Hardin, a spokeswoman for
the United chapter of the Air Line Pilots Association, also
declined to comment.
   UAL's stock lost $1.50 Wednesday in New York Stock Exchange
trading, closing at $157 a share.
   UAL had traded as high as $294 a share amid the buying frenzy
that followed the pilot-management group's $300-a-share offer in
August. British Airways PLC was to have participated as an equity
partner in that transaction.
   But the deal collapsed Oct. 13 when banks refused to finance it,
sparking a 190-point drop in the Dow Jones industrial average.
   Since then, UAL management has been quietly seeking employee
support for a proposal that reportedly would value the company at
$240 a share, or $5.43 billion.
</TEXT>

</DOC>