<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0819EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-ScotusProfiles-Stevens 1stLd-Writethru a0423 12-19 0806</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Scotus Profiles-Stevens, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0423,780</SECOND>
<HEAD>Justice John Paul Stevens Begins 15th Year on Supreme Court</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Top 3 grafs new to raise that today is Stevens' anniversary
on court; picvks up at pvs 3rd graf, They also</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD CARELLI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   John Paul Stevens, the justice in a bow tie,
marches to his own drummer and appears not to care whether anyone
follows.
   Isolation often is the price he pays for intellectual
creativity; a Supreme Court leadership role that he has shunned
willingly since joining the court 14 years ago today.
   For all his years on the nation's highest court, lawyers, legal
scholars and court watchers have used the same words to describe
Stevens: ``maverick,'' ``wild card,'' even ``intellectual gadfly.''
   They also have used words such as ``brilliance'' and
``integrity.''
   ``He hasn't been a high-impact player,'' said Lawrence Marshall,
a Northwestern University law professor and former Stevens law
clerk.
   ``That which makes a leader on the court is not necessarily
intellectual acumen or integrity but an ability to engage in
politics with a small `p' _ a willingness to compromise and build a
consensus,'' Marshall said. ``Justice Stevens has always considered
his role to be judicial, not political.''
   James Simon, dean of the New York Law School, called Stevens
``the most independently minded and intellectually creative member
of the court, and a man of great integrity.''
   ``The benefit is that he always offers a fresh perspective,''
Simon said, ``but a downside, perhaps, is that he doesn't have much
of a following.''
   While the court's eight other members may disagree over how to
decide an issue, it is not rare for Stevens to file a concurring or
dissenting opinion that says another issue is what's really at the
heart of the matter.
   In ``The Ascent of Pragmatism,'' a new book on the court during
retired Chief Justice Warren E. Burger's 17-year tenure, New York
University law school professor Bernard Schwartz makes the same
point.
   The book calls Stevens ``a loner (who) makes little effort to
win over other members of the court.''
   A pleasant, unassuming man with an affinity for wearing bow
ties, Stevens will turn 70 in April. He has found comfort in his
work and in the relative anonymity it provides. He refused to be
interviewed for this article, but answered several questions
submitted in writing.
   He said he enjoys a regular game of bridge (he's a life master)
and early morning tennis matches, and has not yet closed out his
avocation of flying as a licensed private pilot.
   Stevens' high court tenure began Dec. 19, 1975, after his
nomination by President Gerald R. Ford breezed through Senate
confirmation. He already had distinguished himself as a judge of
the 7th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals in Chicago after being
appointed to that job by President Richard M. Nixon in 1970.
   When in 1978 the Supreme Court ruled that the Federal
Communications Commission could ban the broadcast of ``indecent''
words even if they are not legally obscene, Stevens wrote for the
court:
   ``We simply hold that when the commission finds that a pig has
entered the parlor, the exercise of its regulatory power does not
depend on proof the pig is obscene.''
   Through the 1980s, Stevens served as something of a
self-appointed, in-house critic.
   His opinions occasionally chastised the court for deciding
certain cases more broadly than necessary, what he has called ``an
indefensible brand of judicial activism.''
   ``Judges who have confidence in their own ability to fashion
public policy are less hesitant to change the law than those of us
who are inclined to give wide latitude to the views of the voters'
representatives on non-constitutional matters,'' Stevens wrote in
dissenting from a securities law decision last May.
   Dissenting from a 1984 decision that reinstated a criminal
conviction, Stevens said, ``The court must be ever mindful of its
primary role as the protector of the citizen and not the warden or
the prosecution.''
   He said the court was spending too much time second-guessing
state court rulings that resulted in victories for individual
defendants.
   In most criminal law disputes and in other high-profile issues _
abortion, civil rights and church-state relations _ Stevens can be
found voting with the court's liberal wing.
   But when President Reagan's nomination of Robert H. Bork to the
court was foundering in 1987, Stevens took the unusual, and
unexpected, step of speaking out in favor of Bork.
   ``Surely he knew that once on the court Bork would not vote his
way in most cases,'' law professor Marshall said, ``but Justice
Stevens, in his own apolitical way, saw no reason to keep Bork off
the court.''
   ``Similarly, he repeatedly is the voice of conscience on how the
court wields its power,'' Marshall said. ``That flows from a strong
belief in the integrity of the court.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>