<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0048EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-Panama-WarPowers     12-21 0769</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-War Powers,760</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Military Action in Panama Raises Legal Questions</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM DRINKARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When President Bush launched military action
against Panama's Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega, he cited the
dictator's declaration of war against the United States and attacks
on U.S. servicemen, saying ``that was enough.''
   The decision won Bush strong congressional support. But a few
congressional dissenters and some legal scholars say the legal
underpinnings for the invasion are likely to become the subject of
debate if the stay of U.S. troops in Panama stretches into weeks.
   The most adamant critic was Rep. Don Edwards, D-Calif., chairman
of the House Judiciary subcommittee on the constitution, who
dismissed administration arguments that the invasion was a matter
of self-defense.
   ``There was no danger to our national security from this weak,
small country, nor was the Panama Canal in real peril,'' Edwards
said in a statement issued while he was traveling in Budapest,
Hungary.
   Michael Glennon, an international law professor at the
University of California-Davis, said the United Nations charter
gives countries the right to use force for self-defense. But the
charter is clear that in order to exercise that right, a country's
interests must come under actual attack.
   Threats and intimidation _ for example, the unconfirmed
intelligence reports cited by Secretary of State James A. Baker III
of an impending Noriega attack on U.S. civilians _ are not
sufficient grounds for action, he said.
   Nor is the simple desire to oust a government inimical to U.S.
hopes for Panama, he added.
   Glennon, who was counsel to the Senate Foreign Relations
Committee during consideration of the Panama Canal treaties in
1978, also said any claim that the treaties give the president
additional authority for military action is incorrect.
   ``The treaties make it abundantly clear ... that there is no
authority to use armed force in hostilities that he (the president)
did not have prior to ratification of the treaties,'' he said.
   Justice Department spokesman David Runkel said the
administration believed there was ``clearly legal authority under
both U.S. law and international law'' for Wednesday's military
action.
   Baker listed the U.N. charter and that of the Organization of
American States as the legal basis for the action. Echoing Bush, he
said Noriega's declaration of war and the killing of an unarmed
U.S. Marine this weekend ``gave us the right to take the steps
necessary to remove this threat.''
   Constantine Menges, a scholar at the American Enterprise
Institute and formerly a Latin American policymaker in the Reagan
White House, said justification for the military move went well
beyond events of the past few days in Panama, and included dozens _
and perhaps hundreds _ of incidents involving Noriega's forces and
U.S. military personnel over the past few years.
   ``It's a matter of judgment, and we elected (Bush) to make that
judgment,'' said Menges, who was an architect of the 1983 invasion
of Grenada by U.S. forces that ousted a leftist government. ``It's
reasonable, by any common-sense reading'' of the U.N. charter, he
said.
   That judgment was contested by Jules Lobel, a law professor at
the University of Pittsburgh who also is associated with the Center
for Constitutional Rights, a liberal New York-based civil liberties
group.
   ``I'd say it's clearly illegal under the UN Charter and the OAS
charter,'' Lobel said. ``The United States doesn't have the right
to unilaterally decide to overthrow another government by the use
of force. Nothing that the president said today or the secretary of
state said would give the United States such a right.''
   A second issue raised by the invasion is that if the United
States has the right to intervene in Panama, who within the
American government holds the authority to commit forces? The
Constitution makes the president commander-in-chief of the
military, but gives Congress the sole power to declare war.
   ``As a purely technical constitutional matter, the president
does not have the authority to do what he did,'' said David Cole,
another attorney for the center.
   Several legal scholars agreed, and predicted that if U.S. troops
remain in place for long, Congress will seek to invoke its
prerogatives through the War Powers Act, a post-Vietnam law enacted
in 1973 that requires approval from Capitol Hill for deployment of
force longer than 60 days.
   ``The use of force will rapidly move into the domain of shared
powers,'' said Glennon. International law and domestic
understandings allow the use of force ``to defend American citizens
and members of the armed forces in an emergency situation. Once the
emergency is over, it is necessary to come to the Congress and get
approval.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>