<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0037EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AIDS-Pedicure     12-22 0306</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-AIDS-Pedicure,0316</SECOND>
<HEAD>Posthumous Court Victory For AIDS Victim</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man who died of AIDS won a posthumous legal
victory in his fight with a nail salon that refused to give him a
pedicure.
   The state Court of Appeals on Wednesday upheld the
constitutionality of a West Hollywood ordinance that bans
discrimination against people with acquired immune deficiency
syndrome.
   Paul Jasperson had sued Jessica's Nail Salon for cancelling his
July 1986 appointment for a pedicure after he mentioned to a client
that he had AIDS.
   ``I'm just overwhelmed with happiness. I spoke at his funeral.
... All of us wanted to win this for Paul and for the millions of
people with AIDS,'' his attorney, Gloria Allred, said Thursday.
   In a March 1988 Los Angeles County Superior Court ruling, a
judge found that Jasperson was denied service because of his
illness, but refused to issue an injunction.
   Judge Lawrence Waddington ruled that the pedicure potentially
exposed salon workers to AIDS, and the risk, though marginal, was
unacceptable.
   Jasperson, 37, died of AIDS in May, but his appeal continued.
   On Wednesday, the three-member Second Circuit Court of Appeals
court ruled 2-1 to reverse the lower court ruling and enforce the
ordinance.
   The court said the ordinance, by preventing discrimination,
serves a public health function by encouraging those with AIDS to
make their illness known to ``providers of personal services,'' who
then can take precautions.
   ``This case was extremely important, because we were seeking to
enforce the West Hollywood city ordinance which had been used as a
model and copied by many other cities throughout the nation,'' Ms.
Allred said.
   Attorneys for Santa Monica and Los Angeles, which have similar
ordinances, had filed briefs on behalf of Jasperson, as did the
city of West Hollywood and the American Civil Liberties Union of
Southern California.
</TEXT>

</DOC>