<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0223 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1340EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s e BC-APN--TVWeek Adv31   12-18 0870</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--TV Week, Adv 31,0889</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 31</HEAD>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<HEAD>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 1 b&amp;w photo.)</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JERRY BUCK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Television Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jamie Lee Curtis bucked the trend by going
into television on the heels of a hit motion picture.
   Curtis, after starring in ``A Fish Called Wanda,'' is now
starring with Richard Lewis in the ABC comedy series ``Anything But
Love.''
   ``I got involved in this show before `Wanda' and it actually got
picked up because of the success of `Wanda,''' Curtis says. ``After
`Wanda' I did `Blue Steel.' ABC then picked up this show after
passing on it before and re-tooled the concept.''
   She had her reasons for wanting to switch to television. ``When
you have a child your needs become very immediate to take care of
that child,'' she says. ``You want stability in your life and no
traveling.''
   Curtis, the daughter of actor Tony Curtis and Janet Leigh, is
married to actor Christopher Guest. They adopted a daughter, Annie,
in 1987 and that led to adopting the less-hectic schedule of
television production to have more time for her family.
   ``The hours on a film can be deadly,'' she says. ``You have to
surrender your life for 12 weeks or more when you do a film. But on
a TV comedy series the hours are quite workable. You can have a
professional life and a personal life at the same time.''
   In ``Anything But Love,'' Curtis plays Hannah Miller, who gave
up teaching school to pursue her dream of becoming a writer. She
lands a job on the stylish Chicago Weekly magazine with the aid of
writer Marty Gold, played by Lewis.
   Are they just friends, or will it get more serious than that?
The comedy comes out of the sexual tension.
   ``The original concept, which ABC passed on, was a romantic
triangle between myself and two men,'' says Curtis as she walks
from the stage to the commissary at 20th Century Fox Studios, where
the comedy series is filmed. ``She has a secure but not very
exciting relationship with a solid guy. Then an old boyfriend shows
up. It was the most passionate and exciting sexual relationship
she'd ever had. Was she going to go with the solid guy or the
dangerous guy?
   ``The part that worked was Richard as the rock-solid guy and
that's what they kept. But, how long can you keep them at arm's
length. Experience shows that you can't not bring them together
because the audience demands it. After that you have a cooling off
period and a feeling the story is over once they go to bed.''
   That was one of the things that brought the downfall of
``Moonlighting.'' Once Maddie and David went to bed, the stories
went downhill.
   Curtis goes through the cafeteria line and picks out a salad.
She settles at a table in a deserted corner of the commissary.
She's wearing faded jeans and a jacket and no makeup.
   ``Our characters are not cool and aloof,'' she says. ``Richard
and I offer more menschy characters. They aren't sexual barterers.
They don't use sex as a duel. They're afraid of what sex might do
to their wonderful relationship. They've barely kissed.
   ``Last year, we didn't know what direction we were going in.
Then Peter Noel took over the show. His philosophy is that they are
best friends and should never come together. I don't know what the
pressures will be to make it a sexual relationship.''
   It's the first series for Curtis since ``Operation Petticoat''
in 1977, when she first began and had a small role as one of the
nurses. It was adapted from the 1959 movie starring Cary Grant and
her father.
   Soon after ``Operation Petticoat,'' Curtis was in ``Halloween,''
the first of a series of horror movies that earned her the
sobriquet of ``scream queen.'' But she also had roles in such
pictures as ``Trading Places,'' ``Perfect,'' ``Amazing Grace and
Chuck,'' ``A Man in Love'' and ``Dominic and Eugene.''
   Her TV movies included ``She's in the Army Now'' and ``Dorothy
Stratton: Death of a Centerfold.'' She did a comedy pilot a few
years ago, in which she played a sort of female version of Indiana
Jones. It wasn't picked up as a series.
   In ``Blue Steel,'' she plays a rookie policewoman who is accused
of a crime her first week on the job and is fired. She has to find
the killer to prove her innocence.
   ``I never want to say never to films,'' she says. ``I did this
work in the series and it satisfies my needs as an actor. I didn't
take it so I could then go off and do films. I came from films. But
if something good comes along I may take advantage of it.''
   Her husband was formerly on NBC's ``Saturday Night Live'' and
starred in the movies ``This Is Spinal Tap'' and ``The Princess
Bride.''
   ``I saw his picture in a magazine and called his agent,'' she
says. ``He didn't call me back, but we ran into each other soon
afterward by chance. We married five months later.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>

</DOC>