<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0944EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Britain-Gates     12-28 0376</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Britain-Gates,0387</SECOND>
<HEAD>The Gates of Downing Street: Barrier for Mrs. Thatcher</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Steel security gates built across Downing Street
to block the entry to the official residence of Prime Minister
Margaret Thatcher do not fit, photographs published today suggest.
   A chain and padlock holding the gates together was published in
the Guardian newspaper.
   But a spokesman for the Property Services Agency, the body which
deals with government property, said work hasn't finished on the
10-foot tall gates.
   ``These gates have been put into position but final adjustments
will not be made until next week, which was always the timetable
for this job,'' he said, speaking anonymously in keeping with
British custom.
   ``You get so far with the job and then you send your technicians
in to finish it off. They will come next week. It is not therefore
true to say that the gates don't fit. It is much ado about
nothing.''
   The gates are backed up by a steel screen designed to spring up
from the road in the path of any attacker.
   Downing Street used to be open to anyone to wander along for a
look at the modest building housing the head of government. Crowds
would collect at times of comings and goings for government changes
and over many years a man turned up every day to kneel in the
street to pray for the prime minister.
   All that is now over.
   The street was first closed off by a waist-high wooden barrier
and police guards eight years ago, when the Irish Republican Army
was conducting a bombing campaign in Britain to back its struggle
to end British rule in Northern Ireland.
   The iron gates which have now replaced the wooden barrier were
designed by architect Steve Pashnam and have been criticized by
other architects and by conservationists for their size. They also
have been the butt of jokes by political opponents of Mrs. Thatcher
who say she wants the barrier to protect her from public opposition
to her policies.
   The Guardian said completion of the gates ``marks the final
abolition of what was a public right of way for 200 years.''
   The street is named after Sir George Downing who built the
cul-de-sac of brick row houses in 1680.
</TEXT>

</DOC>