<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0223 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 2116EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APonTV-Harewood Adv26   12-22 0716</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP on TV-Harewood, Adv 26,0736</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv26</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Tues PMs, Dec. 26, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Dorian Harewood Plays Tough Base Commander on `China Beach'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JERRY BUCK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Television Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dorian Harewood is a hard-nosed Army major
who meets the hardhearted K.C. on ``China Beach'' and sees himself
as her Henry Higgins.
   ``He knows she's a prostitute, but he thinks he can be her
savior,'' said Harewood, who makes guest appearances on three
episodes of the ABC series.
   ``He wants to take this hard-as-nails prostitute and mold her
into a great human being. ... He falls for her and she for him, but
they have a communication problem and their flaws get in the way.''
   Harewood made one earlier appearance as Maj. Melvin P. Otis, the
new commander of the Vietnam medical and recreation center that is
the focus of the series. He returns Wednesday in the first of two
more episodes.
   K.C., played by Marg Helgenberger, is a prostitute who is
sometimes referred to as an ``entrepreneur'' since she's out to
make money off the war. K.C. doesn't want to be changed. In one
scene, where she tries on a dress Otis bought her, she looks in a
mirror and says, ``Donna Reed'' _ an obvious reference to Reed's
prostitute role in ``From Here to Eternity.''
   Little is made of the interracial aspect of the romance. ``There
is one scene where someone of limited thinking _ I won't call him a
redneck _ doesn't like to see a romance between a black man and a
white woman,'' Harewood said. ``What's great is that they don't
make that much over the fact that we're different colors.
   ``It focuses on the relationship. These characters have flaws.
They have personality problems. But neither is concerned about
their relationship being interracial.''
   Harewood said that in 1977 he was cast as a doctor in a pilot,
after the female love interest had already been set. ``She was
white and the producer said, `Why change it?' It got great reviews.
But the network was too gutless to put on a series about a black
doctor.''
   Harewood talked about his ``China Beach'' stint while wearing a
blue hospital robe, his head swathed in bandages, for a role in a
new feature film, ``Solar Crisis.'' He co-stars with Charlton
Heston, Tim Matheson and Peter Boyle in the science fiction
thriller set in the 21st century. Interior sets for a spaceship
filled an old warehouse near downtown Los Angeles.
   ``The story is that the Earth's burning up and we're trying to
return the atmosphere to a good condition,'' he said. ``One man
with a multinational corporation is making money off people's
misery and tries to stop us.
   ``I'm an astronaut who's tough but nice. He's similar to my
character on `China Beach,' although Maj. Otis is more of a bad
guy.''
   Early next year, Harewood and Perry King begin work on a new
pilot for ABC called ``The Knife &amp; Gun Club,'' based on a book
about emergency room surgeons.
   It's the second pilot for Harewood and King, who first
collaborated in the 1975 TV movie ``Foster &amp; Laurie.'' They were
police partners who were killed in an ambush in the true story.
   In another pilot, created by Harewood' wife, Ann McCurry, ``We
played brothers who had the same mother and met for the first time
at her funeral. We teamed up as investigative reporters for a
magazine. It was a great idea that wasn't translated to film. ABC
said it didn't work, but liked the chemistry between Perry and
myself and asked us to try again.''
   In ``The Knife &amp; Gun Club,'' slang for an emergency room, they
play two longtime friends who give up their practices to contract
with a hospital to run the emergency services.
   Harewood also is negotiating for a new movie and is developing a
Broadway musical based on ``To Sir With Love.''
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Elsewhere in television:
   INCREDIBLE HULK...Bill Bixby and Lou Ferrigno reprise their
roles as David Banner and his alter ego the Hulk in a new NBC
movie, ``The Death of the Incredible Hulk.'' This is the third
movie based on the comic book creation by Stan Lee. ``The
Incredible Hulk'' was a CBS series from 1978-82.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Dec. 26</NOTE>

</DOC>