<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 0255EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-Bush     12-31 0462</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Bush,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Says It's To Soon to Reduce Troops in Panama</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM RAUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush says he's looking forward to ``an
opportunity to shake hands'' with U.S. servicemen wounded in
Panama, but that it's too early to make sharp reductions in U.S.
troops there.
   ``We don't want to act too precipitously,'' the president said
Saturday as he continued to enjoy a year-end vacation in his
adopted home state of Texas.
   Bush was travelling Sunday to San Antonio, where he was to visit
two military hospitals _ the Wilford Hall Air Force Medical Center
and Brooke Army Medical Center.
   Nearly all the more than 320 U.S. serviceman wounded in the
fighting in Panama were treated at the two hospitals, although most
have since been released. Fewer than 60 were expected to still be
there for Bush's visit.
   ``I would like to, at year-end here, salute them once again for
what they've done, and I will have an opportunity to shake hands
with some of those kids,'' Bush said.
   Speaking with reporters as he finished a game of golf at the
Houston Country Club on Saturday, Bush sought to minimize the
stalemate with the Vatican over the fate of deposed Panamanian
dictator Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   Noriega has been holed up in the Vatican embassy in Panama City
since Christmas Eve. The Roman Catholic Church has balked at U.S.
demands to turn him over to the United States to stand trial in
Florida on drug-trafficking charges.
   ``I think it's time to cool it on both sides and let the
diplomatic process bring this matter to a happy resolution,'' Bush
said.
   The president said he had no quarrel with the Vatican, and might
even call Pope John II if he thinks such contact is needed to
reduce tensions.
   At the same time, Bush said the Vatican has ``a history of
giving asylum to people who are fleeing, even thugs like Noriega.''
   Bush also conceded that a U.S. raid on the residence of the
Nicaraguan ambassador in Panama City was a ``screw-up'' and
shouldn't have happened.
   But while apologizing to Nicaragua for the intrusion, Bush noted
the large arsenal of weapons uncovered inside.
   ``I would like to know what the man's doing with rocket
launchers and grenades and uzis and automatic weapons up to his
eyeballs in his house,'' Bush said. ``It makes you wonder exactly
what our young men are up against down there.''
   Bush said that while he had no immediate plans to pull out any
of the some 26,000 U.S. troops now in Panama, he hoped to bring
some of them home ``very soon.''
   ``I think the sooner we can have our troops that went down there
out, the better it will be,'' Bush said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>