<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0233 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0138EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Panama-Sanctions Bjt   12-22 0667</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Sanctions, Bjt,0689</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lifting U.S. Sanctions Should Benefit Panama's Sickly Economy</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARIANN CAPRINO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. government attorneys are hard at work on a plan to free
about $375 million in Panamanian assets held in the United States,
a move that is sure to be a big boost for Panama's ailing economy.
   A spokesman for the Treasury Department said Thursday he did not
know when a plan would be completed that would unblock Panamanian
bank accounts and allow the Latin American country to collect back
taxes from the U.S. corporations that operate there.
   President Bush called for the ``orderly unblocking of Panamanian
government assets'' held in the United States after the swearing-in
of the democratically elected Guillermo Endara as president earlier
this week.
   The sanctions were imposed by the Reagan administration to
pressure Gen. Manuel Noriega, the Panamanian dictator who has been
indicted in the United States on drug trafficking charges.
   The United States cut off all military and economic aid in July
1987. Further sanctions sharply restricted U.S. companies that do
business in Panama, froze Panamanian assets held in the United
States, held payments relating to operating the Panama Canal in
escrow and forbade American companies from paying taxes and fees to
the Noriega regime.
   Companies were allowed either to put money due the Panamanian
government into escrow accounts overseen by the Federal Reserve
Bank or establish reserve accounts on their own books.
   The Treasury spokesman said the government must develop a plan
that ensures ``the assets go to the legitimate goverment'' and that
U.S. residents and corporations that made escrow payments to cover
fees and taxes owed to Panama be given proper credit.
   An official of a large U.S. company operating in Panama,
speaking on condition of anonymity, said, ``There has been no
signal at this point from the administration as to those taxes
going to this particular government.''
   Economists have estimated that the sanctions cost Panama about
$225 million last year, when the nation's gross domestic product
fell 17 percent.
   For Panama, gaining access to $375 million will mark the first
step in getting its economy in order.
   ``It's not big money to us, but it's certainly big money to
them,'' said Robert Brusca, chief economist at Nikko Securities Co.
International Inc.
   As relations warm, U.S. banks will be more inclined to lend to
Panama, where loan availability has been off sharply.
   ``Noriega's access to the U.S. banking system ... was being
impeded to the greatest extent that we could, and it's very hard to
run a modern economy that way,'' Brusca said.
   Panama owes the rest of the world about $5.3 billion. Though the
figure pales in comparison to other developing countries, it is
extremely high on a per-capita basis. Panama's debt equals about
$2,200 per capita while Brazil's debt is roughly $790 per capita,
according to figures provided by the World Bank.
   Panama first missed a payment to banks in mid-1987 and since has
faced increasing difficulties servicing its debt, said Luis R.
Luis, director of the Latin America department of the Institute for
International Finance.
   Luis said the money due Panama from the lifting of U.S.
sanctions ``could be used to pay back the arrears. It would be a
very good use of funds as far as banks are concerned.''
   Experts said the lifting of sanctions would certainly improve
Panamanian citizens' view of America.
   ``This can really help to pull more of the people onto the U.S.
side. If we can kick out the rat (Noriega) and lift sanctions, it
would improve the economic lot of a lot people,'' Brusca said.
   In addition to lifting sanctions, the U.S. government said it
would not proceed with an order, which would have gone into effect
at the end of January, barring ships bearing Panama's flag from
U.S. ports.
   It was unclear whether a ban on the import of Panamanian sugar
would be lifted, but experts said the amount is insignificant and
that sugar is a minor factor in Panama's economy.
</TEXT>

</DOC>