<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0240EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-EconomicProspects     12-28 0621</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Economic Prospects,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Embargoed for release 11 a.m. EST; time set by source</HEAD>
<HEAD>Congressional Report Urges Tax Hikes, Spending Cuts to Cut Deficit</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN CRUTSINGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Economics Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As a new decade begins, President Bush and
Congress must find a way to raise taxes and cut spending to solve
the country's most pressing economic problem _ the huge federal
budget deficit, a congressional study concluded today.
   Efforts to attack the deficit thus far have relied heavily on
budgetary gimmicks, according to the study by the staff of the
congressional Joint Economic Committee.
   ``The economic policies of the 1980s have not prepared us for a
brighter future,'' said committee chairman Rep. Lee Hamilton, who
directed preparation of the new report. ``We need new polices for
the 1990s.''
   The study offered a somewhat bleak assessment of U.S. economic
prospects, contending the United States must do more to boost
savings, increase investment and spur gains in productivity if it
intends to compete internationally in the 1990s.
   Eliminating the budget deficit, which totaled $152.1 billion in
the fiscal year that ended in September, is the country's top
economic priority, Hamilton said.
   The study said it would be impossible to reduce the budget
deficit without tax increases to accompany spending cuts, a
conclusion Bush has repeatedly rejected.
   His administration is putting the finishing touches on a $1.23
trillion budget proposal for next year which will meet the
Gramm-Rudman target of reducing the deficit to $64 billion without
raising income taxes.
   But the study said Bush's efforts to rely on rosy economic
forecasts and squeezing savings out of already strapped government
programs would prove as unsuccessful for him as it did for
President Reagan.
   A tax increase alone would not be politically acceptable and
therefore it should be part of a package deal including cuts in
spending and a moderate increase in taxes, the report said. It said
the needed revenue could be raised without increasing income tax
rates, which are currently at 15 percent, 28 percent and 33 percent
for individuals. The study, however, did not offer suggestions on
where taxes should be raised.
   Among other findings in the report:
   _Short-term economic growth prospects are weak with the economy
expected to grow at a sluggish pace even if it manages to avoid a
recession in 1990.
   _Attempts to boost America's trade performance have stalled with
the trade deficit expected to remain at more than $100 billion per
year. This unacceptably high level will unleash renewed calls for
the erection of protectionist trade barriers.
   _The problems plaguing the United States in the 1990s are a
direct result of an imbalance between fiscal and monetary policies
throughout most of the past decade. The Reagan administration
pursued a stimulative fiscal policy through tax cuts and big
deficits while the Federal Reserve was keeping monetary policy
tight with high interest rates. The study called this combination
of large budget deficits and high interest rates the ``worst
preparation'' the country could have made for trying to compete
internationally.
   The report devoted an entire chapter to suggestions on how the
country can reduce its huge trade imbalance, but it warned,
``Reaching trade balance will be difficult and painful. We must
change not only our own practices, but also those of other nations
and of the international trade and financial systems.''
   It said efforts to boost the savings rate were essential as a
way of reducing Americans' appetite for foreign goods and providing
a larger investment pool needed to modernize U.S. industry.
   It called for international organizations such as the
International Monetary Fund and the World Bank to devote more
efforts to resolving the Third Word debt crisis, which has severely
limited U.S. export opportunities in Latin America.
</TEXT>

</DOC>