<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0134 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 2243EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China-Dismissal     12-26 0291</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Dismissal,0298</SECOND>
<HEAD>China Names New Chief of Planning</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM ABRAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vice Premier Yao Yilin, an economic expert who
helped steer China back toward more central planning, was replaced
as head of the powerful State Planning Commission by technocrat Zou
Jiahua, it was announced Tuesday.
   Zou, who headed the Machine Building and Electronics Industry,
was appointed by the National People's Congress, China's parliament.
   The official Xinhua News Agency quoted Premier Li Peng as
telling parliament that Yao was being asked to step down so he
could concentrate on helping Li with the work of the State Council,
or cabinet.
   The move did not immediately appear to signify that Yao was in
disfavor. It may be designed to groom Zou, a rising star who has
been mentioned as a future member of the Politburo.
   Yao, 72, moved into prominence the past year with his economic
policies committing China to a lengthy period of austerity,
restoring state controls over many aspects of the economy and
halting market-oriented economic reforms.
   He has worked closely with Li, another economic conservative who
has sought to reverse the fast pace of economic reforms favored by
ousted Communist Party chief Zhao Ziyang.
   Yao is one of the six members of the party's decision-making
Politburo Standing Committee, as is Li.
   The full Politburo, previously composed of 17 members, is now
down to 14 after the death in April of former party chief Hu
Yaobang and the ouster of moderates Zhao and Hu Qili in June
following the military crackdown on the pro-democracy movement.
   Zou, 63, like Li, studied in the Soviet Union in the 1950s and
has a background in heavy industry.
   He has close connections with China's military through previous
offices.
</TEXT>

</DOC>