<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0137 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0736EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APonTV-Rooney Adv27   12-26 0677</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP on TV-Rooney, Adv 27,0697</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv27</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Wed Pms, Dec. 27 and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Andy Rooney Views the Year in Review</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAY SHARBUTT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Television Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Most reporters dread the end of a year. This is
because they are told to write a long story about the year's major
stories and what it all means. But there are those who enjoy such
work.
   His name is Andy Rooney. He is at CBS News and he gets to grouse
on ``60 Minutes'' each week. This Thursday, he has 60 minutes of
his own _ a little less, technically speaking _ to grouse or be
amused about this year.
   His show, ``A Year With Andy Rooney: 1989,'' will arrive two
nights after ABC News' ``Images of the Eighties'' and one after NBC
News' ``The Eighties.'' Those are specials about the decade, not
just one little year.
   Rooney, who is more comfortable with a year, doesn't mind doing
``year-enders,'' as they're called by journalists.
   ``As a writer, it's a lot of fun. All you need is something to
write about. And here it is, all sitting there for you. And every
event spurs an idea or observation. It's a great thing for an
essayist.''
   He is asked if this week's print and broadcast flood of
year-enders and decade-enders has any real virtue.
   ``Well,'' he muses, ``does virtue have any real virtue? But I
think if looking at where we've been helps us where we're going,
yes, to that extent they have some virtue.''
   Rooney, 68, has done five other one-hour essays of the kind
airing Thursday. The last was in 1985, when he took a helicopter
across the United States for a bird's-eye perspective of the nation.
   In preparing a gimlet-eye perspective of 1989, he went by
subject, rather than proceeding chronologically. Business,
education, guns, communism's decline, and even certain TV people
were among the subjects inspected.
   For example, he notes that ABC's Diane Sawyer was induced to
leave CBS for $2 million a year ``and the chance to work with Sam
Donaldson.''
   In contrast, Connie Chung, in leaving NBC for CBS, ``only got
$1.5 million. But she got to work alone.''
   Rooney began work on ``1989'' last summer. When interviewed last
week, he had just heard bad news from CBS officialdom. They said
that what he turned in exceeded an hour by one minute.
   This is not good, as he only really has 47 minutes he can call
his own. Commercials and promotions for other shows get the rest of
the hour. He returns with heavy heart and producer Robert Forte to
the editing room and starts throwing things out.
   A reflection on the death of the famous race horse Secretariat
runs 24 seconds. Out. Who won the Superbowl, the World Series, and
lesser championships run 40 seconds. Adios.
   The obituary of the anguished announcer who reported the flaming
crash of the dirigible Hindenberg in 1937 took 40 seconds. Farewell
to that, likewise a slightly shorter thought on former Secretary of
Defense nominee John Tower.
   ``A lot of good weather'' got the boot, too, Rooney says,
``although we kept Hurricane Hugo.''
   Thirty seconds here, 40 there, 16 here, it adds up. But it is a
heartbreaking task taking it all out after all that work to put it
all in. On the bright side, Rooney does have 47 minutes.
   ``They're doing the decade on the (CBS) `Evening News' in two
seven-minute sections,'' he marvels. ``How the hell do they do
that?''
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Elsewhere in television...
   NIGHT AND DAY, NORVILLE'S THE ONE: The big buildup for Deborah
Norville commenced Tuesday night when she began
substitute-anchoring the ``NBC Nightly News.'' She'll fill in for
vacationing Tom Brokaw for the rest of the week, while also
continuing on NBC's ``Today'' show. NBC still plans for Norville to
succeed Jane Pauley as co-host of ``Today.'' Pauley will end her
13-year stay on Friday, and move on to a prime-time special in
March and her own series in the summer.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Wed PMs, Dec. 27</NOTE>

</DOC>