<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0112 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 2017EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-MailBombs 2ndLd-Writethru a0592 12-30 0923</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mail Bombs, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0592,0944</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mail Bomb Probe Unveils Racist Plot, Fears and Uncertainty</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 8th graf, `The desegregation...' to DELETE reference to
threat being made Saturday as it happened earlier but was made public Saturday.
Picks up 9th graf pvs, ``We did...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARC RICE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two frantic weeks of investigating a series of
mail bombs that killed a judge and a civil rights leader have
produced shadowy outlines of a racist plot against the judicial
system, but uncertainty about who is responsible and when another
attack could come.
   A person or group calling itself Americans for a Competent
Federal Judicial System claimed responsibility for killing U.S.
Circuit Judge Robert Vance on Dec. 16 and Savannah, Ga., lawyer and
civil rights leader Robert Robinson two days later.
   A letter to an Atlanta television station last week threatened
stepped-up violence and claimed the justice system was lenient
toward blacks who attack whites.
   ``Protecting the innocent warrants a higher court priority ...
than granting the blacks' demand for white teachers for their
children,'' the letter said.
   FBI agents wouldn't say what leads they have gotten from bomb
fragments and a hot line set up for tips. They also would not
discuss a published report that the letter to the TV station
contained an identifying code identical to one in follow-up letters
sent to the bomb targets. But agents confirmed the letters
contained information known only to investigators and whomever was
involved in the bombings.
   Authorities said they had never heard of Americans for a
Competent Federal Judicial System, but the threats have been taken
seriously around the Southeast.
   An anchorwoman who received the letter sent to Atlanta station
WAGA received police protection. An NAACP official involved in a
21-year-old school desegregation case mentioned in that letter said
the FBI warned him he might be a target.
   The desegregation case involves the DeKalb County schools, and a
telephone caller to the bomb hotline threatened DeKalb police
earlier in the week.
   ``We did have a call from the FBI telling us they had some
information and we should alert our officers to use extreme caution
and to be extremely alert,'' said Margaret Jones, spokeswoman for
the 650-officer department. She would not elaborate on what the
caller threatened.
   The 600 Southeastern branches of the National Association for
the Advancement of Colored People are all taking precautions, said
regional director Earl Shinhoster. He would not elaborate, but
mentioned that police escorted him on and off a plane when he went
to Savannah.
   Security also is being bolstered for the Jan. 15 celebration of
the birthday of the Rev. Martin Luther King Jr., who was
assassinated in 1968.
   Specialists in terrorism and criminal psychologists say whoever
sent the bombs, if not caught, is likely to strike again after
police and media attention lessens.
   ``What holds an organization like this together, if it is an
organization, is they are action-oriented people. Without action,
the organization disintegrates,'' said Brian Jenkins, a consultant
on terrorism and managing director at Kroll Associates, a Los
Angeles-based international investigative firm.
   ``You could see an attack next month or six months from now,''
he said in a telephone interview.
   William L. Waugh, an associate professor of public
administration at Georgia State University who specializes in
international terrorism, said some terrorist groups seek mainly to
spread fear, and this one may use continued threats as its means of
operation.
   ``Standard terrorism creates a credible threat, and after a
while only the threat makes people nervous,'' he said. ``After a
while they can wait longer and longer'' between violent acts.
   Dr. Dave Davis, a forensic psychiatrist who works for the Secret
Service, said the letter to WAGA reflected a mind filled with
anger, low self-esteem and a willingness to kill for attention.
   ``He's really a sicko. If I had to take a guess right off I'd
say he was a paranoid person,'' Davis told The Atlanta
Journal-Constitution.
   The experts said a small group probably was involved, if the
bombings were the work of more than one person.
   ``Most times, you become a terrorist because you have a cause
and nobody will listen to you,'' said Bill Bailey, president of
Threat Management Associates, a Houston security service. ``They're
politically way out of the mainstream. If they do catch them, they
probably will fit around the dining room table.''
   In addition to the fatal bombs, a bomb was intercepted in
Jacksonville, Fla., where Vance was involved in a desegregation
case, and another in Atlanta. All carried Georgia postmarks. The
letter to WAGA had an Atlanta postmark, as did follow-up letters to
victims.
   ``The likelihood, with the way it's been organized, is that
they're a splinter from another group,'' Waugh said. ``These are
ideas that don't just come out of the blue.''
   Pat Clark, director of the Klanwatch operations at the Southern
Poverty Law Center in Montgomery, Ala., said Friday that the
organization has identified more than 230 hate groups in the United
States, but none calls itself Americans for a Competent Federal
Judicial System.
   Jenkins said the theme and language of the letter reflected
racism and xenophobia common to the Ku Klux Klan and its spinoffs.
Klan groups have vehemently denied involvement.
   Jenkins said the only way to stop the threats was to catch those
involved.
   ``One thing we've learned from dealing with terrorists is we can
displace the risk, spread it around,'' Jenkins said. ``But somebody
has to go out there and apprehend the people and put them out of
business.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>