<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0026EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-ColdRdp 4thLd-Writethru a0413 12-25 0991</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cold Rdp, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0413,1017</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sunny Florida Iced Up, Carolinas Blitzed by Blizzard</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf to UPDATE with Navy tanker running aground off
North Carolina; INSERTS 2 grafs after 19th graf, `It'll be ...,' to give
details, picks up 20th graf, `Along the ...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto DO4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROGER PETTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A state of emergency was declared Sunday in Florida because of
the record cold wave, which stranded travelers and overloaded power
plants and gave parts of the South their first white Christmas in
more than a century.
   Snow drifts stood up to 8 feet high in South Carolina, and
Wilmington, N.C., recorded its greatest snowfall ever _ at least 15
inches. The blizzard caused a 600-foot Navy tanker to run aground
on North Carolina's Outer Banks.
   But warmer weather moved eastward with temperatures hitting 40
at Chamberlain, S.D., and Minneapolis warmed into the 20s after
nearly five straight days below zero. Kansas City, Mo., had a
December record of 16 below zero Saturday, but highs in the 30s and
40s were predicted in the region Monday.
   Temperatures also rebounded into the low 50s in Texas, but
temperatures as low as 11 degrees over the weekend devastated the
lower Rio Grande Valley's citrus crop, and forecasters predicted
more freezing weather on Christmas Day.
   ``It's going to take probably weeks and maybe months to
determine how much damage we've had,'' said Richard Hensz, director
of the Texas A&amp;I University Citrus Center in Weslaco. ``But it's
very extensive.''
   At 5 a.m. Sunday, the wind chill at Orlando, Fla., was about 5
below zero compared with 5 above at Minneapolis-St. Paul, the
National Weather Service said.
   At least 83 deaths have been blamed on the weather since Dec. 15
from the Plains to the East Coast.
   Florida Gov. Bob Martinez declared a state of emergency Sunday
as even Miami plunged to 31 degrees. The cold damaged citrus, sugar
cane and strawberries, stranded holiday travelers and forced
utilities to impose rolling blackouts.
   Record lows were recorded Sunday in nearly every major Florida
city, from 11 in Pensacola to 44 at Key West, where the previous
record of 47 had stood since 1906.
   Records were reported in 56 cities in Alabama, Arkansas,
Connecticut, Florida, Georgia, Indiana, Kentucky, Louisiana, Maine,
Mississippi, New Hampshire, New York, Pennsylvania, Tennessee,
Texas, Vermont, Virginia, and West Virginia, the weather service
said.
   Authorities at Plattsburgh, N.Y., spent part of Sunday working
to blast open ice jams on the Saranac River that caused flooding
that forced more than 120 people from their homes at a trailer
park. The city near the Canadian border had a low of 19 below zero.
   Martinez overnight mobilized National Guardsmen and other state
workers to rescue motorists from gridlocked, icy highways. With
many motels packed, emergency shelters were opened in six northern
Florida counties and 5,200 people spent the night in them,
officials said.
   ``There is no one smiling in Florida agriculture today,'' said
Roy Parke of Parkesdale Farms in Plant City, self-proclaimed winter
strawberry capital of the nation.
   The airport for Wilmington, N.C., was shut down by snow Saturday
morning and remained closed Sunday. Snow also closed the airport at
Myrtle Beach, S.C.
   In Florida, the Jacksonville and Gainesville airports remained
closed because of icy runways Sunday. Air service was nearly back
to normal in Tallahassee and Daytona Beach after numerous
cancellations Saturday.
   The North Carolina coast got the most snow Sunday. At least 15
inches fell at Wilmington, eclipsing the city's all-time record of
12{ inches on Feb. 9 and 10, 1973.
   The Hyde County, N.C., sheriff's department reported drifts of 6
to 8 feet. Only large, dual-wheel trucks were able to travel, and
some of them got stuck.
   Wind blowing at 50 to 60 mph on the Outer Banks islands off
North Carolina knocked down power lines as fast as utility crews
could get them back up. Three beach cottages were tossed into the
ocean.
   It'll be the first white Christmas in Wilmington since 1870 and
on the Outer Banks since 1874, the weather service said.
   Early Sunday, the tow line between a tugboat and the Navy tanker
Benjamin Isherwood broke or came off, said Lt. Cmdr. Stephen
Burnett. The vessel drifted until about 4:30 p.m., when it ran
aground, Burnett said.
   Naval officials said the vessel carried no fuel and no injuries
were reported.
   Along the South Carolina coast, the resort town of Myrtle Beach
had 14 inches of snow on the ground Sunday and 8 inches blanketed
streets in Charleston.
   ``I just moved up from Florida in time for (Hurricane) Hugo, and
now this,'' said Rick Hawkins in Charleston. ``Isn't it lovely?
It's a mess.''
   In Florida, Parke of Parkesdale Farms said he expected 40
percent losses. The state's winter strawberry crop is worth some
$162 million.
   ``Significant'' damage was reported to Florida's $3.5 billion
citrus crop and possible damage to the $1.6 billion sugar industry,
Martinez said. The governor's emergency declaration authorized the
state Department of Transportation to loosen weight restrictions on
roads and bridges to help growers move freeze-damaged crops quickly.
   Not everyone complained. ``This is nice. It's not Christmas
without some cold,'' said Louis Dussault of Montreal, strolling
Miami Beach on Sunday with his wife and two children. The city in
Canada had a low of 6 below zero.
   Florida utilities, faced with high demand for electricity,
called for conservation and said there was no excess power to be
bought from frigid Northern states, meaning rotating blackouts
would be imposed for many Floridians through Christmas morning.
   Snow dusted some northern Florida cities, such as Jacksonville,
where icicles hung Sunday morning from rooftops and ice closed
roads and bridges.
   ``It's a winter wonderland in Jacksonville,'' said Mayor Tommy
Hazouri. ``It's a beautiful sight for a city that doesn't get snow
very often, and it's also a dangerous situation for the same
reason.''
   ``They can take it back,'' grumbled resident Randy Dukes. ``I
want a green Christmas.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>