<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0103 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1835EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Panama-UN     12-23 0410</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-UN,0426</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S., Britain and France Veto Resolution Denouncing Invasion</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER JAMES SPIELMANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>UNITED NATIONS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United States, Britain and France
vetoed a proposed Security Council resolution Saturday to denounce
the U.S. invasion of Panama and demand the immediate withdrawal of
U.S. troops.
   ``We acted in Panama for legitimate reasons of self-defense and
to protect the integrity of the Canal treaties,'' U.S. Ambassador
Thomas Pickering said.
   ``I am not here today to claim a right on behalf of the United
States to enforce the will of history by intervening in favor of
democracy where we are not wanted,'' he said.
   ``We are supporters of democracy, but not the gendarme of
democracy, not in this hemisphere or anywhere else.''
   Britain has expressed complete support in the 15-member council
for the U.S. invasion to oust Panamanian military leader Manuel
Antonio Noriega. France has condemned both the invasion and
Noriega's dictatorship.
   Canada, a non-permanent council member, also voted with the
Western allies.
   The two Communist permanent members, the Soviet Union and China,
voted in favor of the denunciation, along with Algeria, Brazil,
Colombia, Ethiopia, Malaysia, Nepal, Senegal and Yugoslavia.
Finland abstained on the issue.
   Virtually all other nations in the world body have rejected
Washington's argument that it acted in self-defense to protect the
35,000-member U.S. community in Panama, saying no nation has the
right to invade another.
   The 159-nation General Assembly will reconvene Thursday to hear
speeches condemning the U.S. invasion and to adopt a resolution
demanding an immediate troop withdrawal, diplomats said.
   However, General Assembly resolutions are only advisory, unlike
Security Council resolutions, which can be enforced by political or
military action.
   The Security Council resolution, introduced by the Non-Aligned
Movement, would have demanded ``the immediate cessation of the
intervention and withdrawal of the U.S. armed forces from Panama.''
   It would have strongly deplored ``the intervention in Panama by
the armed forces of the United States, which constitutes a flagrant
violation of international law and of the independence, sovereignty
and territorial integrity of states.''
   In October 1983, the United States vetoed a virtually identical
resolution denouncing its invasion of the island of Grenada.
   The Security Council has not decided which of two competing
would-be Panamanian ambassadors represents the legitimate
government _ Noriega's nominee or one appointed by U.S.-installed
President Guillermo Endara.
   Endara is widely believed to have been the winner in
presidential elections May 7, but the balloting was rejected and
nullified by Noriega.
</TEXT>

</DOC>