<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1249EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Ethiopia-Famine     12-27 0364</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ethiopia-Famine,0375</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.N. Appeals For 700,000 Tons of Food</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DIDRIKKE SCHANCHE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NAIROBI, Kenya (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A U.N. agency appealed Wednesday for
700,000 tons of food to avert widespread starvation in northern
Ethiopia where as many as 4 million people are threatened by famine.
   The U.N. Food and Agriculture Organization said its estimate was
based on a recent crop survey which found that serious drought had
cut harvests by nearly 80 percent in Eritrea and 50 percent in
Eritrea's southern neighbor, Tigre.
   The FAO said there also would be food deficits in eastern
Ethiopia and to a lesser extent in pockets of the southern and
central regions.
   An ``international relief operation of major proportions'' is
needed to avert a repeat of the 1984-85 drought and famine when an
estimated 1 million people died, said FAO Director-General Edouard
Saouma, in a statement issued in Nairobi.
   The Ethiopian government has put the number of people threatened
with hunger at 1.8 million and directed the country's own relief
agencies to study ways to get relief food to them.
   The situation has deteriorated since the initial estimates in
September by the Rome-based agency, Saouma said, and ``the
population at risk is increasing at an alarming rate.''
   He said current food stocks in the affected areas would be
exhausted by early 1990.
   Only 270,000 tons of food had been pledged so far by
international donors and appealed for 700,000 tons of emergency
food mostly for the drought-affected northern regions and 400,000
tons of structural and project food aid, he said.
   Saouma also urged donors to provide logistic support to ensure
the ``timely delivery'' of the emergency aid.
   Saouma did not specify the nature of logistic support but
fighting in Eritrea and Tigre between the government and insurgents
has closed many roads, a situation that might require aircraft for
relief deliveries.
   Relief agencies and donors have so far unsucessfully appealed to
the rebels and the government to agree on air and ground corridors
through which supplies can move, unhindered by fighting.
   Another U.N. Agency, the World Food Program, has appealed for
600,000 tons of food to feed as many as 4 million people threatened
with famine.
</TEXT>

</DOC>