<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0111 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 2044EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama 4thLd-Writethru 2Takes 12-23 0847</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama, 4th Ld-Writethru, 2 Takes, a0631,0865</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Panamanian Leaders Tries to Take Control Despite Resistance</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 6th graf, `The Pentagon...' with 2 grafs to UPDATE U.S.
casualty toll with one more dead, more wounded; DROP outdated figure for
detained; pickup 7th graf pvs, `There were....'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos PAN1,2,DOD1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.S.-installed president
struggled Saturday to form a government and create a security force
to restore order as pockets of fighters loyal to the fugitive Gen.
Manuel Antonio Noriega held out against the invasion.
   Two Americans who were taken captive at the outbreak of the
invasion were freed. About 2,000 new U.S. troops began reinforcing
the thousands of troops who have met unexpectedly stiff resistance
by forces loyal to the ousted dictator.
   Troops continued the hunt for the elusive Noriega.
   Lt. Col. Jerry Marguila, spokesman for the U.S. Southern
Command, said Noriega's Dignity Battalions are ``increasing their
activities of harassing attacks with small arms and mortar fire,
threatening the civilian population, and hostage-taking.''
   Gen. Maxwell Thurman, chief of Southern Command, said U.S.
forces are not yet ``over and done with the Dignity Battalions.''
He said earlier that an estimated 1,800 members of the battalions
were active, broken up into small groups.
   The Pentagon reported that 25 U.S. servicemen, four more than
listed Friday, had been killed in the fighting. Officials also said
two American dependents had been killed, 241 U.S. troops had been
wounded, and one was still missing.
   The military said 139 Panamanian soldiers had been killed and 95
wounded. There was no official count of casualties among Panamanian
civilians.
   There were reports of higher casualties. Dr. Elmer Miranda,
deputy director of Santo Tomas Hospital, said his morgue held 200
bodies. He said a colleague said there were 60 more in Gorgas
Hospital, run by the U.S. Southern Command.
   ``Noriega destroyed everything when he fell. Everything went
back to zero,'' said President Guillermo Endara, who was sworn in
Wednesday morning shortly after the U.S. attack began.
   Endara said in an interview that the news of the U.S. invasion
was ``like a kick in the head. It was not the best thing I would
have thought.''
   ``We were not really consulted,'' said Endara, who said he was
``very diplomatically'' told of President Bush's plans only two or
three hours before the invasion was launched. He said plans for
keeping public order should have been worked out better in advance.
   ``I would have been happier without an intervention,'' he said.
But he said he could work with the Americans: ``The gringos have
their defects, but I am used to ... them.''
   The 24,000-member U.S. force has been unable to put down
remaining loyalists, some of whom attacked Southern Command
headquarters Friday. The loyalists periodically surprised the
Americans with mortars and sniper fire. Noriega remained at large,
with rumors flying as to his whereabouts. forces at the
presidential palace had turned themselves in and the building had
been secured.
   Thurman, speaking at a briefing, also said a total of 2,250
people had been detained, 15,500 weapons seized, and 33 armored
vehicles captured.
   Pro-Noriega forces released Jon Meyersohn, a CBS News producer
seized Wednesday at the Marriott Hotel, and Doug Mullen, an
executive with GTE who was taken along with Meyersohn. There had
been no earlier reports of Mullen's captivity.
   Meyersohn told a news conference in Panama City that he and
Mullen were taken to several locations during their captivity,
first to a jungle clearing, then to a farmhouse, then to an
apartment in the city.
   He said their hands had been tied, they were at one point bound
to trees, and they feared for their lives. However, he said they
were not mistreated.
   The hostages were held in the jungle by five captors _ three men
and two women _ armed with knives, pistols, grenades, and automatic
weapons, Meyersohn said. He identified the men as current or former
members of the Panamanian Defense Forces.
   He said Mullen, who speaks Spanish, finally managed to persuade
the captors to let them make a telephone call Friday, allowing them
to contact their families and employers. They were released
Saturday at a neutral location, he said.
   Four days of fighting have left parts of Panama City in ruins,
with buildings demolished by U.S. bombings and streets littered
with debris from rampant looting. The capital of 1 million is
suffering from a growing shortage of food and medicine.
   ``We are trying to open the airport and trying to open the
Bridge of the Americas so we can bring in medicine and food,''
Endara said in the interview.
   Airports around the country and the bridge were closed for the
fourth day. The bridge is the main crossing of the Panama Canal,
which splits the country in two.
   Thousands of Panamanians sought refuge in schools and churches
to escape the fighting and many formed neighborhood vigilante
groups and set up barricades to protect themselves from looters.
About 28,000 people were left homeless by the destruction of the El
Chorrillo neighborhood near Noriega's headquarters.
   MORE
</TEXT>

</DOC>