<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0106 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1218EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-QuayleMisspelling     12-20 0198</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Quayle Misspelling,0203</SECOND>
<HEAD>Quayle Christmas Cards Contain Misspelled Word</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   INDso AM-Panama-Quotes, AM-Panama-Information Line,
AM-Panama-Pentagon Pool, AM-Panama-Grenada, all from WASHINGTON,
and other separates as they develop.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>ROMANIA: Clashes Spread to Other Cities; Ceausescu Returns</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   VIENNA, Austria _ Bloody weekend clashes in western Romania that
reportedly killed hundreds apparently have spread to other cities
in the sealed-off Communist nation. President Nicolae Ceausescu,
whose harsh rule sparked the protests, returns from Iran to a
characteristically lavish official welcome. Slug AM-Romania.
Developing.
   By Alison Smale.
   
   With:
   _ AM-Romania-Opposition from VIENNA: Opposition to Ceausescu is
centered in the ethnically diverse region of Transylvania and the
northern area of Moldavia. New.
   _ AM-Romania-Reax from VIENNA: International condemnation of
Romania's crackdown on unarmed anti-government protesters continues
to pour in. Developing.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>CZECHOSLOVAKIA: Party Admits Mistakes, Urbanek Says He's Guilty</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia _ Communist Party leader Karel Urbanek
said Wednesday the party leadership had made mistakes marked by
``negligence and irresponsibility'' that led the party into its
worst crisis. Speaking at an extraordinary party conference that is
expected to sweep away its discredited leadership, Urbanek admitted
his own guilt as a member of the ruling Politburo in allowing
hard-liners to cling to power.
   Slug AM-Czechoslovakia. New material, should stand. 700 words.
   By roved documents Wednesday calling for a split with Moscow on
their way to a formal break with the Soviet Communist Party that
leader Mikhail S. Gorbachev has struggled to avoid.
   Slug AM-Lithuania.
   By Mark J. Porubcansky.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>HOSPITALS-MORTALITY: High Death Rates at 3 Percent of Hospitals</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   WASHINGTON _ More than 3 percent of the nation's hospitals have
death rates for Medicare patients higher than would normally be
expected for such people, the government reports. Thirty-two
hospitals, including six in Puerto Rico, have had high rates three
straight years.
   Slug AM-Hospitals-Mortality. New material. 600 words.
   By Deborah Mesce.
   
   With:
   _ AM-Mortality-List from WASHINGTON.
   _ AM-Hospital Deaths from BOSTON: People are most likely to die
from their illnesses when admitted to osteopathic, public or
profit-making hospitals, while private hospitals affiliated with
medical schools offer the best chance of getting well, a new study
concludes. For release 6 p.m. EST.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MAIL BOMBS: Jacksonville Scare Recalls Earlier Tensions There</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   JACKSONVILLE, Fla. _ Blacks leaders say they're angry about a
potentially deadly bomb mailed to the local headquarters of the
NAACP in an incident that recalled earlier tensions in the city
such as the one sparked by a busing controversy and the arrest of a
black city councilwoman absent from a council meeting.
   Slug AM-Mail Bombs-Jacksonville. Developing.
   By Ron Word. LaserPhoto staffing.
   
   With AM-Mail Bombs from MOUNTAIN BROOK, Ala.: Squadrons of
police and bomb-sniffing dogs provided tight security Wednesday as
mourners paid their respects to US District Judge Robert Vance,
first person killed in a series of mail bombs. Developing.
LaserPhoto staffing.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>CRASH TRIAL: Closing Arguments for Bus Driver in Kentucky</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   CARROLLTON, Ky. _ Larry Mahoney will forever punish himself for
causing a bus crash that killed 27 people, but Ford Motor Co. was
the real culprit, Mahoney's lawyers say in closing arguments
Wednesday.
   Slug AM-Bus Crash Trial. Developing.
   By Charles Wolfe.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>SCROOGE LIVES! Appalling Tales From the Underside of Christmas</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   UNDATED _ `Tis the season for human folly, or, as the sign in
the New York City bus depot puts it: ``The holidays are here.
PLEASE! Watch your belongings.'' With that in mind, we present our
nominations for the 1989 Ebenezer Scrooge Awards, given just this
once to those who best exemplify the seamy underside of the
Christmas spirit.
   Slug AM-Scrooge Awards. New, should stand. 550 words.
   By Mitchell Landsberg.
</TEXT>

</DOC>