<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0121 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1755EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-UN 1stLd-Writethru a0630 12-28 0531</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-UN, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0630,0543</SECOND>
<HEAD>UN Assembly Meets on Panama, Expected to Deplore U.S. Invasion</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf, In his ... CORRECTING spelling of ambassador's
name. SUBS 9th graf, CORRECTING second reference to Serrano, not Caldera</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY45</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VICTORIA GRAHAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>UNITED NATIONS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.N. General Assembly met Thursday in
emergency session and prepared to rebuke the United States and
deplore its invasion of Panama. Nicaragua said America was trying
to impose ``the law of the jungle.''
   After hearing Nicaragua, the 159-nation assembly adjourned until
Friday.
   It was expected to adopt a resolution then, sponsored by
Nicaragua and Cuba, which demands withdrawal of U.S. forces from
Panama and calls the U.S. military intervention a flagrant
violation of international law.
   In his speech, Nicaraguan Ambassador Alejandro Serrano Caldera
condemned the invasion, saying:
   ``This affront to sovereignty in Panama is a new and especially
dangerous threat to the entire peace process in Central America.
   ``There can be no moral, juridical or political justification
for one country invading another militarily. The day this ceases to
be the case, the day that brute force is justified for any reason .
.. we will have established violence as a norm of conduct and the
law of the jungle will become the guilding principle of foreign
relations.''
   The assembly will reconvene Friday to hear more speakers before
voting on a resolution that ``strongly deplores'' the U.S. invasion.
   U.S. troops drove Panama's Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega from
power last week after diplomatic and economic efforts failed to
budge him following his indictment in 1988 on U.S. drug-trafficking
and money-laundering charges.
   Serrano said the latest military intervention was the sixth time
over the years that the United States has invaded Panama. ``Can
there be any possible justification for this?'' he asked. ``The
U.S. representatives says this was an act of self-defense ... Has
Panama committed an act of armed aggression?''
   Proceedings were delayed because Central American and other
nations offered a compromise resolution to modify the draft measure
proposed by Nicaragua and Cuba, and incorporate elements that would
appeal to more moderate nations.
   The new resolution, expected to pass overwhelmingly Friday, was
still forceful. It used the same language to ``strongly deplore''
the invasion and to ``demand'' withdrawal of U.S. forces. It called
the U.S. intervention a ``flagrant violation'' of international law
and respect for sovereignty.
   But it included an element considered vital by the United
States: It recognized the need to re-establish conditions in Panama
to ensure respect for human rights and democracy.
   Both Nicaragua and Cuba endorsed the new resolution, which
expresses ``profound concern'' over serious consequences the
invasion might have for peace and security in Central America.
   It deletes the statement that the U.S. invasion definitely
endangers peace and security in the region and now says it
``might'' threaten stability there.
   The U.S. government said it launched the invasion to unseat
Noriega and restore democracy in a nation where it had been
trampled by that military leader.
   The new resolution was expected to be supported by most Latin
American nations, the Soviet Union and some of its allies, and the
movement professing non-alignment with either superpower.
</TEXT>

</DOC>