<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0159 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1556EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-Symposium-SouthPacific Adv31   12-26 0661</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Symposium-South Pacific, Adv 31,0677</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 31, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP World Symposium '90s: South Pacific _ Tiny Islands Come of Age</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD BILL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SYDNEY, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The idyllic South Pacific saw its first
coups, political violence and secessionist battles in the 1980s.
But in the decade ahead, the ``Century of the Pacific'' beckons and
the island states expect to have a small but assertive voice in the
world.
   Speaking in unison across a vast expanse of water will be the
voices of a new generation of post-colonial leaders with
intractible problems: malnutrition, fragile economies with scant
export prospects and urban unemployment brought on by villagers
flocking to towns with increased expectations.
   ``One of the continuing difficulties of the small island states
is that many will remain dependent on foreign aid, and in some
respects more in the past as they continue to grapple with these
problems,'' said an Australian government offiical.
   The decade of the 1980s saw unprecented turmoil in the region.
   Fiji had two racially inspired military coups. Civil lawlessness
in Papua New Guinea claimed more than 50 lives. The capitals of
Vanuatu and French Polynesia suffered destructive rioting.
Hostage-taking in New Caledonia triggered a bloody French assault.
   Added to that was a perceived Soviet military threat to the
region, concern about Moscow's growing economic inroads and anxiety
that Libya was making a foothold in an area better known for its
tranquility and palm-fringed lagoons than as a political hothouse.
   Covering 22 percent of the world's surface, the South Pacific is
home to 5 million people, excluding Australia and New Zealand.
   Environmental problems like depletion of the ozone layer over
Antarctica and the Earth's global warming has caused serious
concern in a region of low-lying atolls that could be swamped by
seas swollen by melting polar ice.
   The future of Antarctica is assured a big debate as countries
like Australia push for protected wilderness status against others
who view the world's last great wilderness as a minerals treasure
house.
   ``If for nothing else, that will happen because of the sheer
importance of Antarctica in regard to the world's weather
patterns,'' said the Australian official, who spoke on condition of
anonymity.
   Driftnet fishing _ the casting of huge nets over a large area of
the sea to scoop up tons of fish at once _ was a problem virtually
unheard of six months ago. But it moved into world forums after
island governments banded together to draw up an international
convention and propose United Nations resolutions that forced Japan
and Taiwan to scale down the practice.
   The 1980s gave birth to an anti-nuclear New Zealand and the
declaration of a South Pacific Nuclear Free Zone adopted by 15
island states.
   ``They are increasingly becoming very effective in articulating
their point of view and building up cooperation among member
states,`` said the Australian official.
   ``It is a small, but growing voice helped by a new generation of
more assertive leaders.''
   Against that, he said, ``There are no new bonanzas looming that
are going to provide them with any riches.''
   The concept of the ``Century of the Pacific'' took a first,
tentative step in 1989 when 12 major Pacific Rim countries,
including the United States, met in Canberra, Australia, to plan
the future.
   They agreed to meet again in Singapore in early 1990 and
probably again in Bangkok, Thailand, later in the year to plan an
Asian-Pacific cooperative venture, an idea all agreed was one
``whose time has come.''
   The Canberra meeting brought together U.S. Secretary of State
James A. Baker III with his counterparts from Japan, South Korea,
Australia, New Zealand, Thailand, Singapore, Malaysia, the
Philippines, Brunei, Canada, and Indonesia. They represented 1.9
billion people and $280 billion in trans-Pacific trade, 50 percent
more than trans-Atlantic trade.
   The meeting was described by U.S. State Department officials as
the most important economic initiative in 50 years.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Sunday, Dec. 31</NOTE>

</DOC>