<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1236EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China-Church     12-23 0637</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Church,0652</SECOND>
<HEAD>Catholics Get Back Church, Aim Clear of Politics</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHY WILHELM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Chinese government gave Beijing Catholics a
Christmas gift Saturday, returning St. Michael's church more than
three decades after it was confiscated for secular use.
   Pale winter sunlight gleamed through the few remaining stained
glass windows as more than 200 Catholics, led by Bishop Fu Tieshan,
re-consecrated the 87-year-old Gothic building with song and prayer.
   ``I can't see the music very well but I remember it,'' said
white-haired Brother Zhang Delong, who played the new organ to
accompany the choir as it sang a traditional Latin Mass.
   The church, its gray brick spires towering over a tree-lined
street in central Beijing, was built in 1902 to serve the foreign
diplomatic community. The Communist government seized it in 1958
and made it a school.
   Other churches were closed in the 1960s, during the far-leftist
Cultural Revolution that treated religion as a threat to Communism.
St. Michael's is the fifth Catholic church to reopen in urban
Beijing, where nearly 40,000 Catholics live.
    Its return, two days before Christmas, caps a year that tested
Chinese Christians' longstanding determination to keep out of
politics.
   Some Christians, both Catholic and Protestant, joined the
pro-democracy marches of the spring. A group of young Catholic
seminarians reportedly gave small amounts of money and food to the
protesters, and several Protestants were arrested for their roles
in the short-lived union set up by protesting workers.
   But the church hierarchies, appointed with government approval
and closely watched, kept silent even while other official organs,
such as the government-run union, supported the democracy movement.
   After crushing the protests in June, the government cracked down
hard on most of the traditionally suspect segments of society, such
as intellectuals. But the churches, which suffered in past
hard-line backlashes, have been largely unscathed.
   Since June, the government-sponsored Chinese Catholic Patriotic
Association, which has no ties with the Vatican, has ordained six
new priests, boosting the number in Beijing to 24. Seven young
women took vows as nuns, the first to do so in Beijing since the
Communists took power in 1949.
   ``The events of June did not affect the church. I believe that's
because the church transcends politics,'' said Ying Mulan, vice
secretary-general of the Beijing Catholic Patriotic Association.
   ``We don't want to get involved in political activities,'' she
said. In countries where most of the population is Catholic, such
as the Philippines, she said, churches may play a political role.
But in an officially athiest country such as China, its best policy
is to seek what common ground it can with the government.
   Bishop Fu, addressing the congregation in St. Michael's, told
them to pray for ``anding tuanjie'' _ stability and unity _ words
used often by the government since June.
   Christians who reject the government-sponsored Catholic and
Protestant churches and worship in illegal house churches also try
hard to be politically neutral.
   ``In the spring, we told the faithful three things: don't go
look at the protests, don't speak, and come to services,'' said a
Protestant house-church minister. Because of that, he said, police
have not interfered with the Sunday gatherings of his group of
about 20.
   But conflicts still arise periodically between the government
and religious believers. In contrast with St. Michael's peaceful
transfer, about 1,000 Catholics in central China tried on their own
in April to retake a former church, and were driven out by police.
Catholic sources in Hong Kong said two people were killed.
   The sources have reported at least four arrests this year of
Catholic clergy loyal to the Vatican.
   Since June, some high school and college students disillusioned
with the Communist Party have begun attending Christian churches. A
young man at St. Michael's said they come ``because they feel empty
inside.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>