<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0206 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 2223EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-BusCrashTrial 1stLd-Writethru a0744 12-22 0742</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bus Crash Trial, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0744,0759</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jury Recommends 16 Years for Mahoney</HEAD>
<BYLINE>Eds: SUBS grafs 10-13, `The jury's ..., with 6 grafs to ADD more
relatives' reax, activist's reax; pick up 14th graf:, `Assistant Attorney
...' ^By CHARLES WOLFE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CARROLLTON, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A jury on Friday recommended 16 years in
prison for the man who caused the nation's worst drunken-driving
accident, but some families of Larry Mahoney's 27 victims said it
wasn't enough.
   Mahoney, 36, who had been free on bond prior to his conviction,
was led in handcuffs out of the Carroll County Courthouse and taken
to the local jail after Circuit Judge Charles Satterwhite
discontinued his bail.
   Satterwhite is to sentence Mahoney formally in February. The
judge can give Mahoney a lighter sentence, but cannot exceed the
jury's recommendation.
   It came one day after Mahoney was convicted on 27 counts each of
second-degree manslaughter and first-degree wanton endangerment, 12
of first-degree assault, 14 of second-degree wanton endangerment
and one of drunken driving.
   The recommended sentences totaled 611 years, but the jury opted
to have them run concurrently. That effectively gave Mahoney 16
years of a possible 20-year sentence for assault, the most serious
offense, and he would be eligible for parole consideration in eight
years under Kentucky law.
   The jury determined that Mahoney caused the crash of a
church-owned school bus on May 14, 1988, as he drove on the wrong
side of Interstate 71 while intoxicated.
   The crash five miles south of Carrollton caused a fire that
killed 24 children and three adults who were returning to the
Radcliff First Assembly of God church.
   Forty people escaped, but 12 children suffered severe burns.
They were represented by the 12 assault charges.
   Lawyers on both sides noted the irony of Mahoney's being
convicted of a more serious offense for the burn injuries than for
the deaths. The maximum sentence for second-degree manslaughter is
10 years, which the jury recommended on each of the 27 counts. But
that was made moot by the recommendation that the prison terms be
concurrent, not consecutive.
   The jury's verdict and sentence recommendations were ``a big
letdown'' for the victims' families, since the state had charged
Mahoney with murder in each of the deaths, said William Nichols,
whose only child, 17-year-old William Joseph Nichols Jr., died in
the bus fire.
   ``I've forgiven Larry Mahoney, but he's got to pay for his crime
and eight years is not enough,'' said Nichols.
   ``I really don't think he understands what he's done to all of
our lives,'' said Nichols' wife, Madeline.
   ``It was not manslaughter. It was murder,'' said Janet Kytta,
whose husband, Charles, burned to death on the bus. ``I can't say
Chuck's life was worth five years or 10 years or 20 years, but it
was worth the word `murder.'''
   The leader of a group fighting drunken driving said the jury
missed a chance to send a sobering message nationwide.
   ``It sends out a message that's been sent out thousands of times
before,'' said Ken Nathanson, president of Citizens for Safe
Drivers Against Drunk Drivers and Other Chronic Offenders. ``It
just indicates that American society isn't that serious about drunk
driving.''
   Assistant Attorney General Paul Richwalsky, who prosecuted
Mahoney, said he was disappointed both by the jury's refusal to
convict the chemical plant worker of murder and by the recommended
sentence.
   ``I asked for consecutive (sentences) but they gave
concurrent,'' Richwalsky said. ``I thought all the carnage ... was
worth more than eight years.''
   William Summers, lead attorney on Mahoney's three-man defense
team, said he was ``basically ... pleased with the verdict.''
   ``We beat 27 murder counts,'' Summers said. ``At least (Mahoney)
can hold his head up. He's not a mass murderer.''
   Mahoney is remorseful regardless of the length of his prison
sentence, Summers said. ``If putting him away for life would take
away some of the hurt, he'd do it,'' Summers said.
   
   One of Mahoney's last requests while waiting for the jury's
verdict on Thursday was to meet with Kentucky State Police Trooper
Henry ``Sonny'' Cease, who was the case's lead investigator.
   Cease had to remove the victims' burned bodies the day after the
crash, when the bus was hauled to a temporary morgue at
Carrollton's National Guard Armory.
   In their brief meeting, Mahoney ``just said he holds no grudges
against me,'' Cease said. ``I told him I feel the same way he does:
I wish we weren't here.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>