<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0224 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 2126EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a AM-DoctorsLeaving Adv26   12-22 1112</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Doctors Leaving, Adv 26,1143</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv26</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Wed AMs, Dec. 26, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>No Quick Fixes Seen for Shortage of Doctors</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto CN1 of Dec. 19</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JONATHAN GILL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dr. Sherif Awadallah came two years ago
to set up a program in reproductive endocrinology at Charleston
Area Medical Center.
   Last summer Awadallah pulled up stakes and went back to Ohio,
joining an exodus of doctors who say an indifferent legislature and
a hostile insurance industry make West Virginia a grim place to
practice medicine.
   ``It's complicated,'' he said. ``There was a lot for me to do
there. If I wasn't married with children I probably would have
stayed. But concerns about the regional economy, plus problems with
insurance _ that's a double whammy.''
   A decline in doctors, a national trend, has been worse in West
Virginia in recent years, threatening gains in medical care made
since the 1960s.
   Since the beginning of the year, more than 80 doctors have
stopped practicing in West Virginia, according to a legislative
task force, and fewer are settling here. The state Medical Board
licensed 318 new doctors in 1989, down from 346 last year and 414
in 1987.
   The Charleston Area Medical Center had three applicants for
every opening in its residency program a decade ago. Today, 22 of
118 slots are unfilled. And while 23 percent of the students at
West Virginia's three medical schools come from out of state,
nearly 35 percent won't stay once they've graduated.
   Those trends have left the state with 152 doctors per 100,000
residents, 37th among the states and well below the national
average of 189, according to the American Medical Association. Some
counties have no doctors at all.
   ``Some of the good people that you want standing over you in
surgery are leaving,'' said Dr. Phil Branson, an orthopedic surgeon
in Princeton. ``At this point I am watching how things go.''
   Many of West Virginia's 3,000 doctors blame the state's
political leadership, which they say traditionally has lagged in
controlling medical costs and protecting doctors from excessive
malpractice awards. The Legislature this year moved to control
runaway medical costs. Lawmakers say those measures may drive
doctors away temporarily but ultimately will make going to the
doctor less painful for everyone; most doctors say the law only
deepened the crisis.
   ``The state has never maintained good control of its health care
costs,'' said Dr. Richard Capito of Thomas Memorial Hospital in
South Charleston and a member of the Legislative Task Force on
Uncompensated Health Care.
   ``When corporate America was forming HMOs and PPOs and holding
down costs, West Virginia was an open book _ you charge us and
we'll pay it,'' said Capito, a native of Weirton who graduated from
West Virginia University Medical School.
   Health Maintenance Organizations and Preferred Provider
Organizations are groups aimed at reducing health care costs
through an agreement with a captive group of doctors or hospitals,
guaranteeing income in return for discounts.
   Doctors and lawmakers also blame federal programs in the 1960s
that brought care to isolated areas where people were too poor to
pay for it. One-third more doctors practice here than in the
mid-1970s, and the infant death rate has been halved since 1960,
according to the Department of Health and Human Services.
   But many doctors say they aren't paid enough, and most say they
sometimes aren't paid at all. A West Virginia State Medical
Association report said that doctors write off $142 million in
health care each year.
   High malpractice rates also scare away young doctors, said
Capito, who belongs to a group of emergency care doctors that
contracts services to Thomas Memorial. Each doctor pays $20,000 in
annual malpractice premiums; one who left and moved to South
Carolina now pays $2,000 a year for similar coverage because that
state has set up a joint underwriting association for doctors.
   The Omnibus Health Care Act, which went into effect in July,
averted a $100 million financial crisis by controlling how much the
state spends on care.
   But many doctor say the main features _ fee caps and requiring
doctors and hospitals who see state-insured patients to see 15
percent covered by Medicaid _ will only make things worse.
Lawmakers argue that the state had act to head off a fiscal crisis
that would have jeopardized the entire budget.
   ``It's a piece of the answer, a step in the right direction,''
said Del. Pat White, the administrator of a clinic and a leader of
two legislative health care committees, who has been meeting with
doctors to discuss possible changes in the bill in the coming
session.
   ``In the past there wasn't that dialogue,'' said George Rider,
the West Virginia Medical Association's executive director.
   Advocates for the poor occupy a middle ground between doctors
and legislators, so they haven't been key players in making health
care policy, said Charles Tindley, coordinator of the Mountain
State Health Care Campaign.
   ``To me it's a real attitude of selfishness,'' said Tindley.
``The doctors have become so hostile that they think anyone on the
so-called other side is their enemy. The enemy is poor health
care.''
   Rider applauded the governor for appointing the association's
chief to a task force studying how medical schools can help keep
doctors in the state.
   Not all Rider's 2,300 members are so optimistic. Task force
recommendations aren't due until August, long after the end of the
legislative session. And even then, doctors don't pull much weight
in the Legislature, Rider said.
   ``In dealing with the Legislature in the last three or four
years, there's been little open-mindedness to listen to the medical
community,'' Capito said. ``The health care act affects one-quarter
of the state's population, but there was not a single practicing
physician consulted.''
   The consensus among doctors is that lasting solutions won't come
easy.
   ``The Omnibus Act is a problem, but as an isolated problem it
wouldn't be such a big deal,'' said Awadallah, who now practices in
Cincinnati. ``It's gratifying to practice where people really need
you, but for physicians it's a long-term economic picture.''
   Universal health care would save the state money and help with
the problem of uncompensated health care, analysts say. But doctors
say such a plan would likely drive them away by imposing caps on
the price of procedures.
   Insurance reform will mean making lawmakers face up to one of
the state's most powerful industries. Doctors also face the
possibility of changing the way they practice _ doing fewer tests,
for example, _ to lower fees.
   ``A realistic solution is politically unpopular,'' Branson said.
``It involves a lot of sacred cows.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Tues AMs Dec. 26</NOTE>

</DOC>