<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0282 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1905EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-WallStreet 2ndLd-Writethru   12-18 0494</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Wall Street, 2nd Ld-Writethru,0513</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eds: CORRECTS closing S&amp;P 500 index to 343.77 in 16th graf.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHET CURRIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The stock market took its sharpest drop in five
weeks Monday, hit by selling attributed to spreading worries about
the real-estate outlook.
   The Dow Jones average of 30 industrials fell 42.02 to 2,697.53,
for its biggest single-day loss since it dropped 47.34 points on
Nov. 6.
   Declining issues outnumbered advances by more than 7 to 2 in
nationwide trading of New York Stock Exchange-listed stocks, with
361 up, 1,289 down and 362 unchanged.
   Brokers said traders remained uneasy about the outlook for
real-estate finance and regional banks after the Bank of New
England on Friday announced projected increases in its loan-loss
reserve and non-performing assets.
   In the past couple of weeks, Wall Street has been devoting
increased attention to the soft real estate market in many parts of
the country, and the problems real-estate debt might pose should
prices of properties lag for an extended period.
   Some observers contend that the situation could become a primary
contributing factor to a debt-induced business slump in 1990.
   Also, analysts said, traders began dumping stocks on fears that
a yearend rally they had been anticipating might not materialize.
   Bank of New England shares led the active list, down 1{ at 7{ on
the heels of a 3]-point drop Friday.
   Among other mortgage and regional banking issues, Citytrust
Bancorp fell 2{ to 14|; Bank of Boston ~ to 16\; Shawmut National
1{ to 17~; First Interstate Bancorp 4] to 43[; Federal National
Mortgage 2| to 31[, and Federal Home Loan Mortgage 5~ to 61~.
   The money-center bank group also came under selling pressure.
Bankamerica dropped 2[ to 23~; Chemical Banking 2 to 29\;
Manufacturers Hanover 1~ to 31], and Chase Manhattan 1[ to 31~.
   Losers among the blue-chip industrials included International
Business Machines, down 1] at 93|; American Telephone &amp; Telegraph,
down } at 46; USX, down } at 34[, and McDonald's, down ] at 33~.
   Marriott dropped 1 to 33|. The company announced a restructuring
program, including a planned move out of the fast-food and family
restaurant business, but also estimated lower fourth-quarter
earnings.
   Volume on the floor of the Big Board came to 184.79 million
shares, down from 240.39 million in the previous session.
Nationwide, consolidated volume in NYSE-listed issues, including
trades in those stocks on regional exchanges and in the
over-the-counter market, totaled 223.24 million shares.
   As measured by Wilshire Associates' index of more than 5,000
actively traded stocks, the market lost $57.74 billion, or 1.71
percent, in value.
   The NYSE's composite index of all its listed common stocks
dropped 3.28 to 190.17.
   Standard &amp; Poor's industrial index fell 6.21 to 393.60, and
S&amp;P's 500-stock composite index was down 6.37 at 343.77.
   The NASDAQ composite index for the over-the-counter market
tumbled 7.81 to 436.03. At the American Stock Exchange, the market
value index closed at 370.86, down 4.64.
</TEXT>

</DOC>