<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0144 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1824EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-PanamaMilitary 2nd-LdWritethru a0690 12-21 0914</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama Military, 2nd-Ld Writethru, a0690,940</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cheney Pledges To Get U.S. Forces Back, But It's an Open Question</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-US-Panama Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Updates in top 10 grafs with Cheney describing continuing conflict,
also subs 19th graf, the latest, to update casualty count</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRYAN BRUMLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Defense Secretary Dick Cheney said Thursday
that U.S. troops were still involved in ``conflict and firefights''
in Panama City well into the second day of the U.S. intervention.
   However, he said the operation had been ``enormously
successful'' during its first 36 hours, despite the fact that Gen.
Manuel Antonio Noriega had escaped capture.
   Cheney said taking Noriega had been ``only one of several
objectives'' in the intervention.
   The defense secretary pledged to get U.S. forces in Panama home
``as quickly as we can,'' but he also said the date remains open as
long as is at large and civil unrest continues.
   ``It's still a situation in which there is ongoing conflict and
firefights,'' said Cheney said, acknowledging the possibility of
individual terrorist strikes and the taking of U.S. hostages.
   ``Clearly, we haven't resolved all the potential situations
where there may be Americans being held,'' Cheney said in an
interview with 11 newspaper and wire service reporters. ``We are
aggressively working every one of those cases.''
   Major resistance had ended, he said, and ``we don't have any
reason at this point to anticipate any sort of organized attacks.''
   Pressed to predict when the American invasion force could be
brought home, Cheney said that remains ``an open question.''
   President Bush, meanwhile, said U.S. troops would pursue Noriega
``as long as it takes'' and he called the nation's commitment to
the operation in Panama ``open-ended.''
   Gen. Colin Powell, the chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff,
sat at Cheney's side during the briefing and both men refused to
speculate where Noriega might be hiding. Both men appeared somewhat
tired after their hours-long vigils at the Pentagon.
   Powell said that while there still appears to be resistance by
Noriega loyalists in Panama City ``for the most part it is
disorganized resistance ... it will dry up over time.'' The
four-star general said he did not believe that the resistance was
``under the direction of a central command.''
   U.S. forces encountered sporadic firing in Panama City while
trying to recover American hostages, capture Noriega and restore
democracy, Pentagon officials said.
   Those were the three main objectives of the nearly 24,000 U.S.
troops, who on Wednesday dispersed the Panamanian Defense Forces. A
key to restoring order was gaining control of the streets of Panama
City, where looting was reported overnight.
   U.S. forces were in control of several key points in the city,
including the legislative building, said Pentagon spokesman Pete
Williams, raising the possibility that Guillermo Endara, the new
U.S.-backed president, would go there during the day.
   Lt. Gen. Tom Kelly, director of operations for the Joint Chiefs
of Staff, also said U.S. troops were protecting the Panama Canal
against sabotage by Noriega loyalists. He rated the chances for
successful attacks as ``low _ not impossible, but low.''
   He said all Panamian bases were in U.S. hands, although ``some
shooting'' was reported in the city.
   ``It appears there is some resistance that is organized and some
that isn't,'' Kelly said. Noriega was not believed to be in command
of any units that were resisting, he said.
   ``We do not think he is effectively in command of anything at
this time,'' said Rear Adm. Ted Sheafer, an intelligence specialist
with the joint staff.
   The latest U.S. military casualty count stood at 21 killed in
action, 208 wounded and four missing. The first American dead were
flown back to Dover Air Force Base in Delaware.
   In addition, Candy Helin, 43, the wife U.S. serviceman Steve
Helin, was dead. Mrs. Helin, who taught gifted chiuldren at a U.S.
government school in Panama and was the daughter of a former Army
port commander, was killed by stray fire from the Panamanian
Defense Forces.
   Helin told his sister, Jane Sheaffer of Dixon, Ill., that his
wife was killed in an ambush as the couple drove home on a dark
road early Wednesday from dinner at a friend's.
   ``We don't think she was shot deliberately,'' Kelly said.
   U.S. officials put the casualty count for Panamanian Defense
Forces as 59 killed, 66 wounded.
   U.S. forces captured 1,500 Panamanian soldiers, but were unsure
how many Noriega loyalists remained at large. Snipers were spotted
clad in the black uniforms of Panamanian special forces, Sheafer
said.
   He reported sporadic fighting, saying ``people on the tops of
buildings are the kind of thing I'm talking about.'' Snipers were
reported at the Caracol Hotel in the city.
   U.S. intelligence was tracking dozens of reported sightings of
Noriega, the rate of which increased sharply after the Americans
offered a $1 million reward for him, said Williams.
   The Pentagon believes Noriega still is in Panama, despite
reports that he had fled to Colombia, the Dominican Republic or
Mexico, said Sheafer.
   The lives of American hostages became a prime concern for U.S.
forces as the fighting died down. Williams said there were reports
of an unknown number of Americans being held in separate incidents.
   U.S. troops freed 29 Americans and 35 foreign nationals, mostly
Panamanians, from the Marriott Hotel in Panama City late Wednesday
night, but Williams said a list of the evacuees was not available.
   Overall, 35,000 U.S. citizens live in Panama, and ``there are
Americans scattered throughout the city,'' said Williams.
</TEXT>

</DOC>