<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1343EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-QuietRoom Bjt   12-17 0734</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Quiet Room, Bjt,740</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Gimme Shelter' is Parents' Plea at Rock Concerts</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT M. ANDREWS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LANDOVER, Md. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   While the heavy metal rock band Motley Crue
sent 16,000 screaming teen-agers into high-decibel heaven, Phil and
Kathy Hawkins sat across the hall writing Christmas cards in a
quiet paradise reserved for the kids' chauffeurs.
   The Hawkinses joined more than 200 other parents recently in the
``Quiet Room'' at the Capital Center, a suburban Washington arena
that says it pioneered the idea of providing a noise-free sanctuary
for parents who drive their children to rock concerts.
   Since the Capital Center opened its quiet room in October 1986,
similar facilities for parents have spread to arenas in many other
major cities. They include the Spectrum in Philadelphia, the Great
Western Forum at Los Angeles, Madison Square Garden in New York,
the Superdome in New Orleans, the Miami Arena, the Palace in
suburban Detroit, the Scope at Norfolk, Va., the Richfield Coliseum
at Cleveland and the Nassau Coliseum in suburban New York.
   ``We always had people dropping off their kids and then driving
home again until the concert was over,'' said Matt Amodeo, a
Capital Center spokesman. ``Rather than drive long distances, some
parents would sit in their cars and wait for three hours.''
   When some parents began huddling in the lobby for warmth, Amodeo
and his colleagues invited them into the arena's Capital Club
restaurant, where they were offered free snacks and soft drinks,
magazines and low-volume TV sets.
   Three years later, Amodeo says, veteran rock concert chauffeurs
greet each other like old friends. Some of the single parents who
met in the Quiet Room are dating now. It's become a place to read,
doze, write letters, cut a business deal or fill out income tax
returns.
   ``I'm impressed. This is wonderful,'' said Ruthie Moore, a
visiting nurse who drove her 16-year-old son, Chris, and two
friends from the far-away Mount Vernon area of Virginia. She spent
her first evening in the Quiet Room doing needlework.
   Mrs. Moore and other parents say they like the Quiet Room
because they are close enough to their children to know they are
safe, yet far enough from the musical melee to hear only the
muffled thumps from the megawatt bass speakers.
   Outside the doors, the Capital Center hall was filled with
writhing, stomping ``metalheads'' wearing the de rigeur outfits of
true believers _ torn jeans, leather jackets, black miniskirts,
fishnet stockings, yards of Spandex and pounds of mascara.
   Braces and bellybuttons abounded.
   Brian Hopkins, 15, of Crofton, Md., said he was ready for ``lots
of loud music and fun.'' Aaron Platt, 15, of Reston, Va., stuffed
cotton in his ears in anticipation of ``a whole lot of loud music,
craziness and cigarette smoke.''
   Just as Leslie Morgan, 15, and her sister, Tina, 13, were
watching Motley Crue raise the roof with ``Shout at the Devil,''
their parents, Dennis and Sandy Morgan of Mechanicsville, Md., were
dealing another hand of gin rummy in the Quiet Room.
   ``Any music we like they don't want to buy,'' sighed Dennis, who
prefers country and golden oldies from the 60s.
   ``This is a good place to do some mindless paperwork,'' said
Richard Kenney, 42, opening his briefcase over a supper of pretzels
and ginger ale. Still wearing his business suit, Kenney had raced
his 15-year-old son to the concert from a high school basketball
game in suburban McLean, Va.
   Hawkins, a Coast Guard commander who lives in Woodbridge,
celebrated his 43rd birthday by writing Christmas cards with his
wife while their son, Gary, 15, attended the concert. ``I'm having
a quiet birthday this year,'' he said.
   It was the fourth chauffering stint for Clare Weiland, a
dietician from Waldorf, Md., who drove her 14-year-old daughter,
Kay, and two friends to the show.
   Mrs. Weiland spent the evening reading an Eric Segal novel while
listening to her favorite Kenny Rogers and Neil Diamond tapes on a
portable cassette player.
   ``I remember my first night here,'' she said. ``I sat in my car
out in the parking lot. It was freezing cold. I wore thermal
underwear and layers of clothing, and brought a thermos full of hot
tea. I had a little lamp attached to my paperback so I could read.''
   Mrs. Weiland smiled. ``Crazy, right?'' she said. ``But I'd
rather sit out in the cold than listen to that music.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>