<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1119EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     12-17 0645</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0668</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir was released from
a hospital Sunday after a weeklong stay for a hernia operation, an
aide said.
   The 74-year-old Israeli leader will work from his Jerusalem home
for several days and is likely to return to his office for a weekly
Cabinet session Wednesday, said Yossi Ahimeir, director of the
premier's bureau.
   Shamir underwent the surgery at Hadassah Medical Center in
Jerusalem on Tuesday. He was reported in satisfactory condition
immediately afterward, but his surgeon, Aryeh Durst, later decided
to keep the premier in hospital for rest and observation over the
weekend.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Catherine Crier, who stepped away from a Dallas
courtroom to become a Cable News Network anchorwoman, said she has
been learning from her many critics.
   ``Even in the sour grapes, there is usually some worthwhile
information in there,'' she said in an interview with the Dallas
Times Herald published Sunday. ``I take things very seriously. I
want to do a good job.''
   Ms. Crier, 35, has had a 2-month-long TV career, all as
anchorwoman of CNN's ``The World Today,'' working with veteran
Bernard Shaw. She had no previous journalism experience, causing
many television critics to launch blasts at her.
   ``It really has been an accelerated learning process,'' Crier
said. ``It has been a situation in which I didn't have time to
focus inward; I had to focus completely on getting the job done.
Which was good in terms of alleviating personal stress, because you
just had to get out there and do it.
   ``Each night, it gets better, I believe. I hope. At least, it
gets better for me.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>MILFORD, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ted Nugent hopes to inspire a packed
house, not for one of his frenzied guitar extravaganzas but for
something just as close to his rock 'n' roll heart: the right to
hunt.
   Some residents of Milford Township, claiming the community 50
miles north of Detroit has become too densely populated, have
petitioned to ban hunting. That struck a sour note with Nugent, who
wrote a letter urging opponents of the ban to attend a hearing
Monday night.
   ``You, the good people of Milford Township, should not allow
anyone to take away your God-given, morally sound, environmentally
necessary, Michigan tradition, the right to hunt,'' Nugent said in
a letter to supporters of the Citizen's Rights Protection
Association.
   Nugent probably won't attend the meeting, said his
brother-in-law, Jim O'Keefe, who runs Ted Nugent's Bowhunting World
Inc. in Grand Haven.
   The hearing will be held by the Hunting Area Control Commission,
comprising representatives of the state Department of Natural
Resources, state police, Oakland County Sheriff's Department and
the township. The panel will hear arguments from both sides and
later make a recommendation to the Milford Township Board.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Basketball star James Worthy has plenty of
room to stretch his 6-foot-9-inch frame in his new $2.6 million
digs in Pacific Palisades.
   The Los Angeles Lakers' forward recently paid $2,675,000 for the
house, which contains 5,000 square feet of interior space. The
10-year-old home has five bedrooms, 5{ bathrooms, a library, family
room, three-car garage, swimming pool and spa.
   There was no word on whether it includes a basketball court.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Folk singer Sara Hickman said she purposely chose
a caricature for the cover of her first album.
   ``I didn't want people to look at me as a beautiful, glamorous
person,'' said the 26-year-old singer. ``I wanted people to hear
the music.''
   The strategy apparently worked. The album, ``Equal Scary
People'' was a hit, and was re-released in October by Elektra
Records. Ms. Hickman also is featured in this year's Windham Hill
folk anthology, ``Legacy.''
   She just finished a tour of the Midwest and Canada, and will
begin work on her second album for Elektra in January.
</TEXT>

</DOC>