<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 2322EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Panama-NoriegaLawyer     12-24 0295</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Noriega Lawyer,0304</SECOND>
<HEAD>Noriega's Miami Lawyer Says He'll Never Be Tried on Drug Charges</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An attorney representing deposed Panamanian leader
Manuel Antonio Noriega said Sunday there was little chance he would
be returned to the United States for trial on drug charges.
   Noriega ended an intense manhunt Sunday when he drove to the
Vatican's mission in Panama City and asked for sanctuary. It
remained unclear that night what the Vatican's response would be.
   ``I'm really quite surprised. I was sure he'd die in Panama,''
said Raymond Takiff, Noriega's attorney in Miami. ``Honest to God,
I am really surprised. I'm glad he's alive.''
   Takiff said he tried without success to contact Noriega on
Sunday, but an ambassador from a third country arranged for them to
speak by phone early Christmas morning.
   Takiff said the papal embassy is so well known as a sanctuary in
Panama that he found it hard to believe Noriega could arrive there
unobserved.
   ``Maybe it was a setup, that U.S. troops would look the other
way,'' Takiff said.
   The attorney said he doubted the Vatican would turn Noriega over
to the United States.
   ``The Roman Catholic Church has been sanctuary forever,'' he
said. ``An individual who comes to seek sanctuary will be given
sanctuary. That goes back to the very roots of the Catholic
church.''
   Takiff said prosecuting Noriega, who has a long association with
the Central Intelligence Agency, would reveal so much sensitive
information about U.S. foreign policy that a trial is unlikely.
   ``I've always said they will never want to try him. I always
thought the only option was to kill him,'' Takiff said. ``I never
was clever enough to think of sanctuary in the Vatican. In either
event, he doesn't get tried.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>