<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0216 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0212EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-GATT-Agriculture     12-21 0305</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-GATT-Agriculture,0316</SECOND>
<HEAD>Administration Says EEC Proposal Will Spur Farm Negotiations</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A proposal by the European Economic Community
to overhaul agricultural trade will clear the way for final
negotiations with the EEC in 1990, the Bush administration said.
   ``This is the last of the major proposals to be submitted and
now will permit the final negotiations on agriculture to get under
way early next year,'' said U.S. Trade Representative Carla Hills
and Agriculture Secretary Clayton Yeutter.
   However, they added in a joint statement Wednesday, certain
aspects of the EEC proposal cannot be accepted by the United States.
   The comprehensive EEC proposal was made in Geneva in the Uruguay
Round of trade talks under the General Agreement on Tariffs and
Trade. The GATT negotiations are scheduled to conclude at the end
of 1990.
   ``While the proposal contains some positive indications, we are
concerned with the continued reliance by the (EEC) on managed
agriculture and, in particular, the apparent intention to continue
to rely upon large-scale subsidies and especially export
subsidies,'' the leaders said.
   ``Government programs that manage markets are one of the major
causes of the current trade distortions in agriculture,'' they
said. ``The successful future of trade in agriculture depends on
market liberalization and significant reduction of subsidies that
distort trade.''
   The United States cannot accept the EEC proposal to
``rebalance'' import protection, Mrs. Hills and Yeutter said.
   ``Rebalancing would raise tariffs, reduce market access and
increase the price of food to consumers,'' they said. ``Rebalancing
is simply protectionism by another name, and we believe the other
GATT countries will recognize it as such.''
   Mrs. Hills and Yeutter said the EEC approach ``does little to
liberalize market access'' and that the 12-nation bloc's position
on export subsidies is ``unacceptably weak and totally out of
step'' with other proposals made in the talks.
</TEXT>

</DOC>