<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0132 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1423EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Ceausescu     12-22 0912</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Ceausescu,0940</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ceausescu Built an Imposing Personality Cultist</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Nicolae Ceausescu is pronounced Nih-koh-LIE Chow-SHESS-koo.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos FRA4, NY9</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIOREL URMA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nicolae Ceausescu imposed sacrifice on
all Romanians except his chosen few and established a personality
cult the like of which has not been seen in Eastern Europe since
Josef Stalin.
   His severity earned him the nickname ``Draculescu,'' for Bram
Stoker's bloodthirsty count of Transylvania.
   Absolute power and the cult were his twin props as he pursued
nationalist policies, strayed from the Soviet line in foreign
dealings and ultimately deprived his oppressed people of even
life's basic necessities.
   He invested billions of dollars in a crash industrialization
program and rigidly followed a policy of domestic austerity to pay
off Romania's entire foreign debt of $11 billion.
   Food and energy shortages were pervasive. Despair spread among
the nation's 23 million people as hardships became more severe
through the 1980s, and in the end not even the ubiquitous secret
police or the army could keep them down.
   As his 24 years of autocratic rule ground along, increasing
opposition arose to Ceausescu, the customary star of the daily two
hours of Romanian television, and his crackdowns on dissent grew
harsher.
   About 30,000 coal miners in the Jiu Valley struck in 1977.
   A decade later, in Brasov, at least 10,000 workers demonstrated,
demanding freedom, better living conditions and Ceasuescu's
dismissal. Police arrested hundreds of the protesters and their
leaders disappeared in mysterious circumstances.
   On Dec. 17, his security forces opened fire on thousands of
demonstrators in Timisoara who demanded freedom and a better life,
beginning the chain of events that brought him down. Reports
indicated thousands of unarmed civilians may have been killed in
the Transylvanian city.
   As democratic reform spread through the Soviet bloc, Ceausescu,
71, stuck to rigid Communist orthodoxy.
   ``The triumph of the revolution requires unity, severe
discipline and a spirit of sacrifice,'' he told a Bucharest mass
meeting this year. ``A firm organization is needed, as well as a
tested political leader who knows how to unite and lead the
masses.''
   His ``firm organization'' was the Romanian Communist Party,
which he had turned into a personal instrument since taking over in
1965, and a vast network of security forces.
   He had gradually pushed aside all leaders who opposed his
policies and installed loyalists on the ruling 23-member Politburo.
They included his wife, Elena, who became the second most powerful
person in Romania.
   Ceausescu began building his personality cult in earnest after
1974, when he made himself the first president in Romania's history.
   His pictures and sayings lined the streets of Bucharest and
other cities Bookstores were filled with works attributed to him.
   When he became president in March 1974, an official picture
showed him holding a silver scepter as the symbol of authority. The
propaganda line was the ``golden era'' of Ceausescu, even when the
country that had been known as Europe's breadbasket became one of
its poorest.
   Secret police kept a strict rein on religion and political
expression. Ceausescu said Warsaw Pact allies that pursued reform
were abandoning communism, and Romania became isolated in the East
as well as the West.
   The United States and other Western powers originally had
encouraged Ceausescu's relatively independent stand within the
Soviet bloc. Two U.S. presidents visited Bucharest: Richard M.
Nixon in 1969 and Gerald R. Ford in 1975.
   Britain made him an honorary knight and Norway gave Ceausescu
and his wife the honorary Grand Cross of St. Olav. The awards were
withdrawn Friday.
   Ceausescu continued diplomatic relations with Israel when the
rest of the Soviet bloc broke them in in 1967. He denounced the
Soviet-led invasion that crushed Czecholsovakia's reforms of 1968.
   His was the only East bloc country to send athletes to the 1984
Summer Olympics in Los Angeles, breaking the Soviet boycott.
   He also looked to the West commercially and the United States
was for a time Romania's biggest Western trade partner, largely
because it granted Most Favored Nation trading status.
   Criticism of Ceausescu's human rights abuses grew, however, and
relations with the West deteriorated.
   At home, Ceausescu exhorted Romanians to work hard, and imposed
a six-day work week on nearly everybody despite shortages of food,
medicine and heat in winter.
   ``He was worse than Hitler, who, for all his crimes, at least
sincerely wished the welfare of Germany,'' said Mircea Stoica, a
law professor at Bucharest University who fled to Hungary.
``Ceausescu hates his people, and his wife Elena has often referred
to Romanians as `worms.'''
   He also took care of his family. Mrs. Ceausescu was vice premier
and their son, Nicu, was a regional party chief. Valentin, an
adopted son; Zoia-Elena, their daughter; and Ceausescu brothers
Marin, Ilie, Ion and Nicolae Andruta were given important jobs, as
were several in-laws.
   Romanian and Western sources say about 40 relatives were in the
party and government state hierarchy.
   Ceausescu was born Jan. 26, 1918, in Scornicesti, the third son
of a large peasant family. He did not finish elementary school and
was apprenticed as a shoemaker.
   He later worked in a factory and joined the illegal Communist
party youth organization at age 15, becoming a full party member
three years later in 1936.
   Communist activities landed Ceausescu in jail several times
before and during World War II. He became a protege of Communist
Party chief Gheorghe Gheorghiu-Dej, rose quickly through the ranks
and succeeded to the party leadership after Gheorghiu-Dej's death.
</TEXT>

</DOC>