<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0117 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 2127EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     12-23 0520</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0538</SECOND>
<HEAD>It's Still Cold Out There</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Frigid arctic air continued to grip the central and eastern
states Saturday, setting all-time records along the Gulf Coast and
allowing snow to fall from Myrtle Beach, S.C., to northern Florida.
   The morning low of 11 degrees at New Orleans was the lowest
temperature ever recorded there, as was a low of 2 degrees below
zero at San Angelo, Texas.
   Record lows for the month of December were set in 30 cities from
Texas to Alabama, and record lows for the date were smashed in
dozens more.
   The arctic air mass was so cold and dense that barometric
pressure records were set from Texas to Mississippi, including an
all-time record high reading of 31.02 inches at Brownsville, Texas.
   Record cold also held sway from the central Plains to the
central Appalachains.
   In all, 116 cities reported new record lows for the date
Saturday morning, with 40 of those also being new records for the
month of December. A total of 253 daily record lows have been
established east of the Rockies in the past two days.
   The freezing spell may go down as the coldest on record in
Kansas. Topeka set an all-time low with a reading of 25 degrees
below zero Saturday morning, one day after Concordia and Goodland
set new all-time records with lows of 26 below and 27 below,
respectively.
   Just across the Missouri line in Kansas City it was 23 below,
tying the all-time low set just the day before.
   Overnight temperatures plunged below zero from the Plains to New
England, with readings of 20 below in South Dakota, Nebraska,
Kansas, Missouri, Iowa, Minnesota, Wisconsin and Illinois.
   The low in the Lower 48 states early Saturday was 31 degrees
below zero at Yankton, S.D.
   Morning lows above the freezing mark were confined to the
Florida peninsula, with lows in the 60s in extreme southern Florida
   Snow fell in northern Florida overnight and along the Georgia
and Carolina coast. By sunrise, 5 inches covered the ground at
Myrtle Beach and at Wilmington, N.C.
   Heavy snow continued to fall in North Carolina, with up to 7
inches on the ground at Cape Hatteras and winds producing drifts up
to 2 feet deep.
   Advisories for dangerous wind chill readings were in effect for
North Carolina and extreme southern sections of Virginia, Delaware
and Maryland.
   A freeze warning was posted for southwestern Florida, and a hard
freeze warning was issued for south central Florida. Advisories for
dangerous wind chill readings as cold as 10 degrees below zero were
posted for all of the Sunshine state.
   Westerly winds broke the cold spell in parts of the Plains and
north-central states. The temperature at North Platte, Neb.,
climbed 60 degrees in a few hours from an early morning low of 26
degrees below zero to an afternoon reading above the freezing mark.
   The temperature at La Crosse, Wis., climbed above zero Saturday
afternoon for the first time in nearly four days.
   Dense fog developed in the Pacific Coast region overnight but
otherwise fair weather prevailed west of the Rockies.
</TEXT>

</DOC>