<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1409EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Australia-Quake 4thLd-Writethru a0530 12-28 0805</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Australia-Quake, 4th Ld - Writethru, a0530,0827</SECOND>
<HEAD>Earthquake Kills at Least 11, Injures 122</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 15th graf, `Newcastle, Australia's ...' to correct to sixth-largest,
sted fifth-largest.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos SYD5,10</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWCASTLE, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A strong earthquake today crumbled
buildings and homes in this southeastern city, killing at least 11
people and injuring more than 120, officials said. The army was
called in to help prevent looting.
   Some reports said as many as 30 people died in Newcastle, an
industrial hub of 500,000 people about 75 miles north of Sydney.
Hundreds of thousands of homes were reported without electricity
and phone service was cut off. An insurance official estimated
damage at $1 billion.
   Rescue workers frantically hunted for victims in the rubble.
Severe damage was reported.
   The quake, which measured 5.5 on the Richter scale, struck at
10:28 a.m. and lasted 45 seconds. Police said it was the first in
Australian history to strike a heavily populated area.
   ``It felt like there was someone under my bedroom floor who
lifted the house,'' said one Newcastle resident, who reported two
aftershocks.
   The worst damage appeared to be at the Newcastle Workers' Club
where drinkers, relaxing after night-shift work, were crushed by
collapsed walls, police said. At least eight people died there,
police spokesman Simon Latimer said. Police recovered five bodies
and were working to free three others.
   There could be at least another six still trapped in the
building, Latimer said.
   ``It just shook and everything just caved in, the walls caved
in. Everything inside the club. Piping, machines going down every
way,'' an eyewitness at the workers' club told broadcasters.
   ``The room just shook, everybody just got thrown onto the floor.
It went black. We were all told to get out, there was a bomb in
there.''
   Three people were killed in a suburban shopping center when they
were hit by bricks and awnings from shops, Latimer said. Police
said 122 people were injured.
   Police Inspector Kenneth Holmes, commanding the police rescue
operation, said he expected the death toll to rise.
   ``I saw at least six people lying in the road,'' said a shocked
emergency worker in the city. ``As we looked back, we could see
destruction all around us. The second story of the carpark also
gave way, bringing the structure down and crushing scores of cars.''
   Prime Minister Bob Hawke visited the scene and condemned reports
of widespread looting in the business section. He warned that
looters would be punished.
   Latimer said 200 soldiers were called into the city and to the
suburb of Hamilton to help police patrols. Medical crews were
airlifted from Sydney for the emergency.
   Newcastle, Australia's sixth-largest city, also is a major coal
mining center but there were no immediate reports of any miners
trapped or injured underground.
   The Insurance Council of Australia put damages at $1 billion.
Council chief John Westmore described the figure as ``a very early
estimate.''
   Many buildings were reduced to rubble. The Newcastle Hospital
reported major structural damage and doctors treated the injured on
the grass outside.
   ``Ambulances are reporting lots of devastation, lots of damage,
lots of injuries,'' a spokeswoman for the Child Care organization
was quoted as saying by the Australian Associated Press.
   The quake was felt across New South Wales, Australia's most
populous state. There was a short jolt in Sydney but the temblor
lasted 45 seconds in some places; Newcastle and the adjoining
Hunter Valley wine growing region were hardest hit.
   Vicki Klein, a seismologist at the Australian Seismological
Center in the federal capital of Canberra, said: ``If the quake had
struck right in Sydney it would have brought down (high-rise)
buildings. They are simply not built to withstand something of this
magnitude.''
   Bureau of Mineral Resources Associate Director Peter Cook said
the quake was unusually large for Australia and warned of
aftershocks.
   A quake measuring 5.5 on the Richter scale can cause
considerable damage. The scale is a gauge of the energy released by
an earthquake, as measured by the ground motion recorded on a
seismograph.
   In Canberra, a spokesman for the Australian Seismological Center
put the quake's epicenter at 50 miles northwest of Sydney.
   The Australian Broadcasting Corp. said hundreds of thousands of
homes lost electricity as a result of the quake.
   ``Many homes, banks, shops and stores have been demolished,''
its report said. ``There is severe damage.''
   A traffic control officer said Sydney's Harbor Bridge shook for
three seconds during the quake. He said the windows, desks, and
computer screens in the office built into the bridge shook.
   The quake was the second disaster to hit Australia during the
Christmas season. Last week, a bus crash claimed 36 lives, the
country's worst road crash.
   In London, Queen Elizabeth II offered sympathy to relatives of
the victims and said she was praying for rescuers searching for
trapped victims.
</TEXT>

</DOC>