<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0222EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Panama-Congress     12-21 0663</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Congress,660</SECOND>
<HEAD>Possible Lengthy Military Action in Panama Concerns Congress</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DONNA CASSATA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Members of Congress are tempering their
initial support of President Bush's decision to attack Gen. Manuel
Antonio Noriega's stronghold with concern about the ``renegade''
dictator's elusiveness and a possible long stay in Panama for U.S.
troops.
   ``I can see a scenario whereby the support for this operation
could turn difficult for the president,'' Rep. Les Aspin, D-Wis.,
chairman of the House Armed Services Committee, told reporters on
Wednesday.
   ``If there is a beginning, middle and end to American military
involvement it is far better than having this thing dragging out
over weeks and months,'' added Sen. Robert W. Kasten Jr., R-Wis.
   In the hours after American forces invaded Panama, lawmakers
from both parties endorsed Bush's action as the only option left to
remove suspected drug trafficker Noriega and establish a democratic
government.
   ``President Bush's actions were justified based on the changing
and alarming circumstances of recent weeks in Panama,'' said Sen.
Sam Nunn, D-Ga., chairman of the Senate Armed Services Committee.
   Sen. Richard Lugar, R-Ind., a senior Foreign Relations Committee
member, called the invasion ``an overwhelming success because
democracy has now been inaugurated and installed in Panama.''
   But as the day wore on with reports of Americans held captive
and Noriega still a fugitive, lawmakers hinted that the U.S.
action, dubbed ``Operation Just Cause,'' may prove problematic.
   ``Noriega continues to elude us and we don't know where he is
... plus the hostage situation, that's a very difficult hostage
situation, plus some kind of a continued American presence, loss of
life here and there, occasional sniper fire,'' Aspin said.
   Kasten, ranking Republican on the Senate Appropriations
subcommittee on foreign operations, stressed the importance of the
United States withdrawing its Army rangers and special forces as
quickly as possible.
   International public opinion in Latin America might well turn
against the United States if there is ``sustained fighting with
U.S. troops in uniform and Panamanian blood being spilled,'' Kasten
said.
   Sen. Charles Robb, D-Va., emerging from a classified briefing
conducted by Defense and State department officials, said, ``It's
fair to say the duration of the operation is of serious concern for
a good number of people.''
   But Sen. John Warner, R-Va., ranking minority member on the
Senate Armed Services Committee, cautioned against imposing a
schedule on troop withdrawal.
   ``I don't think we should try to impress a time line,'' Warner
said after the briefing.
   Aspin predicted that some U.S. forces will remain in Panama for
several months, possibly a year, shoring up the decimated
Panamanian Defense Forces, most of whom served as police, custom
inspectors or in some public safety capacity.
   The U.S. presence was likened to the situation in Grenada when
American MPs remained for several months after the invasion.
   In addition to the concern over the presence of U.S. forces,
lawmakers said interpretation of the Panamanian invasion as a major
achievement was complicated by Noriega, who remains at large.
   ``The fact that General Noriega is unaccounted for means that
the principle issue is unresolved,'' Robb said.
   ``Now it is our responsibility to track down the renegade
General Noriega and bring him to the United States, where he can be
tried and punished as the criminal he truly is,'' added Sen.
Christopher S. Bond, R-Mo.
   Aspin said he believes Bush will be ``under some political heat
if two, three days from now we still have not found Noriega and
captured him.'' The Wisconsin Democrat, however, cautioned against
judging the success of the operation on whether Noriega is captured.
   Other lawmakers questioned the invasion's impact on U.S.
relations with Central American nations.
   ``I am gravely concerned ... that this unilateral military
intervention may do long-term damage to our foreign policy, to our
ability to work with other nations in Latin America, and to our
goal of achieving lasting democracy in the region,'' said Sen.
Edward Kennedy, D-Mass., a member of the Senate Armed Services
Committee.
</TEXT>

</DOC>