<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0152EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-WashingtoninBrief     12-18 0599</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Washington in Brief,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bennett Calls Legalized Drug Supporters Indifferent to Minorities</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Federal anti-drug coordinator William Bennett
says the argument that drugs should be legalized is fed by
indifference to the fact that a large number of drug users are
minorities.
   ``I have to tell you I've heard in some circles, `Well, let them
kill each other,''' Bennett said Sunday on the ABC-TV program,
``This Week With David Brinkley.''
   ``That is not worthy of the American people,'' said Bennett. He
did not say who harbored that attitude.
   Bennett, director of the Office of National Drug Control Policy,
has been a vocal opponent of calls to legalize illicit drugs.
Advocates of legalization include Baltimore mayor Kurt L. Schmoke,
who is black, economist Milton Friedman, and U.S. District Judge
Robert Sweet, who last week became the first federal judge to
publicly voice such an opinion.
   Friedman and Sweet also appeared on the show, but did not
address Bennett's comments.
   Bennett made his remarks in response to a question by
conservative columnist George Will.
   ``Do you think if the people disproportionately killing
themselves off were white suburban high school students there would
be a different kind of argument going on?'' Will asked. ``I'm
asking is there a certain racial indifference in this argument?''
   ``I'm afraid there is,'' Bennett responded.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Mosbacher Says US Negotiating Controls With Hungary, Poland</NOTE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United States has begun negotiating with
Poland and Hungary in an effort to prevent diversion to the Soviet
Union of U.S. high-technology exports bound for those two East
European countries, says Commerce Secretary Robert Mosbacher.
   Mosbacher's remarks Sunday came a day after President Bush
signaled that his administration is ready to consider a major
relaxation of export controls with regard to Warsaw Pact nations.
   ``I think it is timely that we take a new look at the commercial
restraints,'' Bush said Saturday at a news conference on the
Caribbean island of St. Martin after meeting with French President
Francois Mitterrand.
   Mosbacher, appearing on NBC's ``Meet the Press'' program, was
asked about a pending request by the Control Data Corp. to sell
several high-powered computers to the Soviet Union.
   The commerce secretary responded that ``we'll have to look at
each item on a case-by-case basis.''
   ``We released middle technology and we're going to look to see
whether it should go higher than that,'' Mosbacher said. ``Eastern
European countries, yes; the Soviet Union, we'd have to be very
careful.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>World Bank Sees More Aid to East Europe</NOTE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The World Bank, the biggest source of aid to
the Third World, is planning new help to Eastern Europe but will
not reduce aid to developing countries, says bank Vice President
Stanley Fischer.
   ``As far as the World Bank is concerned, we don't see how
lending to Eastern Europe is going to detract from our lending to
Africa and Latin America,'' Fischer, the bank's top economist, said
at a news conference Friday.
   World Bank President Barber W. Conable said the bank had $350
million worth of loans prepared for projects in Poland and might
lend as much as $1 billion more in the coming year. So far Poland
has not had any loans from the bank.
   ``As Poland stabilizes, if it does, it's very likely that our
lending program will increase,'' Fischer said.
   Hungary got $345 million in loans, Yugoslavia $198 million and
China $1.3 billion in the year that ended June 30. There would have
been more for China, but Conable cut off new loans when Beijing
violently crushed the movement for more democracy last June.
</TEXT>

</DOC>