<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1205EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-DesegregatedSand Bjt   12-24 0686</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Desegregated Sand, Bjt,0711</SECOND>
<HEAD>After Years Of Protest, South African Beaches Open To All Races</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GREG MYRE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DURBAN, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Black and white children helped each
other build sandcastles. Their older brothers played soccer
together. White lifeguards shouted warnings in Zulu.
   After years of debate, protests and occasional violence, South
Africa has opened all its beaches to all races and buried one of
its most visible and resented apartheid practices.
   As recently as August, police used whips and dogs to keep blacks
off segregated sand. But at Durban's hotel-lined beachfront, the
busiest in the country, the attitude Sunday was swim and let swim.
   ``I preferred segregated beaches,'' said Charles Erasmus, a
vacationing white. ``But what am I going to do? Spite myself and
not go swimming? The law's been changed and we'll have to accept
it.''
   President F.W. de Klerk last month declared an end to
whites-only beaches, settling a conflict that arose every December
when hundreds of thousands of South Africans travel to the coast
for vacation.
   For authorities, opening the beaches has proved far easier than
keeping them segregated in the face of mounting black protest.
   Shortly before de Klerk's declaration, the Durban City Council
spent six hours debating whether to open the last remaining
stretches of segregated beach.
   Their solution: remove the embarrassing ``Whites Only'' signs
but keep the law in effect. Days after de Klerk's announcement, the
council voted 24-5 to integrate the beaches.
   Morris Fynn, a mixed-race man who was arrested several times for
cutting down ``Whites Only'' beach signs, ceremoniously buried his
saw in the sand to mark the formal death of beach apartheid.
   Three years ago, Allan Hendrickse, the first mixed-race member
of the Cabinet, invited reporters to watch him take a dip at a
whites-only beach at Port Elizabeth.
   One of his next public acts was to apologize for his swim after
being rebuked by then-President P.W. Botha.
   Anti-apartheid groups targeted beaches along with other
segregated facilities when they launched a nationwide defiance
campaign in August.
   When protesters arrived at a beach near Cape Town, it was
cordoned off and accompanied by signs saying, ``Police Dog Training
In Progress.''
   When the demonstrators proceeded, they were met with tear gas,
whips and police dogs. Several people were injured.
   Local authorites have complied with de Klerk's proclamation,
though under protest in some cases. But there have been no reports
of racial violence, or even serious overcrowding, since the beaches
were opened.
   ``Look, there are thousands of people here and no
confrontations,'' said Walter Buthelezi, 19, who was visiting the
beachfront with his sisters. ``There was never any need for
segregated beaches.''
   But Durban's Mayor Derrick Waterson disagrees.
   ``This wouldn't have happened easily five years ago.
Conservative whites weren't ready for it,'' he said.
   Waterson and his council have received more than 400 complaints
from whites. In the town of Mossel Bay, about 2,500 whites signed a
petition asking for a return to segregated beaches.
   Many whites insist they are not racist and say they want
separate beaches because of ``cultural differences.''
   Some blacks swim in their underwear and strip naked when washing
off under the shower nozzles at the beach, the whites complain.
   ``It's mostly older people that get offended, but when we talk
to the blacks they always cooperate,'' lifeguard Liam Halforty said.
   Halforty and his colleagues have been taking a crash course in
Zulu to help them communicate with black bathers. Roughly 15
percent of the beach crowd was black over the weekend,
traditionally one of the busiest of the year in Durban.
   ``I'm sure some whites stayed away,'' said Carol Cilliers. ``It
will take about two or three years before they will come back to
these beaches.''
   De Klerk has promised to remove all discriminatory laws, and
most so-called ``petty apartheid'' measures already have been
scrapped.
   The major remaining areas of segregation are public schools,
residential areas, and public hospitals. De Klerk has pledged to
keep these separate for whites who want them, and many do.
   ``Beaches are one thing, schools and neighborhoods are
another,'' said Leo Kotze, a vacationer.
</TEXT>

</DOC>