<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0100 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1516EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-BusinessInvestment     12-21 0444</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Business Investment,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>Capital Spending Increases Expected To Slow Next Year</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN D. McCLAIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   American businesses plan to boost capital
spending in 1990, but the rate of increase is only a little more
than half this year's and includes the first decline in
durable-goods investment since 1986, the government said Thursday.
   Analysts saw the report as more evidence of manufacturing
sluggishness.
   According to a Commerce Department survey completed in November,
spending on new plants and equipment will total $490.1 billion next
year, a 4.9 percent jump but less than the 8.5 percent increase in
1989 spending over that in 1988.
   The 4.9 percent rate of increase is the slowest since a 4.2
percent advance in 1987, the department said.
   The report, said Lawrence Chimerine, senior economic adviser for
the WEFA Group, a Bala Cynwyd, Pa., forecasting group, means
``capital spending is not going to be the contributing factor to
the economy in 1990, at least not like it was ... for much of
1989.''
   David Jones, an economist for Aubrey G. Lanston &amp; Co., New York,
said the survey ``reflects the pattern of weakness that is
concentrated in the manufacturing sector.''
   ``We've had weakness in manufacturing, particularly in autos,
but that's spreading now to computers, defense-related
industries,'' Jones said. ``And that's causing business to turn
more cautious.''
   In addition to a softness in orders for manufactured goods,
Chimerine said corporate debt also is a factor in the slowing of
capital spending.
   ``A lot of companies are paying a lot of interest to service
their debt,'' Chimerine said. ``It's squeezing profits ... so the
report is no surprise. They only question is, will it get much
weaker?''
   In the latest survey, manufacturing companies said they planned
a 1.4 percent increase in capital outlays to $182.8 billion,
compared with a 7.3 percent increase to $180.2 billion in 1989.
   This includes a 1.5 percent decrease in plants that produce
durable goods _ big-ticket items expected to last more than three
years _ and a 4.0 percent gain in companies producing non-durable
goods. The last decline in the durable-goods sector was a 6.7
percent drop in 1986.
   Durable-goods plants increased their investments 4.2 percent in
1989 and non-durable investments were up 10 percent.
   Companies engaged in mining, transportation and other
non-manufacturing ventures indicated they would increase spending
by 7.1 percent to $307.3 billion, compared with a gain of 9.2
percent to $286.9 billion this year.
   Before adjusting for inflation, 1990 plant and equipment
spending is expected to rise 6.4 percent to $505 billion in 1990.
The latest estimate for 1989 spending is $475 billion, 10.3 percent
more than in 1988.
</TEXT>

</DOC>