<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0197 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1848EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Czechoslovakia 1stLd-Writethru   12-20 0758</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Czechoslovakia, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0817,0784</SECOND>
<HEAD>Communist Party Apologizes for Past Abuses</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: LEADS with 5 grafs to UPDATE with election of new party chairman,
first secretary. Pickup 4th, `It also...;' SUBS grafs 19-21 pvs, `The most
... the nation' with four grafs to ADD Adamec comment, details. Pickup
22nd, `Communists must ...</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SYDNEY RUBIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Communist Party apologized
Wednesday for its hard-line policies of the past and for its abuse
of opponents after the 1968 crackdown on reform. Its leader said
the once omnipotent party is nearly bankrupt.
   At a key party congress, the party also elected to leadership
roles two men distinguished by their acceptance of the opposition,
including Ladislav Adamec, who initiated official negotiations with
opposition leader Vaclav Havel.
   Adamec, the former premier, was chosen party chairman. Vasil
Mohorita, former chairman of the Communist youth group and another
main figure in talks with the opposition, was elected first
secretary.
   The apology was the first of its kind to the Czechoslovak
people, who in the last month have come together in a peaceful
revolution that ended the Communists' monopoly on power.
   ``The Communist Party of Czechoslovakia apologizes to the
Czechoslovak people for its past policies,'' said Evzen Prusa, a
top party official who spoke on national television on the first
day of a the congress.
   ``It also apologizes for the events following 1968 and for
expelling and harassing the innocent,'' Prusa said.
   All the leaders installed after the crushing of the 1968
``Prague Spring'' reforms have been ousted from power the past
month, and the party recently condemned the Soviet-led invasion
that ended the Prague Spring.
   The party now is maneuvering to try to make the best showing
possible in free elections expected by July.
   In his opening address to the congress, party chief Karel
Urbanek lashed out at former and present party leaders for
``serious'' political mistakes that he said caused the party's fall
from power.
   Urbanek said that as a member of the ruling Politburo, he also
was to blame for allowing hated hard-liners to remain in the top
ranks.
   Urbanek said the ``party leadership manifested negligence and
irresponsibility worthy of punishment'' for not ousting officials
such as former Prague party boss Miroslav Stepan and others sooner.
   Stepan and former party boss Milos Jakes were accused of being
politically responsible for a brutal police crackdown on peaceful
student demonstrations Nov. 17 that ignited the popular revolution.
   Leaving Stepan on the Politburo was ``an extraordinary,
politically serious mistake,'' Urbanek said.
   Stepan and Jakes have since been forced from power.
   They denied accusations by a parliamentary commission that they
were responsible for the November brutality.
   Urbanek said the party faces bankruptcy, disclosing that party
dues were used to build recreation facilties for top brass ``about
which the rank-and-file only learned today.''
   Detailing the crisis facing the party, Urbanek noted that it had
lost 66,290 of its 1.7 million members in the last month.
   About 1,000 new members have joined, including 143 people purged
from the party after the 1968 invasion who were recently
rehabilitated, he said.
   The speech confirmed the total disarray in which the party finds
itself following the triumphs of the pro-democracy movement.
   ``I'm aware things won't be easy in the future,'' Adamec told
the delegates in his acceptance speech, adding that he took the job
out of a feeling of responsibility to correct past mistakes.
   Adamec resigned as premier this month after failing to form a
government acceptable to the opposition.
   As party chairman, he is responsible for external party policy,
including dealing with other political forces. Mohorita, the first
secretary, handles internal policy and administration.
   Lubos Belka, representing the reform Communist Democratic Forum
at the congress, asked party leaders to renounce their privileges
``so Communists can regain the lost trust of the nation.''
   ``Communists must no longer work in velvet chairs, but must
return to where they came from,'' he said.
   It was not known how many delegates at the congress support the
reform movement.
   But a spokesman for Democratic Forum indicated during a news
conference that the congress seemed about evenly split between
hard-liners and reformers.
   About 40 delegates from the reformist group were invited to
attend the congress as non-voting guests.
   Democratic Forum spokesman Rudolf Prevratil told the official
CTK news agency his group was not allowed to participate in
discussions and charged they had been invited to give the
impression of democracy within the party.
   Also among the non-voting guests were former party members
expelled in the wake of the 1968 invasion.
</TEXT>

</DOC>