<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0139 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1457EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Panama 8thLd-Writethru   12-22 1178</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama, 8th Ld-Writethru,a0699,1212</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Site of U.S. Southern Command Attacked</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 9 grasf to UPDATE with assassination attempt on vice
president. Pickup 6th pvs, `Elsewhere, the...' Minor editing of last 11
grafs to trim, conform.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos DOD9,11-14; WX50; LaserColor PAN4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fighters loyal to Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noriega attacked Quarry Heights, site of the U.S. military's
Southern Command today. Assailants tried to assassinate the
U.S.-installed vice president, Ricardo Arias Calderon.
   Members of pro-Noriega Dignity Battalions opened fire on Arias'
car shortly after he left the National Assembly building, according
to Arias aide Teni de Obaldia.
   De Obaldia, reached at Arias' home by telephone, said Arias
wasn't injured but that two of his aides were wounded. He said
Arias was with the wounded aides at Gorgas Hospital, a U.S.
military hospital near Southern Command headquarters.
   Arias was installed as first vice president shortly after the
U.S. attack on Panama began at midnight Tuesday. He was declared a
winner in elections in May that Noriega, the military dictator,
declared null.
   Fighting was heavy for about an hour around the Southern Command
center, which controls all U.S. forces in South and Central America.
   Mortars were launched from railroad tracks below Southern
Command headquarters at Quarry Heights, overlooking Panama City, at
about 11:25 a.m. Snipers were reported in the hills above, and the
sound of helicopters and machine-gun fire could be heard overhead.
   U.S. military officials and journalists took cover under tables
as the building they were in shook.
   Witnesses in the area said the target of the attack appeared to
be two U.S.-occupied Panamanian government buildings below Quarry
Heights. About a dozen pro-Noriega men attacked U.S. soldiers at
the secret police headquarters and the building that houses
Panama's transportation department, the witnesses said by telephone.
   By 12:30, fighting had died down.
   Elsewhere, the Panamanian Defense Forces barracks in the western
city of David, 200 miles west of Panama City, raised white flags
and surrendered this morning, residents of that city said by
telephone.
   U.S. troops battled stubborn bands of Panamanian fighters in the
chaotic capital, where fighting intensified late Thursday as U.S.
warplanes bombed enemy positions.
   On the third day of what was originally planned as a three-day
operation, President Bush told Congress he could not predict how
long it would last. U.S. military commander Jim Snell said it could
take months to clear the capital of Noriega loyalists and weapons.
   But this morning, some remaining pockets of resistance appeared
resigned to defeat.
   ``It's clear that the gringos are in control of everything. We
don't have the strength they have. We don't have any guidelines. We
don't know where Noriega, our commander, is,'' said a pro-Noriega
municipal official at the Tinajitas barracks in the northeastern
neighborhood of San Miguelito.
   The official, who refused to give his name, said supporters of
the elusive Noriega had run out of munitions and could provide no
resistance when U.S. troops rumbled into the neighborhood Thursday
night.
   Panamanian forces who had controlled several posts along the
Costa Rican border in the province of Chiriqui fled today after
rumors spread that U.S. troops were on their way, said Juan
Barrantes, a Costa Rican border official.
   In Washington, the Organization of American States this morning
``deeply deplored'' the invasion, which has killed 22 Americans,
and called for withdrawal of U.S. forces. The resolution was
approved on a 20-to-1 vote with the United States voting against it
and six members abstaining.
   Three Americans were missing, and Noriega's whereabouts was a
mystery. U.S. soldiers were too busy with snipers, and
house-to-house searches to challenge looters who had helped
themselves to everything from designer underwear to gleaming BMWs.
   ``There are pockets of stiff resistance in the city,'' U.S.
Embassy spokeswoman Jan Edmonson said today by telephone. ``And
also there's just the great element of fear. These people are going
through parts of the city in just mobs, breaking windows, entering
private homes, looting at will.''
   The newly installed U.S.-backed president, Guillermo Endara,
admitted in an interview on ABC's ``Good Morning America'' today
that he cannot safely walk the streets but claimed he had the
``wholehearted support'' of the people.
   ``We would need twice as many soldiers if we were to take over
every small garrison in this country,'' a U.S. Army officer said,
on condition of anonymity.
   Spurred by a $1 million bounty offered by President Bush for
Noriega's arrest, Panamanians reported sightings of the general
throughout the capital.
   There were rumors he was holding out at the Tinajitas garrison,
in northeastern Panama City. One Israeli television report said the
general was spotted on the resort island of Contadora, 40 miles off
the Pacific coast. It said he was preparing to escape to Nicaragua.
   U.S. soldiers who stormed the ``Witch House'' on Wednesday, one
of Noriega's residences, found cigarettes smoldering and believe
they missed the Panamanian fugitive by minutes, military sources
say.
   The Witch House was filled with black magic paraphernalia, and
another of the ousted dictator's quarters was decorated with
portraits of Adolf Hitler, American servicemen told reporters
Thursday.
   There was no word on the whereabouts of most of the members of
Noriega's general staff, although a U.S. Army source confirmed that
Noriega's brother-in-law, Lt. Col. Aquilino Sieiro, had surrendered.
   The U.S. Army announced it had 1,500 prisoners of war, mostly
members of the Panamanian Defense Forces.
   Bush pledged Thursday that U.S. forces would scour Panama ``as
long as it takes'' to capture Noriega, who was indicted in the
United States in 1988 on federal charges of trafficking in
Colombian cocaine and money laundering.
   In a message today to Congress, Bush said: ``Although most
organized opposition has ceased, it is not possible at this time to
predict the precise scope and duration of the military operations
or how long the temporary increases of U.S. forces in Panama will
be required.''
   Bush said he had sent 11,000 U.S. troops to back up the 13,000
already here. U.S. officials previously said they hoped the action
could be completed in three days.
   Pentagon officials today reported 22 Americans killed, including
two civilian women, 202 wounded and two military men missing. It
said 122 Panamanians were killed and 45 wounded.
   CBS news producer Jon Meyersohn, abducted by Panamanian gunmen
from the Marriott lobby Wednesday, also was missing today.
   An official in the office of Leonardo Diaz, medical director of
the Santo Tomas Hospital, said the hospital had taken in 80 dead
and more than 1,000 wounded.
   ``The morgue is now full. We have no place to put the dead,''
the official said, refusing to give her name.
   The dead included a Spanish photographer caught in cross fire
between U.S. troops who mistook each other for Panamanian forces in
the Marriott Hotel parking lot.
   Looters had a field day Thursday, sacking vendors of everything
despite a curfew ordered by Endara, sworn in by a Panamanian judge
minutes before the invasion began at midnight Tuesday.
   Endara and Arias were declared winners in presidential elections
in May, but Noriega nullified the results.
</TEXT>

</DOC>