<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0151 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1452EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--Trekkies Adv07   12-26 0937</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Trekkies, Adv 07,0967</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv07</HEAD>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Jan. 7</HEAD>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<HEAD>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 1 b&amp;w photo.
ColorFoto subscribers get 1 35mm slide.)</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Three ``Trekkies'' who began operating out of a
basement in Colorado have found there's money to be made in fan
magazines and movie memorabilia. They're cashing in on the
popularity of such TV and big screen hits as ``Star Trek,'' ``Star
Wars'' and ``Back to the Future.''
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By SCOTT MAXWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AURORA, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three high school buddies who started a
modest newsletter for fellow ``Star Trek'' fans a decade ago are
now managing a multimillion-dollar nationwide enterprise.
   Star Trek: The Official Fan Club is the creation of Dan Madsen,
John Davis and Robert Allan, who were drawn together by a common
fascination with anything to do with ``Star Trek,'' the television
series that inspired subsequent movies.
   The club, today just part of the men's enterprise called Fan
Clubs Inc., was inspired by the release of ``Star Trek: The Motion
Picture'' in 1979. Madsen, now president of Fan Clubs Inc. and
publisher of the club's magazines, began putting out a small,
photocopied newsletter for fellow ``Trekkies.''
   ``We ran the thing out of my basement,'' Madsen says. ``You
know, there were posters and all kinds of `Star Trek' stuff on the
walls.''
   Madsen began with 15 subscribers to his newsletter. Today,
35,000 people subscribe to the ``Star Trek'' fan magazine.
   Their club is licensed by Paramount Pictures as the only
official ``Star Trek'' fan club. Fan Clubs Inc. also operates fan
clubs for ``Back to the Future'' and Lucasfilms, the movie company
of George Lucas, producer of ``Star Wars'' and ``American
Graffiti.'' Headquarters is a nondescript building in an Aurora
business park.
   Allan estimates that fan club magazine sales will account for
about 50 percent of the $1 million the company will earn this year,
up from $400 in earnings just three years ago. He says that besides
the 35,000 subscribers to the ``Star Trek'' magazine, the company's
Lucasfilms magazine has about 15,000 readers. The inaugural issue
of the ``Back to the Future'' fan club magazine should have about
16,000 readers.
   The men have high hopes for the ``Back to the Future'' magazine
because of the release of the movie ``Back to the Future II'' over
the Thanksgiving weekend.
   The magazines are slick, four-color publications averaging 25
pages. They feature interviews with stars, letters to the editor,
behind-the-scenes looks at the technical wizardry and special
effects of the movies and a list of upcoming conventions and
events. They also contain order forms for merchandise and
classified advertisements for members who want to buy, sell, trade
and swap.
   Allan says the magazines boast impressive renewal rates.
   ``Big magazines like Time and Newsweek are happy if they get a
15 percent renewal rate,'' he said. ``Back when we had 5,000
subscribers, we had a 95 percent renewal rate. Now, with 60,000
subscribers, we have a 70 percent renewal rate. That's nothing to
laugh at.''
   The company also markets movie memorabilia, such as ``Star
Trek'' mugs and action figures and Indiana Jones fedoras.
Merchandise sales have shot up from nothing two years ago to about
$500,000 this year, the entrepreneurs say.
   Allan says fan club members include lawyers, 4-year-olds,
grandmothers and priests. Schools and libraries subscribe as well.
   The three men initially took some ribbing from friends and
relatives who were skeptical of the fan club's potential, but they
learned the necessary skills to make it a success.
   Madsen worked in a print shop, where he learned how to lay out
and design the newsletters. Davis got a college degree in English,
and Allan worked as a waiter to make ends meet.
   Soon after they began marketing merchandise in 1982, Paramount
Pictures contacted them.
   ``They were concerned at first because we were operating and
handling merchandise without a license,'' Madsen says. ``But they
saw our newsletter and they were fairly impressed. So we signed a
contract with them. They thought it had the right amount of
fanaticism and the right amount of professionalism they were
looking for.''
   Madsen, Davis and Allan have since traveled around the world to
meet and interview the stars of the movies and series they write
about. The license gives them exclusive rights to interviews and
photographs and allows them to sell officially licensed merchandise.
   The three admit that Aurora isn't exactly where one might expect
to find the official ``Star Trek'' fan club, but Davis says the
location makes sense.
   ``Well, we live here, for one thing,'' he said. ``And Denver is
one of the hottest markets for `Star Trek' in the country. We can
do just as good a job from Aurora as we could from California or
New York. We do a lot of phone interviews and travel when we have
to.''
   Allan says their respective interests may eventually take them
to new frontiers.
   ``We're looking at expanding into rock fan clubs and celebrity
fan clubs,'' he says.
   Madsen says there may still be other prospects on the horizon.
   ``We're looking at films,'' he says. ``John has considered
writing for movies or episodic television, and I've always thought
about being a director. We'd like to make our own movie
eventually.''
   Madsen says a genuine interest is what has made their efforts
successful.
   ``Everything we've done so far was because we were fans of it.
We're interested in what we're doing,'' he said.
   ``It isn't just a business.''
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Eds: The address is: Fan Clubs Inc., P.O. Box 111000, Aurora, CO
80011
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>

</DOC>