<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1341EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Reconstruction Bjt   12-27 0843</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Reconstruction, Bjt,0865</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ceausescu's Fall Began With Action Against Clergyman</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MORT ROSENBLUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nicolae Ceausescu made the first of
his final mistakes when he tried to deport the Rev. Laszlo Toekes,
a popular pastor of Hungarian heritage who spoke his mind from the
pulpit in Timisoara.
   Romania's durable dictator did not like Hungarians, and a
rambunctious community of ethnic Hungarians challenged his control.
Toekes, articulate and courageous, amounted to a dissident.
   On Friday, Dec. 15, youths in the city about 300 miles west of
Bucharest formed a human chain to shield him from police and
prevent his arrest. They were dispersed with tear gas and water
cannons, but even larger crowds gathered at the cathedral the next
day.
   Crowds again formed on Sunday _ more raucous and threatening _
but still peaceable. Local officials, fearing wrath from the
Ceausescu if things got out of hand, ordered heavy repression.
   Security forces drove assault vehicles into the crowd, and they
opened fire. Innocent protesters died in their friends' arms. So
did children. No one knew the death toll, but word began to spread
around the world.
   Then Ceausescu made another mistake. He ignored the explosive
situation and left on a three-day trip to Iran. Authorities had to
use their own judgment, with only the dictator's iron-willed wife,
Elena, to guide them.
   Because the world had gotten word of what was happening in
Romania, even other Romanians _ for a change _ were informed.
Foreign radio broadcasts, including those from neighboring Hungary,
echoed the news to Bucharest, the capital, and spurred protesters
in Timisoara.
   Despite the violent repression, demonstrators came back, and the
guns fired again. Killings were mostly by the hated Securitate, a
secret police and elite guard fiercely loyal to Ceausescu. But the
army helped subdue protesers.
   What should have been crowd control was a chilling example of
the ruthless terror Ceausescu had applied to keep his increasingly
extravagant personal regime in place: a protest of one man's
impending arrest was suddenly a release for years of pent-up hatred.
   By Thursday, Ceausescu was back in Bucharest, facing the worst
crisis in 24 years of power. That's when he made another mistake.
   Yet again, Ceausescu summoned his masses for a spontaneous
outburst of their warmth and loyalty. At a huge rally, he harangued
them with the old slogans. If students were unhappy, he would raise
their allowances a little. Some subsidies would be increased.
   As for Timisoara, he said, it was the work of ``hooligan
elements,'' and ``external meddlers.''
   Most of the crowd had to be there, and their future in
Ceausescu's society depended upon how earnestly they cheered. But
one group of young people, mostly students, had heard those
Stalinist formulas once too often.
   They whistled and booed Ceausescu to silence, demanding an
explanation for the events in Timisoara. The live TV and radio
broadcast was cut for several minutes to spare the dictator further
embarrassment.
   Ceausescu's face showed disbelief as he plowed on. But he had
lost the crowd. Obedient applause was drowned out by cries of
``Death! Death!'' and ``Down with Ceausescu!''
   When the shaken dictator finished, students staged their own
rally. They snaked through Bucharest streets, picking up in number
and staying slightly ahead of the water cannons. At nightfall,
thousands had assembled around University Square.
   Sometime during the night, the secret police went for blood.
Light tanks crashed into the crowd. Marksmen atop buildings shot
people in the back. Covered trucks carried the bodies to secret
graves.
   But the students came back the next morning, on Friday. Army
tanks rolled up to face them. But they did not fire. Instead,
students stuck Christmas tree branches down their rifle barrels,
and soldiers smiled shyly, in sympathy with the crowd.
   Ceausescu's media pressed on in his service. At 11 a.m., the
television announced that Defense Minister Vasile Milea committed
suicide because he was found to be a traitor. Quickly, word spread
that he was shot for not ordering repressive fire.
   A small delegation walked to the Communists' Central Committee
building and persuaded the army to join the people.
   Ceausescu finally got the message. He and his wife took a
helicopter to a government airbase 30 miles north but could not
arrange a safe haven in another country. They headed north in a
small car, humbled and on the run, until they were captured.
   For days afterward, secret police diehards fought urban
guerrilla warfare to take back the capital. The Central Committee
building and the elegant palace nearby was bombed out and burned.
Many thousands of Romanians had to be buried.
   Nicolae and Elena Ceausescu were tried by a secret military
tribunal. He animatedly argued that the charges against him were
lies, that he ordered no killings, that he and his wife lived as
ordinary Romanians.
   But he made no apparent admission of the mistakes he made. He
and his wife were convicted of grave crimes against Romania, put up
against a concrete wall and executed by three riflemen chosen from
among hundreds who volunteered.
</TEXT>

</DOC>