<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0122 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 2243EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Pizza-Accidents     12-30 0312</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pizza-Accidents,0320</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lawyer: Domino's Pizza Driver Calls Boss After Wreck to Make Delivery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TAMPA, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Domino's Pizza driver who hit another
motorist while making a delivery called his boss and had him come
and get the pie to meet the company's 30-minute guarantee, a lawyer
claims in a negligence lawsuit.
   Ramon Rigal says he suffered back injuries and a concussion when
his Chevrolet Blazer, which was stopped for a turn, was struck from
behind by a Volkswagen driven by a 19-year-old Domino's delivery
man. Police say the April accident caused $9,000 damage to the two
cars.
   ``After the crash, the pizza man calls his boss, who shows up to
take the handoff of the pizza and finish the delivery,'' attorney
Paul Nelson said in an interview Friday.
   The Rigals ``are out there waiting for the paramedics to come,
and all they do is hand off this pizza,'' Nelson said, blaming the
accident on Domino's policy of guaranteeing pizza delivery in 30
minutes or giving customers $3 off their bill.
   Rigal, a commercial artist, is unable to work and on the verge
of bankruptcy, Nelson said. The amount of damages Rigal is seeking
wasn't specified.
   Domino's refused to comment on the lawsuit, which was filed in
Hillsborough Circuit Court last month.
   The lawsuit is the latest in a series of actions blaming a
traffic accident on a Domino's delivery driver rushing to meet the
half-hour deadline. Seven such lawsuits have been filed against the
pizza maker in the last two years in Hillsborough County, and four
have been filed in the last few years in Pinellas Circuit Court in
neighboring St. Petersburg.
   Ron Hingst, director of public relations for Domino's,
emphasizes that drivers aren't penalized if they take longer than
30 minutes. ``The $3 doesn't come out of the driver's pocket; it's
built into the budget of each store.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>