<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0194 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1857EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s f BC-PersonalFile-Long Adv31   12-27 0985</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Personal File-Long, Adv 31,1015</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Sunday Dec. 31</HEAD>
<HEAD>Venerable Bank Boss Known For Leading Pack in Cutting Interest Rates</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ED SCHAFER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At an age when most men would consider waking
up in the morning an accomplishment, Isaac A. Long gets his kicks
by creating headlines in financial publications around the world.
   The 90-year-old chairman emeritus of Southwest Bank of St. Louis
has made a career out of taking the lead in cutting the prime
lending rate and watching other banks follow in his tracks.
   Until Nov. 8, Long was batting .900 as a bellwether. But other
banks didn't match him that time and he became news because
Southwest had to backtrack three weeks later and readjust its prime
from 10 percent to 10.5 percent.
   Considering that it was the first time in at least 10 years that
he has had to retreat, Long took it well.
   ``We're still batting about .875,'' he said. ``That's still a
pretty good average.''
   In fact, Long said, the move was well worth it.
   ``What we really did was give our commercial customers a
Christmas bonus a little early,'' he said. ``We feel it was an
excellent investment from an advertising and public relations
standpoint.''
   The prime rate is important because it is used by many banks as
a basis for determining rates on a wide range of other loans,
including highly popular home-equity loans. A drop in the prime
would be followed by lower interest rates for loans to consumers
and small businesses.
   Speculation has persisted in the past few weeks that banks would
cut the prime rate because their own borrowing costs have declined,
a result of recent credit-easing moves by the Federal Reserve, the
nation's central bank, to forestall an economic downturn. As of
this past week, however, neither Long's bank nor any other appeared
willing to lower the prime rate.
   Using the year 1989 as an example of Long's influence on the
banking industry, the prime rate rested at 11.5 percent until
Friday, June 2.
   That's when Long announced Southwest was dropping its prime to
11 percent. On Monday, the next work day, all the major banks in
the country followed.
   On Friday, July 7, Long again rattled the industry's chains and
dropped his prime to 10.5 percent. The following Monday, only New
York's Chase Manhattan Bank followed Southwest's lead. It wasn't
until the 29th that Bank of America joined them and it was two more
days before the other big banks fell into step.
   Then came Nov. 8 and the cut that separated Southwest from the
rest of the pack.
   ``I.A. Long sort of hung himself out there to dry,'' said Ray
Worseck, chief economist at A.G. Edwards &amp; Son, Inc. a St. Louis
investment firm. ``I think the optimists got a little bit ahead of
themselves on this.''
   Long said one of the reasons he erred was the difficulty in
interpreting the behavior of the Federal Reserve, which
historically has acted with great secrecy in order to keep
financial markets stable.
   But the nation's central bank can send subtle signals about its
possible intentions, partly by control over the amount of money
available to lend. That control sometimes can be seen in the
behavior of the federal funds rate, the interest on overnight loans
between banks.
   The rate had fallen below 8.5 percent in November, convincing
Long that the Fed was easing and it was time for a prime-rate cut.
Then the Fed appeared to suddenly reverse itself and the federal
funds rate rose to 8.75 on Nov. 28, forcing Long to backtrack.
   Some New York bankers may have enjoyed seeing Long with egg on
his face, but the old veteran says his aim, ever since he began his
rate crusade in the 1970s, has never been to make the big banks
look bad.
   ``Our policy, our ambition, is not to upstage the New York
banks,'' Long said. ``Our customers are very appreciative of the
fact that they don't have to wait for what banks in New York or
Chicago do. We make our own decisions.''
   Those decisions, he said, are based on lengthy analysis. He said
Southwest looks at trends rather than specific economic indicators
and he said he prefers to look at a six month period.
   Long broke into banking with the Royal Bank of Canada in New
York in 1920. After organizing the first branch bank in Virginia in
1922, he came to the National Bank of Commerce in St. Louis in 1927
and has never left the area.
   Named president of Southwest Bank in 1953, Long soon became its
largest stockholder. He often is called Col. Long, a title that has
stuck since he served a term as chairman of the St. Louis Police
Board.
   ``The bank has had the same location and the same name for 69
years,'' said Long. The bank's president, Edward C. Berra, and a
vice chairman, Fred A. Giacoma, were both hired by Long 29 years
ago. Long finally sold controlling interest in the institution in
1984.
   ``I think it's interesting that every time we get in the news
for being a national leader they call us `a small bank,''' Long
said. ``But if you look at the figres, we're in the top 5 percent
nationally and we're the largest independent bank in Missouri.''
   As chairman emeritus, Long isn't involved in day-to-day
operations of the bank, but he remains active and is considered an
authority on interest rates.
   ``I enjoy being here every day, keeping in touch with what's
going on,'' he said. ``It's really a lot of fun. I attribute my
longivity to having steady employment and my wife of 51 years.''
   As for retirement, Long said, ``I haven't given it a thought.
I'll worry about it when I get closer to retirement age.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End adv for Sunday Dec. 31.</NOTE>

</DOC>