<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0819EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Poland 1stLd-Writethru a0436 12-18 0981</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Poland, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0436,1010</SECOND>
<HEAD>Debate Resumes On Market System As Economic Shock Treatment</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with Parliament debate resuming
today, PAP reax on Sunday debate. Picks up 3rd graf `The Warsaw Pact...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DANISZEWSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Parliament today debated on a wide-ranging
package to transform the state-run economy to a market system,
taking up first the government budget that cuts off public
subsidies for most goods and services.
   The deputies in the Sejm, the lower house of Parliament, met for
12 hours Sunday and returned to work this morning, with a further
session planned Tuesday and possibly Wednesday.
   The reform package proposed by the Solidarity-led government
will be the most radical economic reform ever attempted in the East
bloc _ and massive unemployment and steep price increases are
initially expected as state subsidies to industry end, forcing
unprofitable enterprises to close.
   Summing up the first phase of debate, the official PAP news
agency commented: ``Concern voiced in each of over 100 questions
asked the government can be boiled down to one question: How will
individual citizens, families, social and professional groups and
economic units `survive' the period of changes?''
   The Warsaw Pact country whose people led the way in forcing an
end to four decades of Communist domination now faces the daunting
task of rebuilding a wrecked economy from the ground up.
   Finance Minister Leszek Balcerowicz announced the program to a
special Sunday session of the Sejm, asking that it be approved in
time to be implemented Jan. 1.
   He said Poland must leave behind a system ``based on
19th-century doctrines'' and embrace one ``based on market
mechanisms ... where skills, knowledge, able hands, talent and
willingness to work all count.''
   Balcerowicz, who is also deputy prime minister, said the new
course would ``open new perspectives of proper living, free
development and fruitful and satisfying work.''
   It will be the biggest test of public support to date for a
government formed in September after Solidarity-backed candidates
trounced Communists in spring elections.
   The plan, backed by Solidarity leader Lech Walesa, is expected
to meet some opposition from Communist lawmakers and some in the
Solidarity bloc, whose industrial worker constituency will be hard
hit.
   With Prime Minister Tadeusz Mazowiecki, the East bloc's first
non-Communist head of government, somberly looking on, Balcerowicz
outlined a virtual dismantling 45 years of Marxist-Leninist
economic policy.
   The plan includes:
   _Instantly balancing the deficit-ridden state budget through
strict austerity.
   _Cutting off most state subsidies to businesses and
institutions, including the Communist Party.
   _Freeing prices.
   _Limiting wage increases.
   _Turning the zloty into a convertible currency, probably in
January or February.
   _Attacking monopolies and beginning an orderly selloff of state
industries to the private sector, probably in phases next year.
   _Reforming the banking and tax systems.
   _Establishing a social safety net for the poor and jobless,
whose ranks are expected to swell as a result of the new measures.
   Referring to the drop in output and inflation of 900 percent
that have rocked the Polish economy this year, Balcerowicz conceded
Poland is launching its reform in ``extremely unfavorable
conditions.''
   The program meets requirements laid down by the International
Monetary Fund, which demanded fundamental reforms before it would
authorize any loans to Poland.
   IMF head Michel Camdessus has said a letter of intent for a $700
million standby loan agreement with Poland will be signed in the
near future.
   That, in turn, will open the way to up to $3.5 billion in
additional loans and liberal rescheduling of Poland's $40 billion
foreign debt by Western nations, which have lined up in recent
months to back Poland in its turn toward democracy.
   Public support of Mazowiecki's government has allowed him to ask
the public to make public sacrifices that would have provoked
massive unrest under the Communists.
   Under the plan, subsidies for goods and services, which last
year ate up 31 percent of public spending, will be reduced to 14
percent. Subsidies will remain, at lower levels, in only a few
areas: for housing, public transport, coal, bread and low-fat milk
and cheese.
   Price increases in the range of 25 percent to 50 percent a month
are expected in the first stage of the program, as enterprises lose
their subsidies and raise prices to survive.
   Coal and energy prices alone are expected to up to sevenfold and
enough companies will be forced to cease operating that the economy
of this country of 38 million people may face an army of 400,000
unemployed, officials have said.
   The price increases and the limits on government spending and
wage increases will cut real incomes by 20 percent next year, with
a projected 5 percent decrease in industrial output and a 2 percent
to 3 percent dropoff in the gross national product.
   But the government-induced recession should squeeze inflation
down to a few percent a month by mid-1990, planners say.
   ``All the vested interests are against (the plan),'' Foreign
Trade Minister Marcin Swiecicki, one of four Communists in the
government, said after Balcerowicz's speech. ``But it will get
through.''
   In one provision that strikes at the old power structure,
political and social organizations like the Communist Party _ which
previously got billions of zlotys from the state Treasury _ will no
longer receive public funds and will be forced to rely on their
supporters and enterprise to raise money.
   But the most sensitive aspect of the program is whether the
public at large, already struggling after a decade of inflation,
lack of consumer goods, stagnant growth and failed reform programs,
can survive a new bout of price increases coupled with the new
threat of poverty and joblessless.
   The finance minister emphasized that the government would be
providing inflation-indexed aid to the weakest members of society:
retirees, the disabled, low-income families and displaced workers.
   ``Nobody should feel his existence is endangered,'' Balcerowicz
said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>