<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1055EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Storms-ColdRdp 1stLd-Writethru a0468 12-18 0729</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Storms-Cold Rdp, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0468,0748</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cold Siege Continues: Snow in South, Homeless Suffer</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 14 grafs to UPDATE with more records falling, two
girls dying in Tulsa, fatalities rising from eighto nine, train passengers
stranded in Chicago; PICKS UP 13th graf, `For the ...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto AU1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GARTIES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation's cold siege lobbed light snow and sleet at the Deep
South today after a weekend of freezing temperatures that chased
the homeless into shelters and brought early snow for skiers.
   Temperatures far below normal were again the order of the day
across much of the country, and snow was expected from the Rockies
across the Plains and into the Great Lakes region. Sleet or
freezing rain fell in Atlanta, Charleston, S.C., and Macon, Ga.,
and snow was forecast from northern Texas through Alabama.
   Forecasters said there's no end in sight to the chill that's
camped over much of the country for several days.
   Winter doesn't begin until Thursday, but today's highs were
expected to remain below zero in the upper Plains, the teens in the
Rockies and the 20s in an arc from Washington through the Texas
Panhandle, the Midwest and New England.
   ``It might not be that unusual if it was the middle of January
... but everyone agrees this is indeed atypical,'' said weather
service meteorologist Edward Yandrich in New York. ``In layman's
terms, it's just been very, very cold.''
   Temperature records fell Sunday in at least 19 cities, among
them: Cincinnati, minus 9; Cleveland, minus 7; Elkins, W.Va., minus
8; Paducah, Ky., and Indianpolis, minus 10.
   Today, records that had held firm for more than a century fell
in Columbus, Ohio, where it was minus 7; in Pittsburgh, where it
also was 7 below, and in Detroit, where it was minus 3.
   Cincinnati set another record for the date, at 3 below, as did
Cleveland, minus 5; Youngstown, Ohio, 8 below; and Charleston,
W.V., 2 above.
   In Tulsa, Okla, where Sunday's high was 30, two girls died after
falling into an ice-covered lake. Authorities said the girls, ages
9 and 12, apparently were sliding on a plastic tray when the ice,
which was only 1 to 2 inches thick, gave way.
   The homeless, ineffectually bundled up against the chill, were
urged to crowd into shelters.
   In Philadelphia, outreach workers scoured streets through the
weekend as temperatures dipped to 17. A transient woman was found
dead of exposure on a downtown bench Saturday, authorities said.
   About 30 homeless people spent Sunday huddled around bonfires
kindled in trash cans in New York City's Tompkins Square Park after
a judge reversed an earlier edict banning the blazes. The city
sought to outlaw the fires as dangerous.
   An exposure death was reported in Baltimore, and nationwide, at
least nine traffic deaths have been blamed on the weather since
Friday. Faulty space heaters may share the blame for a spate of
house and apartment fires that claimed six lives over the weekend
in Chicago, firefighters said.
   As many as 3,000 rail passengers were stranded for up to 4{
hours at Chicago's Union Station when rail switches froze.
   For the more fortunate, the pre-holiday chill got the ski season
off to a fast start. Several inches of fresh powder attracted
skiers to the slopes in New York and New England.
   In the West, the snow was deeper.
   Two to 5 feet of snow has fallen in Colorado during the past
week, building a 59-inch snow base at the Steamboat Springs ski
resort.
   ``It's good powder skiing _ soft powder skiing,'' said Coloradan
Joe Puchek, who was skiing at Copper Mountain.
   Two dozen avalanches were reported in the backcountry north of
Interstate 70 in the 24 hours ending Saturday, according to the
Colorado Avalanche Information Center.
   Twenty-five inches of snow fell this weekend in Syracuse, N.Y.,
within an inch of the average snowfall for the entire month of
December.
   None of this deterred America's dedicated joggers.
   About 500 runners braved 10-degree temperatures Sunday to
compete in a 10- kilometer race along the soon-to-be-opened
North-South Tollway in DuPage County west of Chicago.
   And in New York's Central Park, 1,200 turned out for a
30-kilometer race with temperatures in the mid-20s.
   Park jogger Peter Apostolicas, 32, said his cotton and nylon
clothing was proof against the chill. ``Once you get going it's
fine,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>