<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0651EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Japan-H-Bomb     12-28 0530</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Japan-H-Bomb,0543</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tokyo Closes Book on U.S. H-Bomb Lost off Japanese Coast</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LARRY THORSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Japanese government said today it was dropping
its inquiry into the U.S. hydrogen bomb lost at sea 24 years ago
off the coast of Japan.
   The U.S. Defense Department had said further queries on the
accident could endanger U.S. military policy.
   ``The Japanese government understands the U.S. position and has
no intention of making further requests of it,'' Kyodo News Service
quoted an unidentified Foreign Ministry official as saying today.
   The case embarrassed both governments _ Japan because it bans
nuclear arms but appeared to have turned a blind eye to passage of
such weapons through its waters, and the United States because its
policy of not commenting on the location of such weapons came under
new scrutiny.
   In 1965, a U.S. Navy A-4 Skyhawk accidentally rolled off the
carrier Ticonderoga bearing a one-megaton H-bomb. The pilot died,
and the bomb sank in waters 16,000 feet deep.
   The incident was kept secret until 1981, when the Navy said it
had occurred 500 miles from land.
   But in May it was disclosed that the bomb had sunk about 80
miles from a Japanese island in the Okinawa group.
   Under pressure from the opposition Socialist Party and other
anti-nuclear groups, the Japanese government insisted that
Washington explain what had happened. Scientists tested the waters
near the site for signs of radioactive pollution from the bomb's 33
pounds of plutonium. No radiation was found, the government said.
   The Pentagon has assured Japan that scientists had conducted
experiments and determined that the bomb had been crushed by water
pressure and its nuclear material would have dissolved. It was not
armed when it went into the sea, the Pentagon said, and it could
not explode.
   Japan is the only country ever attacked with nuclear bombs and
the public is strongly against having them in the country. Japan
bans the introduction of nuclear weapons as a matter of policy but
has not passed a law to that effect.
   The Socialists, who oppose the U.S.-Japan defense treaty, say
the ban should be enforced strictly and accuse the conservative
government of giving tacit approval to the transit of U.S. nuclear
weapons aboard Navy warships that dock in Japan.
   The Japanese queried the United States about the 1965 accident
and the Foreign Affairs Committee of the opposition-dominated upper
house of Parliament said on Dec. 13 the government should ask again
for a U.S. report.
   Pentagon officials met with Japanese diplomats in Washington
Tuesday and said the United States understands Japan's special
concerns about nuclear weapons but cannot disclose anymore about
the accident, a Foreign Ministry official said, speaking on
condition of anonymity.
   Kyodo News Service quoted Washington as having said, ``The U.S.
government feels any further discussion on this matter could
compromise our operational policies and have an adverse effect on
our national security interests.''
   Under the U.S.-Japan Security Treaty, the United States is
obliged to consult with Japan about bringing nuclear weapons into
Japanese territory. Japanese officials say that since there has
been no consultation, Japan trusts the United States has not
violated the treaty.
</TEXT>

</DOC>