<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0276 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1344EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f BC-Dollar-Gold     12-20 0316</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Dollar-Gold,0332</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar Mixed, Gold Lower</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: AMer planned by 5:30 p.m. EST</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dollar was mixed against major foreign
currencies Wednesday in hectic but thin European trading after the
U.S. military intervention in Panama.
   Gold prices were lower.
   Traders said the dollar was boosted early in the trading day by
the U.S. military action and by an unexpected upward revision in
the third-quarter U.S. economic growth rate.
   The dollar stabilized later in the day, traders said, and then
slipped back in mild profit-taking.
   ``We think (the Panama situation) is very much a smoke screen
and an excuse to buy dollars,'' said one London dealer. ``If the
market was genuinely frightened from the news, why didn't gold also
gain?''
   Investors traditionally turn to the dollar and gold as safe
havens in times of turmoil.
   Traders cautioned against drawing too many conclusions from
dollar movements in the market, thinned by the holiday season.
   In Tokyo, the dollar rose to a closing 144.23 Japanese yen from
143.80 yen at Tuesday's close. Later, in London, it fell to 143.90
yen.
   In London, the British pound rose to $1.6052 from $1.6005 late
Tuesday.
   Other late dollar rates in Europe, compared with late Tuesday's
prices, included: 1.7355 West German marks, down from 1.7365;
1.5585 Swiss francs, down from 1.5615; 5.9165 French francs, down
from 5.9300; 1.9720 Dutch guilders, up from 1.9575; 1,288.00
Italian lire, down from 1,291.25; and 1.1625 Canadian dollars, up
from 1.1613.
   Gold fell in London to a late bid price of $413.50 a troy ounce,
down from $413.75 bid late Tuesday.
   In Zurich, the metal fell to a closing bid of $413 dollars, down
from $414 dollars bid late Tuesday.
   In Hong Kong, gold fell 76 cents to close at a bid $412.04.
   Silver bullion fell in London to a late bid price of $5.56 a
troy ounce, down from $5.57 bid late Tuesday.
</TEXT>

</DOC>