<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1106EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Iran-Elections     12-17 0419</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iran-Elections,0434</SECOND>
<HEAD>Radicals Capture Parliament Seats In Elections</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ED BLANCHE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Anti-Western radicals have won several
parliamentary seats in special elections, strengthening hard-line
opposition to President Hashemi Rafsanjani's policy of economic
reform.
   The official Islamic Republic News Agency, monitored in Nicosia,
reported late Saturday that former Foreign Minister Ali Akbar
Mohtashemi, a middle-ranking cleric, took 225,570 votes in polling
to win from a Tehran district.
   Another hard-line cleric, Hojatoleslam Movahedi Kermani, also
was elected Friday in Tehran with 287,921 votes, IRNA reported.
   Diplomats said the mid-term elections were seen as a test for
Rafsanjani's policies.
   Sixty-four candidates ran in the elections, called to fill nine
vacant seats in the 270-member Parliament. Iran's official media
reported a heavy turnout but gave no overall figures.
   Most of the seats were left empty when Rafsanjani appointed
legislators to his Cabinet following his election July 28.
   Tehran Radio said four other candidates, including lesser-known
radicals, won seats in provincial centers.
   The state radio, also monitored in Nicosia, said no candidate
won a majority in two other Tehran districts and the provincial
Bandar Turkman constituency, so a second round of voting will be
held.
   The front-runners for the remaining Tehran seats are all
radicals _ former Commerce Minister Habibollah Asgarowladi, former
Labor Minister Aboloasem Sarhadizadeh and former Posts and
Telegraphs Minister Morteza Nabavi.
   Mohtashemi's election marked a comeback for the 43-year-old
Islamic fundamentalist, who has close links with pro-Iranian
militants holding Western hostages in Lebanon.
   Rafsanjani, leader of Tehran's so-called pragmatists, dumped
Mohtashemi and other hard-liners in August, when he formed a
Cabinet dominated by technocrats designed to revitalize Iran's
economy following last year's cease-fire in the eight-year war with
Iraq.
   Mohtashemi is allied with Ahmad Khomeini, son of the late
revolutionary leader Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini and considered a
focal point for the radicals espousing the ayatollah's ideological
legacy.
   The hard-liners oppose Rafsanjani's moves to improve Iran's
relations with the West to acquire badly needed investment to help
the post-war economy.
   They contend his policies move too far from the fundamentalist
principles that form the bedrock of the 1979 Islamic revolution.
   Rafsanjani, while no less committed to the revolution than his
rivals, believes Iran cannot afford to remain isolated and that its
55 million people have had enough hardship after a decade of
turmoil and war.
   Radicals already dominate the Majlis and their gains are likely
to further inhibit Rafsanjani's room for maneuver between guiding
Iran into a more open, prosperous era while preserving Islamic
principles.
</TEXT>

</DOC>