<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1103EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania-China     12-23 0522</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-China,0536</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ceausescu's Fall Increases China's Loneliness</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHY WILHELM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Romanian President Nicolae Ceausescu had already
fled a popular uprising at home when thousands of miles away in
China, television still carried his last speech as if nothing had
happened.
   Ceausescu's sudden fall from power clearly took Chinese
officials by surprise. The Foreign Ministry took more than 24 hours
to issue a substantive comment, and then said simply that it was
following developments with interest and hoped to continue friendly
relations with Romania.
   His fall also left Chinese leaders more isolated than ever in
their rejection of democratic reforms that have swept the socialist
world this year. But it was unlikely to shake their resolve to keep
political power firmly in the hands of the Communist Party.
   Party General Secretary Jiang Zemin, speaking to Hong Kong
publishers Thursday, implied that East European armies lacked
strength to put down the uprisings. China's army, by contrast,
underwent ``the test of lengthy revolutionary warfare'' and
maintained strict political discipline, he said.
   As one Communist Party after another has been forced to share
power in Eastern Europe, Jiang and other Chinese leaders have
insisted that China's vast population and backward economy make
socialism the only viable system.
   In internal discussions, according to the Hong Kong Economic
Daily, they concluded that East Europe's example only proves the
correctness of China's decision to use force against pro-democracy
protesters in June.
   Individual Chinese who heard foreign radio broadcasts of
Ceausescu's fall applauded it but saw no hope that senior leader
Deng Xiaoping would be the next aging autocrat to go. ``We don't
want violence,'' said one, noting the heavy fighting and death toll
in Romania. Given China's size, he said, the bloodshed would be
even greater.
   In the end, China was reserved in its support for Ceausescu.
   ``We ... believe that it's Romania's internal affair,'' the
Foreign Ministry said repeatedly as the protests swelled last week.
   Asked Saturday if China would give Ceausescu a safe haven, the
ministry said only that he had not come nor asked to. It refused to
say what it would do if he did ask.
   Ceausescu had been one of China's most reliable friends abroad.
In the 1960s, when the Soviet Union broke with China and took with
it most of Eastern Europe, Ceausescu refused to take sides and
maintained good relations with Beijing.
   When much of the world condemned China's crackdown on
pro-democracy protesters, he applauded it and sent several
government and party delegations to Beijing. Qiao Shi, a top
Chinese party official, returned the visits in November.
   Ceausescu was quoted frequently by China's media, with his
denunciations of Western imperialism closely matching those of Deng
and Jiang. Chinese papers withheld reports on the violence in
Romania until it became clear he could not return to power.
   A photo exhibit celebrating Chinese-Romanian friendship opened
with fanfare in a Beijing park just one day before Ceausescu's
ouster.
   But Friday, as he fled by helicopter from his palace roof, the
exhibit was deserted and locked. A visitor who rattled the door
roused two surprised attendants.
</TEXT>

</DOC>