<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0166 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1738EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Cold Bjt   12-22 0837</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cold, Bjt,0862</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cold Spell Snaps Temperature Records, Cancels Bobsled Contest</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos WX7, DCT1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEPHANIE NANO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The Deep Freeze snapped temperature records Friday in more than
125 cities from the Rockies to the East Coast, making it one of the
worst cold spells on record, the National Weather Service said.
   The temperature dipped to minus 47 in the southeastern Montana
town of Broadus _ the coldest spot Friday in the Lower 48 states.
   It was so cold in the Adirondack Mountains in New York that a
bobsled competition was canceled. And Hot Springs, Va., wasn't even
lukewarm.
   ``It's just indescribably cold,'' Police Lt. Carl Goolsby said
Friday in Memphis, Tenn., where people ``just don't know how to
dress for this weather.''
   The bitter cold caused concern for citrus growers, farmers and
those who care for the homeless, the poor and the elderly.
Utilities reported record usage as customers tried to keep warm.
   In New York City, where the arctic chill sent 9,200 people to
shelters Thursday night, demonstrators erected four tombstones
outside City Hall to mark the deaths of four homeless people who
died of exposure while sleeping in the city subway system last
weekend.
   ``These tragic deaths have gone virtually unnoticed, and we more
affluent New Yorkers seem to have let our hearts grow colder and
more hardened than the bitter winter,'' said David Beseda of the
Coalition for the Homeless.
   Nationwide, nearly 60 deaths have been blamed on the week-long
cold spell. The cold was blamed Friday for the death of a
35-year-old Oklahoma City man who died while walking a half-mile
home after his car apparently ran out of gas.
   ``If it gets cold enough long enough, we've got a disaster,''
said William Moon, sales manager for Zellwin Farms in Jacksonville,
Fla., which has everything from carrots and lettuce to parsley and
radishes in the ground in northwest Orange County.
   The strain on utilities caused scattered power outages and
prompted Potomac Electric Power in Washington, D.C., to temporarily
cut its voltage by 5 percent Friday morning to prevent blackouts.
   Potomac Electric Power spokesman Tom Welle said oil-fired
generators were using fuel quicker than the pipeline supplying the
plant could deliver it.
   Among the cities to set cold records were: Beckley, W.Va., minus
13; Bismarck, N.D., minus 32; Calico Rock, Ark., minus 5; Cedar
Rapids, Iowa, minus 19; Del Rio, Texad, 17; Duluth, Minn., minus
22; Paducah, Ky., minus 10, Kansas City, Mo., minus 19; Omaha,
Neb., minus 25.
   The National Weather Service said more temperature records were
expected to topple throughout Friday.
   ``The number of record lows today was as great as that of
Christmas Day in 1983, and establishes this cold wave, along with
those of December 1983 and February 1899 as one of the most severe
of all time for the central and eastern U.S.,'' said Hugh Crowther
of the weather service.
   A reading of 23 degrees below zero in Indianapolis was the
coldest reading of the century in that city. It was minus 13 in Hot
Springs, Va.
   In the Adirondacks on Friday, a two-man bobsled competition
sponsored by the U.S. Bobsled and Skeleton Federation was called
off because temperatures reached minus 18 degrees at the top of
Mount Van Hoevenberg.
   The cold wasn't keeping shoppers home, however.
   ``'Tis the season and everyone's here doing their last minute
shopping,'' said Joan Lincoln, marketing director at Marketplace
Mall in Rochester, N.Y.
   Lincoln said many people put off their shopping until the last
minute because of December's wintry weather and ``Now they have no
choice.''
   The only readings above freezing in the nation were confined to
Florida, the Pacific Coast and southwestern deserts.
   Weather forecasters promise a return to more seasonal weather by
Christmas. It won't be warm, just not as cold.
   The lingering cold meant an early Christmas break for some
workers and students, as schools closed in Tennessee, Ohio,
Missouri, and Minnesota. Snow, sleet and ice shut down the bus
system in New Orleans, stranding commuters.
   ``This is state-of-the-art cold,'' said Ronnie Perkins, who
arrived for work Friday in downtown Nashville wearing a snowsuit
and face-covering muffler. ``I mean, we are talking high-tech
weather as we go into the '90s. This is the sultan of frigid.''
   On the Mississippi River, about 1,000 barges remained stalled in
the St. Louis area because of a massive bank-to-bank ice jam at the
confluence of the Missouri River, a Coast Guard official said. It
was the fourth straight day that river traffic had been restricted
between St. Louis and Cairo, Ill., because of ice and low water.
   And the cold prompted Missouri's major utilities to declare a
moratorium on shutting off service to non-paying customers. They
also have pledged to try to restore service to customers who had
been shut off.
   ``It's really wonderful,'' said Georgia Rusan, chief of family
services for St. Louis' Human Development Corp., which administers
emergency heating assistance to city residents. ``I know it will
take a lot of pressure off people and brighten their holidays.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>