<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0423EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DownAndOut     12-18 0553</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Down And Out,0574</SECOND>
<HEAD>Charities in Massachusetts Seeing New Class of Needy</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALLISON J. PUGH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   With Massachusetts' economy in a tailspin and
hundreds of workers laid off in the Christmas season, charities are
seeing scores of people who never before had problems paying
mortgages or heating bills.
   ``There is definitely people coming in and saying `I lost my
job, I haven't worked in two weeks, I need help,''' said Jody Zeek
of the St. Vincent DePaul Society, a volunteer organization
operating out of the area's Roman Catholic parishes.
   ``I can tell almost immediately by their body language that this
is not their cup of tea, but they are desperate,'' said Herbert
Hershey, a social worker for the Salvation Army in Framingham.
``They've had good jobs, but they are so desperate now they come in
here for food and fuel.''
   He said his chapter has helped 60 percent more people this year
than the year before.
   Massachusetts has been struggling with an anticipated $825
million budget deficit.
   Last week, 706 state employees received layoff notices, and the
number laid off is expected to climb to more than 1,200 by the end
of December.
   The slumping economy also has hurt some of the region's large
employers, such as Wang Laboratories Inc., General Motors Corp. and
Prime Computer Inc., all of which have trimmed their work forces
considerably.
   Marcia Countie, executive director of United Ways of
Massachusetts, which funds the Salvation Army and the Red Cross and
other large charities, said the layoffs have created a ``tremendous
crisis.''
   ``In our economy today, all of us live one paycheck to another,
and when that gets interrupted, for families it's catastrophic,''
she said.
   One woman, a Framingham resident, had a computer job that paid
her about $40,000 before she was laid off. Now she bags groceries
for $6.50 an hour, trying to meet her mortgage payments, Hershey
said.
   ``My heart goes out to those who are very reluctant, very
embarrassed,'' he said. ``How can we help them?''
   A Natick widow with two children in college said her job lets
her pay one bill at a time, but her paycheck doesn't allow for
emergencies.
   In November, she was faced with paying for her daughter's knee
surgery. The surgery led her to the Salvation Army, seeking help to
pay for fuel.
   ``I felt like I had no right to this because there are so many
people with worse problems, but then I see it's a very thin line at
this point, and it probably wouldn't take much to put me there,''
said the woman, who spoke on condition of anonymity.
   The woman said she had taken a part-time retail job to
supplement her income, earning $5 an hour.
   In Natick, a former bank vice president who lost his job came to
the Salvation Army for food during Thanksgiving, spokesman Steve
Copaccia said.
   ``These are people who never knew what the Salvation Army did.
They didn't need us,'' he said. ``Now they come in for help with
paying for their heating bill.''
   Charity volunteers said they also have seen an increase of
people either on welfare or with low-paying jobs because the state
has cut government programs serving the needy.
   ``We've had cutbacks before, but I've never seen it this bad,''
Countie said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>