<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0323EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-Latin     12-21 0725</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Latin,0749</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Invasion of Panama Draws Fire From Latin America</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LA PAZ, Bolivia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A bomb damaged the U.S. Embassy in
Bolivia, Nicaraguan troops went on alert and thousands of Cubans
reportedly protested in Havana as most of Latin America reacted
angrily to the invasion of Panama.
   Peru withdrew its U.S. ambassador, and the Organization of
American States met in emergency session Wednesday following the
pre-dawn mililtary assault aimed at deposing and seizing Panamanian
strongman Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   The OAS refused to recognize the new U.S.-installed government's
representative, and instead considered a resolution condemning the
U.S. action.
   El Salvador's U.S.-backed government was the only one in Latin
American to clearly support the move.
   In La Paz, the bomb went off around 8:30 p.m. Wednesday,
destroying windows at the embassy and surrounding offices. No
injuries were reported.
   Police at the scene said there were no suspects, but the Armed
Liberation Front of Zarate Willka, a radical leftist group, claimed
responsibility.
   ``Death to the Yankee invader; our hatred is unplacable and the
war will be until death,'' the group said in a statement released
just after the bombing. ``We are fighting against aggression and
for the sovereignty of our people.''
   The group has been accused of killing two Mormon missionaries
from the United States in May and has been linked to an attempt to
kill then-U.S. Secretary of State George Shultz during an August
1988 visit.
   Peru's president, Alan Garcia, said he was pulling his
ambassador from Washington in protest. He said a drug summit
scheduled for Feb. 15 with Bush and other Latin American presidents
in Cartagena, Colombia, should be postponed as a result of the
invasion.
   Venezuela also criticized the move, but said in a communique
that lack of an ``effective and firm'' response by Latin American
nations to human rights violations and constitutional norms by
Panama's government had made it necessary.
   In Nicaragua, President Daniel Ortega said the invasion
threatened his Central American country, and placed troops on
maximum alert. Soviet-built tanks rumbled through Managua, at least
20 large howitzers were positioned in the capital and Red Beret
special forces went to the international airport.
   ``In addition to constituting a flagrant trampling of the
sovereignty and territorial integrity of Panama, it is a threat to
the peace and security of all Latin America, Central America and
especially constitutes a serious threat to Nicaragua,'' Ortega said
in a communique read on Voice of Nicaragua radio.
   Thousands of Cubans protested the invasion by rallying outside
the Havana building that houses the U.S. interests section, the
official Cuban news agency Prensa Latina said. The United States
has no embassy in Havana.
   Fidel Castro's government called on the world to unite in
denouncing the United States, the agency said.
   President Jose Sarney of Brazil said in a television interview
that the invasion was a ``step backward in international
relations.''
   Argentina offered aid to Panamanians and said it ``truly
deplores what is happening.'' It called for immediate removal of
the American troops but also described Noriega as an obstacle to
democracy.
   Chile, Mexico, Uruguay and Ecuador also deplored the U.S. move.
   Colombia did not directly comment on the invasian. But Enrique
Pennalosa, its United Nations ambassador who also chairs the U.N.
Security Council, said, ``Colombia, as a matter of principle,
rejects any armed intervention against a sovereign country.''
   El Salvador's government said the United States ``was using its
legitimate right of defense.''
   ``This type of actions could permit the Panamanian people to
identify with a democratic process, to reestablish an elected
government,'' said Vice President Francisco Merino.
   Honduras appeared to give qualified support to the U.S. move,
saying its government ``laments the declaration of a state of war
in Panama and the violent acts taken against American military and
civilians.''
   ``Honduras equally laments that the U.S. government saw it
necessary to take military action, moving away from the principle
of non-intervention, as an extreme measure to guarantee the
security of thousands of its citizens residing in Panama,'' the
Foreign Ministry statement added.
   Costa Rican Foreign Minister Rodrigo Madrigal said in a
statement that his country regretted the U.S. use of force to
``bring about an end to the crisis caused by the despotic
government of Gen. Noriega,'' but hopes that ``peace returns to
Panama with a quick restoration of a democratic government.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>