<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0423EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-TragicGift Bjt   12-26 0805</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Tragic Gift, Bjt,0834</SECOND>
<HEAD>Community Helps Family Put Lives Back Together</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LR1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JANET K. ISBELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BALD KNOB, Ark. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When a fire early one morning claimed the
lives of their three young boys, Dubby and Diana Wilcox made a
bittersweet choice. They donated their boys' organs for transplant
operations.
   Two days later, the heart of 10-year-old Jared Wilcox was
beating in the body of a 48-year-old woman in Arkansas' first heart
transplant.
   The livers of Jared and his 9-year-old brother, Jake, were
transplanted into the bodies of a 14-year-old Pennsylvania boy and
a 33-year-old North Carolina woman.
   And the boys' kidneys went to four Arkansas residents.
   Those who know the Wilcoxes said their decision was typical of
their unselfishness. As word of the tragedy spread, friends,
neighbors and even strangers responded to give to them.
   In a few hours, a radio station's plea for help generated
thousands of dollars. A restaurant planned a benefit dinner, church
groups provided food, children collected pennies and employees of a
grocery chain authorized payroll deductions.
   Others in Bald Knob, a town of 2,700 residents about 60 miles
northeast of Little Rock, contributed clothing, furniture,
appliances, vehicles, utilities and even a house, provided
rent-free for the next year and renovated in a day's time by dozens
of volunteers.
   Diana Wilcox smiled, then cried as she recalled entering the
home for the first time.
   ``You couldn't move,'' she said. ``There were people lined up
all along the walls. And they all hollered, `Welcome home.'''
   The three Wilcox children were sleeping in their beds the
morning of Nov. 8 while Mrs. Wilcox drove her husband to work just
a few blocks away. In those few minutes, the house was engulfed in
smoke, the result of what Police Chief Dave Miller said was a short
circuit.
   Five-year-old Justin died of smoke inhalation that morning.
Jared and Jake died the following day, also of smoke inhalation.
   When first approached about donating their sons' organs, the
Wilcoxes said no. Minutes later, after considering what they
thought the boys would have wanted, they changed their minds.
   Mrs. Wilcox said the knowledge that her children saved lives is
comforting.
   ``There's people that've got loved ones because of my boys,''
she said.
   The transplant of Jared's heart to Mary E. Wilson of
Jacksonville allowed her to celebrate Christmas with her family.
She said Monday she hoped to meet Jared's parents.
   ``I feel that it was a gift from that family, a gift of life
from that family,'' Ms. Wilson said. ``I'm really anxious to get to
know them. I just feel like I'm part of their family now.''
   The Wilcoxes' generosity also has helped others who need an
organ transplant, said Bobby Cumberland, executive director of the
Arkansas Regional Organ Recovery Agency in Little Rock.
   ``We had more organ donor referrals in November than in any
month in our history, and I think a large part of that is due to
this family's decision to tell their story,'' he said.
   Their story has touched people around the country. The couple
received about 3,000 letters. Donations have swelled to more than
$20,000.
   Alan Risener of radio station KWCK in nearby Searcy called the
response to the station's on-air request for donations unbelievable.
   ``Within a few minutes, we had $500,'' he said. ``Within three
hours, we had $6,000, and it just continued to climb.''
   A teary-eyed elderly woman walked in the station's door with a
$100 donation. Students from nearby Harding University carried in
jugs of nickels, dimes and quarters. One man who doesn't drive
arranged a ride 15 miles into town to donate $1.
   After the boys died, friends of the Wilcoxes feared the couple
might leave Bald Knob, particularly since they had no home.
   ``I didn't want them leaving,'' Jimmy Harper said. ``I felt that
if they left, it would have been a big loss in the community. Our
youth program wouldn't be the same without Dubby.''
   Harper said a small group of friends decided to take on
renovation of the house offered by real estate agents Lynn and
Verla Davis. More than 50 people showed up to help.
   The house was little more than a shell. But in nine hours,
volunteers installed electrical wiring, plumbing, a septic tank,
the water line, a heating unit, appliances and bathroom fixtures.
Utilities were turned on, and Simms Gas Co. of Searcy filled up the
fuel tank, leaving behind a ticket that said ``No charge.''
   The workers cleaned, painted, hung curtains and stocked the
pantry and medicine chest. And to make the house a home, volunteers
decorated the walls with items from their own walls.
   ``This is the closest to home right now we can get,'' Mrs.
Wilcox said.
   ``You don't realize how many friends you have 'til something
like this happens,'' Wilcox added.
</TEXT>

</DOC>