<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0305EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-PanamaPool     12-22 0516</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama Pool,510</SECOND>
<HEAD>Controversy Over Whether Reporters Should Have Been Allowed Closer</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRYAN BRUMLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.S. military in Panama opened the doors
to about 350 journalists today after two days of controversy about
restrictions put on the small pool of reporters who accompanied the
original troops.
   Some 50 newsmen and women arrived by charter plane late Thursday
from Costa Rica, and the U.S. Southern Command, based in Panama,
was bracing for the arrival early today of a jumbo jet carrying up
to 300 more.
   A special media pool, in its most significant test since the
concept was created, was activated Tuesday night and flown from
Washington to Panama. However, military officers on Wednesday kept
the journalists from actually covering any hostilities.
   Military commanders in Panama are doing their best to protect
members of the media covering the U.S. military action in that
country, Defense Secretary Dick Cheney said.
   Asked about the problem, White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater
had a complaint of his own, claiming that a news organization had
broken pool security. He would not name the organization.
   ``We were greatly disturbed that one of the major organizations
had divulged their participation and departure before they left
here,'' Fitzwater said.
   It ``does call into question the integrity of the pool and the
commitments made,'' he said.
   News organizations which take part in the pool agree in advance
to keep its activation a secret. Tuesday night, the pool was
activated about six hours before the military assault was announced
publicly.
   Military officials in Panama said Thursday they would let the
new wave of reporters camp in the officer's club restaurant
initially but expected them to have their own accommodations by
Friday.
   Fitzwater's complaint about security was not echoed by the
chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, Gen. Colin Powell.
   ``I think it worked marvelously the other evening,'' he said.
   ``We did what we promised you we would do and the media in the
pool did what they promised they would do,'' he said. Pool members
gathered late Tuesday night and were flown to Panama with the
invasion force under a promise of secrecy.
   ``There never was any concern in my mind it would break security
and it didn't,'' said Powell.
   Pentagon spokesman Pete Williams, sitting with Cheney in an
interview with newspaper and wire service reporters, acknowledged
that ``we wish we could have done a better job getting people
around'' on Wednesday.
   ``I think there was adequate coverage. I think our commanders on
the scene had their priorities straight,'' said Cheney, noting that
media executives had called his office demanding that the military
protect reporters who were not in the pool.
   A photographer who was not in the pool was killed, and other
journalists were taken hostage by forces loyal to ousted Panamanian
Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   Before the joint Cheney-Powell interview, Williams was asked why
pool members had been restricted largely to interviews with U.S.
Embassy officials during most of the first day of the invasion. He
responded: ``Incompetence ... There really is no excuse for it.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>