<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0321EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Panama-USReax     12-21 0706</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-US Reax,0733</SECOND>
<HEAD>Protesters Take to Streets, But Many Favor U.S. Invasion</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DOUGLAS J. ROWE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Protesters took to the streets in four U.S. cities to denounce
the invasion of Panama. But many of them encountered jeers, and
unscientific surveys showed Americans overwhelmingly in favor of it.
   Scholars on Central America were mixed in their reactions.
   ``It's obvious that we don't want democracy. We want client
states,'' said John Donaghy, a member of the Central American
Solidarity Association, which organized a rally Wednesday on Boston
Common.
   About 100 people braved 29-degree temperatures and stiff winds
to attend the demonstration against the pre-dawn U.S. raid to
capture Gen. Manuel Noriega, who faces drug charges in Florida.
   About 25 people from the Rhode Island Central America Network
picketed the federal courthouse in Providence on Wednesday evening,
and about 70 demonstrators held a candlelight vigil in Baltimore.
   Kathy Schaafsma, a demonstrator in Baltimore, said she military
action was illegal and the newly installed government of elected
President Guillermo Endara was a ``puppet government'' that will
ensure U.S. control of the Panama Canal.
   About 200 people gathered in front of a U.S. Armed Services
recruiting center in New York City's Times Square before beginning
to march, chanting slogans such as ``U.S. out of Panama.''
   As they marched up the Avenue of the Americas, they were jeered
by numerous passers-by.
   `I say they're confused,'' said one passer-by, Frankie Ambrosia.
   ``I think this is more than a political thing,'' he said of the
U.S. intervention. ``This was an anti-drug thing.''
   When the protesters began chanting in Rockefeller Center, many
tourists there to view the giant Christmas tree at the skating rink
began booing at them.
   Besides the boos, other barometers bore out strong support for
the military strike.
   Cable News Network asked viewers to call one of two special 900
numbers to indicate whether they support or oppose the U.S. action
in Panama.
   The network said early today that 91 percent of more than
100,000 viewers phoning in supported U.S. intervention and 9
percent opposed it.
   Radio programs that sought opinions from listeners also found
that most callers supported President Bush's decision.
   Cincinnati radio station WLW also received more than 1,000 calls
during a 2{-hour telephone survey, with 844 supporting the invasion
and 233 opposing it.
   Ann Twinam, a Latin American historian at the University of
Cincinnati, said the perception of the invasion will be different
from criticism of other U.S. intervention in Latin America.
   ``Normally, we would suspect universal condemnation, but the
extent of the drug trade by Panama could alter that,'' she said.
   She said Panamanians did not want to settle the country's
problem themselves. ``People weren't really willing to take to the
streets. People really wanted him gone, but they weren't willing to
do it,'' she said.
   But Carlos Munoz, associate professor of Ethnic Studies at the
University of California, Berkeley, called the move the ``most
serious policy blunder since Vietnam.''
   ``I see a Vietnam War in the making,'' he said. ``I hope to God
I'm wrong in this, but I fear the worst.''
   One reason Noriega has been so difficult to remove from power,
Munoz said, is the widespread support for him in Panama.
   ``Rightly or wrongly, he has been a very respected leader in
that country,'' Munoz said. ``I don't like to see dictatorships,
but the government the United States is putting in place does not
have the support of the Panamanian people.''
   In Jacksonville, N.C., home of Camp Lejeune, many residents
approved of the strike.
   ``They (the troops) should have gone in when they had the
coup,'' Harold Schaefer, a retired Marine, said of October's failed
attempt by Panamanian officers to overthrow Noriega. ``They're
doing the right thing.''
   William Little, another retired Marine, said: ``Bush had better
not pull out until they hang him by the neck here in the U.S. ...
Bush has more guts than I gave him credit for. But I'd like to see
old Harry Truman in there now.''
   Still others were upset by the timing.
   ``I question the judgment of the president in sending these
young men into battle this close to Christmas and having them
gift-wrapped in body bags,'' said Victor Carucci, of East Amherst,
N.Y.

</TEXT>

</DOC>