<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1359EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Nazis     12-19 0567</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Nazis,0581</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hunt Launched for Hundreds of Previously Unknown War Criminals</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALLYN FISHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nazi hunters are searching for hundreds of
newly identified Lithuanian war crimes suspects believed hiding in
the United States, Canada, Australia and Britain, the Simon
Wiesenthal Center said Tuesday.
   The names are listed in files of testimony from Jewish survivors
in Soviet Lithuania given three months ago to the Yad Vashem
archives in Jerusalem, which is in charge of documenting the
slayings of 6 million Jews during World War II by Nazi Germany.
   The records were kept secret for more than four decades by an
elderly Lithuanian survivor, Leibl Kuniuchovsky, who now lives in
Sunrise, Fla., said Efraim Zuroff, director of the Israeli office
of the Los Angeles-based center known for tracking down Nazi
suspects.
   ``This material has enormous significance. Based on our past
experience this can lead us to numerous Nazi war criminals now
living in the United States, Canada, Australia and the United
Kingdom,'' Zuroff said.
   He said the approximately 1,300 names on the list are
Lithuanians who collaborated with the Nazis during 1941-42, when
most mass slayings of Jews took place in the Baltic republic. More
than 200,000 Jews are believed to have been murdered by the Nazis
in Lithuania.
   Lithuania was a center of Jewish culture in Eastern Europe in
the 18th and 19th centuries and a nesting ground for the Zionist
ideology that led to the creation of Israel. The Jewish community
there numbered 1.5 million at the turn of the century and only
26,000 after World War II.
   Kuniuchovsky, a survivor of the Jewish ghetto in the city of
Kovno, took the testimony from refugees after the war on behalf of
historical commissions set up by the Allies in displaced persons
camps in West Germany, Zuroff said.
   His records are valuable because they provide rare accounts from
the few Jews who survived the mass slayings that took place in
isolated towns and villages, Zuroff said in an interview.
   He said the 1,300 names were gathered from 1,683 pages of
testimony that Kuniuchovsky took from survivors in 171 towns and
villages.
   Hundreds of the suspects were known to be alive, Zuroff added.
He declined to give names of the suspects, suggesting this could
harm efforts to seek them out for prosecution.
   ``The majority were previously unknown to us,'' he said, noting
the earlier testimony was sketchy about slayings in many isolated
areas because survivors were few and investigators were unable to
find them in later years.
   Zuroff said the Wiesenthal Center is tracking the suspects
through its four branches in the United States, one in Toronto, and
other agencies. The center is named for founder Simon Wiesenthal,
80, an Austrian-born concentration camp survivor who has devoted
much of his life to hunting down Nazi war criminals and documenting
the Holocaust.
   In addition to new suspects' names, Kuniuchovsky's file also
contains surprising information about the numbers of Lithuanians
involved in the killings, Zuroff said.
   ``It is shocking to see such a big role was played by the
intelligentsia,'' Zuroff added. ``We're talking about school
teachers, educated people'' who belonged to vigilante groups or
helped local police carry out killings.
   Zuroff also said he hoped legislation adopted in the past two
years in Canada and Australia, allowing prosecution of crimes
committed overseas, would make it easier to hunt and prosecute the
Lithuanian suspects.
</TEXT>

</DOC>