<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0288 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1853EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f BC-BusinessHighlights     12-22 0848</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Business Highlights,0889</SECOND>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Orders to U.S. factories for durable goods
posted a 5.1 percent gain in November, the sharpest increase in a
year, the government said. Analysts said the report suggested the
economy can avoid a recession.
   The Commerce Department said Friday that orders for durable
goods _ costly items expected to last at least three years _
increased to a seasonally adjusted $130.7 billion last month after
dropping 0.7 percent in October and 1.2 percent in September.
   The gain in orders was spread through all categories and was the
largest since a 7.4 percent jump last December. It averted the
first three-month decline since 1986.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Senate Ethics Committee said it will
formally investigate five senators who intervened with banking
regulators on behalf of a wealthy contributor whose huge savings
and loan was failing.
   The senators all have denied wrongdoing and said they welcomed
the announcement.
   The ethics panel said Friday it will probe the activities of
Majority Whip Alan Cranston, D-Calif.; Banking Committee Chairman
Donald W. Riegle, Jr., D-Mich.; John McCain, R-Ariz.; Dennis
DeConcini, D-Ariz., and John Glenn, D-Ohio.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bank of New England Corp., which expects heavy
losses due to bad real estate loans, has rescinded a common stock
dividend declared last month.
   The announcement Friday came one week after Bank of New England
said it would boost its loan reserves above $1 billion and that it
expected a ``substantial'' loss for the year. The bank struggled
amid a regional real estate slump.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Smithkline Beecham PLC, a major international
pharmaceutical company, has agreed to sell its U.S. and Canadian
household products businesses to a West German company for $107
million in cash.
   Smithkline said Friday the sale to Joh. A. Benckiser GmbH is
consistent with its strategy of focusing on international
healthcare following the merger of Smithkline Beckman Corp. with
Beecham Group PLC earlier this year.
   Household products included in the sale are Calgon, a leading
U.S. bath additive, Cling Free, a fabric softener used in driers,
and Delicare, a detergent for delicate products.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Columbia Pictures Entertainment Inc. has put
McCann-Erickson Worldwide in charge of placing domestic advertising
for both its Columbia Pictures and Tri-Star Pictures movies.
   The decision Friday could mean an extra $70 million to $75
million in annual billings for the giant New York-based agency,
which had previously held the assignment for placing only the
Columbia Pictures ads.
   The loser is AC&amp;R Advertising, a unit of Britain's Saatchi &amp;
Saatchi Co. PLC which had been responsible for placing the
Tri-State Pictures advertising.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ford Motor Co. intends to sell $1.55 billion
in debt securities to pay for its recent acquisition of Associates,
the nation's third-largest independent finance company, according
to documents.
   In a registration statement filed Friday with the Securities and
Exchange Commission, Ford said it is seeking to issue the debt
securities through Ford Holdings Inc., a subsidiary formed in
September to acquire Associates.
   The debt securities will be sold ``to reduce short-term debt,
including borrowings to fund the acquisition of Associates,''
according to the registration statement.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEWARK, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal judge has unsealed confidential
corporate documents in a lawsuit against Mobil Oil Corp. but
withheld the order when lawyers for the oil giant said they would
appeal.
   The company is fighting to prevent the disclosure of the
documents _ reports on environmental conditions at its chemical
division plants _ because it says they are self-critical
evaluations.
   Disclosing such reports would have a chilling effect on a
company's efforts to be candid about its operations, Mobil argued
Friday.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bush administration plans to lift a
congressional ban on government loans to Iraq, a move expected to
antagonize lawmakers critical of Iraq's human rights abuses and
credit problems.
   Officials say President Bush will exercise his right to lift the
ban, imposed by Congress several months ago, on grounds of U.S.
national interests. The officials said the move is expected within
several weeks.
   U.S. oil companies and other businesses have exerted heavy
pressure on the administration to broaden trade ties with Iraq
since the 1988 end of its ruinous 8-year war with Iran.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Westinghouse Electric Corp. is considering
appealing for an increase in the $3.9 million bonus it won for
running the Savannah River nuclear weapons plant despite safety
lapses such as workers sleeping on the job, an Energy Department
official said.
   Westinghouse officials at the South Carolina plant, however,
said Friday there were no plans to appeal.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The stock market worked its way higher in quiet preholiday
trading Friday. The Dow Jones industrial average climbed 20.26
points to 2,711.39, cutting its loss for the week to 28.16 points.
   The dollar tumbled in abbreviated pre-Christmas foreign-exchange
trading.
   Bond prices fell.
   Orange juice futures prices fell sharply; heating oil futures
posted fresh gains as the nation's record-setting cold spell
continued; precious metals advanced; livestock and meat futures
were mixed; and grains and soybeans were mixed.
</TEXT>

</DOC>