<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0107 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1439EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-People     12-18 0955</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0994</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY44,NY11</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Michael Jackson says his hit songs are not his
doing, that he is merely a conduit for tunes already written.
   Jackson made the remarks in a 1984 home video taped in his home
in Encino, Calif. It was scheduled for broadcast Monday night on
``A Current Affair,'' said Jeff Erdel, a spokesman for the
syndicated program.
   In the video, the reclusive star said he feels his songs existed
somewhere else before he wrote them.
   ``I feel I'm just a tunnel, a tube through which they come,''
Jackson said in the video. ``I mean, `Billie Jean' and `Beat It'
and all those songs have been up there somewhere and just came
through to me. So even if I did it, I just can't always take
credit.''
   The video also shows Jackson playing with his pet llamas and
performing scenes from ``Peter Pan.''
   Jackson said he considers children magical.
   ``When I'm around them, I feel more alive, I think, than
anything. I feel like I can do anything,'' he said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor James Naughton, whose life has taken that
familiar theatrical tour of hard work for years only to be declared
an overnight success, says acting is as much fun as baseball.
   The 44-year-old performer's characterization of a tough-talking
private eye turned him into a star when the Broadway musical ``City
of Angels'' opened last week. Naughton, who has a long list of
stage and film credits, landed a plum Off-Broadway role as early as
1971 in ``Long Day's Journey Into Night'' with Geraldine Fitzgerald
and Stacy Keach.
   He acts, he says, because ``It's a lot of fun. It's the same
kind of fun as when I was a kid. And to be able to continue to do
that, it's sort of like playing baseball. You see these guys who
are 40 years old and they're stilll playing ball and they say, `I'm
the luckiest man in the world to be able to play this kids' game
for so long and so successfully.' And it's the same with acting.''
   Naughton played baseball at Brown University, but gave it up to
do graduate work at the Yale University Drama School.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gospel-pop singer Amy Grant was reported
doing well Monday after giving birth to her second child, a girl
named Gloria Mills Chapman.
   The 6-pound, 8-ounce baby was born Saturday night at a Nashville
hospital, said Chaz Corzine, a spokesman for the singer.
   The baby will be called ``Millie,'' Corzine said.
   The singer and her singer-songwriter husband Gary Chapman also
have a boy, Matthew, 2.
   Miss Grant is a four-time Grammy Award winner. Her albums
``Unguarded,'' ``Age to Age'' and ``A Christmas Album'' have all
sold more than 1 million copies apiece.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>FORT PAYNE, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The country band Alabama threw its
seventh annual Christmas for Kids party, and about 3,000 children
showed up.
   Lead singer Randy Owen, bassist Teddy Gentry, guitarist Jeff
Cook and drummer Mark Herndon performed traditional Christmas
songs, plus some of their own hits, at the Sunday afternoon party
in their hometown.
   People from Alabama, Tennessee, Georgia, Kentucky, Mississippi
and Texas traveled to Fort Payne for the festivities.
   Shara Odum, 8, of Atlanta, Ga., baked cookies for the band
members.
   ``I've been to this before,'' she said. ``They always give us so
much, so I thought I should give something back to them.''
   The Christmas for Kids Party is funded with money from the
group's annual June Jam concert in Fort Payne.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hollywood movie executive Jeff Sagansky, 37, was
named by CBS Monday as the president of its troubled entertainment
division.
   Sagansky, president of Tri-Star Pictures and a former top
programming executive at NBC, succeeds Kim LeMasters, who resigned
Nov. 30 after only two seasons as CBS Entertainment president.
   Sagansky will start work Jan. 1 as chief programmer for the
once-dominant network that has been third in prime time ratings for
two consecutive seasons. It has had no hits since ``Murder, She
Wrote'' in 1984, and is expected to be third again when the current
season ends.
   His successor as Tri-Star Pictures president was not announced.
Sagansky joined Tri-Star from NBC in 1985, but had been in his
current job only since March.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>RADNOR, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   CBS's ``Murphy Brown,'' the television
newswoman portrayed by Candice Bergen, isn't far off the mark but
she needs to work harder, her real-life counterparts say.
   ``Her personal life is fairly apropos of most women in the TV
business. We spend so much time working that by the time we get
home, there's not much left for anything else,'' said NBC ``Today''
show news anchor Deborah Norville, in response to a survey by TV
Guide.
   The portrayal of a ``blonde TV newswoman who's as tough as
nails'' is a breath of fresh reality, said Faith Daniels of ``CBS
This Morning.'' ``There's always some line you hear on the show and
then use. For weeks after Murphy used it, we went around at `This
Morning' saying, `Lighten up. It's only morning TV.'''
   But her professional life isn't all that tough, according to a
couple of pros quoted in the magazine's Dec. 23 issue.
   ``Professionally, Murphy's probably a better interviewer than
many women on TV. She also gets better answers,'' said Linda
Ellerbee, former ABC and NBC news anchor, CNN commentator and now
independent producer. ``As for her easy access to the high and
mighty, I don't have that sort of access, but Barbara Walters
does.''
   Murphy's ``personal life is more on the mark than the
professional part,'' said Lifetime's Jane Wallace. ``Most TV
journalists do much more work than Murphy.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>