<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1110EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-ChristianFlight Bjt   12-23 0866</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Christian Flight, Bjt,0893</SECOND>
<HEAD>Christians Fleeing the Birthplace of Christianity</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EILEEN ALT POWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When the Atallah family opened its shop selling
silver crucifixes and painted icons in Jerusalem's Old City four
decades ago, almost all the neighboring stores were owned by fellow
Arab Christians.
   Today, only 20 of the 200 shops that line Christian Quarter Road
remain in Christian hands, says George Atallah, who is Greek
Orthodox.
   ``The churches of Jerusalem could become museums if people keep
leaving,'' Atallah warned.
   A worrisome stream of emigration to the West has steadily
increased, encouraged by a rise in Moslem fundamentalism and the
pressures of the two-year Palestinian uprising.
   The uprising has caught the Christians in the middle. As
Palestinians, they are part of the anti-Israeli revolt. Their
children throw stones and are shot by soldiers. They suffer
economic hardship alongside the Moslems.
   But as the rebellion drags on without real gains, Islamic
fundamentalism is strengthening and Christian hopes for a secular
Palestinian state are fading.
   ``Christians wonder what they are going to do here if Islamic
forces continue to gain power,'' said Geries Khoury, director of a
Christian Palestinian research center near Bethlehem. ``Every day
people are losing hope.''
   The Christian community is particularly outraged at this week's
call by the Moslem fundamentalist Hamas movement for a general
strike on Christmas Day, and Christian leaders say it will not
block religious observance of the holiday.
   More than 30 Christian denominations have followers in the Holy
Land, led by the Greek Orthodox, Greek Catholic and Roman Catholic
churches.
   Monsignor Michel Sabbah, the first Arab to serve as the Roman
Catholic bishop of Jerusalem, believes the diverse Christian
community needs special nurturing to prosper.
   ``To be a Christian in this Holy Land is a special vocation,''
he said in an interview. ``It is a difficult life because of the
nature of the land _ always a land of wars, a land of hostility, a
land of minorities and majorities.''
   The Arab Christians, many descendants of the first followers of
Christ, have been a troubled minority in the Holy Land since the
Moslem conquest in the 7th century.
   In recent decades the Christians have been further overwhelmed
by Jewish immigration and the Moslems' high birthrate.
   Israeli experts estimate that in 1947, there were about 650,000
Jews, 1.1 million Moslems and 150,000 Christians in
British-mandatory Palestine.
   Since the founding of the Jewish state in 1948, the Jewish
population has increased nearly six-fold, and the Moslems have more
than doubled. But the Christian community, numbering just 140,000
in Israel and the occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip, is smaller
than it was four decades ago, government statistics show.
   Palestinian leaders insist the number is even lower, noting
traditionally Christian towns like Bethlehem and Ramallah now have
Moslem majorities. In Jerusalem, many Christians retain their
property but live abroad.
   An official of Israel's Ministry of Religious Affairs said the
government's policy is to protect and encourage the Christians.
   ``The West was always very interested in the fate of the
Christians,'' he said. ``Israel wanted good relations with the
West, with the Christian world, so it was in our own interest to
watch out for the Christians.''
   The official, who insisted on anonymity, blamed the Christians'
increasing minority status on a low birthrate and the ``mixed
blessing'' of ties to Western churches that anger fundamentalists.
   The Palestinian uprising has heightened the Christians' problems.
   Many Christians, well-educated in church schools and often from
prosperous merchant families, found the deteriorating economy too
much to bear, says George Shamas, a Syrian Orthodox writer who has
immigrated to the United States.
   ``Job opportunities are not available,'' Shamas said. ``Life is
more difficult, and people don't want to be stopped by soldiers and
searched and jailed day in and day out.''
   Still, many Christians take seriously their longstanding role as
leaders of Arab nationalism. The Christian town of Beit Sahour has
been an example, carrying out a much publicized tax revolt and
boycott of Israeli-made products.
   But Joseph, a Beit Sahour Christian who has been jailed several
times in the uprising, worries that Moslem Palestinians do not
appreciate the Christian contribution.
   ``There are efforts by some Islamic groups to exclude us, or
maybe to limit our role in the uprising,'' he said, asking that his
last name not be used.
   He added: ``You hear that Christians are going to be equal to
the Moslems if independence comes in the future, but I am sure that
in reality it will not be the case.''
   Islamic fundamentalism also is growing among Israeli Arabs, fed
by what Moslems feel is discrimination by the Jewish state.
Municipal elections last year gave big gains to fundamentalist
candidates.
   Christian Arabs in Israel have responded by forming a ``union of
churches'' in the coastal town of Haifa and the northern Galilee to
protect their position.
   Khoury, the Christian researcher, says Christians in the
occupied territories also must ensure their place in a future
Palestinian state. He calls on churches to play an active role in
the uprising, as Moslem mosques do.
   ``I am not seeking a Christian solution,'' Khoury insists. ``I
am seeking a Palestinian solution that includes Christians.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>