<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0132EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>b i AM-Panama-Fighting 3rdLd-Writethru a0434 12-20 0427</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Fighting, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0434,0436</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Fighting In Panama; U.S. Troops Move Toward Military Headquarters</HEAD>
<UNK>Eds: ADDS details on U.S. attempts to oust Noriega. U.S. troop strength
in the country. No pickup</UNK>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mortar, machine-gun and cannon fire
was heard in the capital Tuesday night as U.S. tanks and truckloads
of American troops headed toward Panama's military headquarters.
   Planes and helicopters were flying over the city.
   The movement indicated U.S. forces were attempting to force
Panama's military leader Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega out of power.
   ABC-TV quoted Panamanian armed forces television as reporting
that the U.S. military had been ordered into action against the
Panamanian Defense Forces.
   It said gunfire and explosions were heard in the vicinity of
Defense Forces headquarters, where Noriega has offices. Gunfire was
heard near the U.S. base Fort Clayton, 6 miles north of the city.
   Three young Panamanian soldiers told an Associated Press
reporter in the capital ``There is all kinds of hell loose out
there.''
   The reporter saw 24 U.S. tanks and at least four trucks carrying
American troops head in the direction of Panamanian Defense Forces
headquarters.
   Troops in olive uniforms ran through the luxury Marriott Hotel
and lights in the hotel went out.
   Channel 8, television station of the U.S. Southern Command,
issued an Echo level alert, its highest, and said movement by
unauthorized U.S. personnel was prohibited.
   The United States has tried to oust Noriega with economic and
political pressure since he was indicted on federal drug
trafficking charges in February 1988. U.S. sanctions have depressed
the economy, but have not budged Noriega, and two coup attempts _
most recently in October _ failed to unseat him.
   U.S. troops in Panama had been on maximum alert and restricted
to base since a U.S. Marine lieutenant was killed by Panamanians on
Saturday in what American officials called an unprovoked incident.
   There had been reports all day Tuesday of unusual U.S. troop and
military plane movement in Panama and the United States.
   The United States maintains 12,000 troops in Panama, at
installations including Fort Clayton, Fort Amador _ a joint
U.S.-Panamanian base across a causeway from the capital and U.S.
Southern Command headquarters at Quarry Heights, bordering the
capital to the west.
   The Panamanian Defense Forces has 15,000 regular troops but
Noriega has also armed citizen ``Dignity Battalians'' of his
loyalists.
   Noriega accuses the United States of trying to oust him so it
can renege on 1977 treaties under which Washington is to cede
control of the Panama Canal by the end of the century.
</TEXT>

</DOC>