<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0453EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Flight103-US     12-22 0506</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Flight 103-US,0519</SECOND>
<HEAD>Flight 103 Anniversary Services Mix Sorrow and Anger</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Bells tolled and candles flickered in memory of those killed on
Pan Am Flight 103, but sorrow mixed with anger for some of the
mourners who feel their loved ones fell victim to inadequate
warning of the terrorist bombing.
   Memorial services in several Eastern cities and in Lockerbie,
Scotland, marked the first anniversary of the Dec. 21 disaster that
occurred when a bomb splintered the New York-bound 747, killing all
259 aboard and 11 on the ground.
   To the bereaved, as to the world at large, the tragedy seemed
more dreadful because it came at the height of holiday
preparations. Mary Mann, a friend of 20-year-old victim Julianne
Kelly, described the feeling to 500 mourners at St. Susanna's Roman
Catholic Church in Dedham, Mass.:
   ``On a day that began with making plans to attend Chistmas Mass,
we received word that Pan Am Flight 103 had exploded. Our holiday
season will never again be as happy as it was before the tragedy.''
   In North Adams, Mass., candles set in brown paper bags lined the
walkways to St. Francis of Assissi Church, where the names of all
the victims were read at a service for native Wendy Amy Lincoln, 23.
   Church bells pealed for the dead at 2:02 p.m. EST in Greensburg,
Pa., and Ramsey, N.J., among other places. Services were held in
New York City, Washington, D.C., and Ridgefield, Conn.
   In Lockerbie, a line of lanterns _ one for each victim _
flickered against a granite memorial dedicated before grieving
relatives and residents in a 19th century graveyard.
   Pan Am held memorial services at airports in New York, London
and Frankfurt, and employees observed a moment of silence at 2:02
p.m., said spokeswoman Pamela Hanlon.
   For some the anniversary was a time to vent anger at the airline
and the government for their perceived failure to warn travelers,
to detect the bomb hidden in a radio-cassette player, to prevent
the mass murder or to catch the terrorists responsible.
   In New York, about 50 of the 330 who attended services at St.
George's Episcopal Church held a silent march outside Pan Am's
offices, carrying signs with messages like, ``Pan Am Flight 103,
the truth must be known.''
   ``The pain will never go away and we have a great deal of
bitterness and emptiness at the lack of support from the
government,'' Jack Schultz, father of victim Thomas, 20, said at
the Connecticut service.
   In the year since the crash, relatives of the dead formed a
group called The Vicitims of Pan Am Flight 103 to work for better
airport security and press the government on the case.
   ``We feel this is a commitment we have made to our son's memory
and we must struggle to do everything we possibly can,'' said Doris
Cory of Old Lyme, Conn., whose son, Scott, was one of 35 Syracuse
University students killed. ``In this instance, my husband and I
feel this was a preventable terrorist act.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>