<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0194 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1231EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f BC-TickerTalk Adv01   12-29 0616</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Ticker Talk, Adv 01,0635</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv 01</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Monday, Jan 1</HEAD>
<HEAD>Ahead to the '90s: Stock Traders Seek To Dodge Recession Risk</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHET CURRIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As the economy heads into choppy waters in 1990,
many investors will try to ride out the storm with what they hope
are recession-resistant stock portfolios.
   For the last several months, managers at investing institutions
have been putting their money in stocks whose fortunes appear least
exposed to the ups and downs of the business cycle.
   At the same time, they have been shunning auto, steel and other
industrial issues that would presumably be most affected by the
first general economic slump since the 1981-82 recession.
   ``The economy's slowing down, no question about it,'' says Peter
Lynch, who runs the Fidelity Magellan Fund, the nation's largest
stock mutual fund with $12.4 billion in assets. ``When that happens
cyclical stocks just don't do very well.''
   The risk of an economy-wide slump ``is higher than at any time
since the 1982 recession,'' says Martin Sass, president of M.D.
Sass Investors Services Inc., an independent money-management firm
with $3.8 billion in accounts.
   Still, Sass assigns only a 25 percent probability to that
outcome, and says he believes lower interest rates and inflation
can help bring new life in 1990 to Wall Street's bull market.
   ``Certainly it's not the early innings of the ball game,'' he
observes. ``But I think there's still some more room here.''
   It's no simple trick to devise a stock-picking strategy for
gains in a rising market while minimizing exposure to losses should
prices decline.
   The traditional way to do that is to concentrate on
``defensive'' stocks like high-yielding utilities and those of
companies with steady, year-in, year-out earnings growth.
   So it comes as no surprise that ``consumer noncyclical'' and
utility stocks ranked first and second in 1989 among the eight
sectors of the stock market tracked by Dow Jones &amp; Co.
   From the end of 1988 through Dec. 26, the consumer noncyclical
index rose 37.86 percent, while the overall Dow Jones equity market
index posted a 24.27 percent gain. The utility index climbed 34.34
percent.
   That struck a marked contrast with increases of just 15.65
percent for the industrial sector, and 5.1 percent for technology
stocks.
   Lynch says those divergent trends have lifted the big-name
consumer stocks to expensive levels. Cyclical stocks may look
cheaper, he says, but they could go lower still if the business
outlook keeps darkening.
   ``I'm still buying stocks every day, but I've been letting cash
build up'' to about 11 percent of the Magellan Fund's assets, he
says. ``I'm not finding many outstanding, attractive bargains.''
   Sass, for his part, thinks the time has come to buy cyclical
issues in such industries as paper, aluminum, steel and chemicals.
   ``The cyclical stocks have gotten killed,'' he asserts. ``Many
of them are trading at levels that already discount a recession, in
my view.
   ``These companies have gotten more lean, more efficient. But the
stocks are very much out of favor, and hardly anyone is
recommending them.''
   Sass pins his hopes that a recession can be avoided partly on
what he sees as a renewed easing of inflationary pressures as the
economy slows. ``The inflation rate could be a positive surprise''
in 1990, he says.
   He also argues that slowdowns in the pace of business can keep
occurring in separate areas of the economy, as they did through
much of the 1980s, without bringing on a recession.
   ``These rolling readjustments,'' he concludes, ``will permit the
long U.S. expansion which began in late 1982 to enter its eight
consecutive year, the longest peacetime expansion on record.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Monday, Jan 1</NOTE>

</DOC>