<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0184 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0040EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-BusinessHighlights     12-19 0751</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Business Highlights,0787</SECOND>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bush administration, under mounting
pressure to increase the pace of its savings and loan bailout, will
tell regulators to start immediately on the huge task of selling
more than $300 billion in S&amp;L assets.
   A strategic plan developed by the Resolution Trust Corp.
Oversight Board directs regulators to begin selling real estate and
other assets even before the government officially closes the S&amp;Ls
owning the assets.
   A copy of the plan was obtained Monday by The Associated Press.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation's Big Three automakers are slashing
January production and laying off more than 107,000 workers as they
struggle with shrinking demand.
   Most of the layoffs, some of which were announced Monday, will
come during the first two weeks of 1990 as traditional Christmas
breaks are extended.
   __
   NEW YORK (AP) _ Former stock speculator Salim B. Lewis was
spared a prison term for stock manipulation by a federal judge who
ordered him to work in a drug rehabilitation clinic, saying ``your
skills should not be wasted.''
   Lewis, a prominent Wall Street veteran whose downfall resulted
indirectly from the Ivan Boesky insider trading scandal, was placed
on three years of probation and fined $250,000 Monday after
pleading guilty to three counts for illegally inflating the price
of Fireman's Fund Corp. stock in May 1986.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Marriott Corp., deciding to concentrate on its
flourishing hotel and service divisions, announced a restructuring
that calls for the sale of its weaker fast-food and family
restaurant divisions.
   The nation's largest hotel company also said Monday it would
reorganize its corporate staff, laying off an as-yet undetermined
number of workers, and buy back 10 million of its shares.
   Marriott said the restructuring would result in as much as $325
million in pre-tax charges against its fourth-quarter earnings.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Reviving a plan to shrink operations by about a
third, Eastern Airlines told creditors it expects to sell its
prized Latin American routes and projected a net loss of $250
million for the fourth quarter.
   At a meeting Monday in New York, Eastern officials presented
major creditors with a revised business plan that takes into
account the sale of the Latin American routes.
   The plan reverts to an April proposal for restructuring Eastern
at about two-thirds its pre-strike size. With the Latin American
routes, the airline would have remained 80 percent to 90 percent of
its original size.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Arctic temperatures in the nation's midsection
are boosting last-minute holiday travel to warmer climes during the
peak Christmas and New Year's season, and airlines have aided the
cold-weather flight by lifting advance-purchase requirements,
travel agents said.
   The agents said Monday a trend to shorter vacations that can be
booked with short notice has been encouraged by the recent cold
weather in much of the country.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Securities and Exchange Commission Chairman
Richard C. Breeden said he is creating an International Affairs
office, going to Japan next month and worrying about inter-agency
squabbles over new financial products because of increasing
internationalization of securities markets.
   Breeden announced the new office at a news conference Monday
where he reported on cooperative agreements reached last week with
securities regulators in France and the Netherlands.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BRUSSELS, Belgium (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The European Community, angered by U.S.
efforts to circumvent a ban on hormone-treated beef, has asked the
United States to slash retaliatory duties imposed in the trade
dispute.
   An official said Monday the 12-nation trading bloc wants the
tariffs reduced because of legislation requiring U.S. commissaries
in Europe to buy their beef from American _ not European _
producers. Commissaries are stores for U.S. military and other
personnel.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BRUSSELS, Belgium (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard A.
Shevardnadze signed a far-reaching trade agreement with the
European Community, a major step toward getting needed Western help
for his nation's ailing economy.
   Shevardnadze, who signed the agreement Monday, called the
10-year accord _ the first between Moscow and the 12-nation trading
bloc _ ``truly innovative.''
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The stock market took its sharpest drop in five weeks Monday,
sending the Dow Jones average of 30 industrials down 42.02 to
2,697.53, its biggest single-day loss since it dropped 47.34 points
on Nov. 6.
   The dollar was mixed in lackluster trdaing.
   Bond prices finished mostly higher.
   Heating oil and oter energy futures prices soared; precious
metals were lower; livestock futures were mixed; and grains and
soybeans were mostly lower.
</TEXT>

</DOC>