<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0128 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 2132EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Livingston 1stLd-Writethru a0675 12-26 0518</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Livingston, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0675,0531</SECOND>
<HEAD>Joseph Livingston, Pulitzer-Winning Financial Columnist, Dies at
84</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS grafs 5-6, bgn `Livingston started...,' to clarify that
Livingston's survey was twice yearly, and his column ran twice weekly.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PIPERSVILLE, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Joseph A. Livingston, a Pulitzer
Prize-winning reporter whose ``Business Outlook'' column appeared
in more than 50 newspapers across the country, has died at age 84.
   Livingston's wife, Rosalie, said she found her husband collapsed
Monday near the doorway of their farmhouse in Pipersville, 35 miles
north of Philadelphia. He was taken to Doylestown Hospital, where
he was pronounced dead.
   A hospital spokeswoman declined to give any details of
Livingston's death Tuesday.
   ``He was one of the outstanding journalists of his time,'' said
Eugene L. Roberts Jr., executive editor of The Philadelphia
Inquirer and president of Philadelphia Newspapers Inc.
   Livingston started his twice-weekly column in 1945 and used the
Inquirer as his base from 1972 until his death. He also was
financial editor of the now-defunct Bulletin in Philadelphia from
1948 to 1968, and held the same title briefly at the Philadelphia
Record before that newspaper closed in 1947.
   The Inquirer said Livingston's twice-yearly survey of economists
was one of the nation's first consensus economic forecasts.
   He won his Pulitzer in 1964 for a series of articles titled
``The Power Pull of the Dollar.'' They described how communist
countries, particularly those of Eastern Europe, were being pulled
toward the West by a variety of economic forces.
   Livingston received a number of other awards in business
journalism, including the Loeb Award four times, the Hancock Award
three times and the Overseas Press Club award for excellence in
business reporting from abroad three times.
   Livingston said he developed an interest in economics after he
and a group of friends got together one night and decided to invest
jointly in the stock market. That was in September 1929. The stock
market crashed the next month, heralding the Great Depression.
   ``I decided then that I ought to find out more about business
and finance,'' Livingston once said.
   He took courses at City College of New York and became editor of
a business publication called the New York Daily Investment News.
   In 1935, he became editor and economist at Business Week, a post
he held for seven years. While there, he successfully argued in
favor of writing about the U.S. interest in the war in Europe.
   ``I was a pariah among the isolationists,'' he said. ``But I
said it was our war, that we should enter into it, that it would be
a disaster for Hitler to win.''
   After the United States entered the war, Livingston went to
Washington to work as an economist for the War Production Board and
later the Office of War Mobilization and Reconversion.
   He began his column in 1945, when his first client was The
Washington Post. He started his survey of economists in 1946.
   In 1978, the Philadelphia Federal Reserve computerized the
information from Livingston's previous surveys and today continues
to produce the Livingston survey.
   He is survived by his wife and a daughter, Patricia Herban, and
a grandson.
</TEXT>

</DOC>