<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1632EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Christmas-Queen     12-25 0495</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Christmas-Queen,0508</SECOND>
<HEAD>Queen Says All Nations Should Learn To Love Their Neighbors</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-World Christmas, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Queen Elizabeth II said in her annual Christmas
broadcast that ``it would be splendid'' if all nations learned to
love their neighbors and united to save the Earth from further
environmental damage.
   The queen also spoke of ``the exciting news'' that barriers
between Eastern and Western Europe were coming down and people on
both sides were beginning to think about their future as neighbors.
   ``It's still hard for us to be sure what is going to happen as a
result of these great events, but it would be splendid to think
that in the last years of the 20th century Christ's message about
loving our neighbors as ourselves might at last be heeded,'' she
said in the 11-minute broadcast.
   She addressed her message particularly to children in the
49-nation Commonwealth of Britain and its former colonies, saying
they brought out the best in grown-ups and ``part of that `best' in
us could be a particular tenderness towards this Earth which we
share as human beings.''
   ``If we can reduce selfishness and jealously, dishonesty and
injustice, the 90s can become a time of peace and tranquillity for
children and grown-ups, and a time for working together for the
benefit of our planet as a whole.''
   The queen broke a tradition of keeping her message secret until
Christmas by delivering part of it to an audience of 6,000 at
London's Royal Albert Hall last Tuesday night.
   Spotlighted in the hall's vast arena, the queen explained that
she wanted to use the presence of 2,000 children at the
fund-raising gala for the Save the Children charity to send a
special message to all children in the Commonwealth.
   A group of youngsters, whose parents work for Commonwealth high
commissions or embassies in London, were allowed to ask the queen
questions during intermission.
   She told them she found her crown ``quite heavy,'' admitted she
was sometimes nervous in front of big crowds and said she liked to
believe in Father Christmas, the English name for Santa Claus.
   One small girl asked, ``Do you like being the queen?'' The queen
replied indirectly, saying, ``It's a very busy life.''
   Another child asked, rather shyly: ``What are you going to buy
Prince William for Christmas?''
   With the 7-year-old prince, son of Prince Charles and Princess
Diana, hovering in the background, the queen neatly sidestepped,
replying: ``I don't think I had better say it too loudly. He might
hear me.''
   In her message, the queen said she received many letters from
people worried about the greenhouse effect caused by warming of the
Earth's atmosphere, crop devastation caused by floods and drought,
and the destruction of forests.
   ``These problems ... make neighboring cooperation throughout the
world a pressing necessity,'' she said. ``... The great thing to
remember is that it is not too late to reduce the damage if we
change our attitudes and behavior.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>