<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0148 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1602EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Romania 15thLd-Writethru a0710 12-22 1269</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania, 15th Ld-Writethru, a0710,1306</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Romania's Hard-line Government Overthrown; Fighting Continues</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE with further reports on Ceausescu's whereabouts,
his son shown on state TV, captured and bloodied. No pickup.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto FRA14</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALISON SMALE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An outraged nation today drove Romanian
President Nicolae Ceausescu from power, but forces loyal to the
Communist hard-liner staged a counterattack and battled for control
of the country.
   There were conflicting reports about Ceausescu's whereabouts.
One report said he was arrested while fleeing the country, another
said he had escaped, and a third said he was holed up in a town
northeast of Bucharest.
   Ceausescu's son Nicu, former Communist Party chief in the south
Transylvanian town of Sibiu, was captured and shown on Romanian
television.
   A uniformed man and a civilian held his arms and said he would
be brought to trial. Nicu had a little swelling and traces of blood
above his left eye. He was being pushed around as he was led away.
The uniformed man said Nicu had left Sibiu giving orders to
security forces loyal to his father not to shoot.
   In Bucharest, the presidential palace was on fire, and
demonstrators waved Romanian flags in front of the burning building
as gunfire rang out. Reporters in the city said the Central
Committee building also was damaged.
   Yugoslav television reported hundreds killed. It did not cite
sources.
   The counterattack began after rallies by hundreds of thousands
of people in the streets of Bucharest and other cities to celebrate
Ceausescu's ouster after 24 years of hard-line rule.
   Romanian television said about 2,000 pro-Ceausescu forces moved
into the capital, and radio reports said loyalists were also
fighting for control in Brasov, a city 90 miles to the north.
   Romanian radio, which was taken over by protesters earlier
today, reported ``fierce battles'' between army troops and
pro-Ceausescu forces that it branded ``terrorists.''
   ``Eventually, the terrorists surrendered, but there are other
attempts to crush our revolution in other parts of the city,'' an
unidentified man said on the radio.
   Ceausescu was toppled by a popular revolt that lasted less than
a week but that is believed to have claimed the lives of thousands
of anti-government demonstrators.
   The upheaval in Romania comes at the close of a remarkable year
during which the hard-line leaderships of Poland, Hungary,
Czechoslovakia, East Germany and Bulgaria were ousted by massive
protests and replaced by reformers.
   By early evening, anti-Ceausescu appeared to have gained the
upper hand, with radio reporting that security forces had laid down
their arms. ``Criminal elements were neutralized or arrested,'' the
radio reported tersely.
   But shortly after 7 p.m. (noon EST), news media said
pro-Ceausescu forces were attacking Bucharest. ``Dead and wounded
are reported from all parts of city,'' the Czechoslovak news agency
CTK said.
   The Soviet news agency Tass said there was heavy shooting in
Bucharest.
   Television said Bucharest jails had been opened by the
anti-Ceausescu supporters. Engineer Nicu Stefanescu, one of those
released, said that thousands of people had been arrested Thursday
night during the huge unrest that forced Ceausescu to flee.
   Even children were detained, he said, reporting that there were
so many wounded in the jail that blood was seen in the corridors.
   News reports said Ceausescu, 71, and his wife and second-in
command, Elena, fled their palace by helicopter. Romanian
television, urging everybody in the country to stop the ruler
fleeing, said they landed at the Titu military airport outside
Bucharest, then fled by car.
   Television reported first that they had been seized near the
town of Tirgoviste, 45 miles northwest of Bucharest. Minutes later,
television cast doubt on its report, saying Ceausescu apparently
fled again.
   The Romanian news agency Agerpres said Ceausescu had been
arrested, but it appeared to be referring the first, outdated TV
report.
   A later report from the Yugoslav news agency Tanjug said he was
holed up at the town of Trgoviste. Then, in the evening, Romanian
television announced without further detail that Ceausescu and his
wife Elena had left the country.
   Earlier reports described fierce fighting between army troops
and paramilitary police in Sibiu, where Ceausescu's son had ruled.
``A massacre is going on,'' an unidentified general said on
state-controlled media.
   Later, an unidentified general, who may have been the same
officer, claimed that fighting had ceased throughout the country.
   Corneliu Manescu, a 73-year-old former foreign minister, said on
Romanian television that he was head of a provisional government
that would stay in power until free elections could be held, the
East German news agency said.
   Manescu has for many months been under house arrest in an
agro-industrial complex in the vicinity of Bucharest, informed
sources said. In March, he and five other senior officials sharply
criticized the Ceausescu leadership.
   The Romanian state news agency Agerpres, which announced the end
of censorship and promised truthful reporting in the future, said
Ion Iliescu, a former Central Committee secretary ousted by
Ceausescu in 1971, had announced on television that a ``National
Salvation Front'' had been set up.
   Speaking from a balcony of the Central Committee building in
Bucharest, Iliescu told a jubilant crowd there were reports the
ousted ruler had been arrested near Tirgoviste.
   ``If these reports are confirmed, he will be arrested and
submitted to public justice,'' Iliescu said.
   Hundreds of thousands of people were in the streets of Bucharest
and in the streets of Timisoara, the west Romanian city where
troops fired on protesters last weekend, igniting the week of the
nationwide revolt against Ceausescu's autocratic rule.
   An Associated Press reporter said from Timisoara that the entire
city appeared to be on the streets.
   ``This is something we never expected to happen. The dictator is
gone,'' Ingeborg Kziraska said in front of a cathedral where she
said more than 30 children were gunned down Sunday during protests.
   Reports from Timisoara put the deaths during the week of
protests in the city at between 2,000 and 4,500.
   The two other countries in East Europe that are not part of the
Soviet bloc are Albania, which remains a hard-line socialist state,
and Yugoslavia, which has been torn by ethnic unrest that has
overshadowed reform proposals.
   Ceausescu was the last hard-line Soviet alliance leader. With
his family he strictly controlled the spartan society he had built
and refused to adopt reforms despite chronic shortages of food and
energy that made life miserable for most Romanians.
   He apparently felt so secure with the dominance of his cult of
personality that he traveled to Iran earlier this week during the
growing protests, and held a pro-government rally on Thursday that
turned into a huge chorus of denunciations of his rule.
   Ceausescu tried one more time to address crowds before fleeing
from his palace, the Bulgarian news agency BTA reported. He was
shouted down with cries of ``Death, Death,'' the agency said.
   While still in Ceausescu's hands, Romanian radio reported early
today that defense minister Vasile Milea had committed suicide and
blamed him for the national unrest. But a later radio report denied
that.
   The uprising began on Dec. 15 with a few hundred people
defending an ethnic Hungarian pastor threatened with arrest in
Timisoara. The protests swelled last weekend, with thousands of
protesters chanting for more food and the overthrow of Ceausescu.
   Security forces massacred hundreds, possibly thousands, of
unarmed civilians in Timisoara last Sunday. The Hungarian news
agency MTI reported today that two mass graves containing 632
bodies had been found outside Timisoara, while Czechoslovak media
gave the latest death toll as 4,700.
   Other Romanian cities, learning of the reported massacre, also
staged anti-Ceausescu protests during the last week.
</TEXT>

</DOC>