<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0173 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1954EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-Spies 1stLd-Writethru a0693 12-20 0314</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Spies, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0693,0318</SECOND>
<HEAD>East, West Germany Begin Exchanging Spies</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to UPDATE with major spy exchanges already
occurring; picks up 5th graf pvs, `East German...'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BONN, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   East Germany and West Germany have
begun a major exchange of convicted spies, government security
officials said Wednesday.
   The officials, who spoke on condition of anomyity, said East
Germany has begun releasing about 25 imprisoned Westerners, some of
whom were serving life sentences.
   West Germany will release four former Communist agents in
return, they said.
   The four include two top catches of West German
counterintelligence efforts: Margret Hoeke, an ex-secretary to West
Germany's president, and Elke Falk, a former secretary in the
chancellor's offices.
   Pardons for the two women were announced earlier in the day by a
spokesman for West German President Richard von Weizsaecker. The
spokesman, Gernot Fritz, said he did not know if they had been
released from prison.
   The two women have said, however, that they don't want to be
handed over to East Germany and they won't be forced to leave West
Germany, security officials said.
   Officials did not release the names of any other agents being
released.
   East German Premier Hans Modrow and West German Chancellor
Helmut Kohl met in Dresden, East Germany, on Tuesday and said there
were plans to release as many political prisoners as possible
before Christmas.
   Ms. Hoeke was convicted in 1987 of spying for East Germany and
sentenced to eight years in prison. She had worked in the offices
of several West German presidents, including Weizsaecker, before
her arrest in August 1985.
   Ms. Falk, was convicted of spying for the Soviet KGB in 1989 and
sentenced to 6{ years in prison. She had worked as a secretary in
the offices of the chancellor, the transport ministry and economic
cooperation ministry before her arrest in 1988.
</TEXT>

</DOC>