<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0135 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1746EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Sudan-Plane     12-21 0363</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sudan-Plane,0372</SECOND>
<HEAD>Plane Shot Down in Sudan, 4 Humanitarian Workers Killed</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS throughout to UPDATE with government accusing rebels of
shooting down plane, U.N. comment, details. No pickup.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NAIROBI, Kenya (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A plane carrying four humanitarian workers
from a southern Sudan town that is surrounded by rebels was shot
down Thursday shortly after takeoff, and all aboard were killed, a
United Nations source said.
   In the Sudanese capital of Khartoum, a statement by the Armed
Forces General Command accused rebels of the Sudan People's
Liberation Army of downing the plane with a Sam-7 missile.
   The U.N. source, who refused to be identified, said the
twin-engine plane was headed for Khartoum from Aweil when it was
downed by ground fire, the source said.
   Aweil, 590 miles southwest of Khartoum, is a government garrison
town said to be surrounded by rebels of the Sudan People's
Liberation Army.
   The source said three of the victims were French nationals, the
fourth a Sudanese. He was unable to provide names, but said the
doctor and nurse worked for Doctors Without Frontiers, a French
organization.
   Officials at the Paris-based organization identified the dead as
Yvon Feliot, a pilot working for the humanitarian group; Laurent
Fernet, a supply specialist; and Jean-Paul Bescond, a doctor, all
French nationals. The fourth was Frazer Ariyaba, a Sudanese
technician for the World Food Program.
   The Sudanese army statement said the plane's four passengers
were ``humanitarian messengers who devoted their lives to the
service of man in his most difficult times.''
   It said the downing of the plane was aimed at undermining peace
efforts and destabilizing the country.
   The plane belonged to the Sudanese government, the U.N. source
said. He said it was not clear what type of weapon was used to down
the plane or who fired it.
   The rebels have been battling the Moslem-dominated government in
Khartoum for six years in an effort to win greater autonomy and
economic benefits for the largely Christian south.
   In New York, U.N. Secretary-General Javier Perez de Cuellar said
he was grieved by the incident and called on the government and
rebels to ``reinstitute a cease-fire and ensure safe passage for
the humanitarian assistance.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>