<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1408EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Panama-Civilian 2ndLd-Writethru a0623 12-21 0355</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Civilian, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0623,0359</SECOND>
<HEAD>American Civilian Killed in Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 4th graf pvs, `Her husband ...' with relative saying husband
was a civilian.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DIXON, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An American schoolteacher who lived most of
her life in Panama was killed by stray machine-gun fire from
Panamanian forces during the early hours of the U.S. invasion, the
State Department said today.
   Candy Helin, a 43-year-old whose husband is a former Dixon
resident, was the only U.S. civilian reported killed in the attack
begun early Wednesday.
   Mrs. Helin was a teacher of gifted students at a U.S. government
school and is the daughter of a former Army port commander, family
members said.
   Her husband, Steve Helin, 45, is a civilian financial analyst
for the Panamerica Commission, an organization that oversees
operation of the Panama Canal, his sister said. The former U.S.
soldier has lived in Panama since 1962, when he joined the Army,
according to his family.
   Douglas Rose, a spokesman for the State Department's Panama Task
Force, said today that Mrs. Helin was killed by stray fire from the
Panamanian Defense Forces. He said he had no additional details of
her death.
   Helin's sister Jane Sheaffer of Dixon said Helin told her that
his wife was killed in an ambush near the Albrook Air Force Base as
the couple drove home on a dark road early Wednesday from dinner at
a friend's.
   ``Obviously, he's really distraught _ distraught, angry and
everything else, I suppose,'' Dean Sheaffer, Sheaffer's husband,
said of Helin. ``It just doesn't seem real. She was murdered by the
Panamanian government.''
   Mrs. Helin was told recently her teaching position was being
eliminated next year, but Mrs. Sheaffer said she did not know if
that meant the couple had planned on returning to the United States.
   The couple have two children, Stephanie, 16, and Tracey, 20,
family members said.
   Mrs. Sheaffer said her brother told her he did not know of the
impending danger. Mrs. Scheaffer said a memo warning U.S. civilians
to restrict their movements came after Helin had left work for the
day on Tuesday.
</TEXT>

</DOC>