<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0031EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-US-Romania     12-25 0517</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-Romania,510</SECOND>
<HEAD>Baker Says No U.S. Objections If Soviets Intervene in Romania</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRYAN BRUMLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A top Soviet official rules out military
intervention in Romania, but Secretary of State James A. Baker III
says the Bush administration would not object if Soviet troops
helped revolutionaries battling loyalists to deposed communist
despot Nicolae Ceausescu.
   Romanians are ``attempting to put off the yoke of a very, very
oppressive and repressive dictatorship, so I think that we would be
inclined probably to follow the lead, follow the example of France,
who today has said that if the Warsaw Pact felt it necessary to
intervene on behalf of the opposition, that it would support
that,'' Baker said Sunday on the NBC-TV program ``Meet the Press.''
   Dutch government officials also said they would not oppose
Soviet or Warsaw Pact military intervention if it would ``support
the aspirations of the Romanian people.''
   However, Soviet Premier Nikolai I. Ryshkov said Saturday that
sending the Red Army to Romania would be ``impermissible'' and a
repetition of past mistakes.
   U.S. officials by late Sunday detected no sign of foreign
intervention in Romania, where fierce fighting continued between
Ceausescu backers and the National Salvation Committee, said
Defense Secretary Dick Cheney.
   ``It is obviously our hope that the pro-reform forces will win,
but it's still a very hairy situation, a great deal of violence,
and I would think that the outcome is probably still in doubt,''
Cheney said on the ABC-TV program ``This Week With David Brinkley.''
   ``We haven't seen any sign of any outside intervention,'' said
Cheney.
   President Bush, speaking briefly to reporters in Washington,
said the British ambassador to Romania took refuge in the U.S.
Embassy in Bucharest because his embassy was destroyed.
   ``The British Embassy was razed and so the British ambassador is
now our guest, I understand. So that has been a very traumatic
pre-Christmas uprising,'' Bush said after speaking by telephone
with the U.S. ambassador to Bucharest, Alan Green.
   The French offered to send volunteers to fight for Romania's
National Salvation Committee. Baker, asked whether America was
prepared to send U.S. troops into Romania, said any such decision
would rest with Bush.
   White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater told reporters later,
``We don't have any indication that there is a chance of the
Soviets' going in, at least not at this time. So we don't expect
that to occur.''
   Asked about Baker's comment, Fitzwater added: ``We could see a
situation that might be severe enough where there'd be a need to
help establish law and order.'' But he said that it ``certainly is
not necessary now and does not appear to be necessary.''
   Baker said U.S. officials were in contact with the
revolutionaries but he declined to give specifics.
   ``We've had some discussions with representatives of the new
group and we've been encouraging in our comments and frankly we
would like to see this be resolved in as peaceful a fashion as
possible, but we think it is important that there be a move toward
freedom and greater political pluralism in Romania,'' Baker said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>