<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0192 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1209EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-Campbell-Dorrance 3rdLd-Writethru f0075 12-28 0330</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Campbell-Dorrance, 3rd Ld-Writethru, f0075,0339</SECOND>
<HEAD>Investor Group Pushing For Campbell Soup Sale</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf to fix spelling of `nieces' and 6th graf to UPDATE
with noon stock price</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIVIAN MARINO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three members of the family that founded
Campbell Soup Co. disclosed today they would sell their 17 percent
stake and urge a sale of the entire food-products company.
   The announcement intensified speculation that Campbell, the
company that founded condensed soup popular with millions of people
around the world, would be put on the auction block due to a rift
among family members who control it.
   An investor group pushing for the sale, composed of nieces of
Campbell's late chairman John T. Dorrance Jr., said in documents it
planned to file with the Securities and Exchange Commission that it
was seeking ``a price per share significantly in excess of current
market value.''
   The group also said it actively would encourage Campbell's board
of directors to do the same and would consider trying to oust
members opposed to the sale.
   James H. Moran, a spokesman for Camden, N.J.-based Campbell,
said the company had no comment on today's announcement.
   Wall Street, however, responded enthusiastically. On the New
York Stock Exchange, Campbell soared $3.75 to $56.75 in active noon
trading.
   ``It's not particularly surprising,'' Pavlos M. Alexandrakis, an
industry analyst with Argus Research in New York, said of the
Dorrance familiy announcement. ``There has been a split among the
family members for some time.''
   Alexandrakis said those pushing for the sale of Campbell
probably had little interest left in running the company, and with
the right price could draft other family member to their cause.
   He described Campbell as a laggard in the food industry, slow to
update facilities and products.
   Heirs of Campbell founder John Dorrance Sr., Dorrance's father,
control about 59 percent of Campbell's 129.6 million outstanding
common shares. Speculation about their intentions have grown since
Dorrance Jr. died last April.
</TEXT>

</DOC>