<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1127EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Panama-Wounded     12-27 0433</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Wounded,0447</SECOND>
<HEAD>Official Deals with Emotional Roller-Coaster</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SCOTT ROTHSCHILD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN ANTONIO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When American wounded began arriving last
week from Panama, Maj. Nelson Smith and hospital staff quickly
realized that the injured soldiers' families were going to need
help, too.
   ``The military does things differently than other people do,''
Smith observed Tuesday. For the families of the wounded,
particularly those unfamiliar with the military bureaucracy, ``it
was something of a culture shock,'' he said.
   For instance, families had to apply for identification badges
before seeing their loved ones, and could not visit them without an
escort.
   ``We're more structured to protect the privacy of the patient
than a civilian hospital,'' said Smith, a clinical social worker.
   Smith, the chairman of the social work department at Wilford
Hall Medical Center, and others established a reception center to
help the visiting families deal with wounds and injuries to their
sons and husbands.
   About 250 wounded soldiers have been treated at Wilford and
Brooke Army Medical Center since the United States invaded Panama
last week.
   Many soldiers have been released or transferred to their home
bases. Tuesday marked the first day in a week that military
hospitals did not receive wounded soldiers from Panama, and today
there were 41 soldiers at Wilford Hall and 17 across town at Brooke
Army Medical Center.
   President Bush will visit the wounded soldiers Sunday, the White
House said.
   Smith, 42, said the sight of loved ones being reunited with
those wounded in Panama recalled the return of American hostages
from Iran in January 1981.
   Smith was assigned to the U.S. hospital in Wiesbaden, West
Germany, where the newly freed hostages were taken for observation
and treatment before returning to the United States.
   Both the hostages returning from Iran and the soldiers wounded
in Panama were very emotional. ``It was the same sense of relief
that they had survived,'' Smith said.
   He said the soldiers from Panama and the hostages behaved
similarly, concentrating on televised news accounts of the event of
which they were part.
   Smith said the hospital and volunteers have been working hard to
help families of casualties through reception centers staffed by a
clinical social workers and two mental health technicians.
   He said the first thing family members want to do is to see
their loved ones. Regardless of the wound or injury, Smith said,
relatives must be accompanied by a hospital staff person or
volunteer during that initial encounter to give them whatever
emotional support they may need.
   ``We don't let them go up by themselves,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>