<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0006EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-Chorrillo     12-26 0709</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Chorrillo,0730</SECOND>
<HEAD>Panamanians Accept Loss as Price for Noriega's Ouster</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Tuesday AMs report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DOUGLAS GRANT MINE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Manuel Blanco rummaged through the
ashes that had been his home and salvaged a balpeen hammer with a
charred handle and a blackened pair of pliers.
   The two tools and the clothes on his back are what remains of
his earthly possessions. Even so, the 70-year-old retired auto
mechanic says he is glad U.S. forces invaded Panama and overthrew
the dictatorship of Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   ``It hurts that I've lost everything, but what are you going to
do? The gringos had to do it like they did. I only wish they would
have done it long ago,'' he said.
   He stood on blackened sheets of corrugated zinc that had been
the roof of the two-story wooden apartment building, where he lived
with his wife and their granddaughter. The only remnans of the
building are two masonry columns that supported the communal
bathrooms.
   Blanco and his neighbors had the misfortune to live a block from
the headquarters of the Panamanian Defense Forces, Noriega's
command center.
   U.S. tanks and rocket-firing helicopters destroyed the military
headquarters before dawn Wednesday. The barrage sparked fires that
raced through housing in the working class Chorrillo neighborhood,
creating at least 20,000 refugees.
   ``No one has more right to speak than we do, the ones hurt most
by the attack,'' said Ruben Camargo, 37, standing in front of his
ruined home. Camargo, a goldsmith, is luckier than Blanco in that
he lived with his wife and two children in a more substantial
cinderblock structure.
   U.S. forces evacuated the area at daybreak Wednesday, hours
after the assault began.
   Camargo said his 4-year-old daughter was traumatized by the
hours of fire and bombing, and she wakes up crying during the night.
   ``One single person is guilty of all this. So much death because
of one man, and that man's name is Manuel Antonio Noriega,'' said
Camargo when asked if he resents the invaders.
   Of a dozen Chorrillo residents inteviewed by The Associated
Press, all applauded the U.S. action.
   The closest thing to criticism was voiced by taxi driver Bolivar
Escobar, 32, standing in his flooded home on the ground floor of
the destroyed housing block. Most of his family's possessions were
wrecked or looted. He had salvaged a red cape embroidered with
silver trim _ a costume that his 11-year-old daughter had worn.
   ``The invasion itself was correct, the form no,'' he said.
``They should have come with much more personnel to establish
positions corner by corner, to prevent looting. And they could have
used less shelling. A lot of people died in their sleep. Now we
have to start from zero,'' he said.
   Hospital authorities estimated between 200 and 300 people were
killed in the invasion, at least half of them civilians. Hundreds
more were injured.
   ``It was the only way to get him (Noriega) out,'' said Camargo.
``He could have quit and given us all the gift of a happy
Christmas, not this bitter Christmas we're having.''
   The perception of the Americans as liberators underscores the
relationship the United States and Panama have enjoyed since Panama
was created, through seccession from Colombia, by President
Theodore Roosevelt's gunboat diplomacy in 1903.
   Panama's currency is the U.S. dollar and its economy has always
been closely linked to the U.S.-built and jointly administered
canal. The national pastime is baseball and virtually all males
over 8 years old follow the U.S. big leagues.
   ``Not only are we happy with the invasion. Most people here
would like Panama to be the 51st star on the U.S. flag,'' said a
middle-aged woman.
   Camargo, Blanco and about 9,000 Chorrillo refugees are being
sheltered and fed by U.S. troops at Balboa High School, two miles
away.
   They, like a dozen others interviewed in the wasteland around
the Defense Forces headquarters, appealed for reconstruction aid
from the U.S.-installed government of President Guillermo Endara
and from Washington.
   Sergio Delgado loaded some soggy sofa cushions from his house
onto his brother-in-law's pickup.
   ``We've suffered, but finally that corruption is ended,'' he
said. ``The Panamanian people have been asking for a long time for
the North Americans to intervene.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>