<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0201 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0809EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv24   12-18 0421</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv24,0440</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv24</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 24</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is Sunday, Dec. 24, the 358th day of 1989. There are seven
days left in the year. This is Christmas Eve.
   Today's Highlight in History:
   On Dec. 24, 1814, the War of 1812 officially ended as the United
States and Britain signed the Treaty of Ghent in Belgium. However,
because of the slowness of communications at that time, the
countries fought the Battle of New Orleans the following month.
   On this date:
   In 1524, Portuguese navigator Vasco da Gama _ who had discovered
a sea route around Africa to India _ died in Cochin, India.
   In 1851, fire devastated the Library of Congress in Washington
D.C., destroying about 35,000 volumes.
   In 1865, several veterans of the Confederate Army formed a
private social club in Pulaski, Tenn., called the Ku Klux Klan.
   In 1871, Giuseppe Verdi's opera ``Aida'' had its world premiere
in Cairo, Egypt, to celebrate the opening of the Suez Canal.
   In 1906, Canadian physicist Reginald A. Fessenden became the
first person to broadcast a music program over radio, from Brant
Rock, Mass.
   In 1920, Enrico Caruso gave his last public performance, singing
the role of Eleazar in Jacques Halevy's ``La Juive'' at the
Metropolitan Opera in New York.
   In 1943, President Roosevelt appointed Gen. Dwight D. Eisenhower
supreme commander of Allied forces as part of Operation Overlord.
   In 1968, the Apollo 8 astronauts, orbiting the moon, read
passages from the Old Testament Book of Genesis as part of a
Christmas Eve television broadcast to Earth.
   In 1980, Americans remembered the U.S. hostages in Iran by
burning candles or shining lights for 417 seconds _ one second for
each day of captivity.
   In 1986, French hostage Aurel Cornea, held in Lebanon for 9{
months, was released by his pro-Iranian Shiite Moslem captors.
   Ten years ago: Four clergymen from the United States were
allowed to meet with some of the American hostages in Iran to hold
Christmas services.
   Five years ago: The Soviet Union held funeral services for its
late defense minister, Dmitri F. Ustinov. The absence of President
Konstantin U. Chernenko fueled rumors of serious illness.
   One year ago: President-elect Bush nominated Elizabeth H. Dole,
onetime transportation secretary during the Reagan administration,
to be his secretary of labor.
   Today's Birthday: Actress Ava Gardner is 67.
   Thought for Today: ``Christmas is the season when people run out
of money before they run out of friends.'' _ Anonymous.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Advance for Sunday, Dec. 24</NOTE>

</DOC>