<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0126EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     12-28 0304</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0316</SECOND>
<HEAD>On the Light Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>COLORADO SPRINGS, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A men's climbing club plans to
celebrate the new year with a bang atop 14,110-foot Pikes Peak,
while a women's group plans a more sedate celebration on top of a
nearby mountain.
   The AdAmAn Club plans to set off $3,000 worth of fireworks,
including a barrage of rockets and mortar shells, from atop Pike's
Peak on New Year's Eve.
   It will be the 66th annual climb for the AdAmAn Club, which gets
its name from the practice of adding a new member each year, said
Jim Bates, the club historian.
   Meanwhile, the AdaWoman Club, formed in 1982 partly as a spoof
of the AdAmAn Club, planned to ring in 1990 with champagne and
$7.50 in sparklers atop 8,720-foot Pyramid Mountain.
   At midnight, the women plan to wave sparklers and sing, ``I Am
Woman,'' the song made famous by Helen Reddy.
   ``We're just out to have a good time,'' said club President Rita
Randolph.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LAKE MACATAWA, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dorothy and her little dog, Toto,
survived a Kansas tornado, but a Michigan winter would have just
been too rough for the Hollywood types making a movie about
``Wizard of Oz'' creator L. Frank Baum.
   Baum wrote the story at his cottage on Lake Macatawa in western
Michigan, and some of the characters are believed to be based on
local people and places.
   So when NBC announced plans for the TV movie ``Dreamer of Oz,''
resort officials campaigned to have the movie filmed on location.
   But Michigan's unpredictable and often nasty winter weather
persuaded NBC to make the movie in sunny Southern California.
   ``The weather everywhere else is really unpredictable,'' said
NBC spokeswoman Kathi Banks. ``And the weather down here is the
same all year.''
   The movie is expected to air come spring.
</TEXT>

</DOC>