<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0557EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AlaskaVolcano     12-20 0491</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Alaska Volcano,0506</SECOND>
<HEAD>Redoubt Rests, Air Transporation Picks Up</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSAN GALLAGHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Redoubt Volcano's eruption subsided,
allowing scientists to get their closest look yet, and holiday
travelers got off the ground as fears eased that volcanic ash would
clog jet engines.
   The Alaska Volcano Observatory said no more ash reached
Anchorage after a plume consisting mostly of gas gushed from the
volcano early Tuesday.
   ``The plume appears to be moving primarily toward the southwest
and west,'' observatory geologist Steve Brantley said.
   He said the volcano, about 115 miles from Anchorage, sent forth
little ash.
   Redoubt erupted Thursday after 23 years. The fallout brought
Anchorage air traffic to a virtual halt Saturday as the hectic
Christmas travel season opened.
   Geologists made a research flight over Redoubt on Tuesday, but
clouds obscured the top of the 10,197-foot volcano, and
observations were limited, Brantley said. He said earthquake
activity beneath the volcano appeared to slacken early in the
afternoon.
   ``It's too early to tell whether this indicates a significant
change in the volcano's behavior, or whether it's just a short-term
fluctuation,'' Brantley said.
   The main carrier serving the Anchorage-Seattle route resumed
regular operations Tuesday and added flights to deal with a backlog
of about 1,200 passengers in Anchorage.
   ``We're moving them,'' Alaska Airlines spokesman Lou Cancelmi
said. ``We are also moving post office mail, and we've got
additional freighters scheduled. It's going pretty well.''
   At Anchorage International Aiport, the operations office said
crowds awaiting flights thinned as airlines began flying, although
some interstate carriers with relatively light Alaska schedules did
not resume service.
   Carriers serving Alaska points from Anchorage were back in the
sky, but some international lines continued to divert flights to
airports elsewhere, airport officials said.
   About 70 of 240 passengers with tickets for Korean Airlines
Flight 25 remained in Anchorage on Tuesday for what they said were
safety reasons, said Lee Steiner, KAL's customer relations manager
in Los Angeles. The others left aboard a Korea-bound flight early
in the day.
   Last week, a Boeing 747 operated by KLM Royal Dutch Airlines
fell about two miles after it passed through volcanic ash and lost
power to all four engines. The engines were restarted and the plane
made an emergency landing at the Anchorage airport.
   Steiner said the KAL passengers who stayed behind would be put
aboard the next available plane to Korea, ``but we don't know when
that will be at this point. It depends on the climatic conditions.''
   Aside from passengers, the U.S. Postal Service continued to
charter aircraft to haul the usual upsurge in holiday mail between
Anchorage and Seattle.
   By Tuesday morning, 60,000 pounds of mail waited to be flown
from Anchorage, some of it left from Monday and the rest deposited
overnight at the airport's 24-hour post office, the Postal Service
said.
   About 90,000 pounds awaited transportation north from Seattle.
Officials expected the backlogs to be cleared up by today.
</TEXT>

</DOC>