<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0445EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AcidTongue     12-20 0577</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Acid Tongue,0599</SECOND>
<HEAD>New York High Court Throws Out State Harassment Law</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Note language in 5th graf</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BELLAFIORE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   New York's highest court ruled the state's
harassment law unconstitutional, saying speech that may be abusive
is still protected by the First Amendment.
   The decision may spark challenges against such laws in other
states, attorneys said.
   Civil rights advocates applauded the decision and said it would
prevent police officers from arresting people, especially
demonstrators, for using language that could be considered
offensive.
   ``I think it's clear now that you can't prosecute someone for
cursing someone out on the street,'' said Norman Siegel, executive
director of the New York Civil Liberties Union.
   The case involved a dispute in which a woman called a neighbor a
bitch and her son a dog as they passed by her door. The woman,
Jackie Dietze of Raymondville, also allegedly threatened to ``beat
the crap out of'' the woman.
   Dietze, 19, was sentenced to 15 days in jail and fined $50.
   On Tuesday, the state Court of Appeals, in a 7-0 decision, threw
out her conviction. It ruled 5-2 that the law was unconstitutional.
   The court said the harassment statute ``prohibits a substantial
amount of constitutionally protected expression.''
   Judge Stewart Hancock Jr. said the law needed to be undone
``because its continued existence presents a significant risk of
prosecution for the mere exercise of free speech.''
   ``Casual conversation may well be abusive and intended to annoy.
So, too, may be light-hearted banter or the earnest expression of
personal opinion or emotion,'' Hancock said. ``But unless speech
presents a clear and present danger of some serious substantial
evil, it may neither be forbidden nor penalized.''
   Most states have anti-harassment statutes similar in intent to
New York's. William E. Hellerstein, a professor at the Brooklyn Law
School and a specialist on the First Amendment, said the decision
was bound to spur challenges in other states.
   The U.S. Supreme Court has not addressed the issue of whether
words _ unless representing a direct threat to safety _ can
constitute harassment, Hellerstein said.
   ``This should be a victory for all of us in protecting
liberty,'' said Douglas Lasdon, executive director of the Legal
Action Center for the Homeless, of Tuesday's decision. ``We don't
want to become a society where people get intimidated for being
creative or eccentric.''
   ``I guess the standard now is `fighting words,''' said Nancy
Connell, spokeswoman for state Attorney General Robert Abrams, who
was on the losing end of the case. ``You cannot say something that
is going to incite someone to an immediate act of violence.''
   Dietze's words drew tears from her neighbor, Shelly Lazore.
   Dietze denied using the language cited in the court case and
said that the incident with Lazore stemmed from a feud over a
boyfriend. Dietze said she was ``relieved'' that the case was over.
   Dietze's lawyer, Robert Ballan, said that while the decision may
expand freedom of speech, it could also have another impact.
   ``There are people who are quite obnoxious and are in the habit
of using foul language,'' Ballan said. ``These people are going to
feel like they can be as obnoxious as they wish.
   ``But those are the effects of freedom,'' he said.
   St. Lawrence County District Attorney Charles Gardner did not
return telephone calls. Prosecutors had maintained that Dietze
stepped over the line of acceptable behavior and that the
Constitution doesn't apply to abusive language.
</TEXT>

</DOC>