<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2349EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AIDSUpdate-Ads     12-18 0952</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AIDS Update-Ads,0983</SECOND>
<HEAD>How Much Is Too Much for Anti-AIDS Ads?</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Tuesday AMs report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL GEITNER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It begins with a male actor recounting a
romantic date _ dinner by candlelight, conversation by the
fireplace.
   ``Finally, we kissed,'' the actor says. ``Then he asked if I
enjoyed safer sex. I have never felt so good about saying yes.''
   The city unveiled the 30-second television spot, which ends with
the line ``rubber up for safety,'' with much fanfare last summer as
part of its latest AIDS education campaign.
   Months later, viewers of late-night programming on a local cable
channel are about the only ones who have seen it.
   To avoid acquired immune deficiency syndrome, the surgeon
general recommended that people learn how the disease is
transmitted and how it can be prevented through use of condoms.
   The sloganeering has changed from ``safe sex'' to ``safer sex,''
acknowledging that no sex practice, including condoms, offers
fool-proof protection against AIDS.
   But getting the message to some of the people most at risk, such
as homosexual men or inner-city youths, without offending the
masses is difficult at best, say the people charged with creating
the ads.
   Critics of explicit AIDS education campaigns warn they could
backfire on health professionals and erode public support.
   ``I think they're turning people off,'' said Dr. Elizabeth M.
Whelan, president of the American Council on Science and Health, a
consortium of more than 200 physicians and scientists active in
consumer education.
   Reed V. Tuckson, the public health commissioner in Washington,
D.C., announced in 1987 that he wanted a sophisticated multimedia
campaign similar to those that ``sell Nike tennis shoes to poor
black youths.''
   The department then argued with city officials and community
groups for more than a year over wording on posters; it negotiated
with local news outlets and the public transit system, which would
not display placards with the word ``condom.''
   ``I did not anticipate ... significant opposition at so many
different levels,'' Tuckson said.
   Reaction was negative in some Boston quarters when a social
service group, Action for Boston Community Development, unveiled
its AIDS poster. It shows four young men, three with hats and one
holding a condom over his head, with the caption ``Be cool. Wear
your jimmy hat.''
   The group received complaints that by using the term ``jimmy
hat'' _ slang for condom and also the title of a rap music hit _
the posters spoke specifically to young people and encouraged them
to have sex.
   ``People who are dying of AIDS and are in their 20s obviously
contracted the disease while in their teens,'' Laura Palmer, an
ABCD spokeswoman, said in reaction.
   Nevertheless, the posters, ready in March, didn't make it onto
city buses and subways until June, held up by Massachusetts Bay
Transportation Authority review.
   New York's ``rubber up for safety'' campaign includes two
television spots, the one so widely rejected and a second ad that
features a talking head: Health Commissioner Stephen Joseph. Two
television stations, including the local CBS affiliate, have aired
the Joseph spot.
   Nancy Davies, vice president at Capriello &amp; Chabrowe, the agency
that designed the campaign, said her people went back and forth
with local TV stations on the more controversial ad, changing it
each time, but the stations still said no.
   ``They wouldn't have anything to do with them,'' she said.
   The city's newspapers have refused to run the campaign's print
ads, but they have shown up in subway cars and on station
billboards. One uses the headline ``Man-to-Man,'' with the letter
``o'' represented by a rolled-up condom.
   Part of the goal, Davies said, was to reach men who engage in
sex with other men but do not consider themselves part of the gay
community and thus do not frequent bars or organizations where they
would see other AIDS education messages.
   ``The bulk of the campaign, when it comes right down to it, is
in the subway,'' said Davies.
   Whelan of the American Council on Science and Health said she
objected to advocating condom use not for moral or ``prudish''
reasons, but because condoms are not 100 percent failsafe even when
used correctly.
   In addition, she said, the ads appear to condone, at least
unintentionally, homosexuality or sex outside a monogamous
relationship, behavior that many people oppose.
   ``If they're meant for homosexual men, I think they should be
targeted at them and not at everybody else,'' she said. ``I think
you end up turning people off and making them less sympathetic.''
   As head of the National AIDS Information and Education Program
at the Centers for Disease Control in Atlanta, Dr. Fred Kroger is
responsible for creating AIDS education materials for the public.
   The first campaign in 1987 offered promotions on the use of
condoms for sexually active people.
   ``In general those were not played by anybody,'' he said.
   Kroger said he had since refocused the message of the TV ads,
avoiding the word ``condom'' but including a telephone number
people can call for information.
   ``Rather than putting lots of money into messages that would not
be seen by anybody, we opted to do less explicit messages,'' he
said.
   Public health officials and the ad agencies say they realize
their work is controversial and they take pains not to be
``unnecessarily provocative.''
   But Tuckson, the District of Columbia health commissioner, says
he feels they have a responsibility to get information on reducing
the risk of AIDS to the people who need it.
   ``This is a society that advertises feminine hygiene deodorant
spray and depicts explicit sexual behavior in prime time,'' he
said. ``What is offensive and insulting is not to give people
information that can help save their lives.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>