<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1144EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Infanticide     12-19 0339</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Infanticide,0352</SECOND>
<HEAD>Doctor Gets Probation and Community Service For Infanticide</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE LINDER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An obstetrician convicted of infanticide
after witnesses said he let an aborted fetus die was placed on
three years' probation today and ordered to perform 300 hours of
community service.
   Dr. Joseph Melnick, 66, was found guilty in a non-jury trial in
June, the first criminal prosecution under Pennsylvania's 1974
abortion law, which requires doctors to do what they can if they
remove a living fetus.
   Common Pleas Judge Lynn Abraham heeded Melnick's plea for
leniency, calling what he did a ``criminal mistake'' for which
neither jail nor a heavy fine was appropriate. She also said she
had no intention of making an example of him.
   The mistake, the judge said, was that the doctor performed an
abortion on a teen-ager in her eighth month of pregnancy. The
doctor said he had been told she was in her fourth or fifth month.
State law prohibits most abortions after six months, but Melnick
was not charged with performing an illegal abortion.
   ``I am very sorry that this unfortunate incident occurred,''
Melnick told the judge. ``Please do not judge me by this one
incident alone.''
   The judge ordered Melnick perform his community service in
medical facilities. He could have received 3{ to 7 years in prison.
Assistant District Attorney David Webb had asked for a jail term
and a fin.
   Witnesses, including nurses at West Park Hospital, where the
1984 abortion on a 13-year-old was performed, had said that the
fetus survived about 90 minutes and moved and gasped but that
Melnick ordered that no care be given. Melnick contended the
3-pound, 9-ounce girl was stillborn.
   The doctor is still practicing. State licensing authorities are
expected to take up the case.
   Defense attorney Richard Sprague said he would appeal on grounds
the verdict was not justified by the evidence.
   Melnick originally was charged with murder, but the charge was
dismissed on grounds of insufficient evidence, and the abortion law
was invoked.
</TEXT>

</DOC>