<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0099 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1547EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-EastGermany     12-28 0583</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany,0602</SECOND>
<HEAD>Officials Warn of Neo-Nazi Tendencies, Soviet Memorial Desecrated</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NESHA STARCEVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An East German newspaper on Thursday warned
of growing right-wing extremism in the country, and the official
news agency reported that a memorial to the Soviet soldiers who
fought the Nazis had been defaced.
   A researcher who requested anonymity told the newspaper Junge
Welt that neo-Nazi groups were growing in number and creating a
``pogrom atmosphere.''
   The newspaper said the researcher, a sociologist, wished to
remain anonymous because of threats from right-wing extremists.
   Junge Welt also printed a letter it said was received recently.
   ``We are not to be stopped anymore,'' said the hand-written
letter, signed with the Nazi salute ``Sieg Heil'' and carrying a
swastika in the bottom left corner.
   East German opposition leaders and the coalition government late
Wednesday issued a joint statement expressing ``deep concern'' over
the increase in neo-fascist incidents.
   The statement said 44 acts of violence by suspected neo-Nazis
were registered by police in 1988, while there were already 144
such incidents by the end of November this year.
   The official news agency ADN said vandals in East Berlin defaced
a 40-foot bronze statue of a Soviet soldier carrying a child, a
momument to Soviet soldiers killed in the 1945 battle to liberate
Berlin from the Nazis.
   One spray-painted message scrawled overnight said, ``Occupiers
Go Home,'' and another said, ``Blast the last prison of peoples,
the USSR,'' ADN said.
   The agency said the slogans were removed but officials had
temporarily closed the park.
   East Germany is the Soviet Union's most important strategic ally
in the Warsaw Pact, and the Soviets keep about 380,000 troops in
East Germany, according to Western estimates.
   In the Junge Welt interview, the unidentified researcher said
that in early 1988 there were about ``1,000 organized neo-fascists,
but their numbers now are much larger, not including their
sympathizers.''
   He said most of the extremists were between 18 and 26 years of
age and were particularly aggressive toward foreigners and
leftists, ``who for them represent slovenliness, disorder and
dirt.''
   Peter Przybylski, a spokesman for the general prosecutor's
office, said 185 people had been prosecuted for neo-Nazi activities
in 1988, while the number rose to 296 in 1989, excluding December.
   He told ADN that about 1,100 people were known to the police
through previous neo-Nazi offenses.
   Since the ouster of the Communist leadership and the opening of
the country's borders, East German officials have frequently warned
of possible infiltration by West German rightist radicals.
   West Germany's Republican Party, which has won as much as 10
percent of the vote in some local elections, claims to have set up
cells in East Germany.
   Ultra-rightists have also been seen distributing leaflets to
reunification advocates at pro-democracy rallies in Leipzig,
despite vows by authorities that the party will not be allowed to
function in East Germany.
   At recent rallies, students said so much disdain had built up
against the Communists in 40 years that they thought East Germany
could provide fertile soil for rightist sentiments.
   A wave of protest demonstrations forced the resignation of
hard-line Communist leader Erich Honecker on Oct. 18 and his
replacement by Egon Krenz. Krenz opened the Berlin Wall and gave
East Germans freedom to travel but growing pressure from the
pro-democracy movement forced the entire Communist leadership to
step down on Dec. 3.
   The Communist-led coalition government of Premier Hans Modrow
and the opposition have agreed to hold free elections on May 6.
</TEXT>

</DOC>