<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0123 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1349EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PTLHearings     12-20 0379</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-PTL Hearings,0387</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Involved With PTL Released on $25,000 Bond</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHARLOTTE, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The evangelist who introduced PTL founder
Jim Bakker to Jessica Hahn, leading to the scandal that destroyed
the television ministry, was released on $25,000 bond Wednesday on
federal perjury charges.
   In his first court appearance on the charges, John Wesley
Fletcher appeared without a lawyer before U.S. Magistrate Paul
Taylor, who imposed several conditions for his release, including
surrendering his passport and refraining from the use of alcohol.
Fletcher recently was arrested in Durham on a charge of driving
while intoxicated.
   According to the Dec. 5 indictment, on Sept. 24, 1987, Fletcher
denied during testimony before the grand jury that indicted Bakker
and three associates that he took Ms. Hahn to a Florida hotel to
have sex with Bakker. At a later appearance, Fletcher told the same
grand jury that he agreed when Bakker told him: ``Get me a woman.''
   In a separate hearing, the Rev. Sam Johnson, a former PTL
minister, was released on the same unsecured bond. Johnson is
accused of lying to the special grand jury about a $10,000 loan he
made to former PTL executive Richard Dortch that later went to Ms.
Hahn.
   The payment to Ms. Hahn was made Nov. 1, 1984, before the former
church secretary received $265,000 in PTL money in exchange for her
silence about her 1980 sexual liaison with Bakker. Disclosure of
the payment eventually brought down the PTL evanglism empire built
by Bakker, who is now in federal prison after being convicted in
October of fraud and conspiracy charges.
   ``I feel very confident,'' Johnson said as he left the
courthouse. ``This has been a very unfortunate experience.''
   Asked if he would plead innocent, he responded: ``Absolutely.''
   Taylor agreed to appoint counsel for Fletcher after the
evangelist told the magistrate: ``I have nothing, sir, except the
clothes on my back.'' Taylor said later that Fletcher, who filed
for bankruptcy court protection in 1987, had signed an affidavit
saying he could not afford an attorney.
   Johnson faces five years in prison and a $250,000 fine for each
of 12 perjury counts. Fletcher could face the same sentence on one
perjury count.
   No arraignment was scheduled for Fletcher. Taylor scheduled a
Jan. 16 arraignment for Johnson.
</TEXT>

</DOC>