<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1513EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Ceausescu-Sketch     12-25 0940</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ceausescu-Sketch,0965</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ceausescu Created Cult of Personality During 24-Year Rule</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nicolae Ceausescu, a peasant's son who
rose to rule Romania with an iron grip for 24 years, created a cult
of personality unmatched in Eastern Europe since the days of Soviet
dictator Josef Stalin.
   His wife, Elena, became his virtual second-in-command until
their sudden descent from power.
   The two were reported captured Saturday trying to flee a popular
revolution sparked by a massacre of thousands of people. On Monday,
Bucharest Radio said they were executed after a secret trial found
them guilty of ``grave crimes'' _ among them, the deaths of 60,000
protesters this month and spiriting $1 billion in public funds out
of the country.
   Before he was shouted down at a Bucharest rally he orchestrated
Thursday _ his last public appearance _ the 71-year-old Communist
leader's hold on power was so firm that he could carry out a
foreign policy independent of the Soviet Union and the other East
bloc countries.
   Just one month ago, he was overwhelmingly reaffirmed as supreme
leader by a fiercely obedient Communist Party conference. He was
the last hard-line Communist leader in the Soviet bloc after
democratic reforms swept through Poland, Hungary, East Germany,
Czechoslovakia and Bulgaria this year.
   His party hailed himself as the ``Genius of the Carpathians''
and the ``Conducator.'' His severity earned him the nickname
``Draculescu,'' for Bram Stoker's bloodthirsty count of
Transylvania.
   He imposed austerity on the people yet was building a
presidential palace as a monument to himself. He had lavish
mountain and sea retreats.
   Born Jan. 26, 1918, in Scornicesti, Ceausescu was the third son
of a large peasant family. An elementary school dropout, he was
apprenticed as a shoemaker, took a job in a factory and joined the
illegal Communist Party youth organization at age 15. He became a
party member three years later, in 1936.
   Before and during World War II, his Communist activities landed
him in jail several times. He became a protege of Communist leader
Gheorghe Gheorghiu-Dej, rose quickly in the party, and succeeded
his mentor after his death in 1965.
   He turned the party into a personal instrument, gradually
pushing aside all leaders who opposed his policies and installing
loyalists on the ruling 23-member Politburo, including Elena
Ceausescu, who rose to head the country's scientific community
despite doubts about her background and education.
   Nicu, their youngest son, was regional party chief in central
Romania. Valentin, an adopted son, Zoia-Elena, their daughter, and
Ceausescu brothers held prestigious posts, as did several in-laws.
   Western analysts and knowledgeable Romanians estimate that about
40 members of his family held top jobs in the party and state
hierarchy.
   When he was elected president in March 1974, an official picture
showed him holding a silver scepter as the symbol of authority.
   The personality cult he encouraged took on the trappings of
worship and pervaded practically all aspects of public life. His
portrait lined the streets in Bucharest and other Romanian cities
and bookstores were full of works attributed to him.
   The United States and other Western powers originally cultivated
Ceausescu's relatively independent foreign policy stand within the
Soviet-led Warsaw Pact. Two U.S. presidents visited Bucharest,
Richard Nixon in 1969 and Gerald Ford in 1975, and President Jimmy
Carter threw a state dinner for him in Washington in 1978. Queen
Elizabeth II awared him an honorary knighthood.
   Ceausescu maintained diplomatic relations with Israel even after
other Soviet bloc countries broke them during the 1967 Middle East
War.
   In keeping with his maverick image, he denounced the Soviet-led
invasion of Czechoslovakia in 1968, refused to participate and
refused to allow any foreign troops in Romania.
   Romania was the only East bloc country to send athletes to the
1984 Olympics in Los Angeles, breaking the Soviet-led boycott.
   In later years, he grew more dogmatic, rejecting the need for
reform adopted by other bloc allies, such as Poland and Hungary.
Earlier this year, he urged his Warsaw Pact allies to invade Poland
to prevent a Solidarity-led government from taking power.
   Romania became increasingly isolated in both East and West,
particularly after 30,000 Romanians, mostly ethnic Hungarians, fled
to Hungary last year.
   The Hungarians complained about alleged discrimination and
denial of their ethnic and cultural rights, but they also sought
refuge in Hungary to escape chronic hardships under Ceausescu.
   Ceausescu viewed the changes in Eastern Europe with alarm and
accused other Warsaw Pact countries of abandoning orthodox
Communism.
   ``The triumph of the revolution requires unity, severe
discipline and a spirit of sacrifice. A firm organization is needed
as well as a tested political leader who knows how to unite and
lead the masses,'' he told a mass meeting in Bucharest earlier this
year.
   He invested billions of dollars in a crash industrialization
program and rigidly followed a policy of domestic austerity to pay
off Romania's $11 billion foreign debt.
   Romania, once known as the breadbasket of the Balkans, became
one of Europe's poorest countries. The longer the food lines and
the more vocal the people's complaints, the more harshly the regime
cracked down on critics.
   Despair spread among the nation's 23 million people as hardships
became more severe throughout the 1980s, and in the end not even
the secret policy or the army could keep them down.
   On Dec. 17, his security forces opened fire on thousands of
demonstrators in Timisoara who demanded freedom and a better life,
beginning the chain of events that brought him down.
   He looked surprised and dismayed as his orchestrated rally
Thursday turned into an anti-Ceausescu rally. Protesters on Friday
burned his portraits and hurled his books into the street.
</TEXT>

</DOC>