<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0934EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-CeausescuProfile     12-22 0869</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Ceausescu Profile,0900</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romanian Leader's Tough Economic Program Caused Worker Hardship</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Nicolae Ceausescu pronounced, Nih-koh-LIE Chow-SHESS-koo.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIOREL URMA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nicolae Ceausescu, the president and
Communist Party leader of Romania, created a cult of personality
and ruled his country with an iron hand during 24 years in power.
   The 71-year-old Ceausescu's hold was so firm that he could carry
out a foreign policy independent of the Soviet Union and the other
East bloc countries. He also managed to outlast old-line leaders in
Poland, Hungary, East Germany, Bulgaria and Czechoslovakia.
   But the changes encouraged by Soviet leader Mikhail S. Gorbachev
also swept over Romania. After seven days of widespread
demonstrations and attempts by security forces to quell them by
force, Ceausescu was driven from power by a mass uprising.
   The old-style Marxist invested billions of dollars in a crash
industrialization program that led to widespread food and energy
shortages, and despair for Romania's 23 million people.
   The longer the food lines and the more vocal the people's
complaints, the more harshly the regime cracked down on critics.
   At a mass meeting in Bucharest earlier this year, Ceausescu
said, ``The triumph of the revolution requires unity, severe
discipline and a spirit of sacrifice. A firm organization is needed
as well as a tested political leader who knows how to unite and
lead the masses.''
   Ceausescu's ``firm organization'' was the Romanian Communist
Party which he turned into a personal instrument after taking over
in 1965.
   He gradually pushed aside all leaders who opposed his policies
and installed loyalists on the ruling 23-member Politburo,
including his wife, Elena, a chemist.
   The personality cult he encouraged, particularly after he was
sworn in as Romania's first president, took on the trappings of
worship and pervaded practically all aspects of public life. His
pictures lined the streets in Bucharest and other Romanian cities
and bookstores were full of works attributed to him.
   When he was elected president in March 1974, an official picture
showed him holding a silver scepter as the symbol of authority.
   During the Ceausescu era, Romania, once known as the breadbasket
of the Balkans, became one of Europe's poorest countries. Still,
the official media frequently described Ceausescu's long tenure as
Romania's ``Golden Epoch.''
   Billions of dollars were spent on industrial and public works
projects, and food was rationed as the government exported all it
could to pay off its foreign debts. The debt was eventually paid
off in the spring of 1989, but the shortages continued.
   A massive secret police kept strict control on religious and
political expression, and dissent was quickly crushed.
   As he grew older and turned more dogmatic, Ceausescu rejected
the need for reform adopted by other bloc allies, such as Poland
and Hungary.
   Romania became increasingly isolated in both East and West,
particularly after 30,000 Romanians, mostly ethnic Hungarians, fled
to Hungary last year.
   The Hungarians complained about alleged discrimination and
denial of their ethnic and cultural rights, but they also sought
refuge in Hungary to escape chronic hardships under Ceausescu.
   Ceausescu viewed the changes in Eastern Europe with alarm and
accused other Warsaw Pact countries of abandoning Communism.
   The United States and other Western powers originally encouraged
Ceausescu's relatively independent foreign policy stand within the
Soviet-led Warsaw Pact. Two U.S. presidents visited Bucharest,
Richard M. Nixon in 1969 and Gerald F. Ford in 1975.
   Ceausescu, who took power as Communist Party leader on March 22,
1965, maintained diplomatic relations with Israel even after other
Soviet bloc countries broke them during the 1967 Middle East War.
   In keeping with his maverick image, he denounced the Soviet-led
invasion of Czechoslovakia in 1968, refused to participate and
refused to allow any foreign troops in Romania.
   Romania was the only East bloc country to send athletes to the
1984 Olympics in Los Angeles, breaking the Soviet-led boycott.
   Ceausescu placed members of his family in key posts.
   His wife Elena was a Politburo member and first vice premier,
and by the mid-1980s she had become the virtual second-in-command
of national life and shared the limelight with her husband.
   Nicu, their youngest son, was regional party chief in central
Romania. Valentin, an adopted son, Zoia-Elena, their daughter, and
Ceausescu brothers held prestigious posts, as did several in-laws.
   Western analysts and knowledgeable Romanians estimate that some
40 members of his family held top jobs in the party and state
hierarchy.
   Born Jan. 26, 1918, in Scornicesti, Ceausescu was the third son
of a large peasant family. An elementary school dropout, he was
apprenticed as a shoemaker, took a job in a factory and joined the
illegal Communist Party youth organization at age 15. He became a
party member three years later, in 1936.
   Before and during World War II, his Communist activities landed
him in jail several times. He became a protege of Communist leader
Gheorghe Gheorghiu-Dej, rose quickly in the party, and succeeded
his mentor after his death.
   The party under Gheorghiu-Dej had grown accustomed to one-man
traditional Stalinist rule, and Ceausescu continued the tradition,
moving trusted associates into key posts.
   ``I don't give orders,'' he once quipped to visiting U.S.
Secretary of State William Rogers. ``I make suggestions. But they
had better be carried out.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>