<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0250EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-NoriegaProfile     12-20 0915</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Noriega Profile,0951</SECOND>
<HEAD>Noriega: ``The Man,'' Accused Cocaine Trafficker, Head of State</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega, who once called
his opponent's bullets ``kisses,'' has been a shrewd and ruthless
survivor who reveled in power and in thumbing his nose at what he
called ``the colossus of the North.''
   At about midnight Tuesday, U.S. forces bent on toppling the
military strongman engaged Panamanian troops less than a week after
his rubber-stamp assembly named him head of state and declared a
``state of war'' with the United States.
   Noriega had eliminated political opposition, nullified the May 7
elections when they were going against him and repeatedly defied
the United States, which indicted him on drug trafficking charges
in February 1988.
   It had long been known that ``Tony'' Noriega enjoyed a crisis
and it was widely said that he would prefer death to losing power.
   Noriega, who comes from El Chorrillo, the Panama City district
where Defense Forces headquarters is located, has survived and
created a mystique that won him the nickname ``The Man,'' the
English word his initials spell.
   Noriega wrapped himself in nationalism, saying it was part of
the historic mission of his generation to take control of the
Panama Canal. Under an accord with the United States, Panama is to
take over the canal by the year 2000.
   Noriega claimed his enemies were plotting to abrogate the canal
pact.
   On Oct. 3, elements of the 15,000-man Defense Forces he
commanded rebelled and claimed they had deposed him, but troops
loyal to him suppressed the rebellion and he personally accepted
the rebels' surrender.
   During his last crisis in May after the opposition swamped his
candidate the annulled presidential elections, Noriega was seen
standing alone before the tomb of his patron, Gen. Omar Torrijos.
   The epitaph on the tomb is: ``I don't want to enter heaven. I
just want to enter the Canal Zone.''
   Torrijos, who seized power in a 1968, signed the 1977 accord
with former President Carter to turn over the canal. Torrijos died
in a plane crash in 1981, and Noriega became commander of the
Defense Forces in 1983, giving him de facto control of the
government.
   Noriega was raised by foster parents and joined the Defense
Forces in 1962. His ascent began when he caught the attention of
Torrijos, then an ambitious young officer.
   In his climb to the top, he dealt with everyone from the CIA to
Colombian cocaine cartels.
   Less than a year after Torrijos took power in 1968 coup, he made
Noriega, then an obscure major, chief of intelligence with the rank
of lieutenant colonel.
   It was like having the keys to the city. Noriega immediately
began compiling dossiers on everyone who counted in Panama. The job
also gave him close contact with U.S. intelligence agencies, and he
formed powerful alliances.
   One U.S. official who dealt with Noriega at the time, on drug
enforcement efforts, said Noriega was polite but when it came to
something he wanted, he was ``the coldest man I ever met.''
   After Noriega became the Defense Forces commander, he acquired a
fleet of expensive cars and a home in an exclusive neighborhood.
   His financial interests reportedly included a vast array of
businesses including hotels, casinos, a television station, radio
stations, maritime services, duty-free liquor stores and
prostitution.
   Rumors about his personal life were plentiful, but there were
few facts. Even his age was disputed. The general has said he is
51, but the date in his high school yearbook would make him 54.
   He is married and has a daughter who lives in the Dominican
Republic.
   Although his private life is that of a rich man, he worked hard
to develop a populist image modeled on the revered Torrijos,
spending weekends meeting with residents of towns and villages in
this nation of 2.2 million.
   Noriega often speaks of his humble origins and characterizes his
domestic opponents as rich and white. ``The humble, the poor and
the blacks, they are the utmost authority of the people,'' he once
said.
   As the standoff with the United States dragged on, Noriega
enjoyed underlining what he termed Washington's helplessness,
despite the 12,000 troops it has stationed in Panama.
   Noriega exercised power with ruthless assurance. He closed
newspapers for months at a time, and presidents served at his
pleasure.
   Rumors of opposition inside the Defense Forces were met with
purges and reorganizations. ``Kisses,'' was how he described the
bullets fired in an attempted coup in March 1988.
   The United States, long his ally, began to distance itself after
the headless body of one of his opponents, Hugo Spadadora, was
found in a U.S. mailbag in Costa Rica in 1985.
   A full break came in February 1988, when two federal grand
juries in Florida indicted Noriega on drug-trafficking and
money-laundering charges.
   The domestic opposition began to intensify its campaign against
Noriega and Washington imposed crippling economic sanctions.
   Noriega didn't budge.
   Noriega, through his control of the Defense Forces, was named
chief of government on Dec. 15 by a rubber-stamp assembly. It said
his leadership was needed to confront a ``state of war'' caused by
U.S. economic sanctions and other efforts to oust the general.
   He claims Washington wants to oust him to make it easier for the
United States to renege on the Panama Canal treaties.
   Shortly after the indictments in Floria, Noriega delivered a
speech. He brandished a machete above his head, then brought it
crashing down on the podium.
   ``Not one step back!'' he shouted.
</TEXT>

</DOC>