<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0249 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0510EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-SPE--Bride&amp;Groom:Briefs     12-18 0508</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-SPE--Bride &amp; Groom: Briefs,0512</SECOND>
<HEAD>SPECIAL EDITION</HEAD>
<HEAD>Bride &amp; Groom: Briefs</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY705</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The new edition of ``Bridal Guide: A Complete Guide on How to
Plan Your Wedding'' by Pamela Thomas is a combination source and
workbook to help you cope with all the details of your wedding.
   Besides the obvious arrangements of setting the date and places
for the ceremony and reception, the book covers details that might
get overlooked -- changing names on legal documents, or parking
facilities for guests. The book gives a countdown plan to keep
track of how far ahead arrangements should be started. Chapters
cover budgeting, showers, bridal registry, invitations, clothing,
flowers, videos and photography, transportation, the licence, the
cake, the honeymoon and many other details.
   The book is published by Bridal Guide Ltd. of La Crosse, Wis. _
   A new column in Bride's magazine helps steer bridal consumers
away from scams and shoddy goods and services. Called ``Watch
Out!!!,'' the column will offer precautionary tips and tell what to
do if you get stung.
   ``Many brides have been victimized by disreputable wedding
professionals when they are most vulnerable _ frenzied due to the
enormous task of arranging a wedding, and panicked over the amount
of money they're spending,'' writes columnist Laurie Werner. _
   If the bride doesn't receive an electric frypan, blender and
iron as gifts, these are the first appliances she'll buy herself,
according to a survey by the Association of Home Appliance
Manufacturers and Bride's magazine.
   The survey showed that all brides want small appliances as gifts
and that blenders and frypans top the list, desired by 74 percent
of those surveyed. Other popular appliances are automatic drip
coffeemakers, electric can openers, hand-held mixers, toasters and
irons. _
   Most men and women would re-marry their spouses if they had it
to do over, according to a survey commissioned by Korbel Champagne
Cellars.
   Among those surveyed, 91 percent said they'd pick the same mate.
The happiest of the sample are those who have been married for less
than seven years.
   ``Both men and women appear to be equally happy with their
choice of a spouse,'' says Marie Rama, Korbel's director of
weddings and entertaining. ``Regionally, Northeasterners say they
have the highest number of happy marriages, with 94 percent of
those surveyed maintaining that they would re-marry their spouses.
Respondents living in the North Central region of the country, with
89 percent, are the least likely to say `I Do' again.'' _
   A two-piece bridal set in sterling silver from Towle
Silversmiths features a cake knife and trowel for serving wedding
cake, which can be used for other cakes and pies after the wedding.
The set comes in all patterns and is boxed in a hand-rubbed
hardwood storage chest. Price is about $125. _
   Easy care glamour for the trousseau might include lacy,
old-world lingerie done up in modern fibers, such as Creme de
Captiva or Patina from Allied Fibers. Makers using the fabrics
include Character, Val Mode, Gilligan &amp; O'Malley, Fernando Sanchez,
and Nightflowers. _
</TEXT>

</DOC>