<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 2124EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Flight103 1stLd-Writethru a0734 12-17 0881</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Flight 103, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0734,0898</SECOND>
<HEAD>Flight 103 Trials Likely to Take Place in U.S., Report Says</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS two grafs after 9th `The Pan...' to UPDATE with memorial
to victims dedicated; pickup graf 10 pvs `The Sunday...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LESLIE SHEPHERD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scotland's chief law officer was quoted Sunday as
saying criminal trials arising from the bombing of Pan Am Flight
103 would probably take place in the United States.
   ``In this matter, on terrorists, I think there can be little
doubt that the Americans could assert a jurisdiction,'' Lord
Fraser, the lord advocate, was quoted as saying in an Edinburgh
weekly newspaper.
   But a spokesman for the lord advocate ``firmly refuted'' reports
that police have gathered enough evidence to charge several
suspects in the Dec. 21, 1988, bombing of the New York-bound flight.
   The Sunday Times of London said that despite their cautious
public statements, Scottish investigators told a secret,
five-nation summit of security services that ``charges are now
possible against certain persons.''
   The report said that police heading the international manhunt
told the meeting in Meckenheim, West Germany, that because of
extradition obstacles, some suspects might have to be tried abroad.
   The newspaper said leaders of security services in Britain, West
Germany, the United States, Sweden and Malta attended the summit.
It did not identify the source of its information or say when the
meeting occurred.
   A spokesman for Scotland's Crown Office, speaking anonymously in
keeping with British custom, said: ``The lord advocate has no
evidence before him with which to initiate warrants or extradition
proceedings.''
   Lord Fraser and Chief Constable George Esson of the Dumfries and
Galloway Constabulary told a news conference on Friday that
considerable progress had been made in their investigation but that
no arrests were imminent.
   The Pan Am flight originated in Frankfurt, West Germany, and
changed in London to a larger Boeing 747 which exploded over
Lockerbie, Scotland, killing all 259 people on board and 11 on the
ground. Investigators say the blast was caused by a bomb made of a
plastic explosives and packed in a radio-cassette player that was
placed in a suitcase loaded into a forward cargo hold.
   About 40 Lockerbie residents whose houses were damaged in the
crash gathered in the rain Sunday to witness the dedication of a
stone memorial to the victims.
   A piper played a Scottish lament, and three clergymen led
prayers and blessed the red sandstone block memorializing the
victims.
   The Sunday Times said police ``have for some time suspected who
the killers are'' but would probably wait until their inquiries are
completed in three or four months before starting criminal
proceedings.
   Esson told the news conference he could not put a timetable on
his investigation. He confirmed that Ahmed Jibril's radical
Palestinian group, the Popular Front for the Liberation of
Palestine-General Command, or PFLP-GC, has been under
investigation. Esson also confirmed investigators' interest in
Mohammed Abu Talb, a member of another Palestinian group, the
Popular Struggle Front, who is in jail in Sweden awaiting verdicts
Thursday on unrelated bombing charges. The Sunday Times said
Scottish police will interview him Monday.
   Terrorism experts and Western media say the PFLP-GC may have
been hired by Iran to avenge the July 1988 downing of an Iran Air
jetliner with 290 people aboard, by a U.S. warship in the Persian
Gulf. Iran has denied involvement.
   CBS reported in February that the attack was in revenge for the
1986 U.S. bombing of Libya and the U.S. decision to talk with the
Palestine Liberation Organization. They said Jibril cleared the
operation with Syrian intelligence and had the full backing of the
Libyan secret service.
   In his interview with the weekly newspaper Scotland on Sunday,
Lord Fraser said criminal trials would almost certainly take place
in the United States if it claimed jurisdiction under international
law. On Friday, he said it was possible trials could be held in
several countries.
   ``While this is an outrage to Scotland ... I never lose sight of
the fact that this was intended as a direct assault on American
sovereignty and for that reason I understand the strength of their
feeling, of their claim to American jurisdiction.''
   Lord Fraser was quoted as saying that Scotland would not compete
with the United States to extradite suspects from other countries,
unless a country holding a suspect refused an extradition request
because the United States has the death penalty.
   ``If, on the other hand, the United States was in that position
to secure extradition when the United Kingdom couldn't, I want
these people brought to justice and I wouldn't stand in the way of
anything,'' he was quoted as saying.
   Lord Fraser was quoted as saying he considered winding down the
police inquiry during the summer because of lack of progress, but
police then discovered new leads pointing to the Mediterranean
island of Malta.
   Unconfirmed news reports have said the suitcase bomb was
transferred to Flight 103 in Frankfurt from an Air Malta flight.
Some reported that police have traced scorched clothing and an
umbrella in the suitcase to Malta.
   Transport Secretary Cecil Parkinson said Sunday that Britain's
airports are more secure now than at the time of the bombing,
particularly for American aircraft ``which are regarded as a higher
risk than ours.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>