<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0313EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-US-PanamaStatement 4th(Final)Add   12-20 0420</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-US-Panama Statement, 4th (Final) Add,a0474 et. seq.,360</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHN: world leaders.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Q. Do we know the whereabouts now of Noriega and are U.S. forces
under strict orders not to shoot him or to injure him in any way?
   A. I just can't comment on the location of General Noriega or
what we do know about him. That would jeopardize the mission. I
just could not offer any comment.
   Q. What about the question of whether there are strict orders
not to shoot him or injure him, to make sure that he is apprehended
alive?
   A. The orders are to apprehend General Noriega. I would not go
beyond that.
   Q. Is President Endara in this country or in Panama?
   A. He's in Panama.
   Q. While the Panamanian Defense Forces perhaps may not measure
up to U.S. forces, nevertheless they're 6,500-strong. They're not
necessarily a pushover by any means. Yet you said tonight that
there was pretty much assurance on the part of the administration
that this mission would be successful. That indicates that there
may have been some communications with PDF Forces to either
participate or perhaps not resist. Was there any kind of
communication with PDF forces beforehand?
   A. I did not use the word ``assurance.'' I said that we would
not undertake such a mission if we did not feel confident that we
could carry it out successfully. I'm not aware of any
communications directly with the PDF.
   Q. You said the U.S. forces will be withdrawn as quickly as
possible. They will not be withdrawn until we have captured Noriega?
   A. We are not willing to specify how long or in what
circumstances they would be _ remain there.
   Q. Who's got operational control?
   A. Operational control is in the Pentagon.
   Let me just do one last thing on briefings, that I would expect
the next detailed briefing to be operationally oriented and related
to logistics and that will come from the Pentagon. We do not have a
time yet. I would not anticipate it soon, probably later in the
morning. I don't think there's any need for you all to stay here
the rest of the night, but you might want to hang around for a
while anyway. One final question.
   Q. You're sending massively troops in to get one man?
   A. There are four objectives to this. Getting General Noriega
out is certainly one of the main ones. It certainly is an
objective, yes. Thank you very much.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   END US-PANAMA STATEMENT _ 5 Takes
</TEXT>

</DOC>