<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1127EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel     12-25 0515</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel,0530</SECOND>
<HEAD>Trial Ordered for Colonel Who Ordered Beatings of Palestinians</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LOUIS MEIXLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The army Monday ordered the court-martial of an
Israeli colonel accused of telling troops to break the bones of 20
bound and gagged Palestinian prisoners.
   Col. Yehuda Meir will be the highest ranking officer to face
trial during the 2-year-old Palestinian uprising against Israeli
occupation, and the proceedings are expected to touch off debate
over the military's orders concerning the beating of Palestinians.
   In related developments Monday, a pathologist disclosed that a
Palestinian prisoner died while in the custody of the secret
police, and the military said an Israeli coronel would be indicted
for a shooting in which a 15-year-old Palestinian was killed.
   The army announcement to prosecute Meir came one day after the
Supreme Court overturned the military's decision not to press
charges. The announcement gave no date for the trial.
   Meir was reprimanded by Lt. Gen. Dan Shomron, the armed forces
chief of staff, for the January 1988 incident and given the choice
of leaving the army or standing trial. Meir, the former military
commander in the occupied West Bank city of Nablus, resigned in
April.
   The army's chief prosecutor, Brig. Gen. Amnon Straschnow, had
argued that Meir's dismissal from the army was adequate punishment
and trying the coronel would be difficult because the army's orders
on the use of force were ``foggy.''
   Testimony in trials of other soldiers showed that at the time
army orders allowed soldiers to beat stone-throwers to deter
further acts. The orders have since been changed to ban such
beatings.
   The independent Maariv newspaper, quoting military sources, said
Straschnow may resign after the Supreme Court rejected his decision
and accepted the appeal by four Palestinians and the Association
for Civil Rights in Israel.
   Justice Yaakov Kadmi wrote that Meir's orders to beat
Palestinian detainees ``stands in complete contradiction to the
basic foundations of the nation of Israel.''
   Meir is accused of ordering troops to beat and break the legs of
20 bound and gagged Palestinians from the nearby towns of Hawara
and Beita.
   Soldiers under his command left beaten and bound Palestinians in
a field until other Arabs arrived and rushed then to a hospital.
   He was also investigated in connection with an incident in which
troops beat two Palestinian teenagers in Nablus. The incident was
filmed by a U.S. television crew.
   The military disclosed Monday that Straschnow decided last week
to indict an unidentified colonel for firing plastic bullets in
violation of army orders and fatally wounding a 15-year-old Gazan
five months ago.
   Also Monday, pathologist Michael Baden said a prisoner from the
occupied Gaza Strip died from internal bleeding caused by blows to
the abdomen.
   Baden, who works for the New York City police department, was
called as an independent investigator by the family of Khaled Kamel
Sheikh Ali. Ali, 27, was found dead Dec. 19 in his prison cell
while in the custody of the Shin Bet secret service.
   Baden questioned five Shin Bet investigators who were involved
in Ali's interrogation, Israel radio said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>