<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1337EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Romania 7thLd-Writethru a0578 12-21 1051</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania, 7th Ld-Writethru, a0578,1082</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Security Forces Reportedly Open Fire in Romanian Capital; Deaths
Reported</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 10 grafs to UPDATE with Politburo reported meeting,
witness account of tank crushing protesters. Pickup 9th pvs, `The Western...</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALISON SMALE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Security forces opened fire on crowds of
anti-government protesters in the Romanian capital of Bucharest
today, and several demonstrators were killed, Yugoslav radio
reported.
   Military tanks rolled through the city and formed a circle
around several thousand mostly young people at a main intersection
in an effort to control the burgeoning unrest, said a Yugoslav
reporter.
   A Soviet news report from Bucharest said, ``Along the central
street of the capital, tanks are moving, following the lines of
submachine gunners pushing back the crowds. Bursts of automatic
weapons fire are being heard. Panic-stricken people are hiding in
doorways and courtyards.''
   The unrest was the first reported in the capital since
demonstrations against the hard-line president, Nicolae Ceausescu,
broke out over the weekend on the other side of the country in the
city of Timisoara.
   There were chilling reports by Yugoslav media that soldiers and
police who refused to shoot at demonstrators in Timisoara were
publicly executed. And Tass said workers occupied businesses in the
western city today and threatened to blow them up if demands for a
new government were not met.
   Hungarian radio said the Romanian Communist Party's ruling
Politburo was meeting in an unannounced session, which was likely
to discuss measures to curb the unrest. It said some protesters
chanted, ``The army is with us!''
   The unrest is the biggest challenge to Ceausescu's 24-year-long
authoritarian rule and reportedly has spread to a dozen cities.
Access to the country by foreign reporters is strictly curtailed,
but witnesses have said hundreds and perhaps thousands of people
have been killed.
   Shots were also reported fired today at protesters in the city
of Arad, about 40 miles from Timisoara. There was no immediate word
on casualties there. Security forces first used tear gas to try to
quell protests in Bucharest, a reporter for the Yugoslav news
agency Tanjug said on Belgrade radio.
   The protest turned into ``bloody riots'' as police fired into
crowds and killed and wounded several people, the correspondent
said. The number of casualties was not known.
   The Yugoslav journalist, Petar Tomic of Yugoslavia's state-run
Tanjug news agency, said an armoured vehicle crushed two students.
Other students rushed to their aid and security forces opened fire,
killing or wounding around 20 people, Tomic said.
   
   The Western diplomat reported seeing at least four ambulances in
the city center shortly after the protests began.
   Tass reported ``a great many'' fire trucks and military vehicles
in the center of the city and said all approaches to the
Presidential Palace and Communist Party headquarters were blocked
by army units.
   ``The crowd of protesters, which first numbered a few hundred,
has now increased to several thousand,'' it reported. ``Those
gathered in the square are shouting the slogans `Freedom!' `Down
with dictatorship!' They are stopping buses and cars.''
   Security forces also fired on protesters during a general strike
in Arad, according to Klaus Lanz, a spokesman for ethnic German
Romanians based in Munich.
   A Romanian who arrived in Yugoslavia today from Timisoara said
that city was in the second day of a general strike. Asking that he
not be identified, he told reporters at the border he had heard
reports of demonstrations today in the southern city of Craiova and
in Suceava in the north.
   Tass said factories in Timisoara were closed and occupied by
workers who demanded that the government resign, the military leave
the city, and leaders be called to account for the loss of lives in
the city.
   ``According to the latest information, the military units have
started to leave,'' Tass said.
   In East Germany today, the government recalled its ambassador
from Bucharest, and Czechoslovakia issued a formal protest as
European nations formed a united front to condemn the repression.
   President Francois Mitterrand of France said Ceausescu's days
are numbered and called for his replacement. But he ruled out
foreign intervention to topple Ceausescu, who has refused to adopt
the reforms accepted in other East bloc countries.
   Elsewhere in the East bloc today:
   _The Czechoslovak Communist Party voted to immediately disband
the hated paramilitary People's Militia, which was used to help
crush dissent, a day after publicly apologizing for its hard-line
policies of the past.
   _Hungary's Parliament paved the way for free elections next year
by voting to dissolve itself in March.
   The Western diplomat in Bucharest, who spoke on condition of
anonymity, said by telephone that Ceausescu was interrupted today
at an official rally called to support his tough stance against
protesters.
   The speech was broadcast on radio and television. When shouts
erupted, the broadcast abruptly switched to patriotic music for
about three minutes. It then then resumed with Ceausescu in
mid-sentence.
   As Ceausescu returned to the air waves, people were heard loudly
applauding his promises of a higher minimum wage, increased
allowances for families with children, and other benefits
apparently intended to quell discontent, the diplomat said.
   But protesters then marched through the streets of Bucharest
shouting anti-Ceausescu slogans, the source said. Hungarian radio
said people burned banners they were issued for the pro-Ceausescu
rally.
   Witnesses say hundreds, possibly thousands, of unarmed people
were shot to death in Timisoara on Saturday and Sunday while
protesting Ceausescu.
   The 71-year-old president declared a state of emergency in the
Timisoara region Wednesday after tens of thousands of people
chanting ``Give us our dead!' reportedly protested.
   The Belgrade daily Politika quoted witnesses Wednesday as saying
they saw two soldiers and an officer killed ``on the spot'' by
security agents after refusing to fire on anti-government
demonstrators.
   The Yugoslav news agency Tanjug reported that a group of Syrian
students arriving in Yugoslavia this morning from Timisoara said
demonstrations were still going on in the city during the night.
   A resident of Timisoara told Hungarian television that 80,000 to
90,000 people took part.
   Breaking his silence on the unrest Wednesday, Ceausescu blamed
the protests on ``hooligans'' incited by ``a brazen campaign of
slander and lies'' from abroad, especially Hungary.
   He has been accused by Budapest of persecuting ethnic
Hungarians, who are concentrated in the Transylvanian region that
includes Timisoara.
</TEXT>

</DOC>