<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0172 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 2320EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Panama-Funerals     12-29 0920</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Funerals,0950</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mourners Honor Servicemen Killed in Panama Invasion</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MONTROSE, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An 18-year-old paratrooper killed in the
Panamanian invasion was among six U.S. servicemen buried with
military honors Friday.
   Army Pvt. James A. Tabor, Jr., who died one week ago when U.S.
forces invaded to dislodge dictator Manuel Noriega, was eulogized
at a ceremony in Montrose, Colo., by his great-uncle.
   ``From time to time we must enforce our principles of liberty
and human dignity with action,'' said retired Army Col. Vernon
Ebert.
   ``This serves notice again that this country is prepared to give
more than rhetoric,'' Ebert said. ``Jim and the others did not die
in vain. They went out in a noble way, serving their country with
idealism and pride.''
   Tabor was among 23 U.S. servicemen who died in the invasion.
   More than 700 mourners packed the Montrose Christian Church for
the military service for Tabor, who would have been 19 on Jan. 16.
Tabor was buried in Olathe beside his grandfather.
   An Army squad from Fort Carson fired a 21-gun salute and a
bugler played ``Taps'' as the late afternoon sun turned to gold the
winter landscape above the Uncompahgre River.
   Tabor enlisted July 5 and went to jump school at Fort Benning,
Georgia. His family last saw him in November when he came home on
leave and went elk hunting with his father, John, Sr., and one of
his two brothers.
   In South Carolina, Marine Cpl. Garreth C. Isaak, 22, was buried
in Greenville, shortly before Chief Warrant Officer Wilson B.
Owens, 29, was buried in Myrtle Beach.
   Owens died Dec. 20 when his two-man helicopter was shot down.
Having served in both the Navy and most recently the Army, he was
an aviator with B Company, 160th Aviation Battalion, based at Fort
Campbell, Ky.
   About 300 people attended his funeral, including about 20
members of his unit and representatives of the Charleston police,
Myrtle Beach Air Force Base and Brig. Gen. Dennis Leach of Fort
Jackson Army base in Columbia.
   A table by the coffin Friday held Owens' helmet, night vision
goggles and his beret.
   Lt. Col. John Binkley of Owens' unit presented two U.S. flags
used during the service to Owens' parents. And at the grave site at
Southeastern Memorial Gardens nearby, Owens was given a 21-gun
salute and two buglers played taps.
   Issak, based at Camp Lejeune, N.C., had been in Panama since
October and was scheduled to return to the United States in
January. Shot an hour after the invasion began, he died eight days
shy of his 23rd birthday.
   He joined the Marine Corps on May 25, 1985, a week after
graduating from high school. About 1,000 attended his funeral
service at Greenville's Hampton Park Baptist Church, followed by
burial at nearby Woodlawn Memorial Park.
   U.S. Sen. Strom Thurmond called Isaak ``a brave Marine and a
great patriot who fought for his country, believed in freedom and
was willing to give his life for it.''
   In North Carolina, Pfc. Jerry Scott Daves, who was killed in the
early hours of the Panama invasion, was buried at the Fort Bragg
Cemetery, only miles from where he graduated from high school a
little more than a year ago.
   Daves, 20, of Hope Mills, an paratrooper with the 82nd Airborne
at Fort Bragg, was killed Wednesday in a clash with Panamanian
Defense Forces. His battalion attacked a small army post at
Tinajitas within hours of the invasion.
   A private memorial service was held at the base chapel before a
graveside ceremony at the base cemetery attended by some 300
people, including friends and relatives who chartered a bus from
Daves' childhood home in Catawba County.
   After a brief prayer by the Rev. Edward Orinson of Salisbury,
seven riflemen fired a 21-gun salute, and another serviceman played
``Taps.''
   As the service ended, a flag was presented to Daves' mother,
Sherry Henderson of Hickory, who held it briefly to her face and
wept. Another flag was given to Daves' father, Jerry W. Daves of
Hope Mills.
   Daves joined the Army on Aug. 4, 1988, shortly after graduating
from Southview High School in Hope Mills, which is only a few miles
from Fort Bragg. Friends said his dream throughout high school was
to be a soldier. In December of 1988, a day shy of a year before he
was killed, Daves was assigned to the 82nd Airborne.
   In Illinois, 19-year-old Army Pfc. Scott Lee Roth, was laid to
rest under rainy gray skies in the National Cemetery at the Rock
Island Arsenal.
   More than 40 servicemen attended the funeral, including Gary
Travis, Roth's commanding officer from Fort Hood, Texas.
   Roth's wife, Mary _ his high school sweetheart who enlisted with
him after graduation _ attended the service with her family and a
military escort.
   Roth had been stationed at Fort Hood with his wife since last
year. He had been in Panama since August with 124 military
policemen from the Texas base.
   Army 1st Lt. John Hunter, 30, who died Dec. 20, was eulogized in
a funeral service at Lake Havasu City, Ariz., and attended by an
honor guard from the Fort Huachuca Army base in southeastern
Arizona.
   Hunter, a native of Libby, Mont., was a helicopter pilot with
the 160th Special Operations Aviation Group stationed at Fort
Campbell, Ky.
   He enlisted as a private in December 1976 and later attended
Officer Candidate School and, most recently, the Embry Riddle
Aeronautical University. He had been a helicopter pilot for 8{
years.
</TEXT>

</DOC>