<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0156 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1541EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-Symposium-China Adv31   12-26 1045</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Symposium-China, Adv 31,1071</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 31, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WORLD SYMPOSIUM '90s: China _ Aging Leadership, Troubled Times</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM ABRAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An aging, unpopular leadership, a faltering
economy and a restive population make for an uncertain and troubled
future as China enters the last decade of the 20th century.
   Pessimists hold the field as China emerges from one of the worst
of many bad years under Communist Party rule _ a year in which
troops gunned down young demonstrators in the streets of Beijing,
long-nurtured ties with the West collapsed and a decade of economic
reforms ground to a halt.
   China's goals for the end of the century, the quadrupling of
national income compared to 1980, the smooth reversion of Hong Kong
to Chinese sovereignty in 1997 and the triumphant staging of the
Olympic games in the year 2000, are all suspended in doubt.
   The key question is how long China can resist the storms of
change that have swept through the communist autocracies of the
Soviet Union and Eastern Europe.
   Much depends on the health of the 85-year-old Deng Xiaoping, the
pragmatist who brought prosperity to millions of Chinese with his
market-oriented reforms but who also represents the old
revolutionaries using Stalinist repression to stifle popular
dissent.
   Deng's chosen successor is Jiang Zemin, 63, a relative unknown
who became head of the 48-million-member Communist Party in June
after reformist Zhao Ziyang was accused of supporting the
pro-democracy movement and purged from all his party posts.
   Jiang, the former Shanghai party boss, is believed to favor
economic reforms but, following the current line, has come across
as a hardliner since taking office. He needs time to develop his
weak political base and cultivate his political image, but if Deng,
believed to be in frail health, goes quickly, Jiang could face a
rapid ride into oblivion.
   His rivals for power are ideological conservatives such as
Premier Li Peng and octogenarian President Yang Shangkun.
   Their ascendancy would not mean a return to communes, backyard
steel mills and international isolation. But it would accelerate
the trend, already in progress, of re-emphasizing central planning,
stifling private initiative and retreating on economic and
political reforms.
   Their demand for unquestioning loyalty to the communist system
and Communist Party rule also would put them on what many Chinese
feel is an inevitable collision course with the forces of reform.
   The Tiananmen Square movement for a more democratic, open
society, crushed by the military, is quiescent but is certain to
re-emerge when the government lets down its guard. Events in
Eastern Europe have bolstered beliefs that the Chinese government
cannot forever resist popular demand for reform.
   Tiananmen also has clouded China's future relationship with Hong
Kong and complicated its long-term goal of reuniting with Taiwan,
the Nationalist island.
   China has promised not to touch Hong Kong's capitalist system
for 50 years after the British depart in 1997. But the nearly 6
million people of Hong Kong were badly shaken by the events of
June, setting off a wave of emigrations among the colony's most
talented people that is likely to continue until 1997.
   The rival Nationalist government on Taiwan in recent years has
eased restrictions on trade with and visits to the mainland,
raising China's hopes of eventual reunification. But Tiananmen
reinforced anti-Communist sentiments on the island and probably
strengthened the growing movement for Taiwanese independence.
   Internationally, China's relations with the West will remain at
a subnormal level as long as suppression of political dissent is an
issue. That could spell bad news for the nation's economic
planners, who badly need Western investment and technology to carry
out the modernization drive.
   ``The bloom is off the rose,'' said one Western economist, who
noted that Western businessmen will be inclined to spend their
money in more politically palatable places like Eastern Europe or
the Soviet Union.
   Investors are also concerned about the current government's
backsliding on reforms and moves to re-establish the primacy of
central planning, fixed pricing and party influence in the work
place.
   A retrenchment program, to continue at least until 1991, has had
some success in cooling an overheated economy and bringing down
inflation.
   But China is seen by outside experts as being unable to compete
with other rising economic powers such as Taiwan and South Korea
unless it pushes ahead with reforms, notably making prices
correspond to market value.
   Economists see a possibility of China becoming another
Yugoslavia, where high expectations for reform were followed by
poor follow-through and years of dismal performance.
   Beijing's leaders, trying to reassert state authority over the
economy, also are likely to run into a growing trend of
provincialism and regional rivalries fostered over the last decade
when local powers were delegated greater autonomy. There is a real
danger that the provinces, such as the prosperous southern China
area near Hong Kong, will increasingly defy orders from Beijing.
   China, with 1.1 billion people now, will have nearly 200 million
more mouths to feed in the year 2000 and must substantially improve
its stagnating agricultural output if it is to remain
self-sufficient.
   The nation faces other staggering problems:
   _Repayment of international debts of $44 billion reaches a peak
period in the early 1990s and the government will be hard pressed
to find the hard currency.
   _The education system is badly underfunded and little headway is
being made in reducing an illiteracy rate of 20 percent, more than
200 million people.
   _The average annual income is less than $300 a person, the urban
housing situation is abysmal and the welfare system surprisingly
inadequate for a socialist country. More than 20 percent of the
labor force is said to be surplus or redundant and little is being
done to prepare the nation for a serious unemployment problem.
   ``China in transition is a China that will be struggling to
resolve formidable contradictions,'' U.S. Ambassador James Lilley
said in a recent speech.
   ``It may be some years before we can put a name or theme to the
new chapter China will write in the 1990s. In the meantime, we must
be prepared for twists and turns that may defy attempts to label as
pragmatic or political, liberal or conservative, reform or
retrogressive.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Sunday, Dec. 31</NOTE>

</DOC>