<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0140 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1640EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Communists     12-29 0524</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Communists,0542</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romanians Can't Afford to Purge Party</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERRY LEONARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Many Romanians who have thrown off the
yoke of their dictator want to make a clean break with the past,
but the new leadership says the country can't afford to purge
former Communist Party members.
   In Romania, virtually everyone in a leading position was
required to be a party member. And party membership, government
officials say, is not a mark of ideology.
   ``Many Communist Party members are indespensible,'' said Cazimir
Ionescu, one of the vice presidents of the provisional government.
   ``We have not followed the old system of looking at dossiers,''
Ionescu said at a news conference.
   The Communist Party has become a hated reminder in Romania of
the 24 years of Nicolae Ceausscu, who was overthrown, captured and
executed in a bloody revolution that came so swiftly the country
has had no time to plan its future.
   ``Jos Comunismul'' _ ``Down with Communism'' _ is a slogan that
now appears on posters and scrawled on walls around the captial.
   Romanians in the street say they want to wipe the words
Communist Party from their mind and language.
   ``Communism is shame and it should be destroyed everywhere,''
said Gheorghe Chelaru, who described himself only as a worker.
   But members of the provisional government say they are trying to
run a country and an economy. They need managers and organizers
with a proven record. In Romania, all those people once belonged to
the party.
   The new government is trying to take people on the basis of
merit, not their past, said Ionescu.
   Prominent ex-Communists in the new leadership include President
Ion Iliescu, former Ambassador to the United States Silviu Brucan,
and former Foreign Minister Corneliu Manescu.
   Dumitru Mazilu, another leading figure, was a diplomat who was
under house arrest for most of the last two years because he
refused to doctor a report for the U.N. Human Rights Commission in
Geneva.
   Even the poet Mircea Dinescu, one of the country's leading
dissidents, was a member of the party, until last spring.
   ``The party doesn't exist anymore. Where do you see the party?
How can it contribute to the revolution? We don't know. We didn't
ask those who came to the palace (to join the revolution), Are you
Communists?'' said deputy Foreign Minister Corneliu Bogdan. ``I
myself was a member of the party.''
   ``If we begin to count by number, then I think you are missing
the point,'' he told journalists who repeatedly asked how many
former Communists are in the new leadership.
   Bogdan and Ionescu said the new government was committed to
ending the abuses of Ceausescu. They pointed out that the
government moved quickly to repeal some of the most hated laws.
   Romanians are free to travel, ration cards have been eliminated
and food once destined for export has been redirected to the shops.
   Ionescu and Bogdan say they are committed to democracy, to
opening a free market and to holding free elections by April.
   The government officials say if the people don't like the former
Communists, they can vote them out.
</TEXT>

</DOC>