<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0124 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0319EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NewspaperAwards 2ndLd-Writethru a0713 12-30 0550</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Newspaper Awards, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0713,0559</SECOND>
<HEAD>Washington Post, San Francisco Examiner Win Contest</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS grafs 6-8, `Certificates of ..., to CORRECT spelling of
Laurie, sted Lori, and Staats, sted Stalts.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>COLUMBIA, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Reporter Ken Ringle of The Washington Post
won the top award for best story and the San Francisco Examiner won
for the best series in the annual J.C. Penney-University of
Missouri Newspaper Awards.
   Ringle won the Paul Myhre Award for Excellence in Reporting for
a story titled ``Memory and Anger.'' The Examiner staff won the
Myhre award for a series called ``Gay in America.''
   About 1,600 entries were received from 237 newspapers for the
30th annual judging. The winners were announced this week by Dean
Mills, dean of the Missouri School of Journalism.
   The awards are to be presented April 4 at the end of the annual
J.C. Penney-Missouri Newspaper Workshop.
   Joe Bargmann of the Boston Phoenix and Clifford Pugh of The
Houston Post were awarded certificates of merit in the Myhre
category for single stories.
   Certificates of merit also went to Pete Hernon of the St. Louis
Post-Dispatch, Laurie Garrett of Newsday in New York and Long
Island, Paul McEnroe of the Star Tribune in Minneapolis, Minn.,
Marco R. della Cava of the El Paso (Texas) Times, Bob Welch of the
Journal American in Bellevue, Wash., and Donald Patterson of the
Greensboro (N.C.) News &amp; Record.
   Steve Sonsky of The Miami Herald took the top prize in the Arts
and Entertainment category for ``Bye Pal.'' Certificates of merit
went to James Chute of The Orange County (Calif.) Register, Matty
Karas of the Asbury Park (N.J.) Press, Deloris Tarzen Ament of The
Seattle Times, Rick Morin of The Washington Times, and Lynn
Rollings of the Alabama Journal in Montgomery.
   Craig Staats of The Tribune in Oakland, Calif., was the winner
in the Consumer Affairs category. Certificates of merit were giving
to Anne Voegetlin of The Columbian in Vancouver, Wash., and to the
features staff of The Miami Herald.
   The judges did not award a top prize in the fashion category,
saying ``we need fashion writers to tell us not just what style is
popular, but why.''
   Marina Pisano of the San Antonio Express-News and Glenn Kessler
of Newsday were given honorable mentions for fashion writing.
   In Food and Nutrition, Sheryl Julian of The Boston Globe won for
``Getting Food to the Hungry.''
   Steve Sternberg of the Atlanta Journal won in Health and
Fitness. Certificates of merit went to Tom Harris of The Sacramento
Bee and Diana Hunt of the Houston Chronicle.
   Awards were also made for Lifestyle sections.
   The winners were the Jackson Hole (Wyo.) Guide and the Mercer
Island (Wash.) Reporter in circulation 10,000 and under; the
Brazosport (Texas) Facts, the Visalia (Calif.) Times Delta and The
Reporter in Marin, Calif., in circulation 10,000 to 25,000; the
Gwinett (Ga.) Daily News, the Marin (Calif.) Independent Journal
and the St. Cloud (Minn.) Times in circulation 25,000 to 50,000;
the Syracuse (N.Y.) Herald Journal and The Register Guard in
Eugene, Ore., in circulation 50,000 to 100,000; The Washington
Times, the Albuquerque (N.M.) Journal and the Virginian-Pilot in
Norfolk, Va., in circulation 100,000 to 200,000; and The Miami
Herald, the San Jose (Calif.) Mercury News and the Star Tribune in
Minneapolis, Minn., in circulation over 200,000.
</TEXT>

</DOC>