<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1853EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Judge-Explosion 2ndLd-Writethru a0775 12-17 0924</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Judge-Explosion, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0775,0947</SECOND>
<HEAD>Agents Probe Slaying Of Federal Judge Killed By Mail Bomb</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS grafs 5-6, `Asked whether ...,' with 2 grafs to CLARIFY
that Moore was asked whether death was connected to drug cases, DELETE
extraneous word `he' from 6th graf; picks up 7th graf, `U.S. Marshal ...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KENDAL WEAVER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOUNTAIN BROOK, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Federal agents Sunday searched the
secluded estate of a federal judge killed by a mail bomb delivered
to his home. Investigators said a drug-related motive was one
possibility being examined.
   Robert S. Vance, an 11th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals judge,
was killed instantly when the package exploded Saturday afternoon
in the kitchen of his suburban Birmingham home, authorities said.
His wife, Helen, was injured and remained hospitalized Sunday in
serious condition.
   Vance, 58, a progressive force in Alabama during 11 years as
state chairman of the Democratic Party, was the third federal judge
to be assassinated in 10 years. The three are believed to be the
only federal jurists killed this century.
   FBI spokesman Tom Moore said there were ``specific leads'' but
declined to elaborate, saying only that investigators were pursuing
numerous possibilities.
   Asked whether Vance's death was connected to drug cases handled
by his court, ``It is not being ruled out, but it is no more
prominent than several other avenues we are following. We are
reviewing his full case load.''
   Agent Allen Whitaker said every FBI agent in the Birmingham area
was working on the case. He said many details could not disclosed
because of the ``very rapid, breaking nature of this
investigation.''
   U.S. Marshal Thomas C. Greene said Vance had not asked for
protection and the marshal's office was not aware of any threats on
his life. Greene would not say whether security has been increased
for judges because of the slaying.
   Asked about security for other federal judges, Moore said,
``They have been warned,'' but declined to say if any were under
guard. Judges may request security at any time, he added.
   Vance, appointed to the federal appeals court in 1977, served in
a circuit that reviewed cases from Florida, Georgia and Alabama.
   ``As a member of the 11th Circuit Court of Appeals, they heard
many appeal cases related to drugs from Miami,'' Sen. Howell
Heflin, D-Ala., a longtime friend of Vance, said Saturday.
``There's speculation in that regard, but nobody knows.''
   The circuit has 12 judges, as well as six judges on senior, or
semi-retired, status. The judges generally serve on three-judge
panels that review rulings made by trial-level courts.
   In Miami, U.S. District Judge Lawrence King said if Vance's
death were related to drug trafficking, ``you would be more apt to
see this type of violence directed toward a judge or magistrate at
the trial level in Florida, or perhaps Alabama.
   ``But who knows?'' King told The Birmingham News.
   Vance's two-story home in Birmingham's most exclusive suburb was
cordoned off Sunday as federal and local authorities searched it.
   Whitaker said FBI agents and postal inspectors spoke with Mrs.
Vance at the hospital, and she ``has provided information that will
be helpful in an investigation.''
   Whitaker said Mrs. Vance apparently was not standing close to
her husband when the bomb exploded. She was able to call a
neighbor, who then summoned police to the home, Moore said.
   ``Indications are that it was delivered by regular U.S. mail,''
not special delivery, Moore said.
   Moore said Vance's family was being guarded, but declined to
give details. The couple, which had been married 36 years, had two
sons, Robert S. Vance Jr., a Birmingham lawyer, and Charles Vance,
whose residence wasn't known immediately.
   Whitaker and Jefferson County District Attorney David Barber
joined investigators inside the home on a narrow, curving road
lined by houses set deep in wooded estates.
   Vance was appointed to the federal appeals court in 1977 by
President Carter and took his seat the following year. He continued
to live and work in the Birmingham area, although the court is
based in Atlanta.
   As state Democratic Party chairman from 1966 to 1977, Vance was
a force for racial moderation, fighting off attacks by then-Gov.
George C. Wallace against the national Democratic Party.
   In 1974, Wallace sought to wrest control of the state party from
Vance, but in a secret ballot in Birmingham, Vance turned back
Wallace's handpicked choice for chairman.
   ``He was a voice of sanity in turbulent times and a leader of
reasoned action,'' said Heflin, who met Vance more than 30 years
ago when they were young trial lawyers. ``Alabama and America's
jurisprudence has suffered a tremendous loss.''
   It was believed that only two other federal judges have been
assassinated this century.
   U.S. District Judge Richard Daronco, 56, was shot and killed at
his home in Pelham, N.Y., in 1988 by a former policeman angry at
Daronco's dismissal of a sex discrimination lawsuit filed by his
daughter. Charles Koster, 67, killed himself after gunning down the
judge.
   District Judge John H. Wood Jr., 63, was killed by a sniper
outside his home in San Antonio in 1979. Charles Voyed Harrelson
was convicted of the contract killing and is serving two life
sentences in a Texas prison. El Paso drug trafficker Jamiel
``Jimmy'' Chagra, who authorities say ordered the hit, was
convicted of conspiring to obstruct the investigation of Wood's
murder and various drug charges. He is serving a life sentence in
federal prison.
   Chagra had been scheduled to go on trial on drug charges before
Wood the day the judge was slain.
</TEXT>

</DOC>