<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0092 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1759EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-StadiumPlan     12-25 0295</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stadium Plan,0304</SECOND>
<HEAD>No Way To Repay Site Purchase Debt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A private, non-profit corporation working for a
new stadium in Cleveland has no way of repaying $24.2 million in
real estate loans that have come due, but banks aren't upset.
   The obligation came due Saturday, but with planning for a new
stadium stalled, the Greater Cleveland New Stadium Corp. ``does not
have the resources to repay the debt at this time,'' said spokesman
Richard Shatten.
   The New Stadium group borrowed the money to acquire the stadium
site in the old Central Market neighborhood.
   A group of Cleveland banks loaned $18 million and the state
loaned $4 million. Both loans came due in full in June but the
banks and the state approved six-month extensions. Interest owed
amounts to $2.2 million.
   Edward Brandon, representing the group of banks, said Friday the
institutions would not move to collect the debt now.
   ``Officially, whether we extend or let it run past due, it
doesn't matter,'' said Brandon, who also chairs Cleveland-based
National City Corp. ``The only important thing is the banks haven't
gotten their backs up and don't feel they have been betrayed and
won't start legal proceedings.''
   Brandon said the banks supported current stadium development
talks among elected officials and would ``work toward seeing the
proper results come out of those conversations.''
   Joseph Marinucci, state deputy director of business development,
said a formal payment notice for the state's share of the debt
would go to the stadium group this week.
   ``We will ask them to provide to us, in writing, what they're
going to do,'' he said.
   Stadium talks are focusing on bringing local elected officials
to agreement on how to develop a new ballpark for the Cleveland
Indians and-or the Cleveland Browns.
</TEXT>

</DOC>