<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1235EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China-HongKong     12-19 0535</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Hong Kong,0546</SECOND>
<HEAD>China Criticizes Calls for Greater Democracy in Hong Kong</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHY WILHELM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   China on Tuesday criticized demands for greater
democracy in Hong Kong as an attempt to ``bring the Chinese
government to its knees'' and limit its sovereignty after Britain
returns the colony in 1997.
   It also said it was up to Britain to ``come back to the correct
road of friendly cooperation.'' China's relations with Britain, as
with most Western countries, have deteriorated following the
Chinese army attack on pro-democracy protesters in June.
   The comments came in a lengthy essay excerpted in the official
People's Daily and other newspapers, to be published in full in the
weekly Beijing Review magazine. The essay marked the fifth
anniversary of the signing of the Sino-British Joint Declaration in
which Britain agreed to return Hong Kong and China agreed to let it
remain capitalist for at least 50 years.
   The essay said that although Hong Kong will retain a ``high
degree of autonomy'' after 1997, its relationship to Beijing will
be that of a local government to a sovereign central state.
   ``Some people, in an attempt to pit `democracy against
communism,' suggest that the `democratic process be accelerated' in
developing Hong Kong's democratic system,'' the essay said.
   ``They stress that this is the desire of the Hong Kong people in
an attempt to create a de facto situation to bring the Chinese
government to its knees. These people are actually seeking, under
the pretext of democracy, to establish a power pattern in Hong Kong
after 1997 that will ... harm China's sovereignty,'' it said.
``This, we resolutely oppose.''
   Some Hong Kong residents, fearful of Chinese rule, have pressed
the colonial government to introduce more democratic rule in the
hope that China would find it hard to undo such reforms after 1997.
The Hong Kong government has agreed to allow elections in 1991 to
fill 10 of the 56 seats in the colony's legislative council, which
is appointed by the government and local interest groups.
   There also have been calls for at least 40 percent of Hong
Kong's post-1997 legislature to be popularly elected. But the Hong
Kong-Chinese committee drafting the colony's post-1997 basic law
recently agreed that only 30 percent of the delegates should be
chosen by elections.
   China has reiterated that it will not allow Hong Kong to become
a base for anti-government and anti-Communist activity, and has
moved to include in the basic law provisions against subversive
activity.
   The essay said Hong Kong residents will be allowed after 1997 to
raise opinions about China's state affairs, but only through legal
channels.
   ``If unsuitable means are adopted to express one's own
viewpoints, things might go contrary to their wishes and damage
might be brought upon the friendly relationship between the
mainland and Hong Kong,'' it warned. All political activity will
have to respect the mainland's socialist system, it said.
   The mainland's Constitution allows no political activity
independent of the Communist Party.
   A committee of 33 mainland delegates and 23 Hong Kong delegates
is working on the final draft of Hong Kong's post-1997 basic law.
It is to be submitted to China's legislature in the spring for
approval.
</TEXT>

</DOC>