<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0317EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Romania-WhatNext?     12-23 0857</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-What Next?,0885</SECOND>
<HEAD>Discredited Romanian Communist Party Has Little Chance For Survival</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIOREL URMA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Discredited by Nicolae Ceausescu's harsh
rule and its central role as his loyal cheerleader, the Communist
Party in Romania appears to have little chance of staying at the
helm.
   Ceausescu, who had ruled since 1965 and cut off any attempt at
organized opposition, was overthrown Friday in fierce battles that
left hundreds dead.
   In the bloodiest decision during his long rule, Ceausescu
ordered the use of lethal force one week ago against protesters in
the western city of Timisoara who demanded his ouster.
   Security forces there reportedly killed several thousand people,
including many children and woman, and dumped their bodies into
mass graves in a forest near the city.
   Ceausescu's use of deadly force, intended to perpetuate the last
Stalinist regime in Eastern Europe at any cost, contrasted sharply
with recent Communist responses to protesters in other Soviet bloc
countries.
   Police in East Germany, Czechoslovakia and Bulgaria did not fire
on proteters.
   Romania is different in many ways from its Warsaw Pact allies.
Ceausescu created a personality cult around himself that seemed to
entwine his own political survival with that of the Communist Party.
   Much like North Korea's Kim Il Sung, Ceausescu created a family
dynasty in Romania, with some 40 relatives reportedly placed in key
state and party jobs.
   ``In Romania, the Communist Party existed only to clap and cheer
Ceausescu. It hardly was a political party,'' said Ion Ratiu,
chairman of the London-based World Union of Free Romanians.
   ``After Ceausescu's ouster, the Communist Party will likely
crumble, unlike in Czechoslovakia, Poland and East Germany where a
degree of divergent views was tolerated,'' said a Romanian exile at
the U.S.-financed Radio Free Europe radio station.
   Mircea Stoica, a professor at Bucharest University who this week
defected to Hungary, said a party congress last month where
Ceausescu was ``unanimously'' elected for another five years was
``actually 90 percent organized and run by the secret police.''
   ``The 5,000 delegates to the congress, before entering the
Palace Hall, were searched for alleged weapons like common
criminals and had to pass through metal detectors. What bigger
humiliation for a Communist do you want?'' Stoica said.
   On Friday, Ion Iliescu, a former Central Committee secretary
ousted by Ceausescu in 1971, announced the formation of the
``National Salvation Front'' described as the ``new organism of
state power.''
   ``We will establish a new structure of political power. The old
structure of party and government was liquidated,'' Iliescu told a
Bucharest crowd.
   ``We will establish a provisional structure, which will prepare
free elections in which the people will be the decisive factor for
our public life,'' he said.
   In a late night statement broadcast live by Romanian radio and
television, Iliescu said the front ``includes all healthy forces in
our country and is supported by the army,'' which rallied with the
people against Ceausescu's security forces.
   The front includes leading dissidents Doina Cornea, Ana
Blandiana, Dumitru Mazilu, Rev. Laszlo Toekes, the protestant
pastor of Hungarian extraction whose persecution sparked the
revolt, former Foreign Minister Corneliu Manescu, ex-Washington
Ambassador Silviu Brucan and three army generals.
   Iliescu said the front urges the abandonment of the leading role
of a single party, the organization of free elections by April, and
changing the country's name to Romania, rather than the Socialist
Republic of Romania.
   Iliescu, 59, reported to be an old friend of Soviet President
Mikhail S. Gorbachev from the years when both studied in Moscow,
made no mention of the Communist Party, an indication that
Ceausescu's former fiefdom will play little if any role in future.
   ``I know how opportunistic Communists are. After Ceausescu's
ouster, tens of thousands of them will throw away the red cards,
saying they hated the party and its leaders,'' said Sandu
Poberzenic of the World Union of Free Romania.
   The Communist party has currently a membership of 3.8 million
members.
   Addressing each other Friday after Ceausescu's ouster, army
generals and other officials used the word ``domnul'' (Mr.) rather
than the word that until now has been mandatory, ``comrade.''
   ``The Romanian Communist Party had been the weakest in the whole
of Eastern Europe before the war when it numbered less than 1,000
members,'' Ratiu said. ``Its policy on international issues often
ran counter to Romanian national aspirations.''
   Still, it was not known how and what other parties will be set
up in Romania to contest the planned elections next year.
   The front's platform made no mention of the country's former
king, Michael, now 67 and living in Switzerland. It emphasized that
a committee will immediately start working out a new constitution.
   ``We must learn how to function as a democracy,'' said dissident
poet Ana Blandiana, now a Front member. ``Let's cleanse the shame
and humility in which we were forced to live in the past 24 years.''
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   EDITOR'S NOTE: Viorel Urma, now a correspondent for The
Associated Press in Vienna, worked for The AP for 14 years in
Bucharest before increasing harassment from Romanian authorities
forced him to leave late in 1987.
</TEXT>

</DOC>