<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0650EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-RacialPoster     12-28 0316</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Racial Poster,0330</SECOND>
<HEAD>Poster Showing Blacks as Roaches Will Be Recalled</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SHREVEPORT, La. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A poster map of Shreveport that depicts
blacks as roaches being sprayed by a white hand will be recalled,
the head of the local tourism bureau said.
   The poster, a cartoon map of the Shreveport area, shows roaches
in predominantly black neighborhoods being sprayed by a white hand
bearing a can of insecticide. Blacks also are shown as suspects
running from a white judge.
   In the Cedar Grove area, torn by race riots in 1988, a large
gorilla was shown saying ``Yea, we bad!''
   The poster, in the style of humorous promotional maps produced
by booster groups in many cities, was printed by Centennial
Publishing of Lafayette, which sold spots on the map to Shreveport
area businesses.
   It bears the logo of the Shreveport-Bossier Convention and
Tourist Bureau, whose chief, Preston Friedly, promised to have the
posters recalled and burned.
   Friedly apologized to citizens and the City Council Tuesday,
calling the poster ``totally repugnant and in poor taste.''
   The tourist bureau gave the publisher a letter of introduction
to local businesses, but didn't approve the design, Friedly said.
   The artist who designed the poster, former Shreveport resident
Doug Fowler, apologized earlier, explaining he intended to poke fun
at all groups in town.
   The City Council voted unanimously to denounce the poster as
racist.
   Shreveport psychiatrist Strother Dixon was one of those who
complained to the council about the poster.
   ``We have ghosts in Shreveport that are haunting us,'' Dixon
said. ``There are no black businesses represented in the
Shreveport-Bossier area. It tells me that black people and people
of color are non-existent.''
   Councilman Larry Ferdinand said the poster could deter
businesses from investing in the area.
   ``It's not going to help us with Wall Street, with our bond
rating, or to help us get McDonnell Douglas in here,'' Ferdinand
said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>