<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0178 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1229EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APonTV-`Hudson'Writer Adv02   12-29 0735</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP on TV-`Hudson' Writer, Adv 02,0746</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv02</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Tues PMs, Jan. 2</HEAD>
<HEAD>Gay Writer Identifies With `Rock Hudson' Story</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JERRY BUCK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Television Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Screenwriter Dennis Turner at first turned
down an offer to write the screen biography of Rock Hudson because
he had also led a double life.
   ``I said no a few times, but they kept coming back,'' Turner
said. `I'm glad they did. I said no because I didn't know how
seriously they wanted to treat his homosexuality. I didn't want to
do a travelogue of his life, nor did I want to do an exploitation
story because it was too close to my own life.
   ``I didn't want it to be like the `Liberace' movies where they
didn't adequately acknowledge his homosexuality. If you're going to
do a Rock Hudson movie it didn't make sense to me not to go into
all the corners.
   ``I was persuaded when ABC and the producers agreed it would be
a serious study. I knew it was going to be done and felt as a gay
man who had shared a lot of experiences that it should be done by
someone who would understand what was going on.''
   Actor Rock Hudson was one of Hollywood's most handsome and
virile screen lovers whose secret life as a homosexual became
public knowledge when he became stricken with AIDS. His death in
October 1985 helped create an awareness of the disease.
   The two-hour ``Rock Hudson'' will be telecast on ABC next
Monday. It stars Thomas Ian Griffith as Hudson; Daphne Ashbrook as
Phyllis Gates, his former wife; William R. Moses as Marc Christian,
his companion, who later successfully sued the estate; and Diane
Ladd as his mother.
   Andrew Robinson, who played Liberace in one film version, is
Henry Willson, the agent who changed Roy Fitzgerald's name to Rock
Hudson.
   NBC also has a Rock Hudson project in the works, based on ``Rock
Hudson: His Story,'' which Sara Davidson wrote in cooperation with
Hudson and his estate. The movie is currently in development with
no announced plans for production.
   Turner said he felt his own background would help him bring an
understanding to the story. ``I had been married and had
children,'' he said. ``I'm a recovering alcoholic and he was an
alcoholic who did not recover. We're both gay. We're both products
of the 1950s, although he was older, and we both suffered in that
secretive environment.
   ``You felt you were the only person on the planet who was gay.
The thought of being excluded was frightening. Rock's secrets were
eating away at him and they ultimately killed him. He would not
reveal his personal life, even to his closest friends. I think the
fact that he couldn't be truthful contributed to his drinking. The
alcohol in turn contributed to his promiscuity. He was incapable of
having a long-term relationship with anybody. I don't think he was
living the kind of life he wanted. It destroyed him.''
   Turner said he interviewed Phyllis Gates, Marc Christian and
others who knew Hudson. The screenplay is also partially based on
Gates' book, ``My Husband Rock Hudson.''
   ``The story takes him from 21 to 58,'' he said. ``It begins in
1948 when he got his first job in a movie. He had one line in
`Fighter Squadron,' which starred Edmond O'Brien and Robert Stack.
   ``His homosexuality had already manifested itself by then,''
said Turner. ``I think he and Phyllis loved each other. They had a
romantic relationship before they married. Rock wanted to be
straight, he wanted to have a family. He gave it his best shot.
   ``I want this movie to show the complexities of a man who
happened to be gay and a human being. I'm tired of the media, and I
guess the everyday population, treating gays or any minority as a
stereotype, a joke or a walking disease. I wanted to show that
keeping secrets, not being able to be honest or choosing not to be
honest, is destructive to everyone.''
   A former New York playwright, Turner previously has written such
film projects as ``Poor Little Rich Girl,'' ``The Long Hot
Summer,'' and ``Between the Darkness and the Dawn.'' He's also a
former staff writer for ``Dynasty,'' where he met Hudson when he
was on the show in the 1984-85 season.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Tues PMs, Jan. 2</NOTE>

</DOC>