<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0208 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 2236EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-BankofNewEngland 2ndLd-Writethru f0237 12-26 0676</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bank of New England, 2nd Ld-Writethru, f0237,0689</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bank Of New England Chairman To Drop CEO Post as Bank Studies Problem
Loans</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 6th graf, `The announcement ...,' to UPDATE with Bank of
New England shares the most active on the New York Stock Exchange and closing
price; ADDS 2 grafs with Tisch stake in Bank of Boston.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Walter J. Connolly Jr., chairman and chief
executive officer of the Bank of New England Corp., will resign his
CEO position when a replacement is found, the troubled bank said in
a statement Tuesday.
   Asked if this meant Connolly will stay on as chairman, Marcia
Ryan, a bank spokeswoman, said only ``the word of the release is as
it stands.'' She acknowledged ``there is an ambiguity'' about the
wording regarding Connolly's future position with the bank.
   Bank of New England also announced Tuesday it had designated the
executive committee of its board of directors and three special
board committees to examine key structural aspects of its business
and operations.
   Since the bank's troubles began, federal banking regulators have
increased scrutiny of its operations. Financial analysts had
speculated that a major reshuffling of the bank's top management
was forthcoming.
   ``It's certainly been rumored around Hartford and Boston that he
(Connolly) might step aside,'' said Tracey Stangle, an analyst with
First Albany Corp., who works out of Hartford, Conn. ``I guess for
that reason it didn't come as a surprise.''
   The announcement came after the stock market closed Tuesday.
Bank of New England was the most active issue on the New York Stock
Exchange, with more than 2.2 million shares changing hands. The
shares fell 12.5 cents to close at $7.37{.
   Stangle said Connolly has been a driving force at the bank.
``He's a very strong-willed guy that has run the institution for
the past 10 years or so,'' he said, adding it was unclear who would
take his place as chief executive.
   The bank's board appointed a committee to begin a search for
candidates to succeed Connolly, who said he would resign his post
as chief executive when a replacement is found, the company said in
a statement.
   The statement said Connolly will continue working with another
board committee on further expense reductions, financial matters
and other improvements in operations.
   In another sign of its financial difficulties, the bank on
Friday rescinded its common stock dividend of 34 cents a share for
the fourth quarter. Earlier this month, the bank said it would
boost its loan reserves above $1 billion and that it expected a
``substantial'' loss for the year.
   The new special committees are ``designed to assure that the
problems faced by the organization as a result of the unprecedented
developments in the real estate market are addressed in a timely
and comprehensive manner,'' the statement said.
   The special committees, made up of non-management board members,
would work closely with the corporation's management and the bank
regulatory agencies, the company said.
   Gordon I. Ulmer, the company's president, was named to begin an
effort to address all aspects of the real estate loan portfolio of
Bank of New England's banking subsidiaries in Massachusetts. He was
charged to report to the executive committee of the company's
board, assisted by the board's special advisor, Washington-based
Secura Group.
   Industry analysts said the move reflected the serious trouble
Bank of New England faces due to a real estate slump that affected
a number of other banks in the region.
   Bank of New England also said Tuesday it is continuing to work
with the investment firm Lazard Freres &amp; Co. to explore possible
asset sales or mergers. A special board committee has been named to
oversee this effort, the company said.
   Separately Tuesday, an investor group that includes CBS Inc.
Chief Executive Laurence M. Tisch said it holds a 6.6 percent stake
in Bank of Boston Corp., New England's largest bank.
   In a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission, the
group said it acquired the 4.7 million shares for investment
purposes only. It paid $94.5 million for them.
</TEXT>

</DOC>