<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0105 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1858EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-PanamaTown-Pool     12-23 0596</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Panama Town-Pool,0613</SECOND>
<HEAD>Panama Town Cheers Surrender of Noriega Loyalists.</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDITOR'S NOTE: Retransmitting to fix slugline, category code. The
following is a pool report filed by Steven Komarow of The Associated Press
and Kathy Lewis of the Houston Post.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LA CHORRERA, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A crowd of about 1,500 on streets and
rooftops cheered, whistled and ate snowcones Saturday as members of
Gen. Manuel Noriega's defense force surrendered to U.S. soldiers at
a former Noriega compound.
   Alone or in small groups, the men materialized out of the crowd
and laid down their weapons. The mass of people surged forward
against a ropeline signaling their approval for the surrender.
   When the weapons were given up, a cheer rang out as if a
touchdown had been made in a football game.
   Even the new prisoners had to smile at the crowd's antics.
   Lt. Col. Jeff Rock of the 7th Infantry Light Division from Fort
Ord, Calif., said the surrenders began shortly after dawn and
continued nonstop into the afternoon.
   He spoke to the first reporters to visit the town, which is at
the western most edge of the U.S. controlled sector.
   About 200 Noriega loyalists surrendered just outside of town at
about 8 a.m. and a steady stream of former Panama Defense Force
soldiers arrived at the military post throughout the day. By late
afternoon more than 400 men had surrendered, U.S. officials said.
   ``They come in twos, fours, sixes,'' said Specialist Pierre
Remy, also of Fort Ord, who was manning a guardpost. ``We had three
buses that came in.''
   Marines first entered the town Wednesday during the initial U.S.
invasion. Attack planes and armored vehicles partially destroyed
the Panamanian army compound, said Marine Chief Warrant Officer
Charles Rowe.
   The U.S. Army returned to the town Saturday morning to restore
order after several days of looting.
   Reporters touring the village saw little sign of looting on
Saturday, although one group of men was observed using a welding
torch to cut through the security gates of a store.
   Buildings along the main avenue of the town were spray painted
with anti-American graffiti, but residents said the signs predated
the U.S. invasion when, they maintained, people were forced to
feign support for Noriega.
   Rock said there was no resistance to the U.S. force when it came
back into the town Saturday and that many people cheered. When a
reporter asking onlookers how much support remains for Noreiga, the
crowd responded in unison, ``Nada, nada'' - meaning none.
   Silfredo Diaz Pinzon blamed the looting on the Noriega bands
known as the dignity battalion. A smiling woman wearing a ``Don't
worry, be happy'' t-shirt shouted in Spanish, ``Indignity''
whenever someone referred to the dignity battalion.
   She and others said the U.S. troops were the first Americans
they had ever seen in their town. Despite the celebrating, one
woman said, ``I won't relax until Noriega is captured.''
   Nariciso Miranda, a leader in the Christian Democratic Party,
said he never thought ``this great day would ever come.'' When
Noriega came to power he thought it was ``the end of Panama,'' he
said.
   Except for the minor looting and the crowd scene outside the
military compound, life appeared near normal at La Chorrera.
Taxicabs were running, U.S. soldiers were keeping order at two open
grocery stores, and a gas station was operating.
   But Rock said the U.S. soldiers might have to stay for a while.
   ``There is absolutely no city government left here whatsoever,''
said Rock, adding that talks are underway with local officials to
try to establish post-Noriega town government and police force.
</TEXT>

</DOC>