<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0163 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1357EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s w BC-LeapSecond Adv31   12-28 0460</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Leap Second, Adv 31,0472</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 31</HEAD>
<HEAD>`Leap Second' Puts Earth Clocks in Sync with Heavens</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RANDOLPH E. SCHMID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Poised on the brink of a new decade the world
will pause tonight for just a second.
   A ``leap second'' will occur at the very end of Dec. 31, 1989,
making it the longest day of the year.
   The extra second is needed to keep the world's clocks in time
with the rotation of the planet, according to government
timekeeping officials.
   The turning of the Earth has always been the time standard for
humans, who marked the passage of days by the hours of light and
darkness and years by the seasons as the planet moved around the
sun.
   But while early timekeeping sought to measure the planet's
movement, today's clocks might be called more accurate than the
Earth itself.
   ``Time measured by the rotation of the Earth is not uniform when
compared to time kept by atomic clocks,'' reports the U.S. Naval
Observatory, the government agency in charge of keeping track of
what time it is.
   As a result of this difference, atomic clocks can get out of
sync with the Earth and have to be adjusted. Since it's the atomic
clocks that are used to set all other clocks, a leap second has to
be added or skipped from time to time to make up the difference.
   Fifteen leap seconds have been added to human time since an
international time agreement was signed in 1972, when a full 10
seconds had to be added to the atomic clocks to get them together
with the Earth. This will be the first leap second in two years.
   The leap second will occur officially at 23 hours, 59 minutes
and 60 seconds, Coordinated Universal Time, when a one-second pause
will occur before the arrival of zero hours on New Years Day.
   Coordinated Universal Time, popularly known as Greenwich Mean
Time, is the time experienced in London, England, and serves as a
standard reference for the world's timekeepers.
   In the United States, the actual adjustment will be made one
second before 7 p.m. EST.
   Atomic clocks are extremely accurate because they measure time
based on the frequency of regular events in atoms of cesium,
hydrogen, rubidium or mercury.
   The National Institute of Standards and Technology, formerly
called the National Bureau of Standards, is the government agency
in charge of timekeeping.
   Over the years the rotation of the Earth has tended to slow down
somewhat, and thus all 15 leap seconds needed so far have had to be
added to atomic clocks. If the Earth were to speed up, leap seconds
would have to be subtracted.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, Dec. 31</NOTE>

</DOC>