<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0225 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1554EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-ResponsibleDrinking     12-19 0467</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Responsible Drinking,0485</SECOND>
<HEAD>Miller Launches $2 Million `Think When You Drink' Campaign</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOYA L. WESLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MILWAUKEE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Miller Brewing Co. will add a new medium this
week to its effort to teach consumers to drink responsibly when the
beermaker begins a $2 million television advertising campaign for
the holidays.
   The company has used the slogan ``Think When You Drink'' as a
tag line in its print advertisements and in taverns and liquor
stores, but this year's campaign will be the first time Miller has
used the slogan in a television campaign, spokeswoman Elizabeth
Conlisk said.
   ``We looked for a long time for the right tone and the right
message,'' Ms. Conlisk said. ``When we did it, we wanted to do it
right.''
   The television commercials were to start Thursday and run
through Dec. 31 and will have a ``warm and cozy feeling to them,''
Ms. Conlisk said.
   Rather than focusing on the problems irresponsible drinking can
cause, the commercials feature traditional American taverns.
   ``Taverns are places where people have gone for years to have
and beer and be with their friends,'' Ms. Conlisk said. ``These
commercials make people feel good about that.''
   The commercials include the message:
   ``The next time it's Miller Time for you, we'd like to ask you
to do one very simple thing. Be responsible. Think when you drink.''
   Milwaukee-based Miller, the No. 2. U.S. brewer, has sponsored
educational programs since 1984, based on what Ms. Conlisk called
the company's belief that education is the way to reduce alcohol
abuse.
   In the past, Miller has been criticized by anti-drinking
activists who claim the brewer has taken an inconsistent and
irresponsible approach toward selling its product.
   In March, for example, Miller was rebuked for running
advertisements in college newspapers' advertising supplements
intending to capitalize on the rollicking atmosphere of spring
vacation. Miller later withdrew and apologized for the ads, which
featured tips for men on how to `scam babes'' at the beach.
   In June, then-U.S. Surgeon General C. Everett Koop issued a set
of proposals that would ban alcohol advertisements on college
campuses and outlaw ads using celebrities who appeal to youths.
   Beer industry officials complained Koop's effort amounted to an
anti-alcohol campaign. They said while Koop's proposal went too
far, the industry as a whole was moving toward empashizing more
responsible drinking in an effort to discourage drunken driving.
   On New Year's Eve, Miller and its distributors will sponsor free
bus and taxi rides and designated-driver programs in many U.S.
cities to promote responsible drinking and safe driving, Ms.
Conlisk said.
   ``This is really a concerted effort nationwide to reinforce the
moderation theme,'' she said.
   Anheuser-Busch of St. Louis, Miller's top competitor, will use
the Budweiser Clydesdales in the brewers' long-running ``Know When
to Say When'' advertising campaign.
</TEXT>

</DOC>