<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0349EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-Reconstruct Bjt   12-22 1204</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Reconstruct, Bjt,1253</SECOND>
<HEAD>After Days Of Rising Tension, The Sound of Planes</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   This story was reconstructed from accounts by
U.S. and Panamanian officials, interviews with Panamanian citizens
and reporting by Associated Press correspondents in Panama.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By SUSANA HAYWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The first sign of trouble came with the planes _ giant C-141 and
C-5 jet transports landing every ten minutes at Howard Air Force
Base, only four miles west of Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega's Panama
City headquarters.
   Hours later, just after midnight, mortar blasts and machine-gun
fire lit the sky. The dark shapes of helicopters roared through the
moonlit night, their running lights out.
   Operation Just Cause was under way. President Bush was striking
for Noriega, the accused drug trafficker who had controlled Panama
and thumbed his nose at American power for years.
   Thousands of soldiers, Marines, sailors and pilots were on the
move by 12:30 a.m. Wednesday. Paratroopers landed at Omar Torrijos
International Airport to secure it for landing.
   In a blaze of gunfire, American soldiers battled Panamanian
forces and surrounded Noriega's Defense Forces headquarters. By 2
a.m., flames a hundred feet high rose from the building.
   ``We're kicking ass tonight,'' boasted one U.S. soldier.
   But the target, Noriega, disappeared into the night. Noriega
bodyguard Lt. Asuncion Gaitan said by radio that the dictator had
been warned.
   Shortly after the fighting broke out, opposition leader
Guillermo Endara was sworn in as president and asked Panamanian
forces to surrender.
   Noriega loyalists, however, did not. And the massive U.S.
military operation turned bloody in the metropolis of 1 million.
   With garrisons destroyed or under siege, many Panamanian
officers in Noriega's 15,000-strong Defense Forces joined
paramilitary groups and the so-called Dignity Battalions of armed
citizens.
   A media war began.
   U.S.-controlled television urged surrender and said ``The United
States has no territorial ambitions in Panama,'' an unintentional
reminder that until a decade ago Washington controlled a
10-mile-wide zone through Panama's center.
   On a pro-Noriega radio network, radio announcers called for
neighborhood resistance and guerrilla war.
   The Panama Canal, the root of U.S.-Panama conflict by its very
existence, closed at 1 a.m. even though there were ships in the
waterway. Under 1977 treaties, the United States cedes control of
the canal by century's end.
   Frightened residents fled combat zones around the neighborhoods
of Chorillo and Old Panama, the colonial quarter of the city where
a Panamanian cavalry unit was based. In the neighborhood of San
Miguelito to the northeast, U.S. jets strafed a Defense Forces
barracks.
   Fighting was also reported at the Panamanian bases of Fort
Cimarron, 20 miles east of the capital; Rio Hato, 80 miles
southwest, and David, 240 miles to the west, where U.S. troops hit
the airport.
   Panamanian forces also attacked the U.S. Embassy and caused
light damage before it was secured by U.S. forces at around 4:30
a.m.
   During the morning armed Panamanians raided the luxury Marriott
Hotel and temporarily held 12 people, including eight Americans.
Elsewhere in Panama, Noriega supporters targeted U.S. citizens for
capture.
   Although scattered combat continued through the day, by 4 a.m.
Wednesday the heaviest fighting was over.
   At dawn, a pall of smoke lay over the city as dazed civilians
sought shelter. Santo Tomas Hospital, near the Defense Forces
headquarters, counted 80 bodies in its morgue and about 1,000
injured, hundreds of them civilians.
   Red Cross ambulances raced to pick up bodies rotting in
99-degree heat.
   The Pentagon said U.S. troops took 1,500 prisoners, most from
the Defense Force.
   In a somber speech on national television at 7 a.m. Wednesday,
President Bush announced that American servicemen had been killed.
The U.S. death toll began a climb into double figures.
   Bush said he ordered the invasion to protect the lives of 35,000
Americans in Panama in light of Noriega's announcement five days
earlier that Panama was in a ``state of war'' with the United
States.
   Bush said the assault was aimed at capturing Noriega, who had
just been named Panama's chief executive, to bring him to trial in
the United States on charges of cocaine trafficking.
   It was the first U.S. attack against a government since the 1986
air raid on Libya and the first U.S. invasion of a country since
the Grenada intervention in 1983.
   Latin American allies condemned the action and called for
withdrawal. The Soviet Union called it ``gunboat diplomacy.''
   Sources in Washington later said Bush decided on Sunday to mount
the assault, one day after a U.S. Marine lieutenant was killed at a
Panamanian Defense Forces checkpoint and a U.S. Navy couple was
held, beaten and the woman threatened sexually.
   Panama was tense after the killing of the Marine, with American
troops on maximum alert and Panamanian news media trying to whip up
a frenzy of anti-American sentiment, screaming that Bush was
preparing an invasion.
   On Monday, a U.S. Army officer wounded a Panamanian policeman
because he thought the man was going to draw a weapon.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III claimed the invasion came
after the administration received unconfirmed reports Noriega
planned to attack a U.S. residential neighborhood.
   On Wednesday, the Bush administration offered a $1 million
reward for information on Noriega's whereabouts.
   From an undisclosed location that night, the elusive Noriega
spoke briefly over national radio and vowed to fight. ``We're in
trench warfare now and we will maintain the resistance,'' he said.
   Pro-Noriega radio stations were able to keep broadcasting all
day, but finally were shut off the air shortly after Noriega made a
brief statement.
   On Thursday, the U.S. troops were in control of Panama's
strategic points but scattered fighting took place in the capital.
Despite a massive manhunt, Noriega remained at large.
   A massive wave of looting that began Wednesday spread throughout
the city Thursday. Every kind of business from bakeries to car
dealers was picked clean by swarming hordes of Panamanians.
Entrepreneurs stripped warehouses and set up bargain street stalls
to sell the merchandise.
   Endara, the candidate elected in a May 7 election nullified by
Noriega, left his shelter on a U.S. base and spoke at the National
Assembly, announcing a curfew to try to control looting.
   In the absence of police, who as members of the Defense Forces
were either in combat or vanished, his order had little effect.
   U.S. troops rescued 29 Americans and 35 foreign nationals
Wednesday night at the Marriott Hotel, but other U.S. citizens were
still missing Thursday and three photographers were shot, one of
them dead, by American troops in the hotel parking lot.
   The 51-mile Panama Canal opened Thursday, but only during
daylight hours. Not enough workers could get in to keep the canal
open at night, a spokesman said.
   The White House said the occupation could last for a
considerable time but Defense Secretary Dick Cheney said some
troops might return by Christmas. Other officials worried the
United States had impulsively entered an open-ended commitment that
might end in guerrilla war.
   Bush said Thursday the military mission ``is not over, but
pretty well wrapped up.''
   He vowed to continue the search for Noriega, who had commanded
the Defense Forces since 1983 and earned a reputation as a miracle
man by defying U.S. economic sanctions and frustrating two coup
attempts.
</TEXT>

</DOC>