<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0636EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Panama-USHispanics     12-21 0614</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-US Hispanics,0634</SECOND>
<HEAD>Central American Natives in U.S. Mixed in Reaction to Invasion</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Central American natives living in the United
States reacted to the U.S. military invasion of Panama with
feelings from ecstatic relief to condemnation.
   About 200 members of Miami's Panamanian exile community
celebrated the U.S. action to oust Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega
after a prayer vigil in the city's Coconut Grove section.
   ``Viva Bush, he brought down Noriega, he brought down the rat,''
they chanted, unfurling a 15-foot Panamanian flag.
   ``I'm here to thank the Lord for the American invasion,'' said
one Panamanian at the gathering, Jeanne Friend. ``Because that's
what I really wanted _ for the Americans to come in and take hold
of Noriega.''
   But in Los Angeles, a native of El Salvador denounced the
invasion.
   ``The time has long passed when the United States had to be the
police force for South America,'' said Mario Rivas, spokesman for
Our Lady Queen of Angels church. ``My reaction is: United States,
get out of Panama. Let Panamanians work the situation out for
themselves.''
   Rivas, a Salvadoran refugee who came to the United States eight
years ago, said several Panamanian refugees told him they were
outraged by the attack.
   ``I hope the invasion fails because it's imperial thirst to
conquer foreign lands,'' Rivas said. ``That's not democracy. Let's
practice democratic ways and means.''
   In Miami, Ivan Chacon, who was beaten by Noriega supporters in
attacks on opposition candidates after Panama's elections in May,
had a different view. He said U.S. intervention was the only way to
bring democracy to his homeland.
   ``The people couldn't bring (Noriega) down waving little white
handkerchiefs,'' Chacon said.
   Aurelio Barria, who last year headed the anti-Noriega opposition
until he was forced into exile in Miami, said Panamanians would
blame Noriega for the bloodshed, not the United States.
   ``It's a mixed feeling _ we have been fighting so long through
non-violent ways to get Noriega out,'' Barria said. ``But he just
became a psychopath _ he went a few steps beyond the limit.''
   ``We aren't happy that our country has been invaded,'' said
Roberto Dominguez, the former Panamanian counsul in Miami. ``But it
is an action to get rid of someone who has held our country
hostage.''
   At the rally, Susana Toral wept with joy.
   ``I cry for not being there,'' she said, ``I left Panama because
I was afraid, but I don't want to live here. I want to return to my
Panama.''
   Luis Endara, a cousin of Panama's new President Guillermo
Endara, said the longing to return home remains great among the
estimated 5,000 to 7,000 members of Miami's Panamanian community.
   ``We will probably see for the first time an emigration back to
a country that has been liberated,'' Endara said.
   Adela Bonilla de Giroldi, widow of Maj. Moises Giroldi, the
leader of a failed Panamanian military coup against Noriega on Oct.
3, said her feelings were mixed. Her husband was killed after
troops loyal to the general rallied. Some accounts said Noriega
shot Giroldi.
   ``I am glad that my husband is dead,'' Mrs. Giroldi said,
``because if he had been there today, I am sure he would have died
defending his barracks.''
   The U.S. intervention ``is not the best way, but it had to be
done,'' she said.
   In Texas, the nation's largest Hispanic rights organization came
out strongly in favor of the U.S. military strike.
   ``We stand squarely behind our commander in chief on this
issue,'' said Jose Garcia De Lara, president of the San
Antonio-based League of United Latin American Citizens. ``What
we're doing here is getting rid of a hooligan that is causing great
turmoil in our hemisphere.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>