<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0228 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0804EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-KrogerRefinancing     12-21 0337</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Kroger Refinancing,0348</SECOND>
<HEAD>Grocery Chain Refinances Debt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CINCINNATI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Kroger Co. says it has obtained new loans and
a rotating credit line to refinance more than $2 billion in debt
from a corporate restructuring in 1988.
   New terms with lenders led by Citibank, Chemical Bank and First
National Bank of Chicago coincide with a mortgage refinancing plan
that let the supermarket chain reduce the cost of some debt, the
company said Wednesday.
   Under the new terms, Kroger finananced $2.05 billion to include
a $1.2 billion loan and an $850 million revolving line of credit
for working capital and general corporate purposes.
   The interest rate on the credit line will decline by about
three-fourths of a percent, with additional rate reductions based
on improvement in the ratio of cash flow to cash interest expenses,
Kroger said.
   ``Our lending banks recognize that in order for Kroger to remain
a strong, viable company, it must have the ability to respond to
constantly changing competitive conditions,'' Kroger Chairman Lyle
Everingham said.
   ``By fixing amortization payments at a lower level, the new
terms provide us the flexibility to maintain state-of-the-art
retail stores and to remain competitive in all our markets,''
Everingham said.
   Kroger said it expects cash interest in 1990 to be about $460
million, and total interest expenses to reach $590 million. That
compares with $510 million cash interest and $637 million in total
interest expenses previously estimated.
   Kroger borrowed $3.6 billion in October 1988 for a corporate
restructuring and a special dividend after two unsuccessful
takeover attempts against the company. Kroger said strong sales of
some assets and proceeds from refinancing have enabled it to reduce
its debt faster than expected, and to lengthen the maturities on
remaining debt.
   ``The new terms are a major step forward in reducing the cost of
Kroger's debt and giving the company more operating latitude,''
Kroger President Joseph Pichler said.
   But he said the $4.7 billion in debt remaining on the company's
books will mean the company has to maintain operating performance.
</TEXT>

</DOC>