<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0177 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2053EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Brazil 3rdLd-Writethru a0681 12-18 0853</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0681,0875</SECOND>
<HEAD>Conservative Presidential Candidate Winning in Brazil</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 17 grafs to UPDATE official tally; comment from leftist's
camp; DELETES outdated material; pickup graf 19 pvs `De Silva...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto staffing</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TODD LEWAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRASILIA, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vote counts and projections Monday
indicated free-market advocate Fernando Collor de Mello, a
conservative, had defeated his socialist opponent in Brazil's first
direct presidential election in 29 years.
   In this capital city, Collor de Mello supporters celebrated in
the streets, beating drums and waving party flags. The dapper
candidate appeared briefly for photographers outside his Brasilia
mansion, smiling and making a ``V'' for victory sign but offering
no comment.
   However, officials of leftist Luis Inacio Lula da Silva's party
said it was too early for their candidate to concede defeat.
   ``We won't give up until the last vote is counted,'' said
Workers Party President Luiz Gushinken. ``The important thing are
the Court's official figures.''
   The Supreme Electoral Court said leftist Luis Inacio Lula da
Silva was leading Collor de Mello by less than 1 percent in a tally
based on 60 percent of the votes. The official tally was slow
because state returns were being double-checked to avoid error.
   But Irineu Tamanini, spokesman for the Electoral Court, said
Collor de Mello would overtake da Silva by late Monday as returns
came in from the candidate's strongholds in remote central and
northern regions, where ballot boxes were taken to vote-counting
centers by canoe and mule.
   The final result will be announced by Wednesday, Tamanini said.
   The winner is to succeed President Jose Sarney on March 15 and
serve five years, but pressure is growing for Sarney to resign
earlier. Two Cabinet members said Sunday said the president-elect
should take office soon because of severe economic problems.
   In a first round of voting Nov. 15, Collor de Mello and da Silva
got the most votes of 21 candidates, but neither won a majority.
   Collor de Mello, 40, formed the National Reconstruction Party
less than a year ago. He is a proponent of free markets, cleaning
up corruption in government and paying the $110 billion foreign
debt _ largest in the developing world _ but on less burdensome
terms.
   The business, military and media establishments united behind
Collor de Mello, who comes from a wealthy family with a long
political tradition.
   Da Silva, 44, urged sweeping land reform, redistribution of
income and immediate suspension of payments on the foreign debt.
   Near the northeastern city of Santa Barbara, five cars carrying
people back from voting dropped into a 30-foot-deep crater left in
a road by heavy rains, said civil defense official Gloria Pires da
Silva. She said 15 people were killed in Sunday's accident.
   Globo TV, the nation's largest television network, projected
Collor de Mello as the winner and had him ahead by 3 million votes,
or 5.1 percent, in an unofficial tally based on 86.8 percent of
returns.
   Network owner Roberto Marinho supported Collor de Mello, but
Globo TV said all its results were compiled from returns announced
by state election officials.
   Four private polling institutes said Monday afternoon Collor de
Mello would be the winner by 3.5 to 4.5 million votes, a 4 to 6
percent margin.
   ``There is no doubt that Collor de Mello is the next president
of Brazil,'' said Carlos Matheus, director of the Gallup polling
institute.
   Da Silva _ known as Lula, the nickname he has made part of his
legal name _ led early in the official count on the basis of
returns from two strongholds, the southern cities of Porto Alegre
and Rio de Janeiro.
   Collor de Mello rebounded with a strong showing in Sao Paulo,
Brazil's wealthiest and most populous state, and in the
southeastern industrial and farming state of Minas Gerais.
   Roberto Rosas of the Electoral Court said the Electoral Court
was investigating charges by the Workers Party, da Silva's
organization, that voters could not get to polling stations in
Bahia and Ceara states, both da Silva country, because private bus
companies took their vehicles off the street.
   ``If the difference between the candidates is slight, the Court
will set a third election date for municipalities that had trouble
voting,'' Rosas told The Associated Press.
   News of Collor de Mello's lead stabilized financial markets
Monday and caused a sharp decline of the dollar's value on the
illegal, but tolerated, black market. The price of a dollar was 17
new cruzados Monday, down from 22 at the close of business Friday.
   Brazil was ruled by the military in 1964-85 and Sunday's
election was hailed as a significant step toward full restoration
of democracy.
   On the minds of the 82 million registered voters in this nation
of 150 million people were annual inflation of 1,500 percent,
declining real wages, official corruption and the largest foreign
debt in the Third World.
   The last Brazilian president chosen directly by the people was
Janio Quadros. He resigned in 1961, after seven months in office,
and the military overthrew his vice president and successor, Joao
Goulart, in 1964.
   Sarney was chosen by an electoral college in 1985.
</TEXT>

</DOC>