<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0129 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1416EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-Panama-Congress 1stLd-Writethru a0432 12-22 0578</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Congress, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0432,550</SECOND>
<HEAD>PDF Elements Escaped Because of Element of Surprise Incomplete</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: New throughout with report from briefing</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAWRENCE L. KNUTSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Failure of U.S. troops to achieve complete
surprise in their attack in Panama resulted in the disappearance of
substantial forces loyal to ousted leader Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noriega, Sen. Sam Nunn, D-Ga., said today.
   Reporting on a three-hour briefing by Pentagon officials, Nunn
and Sen. John Warner, R-Va., said substantial amount of cocaine and
cash were seized in Noriega's personal headquarters in Panama City.
Noriega faces drug-trafficking charges in the United States.
   Nunn and Warner, the chairman and ranking Republican member,
respectively, of the Senate Armed Services Committee, noted that
Noriega last year had been given the opportunity to leave Panama
and go to a country from which he could not be extradited to the
United States.
   ``He was given the opportunity to shove off and go to another
nation and spend his dollars and not come back,'' Warner said.
   Warner said Noriega's refusal of the offer to leave the country
was evidence of irrationality.
   ``His psychology, his neurotic tendencies were beginning to
overcome him and destabilize him to the extent that ... he pushed
those options aside, hunkered down and determined to cross that
line which he had adhered to in the past, of not seeking Americans
as targets of opportunity,'' Warner said.
   The diplomatic initiative came not just from the United States,
but from other countries as well, Warner said.
   Because of that downturn and Noriega's increased
``irrationality'' and attacks against Americans, President Bush
``had every reason to believe violence was going to escalate if he
did not act,'' Nunn said.
   He said an exhaustive search is continuing, but ``we did not
have Noriega pegged down and he is still at large.''
   Nunn said that while there was some surprise in the U.S. attacks
that began at 1 a.m. Wednesday, it was not complete and that at
least two companies of Panamanian troops are entirely unaccounted
for.
   He said some troops and members of Noriega's paramilitary force
known as the Dignity Battalions have dispersed into the
countryside, where he said ``thuggery and violence'' are going on.
He described the forces as ``armed and certainly very dangerous.''
   Nunn said it is obvious that American military police will have
to be used in Panama to stop looting and restore order. ``If that
kind of chaos and looting goes on, I think Americans will be looked
at by the Panamanian people with increased distaste,'' he said.
   Nunn said the administration intends to speed economic aid to
Panama, adding that it is important ``that we get food in there
very quickly.''
   Army Lt. Gen. Tom Kelly, director of operations for the Joint
Chiefs of staff, and other defense officials conducted the
congressional briefing.
   Nunn said the briefing, which lasted more than three hours,
reinforced his earlier view that Bush was fully justified in
ordering the invasion. He cited Noriega's ``increasing
irrationality'' and said more American lives might have been lost
had Bush not acted.
   Nunn was critical, however, of the Reagan administration's
indictment of Noriega on drug charges last year, saying he thought
the move was ill-considered and had led to unnecessary trouble.
   ``Looking at lessons learned, when the Justice Department
indicts someone, they ought to know what they are going to do
next,'' Nunn said. ``I hope the Justice Department will learn a
lesson out of this.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>