<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0549EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-S&amp;LContempt     12-23 0387</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-S&amp;L Contempt,0396</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ex-Owners Convicted of Violating Spending Ban</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BOB EGELKO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal court ruling could mean 6{ more
years in prison for two brothers found guilty of bank fraud in the
collapse of their Northern California savings and loan, a
prosecutor said.
   The ruling by U.S. District Judge Robert Peckham, made public
Friday, found Leif and Jay Soderling guilty of contempt of court
and violating their probation for indulging in a $500,000 spending
spree during a court-ordered freeze on their assets.
   The ruling should send Leif and Jay Soderling of Windsor, north
of San Francisco, back to prison for 6{ years, said prosecutor
Ronald Smetana, because of the violation of probation conditions in
their original sentence.
   The Soderlings' lawyer, Richard Freeman, could not be reached
Friday.
   In 1987, the brothers pleaded guilty to bank fraud and were
sentenced to seven years in prison. But most of the sentence was
suspended and they spent about nine months in prison before their
release last year.
   Smetana said the Soderlings owe about $4.8 million out of $6.7
million in restitution required by their sentence, and are being
sued by federal bank regulators for additional amounts lost in the
failure of their Golden Pacific Savings and Loan in 1985.
   Peckham said the Soderlings violated his order requiring them to
cooperate with the Federal Deposit Insurance Corp. in paying
restitution, and prohibiting them from spending any of their assets
without court approval, except for $2,500 per family in living
expenses.
   The judge said family trust funds created by the brothers spent
$500,000 between September and December 1988, shortly after the
order was issued, without seeking court approval or notification.
   The money was used, among other things, to buy cars, computers,
cellular phones and a horse trailer, Peckham said.
   The brothers argued that the money was spent by their wives and
that the trust funds were immune from restitution. Jay Soderling's
wife, Evelyn, and Leif's wife, Sydney, are awaiting trial
separately for contempt of court.
   Rejecting the Soderlings' claim that they were not given notice
of the terms of their probation, Peckham said they appeared to
believe ``they can continue to push the line of legality in new and
creative ways, and the burden is on the government to anticipate
every possible maneuver.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>