<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0342EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-KeatingLawsuit     12-30 0351</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Keating Lawsuit,0361</SECOND>
<HEAD>Keating Brother Dismissed As Defendant In $1.1 Billion Lawsuit</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM F. RAWSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Federal lawyers have dismissed William J. Keating
as a defendant in a $1.1 billion lawsuit stemming from the failure
of a savings and loan run by his brother, millionaire Charles H.
Keating Jr.
   The lawsuit accused Charles Keating, several family members, and
other senior executives of his American Continental Corp. of
devising a scheme to loot money from Lincoln Savings and Loan
Association of Irving, Calif., which American Continental owned.
   Federal regulators seized the thrift April 14, one day after
American Continental sought protection from its creditors under
federal bankruptcy law. The thrift's failure is expected to cost
taxpayers more than $2 billion.
   The Resolution Trust Corp., the federal agency created to clean
up the savings and loan industry, filed the lawsuit under civil
fraud and racketeering statutes in U.S. District Court in September.
   William Keating, chief executive officer of the Detroit
Newspaper Agency and chairman of the board of The Associated Press,
wasn't accused of fraud and racketeering but was named in three of
15 counts and was accused of negligence and breach of fiduciary
duty.
   William Keating served for five months in 1986 on American
Continental's board of directors, said his lawyer, Chester T. Kamin
of Chicago.
   Resolution Trust Corp. lawyers filed notice Friday in federal
court that William Keating had been dismissed, without prejudice,
as a defendant in the case.
   Kamin said that because the dismissal is ``without prejudice,''
William Keating theoretically could be reinstated as a defendant in
the case. But it is unlikely that he would have been dismissed if
the government had any intention of including him in the
litigation, Kamin said.
   Michael C. Manning, a Phoenix lawyer who has represented the
Resolution Trust Corporation in the case, wasn't available for
comment Friday. His secretary said he was on vacation.
   P. John Owen, a Kansas City lawyer who signed the notice of
dismissal on behalf of the Resolution Trust Corporation, was out of
his office and unavailable until Tuesday, his secretary said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>