<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0247 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1037EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APonTV-`Home     12-20 0802</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP on TV-`Home,' Adv 21,0823</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv21</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Thursday PMs, Dec. 21</HEAD>
<HEAD>Producer Applies Personal Life to ABC's `Home'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JERRY BUCK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Television Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When producer Woody Fraser created ABC's
``Home'' show two years ago to help people live their lives he
didn't know it was going to get so personal.
   ``What the show is really about is to give people ideas and help
them make decisions,'' said Fraser.
   The morning show offers practical suggestions on health,
cooking, home buying and remodeling, automobiles and arts. It has a
number of regular experts, including one who reviews movies and
videos from the standpoint of families with small children.
``Home'' marks its 500th show on Thursday and celebrates its second
anniversary on Jan. 18.
   But for Fraser, who established ABC's ``Good Morning America,''
``The Mike Douglas Show,'' ``That's Incredible'' and many other
shows, it got very personal seven months ago.
   Fraser, 55, suffered a heart attack and underwent bypass
surgery. Since then, he's lost 47 pounds by changing his eating
habits and exercising.
   ``I cut out fats and dairy products from my diet and took up
exercise,'' he said. ``I went from being a sedentary individual to
a person who's active again. I get more sleep. I do yoga. I found
that doctors don't know anything about diet. I read all the books
that people sent me when I had my heart attack. I picked out the
things that worked for me.''
   He put his personal experiences on the air and made a rare
appearance as a guest. Last July, after he returned to work, he
devoted a week to a series called ``Heart and Soul.'' The show was
devoted to a study that showed yoga, meditation and positive
affirmation are helpful in preventing and recovering from heart
attacks.
   ``Home'' also undergoes a change next Tuesday. Gary Collins
takes over as host, replacing Robb Weller. Collins has been host of
the Miss America Pageant for the past five years and was the
Emmy-winning host of ``Hour Magazine.''
   Fraser said he's wanted to do ``Home'' ever since he founded
``Good Morning America'' in 1975.
   ``I wanted a show that would go later in the morning,'' he said.
``Its purpose is to give women information that they can apply to
their lives. The key word here is information. I said to ABC, `Give
me 60 minutes and I'll give you 30 ideas you've never heard of.'
It's a hard show to promote because we offer help for the home.
   ``Recently in the TV listings `Oprah' had a show about women who
had shot their husbands and still loved them. `Geraldo' had satanic
babies. `Donahue' had cross-dressing. And we had a show about
barbecuing.
   ``We don't have a great come on. But the people who watch our
show come back. That's why Gary Collins is taking over. I want to
add his marquee value to the show. I think he'll bring us viewers.''
   Of all network shows on daytime television, ``Home'' has the
largest audience among women 18-34, Fraser said. ``Home'' also puts
out a newsletter that goes to two million subscribers.
   A show on poisons in the home got 44,000 responses to a 900
number. For $2 viewers got a newsletter, information on poisons and
$6 in coupons. The sponsor had expected only about 5,000 responses.
   Since it began, the show has expanded to an hour from 30 minutes
and has gone to live telecast instead of tape. The live telecast
allows the show to have satellite remotes and to take instant polls.
   ``Home'' has also taken its name to heart and has purchased
three houses and is about to purchase a fourth.
   ``We take the viewer through every step of the purchase and
financing,'' said Fraser. ``Then we go in and remodel and
redecorate the house. We started with a house that cost about
$160,000. Then we sold it and bought a house for $240,000. Each
time we apply the profit to buying a more expensive house. The last
house we bought for $300,000 but we haven't been able to sell it
because of the poor real estate market.
   ``The last house is a duplex. People had asked us to do
something on apartments. Each side of the house is like an
apartment, so we were able to show people things to do with smaller
space.''
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Elsewhere in television:
   CHILDREN'S SHOW _ Hanna-Barbera is preparing a new series for
morning children's television called ``Wake, Rattle &amp; Roll.'' The
half-hour show, set for next fall, will combine animation, live
action and robotic action. R.J. Williams will play a teen-ager
named Sam, whose bedroom is filled with futuristic toys and
innovative gadgets. Sam will have a robotic sidekick called Rewind.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Thurs PMs, Dec. 21</NOTE>

</DOC>