<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0161 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1845EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-Bush-Text     12-18 0554</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Bush-Text,4th Add, a0650-a0657-a0666-a0678,650</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHN: to it.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Q: Could I ask you about the drug summit?
   BUSH: Yes.
   Q: On domestic trips, it's frequently not announced that you're
going to go some place until about two or three days ahead of time
because of security concerns. But here it is, two months before
this drug summit in Colombia, where there's been a lot of violence,
and the trip has already been announced. Doesn't that sort of
invite some type of attack or assassination attempt by these drug
lords?
   BUSH: I don't think so. And I think that here we're dealing with
an international meeting that's been discussed for a long time.
It's not as if it were just something that's a spur-of-the-moment
meeting. We've talked about an Andean summit for a long, long time.
And the President of Colombia was anxious to go forward with the
announcement and let it be known that we were going to have the
summit. So I think it's different than just kind of a drop-in on
some event here in the United States. I mean, we announced the
summit with the Soviet Union, you know, months ahead of time. We
got _ the G-7 meeting was set a long, long time ago. So I'd say
this is more in keeping with how you handle normal international
conferences.
   Q: _ is reporting that there has been a specific threat against
you. It said about $30 million.
   BUSH: I wish they'd bring the source in so we could take a look
at it. There's nothing to it. I really think that's _ I'd better
read it before I wax indignant.
   Q: Will you feel responsible if anyone _
   BUSH: Tell me what it said.
   Q: It said that some drug lords have said that they are ready to
spend $30 million to have you assassinated.
   BUSH: Were there any quotes which drug lord or anything about it?
   Q: It says that there are rumors in Washington, I think _
   BUSH: That's what I saw, something about rumors. Well, I just
wonder if I was missing something. I've got total confidence in our
security people. I am not going to do anything reckless; you know
me. (Laughter.) And I am going to be as supportive as I can of
President Barco. And we've got outstanding Secret Service people.
And so let me take this opportunity to reassure the American people
that we will not unduly risk anyone's life here, and that I know
that I feel confident that the security provisions in Cartagena
will guarantee the safety of the president of the United States.
   Q: Mr. President, isn't the nature of the meeting, though, doing
it on a military base, as I understand it, for about three hours so
we can get out of town quickly, in itself an implicit admission?
   BUSH: Listen, nobody has to go but me. I'm the only one who's
invited. So where do you get this ``we'' stuff, Tonto? (Laughter.)
   Q: Yes, well, then you're only going to be there for three
hours, and _ isn't that an implicit admission that there is a
serious concern about security there and _
   BUSH: How long were we in St. Martin's? That was an important
meeting.
   Q: We even wondered why that was so short. (Laughter.)
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>