<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0150 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1607EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Panama-US-Police 1stLd-Writethru a0729 12-22 0560</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-US-Police, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0729,560</SECOND>
<HEAD>Army MPs, Working With Panamanians, Could Be in for Long Stay</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: CORRECTS 11th graf, American MPs, to insert dropped word ``unlike''
in quote</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   With Panama in chaos, U.S. officials said
Friday that military police trained to restore and enforce law and
order will play a large role in the country, possibly staying as
long as a year.
   Gen. Maxwell Thurman, head of the U.S. Southern Command, told
reporters at a new conference in Panama that a top U.S. priority
was to ``raise the (Panamanian) police force and get it back in
operation.''
   In Washington, Gen. Tom Kelly, director of operations for the
Joint Chiefs of Staff, stressed the importance of the military
police.
   ``The role we will play is assisting the Panamanians ... in
maintaining order and recapturing and controlling of their
institutions like the police,'' he said.
   ``We've got to re-establish law and order throughout Panama
City,'' said Lt. Col. Bill Bennett, a top military planner.
   Military experts said the military police might work with
Panamanian Defense Forces loyal to new President Guillermo Endara,
training them and incorporating them on patrols.
   U.S. officials spoke while mobs, some devoted to ousted Gen.
Manuel Noriega, roamed Panama City, ``breaking windows, entering
private homes, looting at will,'' according to Jan Edmonson, the
U.S. Embassy spokesman in Panama City.
   By Friday _ the third day of the U.S. intervention _ the
military police numbered 3,000, Bennett said. Some 1,500
reinforcements from Fort Bragg, N.C., were brought in to help. All
told, U.S. troops number about 24,000.
   U.S. military officials refused to say how long they would keep
combat troops in Panama, but Rep. Les Aspin, D-Wis., chairman of
the House Armed Services Committee, predicted the military police
might be in for a long haul.
   ``I would not be surprised to see them there on Christmas Eve a
year from now,'' he said.
   Military police _ or MPs _ have a number of specific tasks,
including security and law enforcement at U.S. bases, the support
of combat forces and protection of prisoners of war. In Panama,
some 1,400 pro-Noriega loyalists are being held prisoner, Thurman
said.
   American MPs ``are not too much unlike a civilian police
force,'' said Michael Abrams, a spokesman at Fort McClellan near
Anniston, Ala., home of the U.S. Army Military Police School.
   MPs were recently in the headlines when they were sent to the
Virgin Islands to restore calm after Hurricane Hugo. But Abrams
said the situation in the Virgin Islands differed substantially
from that in Panama.
   In the islands, MPs worked in concert with local law enforcement
officers, letting the civil authorities play the lead role in
making arrests and controlling disorderly conduct.
   But in Panama, ``it seems like the whole country has been turned
upside down,'' he said. ``I haven't the faintest idea how they are
operate.''
   Richard Armitage, a former Defense Department official,
suggested the new government in Panama temporarily might empower
the MPs with authority to make arrests and handle other problems.
   MPs, often the most visible servicemen because of their public
function, are trained to handle scores of tasks from criminal
investigations to traffic. On bases, they commonly patrol housing
areas, set up speed traps and make arrests.
   They also protect convoys, set up perimeter security and quell
disturbances.
</TEXT>

</DOC>