<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0281 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2252EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s f BC-Nintendo Adv24   12-20 0993</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Nintendo, Adv 24,1026</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv24</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Sunday Dec. 24</HEAD>
<HEAD>Next For Nintendo: Keeping Fan Loyalty</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE TIBBITS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>REDMOND, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   On a conference room wall at Nintendo of
America Inc.'s headquarters hangs a 20-foot-long picture frame,
crammed with hundreds of snapshots and school photos of children.
   They're pictures kids just sent on their own, says Nintendo
spokesman Bill White, usually with a note about how they did on a
Nintendo video game.
   For a company that gets thousands of photos, tens of thousands
of letters and millions of phone calls from customers, 1990 may
pose a problem: How to keep that loyalty.
   With a Nintendo Entertainment System in one out of nearly four
American households, toy industry watchers wonder whether the
market is getting saturated.
   ``I look at Nintendo as a fad that is moving into its fourth
year,'' says Paul Valentine, an analyst at Standard &amp; Poor's Corp.
in New York. If for no other reason, he said, that makes Nintendo
vulnerable to a slump.
   ``We've certainly seen the predictions of the doomsayers that
we've reached saturation,'' says White. ``That certainly hasn't
been the case.''
   Nevertheless, gamesters and marketeers at Nintendo are hustling
to keep their top-selling toy fresh among customers. Beyond
scouting new and more detailed games, ideas range from ``store
within a store'' retail displays to marketing tie-ins with Pepsi to
a feature-length movie.
   This Christmas, Nintendo introduced its hand-held game, ``Game
Boy,'' which it hopes will sell 1 million units. It forecasts
selling 9 million of the entertainment system consoles this year.
   By late 1990, Nintendo plans to have its ``NES Network''
running, which will allow the machines to be used to trade
securities and mutual funds through Fidelity Investments and for
game players to compete in nationwide tournaments.
   At Nintendo's U.S. headquarters in this Seattle suburb, the
bustling hallways, jingling phones and jammed shipping docks during
the Christmas selling season testified to the prosperity of a
company that's had the nation's No.1 toy the past three years.
   The subsidiary of Nintendo Co. Ltd. of Japan projects more than
$2.7 billion in retail sales for 1989, $1 billion more than last
year and nearly nine times as much as in 1986.
   This year, NEC Home Electronics (U.S.A.) Inc. and Sega of
America Inc., also subsidiaries of Japanese companies, brought out
competing machines offering more computing power than Nintendo's.
Atari Corp. also has introduced a competitor to Game Boy, called
Lynx.
   Still, Nintendo claims a 79 percent share of a video game market
it estimates at $3.4 billion. Its Japanese parent may introduce a
more high-powered system in Japan next summer, White said.
   Nintendo expects to have sold 20 million video game systems by
the end of this year, with the devices in 22 percent of all U.S.
households.
   But Valentine said he thinks sales will drop sharply in 1990.
Toy crazes, he says, just don't last over three or four years.
   ``I think when the fad goes we'll see a sharp contraction of
sales, anywhere from 40 to 70 percent over two years,'' he said.
Still, he said, that would leave video games as the largest
category within the toy industry.
   Many toy makers are hoping Nintendo crashes, says Larry Carlat,
editor of Toy and Hobby World magazine. ``It probably will be down,
but a lot of it is wishful thinking,'' he said.
   ``No company has been really able to hold onto a smash and be
able to manage it in the past. It's always been a boom and bust
cycle,'' Carlat said. ``It doesn't look like that is going to
happen with Nintendo. People in the toy business use the term `soft
landing.'''
   Nintendo introduced its game system in 1983 in Japan and has
sold it to 37 percent of households there. The goal, Nintendo says,
is similar market penetration in North America and Europe.
   Nintendo has been credited with reviving the video game
industry, which had all but vanished by the early 1980s because of
poor quality software. It did so by carefully contolling licensing
and manufacture of the games that can be played on its system.
   White says there are encouraging signs of market longevity in
the United States. Two years ago, he said, 75 percent to 80 percent
of the primary users of Nintendo games were boys aged 6 to 14. The
interest has broadened, he said, so that segment only represents 46
percent of the main users today.
   Men 18 and older now make up 30 percent of the primary users,
while women and girls comprise a 24 percent share, White said.
   ``The biggest change has been the widespread adoption of the
Nintendo Entertainment System as a true entertainment option'' to
television, video cassettes or stereos, he said.
   Nintendo does its best to cultivate fan loyalty, White says. It
has 400 game counselors at its U.S. headquarters, who handle
140,000 calls a week from stumped players.
   Its magazine, Nintendo Power, has 1.8 million subscribers. The
company gets 15,000 letters a week, and a roomful of writers
responds to each personally.
   ``You've got to bond with them,'' White says.
   So far, Nintendo has lent its name to 200 licensed products,
from sweatshirts to dolls, bedsheets to breakfast cereal. It's also
set up about 5,000 ``World of Nintendo'' store displays to sell the
merchandise.
   In addition, there are two television series. Earlier this month
a Nintendo-themed movie, ``The Wizard,'' opened nationally.
   While the licensing earns money, it also is a powerful marketing
tool for Nintendo, White said. Likewise, he said, a Christmas-time
promotion with Pepsi broadens Nintendo's advertising.
   White, however, said the tie-ins and licensing deals still are
secondary to the core of the industry, the games.
   Nintendo has sold 101 million individual games, and hopes for a
new hit when it brings out Super Mario Bros. 3 next year, a far
more intricate version of this year's best-selling game, he said.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End adv for Sunday Dec. 24.</NOTE>

</DOC>