<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0200 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0746EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Sears     12-19 0595</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Sears,0620</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sears Drops Tiegs, Loosens Ties to Disney</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID DISHNEAU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sears, Roebuck and Co. and Cheryl Tiegs are
parting ways after 10 years, but analysts say the split should
cause no pain to the world's largest retailer.
   Chicago-based Sears also says it has loosened its marketing ties
to Walt Disney Co.
   ``It has always been a mystery to me why retailers have been
under the illusion that puting a celebrity's name on a line
enhances its value,'' said analyst Edward Weller of Montgomery
Securities Inc. in San Francisco.
   ``I think image, over the course of years, has become less
important than substance,'' he said.
   That's exactly what Sears is hoping as it continues its
transformation from old-line retailer into a nationwide chain of
stores featuring superstore-like ``power centers'' and everyday low
pricing.
   Dropping the Cheryl Tiegs line of women's sportswear, a private
label carried by Sears since 1980, reflects a commitment by the
retailer to offer more name-brand goods, said Sears spokeswoman
Mary Jean Houde.
   ``Recent trends in women's apparel have indicated a preference
for national-brand merchandise and less demand for celebrity
lines,'' she said Monday.
   Ms. Houde said the decision to discontinue the relationship with
Ms. Tiegs was by mutual agreement.
   In an interview with Crain's Chicago Business, a local business
weekly, Ms. Tiegs said Sears was no longer interested in promoting
the Cheryl Tiegs line.
   ``When we started the program, there was a lot of advertising,
enthusiasm and backing,'' she said. ``Now, there's no advertising
support for female apparel. It's gotten lost in the shuffle.''
   But analyst Walter Loeb said Sears was better off without Ms.
Tiegs.
   ``I think she was a person for the '80s,'' said Loeb of Morgan
Stanley &amp; Co. in New York. ``Sears is moving with the times.''
   Sears also has apparel marketing agreements with actress
Stephanie Powers, tennis player Yvonne Goolagong and golfer Arnold
Palmer.
   The company announced earlier this year it was phasing out its
men's dresswear department, which includes a line of Johnny
Carson-label clothes.
   Ms. Houde said Sears' affiliation with Palmer and Ms. Powers
would continue, at least until their contracts expire. She said she
did not know the status of Sears' affiliation with Ms. Goolagong.
   Ms. Houde also said Sears and Disney had modified a 10-year
marketing agreement signed with much fanfare in 1987. The new pact
sharply curtails Sears' rights to market Disney-character products.
   Under the old agreement, Sears would have obtained exclusive
rights to develop products using characters from re-released and
new Disney animated films. The deal also called for Sears to
sponsor a major attraction at the new MGM-Disney theme park in
Orlando, Fla.
   Under the revised deal, which was struck last February, Sears
has rights to sell new Disney merchandise on a case-by-case basis
and maintains exclusive rights until 1991 of about 250 characters
from classic Disney films and to certain Disney-themed products
Sears has developed.
   Disney spokesman Tom Deegan said Monday the old agreement was
``confining,'' especially since Disney has been rapidly expanding
its own retail outlets in the past year.
   Deegan said there will be 41 Disney stores, carrying only
Disney-character merchandise, by the end of this year, with 100
planned by 1992.
   Last March, Sears began a changeover to everyday low pricing, a
retailing strategy that includes more brand names, lower prices and
fewer temporary price-cutting sales.
   The move was designed to fight discount chains and specialty
superstores, which have been steadily eroding Sears' market share.
   But after an initial surge, Sears' same-store sales growth has
been sluggish.
</TEXT>

</DOC>