<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0101 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1340EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-Noriega 2ndLd-Writethru a0567 12-29 0593</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Noriega, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0567,590</SECOND>
<HEAD>Noriega Was Warned of Impending U.S. Invasion, Sources Say</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS grafs after 7th graf, Taylor said, to include White
House comment.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Panamanian strongman Gen. Manuel
Noriega was tipped off two days in advance of the United States'
plans to invade his country, Bush administration sources say in a
published report.
   Sources were divided on exactly how and when the former
strongman, who managed to evade the U.S. military and later sought
refuge in the Vatican Embassy, was warned.
   But one source told The Washington Times there is ``hard
evidence'' the tipoff came in the form of a telephone call to
Panama from the State Department about 48 hours before the military
operation was launched at 1 a.m. Dec. 20.
   The call was intercepted by a National Security Agency listening
post near Panama City, sources said.
   ``There was a leak tipping Noriega before it was coming,'' one
government official said. ``We don't know who it was, but we
believed it was somebody at State.''
   Pentagon spokesman Bob Taylor denied Noriega was warned, saying,
``We don't have any indication at this time that there was a major
OPSEC (operational security) problem.''
   Taylor said a captured Noriega bodyguard told U.S. interrogators
the Panamanian leader was informed of the military action about
three hours before it happened but refused to believe the
information.
   In Corpus Christi, Texas, where President Bush was vacationing,
White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said he had no information
to give out on the report. In any event, Fitzwater said, ``it's
history now.''
   According to the newspaper, administration sources said some
Noriega forces and the general himself knew in advance about the
operation, dubbed Operation Just Cause. The sources based their
assessment, in part, on four incidents:
   _The night before the military intervention, Cuban MiG-21s
``shadowed'' C-141 Starlifters carrying U.S. Army paratroopers from
Pope Air Force Base, N.C., to Panama, the sources said. The
Pentagon is investigating whether one of the Cuban planes may have
fired its cannon as a warning shot. Noriega, with his relationship
with the United States crumbling in recent years, had increasingly
turned to Cuba for military and intelligence support, according to
administration sources.
   _Noriega intensified his nocturnal activities two days before
the U.S. assault, and the Pentagon has ``indications'' he visited
the Cuban Embassy at one point the night of Dec. 19-20 but left
when U.S. troops surrounded the compound, sources said.
   _Panamanian Defense Forces appeared to be lying in wait and
opened fire on Navy SEAL, or sea-air-land, commandoes who
parachuted into the area of Panama's small Paitilla Airport, where
the deposed leader maintained his private jet. The Pentagon said
four SEAL members were killed.
   _Noriega's most elite jungle warfare unit had vanished from its
battalion's facility when U.S. troops arrived to attack.
   The deposed Noriega today remained holed up in the Vatican
embassy in Panama City, where he sought asylum on Christmas Eve.
   A Panamanian official said new President Guillermo Endara's
government sent a letter to the Vatican asking that Noriega be
expelled.
   The official, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said he did
not know whether the government asked that Noriega be turned over
to U.S. authorities or to Panama.
   In Texas, where President Bush was hunting, White House
spokesman Marlin Fitzwater reiterated the U.S. stance that Noriega
should be handed over to the United States to stand trial on drug
trafficking charges.
   Vatican spokesman Joaquin Navarro said in Rome that officials
still hoped to resolve the crisis within days, but he gave no
details.
</TEXT>

</DOC>