<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0139EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     12-22 0456</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0470</SECOND>
<HEAD>On the Light Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   If Don and Lee Williams of Edgewater, Fla., are
wondering what happened to the check they mailed with their water
bill last month, it just arrived _ in New York City.
   The $33.87 check sent to ``City, Box 100,'' was rerouted by the
post office in Jacksonville, Fla., to the Big Apple, where it
showed up at the Department of Investigation, said department
Commissioner Kevin Frawley.
   ``This is the kind of thing, if you live in New York, that
convinces you this is `The City' in this country,'' said Frawley.
   Box 100 is an address set up by New York City officials for
residents to send complaints, tips on wrongdoing or just about
anything else, Frawley said. The same address in Edgewater,
apparently is where you pay your water bill.
   Frawley said he had not yet contacted the Williams couple to
find out if they have had any trouble with their water service.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   If President Bush doesn't eat the 75-pound
health-food tamale sent by a tortilla factory, he can donate it to
a homeless shelter, but he ought to try some of the smaller tamales
included in the box, said the tamale maker.
   Taylor Ford of La Suprema Tortilleria restaurant and tortilla
factory said Thursday he hoped the 5-by-3-foot, 22-inch thick
chicken tamale would ``promote good eating. You know, the president
is going to need his energy during this Panama crisis.''
   Ford's wife, La Suprema manager Lucy Cruz, said the tamale is a
``Texas-size holiday greeting to the president and his family.
President and Mrs. Bush can eat healthy but still enjoy holiday
feasting.''
   Unlike other tamales _ a native Mexican food of minced meat,
peppers and seasonings rolled in cornmeal and wrapped in corn
shucks _ the one steamed for El Presidente contains no
preservatives, lard, salt or sugar, Ford said.
   It contains 50 pounds of organic blue corn meal and 25 pounds of
chicken smothered in pureed red chile. ``Red, white and blue _
isn't that appropriate?'' Ford said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>HUNTINGTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Richard Beckner won't slide down your
chimney, but for a small fee he will bring packages to your door
dressed as Old St. Nick.
   ``I'll take my time, do a little ho-ho with them and ask the
kids what they want for Christmas,'' said Beckner, one of a handful
of Postal Service employees who will deliver packages over the
weekend dressed as Santa Claus. ``You just don't put the box down
and say goodbye.''
   The Santa service costs $12.
   ``We just decided to do something for the community,'' said Joe
Stultz, superintendent of window services for the Huntington Post
Office. ``We're losing money on it.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>