<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0167 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1937EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-KingDay     12-22 0663</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-King Day,0680</SECOND>
<HEAD>Petition Drive Puts King Holiday On Hold in Arizona</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LARRY LOPEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A paid state holiday honoring slain civil rights
leader Martin Luther King Jr., a political quagmire in Arizona for
years, again has become a dream deferred.
   A bill trading in the Columbus Day holiday for King Day cleared
the Legislature earlier this year and was signed by Gov. Rose
Mofford, but opponents of the King holiday and fans of Christopher
Columbus formed an uneasy alliance to hold up the law pending a
possible statewide referendum.
   Secretary of State Jim Shumway declared the holiday suspended
and said he believed the groups had filed enough signatures to
force a referendum next November.
   State Rep. Sandra Kennedy, a backer of the holiday, called an
opponent, president Pat Quaranta of the Arizona American Italian
Club, ``a bigot'' and said she feared a statewide vote on the
holiday because ``this state is almost Mississippi.''
   Tempe architect Julian Sanders, a King opponent who started the
referendum drive, said he didn't accept ``the argument that we're
going to be embarrassed by having Arizonans express themselves at
the polls.''
   Sanders and his backers gathered about 40,000 signatures on the
referendum petitions, while Quaranta and his allies gathered about
45,000. It only takes 43,500 valid voter signatures to force a
referendum.
   Supporters of the bill said they would campaign for the holiday
if the measure gets on the ballot. They also said they were still
considering a legal challenge to the petitions or introduction of a
new bill in the Legislature.
   Controversy over a King holiday has dogged the state's
politicians for years. Democratic Gov. Bruce Babbitt declared a
holiday by executive proclamation as he was about to start a
presidential bid in 1986. But Republican Attorney General Bob
Corbin called it an illegal usurpation of the Legislature's role
and Republican Gov. Evan Mecham rescinded it days before it would
have taken effect.
   The furor fueled a recall drive against Mecham, but a Senate
Court of Impeachment ousted him on other grounds before the recall
vote could be held and the battle over King shifted back to the
Republican-controlled Legislature.
   GOP lawmakers offered to put the King Day issue on the ballot.
Supporters refused to go along, saying privately that they feared
such a bill would be defeated and publicly that they believed it
would be divisive and harm the state's image.
   Democratic Gov. Rose Mofford, who succeeded Mecham, upped the
ante during a special session this year when she got business
leaders to say that a King holiday was needed to help Arizona's
chances of landing a Super Bowl.
   Lawmakers then agreed to King holiday, but only if it supplanted
Columbus Day so that state and local governments would not have any
additional expense.
   That angered two groups of voters: those who didn't believe the
civil rights leader deserved a holiday in the first place, and
those who wanted a holiday for King but did not want Columbus Day
downgraded.
   Quaranta said his faction favored a federal-style holiday that
would combine the state's separate Lincoln and Washington holidays
into a single Presidents Day to make room for a King Day without
affecting Columbus Day. Sanders said his faction opposed the
federal-style holiday.
   Supporters of the King Day bill, meanwhile, remain split over
whether to challenge the petitions in court, return to the
Legislature for a new bill that would effectively wipe out all the
petition signatures, or dig in for a campaign next year.
   ``I'm afraid of a vote,'' said the bill's sponsor, Sen. Carolyn
Walker.
   Babbitt, announcing the formation of a group to support King
Day, said he was ready to fight it out at the voting booth instead
of in the courthouse.
   ``Ultimately, people have the right to decide,'' he said,
echoing others who have said it would be hypocritical to deny
people a vote on the issue when King struggled for years to expand
voting rights.
</TEXT>

</DOC>