<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0318EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Panama-Political Bjt   12-22 0807</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Political, Bjt,800</SECOND>
<HEAD>Endara Seeks to Establish Government</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   EDITOR'S NOTE: Steven Komarow is a member of the Pentagon press
pool covering U.S. military operations in Panama.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By STEVEN KOMAROW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S.-backed President Guillermo
Endara, promising ``peace and justice in Panama,'' is moving to
establish his government by organizing a new national police force
and making his first handful of appointments.
   Under heavy U.S. guard, Endara and his two vice presidents met
Thursday with members of the national legislative assembly. Later,
he said he hoped to organize a new police force to take over within
a month from U.S. military forces now seeking to impose order and
searching for ousted dictator Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   ``I think we can lift up the country and ... do our duty in
making peace and quiet in Panama, peace and justice in Panama with
Noriega in hiding,'' Endara said in a telephone interview with
ABC's ``Nightline'' program Thursday night.
   ``I hope in a month we can put up a police force, a public force
good enough to keep peace and order in all Panama. And then the
U.S. forces would leave according to what Mr. Bush promised us,''
Endara said.
   In Washington, President Bush told reporters on Thursday, ``I'm
pleased that the Endara government is taking charge, and they made
several appointments today _ starting to govern the country.''
   Endara said he talked to Bush by phone and asked him for
immediate emergency help in ``food and medicine for those who are
injured, hungry and sick.'' He said he was told aid was coming.
   Gunshots echoed in the streets outside as Endara _ making his
first appearance since he was sworn in early Wednesday _ and Vice
Presidents Ricardo Arias Calderon and Guillermo Ford presided over
the legislative meeting. Sprinkled through the audience were U.S.
soldiers who wore jeans, sweatshirts and other civilian clothes at
the request of Panamanian officials who sought to avoid the image
of heavy U.S. control.
   In New York, Endara's designated envoy to the United Nations,
Eduardo Vallarino, said if Noriega is captured he should not be
extradited to the United States to face drug-smuggling charges but
should be tried in Panama.
   ``If Noriega is apprehended by the authorities in Panama, he
will have to be duly charged and tried in Panama,'' Vallarino said,
but added that the situation was ``irregular.''
   Speaking to the legislative assembly, Endara held out an olive
branch to Noriega's followers and said he would welcome back
members of Noriega's defense forces ``who can show they support our
democracy.''
   But he said on ABC that in organizing his new police force, he
would rely on officers ``that were not implicated in any kind of
corruption, officers who were not implicated in any kind of beating
of the people.''
   Endara asked Panamanian exiles to return because ``the military
dictatorship has fallen.''
   Endara ordered a curfew, expiring this morning, in hopes of
maintaining law and order as thousands of looters roamed the
streets smashing in windows and hauling away goods from virtually
every shop in the city.
   ``One of our first problems is that of anarchy and the civil
order,'' Endara told the national assembly. ``I hope these steps
and others will restore the order that we need,'' he said.
   Several people attending the session said they were grateful for
the U.S. intervention.
   ``The United States is responsible for delivering the dream we
have had since 1968,'' said cattleman Felix Espansona, an assembly
member in 1952-1956. ``We have had a dictatorship for 20 years and
now we feel liberated.''
   Vice President Ford said it will take some time to restore
order, but U.S. troops should leave ``the sooner the better.''
   The new government, by the accounts of most foreign observers,
overwhelmingly won an election on May 7, but Noriega canceled it
and continued his rule until U.S. troops invaded early Wednesday.
   Endara contended on ABC that even if Noriega remains at large he
would not be a major threat to the new government because he lacks
popular support.
   ``He was able to thwart the will of the people because he had a
dictatorship that was powered by fear,'' Endara said, but added,
``The people are not hiding Noriega ... I think Noriega really does
not count that much in Panama.''
   Endara appointed First Vice President Ricardo Arias Calderon as
minister of government and justice, responsible for internal
security. He named Second Vice President Ford as minister of
planning and political economy.
   Endara also announced the appointments of Vallarino as
ambassador to the United Nations, Lauren Fabrega as ambassador to
the Organization of American States and Carlos Rodriguez as U.S.
ambassador.
   Francisco Rodriguez, who was appointed Noriega's provisional
president after election results were annulled, told reporters
Wednesday, ``We are prepared to resist.'' Rodriguez apparently was
in hiding Thursday.
</TEXT>

</DOC>