<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0160 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1327EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-WhittleBusiness Adv31   12-28 1117</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Whittle Business, Adv 31,1152</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 31, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Brash Communications Company Incites Criticism, Competition</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also on financial wire</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY301 of Dec. 26; Graphic planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SKIP WOLLENBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   From classroom news video to waiting-room TV,
hardcover book inserts to Spanish magazines, Whittle Communications
keeps inventing ways for advertisers to reach the audiences they
want.
   The gutsy media company has angered Madison Avenue critics who
say its new ad vehicles aren't road-tested and may not work. But
Whittle has forced rivals to at least think about similar
strategies and concoct a few of their own.
   Whittle executives say the competition is one reason they are
scrambling to devise other offbeat ways to reach consumers through
the power of advertising. They say their approaches are the best.
   ``We have minor competition in virtually every area of our
business,'' said Whittle founder and chairman, Christopher Whittle.
   But he said no competitor had yet matched all 40-odd areas in
which Whittle offers advertisers a focused approach to reach
specific customers, from high-school sophomores to blue-chip CEOs.
   Whittle, a Knoxville, Tenn.-based concern 50 percent owned by
multimedia giant Time Warner Inc., has ambitious expansion plans
that easily could double the $180 million in revenue expected for
the year ended next June 30.
   In November, Whittle debuted the first in a series of short
hardcover books with ads interspersed among the pages, like those
in conventional magazines.
   That concept has stirred considerable skepticism among big book
publishers, who historically have limited ads in hardcover books to
short plugs for an author's other works on the inside jackets.
Whittle said its books, written by such well-known authors as David
Halberstam and John Kenneth Galbraith, will be sent free to people
whom the company considers American opinion leaders.
   Whittle perhaps is best known for its Channel One daily news
program for the classroom, scheduled to debut in March. The company
is signing up schools nationwide for the program, which has aroused
heated debate among educators because it is sponsored by
advertisers, like ordinary television shows.
   Schools get free video equipment for subscribing to Channel One,
but in return they subject captive audiences of students to ads for
products ranging from jeans to dandruff shampoo.
   The uproar over Channel One evidently was enough to convince
another pioneering media entrepreneur, Ted Turner, to launch a
rival news show for high schoolers in August. Turner's program
contains no ads but subscribers must use their own video gear.
   Unfazed by the Channel One controversy, Whittle is evaluating
whether to make televised programming available in another
captive-audience situation, doctors' waiting rooms. Some physicians
already subscribe to Whittle's Special Reports quarterly magazines
for patients to browse.
   The company plans a Spanish-language magazine distributed
through medical offices and beauty salons in Hispanic
neighborhoods. Whittle also will produce brief programs for
Spanish-language TV.
   Additional projects are under study _ a magazine for women in
beauty salons and a magazine for senior citizens, for example.
   Whittle's aggressive approach has raised questions about whether
the company is moving too fast into too many untested areas. But
the company's founder said it was designed to concoct ways to
communicate a message to a tightly defined group.
   ``For virtually everything we are doing now, we started planning
three years ago,'' said Whittle, a doctor's son and
multimillionaire who started the company as a college graduate in
1971.
   While some projects have died in the laboratory, Whittle said,
``I can't remember putting a property into the marketplace that
doesn't work.''
   One reason so many projects can be launched simultaneously, he
said, is that the company is divided into five parts, each headed
by a partner responsible only for its performance.
   Ed Winter, for instance, runs the Channel One school project,
while Peter Finn heads the division with the book and
Spanish-language projects and Alan Greenberg is in charge of
publishing Special Reports magazine and evaluating a pilot project
the company is calling Waiting Room TV.
   While they operate separately, one division's work often helps
the others.
   Whittle said the staff of 70 trained to sell the Channel One
system in schools probably will be pressed into service next year
to help sell Waiting Room TV to physicians if the company proceeds
with that project. The same goes for the Channel One network of
equipment installers.
   ``We realized that to develop all of that infrastructure and
then to dismantle it didn't make any sense,'' Whittle said.
   He usually goes directly to top management of companies such as
Kraft General Foods and Federal Express Co. with his proposals,
bypassing ad agencies. He argues that his magazines and TV programs
give advertisers the opportunity to precisely target the people
they want as buyers, without having to compete for airtime or page
space purchased by other advertisers.
   Whittle's approach has aroused some hostility among traditional
Madison Avenue ad agencies. Some ad executives also have expressed
skepticism about Whittle's claimed results.
   ``None of his media projects are proven yet,'' said Richard
Kostyra, director of media services at J. Walter Thompson Co., one
of the largest and best-known ad companies.
   Kostyra said Whittle's own audience research results for Special
Reports waiting-room magazines, for example, are inconclusive. This
has complicated the agency's efforts to advise clients on where to
place their ads.
   Other agency executives, speaking privately, said they suspected
Whittle's Waiting Room TV project might be an effort to boost ad
renewals for Special Reports, now in their second year.
   Whittle called such talk ``competitive chatter'' from rivals and
ad agents who feel threatened.
   He said his company had to create its own audience research
system because Whittle products are different. ``The measurement
system for newsstand magazines can't measure what we do,'' he said.
   Special Reports overseer Greenberg said he expects current
sponsors will buy two-thirds of the advertising space in the
magazines and new advertisers will buy the rest.
   Several Special Reports advertisers declined comment on their
plans. But Kraft General Foods spokesman Mike Caruso said that
company doesn't dispute Whittle's research.
   Greenberg denied that Waiting Room TV was promoted now to
invigorate renewals in Special Reports. Nonetheless, advertisers in
the magazines get the first opportunity to advertise on the TV
program.
   Whittle said the company was promoting the Waiting Room TV
project because it knew waiting rooms were a powerful media
environment. ``We knew we had better get into that business or
someone else will,'' he said.
   He was right. Another company, headed by former advertising and
programming executive Frederick Doner, is testing the Good Health
Channel, a program on health topics with commercials, to debut in
doctor's waiting rooms by April.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, Dec. 31</NOTE>

</DOC>