<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1239EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p AM-FirstStirrings Bjt   12-24 0494</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-First Stirrings, Bjt,500</SECOND>
<HEAD>RETRANSMITTING a0721 with `p' category code</HEAD>
<HEAD>1992: Nobody's Running, but Nobody's Sitting Still Either</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DONALD M. ROTHBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Political Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The name doesn't matter. Any Democratic
heavyweight will do: They're all professing no interest whatsoever
in taking on President Bush in 1992.
   ``I have no plans to run for president in 1992,'' declares Sen.
Sam Nunn of Georgia.
   ``I'm focusing on my re-election next year,'' says Sen. Al Gore
of Tennessee.
   ``I'm not running and I'm not making any plans to run,'' chimes
in Sen. Lloyd Bentsen of Texas.
   Ditto for Sen. Bill Bradley of New Jersey, Gov. Mario Cuomo of
New York and civil rights leader Jesse Jackson.
   So is it Bush and Quayle unopposed for re-election in 1992?
   No chance.
   While there is remarkably little overt activity among the
potential Democratic challengers, there is always something
stirring in presidential politics. Even those who deny any interest
find their hearts beat a little faster when they breathe the cool,
clean air of Iowa and New Hampshire.
   Bradley was in Des Moines over the summer to speak at a
fund-raiser for Sen. Tom Harkin, D-Iowa, who faces a tough
Republican challenge in 1990. While he was there, he met with Tony
Bisignano, a union official and state legislator.
   Bisignano was impressed.
   He said they didn't talk about 1992, but he'd be eager to start
a ``low-key, grassroots organization'' to drum up support for
Bradley.
   Bentsen, meanwhile, was the featured speaker at the Iowa
Democratic Party's Jefferson-Jackson Day dinner this fall.
   New Hampshire, the state which has the quadrennial distinction
of holding the first presidential primary, has had visits in 1989
from Rep. Pat Schroeder of Colorado and Gov. Richard Celeste of
Ohio. Both came close to entering the 1988 presidential race.
   Sen. Robert Kerrey of Nebraska had a long lunch in Boston this
fall with a group of political operatives who have had extensive
experience in Democratic presidential campaigns.
   ``He just wanted to know what was on people's minds,'' said
Larry Rasky, a public relations executive who worked on Sen. Joe
Biden's 1988 campaign.
   Cuomo has said an indication that he is planning a presidential
bid would be an announcement that he will not run for a third term
as governor of New York. He's not giving that signal, at least not
now.
   In a telephone interview, he said he's leaning toward another
gubernatorial campaign.
   ``There's just nothing I can do that's as important as this,''
he said.
   But somehow, Cuomo finds it impossible to stop thinking about
running for president.
   An example of his ambivalence came last summer when he invited a
reporter to ask him about the possibility that he might seek the
presidency.
   ``I want to talk about it, because I want to dispose of it,'' he
said, declaring that he was tired of speculation about his plans.
   ``And so,'' he said, ``for the time being I'm not going to
discuss it.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>