<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1203EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania-Nastase     12-24 0369</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Nastase,0378</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tennis Star's `Legs Were Shaking' As He Witnessed Fighting</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Romanian tennis star Ilie Nastase says his legs
shook as he watched tanks firing at buildings in Bucharest last
week.
   In a statement published in The Sunday Telegraph, Nastase was
quoted as saying he was ``hoping and praying'' that the people won
their fight against forces loyal to ousted Communist President
Nicolae Ceausescu. He said he left Bucharest on Friday, the same
day Ceausescu fled the presidential palace.
   ``All week the rumors were growing of what was happening. But we
believed Ceausescu was too powerful for the people to succeed,''
Nastase said.
   He said he was aware of ``pressure building up in Romania, but I
didn't think things could happen so quickly.''
   ``On Thursday I had to go to see what was happening. ... I did
not fight but I just wanted to be part of what all these people
were doing. I was shocked. I saw people falling down as soldiers
and police opened fire. Then in the evening they were firing on
them from helicopters.''
   Nastase, 43, who had ``never seen a dead person in my life
before,'' was quoted as saying a tank started firing behind him
and, ``I wasn't a normal person, my legs were shaking, everything
was shaking.''
   At Bucharest Airport on Friday, his flight out was delayed
several hours because it was feared anti-Ceausescu forces might
shoot it down, Nastase was quoted as saying.
   Nastase said his army officer rank was an honorary one, ``given
to me because of my tennis playing. I don't have any links with
them. As for the security police, everybody fears them. That's why
we thought a revolution could never succeed.''
   He said he met Ceausescu only once, ``when he gave me a
decoration a long time ago.'' But he knew Ceausescu's son,
Valentin, who he said ``has nothing to do with his father and has
criticized him in the past.''
   In his tennis-playing heyday in the 1970s, Nastase was famous
for his flamboyant on-court antics and won the 1972 U.S. Open and
the 1973 French Open. He now plays on the seniors tour, an
international circuit for veteran stars.
</TEXT>

</DOC>