<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0129 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 2257EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Panama 5thLd-Writethru a0632 12-23 0863</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Panama, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0632,820</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Sends 2,000 More Troops to Panama; Casualties Mount</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: inserts new 19th graf to add that F-117 involved in one mission;
picks up 19th graf pvs, bgng: Defense Secretary</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE BYRD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two thousand fresh American troops were
airlifted to Panama on Saturday as U.S. commanders conceded alarm
over the unexpectedly stiff resistance by forces still loyal to
fugitive Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   The reinforcements, including a helicopter company, were sent
from the Army's 7th Light Infantry Division at Fort Ord, Calif.,
and joined 24,000 other U.S. soldiers, many of them bone-weary, on
Day Four of the nation's largest combat operation since the Vietnam
War.
   It is an operation that has turned quickly from the conventional
warfare of the initial strike, which virtually neutralized the
Panamanian Defense Forces, to the more perplexing mission of
countering guerrilla attacks and policing a nation in institutional
chaos.
   The Pentagon reported that 25 U.S. servicemen, four more than
listed Friday, had been killed in the fighting. Officials also said
two American dependents had been killed, 241 U.S. troops had been
wounded and one was still missing.
   The military said 139 members of the PDF had been killed, and 95
wounded. There was no official count of casualties among Panamanian
civilians.
   U.S. forces said they had recovered 15,500 weapons, including 33
armored vehicles, with an increasing number of arms laid down
voluntarily by surrendering members of the Panamanian Defense
Forces, including the garrison which guarded the presidential
palace. The number of PDF detainees totaled 2,250, according to
Gen. Maxwell Thurman, head of the U.S. Southern Command.
   Despite the massive recovery of weapons, commanders said
Noriega's ``dignity battalions'' continued to draw fresh arms and
ammunition for hit-ad-run attacks upon troops and civilians.
   One American officer said the loyalists of the self-styled
``maximum leader'' _ whose whereabouts remained undetermined _ had
used ambulances to shuttle their weaponry around Panama City.
   Still, Thurman, briefing reporters in Panama, offered several
bits of ``good news'' late in the day. He said:
   _Nine employees of Evergreen International Airlines, an American
cargo carrier, had been released by pro-Noriega forces and
evacuated by U.S. troops to the safety of Howard AFB. According to
Thurman, the airline employees had been stripped to their underwear
and beaten, but were not seriously hurt.
   _The effort to create a new Panamanian police force under the
new, U.S.-installed government of Guillermo Endara was proceeding
at an encouraging pace. ``Today we brought down 750 uniforms and
1,000 people showed up,'' he said.
   ``The people are cooperating with us and are beginning to lay
down their weapons,'' the general said. In areas torn both by
looting and combat, he said, ``people are ... cleaning up the
debris.''
   CBS News, meanwhile, reported that CBS producer Jonathan
Meyersohn, who had been held by pro-Noriega forces since the early
hours of the U.S. assault, had been released.
   Thurman, while stressing progress in the effort to pacify the
PDF, conceded ``that does not mean we're over and done with with
the dignity battalions,'' the guerrilla-styled irregulars still
loyal to Noriega.
   The Southern Command also reported that prisoners at an island
penitentiary in the Pacific, about 60 miles from the capital,
apparently had overcome their pro-Noriega guards and had radioed
for help from American forces. The prison group was said to include
some of the former Panamanian officers who led a failed coup
attempt on Oct. 3.
   Lt. Col. Jerry Marguila, spokesman for the Southern Command,
said Saturday that the dignity battalions were ``increasing their
activities _ of harassing attacks with small arms and mortar fire,
threatening the civilian population, and hostage-taking.''
   Pressed for specifics, Marguila replied ``I don't have in my
mind an increase in numbers between today and yesterday of
dignity-battalion efforts. It's just that they are becoming more of
a concern, because they are taking more of our time as opposed to
the PDF.''
   At the Pentagon, one military official, speaking on condition of
anonymity, conceded the ferocity of the dignity battalions had
caught U.S. commanders off guard.
   A Pentagon spokesman also said the F-117 stealth fighter-bomber
was among the new weapons used for the first time during combat in
the Panama attack. Lt. Cmdr. Edward Lundquist said the plane, which
is designed to evade enemy radar, was used successfully on one
mission, bombing a field near a PDF barracks to create ``confusion
and alarm'' among the enemy.
   Defense Secretary Dick Cheney was at his office on Saturday to
keep tabs on developments in Panama as well as the bloody
revolution which ousted Romanian dictator Nicolae Ceausescu.
President Bush was at Camp David, Md., where he worked on a
Christmas Eve address to the American military men and women around
the globe, including a ``special message'' for those in Panama.
   Bush planned to tape the Armed Services Network broadcast at the
Pentagon on Sunday, where he also was to receive an extended
briefing on the Panama fighting.
   Bush was briefed by telephone Saturday by national security
adviser Brent Scowcroft on both Panama and Romania.
   The president plans to go to a Houston hospital on Dec. 31 to
visit soldiers wounded in Panama.
</TEXT>

</DOC>