<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0107 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1851EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SoCalQuakes     12-28 0447</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SoCal Quakes,0461</SECOND>
<HEAD>Quake Sequence Raises Concern About Big Jolt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A series of small earthquakes rattled
Southern California on Wednesday and Thursday, raising scientists'
concern somewhat about the possibility of a major jolt.
   A quake measuring 4.3 on the Richter scale jarred people awake
at 1:41 a.m. Thursday in an area stretching about 120 miles from
Los Angeles to east of Palm Springs. No injuries or damage were
reported.
   That quake was the largest of about 10 that began Wednesday
afternoon and were centered in an area seven miles from downtown
San Bernardino, said seismologist Kate Hutton of the California
Institute of Technology in Pasadena.
   A magnitude-3.3 aftershock at 2 a.m. Thursday and a 3.2
foreshock at 2:10 p.m. Wednesday were in the same area.
   The tremors were cause for slightly increased concern because
they were centered close to the San Jacinto Fault, which itself
produced several quakes this month.
   ``We've had slightly unusual activity, and we're keeping a watch
on it,'' said Lucile Jones, a seismologist at the U.S. Geological
Survey's Pasadena office. ``I'm a little more concerned than I was
yesterday, but not much more.''
   A 1988 forecast by the Geological Survey said a magnitude-6.5 to
7 quake is 50 percent likely by the year 2018 somewhere on the San
Jacinto Fault, which starts at a point northwest of San Bernardino
and runs roughly 130 miles southeast into eastern San Diego County.
   State emergency services officials said in 1988 that such a
quake could kill a few hundred people, injure 1,000 and cause more
than $1 billion damage.
   Hutton noted that previous quake sequences, situated a bit
farther northwest of San Bernardino in Cajon Pass, ended without a
large jolt.
   In southeastern Australia on Thursday, a strong earthquake
crumbled buildings and homes in Newcastle, killing at least 11
people and injuring more than 120, officials said. Scientists don't
believe quakes in widely distant areas are related.
   Thursday's magnitude-4.3 quake in California ``was a good sized
one,'' said Jay Diamond, a disc jockey at San Bernardino station
KFRG-FM, which received several calls from jittery residents. ``It
shook us pretty good. The glass on the booth was shaking.''
   ``There was a bit of a rolling, then a sharp jolt,'' said
Christie Hall, who was awake in her Lake Arrowhead home when
Thursday's quake and aftershock struck. ``The aftershock was much
milder.''
   Quakes ranging in magnitude from 4 to 5 on the Richter scale of
ground motion are considered small to moderate but can produce some
local damage knocking items off shelves and sometimes breaking
windows.
   Palm Springs is about 100 miles east of downtown Los Angeles.
</TEXT>

</DOC>