<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0200EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-USInterventions     12-21 0653</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-US Interventions,0674</SECOND>
<HEAD>A Chronology of U.S. Military Intervention</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The military strike in Panama to seize Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noriega is the latest in a long history of U.S. military
interventions in the Western Hemisphere. Here is a chronology:.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   1823 _ President James Monroe enunciates ``Monroe Doctrine,''
stating U.S would regard as unfriendly acts any interference with
Western Hemisphere nations by European powers.
   1855-60 _ American adventurer William Walker installs himself as
Nicaraguan dictator, is ousted, captured by British, turned over to
Honduras and executed.
   1898 _ After Spanish-American War, U.S. troops occupy Cuba.
Troops are later withdrawn but are sent back three times, in 1906,
1912 and 1916, to put down rebellions.
   1903 _ President Theodore Roosevelt dispatches warships and
troops to isthmus of Panama to assist Panamanians trying to secede
from Colombia after Colombia rejects treaty with U.S. to build
canal across isthmus. Rebel victory ensures building of Panama
Canal and U.S. occupation of Canal Zone.
   1904 _ Roosevelt adds ``Roosevelt Corollary'' to Monroe
Doctrine, saying U.S. might be compelled ``in flagrant cases of ..
. wrongdoing or impotence to the exercise of an international
police power.''
   1909-10 _ Rebels backed by U.S. oust regime of Nicaraguan
President Jose Santos Zelaya. U.S. banks lend money to Nicaragua
under conditions that give them control of nation's finances.
   1912 _ Marines sent to Nicaragua at request of President Adolfo
Diaz and U.S. banks to restore order and put down forces opposed to
U.S. control. Marines remain in Nicaragua until 1925.
   1912-26 _ U.S. forces land in Honduras on three separate
occasions to protect American interests, particularly U.S business
interests such as banana-growing United Fruit Co.
   1915 _ Marines land in Haiti when bloody disorders erupt during
summer, threatening American banking interests. Anti-U.S.
insurrection erupts and lasts two years, taking 1,500 Haitian
lives. Marines left in 1934.
   1916 _ President Woodrow Wilson sends Marines to Dominican
Republic after that nation's president, who opposed U.S.
intervention to prevent a threatened revolution, resigns. U.S.
military government takes over and lasts eight years.
   1927-33 _ Marines return to Nicaragua to put down revolution led
by Cesar Augusto Sandino. Forces pull out in 1933 as criticism of
intervention grows in U.S. Sandino assassinated in 1934 on order of
Anastasio Somoza Garcia, head of U.S.-backed national guard.
   1934 _ President Franklin D. Roosevelt institutes ``Good
Neighbor'' policy of non-intervention in Central American internal
affairs.
   1954 _ Leftist government of Guatemalan President Jacobo Arbenz
Guzman initiates land reform in Guatemala, expropriating two-thirds
of United Fruit's 332,000 acres. Eisenhower administration, through
CIA, supports rebels who overthrow Arbenz and establish military
dictatorship.
   1961 _ Invasion force of anti-Castro Cuban exiles trained by CIA
lands at Bay of Pigs in Cuba and is quickly crushed.
   1965 _ President Johnson sends 20,000 troops to Dominican
Republic after civil war breaks out. American forces, whose mission
was ostensibly to protect American lives, fought against rebels.
Some 2,000 Dominicans and 20 American soldiers were killed before
peace was restored and elections held. U.S. troops withdrew in 1966.
   1980 _ U.S. sends military advisers to El Salvador to counter
Cuban aid to leftist rebels as that nation slides towards civil war.
   OCT. 25, 1983 _ U.S. invades Grenada to oust hard-line junta
that took power from another Marxist government in a bloody coup.
All American combat troops were withdrawn within two months and
remaining advisers left in 1985.
   NOVEMBER 1982 _ First reports emerge alleging covert U.S. aid to
anti-Sandinista Contra rebels in Nicaragua.
   APRIL 8, 1984 _ Congressional sources say CIA has been
supervising mining of Nicaraguan ports, to undermine Sandinista
government.
   MARCH 17, 1988 _ Additional American troops arrive in Honduras
as show of force against Nicaragua, whose forces crossed Honduran
border chasing Contra rebels.
   DEC. 20, 1989 _ U.S. troops attack military bases in Panama to
oust Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega and install a new government.
</TEXT>

</DOC>