<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 0144EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TrafficAccidents 1stLd-Writethru a0602 12-31 0538</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Traffic Accidents, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0602,0556</SECOND>
<HEAD>Six Killed in Interstate Chain Pileup Outside Flagstaff</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS grafs 8-10, bgng `Six people...', with 3 grafs to UPDATE
with initial death toll revised downward to five, but 14-year-old girl
then dying; Pick up 9th graf, `At least ...'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FLAGSTAFF, Ariz. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A chain of collisions on an icy,
fogbound interstate outside Flagstaff left six people dead and at
least 34 injured Saturday, authorities said.
   Another series of collisions on a foggy stretch of interstate in
northern Florida injured 15 people, one seriously.
   The mid-morning accidents in Arizona involved about 40 vehicles,
including 16 to 18 tractor trailers, said Sgt. Allan Schmidt, a
spokesman for the Arizona Department of Public Safety.
   There were at least three separate accident sites over a
quarter-mile stretch of Interstate 40 about five miles east of
Flagstaff in northern Arizona, officials said.
   Emergency personnel and equipment were brought in from as far
away as Kingman, 160 miles to the west.
   ``This is the all-time worst accident that I've ever personally
witnessed,'' said Coconino County Sheriff Joe Richards, a 17-year
veteran.
   ``The extensive amount of injuries, damage and death, it's
almost unbelieveable. It's nightmarish in its magnitude.''
   Schmidt initially said six people were confirmed dead, but
Flagstaff Fire Capt. Paul Hellenberg revised that figure downward
to five, including three people whose bodies were pulled from a car
trapped between three tractor-trailer rigs.
   Then an unidentified 14-year-old girl who was freed from the
same car after more than five hours died of her injuries in a
hospital, bringing the toll back up to six, Hellenberg said.
   Thirty-three other people were taken to Flagstaff Medical Center
with injuries, hospital spokeswoman Lauren Bosse said. Ten people
were treated and released, she said. Bosse said she did not know
the conditions or injuries of the others.
   At least six people were injured seriously, Fire Capt. Mike
Giovando said.
   The accidents closed the eastbound lanes of I-40, heading toward
Albuquerque, N.M., for the day. Westbound lanes were reopened a
couple of hours after the accidents.
   Traffic was backed up for several miles and had to be rerouted.
   Officials said they were investigating the cause.
   Giovando, one of the first authorities on the scene, said the
accidents apparently were the result of icy roads and fog. Up to 2
feet of snow has fallen in Flagstaff since Thursday night.
   ``It was a real heavy fog,'' Giovando said. ``We were trying to
get a hose line, then we heard people screaming that they were
being burned by the fire.''
   One truck was destroyed by fire, officials said.
   A shelter for survivors was set up at a local elementary school.
   In Florida, four chain-reaction collisions involving 25 vehicles
closed Interstate 95 for more than two hours in both directions
just south of the Georgia border, the Florida Highway Patrol said.
   Nine people were taken to hospitals, including a 5-year-old boy
who was in serious condition in the pediatric intensive care unit
of Baptist Hospital in Jacksonville, nurse Bonnie Lundblom said.
   The boy's younger brother, believed to be about 18 months old,
was in stable condition and ``doing fine,'' Lundblom said.
   Trooper Charlie Creel said the two boys were flown to
Jacksonville by helicopter.
</TEXT>

</DOC>