<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0122 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1932EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MailBombs-HateGroups     12-19 0594</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mail Bombs-Hate Groups,0610</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hate Group Monitors Say Racists Most Logical Suspects in Mail Bombs</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Mail Bombs, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SONYA ROSS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   People who track hate groups said Tuesday that
white supremacists are logical suspects in the mail-bomb killings
of a federal judge in Alabama and a lawyer in Georgia.
   Racist mentalities fit the bill in both motive and mode: they
are angry over recent defeats in court cases, and they have a
historical bent for bombings, according to two hate group watchers.
   ``There's no reason to disbelieve they would be connected to
these incidents. They have planned to kill federal judges before,
and there have been similar incidents with bombs,'' said Danny
Levitan, executive director of the Center for Democratic Renewal in
Atlanta.
   On Saturday, a mail bomb killed 11th U.S. Circuit Court of
Appeals Judge Robert S. Vance, who wrested control of the Alabama
Democratic Party from white supremacists during the 1960s, at his
home in a Birmingham, Ala., suburb. On Monday, another mail bomb
killed Savannah, Ga., Alderman Robert Robinson, an attorney who was
working on a long-running school desegregation case.
   A fourth bomb was found Tuesday at the Jacksonville, Fla.,
office of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored
People. The office was evacuated and the bomb, which arrived in the
mail Monday but was left unopened, was disarmed, officials said.
   FBI Director William Sessions told a Washington news conference
Tuesday that the pattern didn't fit white supremacist groups, but
said they weren't being ruled out. The FBI has warned civil rights
activists as well as lawyers and judges to beware of strange
packages because of the possibility white supremacists mailed the
Savannah bomb.
   The bombs that killed Vance and Robinson were pipe bombs
containing nails, authorities said.
   Racist groups typically use that sort of bomb, said Leonard
Zeskind, research director for the Center for Democratic Renewal.
   ``The Klan and Nazi groups are more likely to use pipe or powder
bombs,'' he said. ``Plastic (explosives) is drug stuff.''
   Recent court losses have hurt racist groups in the pocketbook
and in efforts to recruit more members, giving them a potential
motive for retaliation, said Pat Carter of Klanwatch.
   ``Some of these groups are perturbed that they are losing their
assets,'' she said. ``It has made their membership very bitter.''
   In 1987, a U.S. District Court jury awarded $7 million to the
mother of a Mobile, Ala., teen-ager murdered in 1981 by two Ku Klux
Klansmen. Last year, a U.S. District Court jury in Atlanta awarded
$950,400 in damages to two civil rights leaders because of violence
surrounding the first of two civil rights marches in Forsyth
County, Ga., in 1987.
   White supremacist groups have enjoyed renewed popularity in the
South over the past decade. Incidents of racial hatred surged from
eight in 1978 to 276 in 1986, the last year for which figures were
available, according to statistics compiled by the U.S. Justice
Department's Community Relations Service.
   The Center for Democratic Renewal, formerly the Anti-Klan
Network, found 3,000 racial incidents reported between 1980 and
1986, including about 500 in 1986 alone, Levitan said.
   ``We view the level of hate crimes as having reached epidemic
proportions,'' he said. ``Skinheads and youth are at the cutting
edge.''
   Skinheads favor extremely short haircuts. Many, but not all,
also embrace white supremacist ideology.
   Klanwatch, a unit of the Southern Poverty Law Center in
Montgomery, Ala., has identified at least 11 active hate groups in
Georgia and Alabama, including two Skinhead groups in Alabama and
one in Georgia.
</TEXT>

</DOC>