<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1153EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-TaxMailout     12-25 0782</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tax Mailout,800</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tax Forms Ready For Mailing</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN CRUTSINGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Economics Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Along with late greeting cards and Christmas
bills, more than 107 million American households will get unwelcome
mail from the Internal Revenue Service starting Tuesday _ their
annual tax forms.
   The mass mailing of tax packages, which carries a $26 million
pricetag for printing and postage, is conducted every year
immediately after Christmas.
   Some taxpayers may already have received their forms, because
their local postmaster jumped the gun. The forms have been sitting
in post offices with IRS instructions not to mail them until after
Christmas, but every year some postmasters send them early anyway.
   In an effort to reassure jittery taxpayers, officials are
stressing that the forms contain few changes. But much to the
chagrin of the IRS, one of the changes should not have been made.
   The problem involves the catastrophic health program, which
Congress voted to repeal in November after a revolt among the
elderly who would have had to foot the bill. The wealthiest senior
citizens would have faced an added tax burden of $800.
   The tax liability was abolished along with the decision to scrap
the program. However, the congressional action came too late to
change the tax forms, which were printed up in October with
outdated information about the now obsolete tax.
   The IRS hopes to keep confusion to a minimum with a publicity
campaign. Also, no form exists for taxpayers to compute their
liability under the catastrophic program.
   If some taxpayers still fail to receive the word and include an
amount on the line for the Medicare premium, the IRS says it will
refund the money. IRS official Arthur Altman estimated 12 million
elderly taxpayers could be led astray.
   The IRS said this year's forms, which should be in most homes
before New Year's Day, will offer relatively minor changes.
   Among them:
   _ The personal exemption, the amount you may exempt from
taxation for yourself, your spouse and each dependent, increases to
$2,000 per person, up from $1,950 last year.
   _ The standard deduction, claimed by people who do not itemize,
rises to $3,100 for a single person, up from $3,000 last year,
while the exemption for a couple increases to $5,200, up from
$5,000 last year.
   _ Tax rates remain the same at 15 percent, 28 percent and 33
percent, but the tax brackets have been widened so that more income
will be taxed at a lower rate, thus compensating for the impact of
inflation.
   _ Bowing to the increase in separate last names for husband and
wife, the IRS for the first time will include two lines, instead of
one, so that spouses filing a joint return can enter their names
and Social Security numbers on separate lines.
   _ Taxpayers must show the Social Security number for any
dependent they claim who is age 2 or older. Last year, the cutoff
was age 5.
   _ Families with income as high as $19,340 may qualify for an
earned-income credit, up from a limit of $18,576 last year.
   _ In one of the few changes with an adverse impact, only 20
percent of interest paid on credit card debt, auto loans and other
personal debt will be deductible on 1989 returns, down from 40
percent last year.
   The tax forms must be filed this year by April 16, one day later
than normal because April 15 falls on a Sunday.
   The IRS expects about 111.2 million individual income tax
returns will be filed for the 1989 tax year. The majority of
taxpayers, 65 percent, will end up using the comprehensive Form
1040, designed for taxpayers who itemize or who have incomes above
$50,000 annually.
   The rest who do not itemize and meet other qualifications can
file the more simple Form 1040A or the simplest of all, the
nine-line Form 1040EZ. The form a taxpayer receives in the mail is
based on the form the taxpayer used last year.
   All the tax forms come with a pitch from new IRS Commissioner
Fred T. Goldberg Jr. urging taxpayers to consider filing their
returns electronically.
   Offered this year for the first time nationwide, electronic
filing features the advantage of cutting down the time required to
process refund checks to three weeks, compared to the normal six to
10 weeks.
   In 1988, two-thirds of all taxpayers qualified for a refund with
the average refund totaling $875.
   The IRS hopes that 2 million taxpayers will file their returns
electronically this year and it is providing a toll free telephone
number, 1-800-424-1040, for people to call for a list of tax
preparers in their area who have the capability of filing returns
electronically.
</TEXT>

</DOC>