<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0125 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1813EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Inventor     12-19 0433</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Inventor,0452</SECOND>
<HEAD>Inventor Has Ideas, Lacks Buyers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By J.L. SCHMIDT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LINCOLN, Neb. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jack Scherbak said he always figured if you
built a better roach killer, the world would beat a path to your
door.
   He claims he has. They haven't.
   A self-proclaimed jack-of-all-trades, he admits to only a slight
frustration in his latest attempt to crack the corporate
marketplace with a new idea.
   ``Some people have money and no ideas. Other people have ideas,
and no money,'' he said in an interview. ``I'm in the latter
category.''
   Scherbak, 49, who also works as a carpenter and plays classical
guitar at nightclubs and restaurants, majored in physics and math
for one year at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. But literature
finally won out over math.
   ``Science has always been restricted,'' he said last week. ``In
a sense, it's just like the guitar. You have to practice to be able
to express your emotion.''
   Inspired by beat poet Jack Kerouac, Scherbak left college and
hit the road. He joined the Army and was a medic in Texas, then
took art and sculpture classes in New York City.
   Several years ago he submitted a plan to the Nebraska Energy
Office to fill discarded aluminum cans with popped pocorn and build
insulating panels, walls, roofs, ``even a whole house,'' he said.
   ``They said it was a novel idea, but no loan company would give
a person a loan to build with something so unconventional,'' he
said.
   Earlier this year, Scherbak confronted a real and present
problem: roaches under the kitchen sink.
   Commercial roach traps didn't work, he said. Sprays were toxic
and he didn't want to endanger his family's health.
   So, he began mixing common household ingredients until he found
a nontoxic combination that worked. He won't say what's in it
because it's not patented yet.
   He put it in a spray can labeled ``ZEZ, the world's first
non-toxic roach spray.''
   He carries the can along with a plastic gallon jug full of live
roaches and a large metal kettle for demonstrations.
   After dumping four roaches into the kettle, he sprayed them with
ZEZ. As they died, he sprayed the product into his eyes and mouth.
   ``The roaches are dead but I'm OK,'' he said.
   He's not bashful in attempts to market the stuff.
   Last month, he wrote to the entertainment director of ``The
Tonight Show,'' saying he'd like to meet Nebraska native Johnny
Carson and demonstrate his product on the television show.
   ``There's still no word from Hollywood, but at least we don't
have roaches under our sink anymore,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>