<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0147 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 2233EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Nicaragua-US     12-27 0274</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nicaragua-US,0282</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nicaragua Threatens `Traitors' If United States Invades</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MANAGUA, Nicaragua (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Defense Ministry said Wednesday
all those supporting U.S. military intervention in Central America
will be ``neutralized, cut off and executed'' if the United States
attacks Nicaragua.
   The threat by the ruling leftist Sandinista government was not
specific, but appeared aimed at the 14-party National Opposition
Union coalition and its presidential candidate, Violeta Chamorro,
in national elections Feb. 25.
   The warning came in a special communique to all military units
broadcast over government radio and part of a maximum alert of
armed forces ordered Dec. 20 by President Daniel Ortega, hours
after the U.S. invasion of Panama.
   It said that at the start of any ``Yankee intervention,'' all
units are ordered ``to apply plans to neutralize, cut off and
execute all recalcitrant traitors who openly or covertly have been
encouraging such Yankee intervention.''
   Earlier Wednesday, the Sandinista newspaper Barricada said
Nicaragua will not let a U.S. plane carrying monthly supplies for
the U.S. Embassy land as scheduled on Jan. 11.
   Foreign Minister Miguel D'Escoto told U.S. Secretary of State
James Baker III Tuesday night the measure was taken because U.S.
forces would not let Nicaraguan planes land in Panama and
surrounded the Nicaraguan Embassy in Panama City, Barricada said.
   U.S. Embassy spokesman Lou Falino said he had no comment.
   Last week, Nicaraguan troops surrounded the U.S. Embassy in
Managua in response to Nicaragua's embassy in Panama being
surrounded. U.S. officials were trying to prevent any effort by
ousted Panamanian strongman Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega to flee to
that embassy.
   Instead, he took refuge in the Vatican embassy.
</TEXT>

</DOC>