<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0137 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1617EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-ExplodingBody 1stLd-Writethru a0556 12-29 0657</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Exploding Body, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0556,0668</SECOND>
<HEAD>Corpse Explodes at Airport; Sabotage Feared</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 12 grafs to UPDATE with France saying it will pressure
Sudan to investigate incident, reax from aid organization; picks up 9th
pvs, ``The relief ...''</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NAIROBI, Kenya (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The body of a French citizen killed when a
relief plane was shot down in southern Sudan suddenly exploded in
Khartoum just before it was to be flown back to Paris for funeral
services, sources said Friday.
   The sources, who spoke on condition they not be identified, said
medical personnel at the scene did not believe the Thursday blast
was caused by a buildup of natural gases and feared the corpse had
been booby-trapped.
   If the body indeed was sabotaged, it was unclear if it was meant
to explode on the UNICEF flight that carried the corpse back from
southern Sudan to Khartoum, or on the flight to Paris, the sources
said.
   ``It was not an accident, but we don't know whether it was the
responsibility of an organized movement or an individual,'' Dr.
Rony Brauman, president of the aid group Doctors Without Borders,
said in Paris.
   Bernard Kouchner, the French secretary for humanitarian affairs,
said France would urge Sudan to investigate the bombing and the
downing of the plane.
   The dead person was one of four relief workers killed in the
attack over southern Sudan. Three were French nationals working for
the aid group Doctors Without Borders and one was a Sudanese
employee of the World Food Program.
   The identity of the person whose body exploded was not known,
but the sources said it belonged to one of the French nationals.
The sources said the bodies that were bound for Paris were flown
there on Friday.
   The four were killed when their twin-engine Britten-Norman
Islander was shot down near Aweil on Dec. 21.
   The explosion was described as relatively small, but big enough
to knock a passenger from the truck that was carrying the bodies to
the France-bound flight and to cause a fire that burned the driver,
the sources said.
   The blast occurred on the tarmac of the Khartoum airport as the
bodies were being taken to the plane.
   ``Our people in one of the trucks heard a small explosion and
then the body just started to burn,'' Brauman said. ``It burned the
whole truck. One of our local employees broke his arm when he fell
on the tarmac to get away.''
   Brauman refused to specify which body had burned, but said
toxicologists would test clothing and the body bag for traces of
explosives. He made their comments before a closed-casket service
Friday for the three French nationals at his organization's
headquarters.
   The relief group identified the victims as Yvon Feliot, a pilot
for the group; Laurent Fernet, a supply specialist; and Dr.
Jean-Paul Bescond. The Sudanese was Frazer Ariyaba.
   Doctors Without Borders operates a hospital at Aweil, a
government garrison town about 590 miles southwest of Khartoum that
is said to be surrounded by Sudan People's Liberation Army rebels.
   Sudan's government has accused the rebels of downing the plane
with a missile. But the rebels said the Sudanese army shot down the
plane to ``justify its continuing ban on relief activities in
southern Sudan.''
   The government two months ago banned relief flights into
southern Sudan. It later accused the UNICEF relief effort of using
relief flights to ferry arms and ammunition to the rebels. The
United Nations has denied the accusation.
   Operation Lifeline Sudan since April has been moving relief food
and supplies into southern Sudan to avert a famine it said
threatened up to 250,000 people with starvation. U.N. officials say
they succeeded in staving off the famine for this year, but fear
the situation could deteriorate next year if the ban is not lifted.
   The rebels have been fighting Sudan's Moslem-dominated
government since 1983 seeking greater autonomy for the country's
predominantly Christian and African south.
</TEXT>

</DOC>