<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0110 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1649EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Lithuania 2ndLd-Writethru a0630 12-19 0801</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lithuania, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0630,0822</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lithuania's Communists Urge United Political Front</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: CORRECTS names to Algirdas, sted Algirdis, graf 2; Romas Gudaitis;
sted Gudaititis, graf 8; Juozaitis, sted Jouzaitis, graf 17 and final graf.
No pickup</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Soviet-Congress, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK J. PORUBCANSKY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VILNIUS, U.S.S.R. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lithuania's Communist Party leader
Tuesday urged a united political front with other parties to press
for sovereignty and protect the Baltic republic from Kremlin
pressure.
   Algirdas Brazauskas, in an address to more than 1,000 delegates
at the opening session of the Lithuanian Communist Party Congress,
avoided calling for an immediate, direct break with the Soviet
Communist Party or for Lithuanian indepenence. But he left open
both possibilities.
   Lithuania, he said, saw itself as part a union of Soviet
republics undergoing a radical transformation under President
Mikhail S. Gorbachev's reforms that ``will allow us to build a
Soviet Union from which we can secede if we wanted to.''
   Gorbachev has spoken out against plans to split the Lithuanian
party from the national Communist Party and to restore the
independent Lithuanian state that existed between the World Wars.
But the Lithuanians have continued to press for more autonomy, and
an initial step Dec. 7 removed constitutional language that made
the Communist Party the leading force in society.
   The national Congress of People's Deputies last week refused to
discuss such a move, but Communist parties in Eastern Europe
already have given up that special status as change sweeps the
region.
   Brazauskas told the delegates in a nearly 1{-hour speech: ``Only
with an independent Communist Party is it possible to compete
normally and on an equal footing with oher political forces.''
   ``Political power is achieved only through democratic
elections,'' he added.
   Romas Gudaitis, a Lithuanian writer, said separation was
justified because ``the Soviet Commuinist Party is still mired in
Stalinism.''
   Brazauskas said the Lithuanian party, freed from its
subordination to Moscow, was prepared to cooperate with the
powerful political movement Sajudis and other parties in a ``united
front'' to govern the republic of 3.7 million people.
   ``Practically all parties in Lithuania today proclaim the same,
or practically the same, goals,'' he said.
   Those newly formed parties include the Social Democrats and a
party advocating outright independence from the Soviet Union.
   ``A united front, if it became truly united and consolidated
Lithuania, would be a good counterbalance to any attempts from
outside to restrict our achievments,'' he said in an obvious
reference to fears that Moscow might try to limit Lithuania's drive
for sovereignty.
   Progressive Communist leaders in Lithuania and the other Baltic
republics of Latvia and Estonia, are already closely identified
with Sajudis and other people's fronts organizations, but
Brazauskas' proposal was to extend and formalize that relationship,
apparently to make the Communist Party a coalition partner.
   Arvydas Juozaitis, a member of the Sajudis governing council,
told reporters that Sajudis was not interested in a united front.
   ``I'm not sure they are absolutely acceptable to us under this
name,'' he said.
   The Communist Party, regardless of what decision it makes at
this week's congress, is nearly dead, he said. ``They are reburying
a dead body in another grave, from a Soviet grave to a national
grave,'' he said.
   Juozaitis added, however, that it was ``very possible'' the
Lithuanian Communist Party would soon change its name.
   Lithuanian leaders have said they needed to compete in Feb. 24
local elections and that requires them to develop a program
independent of Moscow.
   Many local Communist leaders in March were beaten badly in
elections to the national Congress of People's Deputies because
they were too closely identified with decades of Moscow's
heavy-handed policies.
   Although the party's proposed rules do not mention any firm
relationship with the Soviet party, Brazauskas vowed their would be
no immediate break with it.
   ``The declaration and legitimization of the statutes of the
independent Lithuanian Communist Party does not mean breaking off
the relationship with the Soviet Communist, but reshaping it and
(making) a transition from subordination to partnership,'' the
party said in a draft document.
   Outside, hundreds of people gathered on the steps of the opera
and ballet theater where the Congress was being held. They carried
red, green and yellow Lithuanian flags and banners backing the
party's proposed independence from Moscow.
   A small group of demonstrators marched down Gediminas Avenue,
the main street, to protest even a reformed Communist Party. One
sign proclaimed, ``Stop Communism in Lithuania,'' with the word
``Communism'' painted red to simulate dripping blood.
   The Congress is to last most of the week and observers expect a
vote on the party's status to take place Wednesday or Thursday.
   Juozaitis said he thought Latvia, Estonia, Georgia and Armenia
soon might follow the lead of the Lithuanian party in separating
from the national organization, strengthening Lithuania's hand in
dealing with Gorbachev.
</TEXT>

</DOC>