<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0104 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1857EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania-PrimeMinister     12-26 0321</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Prime Minister,0329</SECOND>
<HEAD>Interim Prime Minister Faces Enormous Tasks</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Petre Roman, Romania's interim prime
minister, is a young intellectual who faces the daunting task of
finding ways to mend a country torn by bloody strife and a battered
economy.
   ``It's clear that our difficulties are great,'' Roman told
Soviet television in an interview Tuesday.``The greater part of the
cadres we need for our economy have not yet resumed their work.''
   The 43-year-old university professor said he and the rest of the
37 members of the National Salvation Committee, Romania's main
organ of power since the Dec. 22 toppling of dictator Nicolae
Ceausescu, have not had time to examine what exactly to do about
the economy.
   ``What we have achieved so far is to solve only emergency
problems,'' Roman told the Vremya news program. ``The questions
I'll be dealing with are connected with restoration of the economy
under new conditions.''
   Romania was badly mishandled during Ceausescu's rule, leading to
widespread shortages of basic foodstuffs, commodities and energy.
   Ceausescu, who rejected the kind of reforms under way elsewhere
in the Soviet bloc, advocated a Stalinist-type centrally planned
economy, entirely disregarding market forces and outlawing private
property.
   In another interview Tuesday with French television, Roman said
the reason for executing Ceausescu and his wife, Elena, only two
days after their capture was that the Council feared Ceausescu's
secret police were planning a rescue attempt.
   Roman graduated from the Faculty of Hydromechanics of the
Polytechnic Institute in Bucharest, where he now is a professor.
   He did post-graduate work at the National Polytechnic Institute
in Toulouse, France, where he graduated magna cum laude.
   He is married and the father of two children.
   Roman's late father Valter was a prominent sociologist who
fought in Spain against anti-Franco forces during the Spanish Civil
War. His mother, Hortensia, now retired, for years had a high-level
post at the state-run Radio Bucharest.
</TEXT>

</DOC>