<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0234EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     12-29 0324</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0336</SECOND>
<HEAD>On the Light Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An 800-foot-long holiday card is on its way to
Soviet President Mikhail Gorbachev, bearing season's greetings
serious and light from half a million Americans.
   ``One world, one people,'' Yoko Ono wrote on one of the
100-foot-long, 12-foot-wide rolls of paper that James Lawlor, 34,
of Iowa, has carried around the country since May.
   ``Hey dude, hang tough. Your bud _ Dennis,'' someone in Seattle
offered.
   ``Hey Gorby, let's do lunch,'' wrote someone in San Diego.
   Lawlor said he got the idea a year ago, and put his
safety-goggle business in Iowa on hold to travel to all 50 states.
He collected signatures on enough paper to cover the side of an
80-story building one block wide, financing the $125,000 cost
through T-shirt sales and donations.
   He said he wanted to give Gorbachev a boost.
   ``I felt the man needed encouragement,'' Lawlor said. ``I liked
the changes he was making.''
   To get the card noticed, he chose ``to make it huge and have
everybody in America sign it.''
   With help from the Soviet Embassy and the national airline,
Aeroflot, the card will be flown today to Moscow and will be
displayed near the Kremlin so Soviet citizens can read it. Lawlor
and an assistant will go along.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Attention shoppers: Coming soon, at the
office next to Sears at the shopping mall _ a place to pay your
parking tickets.
   Traffic Court will open an outlet next to Sears at Baldwin Hills
Crenshaw Plaza on Jan. 16 for people who want to pay fines,
schedule court appearances or register for traffic school, court
and mall officials announced this week.
   It will be the county's third satellite ticket payment center.
The other two average about 6,000 customers a month, Municipal
Presiding Judge Larry Fidler said. He said it would make paying
tickets easier and ease congestion at the traffic courthouse
downtown.
</TEXT>

</DOC>