<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0175 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2030EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Peru-Tourists     12-18 0441</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Peru-Tourists,0454</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Foreign Tourists Murdered in Peru</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANDREW SCOTT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LIMA, Peru (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two young tourists, an Australian man and a
New Zealand woman, were found murdered in a rebel-infested region
of the southern highlands with a note saying, ``This is how
capitalists die,'' officials said Monday.
   The two had been backpacking through Latin America.
   Julie Gold, spokeswoman for the Australian Embassy in Brasilia,
Brazil, told The Associated Press military troops found the bodies
on Dec. 7 near Puquio, 360 miles southeast of Lima, in an area of
the Andes where Maoist Shining Path guerrillas are active.
   Military officials said the victims were killed about Nov. 22,
she said. It was not known if the two were going by bus through the
area or hitchhiking.
   A spokesman for the Foreign Ministry in Lima, who demanded
anonymity, said it had not been determined whether guerrillas or
common criminals killed them and the matter was under investigation.
   Ms. Gold identified the man as Paul David Linsdell, 25, of
Melbourne. The New Zealand Embassy in Lima identified the woman as
Vivienne Joy Barbour, 26, of Hamilton. Australia does not have an
embassy in Peru.
   Ms. Gold said Linsdell had been strangled and that the note was
found near the bodies. The note indicated the two were killed by
the Shining Path, which often leaves similar notes next to their
victims.
   Neil Johnson of the New Zealand Embassy said the bodies were
found on the road between Puquio and Abancay, the same road where a
German couple was taken from a bus and murdered by Shining Path
rebels in May.
   Ms. Gold said Linsdell and Ms. Barbour had traveled together
since June, and had gone to Mexico, Brazil and Bolivia before
coming here. She said they had planned to fly from Lima to London
this month.
   Ms. Gold said their remains would be returned home.
   The government has declared the area around Puquio and Abancay
an emergency zone and put it under military control to fight
leftist insurgents.
   The U.S. Embassy and other foreign embassies have issued
advisories urging tourists not to travel to the emergency zones,
which cover a third of the country and affect more than half of
Peru's 21 million people.
   At least 20 foreigners, including tourists, aid workers and one
journalist, have been killed in terrorist violence since the
Shining Path launched its insurgency in 1980. Eight foreigners died
in June 1986 when rebels bombed the tourist train to Machu Picchu,
the ancient citadel of the Incas near Cuzco.
   The government says more than 17,000 people have died in the
violence the past nine years.
</TEXT>

</DOC>