<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1259EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Panama 3rdLd-Writethru   12-26 0863</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama, 3rd Ld-Writethru,a0525,0886</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Forces Capture Hundreds of Noriega Loyalists</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 11th pvs, `Cuba has...' to UPDATE with Cuban diplomats,
U.N. officials reporting Cuban complaint; picks up 12th pvs, `Endara, elected...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos PAN1,2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOSEPH B. FRAZIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 400 troops loyal to Gen.
Manuel Antonio Noriega were captured in airborne assaults and
scattered combat erupted overnight throughout parts of the capital,
U.S. military spokesmen said today.
   Noriega remained in the Vatican Embassy after seeking asylum on
Christmas Eve. The United States has demanded his surrender to face
U.S. drug charges, but church authorities refused. Spain has denied
political asylum, and there was no new word about where he might go.
   Army Lt. Col. Jerry Murgia said 440 Noriega loyalist troops and
about the same number of weapons were captured in airborne assaults
Monday on David, 200 miles to the west, and La Palma, just
southwest of Panama City.
   He also said Noriega's intelliegence chief, Col. Guillermo Wong,
surrendered Monday. Wong had been arrested after a coup attempt in
October, but was released.
   Murgia said 30,000 pounds of emergency medical supplies had
arrived in the past day and civilian relief agencies would send
workers starting today to help with redistribution.
   Twenty-three American soldiers are known to have died and
another 330 wounded, Murgia said. The figures for the number of
wounded rose because of late-arriving reports, he said. Two U.S.
dependents were killed.
   Panamanian casualties were listed as 293 killed, 123 wounded and
4,446 captured, according to U.S. military authorities. Panamanian
doctors said more than 100 civilians were killed and hundreds more
injured.
   Heavy fighting was reported overnight near a downtown sector
where many embassies are located, and the building housing the
Banco General was burned. Bank officials and U.S. soldiers said the
blaze started after American troops returned fire coming from the
building.
   There also was fighting near Santo Tomas hospital close to the
American Embassy. Caches of arms and ammunition have been found
hidden in the hospital in recent days.
   Small arms and mortar fire were heard near the Cuban Embassy,
which was surrounded by U.S. troops, as well as the Foreign
Ministry, where the U.S.-installed government of President
Guillermo Endara has set up shop.
   Cuba today said the U.S. soldiers surrounding its embassy
violated international law and asked the U.N. Security Council for
help in ending the situation, Cuban diplomats and U.N. officials
said.
   Endara, elected in May balloting that Noriega nullified, moved
Monday to consolidate his authority. First Vice President Ricardo
Arias Calderon said a governor had been appointed for six of
Panama's 10 provinces.
   Presidential spokeswoman Anel Belis called on government workers
to go back on the job today. Government services have largely been
paralyzed since the United States invaded one week ago to oust
Noriega.
   Dozens of U.S. soldiers and armored vehicles encircled the
Vatican mission after Noriega entered it Sunday. Gen. Maxwell
Thurman, chief of the U.S. Southern Command, said he ordered the
embassy surrounded to prevent Noriega supporters from ``blowing
into the place.''
   Reporters saw soldiers using pellet guns to shoot out street
lights on the avenue running by the mission late Monday. They left
just four lamps lit.
   In Rome, Vatican spokesman Joaquin Navarro said Monday that
``concerned parties,'' including the Endara government, would
examine Noriega's case.
   Asked if a ``simple'' turnover of Noriega to the United States
was foreseeable, Navarro replied, ``Well, I don't think so. There
isn't an extradition treaty.''
   Sources in Panama said the Vatican Embassy mentioned the
possibility of Noriega going to Spain or Cuba.
   But in Madrid, Spanish Foreign Minister Francisco Fernandez
Ordonez was quoted as saying, ``Spain is not the ideal country to
accept Noriega because of its extradition agreement with the United
States, which includes drug trafficking (cases).''
   American troops had surrounded the Cuban, Libyan and Nicaraguan
embassies to prevent Noriega from seeking refuge there, but none
were at the Vatican building when Noriega arrived Sunday afternoon.
   Asked why, Defense Secretary Dick Cheney told a news briefing in
Panama, ``We had our hands full carrying out our basic mission.''
   Cheney said he would like to bring U.S. troops home ``as soon as
possible,'' but he added, ``They will stay as long as they are
needed.''
   Panama's new foreign minister, Julio Linares, said the U.S.
invasion would ensure that the 1977 Panama Canal Treaties are
fulfilled ``as they were signed. In other words, on December 31,
1999 (the canal) will revert to Panama, as well as all its
installations.''
   A Panamanian officer who also faces drug-related charges in
Florida was escorted to Miami on Monday by U.S. drug agents, the
Justice Department said. Lt. Col. Luis del Cid surrendered to U.S.
forces in Panama on Saturday.
   U.S. troops arrested Mario Rognoni, a commerce minister under
Noriega, according to witnesses who saw him being taken from his
house. It was not known why he was apprehended.
   American military officials said most of Noriega's 15,000-member
Defense Forces had surrendered and that the resistance of his
loyalists had dwindled. Helicopters dropped thousands of ``safe
conduct passes'' in resistance areas for those who wanted to turn
themselves in to U.S. authorities.
</TEXT>

</DOC>