<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0138 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 2000EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Syria-Egypt 1stLd-Writethru a0600 12-27 0638</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Syria-Egypt, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0600,0655</SECOND>
<HEAD>Egypt, Syria Agree to Restore Relations After 12-Year Break</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with Israeli reaction. No pickup</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LOUIS FARES</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DAMASCUS, Syria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Egypt and Syria agreed to restore
diplomatic relations Wednesday after a 12-year rift caused by the
late Egyptian President Anwar Sadat's peace negotiations with
Israel.
   A summit between presidents Hafez Assad of Syria and Hosni
Mubarak of Egypt will take place in early January, the prime
ministers of both countries announced. Syrian Prime Minister
Mahmoud Zoubi said restoring ties ``will open a new page in the
history of our common destiny.''
   The accord was announced at the end of a one-day visit to
Damascus by Prime Minister Atef Sedki of Egypt. At a news
conference, Sedki and Zoubi said they agreed to exchange
ambassadors. They gave no date for the January summit.
   In Jerusalem, Israeli officials said the development could
improve Israel's peace prospects with the Arab world. Egypt is the
only Arab nation with which Israel has a peace treaty, and Syria
has been an implacable foe.
   A statement released in Cairo and Damascus said: ``The
governments of the Syrian Arab Republic and the Arab Republic of
Egypt have agreed to resume full diplomatic relations, effective
Wednesday, Dec. 27, 1989. This comes to express the determination
of the two peoples to consolidate brotherly relations in all
fields.''
   The announcement said changes worldwide made both countries
realize the ``necessity of achieving comprehensive Arab entente as
a sound basis for joint Arab action.''
   Syria and Egypt were united in 1958 under a pan-Arabic movement
led by Sadat's predecessor, Gamal Abdul Nasser. They resumed
independent governments in 1961.
   Assad broke ties after Sadat made a dramatic visit to Jerusalem
in 1977, the opening move in two years of negotiations that
resulted in the Egypt-Israel peace accord.
   Avi Pazner, aide to Israeli Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir,
characterized Wednesday's agreement as ``part of Egypt's going back
to the Arab world'' after its ostracism.
   ``We hope it will bring about a bigger realization in the Arab
world that peace with Israel is possible and desirable,'' he told
The Associated Press.
   However, Shamir spokesman Yossi Ahimeir said Israel did not see
the agreement as ``signifying any change in the Syrian position
regarding Israel or peace.''
   Sedki, the first such high-ranking Egyptian official to visit
the Syrian capital since the rift, met for two hours with Assad
before the announcement. He said the results of the meeting were
``even more than I originally expected.
   ``President Assad talked very warmly about Egypt and recalled
all the past and historic ties between the two countries. He
further qualified the period of complications as an experience we
should profit from.''
   Damascus radio said Sedki carried a message to Assad from
Mubarak. He did not disclose its contents.
   ``The purpose of this trip is to take the last step, following
which comes the resumption of ties,'' Sedki said. ``Egypt's goal is
to unify ranks with Syria and consolidate cooperation between our
two countries.''
   In a brief statement to reporters, Zoubi said developments
``witnessed by the Arab world require that Syria and Egypt return
to each other on the basis of their historical and fraternal
bonds.''
   Mubarak said Tuesday that he and Assad planned to meet, but
indicated this would follow restoration of diplomatic links.
   Mubarak said his policy was never to allow improvement of
Egypt's relations with any country to affect ties with another
nation.
   This appeared aimed at both Syria and Iraq, ruled by rival wings
of the Arab Baath Party and at odds for years.
   Egypt aided Iraq militarily in its eight-year war with Iran.
Syria backed Iran.
   Seventeen Arab states severed relations with Egypt after the
Camp David peace accords with Israel in 1979. All except Libya now
have restored diplomatic ties with Egypt.
</TEXT>

</DOC>