<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0157 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1551EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-Symposium-Mideast Adv31   12-26 0779</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Symposium-Mideast, Adv 31,0801</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 31, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WORLD SYMPOSIUM 90s: Middle East _ Peace Still Far Off</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ED BLANCHE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Efforts to end the Arab-Israeli conflict
and other disputes in the Middle East are slow, but growing
superpower detente could nudge the region toward greater stability
in the 1990s.
   Iran-Iraq peace talks have stalled and both sides are rearming
amid a widening proliferation of long-range missiles in the region.
   This is eroding Israel's long-held technological superiority and
heightening superpower concern of a new arms race, including
nuclear and chemical weapons, in the volatile region.
   The pace of the Arab-Israeli peace process is unlikely to gather
momentum for some time, until Israel's right-wing prime minister,
Yitzhak Shamir, relaxes his hardline position of refusing to
negotiate with Yasser Arafat's Palestine Liberation Organization.
   Many observers believe this is unlikely unless there is intense
pressure from Washington. Shamir, at odds with a faction of his own
Likud Party as well as his Labor coalition partners, is in no
position to start making concessions.
   Egypt is expected to remain the crucial mediator between Israel,
with whom it signed a peace treaty in 1979, the Palestinians and
other Arab states in trying to reach a comprehensive Mideast peace
settlement.
   The current focal point of the peace process is a 10-point plan
produced by Egypt's President Hosni Mubarak, designed to break the
deadlock over Israel's blueprint for elections in the troubled
occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip, torn by a Palestinian uprising
for the last two years.
   The main stumbling block is the Israeli government's refusal to
negotiate with Palestinians they believe will speak for Arafat's
PLO.
   Arafat, backed by the Arab League, insists there can be no peace
conference not attended by the PLO, which Arabs acknowledge as the
Palestinians' sole representative.
   Despite Israeli claims the uprising is foundering, it shows no
sign of collapsing. The fear is that if there is no discernible
progress in the peace process, it will intensify.
   Analysts believe Arafat, after publicly renouncing terrorism and
recognizing Israel's right to exist, has gone as far down the road
to moderation as he can without alienating the PLO's hardliners.
   A year-old dialogue with the United States has failed to result
in Washington jarring any concessions from the Israelis. Failure to
produce substantive results will leave Arafat exposed and his peace
initiative discredited from within the PLO.
   Hardliners like George Habash of the Popular Front for the
Liberation of Palestine have made clear their patience is running
out.
   The Arab-Israeli peace process, which has dragged on for more
than 20 years with only Egypt's peace treaty to show for it, has a
profound impact on the region's other conflicts.
   This is most pronounced in Lebanon, the Middle East's proxy
battleground, where the Arab League was finally jolted into taking
forceful action to end 14 years of civil war.
   But the peace settlement it brokered has stalled because the
Christian leader, Gen. Michel Aoun, rejects it, citing its failure
to provide cast-iron guarantees of a Syrian withdrawal.
   The Syrians, their efforts to pacify their unruly neighbor
thwarted yet again by Lebanese Christians, are becoming frustrated
and may yet move against Aoun.
   Radical Syria, which needs Lebanon as a security buffer between
itself and Israel, is likely to come under pressure from Moscow to
moderate its stand on the overall Middle East settlement as detente
improves.
   Moscow, increasingly crucial to the peace process after years of
being edged out by Washington, is already seeking to persuade Syria
to abandon its drive for military parity with Israel.
   The Kremlin, increasingly concerned with economic and social
upheaval at home, has made clear that Syria must end its rifts with
Iraq, Egypt and the PLO to achieve the long-elusive Arab unity that
is a prerequisite for an international peace conference.
   Iran, Syria's ostensible ally, also is in transition following
the death of Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini and the election of
Hashemi Rafsanjani, leader of the so-called pragmatists, as
president last summer.
   He seeks to open up Iran after a decade of isolation, attract
Western investment and technology to revitalize the moribund
economy following the 1988 cease-fire in the 8-year war with Iraq.
   He is opposed by revolutionary hardliners and much will depend
on whether he can fend off the challenge and ease economic
hardships for Iran's 55 million population, growing at an alarming
3.5 percent a year.
   If he can, one key consequence could be the release of Western
hostages held by pro-Iranian militants in Lebanon and the removal
of a major source in instability in the region.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Sunday, Dec. 31</NOTE>

</DOC>