<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0099 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1739EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Panama 1stLd-Writethru a0602 12-26 0932</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Panama, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0602,880</SECOND>
<HEAD>Administration Eyes Attempt To Freeze Assets Held By Noriega</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 2 grafs following 4th graf pvs, bgng, The administration
xxx etc., to UPDATE with Thurman negotiating in Panama, picks up 5th graf
pvs, The Vatican x x x</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bush administration, still struggling to
get custody of deposed dictator Manuel Antonio Noriega, said
Tuesday it wants to freeze millions of dollars in assets he
allegedly transferred out of Panama.
   Justice Department spokesman David Runkel said U.S. officials
will file papers Wednesday in more than a half-dozen countries
where, he said, Noriega had hidden ``illegal drug money'' amounting
to more than $10 million.
   Runkel said the U.S. would try to freeze cash, or liquid assets,
which are in European bank accounts. He refused to identify the
banks, although he did say that none of Noriega's money has been
traced to the United States.
   The administration was training its legal sights on Panamanian
money assets as officials remained embroiled in tense negotiations
over Noriega, wanted in this country on drug-trafficking charges.
The administration sought to pry Noriega from the custody of the
the Vatican Embassy in Panama City.
   In Panama City, Gen. Maxwell Thurman, head of the U.S. Southern
Command, conferred three time on the street outside the embassy
with Monsignor Sabastian Laboa, the papal nuncio.
   Despite the negotiations, Defense Secretary Dick Cheney said the
situation with Noriega might be prolonged for an indefinite period
of time. ``It could be that they'll have a long-term resident in
their embassy in Panama City,'' he said.
   The Vatican, which has no extradition treaty with the United
States, refused to simply hand Noriega over to Washington. And it
has maintained that stand since the deposed Panamanian leader,
along with what Runkel described as ``10 associate thugs,'' sought
asylum at Papal Nunciature Sunday afternoon.
   ``Our position is, we mean to bring him back to the United
States,'' White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said. But he
refused to rule out the possibility that other options might be
considered. One scenario is that Noriega might stand trial in
Panama. Another had him possibly going to a third country.
   ``Everybody is talking to everybody,'' Fitzwater said. But he
said ``it's too soon to characterize it as progress.''
   Although Bush has not talked directly either with Pope John Paul
II or with the nunciature in Panama about Noriega, Fitzwater said
U.S. officials have used diplomatic channels to press their demand.
   ``We told them very directly what our feeling were,'' he said.
   Fitzwater spoke at the White House as President Bush was having
a working lunch with top advisers at his Camp David, Md., and as
the chief Pentagon spokesman said conditions had stabilized in
Panama.
   Bush was briefed by Cheney, newly returned from a visit to U.S.
troops in Panama, along with national security adviser Brent
Scowcroft and Gen. Colin D. Powell, chairman of the Joint Chiefs of
Staff.
   Defense Department spokesman Pete Williams revealed that when
Noriega turned himself in Sunday, he was ``said to be so exhausted
from the chase that he could barely speak.'' Williams said Noriega
had been on the run since the U.S. operations began six days
earlier, and said he never was in command of the Panamanian Defense
Forces which resisted U.S. soldiers.
   A task force composed of officials from the departments of
State, Justice and Defense, as well as National Security Council,
was formed to tackle the negotiations on Noriega's fate. The group
conducted most of its meetings in telephone conferences.
   The United States has rejected the idea that Noriega might be
entitled to political asylum. Under international law, such asylum
can only be granted on the grounds that a person is subject to
persecution because of religious or political views, Runkel said.
   ``Noriega does not fit either category,'' he said. ``His fears
are of prosecution in the United States on two indictments.''
   Fitzwater said the United States had offered Noriega a deal as
recently as October if he would step down, but Noriega refused. The
United States will not compromise with Noriega now, he said.
   Meantime, one U.S. official, speaking on condition he not be
identified, said the pope's representatives have contacted several
Latin American and European countries in hopes one will agree to
take Noriega.
   ``He has no place to go yet,'' the official said. ``No one wants
him.''
   Officials said there was no way Noriega could flee from the
nunciature because it is surrounded by U.S. troops intending to
remain in place as long as Noriega is inside.
   ``There's no way he can get out,'' Cheney said in an interview
on ABC-TV. ``But by the same token, we do not have the authority to
go in and take him out because of international law.''
   Cheney, back from a Christmas Day tour of Panama where visited
an estimated 26,000 troops, said the situation in the country was
``much quieter than it's been'' since the U.S. invasion last week.
   Despite occasional sniping incidents, Cheney said the
``overwhelming sense is a return to normalcy.'' Cheney said the
``U.S. military did its job,'' and now ``the lawyers and the
diplomats have to take over.''
   If the situation in Panama continues to improve, Cheney said,
the United States might speed up the withdrawal of troops. He gave
no timetable, though.
   Williams said Panamanian citizens have been turning weapons over
to U.S. troops and revealing the whereabouts of large weapons
caches.
   ``The best I can tell you is that about 33,000 weapons have now
been captured, discovered, or turned in,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>