<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1459EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania-Iran     12-23 0453</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Iran,0467</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iranian Newspaper Complains About Ceausescu Visit</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN MARRIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iranian newspapers on Saturday criticized
last week's official visit of Romanian leader Nicolae Ceausescu,
who was later ousted in a popular revolution.
   The daily Ettela'at said the visit provided an opportunity for
international news media to defame Iran, the Islamic Republic News
Agency reported.
   ``The Foreign Ministry would do well to offer some explanation
why it arranged for Ceausescu to visit Tehran at an inopportune
time when his ouster was not something difficult to guess,'' it
said.
   The English-language Tehran times joined in the criticism by
writing: ``The nagging question is why should he be received in our
capital while a whole nation has risen up against his rule?''
   ``How can the Iranian nation, which made one of the most
vigorous revolutions against an armed-to-the-teeth dictator, not
share the sentiment of the Romanian people standing up to an
autocratic rule?'' it added. ``The Romanian nation's victory is a
triumph of all nations.''
   The newspaper's editorial, to be published in Sunday's issue,
was quoted in advance by IRNA.
   The staff of the Romanian Embassy in Tehran on Saturday declared
its support for the uprising in Bucharest and for the new National
Salvation Committee, the news agency quoted Ambassador Ilie Sisu as
saying.
   During his visit to Iran that ended Wednesday, Ceausescu signed
a deal under which Iran would export 41 million barrels of oil and
1 billion cubic meters of natural gas a year to Romania.
   Ceausescu, 71, also visited the tomb of the late Ayatollah
Ruhollah Khomeini in a near-obligatory stop for foreign dignitaries.
   The Times of London reported Saturday that Iranian leaders had
difficulty persuading Ceausescu to visit the tomb at the Behesht
Zahra cemetery outside Tehran.
   Ettela'at criticized the large number of Ceausescu relatives he
installed in high places in the Romanian government. It also
blasted his role in facilitating contacts between former Egyptian
and Israeli leaders Anwar Sadat and Menachem Begin.
   ``Let us hope Ceausescu was the last falling star to come to the
Islamic Republic for his last meal,'' the newspaper wrote.
   ``Let us respect the will of the people of Romania. The
inopportune visit to Tehran by Ceausescu may be made good by
saluting the struggle of the Romanian people.''
   The daily, generally considered pro-government and supportive of
the private sector, said an Iranian student was among the hundreds
of demonstrators killed in the western Romanian city of Timisoara
while Ceausescu was in Tehran.
   Romania is Iran's second-biggest trading partner in Eastern
Europe, with the volume of trade estimated at about $1.8 billion.
The new agreements, if they remain in place, would boost that to $3
billion a year.
</TEXT>

</DOC>