<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0235EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AIDSTests     12-22 0575</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AIDS Tests,0593</SECOND>
<HEAD>Study: Some Labs Issue Confusing, Wrong Results to AIDS Tests</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-AIDS-Discriminaton, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SARAH NORDGREN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Laboratories that conduct AIDS tests should
double-check their results and report them clearly to doctors, say
researchers who got incorrect or confusing AIDS reports from six of
13 labs.
   The researchers also suggested that criteria be developed to
help labs lessen the number of ``indeterminate'' results, so they
can say with more certainty whether a person carries the AIDS virus.
   The report, in today's Journal of the American Medical
Association, was based on tests on blood samples sent to 13 labs,
all but two of them in California.
   Dr. Abram Benenson of the San Diego State University School of
Public Health said in a telephone interview Thursday that
laboratories frequently return their results to doctors and
hospitals with ``so much gibberish on the report that it hides and
obscures the data.''
   He and his colleagues urged supplemental tests and standardized
criteria to ensure positive results.
   In the summer 1988, the researchers provided medical facilities
with specimens that carried the human immunodeficiency virus, which
causes AIDS.
   The hospitals, clinics and one doctor's office that got them
were asked to submit the samples to the laboratories they generally
use for AIDS tests. The laboratories weren't told the samples were
part of a study.
   The medical facilities were all in San Diego County while some
of the laboratories were elsewhere in California and in two other
states.
   Benenson said that most laboratories first test for the virus
using an enzyme immunoassay, or EIA, test. If that test is
positive, they repeat it.
   If the second test is also positive, labs often then use another
test _ frequently one called the Western blot _ to verify the
results.
   The problem with the Western blot test, Benenson said, is that
it has had inconsistent criteria which made a positive
determination ``a matter of interpretation.''
   Of the 13 labs reporting back in the study, all reported
positive results to the EIA test on the sample that did in fact
carry the AIDS virus.
   But at the next stage, in which the positive result is verified
by a second kind of test, the labs didn't fare as well, the study
said.
   Eleven used Western blot testing to back up the EIA results. Of
those, five reported the specimen was positive, five reported
indeterminate results, and one lab returned the raw results to the
physician and told him to do his own interpretation, the study said.
   One of the labs didn't do a confirming test, and one used an
immunofluorescence test to correctly confirm the positive result.
   The researchers said some of the labs gave ``excessive and
potentially confusing information'' when reporting back. Some of
the language was so confusing it would be difficult for a physician
to know if the test was positive or negative, the authors said.
   One lab said a positive result ``is not diagnostic of AIDS, only
of possible risk-exposure.''
   ``So far as we know, if you have a positive seriological test,
you have the virus and you are capable of transmitting the
infection,'' Benenson said, adding that labs may use obscure
language ``to try to be kind and not frighten the patient.''
   In an accompanying editorial in the journal, two doctors at the
federal Centers for Disease Control in Atlanta said they
``enthusiastically endorse'' the study's recommendations for clear,
concise laboratory results.
</TEXT>

</DOC>