<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0136 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1442EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-Panama-Military 2ndLd-Writethru a0560 12-22 0827</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Military, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0560,800</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Troops to Patrol With Panamanian Police</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Top 7 grafs with joint patrols proposed; picks up at pvs 4th
graf, Gen. Colin</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSANNE M. SCHAFER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Military Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   American military leaders today called on
Panamanian police to join with them in restoring order in the
beleagured country, urging officers once loyal to Gen. Manuel
Antonio Noriega to return to work for the new government.
   Lt. Gen. Tom Kelly said he hoped local police would work side by
side with U.S. military police. ``The primary endeavor of the
movement is to clear Panama City and assist the government in
restoring law and order,'' he said.
   Kelly, director of operations for the Joint Chiefs of Staff,
spoke at a Pentagon briefing at which he also said it might take
five to 10 days for the U.S. troops to restore aide and raised the
possibility that even more American troops might be sent to Panama.
   The comments by Kelly and others suggested that what U.S.
officials repeatedly have referred to as a ``mopping up'' operation
was far from over.
   In an interview Thursday, Defense Secretary Dick Cheney said the
Bush administration intends to maintain a signficant military
presence in Panama to restore a ``condition of normalcy,'' even if
some U.S. troops are withdrawn relatively quickly after this week's
massive strike.
   Cheney said U.S. troops in Panama City were ``not trying to hold
every street corner. ... We're moving to areas where there
continues to be resistance or where there is a need for presence.
   ``We're not attempting to occupy the entire city because we
don't have that many troops down there,'' he said.
   Gen. Colin Powell, chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, said
the principal goal for the U.S. military forces ``is to restore a
semblance of civic order. I still think we're in the mopping-up
phase with respect to resistance'' from forces loyal to deposed
dictator Manuel Antonio Noriega, he said.
   Cheney acknowledged that U.S. troops were still involved in
``conflict and firefights'' in Panama City well into the second day
of the American intervention.
   As of this morning, the U.S. military casualty count stood at 20
killed in action, 202 wounded and two missing. In addition, two
civilian American women were reported killed. The Pentagon said 122
members of the Panamanian Defense Forces were killed and 45 were
wounded.
   Cheney said the operation was ``enormously successful'' during
its first 36 hours, even though Noriega had eluded capture. Both
the defense secretary and Powell appeared somewhat weary but spent
more than 30 minutes answering reporters' questions.
   President Bush said U.S. troops would pursue Noriega ``as long
as it takes'' and said the nation's commitment to the operation in
Panama was ``open-ended.''
   Neither the secretary nor the four-star general would provide
any details of the manhunt for Noriega, except to say they believed
he still was in Panama. U.S. officials have offered a $1 million
bounty for the deposed leader.
   Powell said that while there still appeared to be resistance by
Noriega loyalists in Panama City ``for the most part it is
disorganized resistance ... it will dry up over time.'' The
four-star general said he did not believe the resistance was
``under the direction of a central command.''
   The defense secretary pledged to get U.S. forces in Panama home
``as quickly as we can,'' but he also said the date would stay open
as long as Noriega remained at large and civil unrest continued.
   The secretary said that over time, as the government of
Guillermo Endara demonstrates it ``is there to stay ... all the
violence will cease ... and we'll get back to a condition of
normalcy.''
   The secretary noted that the 9,500 military personnel sent into
Panama was a supplemental force to the 13,000 who are permanently
based there.
   ``When we went in, we did not know precisely how long we would
have to stay and we still don't know that,'' Cheney said, noting
that the U.S. military has a right to be in the country under the
Panama Canal treaties.
   ``So even after we bring out those forces that were sent in ...
there will still be a significant military presence in Panama,'' he
said.
   Cheney acknowledged the possibility of individual terrorist
strikes and the taking of U.S. hostages.
   ``Clearly, we haven't resolved all the potential situations
where there may be Americans being held,'' Cheney said. ``We are
aggressively working every one of those cases.''
   Both men argued that nabbing Noriega was not the primary
objective of the mission _ the nation's largest military endeavor
since the Vietnam War.
   ``Our purpose was not to snatch Noriega. Our purpose was to
safeguard American lives, safeguard American interests under the
(Panama Canal) treaty, help restore democracy in Panama,'' Cheney
said, adding, ``We'd love to get Mr. Noriega. We're going to
continue to work on that and we may in fact be able to do that,
too.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>