<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1527EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AIDSBabies-Quilts     12-23 0556</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-AIDS Babies-Quilts,0574</SECOND>
<HEAD>Quilters Wrap AIDS Babies in Handmade Love</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FRANK BAKER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NORTHWOOD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At an age when many people are slowing
down to enjoy their golden years, 70-year-old Ellen Ahlgren is busy
heading an international drive to help babies afflicted with AIDS.
   Ahlgren runs an organization called ABC Quilts _ AIDS Baby Crib
Quilts _ whose members make and distribute small quilts to babies
with acquired immune deficiency syndrome. So far, they've made
nearly 1,300.
   ``When you can't do anything, it's depressing,'' she said.
``When you can, it's a very good feeling.
   In 18 months, ABC Quilts has grown from a contingent known as
``Ellen's Elves,'' who worked out of her living room, to a network
of hundreds of quilters in 44 states and several countries,
including Japan, Australia and England. The project is supported
solely through donations.
   The quilters use original patterns and designs, and each quilt
has a patch that reads ``Love and comfort to you'' and has the name
and city of its maker.
   Most are sent to Ahlgren's home which has become a sort of
command center, with maps, tables and papers, not to mention
quilts, cluttering the living room waiting for distribution.
   ``Every day is like Christmas here,'' Ahlgren said in a recent
interview. ``There's always boxes being opened.''
   Ahlgren contacts hospitals across the country to see where
quilts are wanted and sends them off to places like New York City,
Chicago, Philadelphia, Houston and Washington, D.C.
   Those cities are a far cry from Ahlgren's rural home, located
about 60 miles north of Boston in a town with 2,400 residents. From
her kitchen is a view of a snowy field and thick woods.
   It's a much different setting from the impoverished and
depressing surroundings where many of the AIDS babies live.
   ``A baby's a baby no matter where they're sick,'' she said.
   Though she realizes the babies she is helping probably won't
live long, it doesn't discourage her.
   ``This (project) taps into a tremendous energy of love,
compassion, generosity. It raises the awareness of people and helps
them learn about this horrible epidemic.... It's not just
statistics.''
   Ahlgren, a mental health counselor who worked at a hospice
before retiring, launched the quilt project after reading an
article about AIDS babies.
   ``I had made about 20 quilts for my own family and had seen how
much they enjoyed them, so I put two and two together,'' said
Ahlgren, who has five children and nine grandchildren.
   Ahlgren said she and some of her relatives and quilting friends
made fliers outlining the project and asking for help. They posted
them in various towns in New Hampshire and Massachusetts. Then an
article about the fledgling group appeared in a national quilting
magazine.
   ``I had been on vacation and when I returned, there were 360
letters waiting for me,'' she said.
   Since then, nearly 1,300 quilts have been made and distributed.
Ahlgren's goal is to pass out 10,000 by 1991, a number that would
equal the projected number of AIDS babies.
   Ahlgren likes to tell a story about a 2-year-old AIDS baby from
Philadelphia. Nurses said all the infant did for most of the day
was cry _ until they gave him an ABC Quilt.
   ``He reached out and hugged it and went to sleep,'' Ahlgren
said, smiling.
</TEXT>

</DOC>