<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0212 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1840EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-OilPrices     12-28 0462</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Oil Prices,0484</SECOND>
<HEAD>Energy Futures Decline</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Energy futures prices, which had risen sharply
in recent days, dropped Thursday amid profit-taking and higher
deposit requirements imposed by the New York Mercantile Exchange.
   January heating oil, which has led the recent price jump, fell
3.31 cents to 96.40 cents a gallon on the exchange after surging
7.23 cents Wednesday. The February contract rose 0.28 cent to 74.17
cents a gallon, while contracts for later delivery fell between
0.54 cent and 1.43 cents.
   Meanwhile, wholesale unleaded gasoline for January delivery lost
0.74 cent to close at 60.11 cents a gallon and West Texas
Intermediate, the U.S. key grade of crude oil, dropped 28 cents to
$21.50 cents a barrel.
   Analysts said selling activity began at the opening bell after
Wednesday's late announcement by the New York Merc that it was
raising margin, or deposit, requirements for customers.
   At the start of trading Thursday, cash deposits for spot heating
oil and unleaded gasoline contracts, rose from $4,000 to $7,000 per
contract, said Nacamah Jacobovits, spokeswoman for the exchange.
   Those requirements will go up to $10,000 starting Friday and to
$15,000 on Tuesday, the next regular trading day after the New
Year's Day holiday.
   ``To raise the money, many investors have to liquidate their
contracts,'' Ms. Jacobovits said.
   Energy analysts said the new requirements began forcing out the
weaker players in the market.
   ``It put a big damp towel on the market and got rid of the
phonies _ the people that don't belong there,'' said Kevin Breslin,
analyst with United Energy Inc.
   Heating oil and gasoline contracts comprise 42,000 gallons each.
   Analysts said profit-taking also contributed to the price
erosion after the recent steady rise in futures prices.
   Heating oil had soared more than 40 percent in the the last two
weeks _ from 70.42 cents a gallon on Dec. 15 for the January
contract to 99.71 cents on Wednesday.
   Analysts said in addition to the margin requirements, new
imports may help to dampen prices in coming days, which would be
good news for consumers.
   About 30 cargos, or 270 million gallons, of heating oil are
headed for the United States from Europe, said Sal Gilbertie,
assistant vice president and energy analyst with Elders Futures Inc.
   ``When prices rose sharply everyone with spare heating oil in
Europe began shipping to the U.S.,'' he said.
   Record-setting cold temperatures across the nation in the last
two weeks raised the demand for heating oil, depleted already low
inventories and sent retail prices rocketing. In some states,
heating oil prices nearly doubled.
   Furthermore, frigid weather caused refinery problems in Texas
and Louisiana that delayed the shipment of crude oil to some areas.
   ``We hope to see retail prices stabilize over the next week,''
Gilbertie said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>