<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0086 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1559EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Virginia'sHouse 1stLd-Writethru a0567 12-23 0705</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Virginia's House, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0567,0720</SECOND>
<HEAD>Yes Virginia, Your Home Still Stands, But It's Gutted</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 13th graf, `The non-profit..., with 2 grafs to clarify
that five houses developed, six including Virginia's remain undeveloped.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY13</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LARRY NEUMEISTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The red-brick rowhouse is still standing where
little Virginia O'Hanlon lived, where she penned the letter nearly
a century ago that implored a newspaper editor to tell her the
truth: Does Santa Claus exist?
   But no one lives at 115 W. 95th St. anymore. And Santa Claus
would find no stockings hung by the chimney with care. He would
find boarded-up windows, a gutted interior and a flock of pigeons.
   In a neighborhood that has had hard times, only to rebound into
affluence _ in a city that cries out for housing _ the vacancy of
Virginia O'Hanlon's four-story house and five others on the street
has caused controversy.
   Virginia is all but forgotten in the dispute.
   But at least one person remembers. Last Christmas, someone
pinned an unsigned Christmas card on the door, along with a
clipping from a newspaper that reprinted Virginia's letter and the
response.
   ``Please tell me the truth, is there a Santa Claus?'' Virginia
wrote. She was 8 years old, and some of her classmates were
skeptics.
   In an editorial published on Sept. 21, 1897, in the New York
Sun, Francis Pharcellus Church replied: ``Yes Virginia, there is a
Santa Claus.''
   ``He exists as certainly as love and generosity and devotion
exist ...,'' Church said. ``How dreary would be the world if there
were no Santa Claus. It would be as dreary as if there were no
Virginias.''
   Virginia O'Hanlon Douglas died on May 13, 1971. A decade
earlier, she had reaffirmed her belief in the Santa Claus spirit,
saying it ``stands for love and sharing, the joy of giving and the
extension of it to all people.''
   But at the time of her death, her childhood home already had
been vacant for about five years, recalls Jeanne L. Beatty,
president of the West 95th Street Development Corp., which holds
the house's title.
   And now Santa himself probably couldn't find Virginia's house _
the street numbers are missing. Chicken wire blocks the entrance.
   Someone has scrawled ``AIDS Housing Now'' in red on the door.
Not long ago, a human body was drawn on the sidewalk out front,
with the caption: ``Homeless people are freezing to death and this
building stands vacant.''
   The non-profit West 95th corporation developed five houses on
the street and was supposed to arrange the refurbishing and
development of six others, including Virginia's home, which was to
hold five families.
   But the corporation instead became involved in a legal snarl in
which the city and neighbors are trying to get back the houses,
claiming Ms. Beatty is holding the property until prices rise. She
says the legal battle has prevented her from refurbishing the
buildings.
   The fight has dragged on for more than a decade.
   ``For the last 10 years, the corporation has acted in a totally
illegal manner by having no board of directors, no bylaws, no
annual meetings, or any other kind of control beyond the one-woman
control of Jeanne Beatty,'' lawyer and neighbor Lawrence J. Gross
charged in a letter to the state attorney general's office.
   He estimated the six buildings, once worth about $20,000 apiece,
could now bring several million dollars.
   But Ms. Beatty says she's no Scrooge.
   ``My money is sitting there and has been carrying all of this.
I'm the one who's been going through all the stress. It has impeded
my health and career. It's been bleeding me, frankly. The money I'd
been making in real estate is gone,'' she said.
   Ms. Beatty said the buildings must be totally refurbished except
for walls and ceilings.
   Much has changed since Virginia wrote her letter, but Ms. Beatty
insisted the Christmas spirit lives on West 95th Street.
   ``It's in mourning really,'' she said. ``Perhaps I should put a
wreath on the door this year. We hope in 1990 it will be occupied
and lights on again in the window and laughter and cheer for the
next holiday. And carolers can stop by.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>