<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0128 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1845EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Colombia     12-28 0621</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia,0639</SECOND>
<HEAD>Authorities Capture Members of Drug Trafficking Clan</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STAN YARBRO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police were holding eight reputed
members of a notorious Colombian drug ring on Thursday to determine
if they should be extradited to the United States, a police
official said.
   Miguel Gomez Padilla, the national police chief, said the men
belong to the so-called ``Ochoa clan'' and would be held until
authorities could establish whether they were wanted in the United
States on drug trafficking charges.
   Gomez Padilla said there were apparently no outstanding charges
against the men in Colombia.
   He added that all were close relatives of Jorge Luis
Ochoa-Vasquez, Juan David Ochoa-Vasquez and Fabio Ochoa-Vasquez,
the three brothers considered central figures in the powerful
Medellin cocaine cartel. The three are on a list of 12 top drug
traffickers wanted by the United States.
   An anti-narcotics police unit captured the suspects in a raid on
a ranch Wednesday about 125 miles north of Bogota. They were
brought to this capital city.
   Gomez Padilla said authorities were searching intensely for
Pablo Emilio Escobar-Gaviria, the reputed leader of the Medellin
cartel and the most wanted man in Colombia. But he stressed that
the manhunt was part of a general battle against the drug
traffickers.
   ``We are not obsessed with the capture of one or two bandits,''
the police chief told reporters at a news conference on Wednesday.
   Gomez Padilla said that the government's drug crackdown would be
reinforced by the installation of a new government in neighboring
Panama.
   The Colombian press, echoing charges by the U.S. government, has
repeatedly said the country's former dictator, Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noriega, was an important ally of the drug cartels.
   It is charged that Noriega allowed the Colombian cartels to
import cocaine processing chemicals from Panama, to launder drug
money in the country and to use it as a transfer point for cocaine
deliveries to the United States.
   Colombian security forces have seized 31 tons of cocaine this
year, and in the last four months the administration of President
Virgilio Barco has extradited 11 drug suspects to the United States.
   Gomez Padilla said the immediate objective of the government
campaign was to destroy the traffickers' terrorist and paramilitary
organizations.
   Officials have said that the groups are responsible for the 260
terrorist attacks that have killed 209 people since the government
declared war on the traffickers in August.
   The government scored its biggest victory in the struggle when
police shot and killed Jose Gonzalo Rodriguez-Gacha, 42, a Medellin
cartel leader, in a Dec. 15 gunfight on Colombia's northern coast.
   The police chief said that groups of criminals formerly owing
their allegiance to Rodriguez-Gacha had begun to disband as a
result of his death.
   In the last two weeks, police have found the bodies of 22 people
suspected of formerly working for Rodriguez-Gacha, and riots in two
Bogota jails have resulted in the death of 12 prisoners also linked
to the Medellin cartel.
   Officials have blamed the violence on traffickers and other
gangsters battling for control of the slain drug lord's vast
criminal enterprise, which generates billions of dollars each year.
   On Wednesday, a White House spokesman said the Pentagon was
studying a naval and air blockade of Colombia, particularly along
Colombia's Caribbean coast, to cut the flow of cocaine reaching the
United States.
   But the U.S. Embassy here said in a statement Thursday that it
``never has considered a blockade of Colombia'' and that a proposed
anti-drug operation would be conducted in international waters
without affecting legitimate shipping interests.
   The report caused outrage among many Colombians, who think their
country's battle against drug traffickers since the August slaying
of a leading presidential candidate has helped the United States.
</TEXT>

</DOC>