<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0209EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-CarBook     12-22 0663</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Car Book,670</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Automakers See Competitive Edge in Safety</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DENISE CABRERA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   American automakers, inspired by consumer
demand for safer cars, are trying to regain the competitive edge by
offering more safety features than imports, says the head of a
private consumer group.
   That change is reflected by an increase in the number of
American cars among the highest rated in the 1990 edition of ``The
Car Book,'' an annual car buying guide, said Jack Gillis, exectuive
director of the Center for Auto Safety and principal author of the
book.
   ``We are seeing a marked improvement in the overall quality and
safety of cars being offered to the American consumer,'' said
Gillis in a telephone interview following release of the book
Thursday.
   ``The reason is because more and more consumers are considering
safety in the purchase of a new car and because the automobile
represents one of the most potentially dangerous products that we
will purchase,'' Gillis said.
   ``Most of the cars tested very well. There were very few poor
performers,'' added Gillis, explaining crash test information is
not available for many of the vehicles.
   Gillis said the government hasn't crash tested them because
requirements for automatic crash protection standards _ safety
belts, air bags or other mechanisms _ are new with 1990 cars.
   The guide also rated cars on their performance in five other
categories _ fuel economy, repair costs, warranties, insurance
costs and complaint history.
   Gillis gave more weight to crash safety than to other rating
components. However, since that information was limited Gillis'
guide names only automobiles in various size categories that were
``best'' in the overall rating.
   Gillis said U.S. carmakers are taking back the competitive
advantage they lost in the late 1970s when Japanese auto
manufacturers built more safety into their small cars.
   ``Now we see the pendulum swing the other way and the U.S.
carmakers ... are gaining a strong safety competitve advantage over
the Japanese because of the widespread offering of air bags,'' said
Gillis.
   The tenth edition of the guide, first produced in 1981 for the
government but now published as a private venture, also offers a
list of cars which include air bags as a standard or optional
feature.
   The Center for Auto Safety is an non-profit consumer group
established in 1970 to improve vehicle quality and highway safety.
   The group's book offers a best and worst list of 1990 minivans
because those vehicles, which don't have to meet the same safety
standards as cars, have been crash tested.
   The best overall rated 1990 cars and minivans include 13
American, 4 Japanese and one German cars.
   But he said the distinctions may soon disappear as more cars are
jointly produced by manufacturers.
   According to Gillis, here are the best overall rated 1990 cars
by size category:
   _ Subcompact: Toyota Corolla, Mercury Tracer, Volkswagen Golf,
Pontiac LeMans, Ford Escort. Only the 1989 Mercury Tracer is
offered for sale until introduction of the 1991 model.
   _ Compact: Pontiac Grand AM 2-door, Buick Skylark 2-door, Toyota
Camry, Oldsmobile Cutlass Calais 2-door.
   _ Intermediate: Oldsmobile Cutlass Ciera, Oldsmobile Cutlass
Supreme, Buick Regal.
   _ Large: Pontiac Bonneville, Mazda 929, Cadillac Eldorado.
   _ The book lists the best minivans as the Plymouth Voyager,
Mitsubishi Van and Dodge Caravan. The worst includes the Ford
Aerostar, Volkswagen Vanagon, Chevrolet Astro and Toyota Van.
   A companion guide, ``The Used Car Book'' names the 30 best and
worst older autos based on a complaint index devised by Gillis. The
index is based on the ratio of the number of complaints received by
the government from carowners to the number of cars sold.
   The government figures show four cars _ three Japanese and one
American _ had no complaints.
   Copies of ``The Car Book,'' published Harper &amp; Row, may be
obtained at bookstores or by writing to the Center for Auto Safety,
2001 S St. NW, Washington, D.C. 20009. The cost of $10.50 includes
postage and handling.
</TEXT>

</DOC>