<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0138 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1432EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Panama-Grenada     12-20 0749</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Grenada,710</SECOND>
<HEAD>Operations Superficially Similar, but Really Very Different</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-US-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RUTH SINAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Then as now, the invasion was launched in the
pre-dawn hours. Then as now, the declared goal was to protect
American citizens.
   But the similarities between the American landing on the
Caribbean island of Grenada on Oct. 25, 1983 _ the last time U.S.
troops were sent on an invasion _ and Wednesday's American
intervention in Panama are mostly superficial.
   Both were described as pre-emptive operations, but logistically
and strategically they are largely different.
   The invasion of Grenada, spearheaded by 1,900 Marines and Army
Rangers, was undertaken with the stated purpose of protecting the
lives of more than 600 American medical students from a Marxist
government that had taken the island's government by force Oct. 19.
   President Bush, too, said he had ordered U.S. troops into Panama
to protect the lives of Americans, this time an estimated 35,000,
many of them soldiers.
   The presidential statements justifying the invasions was similar.
   Said Reagan in 1983:
   ``The United States' objectives are clear: to protect our own
citizens, to facilitate the evacuation of those who want to leave,
and to help in the restoration of democratic institutions in
Grenada.''
   Said Bush on Wednesday:
   ``The Panamanian people want democracy, peace, and the chance
for a better life in dignity and freedom. The people of the United
States seek only to support them in pursuit of these noble goals.''
   In Panama, U.S. forces were under orders to capture Manuel
Antonio Noriega, the country's ruler who is under indictment in
Florida on drug-trafficking charges.
   While both presidents said they were acting to restore
democratic governments, the Grenada operation had broader regional
implications.
   Reagan had grown increasingly concerned since 1981 about what he
perceived as a Cuban and Soviet military buildup on Grenada.
   The U.S. invasion was lent legitimacy by a request from six tiny
eastern Caribbean nations for U.S. help to stop the military
buildup, which they believed could endanger their democratic
governments.
   Indeed, the U.S. force was accompanied by 300 police officers
and defense forces from four of Grenada's Caribbean neighbors.
   Although plans for both operations were long in the making _ the
Grenada invasion replicated a 1981 exercise _ the landing on
Grenada was much more of a surprise to the world. Many people
didn't even know how to pronounce the name of the nutmeg-producing
island and its new leader, Bernard Coard, while years of U.S.
clashes with the defiant and provocative Noriega have become almost
legend.
   The surprise six years ago was compounded by a lack of
information about the operation in Grenada because of a complete
Defense Department news blackout. Reporters were given access to
the island only on the fifth day.
   The fighting in Panama was closely covered from the start by the
resident news corps and, hours after the fighting began, by a pool
of U.S. reporters flown there by the Pentagon.
   In Panama, the U.S. invasion was supported and prepared by some
13,000 troops already stationed at American bases there. In
Grenada, there were no U.S. military personnel on hand before the
invasion.
   ``The logistics of getting there were much harder,'' said
Langhorne A. Motley, who served as assistant secretary of state for
inter-American affairs at the time of the Grenada invasion.
   The handkerchief-size Grenada _ 8 by 18 miles with a population
of less than 100,000 _ was a less complicated target than Panama,
with its 30,000 square miles and population of 2.3 million.
   ``Panama is a much messier place to operate, with Americans
scattered around the country'' and a professional, U.S.-trained
military, Motley said.
   In Grenada, the U.S. force _ which at the height of the invasion
numbered about 7,000 _ encountered a military force of several
thousand Soviet-armed troops, aided by about 600 armed Cubans there
to construct a 9,500-foot airport runway that the United States
said had no civilian use.
   Nineteen Americans were killed in Grenada, several of them in
accidents, as well as 24 Grenadans, most of them when U.S. planes
mistakenly bombed a mental hospital. Also killed were 24 Cubans.
   The actual fighting for control of the island lasted about 36
hours, said Otto Reich, a diplomat who headed the State Department
campaign to enlist public support for the Grenada operation. U.S.
troops stayed about seven weeks to defend the interim government
and clean up pockets of Cuban resistance.
   ``But there was no real urban warfare, unlike Panama,'' said
Reich.
</TEXT>

</DOC>