<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1011EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Romania 3rdLd-Writethru a0484 12-25 1146</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0484,1171</SECOND>
<HEAD>More Scattered Fighting; 80,000 Reported Dead</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 17 grafs to UPDATE with details of Timisoara fighting,
man seized outside cathedral, transit returning, denial of high casualty
figure, pope's prayer, Picks up 15th graf, `Ceausescu, 71, ...'; SUBS grafs
22-24, `Romanians rejoiced ...' with 1 graf with journalist killed; DELETES
last 3 grafs.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DUSAN STOJANOVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The provisional government appealed
for a cease-fire today by pro-Ceausescu forces who killed thousands
in vicious weekend street battles. Christmas carols rang out for
the first time in 42 years.
   Scattered fighting was reported in Bucharest and other cities,
but public transit was back in operation in the capital three days
after hard-line Communist President Nicolae Ceausescu was
overthrown.
   There were reports that as many as 80,000 people had died and
300,000 were wounded since the popular revolt began Dec. 15.
Hungary's Budapest Radio and the British Broadcasting Corp.
reported the same figures Sunday night, quoting ``authoritative
sources in Bucharest'' but giving no details.
   The reports, like others on casualties, were impossible to
verify independently. But if accurate, the Romanian uprising would
be the bloodiest anti-Communist revolt ever, its death toll far
eclipsing that of the Hungarian revolution of 1956 in which about
30,000 people are believed to have lost their lives.
   Hungarian radio later quoted Victor Ciobanu, health minister
under Ceausescu and now in opposition to him, as denying that
70,000 or more had died but offering no overall casualty estimate.
   Ceausescu, who sternly ruled for 24 years and rejected the
reforms sweeping Eastern Europe, spent Christmas a prisoner of his
own army, awaiting trial for abuses of power.
   But members of the hated Securitate _ the security force
Ceausescu built to protect himself and his Stalinist regime _
fought for their lives in desperate street battles against the
army. Bodies piled up in Bucharest's morgues and hospitals.
   Four men believed to be Securitate agents were arrested by
Yugoslav police today after they crossed the Danube River that
forms the border between Yugoslavia and Romania, Belgrade radio
reported.
   While downtown Bucharest was generally quiet today, radio and
television reported fighting in the southwest suburb of Drumul
Taberei and around the Ministry of Defense building in the
capital's southeast. The reports gave no details on the clashes.
   Hungarian radio and Yugoslavia's Tanjug news agency also
reported fighting today in Timisoara, the western city where the
uprising began, as Ceausescu loyalists barricaded themselves inside
a militia building. Still, street cars and trolley buses resumed
service in Romania's fourth-largest city.
   Tanjug also reported serious fighting in Arad, near the
Hungarian border, and the central city of Sibiu, without giving
details. Sibiu was the former stronghold of Nicu Ceauescu, the son
of the deposed president.
   The National Salvation Committee, the provisional government,
appealed for a cease-fire, and ordered civilians to turn in their
arms today. It broadcast appeals to let the army fight the security
police, who were shooting from rooftops and apartment windows in
the capital and elsewhere.
   A member of the security police was arrested today outside
Bucharest's Mitropolia cathedral after members of a crowd shouted,
``We know this man, he's a terrorist!'' The man wore a bulletproof
vest and had a hand grenade.
   Radio Bucharest played Christmas songs and carols today, the
first time since the Communist takeover in December 1947, and it
reported on the positive foreign reaction to the uprising.
   In Rome, Pope John Paul II sought a special blessing for Romania
and prayed that the hope of Christmas may find fertile ground in
Eastern Europe, ``awakened from a nightmare.''
   A message from President Bush was read to the people over
Romanian radio and television, ``hoping for a peaceful passage to
democracy'' and deploring ``the tragic and senseless loss of human
lives'' since the revolt began.
   The Bush administration and the French government both said they
would not object if the Soviets or other Warsaw Pact nations use
their military forces to assist the uprising. The Soviets said such
a move was ``impermissible.''
   Thousands reportedly were massacred by security forces when they
opened fire on unarmed anti-government protesters in Timisoara on
Dec. 17. The revolt against Ceaucescu's harsh rule spread across
Romania and reached Bucharest Dec. 21, when student protesters
defied gunfire to chant their wish for freedom.
   Ceausescu, 71, fled his capital on Friday in a helicopter and
was captured Saturday with his wife, Elena, in an underground
bunker _ one of several prepared years earlier under his regime.
   Unlike his son, Nicu, and daughter, Zoia-Elena, who were paraded
before TV viewers after their arrests Friday and Sunday, Ceausescu
has not been seen since Ion Iliescu, a leader of the National
Salvation Committee, announced his arrest Saturday. The elder
Ceausescu was reported to be held at a military base.
   The National Salvation Committee pledged that the courts would
mete out punishments of ``the greatest severity'' to ``the dictator
and his former lackeys.''
   Romanian radio said secret police used scores of safe houses and
vast networks of tunnels in Bucharest and in Timisoara to store
weapons and launch attacks. Ceausescu's downtown palace was
connected to the maze of tunnels and contained a bunker designed to
resist nuclear attack, it said.
   At Bucharest's main Orthodox cathedral, Letitia Patrut mourned
the students who were killed by the security forces.
   ``These young people, how they sacrificed for us!'' she said.
``We must pray for these poor young people who defended the
people.''
   Security men who were driven from Parliament fired toward the
300-year-old Romanian Orthodox cathedral. ``They are devils,'' said
Bishop Nifon of Bucharest.
   A Belgian journalist, Danny Huwe of the commercial TV network
VTM, was killed in Bucharest while reporting on the fighting.
Turkish journalist Emre Aygen, was in grave condition today after
being shot twice shot in the head, VTM reported. A French
journalist was crushed to death by a tank Saturday.
   Associated Press correspondent John Daniszewski, New York Times
correspondent John Tagliabue and two European journalists were
wounded by gunfire in Timisoara late Saturday and early Sunday
before the security forces surrendered to army troops backing the
revolt.
   At Bucharest Emergency Hospital, doctors who have not slept in
three days said they had treated 2,000 civilians since Thursday, a
fraction of the city total.
   Bodies lay on the hospital's floors frozen in grotesque
positions, with identity papers taped to bare chests. Sobbing
people spent Christmas Eve looking for lost sons and brothers.
Victims included a pregnant woman and teen-agers.
   ``It is horrible murder,'' said Dr. Stephan Miliesescu, a
plastic surgeon who was working the emergency ward. He said victims
came in with single shots to the head from well-trained snipers.
   Doctors had to sedate and strap down one swarthy security guard,
who shouted that the revolt had upset Ceausescu's socialist
paradise. He yelled: ``You are criminals, and we will kill you
all!''
</TEXT>

</DOC>