<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0252 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0738EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Airlines-Antitrust     12-18 0296</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Airlines-Antitrust,0308</SECOND>
<HEAD>United, American Airlines Cleared of Reservation Monopoly Claims</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A U.S. District Court jury has found no
evidence to substantiate a claim that United Airlines and American
Airlines monopolized the airline reservation market by giving
travel agents underpriced computer systems.
   A federal jury ruled Friday against four airlines that asked for
damages totaling $149 million from United, which operates the
Apollo reservation system, and American, which runs the Sabre
system.
   The plaintiffs contended that travel agents bought the United
and American systems because the airlines undercut the actual
price, and that agents then were asked to sign exclusive contracts.
   ``The jury has confirmed what American has long maintained: that
the marketing of computer reservation systems to travel agents is
extremely competitive,'' Robert L. Crandall, American's chairman
and president, said in a statement.
   United Vice President Edward Hoenicke said that ``United's
position as to the fairness of its pricing for the Apollo service
and its contract and marketing practices have now been vindicated.''
   When the case began about five years ago, a number of airlines
were listed as plaintiffs, but their numbers were reduced by
mergers and out-of-court settlements.
   The remaining plaintiffs were Northwest Airlines, which was
suing American; and Alaska Airlines, Midway Airlines and Muse Air
Corp., which were suing United.
   Max Blecher, an attorney for the plaintiff airlines, attributed
the verdict to U.S. District Judge Edward Rafeedie's decision to
throw out fraud and racketeering claims.
   ``In the case the judge left us to try, we did not have our best
ammunition,'' Blecher said. ``We were not playing with our
strongest suit.''
   In January, Rafeedie is scheduled to preside over a separate
trial on similar claims against American and United, this time by
Continental Airlines and two other carriers.
</TEXT>

</DOC>