<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0222 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2021EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Panama-AirportHostages     12-20 0554</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Airport Hostages,500</SECOND>
<HEAD>Florida, Texas Women Freed By Soldiers' Bluff</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   EDITOR'S NOTE: The following dispatch is a pool filed by Robert
Kearns of Reuters and Steven Komarow of the Associated Press.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two American women were held hostage
at gunpoint in an airport terminal for more than six hours before
they were freed by U.S. soliders who bluffed the Panamanian captors
into believing that Gen. Manuel Noriega had been killed.
   Mary Rebhan, 24, of Hollywood, Fla., and Tara King, 25, of
Dallas, told reporters they were used as shields to buy time for a
group of Noriega loyalists who holed up in a sweltering customs
room at Omar Torrijos International Airport when American forces
moved in.
   ``They had us in choke holds for most of the time,'' said Rebhan.
   ``They made us kneel down and held guns to my back and to her
head,'' said King.
   The two women said they had gone to the airport Tuesday evening
to pick up Rebhan's brother, who was flying in for her wedding
ceremony at the end of the month.
   They were told his flight was delayed, and went outside to wait
in the car _ until about 12:30 a.m. Wednesday when the bombs
started to drop.
   Dashing inside the terminal, the women were accosted by a group
of about 30 armed men in civilian clothes. When it was revealed the
women were Americans, they were taken to a locked room.
   ``A guy named Sanchez was in charge,'' Rebhan said, adding that
two other men were addressed throughout the night as ``sarjinto,''
or sergeant, leading the women to believe they were members of the
Panamanian Defense Forces.
   American troops began to arrive in force to take over the
airport but the Panamanians held them off with the women.
   ``For six hours they made us keep shouting, `Go away. We're
Americans. They're going to kill us and the children if you
come,''' Rebhan said.
   Fake bombs were taped to their bodies. One was a plastic bag
stuffed with a pair of pants.
   King said their captors turned the lights off in the room to
confuse the Americans. Rebhan said Sanchez kept an Uzi machine gun
on her shoulder, pointed at the door.
   The woman, who were both raised in the canal zone, acted as
translators between the Americans and Panamanians.
   Just before dawn, the Americans set a deadline of 6:30 for the
men to surrender and told them they were surrounded and that Gen.
Noriega was already dead. In fact, Noriega's whereabouts were not
known.
   The Panamanians finally gave up, leaving the room with the women
held in front of them.
   ``They were really afraid. We could feel their hearts on our
backs as they held us,'' Rebhan said.
   But the women said they were at least equally frightened.
   ``We were terrified,'' King said. ``I thought I was going to
die.''
   Rebhan, speaking on the airport tarmac before hitching a ride
with a Pentagon press pool, said she was acting calmly because ``it
really hasn't hit me yet. I just really want to get home.''
   Rebhan, whose father is the chief mechanical engineer for the
Panama Canal, said she planned to hold a church ceremony in Panama
on Dec. 30. She was married to Jeff Rebhan in a civil ceremony in
Warren, Ohio.
</TEXT>

</DOC>