<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0178 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1819EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-UndercoverMom     12-22 0661</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Undercover Mom,0683</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mom Goes Undercover Against Drug Dealers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAIGE St. JOHN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TRAVERSE CITY, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It was the death of her 15-year-old
son that gave Wendy Stanek the will and guts to infiltrate the drug
menace corrupting Crystal Falls. But when she did, it hit closer to
home than she thought.
   The mother of six gathered enough evidence to bring cocaine and
marijuana trafficking charges against 23 people this week. Among
those arrested was a counselor at a group home for troubled youth.
   ``One of the guys I busted was my lifelong friend and he came to
me and I said, `Oh my God, I don't want to hear that,''' said
Stanek. Still, she turned him in.
   The 35-year-old woman, who made more than 20 drug buys during a
year of working for a narcotics team, added, ``I want people to
know they can do it. Anybody can do it.''
   The suspects were arraigned Tuesday in a marathon session in
Iron County District Court. Michigan State Police who headed the
sting declined to talk about Stanek's role in dealing with what
they say was a problem commonly known in the Upper Peninsula's
Crystal Falls and nearby Iron River.
   They said, however, that community support and tips are
important to their work.
   During the year she spent undercover, Stanek was amazed at how
easily cocaine flowed in Crystal Falls, an old-fashioned logging
town.
   A local health worker tried two years ago to start a drug
awareness group there. He was encouraged to stop. ``People just
didn't want to admit we had a problem,'' Jerry Schoup said.
   After Stanek made her first covert drug buy, dealers pestered
her with more offers than police could handle. ``It was a piece of
cake, in and out and just like buying groceries,'' she said.
   She was shocked at who was doing the selling _ friends and
childhood acquaintances.
   ``It's scum like you that sell it to the kids,'' Stanek said she
told a suspect who called her after Tuesday's arrests.
   The road that led Stanek to the Upper Peninsula Substance
Enforcement Team began with the death of her son, Ryan. He would
have turned 16 on June 30, 1987, but died days earlier, a passenger
in a car that crashed when a friend grabbed at the steering wheel.
   Tucked in a shoe of one of the passengers, Stanek said, she
found a marijuana pipe. Police filed no charges.
   The next day, Stanek began a log of the drug traffic she saw in
Crystal Falls. A year later, a friend in the Iron County sheriff's
department put her in touch with the newly formed UPSET. She began
the undercover buys.
   The biggest threat to the operation came from Stanek's own
children, who were unaware their mother was working undercover. Her
eldest son, 15-year-old Jamey, was upset at her consorting with
drug dealers.
   ``He said, `Keep your druggy buddies out of our house,''' Stanek
said. ``They were getting angry with me.''
   That and the suicide two weeks ago of one of Stanek's daughter's
friends ended the undercover work. The 14-year-old girl's death was
the second teen suicide in Crystal Falls this year. For Stanek, who
believes the community's drug problem plays a role in the suicides,
``it was just too much.''
   Stanek's kids now know about their mother, the drug buys and the
arrests.
   ``I feel good about what my mom did,'' 8-year-old Joey said.
   ``I think it's good because I know there's been a lot of drugs
going on around here for a long time,'' said Jared, 11. ``Some
people aren't happy because they think drugs are cool. ... I think
they're stupid.''
   And it makes his brother's death ``easier,'' he said.
   Stanek had two notable receptions to her work. One was a death
threat. ``Big deal,'' she said.
   The other was a box of chocolates delivered at her door. The
greeting said ``Thank you, Wendy, for saving our kids.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>