<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1343EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Fed-InterestRates Bjt   12-17 0696</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fed-Interest Rates, Bjt,700</SECOND>
<HEAD>Recession Fears to Prompt Cuts, Experts Say</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN CRUTSINGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Economics Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Policymakers at the Federal Reserve will move
to push interest rates lower, possibly as early as this week,
private economist say.
   The expected round of credit easing in response to evidence of a
weakening economy and moderating inflation would cause a variety of
business and consumer rates to fall, the economic forecasters say.
   Among the rates that could drop would be the prime rate and home
mortgage rates.
   The Federal Open Market Committee is meeting Monday and Tuesday
for its final strategy sessions of the year. Most analysts were
looking for the Fed to decide to reduce a key interest rate, the
federal funds rate, by another 0.25 percentage point.
   ``Fed officials have more than enough evidence to justify
another easing step before the end of the year,'' said David Jones,
chief economist of Aubrey G. Lanston &amp; Co. ``It will take
additional easing steps to guarantee that we don't go into a
recession. I think we will avoid a recession, but just barely.''
   Some analysts said the reduction could come before the week is
out while other analysts said the rate drop might not occur before
early January.
   The federal funds rate, the rate banks charge each other on
overnight loans, is the primary lever the central bank uses to
control short-term interest rates.
   When it does fall, economists were predicting that the benchmark
prime lending rate, to which one-third of all business and consumer
loans are tied, would be cut from 10.5 percent to 10 percent with
another cut to 9.5 percent expected before summer as the Fed eases
further.
   Analysts were looking for mortgage rates to drop as well in
response to the Fed's credit easing moves. Many predicted that
fixed-rate mortgages, which have already fallen to a national
average of 9.75 percent, could fall as low as 9.25 percent by next
summer.
   Jones and other economists point to various signs that the
economy is passing through a period of extreme sluggishness, with
unemployment beginning to inch back up, raising fears that some
unexpected shock could spell the end of a recovery that has already
lasted a peacetime record of seven years.
   When 1989 began, the central bank was in the midst of a
year-long effort to push interest rates higher in an effort to
dampen demand and keep inflationary pressures in check. However, in
May the Fed switched course and began a series of gradual easing
moves as signs mounted that economic growth was beginning to slow
in response to the earlier credit-tightening.
   Inflation has eased with the slowing of growth.
   On Friday, the government reported that wholesale prices fell in
November for the third time in the past five months, with the drop
led by a big decline in gasoline costs.
   ``Inflation has decelerated enough so that the central bank has
a margin of comfort to ease interest rates to boost economic
growth,'' said Allen Sinai, chief economist of the Boston Co.
   The Bush administration has complained that the central bank has
been too timid in its credit-loosening campaign and will have to
bear the blame if the economy does go into a nosedive.
   But the consensus among most economists is that the Fed's dose
of easy money has come in time to keep the country out of a
recession.
   Before the Fed began its gradual credit-easing moves, the
federal funds rate stood at 9.75 percent. It is now at 8.5 percent,
having been reduced in a series of five 0.25 percentage point drops.
   Jones said he expected the federal funds rate would fall to 7.75
percent before the Fed calls a halt to its easing campaign.
   But when the economy begins to rebound next summer, many
economists were looking for the Fed to reverse course once more and
begin tightening up on credit to guard against triggering higher
inflation.
   ``We think the economy will start accelerating in the second
half of next year and inflation will become a little worse as labor
costs begin to accelerate,'' said David Wyss, senior financial
economist at DRI-McGraw Hill, an economic consulting firm.
</TEXT>

</DOC>