<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0096 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1527EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-AmtrakAccident 1stLd-Writethru a0608 12-19 0395</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Amtrak Accident, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0608,0399</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Passenger Train, Truck Collide; At Least 3 Killed</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: UPDATES throughout with three dead, 17 critically hurt, fire,
details on fog. No pickup.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEVE GEISSINGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>STOCKTON, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Amtrak train carrying at least 144
passengers plowed into a tractor-trailer in dense fog, derailed and
exploded today, killing three people and critically injuring 17,
authorities reported.
   The engineer and fireman of the locomotive were killed when the
engine careened off the tracks, overturned and exploded, the
California Highway Patrol said. The CHP said the driver of the
truck was also killed.
   CHP spokesman Bob Whitmire said 54 passengers were injured. He
said 23 seriously injured people were taken by ambulance to
hospitals, and 31 others were taken by bus to hospitals for
examination and treatment of minor injuries.
   ``They still are fighting the fire in the engine,'' said Ron
Baldwin of the San Joaquin Office of Emergency Services. ``They had
a large fire in the engine itself and we're trying to get people
out of the train in case there is an explosion.
   ``One problem is we have heavy fog and we're not able to air
transport victims and it's making it a little more complex.''
   Amtrak spokesman Arthur Lloyd said the train was going about 70
mph when it hit the truck, which apparently had ``ignored the
lights and went right in front of the train.'' The train was en
route from Oakland to Bakersfield.
   ``Our information is that the road crossing is protected by
gates, bells and flashing lights,'' Amtrak spokeswoman Sue Martin
said at railroad heaquarters in Washington. ``We do not know why
the truck was on the tracks. We know the accident occurred id one car was
on its side.
   It was unknown whether tule fog _ an extremely dense wintertime
fog that has made San Joaquin Valley roads dangerous in recent days
_ was a factor. Visibility was zero at the time of the accident,
the National Weather Service said.
   Dense fog caused a 69-vehicle pileup near Tracy west of Stockton
Monday morning, and a series of accidents involved 55 vehicles
farther south in Merced County.
</TEXT>

</DOC>