<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0648EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     12-19 0585</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0602</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sleet, Snow Pelt Plains, Deep South</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Continued cold, sleet and snow slowed much of the nation today
and showed no signs of easing as another wall of Canadian air
churned through the Northern Plains toward the Northeast and
Midwest.
   The upper-level system was moving across the heartland to the
Great Lakes region today, dumping snow on parts of Iowa, Nebraska,
Missouri and Illinois. The center of the arctic air mass should
move into the Upper Midwest by late week, spawning even colder
weather.
   Advisories for freezing rain and sleet were posted today in
southeastern Arkansas, northern Louisiana and northern Mississippi.
   Up to 2 inches of snow were expected in northeastern Arkansas
today. Snowfall was expected to be heaviest in Illinois, where up
to 5 inches were forecast.
   Though winter doesn't officially begin until Thursday, ice has
already choked the Mississippi and Missouri rivers. Sleet iced
roads from Mississippi to the Carolinas on Monday.
   Storms with snow or freezing rain were forecast from Ohio and
western Pennsylvania through the Carolinas and across the South
into northeastern Texas.
   Snow also was expected in the northern Rockies. Wind gusts of up
to 60 mph were predicted today for southeastern Wyoming.
   Snow continued to fall across northern Maine.
   Snowfall for the six hours ending 7 p.m. EST Monday included 3
inches at Concordia and Topeka, Kan.; Kansas City, Mo.; and Omaha,
Neb.
   Record-breaking cold gripped 12 cities Monday, including
Youngstown, Ohio, at 12 degrees below zero; Pittsburgh's 7 below;
and Lexington, Ky., 1 below. The outlook for most of the country is
for below-average temperatures for the next month or so, according
to the National Weather Service.
   Florida remained the nation's only hot spot. Miami's forecast
today called for highs in the 80s.
   On Monday, three Florida cities set record highs for the date:
Ft. Lauderdale, with 87 degrees; Hollywood, 85; and Miami, 87,
which tied its highest-ever December reading.
   Monday's high temperature was 88 degrees at North Dade County
Airport near Miami, Fla.
   Other reports at 3 a.m. EST today:
   _EAST: Albany, N.Y., 3 fair; Atlanta 31 freezing rain; Boston 19
fair; Buffalo 10; Charleston, S.C., 32 rain; Chattanooga 34 rain;
Cincinnati 19 cloudy; Cleveland 8 cloudy; Detroit 11 cloudy;
Hatteras 38 cloudy; Jacksonville 42 drizzle; Key West 72 foggy;
Knoxville 31 freezing rain; Macon 33 rain; Miami 69 foggy; New York
22 fair; Philadelphia 14 fair; Pittsburgh 6 partly cloudy;
Portland, Maine, 8 fair; Richmond 22 cloudy; Tampa 62 foggy;
Washington, D.C., 16 fair.
   _CENTRAL: Birmingham 36 rain; Bismarck 30 fair; Chicago 12 snow;
Denver 4 fair; Des Moines 6 snow; Fort Worth 29; Indianapolis 17
snow; Kansas City 3 fair; Little Rock 28 freezing drizzle;
Louisville 21 snow; Memphis 30 rain; Nashville 31 freezing rain;
New Orleans 47 foggy; North Platte 16 fair; Oklahoma City 22 partly
cloudy; Omaha 3 fair; Rapid City 7 fair; St. Louis 16 snow;
Minneapolis-St. Paul 9 fair; Sault Ste. Marie 5 snow; San Antonio
40 foggy.
   _WEST: Albuquerque 31 fair; Anchorage 17 cloudy; Boise 23 fair;
Casper 8 fair; Fairbanks 10 fair; Great Falls 1 fair; Honolulu 74
fair; Las Vegas 35 fair; Los Angeles 56 partly cloudy; Medford 25
snow; Pendleton 28 foggy; Phoenix 48 fair; Portland, Ore., 33
cloudy; Reno 23 fair; Salt Lake City 20 fair; San Diego 58 cloudy;
San Francisco 48 fair; Seattle 38 drizzle; Spokane 25 cloudy.
   _INTERNATIONAL: Calgary 1 cloudy; Montreal 3 fair; Ottawa 5
snow; Regina 35 fair; Toronto 9 fair; Winnipeg 25 fair.
</TEXT>

</DOC>