<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0357EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Nicaragua-US     12-30 0474</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Nicaragua-US,0493</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nicaragua Expels 20 U.S. Diplomats In Retaliation For Panama Incident</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FILADELFO ALEMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANAGUA, Nicaragua (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Daniel Ortega ordered 20
American diplomats to leave the country in retaliation for a search
by U.S. troops of the Nicaraguan ambassador's residence in Panama.
   In a national radio broadcast late Friday, Ortega said he had
given the U.S. diplomats 72 hours to leave the country.
   He also said he had ordered the U.S. mission to reduce its
support staff from 320 people to 100. Many people who work at the
embassy are Nicaraguan nationals.
   A Nicaraguan government source said there were about 35
accredited U.S. diplomatic personnel in Nicaragua.
   Attempts to reach U.S. Embassy officials by telephone were not
immediately successful.
   Earlier Friday, Nicaraguan Ambassador Antenor Ferrey said U.S.
troops surrounded his residence, ordered all personnel to evacuate
and searched the premises for weapons. U.S. officials said they had
no information on the incident.
   ``They acted arrogantly, like Rambos!'' Ortega said. ``We were
at grave risk of a political-military clash with the United States,
which has maintained an aggressive attitude against Latin American
countries.''
   Ferrey said he and nine other people waited outside the
residence while about 30 American troops searched the building for
about two hours.
   The soldiers seized five rifles that Ferrey said were there for
self-defense. A U.S. Army colonel in charge of the operation later
apologized and returned the rifles, Ferrey said.
   Nicaraguan government sources, who insisted on anonymity, said
that Foreign Minister Miguel D'Escoto was conducting unspecified
``diplomatic contacts'' with U.S. charge d'affaires John Leonard,
the foreign ministers of Spain and Mexico, and Venezuelan President
Carlos Andres Perez.
   The sources said D'Escoto also contacted top officials at the
United Nations and the Organization of American States, but the
sources refused to give details concerning these contacts.
   Leonard is the top U.S. diplomat in Nicaragua.
   The United States has not had an ambassador to Managua since
July 1988, when the leftist Sandinista government expelled
Ambassador Richard Melton and seven other American diplomats to
protest alleged American interference in an opposition rally in the
city of Nandaime.
   The United States responded by expelling Nicaraguan Ambassador
Carlos Tunnerman.
   Diplomatic tensions between the two countries increased after
the Dec. 20 U.S. invasion of Panama and the overthrow of Gen.
Manuel Antonio Noriega. The Sandinistas placed the armed forces on
``maximum alert'' after the invasion.
   American troops surrounded the Nicaraguan, Cuban and Libyan
embassies in Panama City following speculation that pro-Noriega
loyalists had sought refuge in the missions.
   Nicaragua responded by briefly positioning military units around
the U.S. Embassy in Managua, then withdrew them.
   Earlier this week, the Sandinista government barred a State
Department plane from making its monthly supply run to the U.S.
Embassy in Managua. The aircraft normally carries mail, books and
supplies for the embassy Px.
</TEXT>

</DOC>