<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0197 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1443EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f BC-Japan-Businessman Adv02   12-28 0835</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Japan-Businessman, Adv 02,0859</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv02</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Tuesday Jan. 2</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sly Ad Asks Japanese Businessman: Can You Fight 24 Hours?</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID GROSS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   They are singing it, dancing it, acting it, even
chanting it: ``Yellow and black are the sign of courage. Can you
fight 24 hours? Businessman, businessman, Japanese businessman.''
   Japan has gone wild over this catchy theme song to a television
commercial for an energy-restoring health tonic called Regain.
   Whether seen as an ode to the Japanese businessman or as a
satire of his excesses, the Regain commercial has achieved a
popularity akin to Wendy's ``Where's the Beef'' in the United
States.
   Companies play it over loudspeakers. Businessmen sing it at
parties. Students dramatize it at culture festivals. Some Japanese
even use it get out of bed every morning.
   Sankyo Co., the drink manufacturer and Japan's No. 2 drug maker,
says that since the song was first broadcast in May his office has
received 10 to 20 inquiries per day from people anxious to learn
the lyrics.
   The companies that have called Sankyo read like a list from a
Who's Who of the Tokyo Fortune 500: Nissan Motor Co., Nippon Life
Insurance Co., Shiseido Co., Nippon Telegraph and Telephone Corp.,
Recruit Corp., Mitsui Toatsu Chemicals Inc., Mitsubishi Electric
Corp., Japan Airlines and many others.
   Not only companies, but also the Economic Planning Agency, a
police station and a city government office have requested copies
of the song, Sankyo says.
   Even students at prestigious Nada High School, perhaps
anticipating the day when they too will join the ranks of Japan's
business elite, dramatized the song at a school fest.
   The commercial features the swarthy young television star Saburo
Tokito as a businessman stalking deals in foreign lands, keeping
his strength up with the tonic drink.
   In one version, Tokito is rowed through the canals of Venice to
a ship. He climbs a rope ladder while belting out the song and is
greeted on deck by executives waiting for him to sign a contract.
They explode in applause, confetti and clicking cameras. Before the
shot pans to the tonic bottle with its yellow-and-black label,
there is a glimpse of a newspaper headline in English: ``Japanese
Businessman Pulls it Off.''
   A group of engineers at the Hitachi VLSI Device Development
Center used three weeks of their overtime and weekends to adapt the
Regain tune for a company song contest. In their version,
businessmen wielding attache cases dance their way through crowded
train stations and sexy barmaids _ while singing about the trials
of being a Hitachi businessman.
   Why all the fuss?
   Yukichi Amano, a well-known advertising critic, says the
self-lampooning in the commercial has found a very receptive
audience.
   ``Singing in loud voices with one's comrades this obviously
unrealistic, parodying, comic song fits the taste of today's
Japanese,'' he says, citing the absurdity of the song's call to
work 24 hours a day.
   Tokito's robot-like singing and expressionless face when kissed
by a South Pacific beauty in one version of the commercial are jabs
at the stereotypical overserious, overworked Japanese businessman,
Amano says.
   ``That Japan has become the richest country in the world does
not make Japanese truly happy. They love expressing their cynicism,
even self-scorn.''
   Jun Moriwaki, who was Regain's commercial planner, says the ad
was not originally designed to mock the businessman.
   ``We thought of it from the start as a pep song, that if you
drink (Regain) you'd feel energetic again.''
   Moriwaki says he and associates at Dentsu Inc., Japan's biggest
advertising firm, were looking to create a new image of the
businessman, a new ``Japanese hero.''
   ``There's a pattern to the Japanese who appear in Hollywood
movies: with thick glasses and cameras hanging from their
shoulders. We wanted to start off from there. If Tokito is the
Japanese businessman, when he is with foreigners he would not
cower; he would stand equal to them. To go one step further, he
might even look down at them.''
   To the 29-year-old Moriwaki, the image of the Japanese
businessman who never takes a break has always been depressing:
even when he goes home he is ignored by his wife who pays more
attention to the kids. But Moriwaki says his peers, who are now
filling the work force and at whom he is aiming the commercial, are
different.
   ``When we work, we work very hard and don't care about going
without sleep to do our work. But when we rest, we insist on taking
our vacations. The younger the person is, the better he is able to
divide his life that way. These people just enjoy the commercial as
a kind of joke.''
   Some Japanese do not seem to have gotten the punch line, however.
   Shortly after the song appeared, the Labor Ministry made an
informal protest to Sankyo. Ministry officials wanted to make sure
the sponsors of the commercial were not obstructing government
efforts to get Japanese to work less hard.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End adv for Tuesday Jan. 2.</NOTE>

</DOC>