<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0208 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1932EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Korea 1stLd-Writethru a0720 12-20 0604</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Korea, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0720,0619</SECOND>
<HEAD>South Korean Legislator Convicted of Spying for North</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to RECAST. Picks up 4th, `The defense ..
.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By C.W. LIM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A legislator was convicted Wednesday
of spying for communist North Korea and sentenced to 15 years in
prison.
   Judge Hong Suk-je dismissed Rep. Suh Kyung-won's claims he was
tortured to make false confessions that he was a spy for South
Korea's archenemy.
   ``It was hard to find evidence to support the claims of torture,
considering the confessions signed by the defendant during an
interrogation by prosecutors,'' Hong said.
   The sentence had been expected to be heavier, but the judge said
the breakdown of the Cold War was taken into consideration.
   The defense counsel criticized the verdict as improper and said
the ruling would be appealed. The prosecution, which had sought
life imprisonment for Suh, also said it would appeal. The maximum
penalty for espionage is death.
   Suh had told the court that during a 50-day investigation by the
Agency for National Security Planning, the government intelligence
organization, he was forced to make false confessions that he had
spied for North Korea.
   He said he had been denied contact with lawyers during the
period and kept awake for many days. Government officials denied
the charges.
   Also Wednesday, riot police firing tear gas stormed a university
campus in Seoul to break up a rally by hundreds of students
demanding the release of Im Chong-suk, a jailed radical student
leader.
   About 700 students throwing firebombs and rocks fought police
for two hours in and around Yonsei University in the third day of
campus protests. Several students were taken away by police, but no
figures were available on arrests or injuries.
   Im was chairman of the National Council of Student
Representatives, a nationwide anti-government, anti-U.S.
organization.
   The spy case was generally considered the most serious in recent
South Korean history because it involved a national lawmaker with
ongoing contact with communist North Korea. Suh admitted he visited
North Korea but denied he was a spy.
   Suh, a farmer-turned politician, was convicted of espionage and
``leaking state secrets'' to North Korea.
   The judge said overwhelming evidence indicated Suh, 52, secretly
visited North Korean leader Kim Il Sung last year, received
$120,000 from communist agents and had ongoing contact and
communications with the communist nation, all in violation of the
National Security Law.
   The judge also ordered Suh to forfeit $49,000 in unspent funds,
allegedly from North Korea.
   The judge, in handing down the sentence, said, ``It was taken
into consideration that international trends have turned from the
Cold War era to an atmosphere of reconciliation since his (Suh's)
visit to the North and the Seoul government has been pursuing an
active Northern policy'' aimed at easing tensions.
   He said the state secrets leaked by Suh to North Korea were not
sensitive but said Suh contacted North Korea before his 1988
election to the National Assembly, as well as after.
   After Suh's arrest June 28, a dozen lawmakers, businessmen and
aides were questioned or jailed by national security agents.
   Two-time presidential candidate Kim Dae-jung, leader of the
leading opposition Party for Peace and Democracy, was indicted for
allegedly failing to report Suh's visit to North Korea. Kim denied
it and Suh was expelled from the party.
   Suh's aide, Pang Yang-kyun, was convicted of being an accessory
Wednesday and sentenced to seven years in prison. Six others were
given suspended sentences ranging from 10 months to one year for
failing to report Suh's trip to North Korea, as is required by law.
</TEXT>

</DOC>