<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0643EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-Vatican     12-26 0483</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Vatican,0499</SECOND>
<HEAD>Vatican: Violence In Panama Should End After Noreiga Sought Asylum</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VICTOR L. SIMPSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VATICAN CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Vatican avoided a quick decision on what
to do with Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega but said fighting in Panama
would likely end now that the ousted strongman has taken refuge in
its embassy in Panama City.
   In the Vatican's first official statement since Noriega sought
refuge in the embassy on Sunday, spokesman Joaquin Navarro said
Monday that the ``concerned parties'' would examine Noriega's case.
   Navarro said one of the parties was the government of Guillermo
Endara, installed after the U.S. forces invaded. He declined to
elaborate on the others.
   He said it was premature to say whether Noriega would be turned
over to the United States, where he is wanted on drug charges, or
given passage to another country, although reports from Panama
mentioned the possibility of Noriega going to Spain or Cuba.
   In Madrid, Spanish Foreign Minister Francisco Fernandez Ordonez
was quoted as saying Monday that asylum for Noriega was the
exclusive problem of the Vatican, the United States and the new
Panamanian government.
   In comments to EFE, Spain's national news agency, Fernandez
Ordonez was quoted as saying, ``Spain is not the ideal country to
accept Noriega because of its extradition agreement with the United
States, which includes drug trafficking (cases).''
   Navarro was asked by Italian state TV, if a ``simple'' turnover
of Noriega to the United States was foreseeable.
   ``Well, I don't think so,'' said Navarro. ``There isn't an
extradition treaty or anything.''
   Earlier, another Vatican official said he doubted the Vatican
would hand Noriega over directly to the government of an invading
army and suggested the Vatican could hand him over to the new
Panamanian government on condition of a fair trial.
   The Vatican depicted the situation as an opportunity to bring
peace to the Central American country and indicated it knew of
Noriega's position before he showed up Sunday afternoon.
   ``I can announce with satisfaction that the conflict in Panama
seems to be nearing a solution without further shedding of blood,''
Navarro said in a four-paragraph statement. ``And this is good news
for Christmas Day.''
   ``Concerning the situation of Gen. Noriega in particular, I can
confirm that at this moment he is in the Apostolic Nunciature in
Panama City, after having expressed the will to end the conflict.''
   Asked about any negotiations or discussions preceeding Noriega's
arrival at the embassy, Navarro declined to respond.
   There have been previous cases of people seeking refuge at
Vatican embassies, including Endara. The embassy in Panama
sheltered him for a month after he was beaten by Noriega's soldiers.
   Navarro said Pope John Paul II was informed of the Noriega case
Sunday evening before going to St. Peter's Basilica to say
Christmas midnight Mass. The pope made no direct mention of Panama
in his Christmas address.
</TEXT>

</DOC>