<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0095 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1651EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-KangarooCourt     12-23 0567</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Kangaroo Court,0589</SECOND>
<HEAD>Justice Swift in Kangaroo Court; Citizens Taking Control</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CANDICE HUGHES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Justice was swift in a kangaroo court
on the streets of Panama City on Saturday. Time elapsed from arrest
to trial to release: 30 minutes.
   The streets of the beleaguered capital had calmed somewhat by
Saturday, four days after the U.S. invasion unleashed a frenzy of
looting.
   There was little left to take by the weekend, and the level of
gunfire had dimmed to sporadic exchanges in most of the city.
   The balance appeared to have tilted in many areas in favor of
the armed citizen patrols barricading their neighborhoods with
everything from exercise bikes and toilet bowls to overturned
trucks and concrete blocks.
   ``Where are the gringos? Where are the MPs? Where are the
police?'' demanded a man helping guard a supermarket, where steel
bars staved off looters.
   ``We know this invasion was necessary,'' he said. ``But Panama
has been looted because they are not around. They have not made any
effort to protect decent citizens.''
   He and his neighbors, armed with everything from pistols to
double-barreled shotguns, had been guarding Punta Paitilla, a
middle-class area, for days. Nerves were on edge.
   They were letting shoppers enter the market in groups of five.
Hundreds of people stood in the hot sun waiting their turn at the
dwindling stock.
   Suddenly, a group of vigilantes came down the street herding
four prisoners _ suspected looters stopped at a barricade nearby.
   The men were put face down on the pavement and searched. Their
hands were tied behind their backs with shoelaces and belts as a
crowd gathered.
   The mood was ugly.
   ``Shut your mouth!'' a gray-haired man shouted as one of the
prisoners tried to speak.
   ``Look at the fat one!'' another man cried. ``He's trembling!''
   One of vigilantes began kicking the man in the head.
   ``Stop it!'' people shouted, rushing to pull the vigilante back.
Another self-appointed cop fired his pistol into the air. Things
calmed down.
   ``I know this man,'' one bystander said, coming forward. ``He's
no thief.''
   The captors moved their prisoners to a curb, sat them down and
began to question them as others came forward to vouch for the man
or question the vigilantes about the ``arrest.''
   A spontaneous ``court'' was in session.
   The man who had been kicked showed his identity cards.
   He was Felix Suarez, a 52-year-old minibus operator with a
contract to transport employees of Fort Clayton, one of the U.S.
bases near the city. He also held a permit for the .32-caliber
pistol he had been packing.
   ``This is a mistake,'' Suarez said. ``It's a bad mistake.''
   The vigilantes admitted the gun was what sparked their
suspicions. Suarez and his companions, all more poorly dressed than
most in the crowd, had not been caught in the act of looting.
   ``We're going to let them go,'' someone declared, and people in
the crowd nodded their approval. ``There is no proof they did
anything wrong.''
   As Suarez and his companions were untied, a doctor who asked
that his name not be used watched his neighbors thoughtfully.
   ``We are trying to impose some order here,'' he said. ``So far,
people have not done savage things. But we don't have anywhere to
send them (prisoners). We don't have any police. Someday we'll have
to say: let's eliminate them.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>