<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 1738EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-GasExplosion     12-31 0317</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gas Explosion,0326</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gas Explosion Rips Through Downtown Block</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A gas explosion rattled the financial
district Sunday, injuring at least four people, shattering windows
and sending glass and debris flying through a one-block area,
authorities said.
   The blast happened about 11:30 a.m., one block from the site of
last mon\h9s fatal crane collapse, police said.
   One of the injured refused treatment and left the scene, said
Assistant Fire Chief"Bill Shaughnesy. Others were treated by
ambulance crews. It could not immediately be determined whether any
victims were taken to the hospital, but all the injuries were
minor, Shaughnesy said.
   Traffic was rerouted around the area, which is bordered by
Chinatown and the financial district, police said. At least 10
buildings were damaged.
   Most businesses along the block were closed at the time. At
least two of the injured were sitting in cars when they were struck
by flying glass, Shaughnesy said.
   ``It was such an explosion that a lot of the evidence is gone
right now. When we arrived, it looked like a bomb had hit here. If
it had happened during a workday, I'm sure there would have been
some serious personal injured,'' Shaughnesy said.
   Officials had no estimate as yet of the monetary damage caused
by the blast, he said.
   Police and fire officials said the explosion was being
investigated, and Pacific Gas &amp; Electric Co. crews were on the
scene trying to determine if the blast occurred inside one of the
buildings or if it was underground.
   One of the buildings near the blast was buckled along the ground
floor, a scene reminiscent of dozens of buildings that collapsed in
the Oct. 17 earthquake that ripped Northern California and killed
67 people.
   Five people were crushed to death on Nov. 28 when a 240-ton
crane toppled from a highrise under construction and crashed to the
ground one block away.
  
</TEXT>

</DOC>