<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0032EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Names     12-27 0740</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Names,0765</SECOND>
<HEAD>Names in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY14</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Columnist Art Buchwald came up with an
original idea when he proposed a movie based on the comic
adventures of an African king in America, says the co-creator of
the old TV series ``Barney Miller.''
   Buchwald is suing Paramount Pictures Corp. for $5 million,
alleging the 1988 Eddie Murphy hit ``Coming to America'' was based
on an idea he optioned to the studio in 1983.
   Paramount's attorney, Robert Draper, has contended that Buchwald
failed to live up to his contract with Paramount because his idea
was not original _ that it was based on a Charlie Chaplin movie
called ``A King in New York.''
   But ``Barney Miller'' co-creator Danny Arnold disagreed. ``I
cannot remember a particular work or motion picture about an
African king transposed into a situation in America,'' he testified
Tuesday in the Superior Court trial.
   The Chaplin movie was about a European king who is kicked out of
his own country and tries to sell atomic energy ideas to U.S.
officials.
   Arnold, called as an expert witness for Buchwald, also testified
that the elusive show business term ``based upon'' refers to the
beginning of an idea. But under cross-examination, he said: ``There
is no industry standard for `based upon.' It's a purely subjective
determination.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BEVERLY HILLS, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor Willem Dafoe said he was
attracted to the role in the new film ``Triumph of the Spirit'' in
much the way he was drawn to his roles in ``Platoon'' and ``The
Last Temptation of Christ.''
   ``They're so unusual,'' said Dafoe, who is picky about parts he
will play. ``They're so huge. They raise so many interesting
questions that you don't quite know what it is before you start
working on it.''
   Dafoe, whose acting career took off two years ago after the
movie ``Platoon,'' is back in the spotlight again with his new film.
   In ``Triumph of the Spirit,'' Dafoe portrays a boxer who fights
for his survival after he is imprisoned at a Nazi death camp with
his family. The critically acclaimed film is based on the life of
Salamo Arouch, a Greek Jew and middleweight boxing champion who was
sent to Auschwitz.
   ``I think I'm attracted to roles that are kind of mythic and
have some size and, you know, are full of possibility,'' he said of
his penchant for playing unforgettable screen characters.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>MERIDIAN, Miss. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. Rep. G.V. ``Sonny'' Montgomery said
he was thankful for the chance to dine with the first family on
Christmas Day at Camp David and didn't even mind being put on the
spot by the president's request that he give the Christmas blessing.
   ``It was a good Christmas,'' said Montgomery, a Democrat. ``I
was honored. That was really something.''
   Along with the traditional meal of turkey and dressing, sweet
potatoes topped with marshmallows and green beans, Montgomery said
guests were given the choice of pumpkin or pecan pie for dessert.
   ``The meal was terrific, the entire day was very well done.
Everyone was definitely in the Christmas spirit,'' he said Tuesday.
   President Bush recently extended the Christmas invitation to the
single Mississippi congressman.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Civil rights leader Hosea Williams, who has
organized a Christmas dinner for the homeless and hungry for 19
years, is hospitalized with bronchitis and pneumonia, but plans to
get back into action soon.
   ``I'm feeling much better, and I hope to be release in a few
days,'' Williams said Tuesday in a telephone interview from his
room at Emory Hospital.
   Williams, 64, said his annual Christmas and Thanksgiving feasts
since 1970 combined have fed nearly half a million people at a cost
of nearly $1 million, and used 65,000 volunteers.
   ``This was our 19th year, and I'd say we fed a total of about
35,000 at the Christmas dinner, counting the deliveries to sick and
old people at their homes,'' he said. ``You watch these families
eating, and you realize, if they didn't eat here, where would they
eat? They'd just go to bed hungry.''
   Williams said the program has expanded so much that he is going
to turn it into a year-round operation.
   ``I've a job, a real obligation to feed the hungry _ they're the
fastest growing population in Atlanta, even more so than the
homeless. A lot of people have homes, they live here, but they have
nothing to eat,'' said Williams.
</TEXT>

</DOC>