<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0655EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ChristmasCharity     12-25 0404</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Christmas Charity,0421</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fire Tragedy Turns One Town into a Gift-Giving Community</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MONROVIA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A fire that left two families and six
children homeless has brought this community together in a spirit
of Christmas giving.
   The outpouring of generosity began after police Officer Ruben
Gonzalez saw a little girl crying after her family's home was
destroyed by fire Saturday night. No one was injured in the fire.
   The officer took up a collection at work so the girl and five
other children _ members of two related families sharing the home _
would have presents to unwrap when they awoke Christmas morning.
   Gonzalez said he was amazed as fellow officers dug into their
pockets and pulled out as much as $30 to $50 each.
   ``I didn't realize people would be so giving,'' he said Sunday.
   It didn't stop with the officers. After the 56-officer police
force raised $500, the Monrovia Police Association matched it.
   Word spread across Monrovia, a city of 33,500 residents about 20
miles northeast of downtown Los Angeles.
   Gonzalez, on a lunch break at a coffee shop, was greeted by
people with wads of money.
   ``The waitresses had heard about the situation and all the
employees and some patrons started dropping money on the table,''
he said.
   A bike shop provided a bicycle and a grocery store kicked in
with a turkey dinner and $200 in food certificates, police Sgt.
Donald Lacher said.
   A local Christmas tree lot gave the family a tree and the police
officers stripped the station of all ornaments to decorate it.
   And Gonzalez said a man who was passing the home as it was on
fire left a motor home there for the family to use.
   ``He stopped and tried to help and he asked if anything can be
done,'' Gonzalez said. ``The motor home is still there, he just
left it for them. I sure would like to know who he is.''
   Officers were planning on delivering the gifts today.
   After the tree was delivered Sunday afternoon, 14-year-old
Robert Fuentes said that the Velasquez and Fuentes families
appreciated all the police had done for them.
   ``They've been a big help,'' Fuentes said.
   He said the families were very frightened after the fire, but
were doing better.
   ``Everybody has calmed down right now,'' he said. ``As long as
none of the kids got hurt, we don't care so much about the material
things.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>