<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0917EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-PanamanianReax     12-20 0405</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panamanian Reax,0419</SECOND>
<HEAD>Noriega Opponents Hope For Democracy; Supporters Urge Resistance</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALINA GUERRERO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Opposition politicians said they
hoped the U.S. invasion of Panama would bring democracy to the
country, but supporters of Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega called it
``genocide against Panama.''
   The U.S. decision to ``remove the obstacle of the dictatorship
was serious news, but we grasp it with hope,'' said Ricardo Arias
Calderon, who was sworn in as first vice president shortly after
the U.S. effort began.
   Arias, who spoke on the radio, was a vice presidential candidate
in the May 7 elections that were voided when results showed Noriega
opponents winning.
   Guillermo Endara was sworn in as president, and Guillermo Ford
was sworn in as vice president along with Arias.
   ``Tomorrow we will have the opportunity to celebrate the era of
democracy with justice and freedom,'' Endara said. He urged the
Noriega's Defense Forces, ``Don't resist, accept instead the peace
that they offer.''
   Ford said the military action ``grieves us because it involves
mourning and pain, but we pray to God that it will be the new
awakening of this nation we love so much.''
   Arias said he hoped ``with this action we can achieve the
Panamanian objectives, among them to immediately establish
democracy with full respect for the will of the people.''
   Noriega's Democratic Revolutionary Party held an emergency
meeting at an undisclosed site, said the government national radio,
broadcasting as the national resistance network.
   Carlos Duque, Noriega's presidential candidate in the May 7
elections, called on all ``nationalist parties'' to join in the
struggle.
   ``The United States has just committed the biggest error and is
going to pay for that,'' he said.
   Rigoberto Paredes, another party leader, called the U.S. action
an ``infamous invasion.'' He asked Latin American countries to tell
the United States ``to stop this genocide against Panama.''
   ``We are not going to surrender,'' he said.
   Not all those outraged by the invasion were Noriega backers.
   A woman in Diablo, just south of the U.S. Army base at Fort
Clayton, said: ``This is humiliating. I feel completely impotent.
My blood is boiling.'' She said she does not support Noriega but
also does not support the idea of a U.S. invasion.
   As she spoke, U.S. trucks passed on a nearby road and fighting
raged near Defense Forces headquarters.
   ``They are not going to enjoy it,'' she said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>