<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0130 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1544EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Albania     12-29 0602</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Albania,0622</SECOND>
<HEAD>Last Hard-Line Eastern European Country Protests Comment on Human
Rights</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PHILIP DOPOULOS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATHENS, Greece (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Albania, the last bastion of Stalinism in
Eastern Europe, has protested criticism of its human rights
policies by the Greek foreign minister, Greece said Friday.
   An official statement said the Greek charge d'affaires was
summoned Thursday to the Foreign Ministry in Tirana, the Albanian
capital, to explain why Foreign Minister Antonis Samaras had made
the statement.
   Samaras commented Monday, saying with the fall of Romanian
dictator Nicolae Ceausescu, all nations should recognize the time
had come for dialogue and human rights.
   ``And in the same way that Christmas is being celebrated in
Romania today, I hope that soon we will be able to see the Greek
Christian minority, the Greeks of Albania, celebrating Christmas in
Albania,'' he said.
   The remarks by Samaras, a member of the conservative New
Democracy Party, were criticized by Greece's socialists and
Communists who also support the government.
   Greece in 1987 ended a technical state of war with neighboring
Albania that had lingered from World War II.
   The Orthodox Church of Greece sharply attacked the decision at
the time by describing it as an ``abandonment of our Christian
brothers.''
   Ethnic Greeks are banned from speaking Greek and practicing
their religion in Albania, a hard-line Communist country of 3
million people that has shut itself off from the outside years for
most of the postwar years.
   Samaras, a member of the conservative New Democracy Party, said
later that ``no Greek wishes it to remain the last unprotected
minority in a Europe (that stands) for human rights.''
   The Orthodox Church of Greece claims 400,000 Greeks live in the
tiny, rugged country on Greece's northwestern frontier. But Albania
says the number of ethnic Greeks do not exceed 60,000.
   With the fall of hard-line Communist governments in Poland,
Hungary, East Germany, Czechoslovakia, Bulgaria and now Romania,
rumors spread through the Balkans that some unrest was noted in
Albania. But Tirana denied that any demonstrations against its rule
had taken place.
   Albanian Embassy officials in Athens were evasive when asked to
discuss the situation in their country.
   One Greek Foreign Ministry official, who spoke on condition of
anonymity, said Greece's embassy in Tirana has reported nothing
unusual going on.
   Sources in northwestern Greece said security on the Albanian
side of the border remains tight with no noticeable change in the
past week. One main road was open for trucks carrying goods between
the two countries.
   Analysts who closely follow events in the isolated Communist
state said they had received no reports of unrest and it appeared
unlikely that the hard-line government of President Ramiz Alia
would be affected by what has occurred in Eastern Europe.
   Alia took power fie years ago following the death of longtime
dictator Enver Hoxha, who broke relations with the Soviet Union in
1961 because of Nikita S. Khrushchev's dismantling of Stalinism.
Museums and monuments in Tirana honor Hoxha amid the shabby
apartment blocks he left behind.
   Secret police check Albanians' contacts with foreigners.
   Albania has accepted only about 10,000 tourists a year, and
diplomats have said that Albanian officials are petrified that
affluent Westerners might raise discontent among the poorest people
in the continent. Thousands of households, lacking any other source
of heat, burn dung and garbage.
   An announcement in Paris earlier this week by a group of
Albanian refugee associations criticized the international
community's inattention to rights abuses in Albania.
   ``From purge to purge,'' it said, ``all of Albania has become a
veritable prison camp, and basic human rights have been violated
since 1945.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>