<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0248 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2231EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-EC-EFTA     12-19 0474</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EC-EFTA,0490</SECOND>
<HEAD>EC and EFTA Lay Groundwork for European Economic Space</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTINA MACKENZIE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRUSSELS, Belgium (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The 19 European Community and seven
European Free Trade Association nations agreed Tuesday to begin
talks early next year on closer economic cooperation aimed at
forging a so-called European Economic Space.
   The idea is to allow free movement of trade, capital, people and
services between the two trade blocs, said officials at a meeting
here of the EC and EFTA foreign ministers.
   The 12 EC nations are to remove their internal borders by late
1992. This project has sparked fears among the seven EFTA nations
that the single market will occur at the expense of trade with them.
   Jon Baldvin Hannibalsson, the foreign minister of Iceland, which
currently holds the EFTA presidency, said he was ``immensely
satisfied'' with the outcome of Tuesday's meeting.
   He said the EFTA nations _ Austria, Iceland, Finland, Norway,
Sweden, Switzerland and Liechtenstein _ hoped the talks could start
in early 1990 and be concluded by the end of the year.
   But EC External Relations Commissioner Frans Andriessen was more
cautious, saying the talks must end before Dec. 31, 1992, the date
by which the EC is to complete its single-market project.
   The EC's two-way trade with EFTA, $217 billion, is only slightly
less than its combined two-way trade with the United States and
Japan, which amounts to $230 billion.
   Andriessen said the ministers singled out problems to be solved
in the negotiations for closer economic ties between EFTA and the
EC. The most important is the institutional aspect of the new
EC-EFTA relationship.
   He said each side ``should respect the autonomy'' of its own
decision-making and that this was ``not negotiable'' for the EC. At
best, he said, he could see ``a kind of osmosis'' between the two
blocs' decision-making institutions.
   Hannibalsson said each bloc would continue to monitor compliance
with its own laws after the two sides have expanded their economic
cooperation, creating what officials term a ``European Economic
Space.''
   The foreign ministers also agreed to widen cooperation among the
19 nations in such areas as research and development, the
environment, education, working conditions and social welfare,
consumer protection, programs for small and medium-sized
enterprises and tourism.
   Some cooperation in these areas has already begun. The 1990
European Year of Tourism, for example, is a joint EC-EFTA effort.
   Separately, the EC and EFTA nations signed an agreement under
which they will exchange information on compulsory technical
regulations. This accord takes effect July 1, 1990, and is designed
to prevent obstacles to trade arising from differences in national
technical standards.
   The ministers also signed an agreement to allow universities and
industries in EFTA and EC nations to develop partnerships, exchange
students and staff and take part in joint training projects. This
agreement comes into force Jan. 1.
</TEXT>

</DOC>