<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0227 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0756EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Gillette     12-21 0401</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Gillette,0416</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gillette Announces It Will Acquire Part of Wilkinson Razors</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gillette Co. is helping finance a buyout of
Swedish Match, and in return it will get part of the Wilkinson
blade and razor line.
   Gillette said Wednesday it was joining a group of investors and
a management group of Swedish Match to buy the match, disposable
lighter and Wilkinson blade and razor lines from Stora of Sweden,
the parent company of Swedish Match.
   As part of the deal, Gillette will acquire Swedish Match's
Wilkinson blade and razor business outside of Europe, which totaled
about $30 million in sales last year, said Gillette spokesman David
Fausch.
   Gillette also will gain a 22.9 percent non-voting interest in
the newly created Netherlands company, Swedish Match BV, which
would retain the European business of Wilkinson as well as the
worldwide match and lighter business of Swedish Match.
   Gillette is investing $155 millon in the deal, which includes
$72 million for Wilkinson's non-European business, $14 million for
the interest in Swedish Match BV, plus $69 million to help finance
the debt for the transaction.
   Gillette said a ``significant'' part of the transaction was
completed Wednesday, and the deal was expected to be completed
early next year. The total price paid by all participants for the
Swedish Match operations is about $600 million.
   While Gillette is gaining a share of the new company, ``the
primary interest is in the non-European Wilkinson blade business,''
Fausch said.
   ``Wilkinson has a very good brand name,'' he said. ``There's a
lot of potential there.''
   Gillette controls about 60 percent of the world razor market,
but Fausch said Wilkinson has a strong presence in certain
countries, such as Brazil with 8 percent and Australia with 17
percent.
   Fausch acknowledged that Wilkinson represents ``a direct head-on
competition with Trac II,'' a Gillette brand, but he said the
company foresees no complications by the acquisition.
   Wednesday's announcement came less than a week after Gillette,
based in Boston, said it was streamlining its operations and
cutting about 750 workers from its payroll. But Fausch said the
purchase of part of Wilkinson's business fits with Gillette's plans.
   ``Blades and razors are a core business for this company,'' he
said. ``This is just a reaffirmation of our core business markets.''
   The transaction is not expected to have a material effect on
Gillette earnings per share in 1989 and 1990, the company said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>