<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0187 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1703EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Campeau     12-27 0532</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Campeau,0554</SECOND>
<HEAD>Manufacturers Watching Campeau Closely</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CINCINNATI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Manufacturers who supply merchandise to
Campeau Corp.'s department stores continued to watch Wednesday for
clues whether the retail operations would file for bankruptcy
protection.
   In the meantime, many of the clothing makers and other companies
that do business with the stores have stopped shipments or
postponed decisions about future shipments amid worries about
Campeau's solvency.
   Toronto-based Campeau's nearly 260 department stores around the
United States are continuing to sell and stock goods but executives
at some of the stores said this week that they have noticed
shipment disruptions.
   Campeau announced three weeks ago that its Cincinnati-based
retail divisions, Federated Department Stores Inc. and Allied
Stores Corp., might seek protection from creditors in bankruptcy
court early next year.
   ``It's now a game of Russian roulette,'' said Alan Millstein,
publisher of the Fashion Network Report. ``The spigot's been turned
off on Seventh Avenue,'' he said referring to the New York garment
district where many apparel companies have their headquarters.
   ``The only way to turn it back on is some sort of resolution of
the current situation,'' he said.
   Merchandise credit companies and several clothing makers
announced before Christmas that they had suspended business with
Federated and Allied as a result of Campeau's financial problems.
   Federated and Allied warned in a quarterly financial statement
in mid-December that they might seek bankruptcy protection as early
as next month if $6.9 billion in debt can't be restructured. The
debt was created as part of Campeau's acquisition of the department
store chains.
   Among Campeau's chains are Bloomingdale's, Burdines, Rich's,
Abraham &amp; Straus, Lazarus and others.
   Donald Van Suilichem, senior vice president and director of
marketing at Atlanta-based Rich's, said there have been some
limited interruptions in shipments.
   ``We expect there will be some more. But at this point, it's
been really negligible,'' he said.
   One of Rich's vendors, New York-based Greif Cos., said it won't
make any shipments until the financial health of Rich's parent
becomes clearer.
   Greif supplies men's suits and sport coats under the Polo
University Club and Perry Ellis labels.
   ``They're hanging and waiting to go out,'' said Norman Fryman,
Greif's president and chief executive officer. He said Greif
already has manufactured hundreds of thousands of dollars worth of
goods for Rich's and other Campeau units.
   Campeau's suppliers are concerned about their prospects if a
filing under Chapter 11 of the bankruptcy code ensues.
   ``What I see happening, and what is going to make me angry along
with all (the) other customers owed money, is a Chapter 11 just
before they have to pay their debts,'' said Bud Konheim, president
of Nicole Miller Ltd., a dress maker. ``The perfect time is just
prior to Jan. 10.''
   The Jan. 10 date is when payment is due for the goods suppliers
shipped to Campeau in late November and December.
   Campeau announced Friday that Citibank had informed Campeau that
it might technically be in default on a loan agreement because it
cannot provide assurance about its solvency. Citibank, which is
Campeau's major lender, could call for full repayment on the $2.34
billion in loans it made for acquisition financing if Campeau can't
remedy the situation by Dec. 31.
</TEXT>

</DOC>