<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0098 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1904EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ExxonExplosion 1stLd-Writethru a0581 12-25 0704</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Exxon Explosion, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0581,0721</SECOND>
<HEAD>Probe Begins Following La. Refinery Explosion That Burned 15 Hours</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf, `One contract ...' with one graf and INSERTS
2 grafs after 11th graf, `The worker ...' to UPDATE with one Exxon worker
missing, details on death of contract worker.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BATON ROUGE, La. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Investigators on Monday slogged through
firefighting foam and charred remains of storage tanks damaged in a
deadly explosion and fire at the nation's second largest
petrochemical refinery.
   The intense blaze at the Exxon refinery burned for 15 hours
before it was extinguished at 5 a.m. Monday, said company spokesman
Dave Gardner.
   One contract worker died Sunday when his pickup caught fire in
the explosion. Crews searched Monday for an Exxon employee missing
following the blast, Gardner said.
   Flames engulfed eight storage tanks holding more than 4 million
gallons of oil and lubricants, and two separator units, which
remove water from oil, officials said.
   It was believed to have been ignited by a gas release, but what
caused the release was under investigation, said plant Manager Ed
Galante.
   ``A maintenance work center, a building that was in the area
that used to be a small office satellite complex, was destroyed,''
Gardner said. ``Luckily there was nobody in there.''
   Production was halted at the refinery, which has a capacity of
455,000 barrels _ more than 19 million gallons _ of crude oil a
day. Exxon spokesman Ron Embry said he did not know whether that
would worsen any shortages of home heating oil during the nation's
record-setting cold snap.
   ``Generally, the limit to fuel oil seems to be due to
transportation problems in bad weather, and not supplies,'' Embry
said.
   Two investigative teams have been assembled, one to determine
the cause of the accident and another to assess the damage and
decide what's necessary to get the plant back in operation, Gardner
said.
   ``It will take some time and some effort. At this point, it's
almost impossible to say how much,'' he said.
   The worker killed in the blast was identified as mechanic Harold
Guillory, 31, of Irwinville, an employee for contractor Vernon
McKenny Enterprise, Gardner said.
   Guillory died when his pickup truck caught fire 100 to 200 feet
from the explosion, Gardner said.
   The missing Exxon worker was not identified and no other
information about his disappearance was released. His family has
been notified, Gardner said.
   Three Exxon employees and four contract workers were treated for
injuries at Baton Rouge hospitals and released Sunday, Gardner said.
   ``Numerous employees had cuts and bruises but didn't go to
hospitals,'' Galante said.
   A skeleton crew was on duty because of the Christmas holiday, he
said.
   The blast shattered windows up to six miles away and was felt up
to 15 miles away. The fire sent a plume of thick, black smoke 500
feet into the air.
   Gov. Buddy Roemer called out 50 National Guardsmen overnight to
prevent looting of stores where plate-glass windows were blown out.
Initial reports said looters hit some stores, but police Lt. Willie
Stevens said Monday that there had been no arrests.
   The refinery, on the Mississippi River in North Baton Rouge, has
been on the site since 1909.
   Petroleum inspectors David Abshire and Wiley Aymond said they
were 300 feet from the tanks when they exploded.
   ``The explosion caved in the whole side of the building,''
Abshire said. ``We would have been worse off if we were inside
because of the all the flying glass.
   ``When I looked up, I saw the sky full of stuff, pieces of wood,
insulation, just a sky full of stuff,'' he said. ``I was in a daze
and was just running in circles, looking for some place to get away
from it all, and there was no place to go.''
   The blast temporarily knocked out electricity and telephone
service in the area and forced the closure of a section of nearby
Interstate 110 for the night.
   State Department of Environmental Quality workers monitored air
outside the plant, but Roemer said the burning chemicals were all
non-toxic hydrocarbons: propane, ethane and diesel fuels. An area
around the area was closed to incoming traffic for a time, but no
evacuations were ordered.
</TEXT>

</DOC>