<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0093 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1318EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthAfrica     12-29 0406</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa,0414</SECOND>
<HEAD>Anti-Apartheid Alliance Says Victory in Reach in 1990s</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID CRARY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The country's main
anti-apartheid alliance said Friday it was entering 1990 with
confidence that ``victory for democracy is in sight.''
   The United Democratic Front and the Mass Democratic Movement,
two overlapping coalitions of opposition groups, said in a New
Year's message that government efforts at repression during the
1980s had failed quell black resistance.
   ``Despite a determined state assault on progressive people's
organizations, the state of emergency (imposed in 1986) failed
miserably in its desire to submit us further to the will of the
minority,'' the statement said.
   It said 1990 would be a pivotal year, bringing the expected
release of jailed African National Congress leader Nelson Mandela
and the possibility of negotiations on a post-apartheid political
structure.
   ``What we will all be doing, from both government and liberation
movement sides, will determine whether South Africa goes through
the path of a bloodbath or takes the high road of a less violent
transition to a non-racial and democratic South Africa,'' the
statement said. ``We enter the 1990s with the hope and confidence
that victory for democracy in our country is in sight.''
   The state-run South African Broadcasting Corp., in a year-end
commentary Friday, said ``the face of South Africa has changed
dramatically and irrevocably in the 1980s'' because of moves away
from racial discrimination and toward limited political
power-sharing.
   ``Ahead lies the further broadening of democracy with the
extension of the principle of power sharing at all levels of
government to black South Africans,'' the commentary said. How to
achieve that ``in a manner fair and equitable to all is the
challenge that awaits the leadership of all political
constituencies in the 1990s.''
   The anti-apartheid Democratic Party, which won 20 percent of the
vote in white parliamentary elections in September, commended
President F.W. de Klerk for his performance since the election.
   The Democrats' three co-leaders praised de Klerk for freeing
several prominent political prisoners, reducing the duration of
mandatory military service and abolishing segregated beaches. But
they said de Klerk and his National Party remained wedded to the
concept of racial groups as the foundation of future political
system.
   ``We need to introduce into our society the principles of equal
and equivalent franchise for all adults,'' the Democrats' leaders
said. ``Anything short of a full democracy is a threat to our safe
future.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>