<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 0003EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Judge-Explosion 7thLd-Writethru a0664 12-17 0833</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Judge-Explosion, 7th Ld-Writethru, a0664,0856</SECOND>
<HEAD>Federal Appeals Court Judge Dies in Bomb Blast</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 23 grafs to UPDATE with authorities having no suspects
or motive, FBI spokesman saying speculation that blast was drug-related,
additional quotes, background on judge; picks up 18th graf, ``It is believed
...''</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto AX2</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOUNTAIN BROOK, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal appeals judge was killed
by a mail bomb that went off at his home Saturday afternoon and his
wife was seriously wounded, authorities said.
   Eleventh U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals Judge Robert S. Vance,
58, died instantly when a package delivered to his home went off
around 3 p.m., FBI spokesman Chuck Steinmetz said in Washington.
   Authorities said they had no suspects or motive.
   ``There is speculation that it is drug-related,'' said Tom
Moore, an FBI spokesman in Birmingham. ``We will review that avenue
along with all the cases he's handled. We will talk to everybody
who might have an inkling of what happened. There will be
absolutely no pebble overlooked.''
   It was believed to be only the third time this century a federal
judge has been assassinated.
   ``Attorney General Dick Thornburgh and FBI Director William
Sessions tonight expressed outrage over the murder,'' Steinmetz
said, reading from a statement.
   The judge's wife, Helen, was in serious condition at St.
Vincent's Hospital with lacerations and internal injuries, said
hospital spokeswoman Barbara Traylor.
   The FBI, Postal Service investigators, the U.S. marshal and
local authorities were investigating the blast, said U.S. Attorney
Frank Donaldson. He added that the federal Bureau of Alcohol,
Tobacco and Firearms might also become involved.
   State Attorney General Don Siegelman told staff members to
``dedicate every resource of this office to find the perpetrators.''
   U.S. Sen. Howell Heflin, D-Ala., said officials were ``greatly
alarmed over his death and we wonder why'' it happened.
   ``As a member of the 11th Circuit Court of Appeals, they heard
many appeal cases related to drugs from Miami,'' Heflin said in an
interview from his home in Tuscumbia. ``There's speculation in that
regard, but nobody knows.''
   Alabama Supreme Court Justice Janie Shores, a friend of Vance,
said the slain judge's colleagues assumed the blast had something
to do with cases decided by him.
   ``But I didn't know Bob had an enemy in the world. It must ave
been a disgruntled defendant,'' Mrs. Shores said. ``They handle so
many drug-related cases.''
   State Democratic Party Chairman John Baker, who said he had
known the judge for about 20 years, said he couldn't imagine who
would want to harm Vance.
   ``I can only speculate that it had something to do with cases he
had handled or was handling on the federal bench,'' said Baker.
``It's been so long since he's been a lawyer that I wouldn't think
it had to do with any of those cases.''
   Steinmetz said Sessions described the attack as ``an affront to
the very strength of our democratic society: our justice system''
   The spokesman said Thornburgh said, ``Violent acts, such as that
which occurred today, are at odds with the underlying belief of our
nation and the rule of law. Such acts are to be condemned.
   ``My heart goes out to the family of Judge Vance, who has served
with distinction on the 11th Circuit Court of Appeals,'' the
attorney general said.
   Gov. Guy Hunt called the attack ``a cowardly thing'' and ``an
affront against civilization, against our form of government.''
   ``Judge Vance had a very sharp legal mind. He was one of the
leading judges in the country,'' the governor said.
   ``I just hope and pray the perpetrators of this crime will be
quickly brought to justice and receive swift punishment, and our
prayers are with the family,'' Hunt said.
   Vance was chairman of the state Democratic party from 1967 to
1977. In 1978, President Carter appointed him to the 11th U.S.
Circuit Court of Appeals, which covers Florida, Georgia and Alabama.
   Heflin said Vance would ``occupy many of the pages of the
history of Alabama for his leadership of reasoned sanity'' as party
chairman during those ``turbulent years.''
   It is believed that only two other federal judges have been
assassinated this century.
   U.S. District Judge Richard Daronco, 56, was shot and killed at
his home in May 1988 by a former New York City police officer angry
at Daronco's dismissal of a sex discrimination lawsuit filed by his
daughter. Charles Koster, 67, killed himself after gunning down the
judge.
   District Judge John H. Wood Jr., 63, was killed by a sniper
outside his home in San Antonio, Texas, in 1979. Charles Voyed
Harrelson was convicted of the contract killing and is serving two
life sentences in a Texas prison. El Paso drug trafficker Jamiel
``Jimmy'' Chagra, who authorities say ordered the hit, was
convicted of conspiring to obstruct the investigation of Wood's
murder and various drug charges. He is serving a life sentence in a
federal prison.
   Chagra had been scheduled to go on trial on drug charges before
Wood the day the judge was slain.
</TEXT>

</DOC>