<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0226 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2052EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Panama-TV     12-20 0725</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-TV,0743</SECOND>
<HEAD>TV Networks Cover Panama Operation</HEAD>
<BYLINE>Eds: Eloi in 8th graf is correct ^By JAY SHARBUTT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Television Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It may be the news-by-satellite era. But when
the major networks began coverage of Wednesday's U.S. military
strike in Panama shortly after midnight, the reports from their
correspondents there came by phone.
   The reason: Gunmen loyal to Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriegia barred
them from a satellite transmission, network executives said. No
pictures of the U.S. attack's results or street scenes in Panama
City were seen until after 9 a.m. EST, and then they were on tape,
not live.
   NBC got embroiled in a small war of its own _ complaints from
WTN, a London-based TV news agency serving CBS, ABC and CNN, that
NBC had aired nearly four minutes of WTN footage without
permission. An NBC spokesman said that was inadvertent, and that
NBC anchor Tom Brokaw told viewers the same thing.
   But WTN president Kenneth A. Coyte, in a letter to NBC News
president Michael Gartner, protested ``in the strongest possible
terms'' NBC's action, calling it a ``cynical breach of professional
standards.''
   However, NBC officials said, all four U.S. networks shortly
afterwards agreed to pool their Panama footage. By mid-morning, the
networks simultaneously were airing long-distance night shots of
military buildings burning, white tracer bullets shooting
occasionally shooting skyward and shadowy gunmen on streets.
   The networks also aired early daytime shots of Army helicopters
landing, two Air Force C-130 transports flying several thousand
feet above Panama City's Marriott Hotel, and U.S. paratroopers,
faces daubed in dark green camouflages, taking positions near
trees, signs and parks.
   At times, the war on TV took on an Alice-in-Wonderland quality.
Brokaw, interviewing a Panama City resident by phone on the
``Today'' show, asked him what local broadcasters were reporting.
   Eloi Benedetti said he was watching reports of the U.S. strike
on the U.S. Armed Forces TV station, which also carried CNN. Brokaw
asked if the station was describing what was going on on the ground
in Panama.
   ``Well,'' Benedetti said, ``they're actually relaying the CNN
broadcast.''
   It was a risky story for correspondents _ CNN used a stringer,
Berta Thayer _ and producers. Some among the crowd of journalists
at the Marriott Hotel reported that gunmen waiting outside had
threatened them, made it too dangerous to leave the hotel.
   Four men thought to be Noriega loyalists seized two network
producers in the hotel lobby. They later released one, ABC's Robert
Campos, several hours later, ABC said. CBS said it was checking
unconfirmed reports that the other producer, Jon Meyersohn, who
worked for CBS, also had been freed.
   NBC's Ed Rabel, reporting from the Marriott, fled to a nearby
U.S. military installation after gun-waving ``goons'' threatened
his life, according to NBC News senior vice president Joseph
Angotti, running NBC's operation here.
   ``They said they didn't want him or any other gringos around,
that if they found him the next time they came around, they'll kill
him,'' Angotti said.
   The U.S. military operation against Noriega was accompanied by a
Pentagon news pool that included NBC's Fred Francis, pool reporter
for the networks. One of his reports, shown on CNN, included a
discussion with CNN anchor Bernard Shaw of what he'd seen.
   The reporters were flown in on Air Force transports, but not
early enough, one CBS executive said.
   ``We stll don't have information why the pool didn't go in with
an early wave (of soldiers), or why they were held back ... until
pretty late in the game,'' said Don Decesare, CBS' vice president
for news coverage.
   The pool system was developed after a controversy over the ban
on reporters accompanying the initial phases of the U.S. attack in
Grenada in 1982. This group's TV gear included a portable satellite
ground station.
   But even though reporters were flown around the battle areas in
helicopters, it appeared late Wednesday afternoon that unexplained
snags had developed and there'd be no pool pictures from the
transmitter, DeCesare said.
   ``They have the capacity to feed (video reports),'' he said.
``However, we still have yet to receive anything.''
   He and his NBC and ABC counterparts were relieved when, at about
35 minutes before their networks' first evening newscasts, the
pool's videotape footage began coming in from Panama. Some shots
were taken over a the shoulder of a helicopter door gunner.
</TEXT>

</DOC>