<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0112 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1914EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Hanukkah     12-26 0322</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Hanukkah,0332</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jews at Western Wall Celebrate Hanukkah with World via Satellite</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Several thousand people at Jerusalem's Western
Wall celebrated Hanukkah Tuesday via satellite with Jews in New
York, Moscow, London and Paris.
   The mostly ultra-Orthodox crowd watched quietly as prayers were
chanted and the fifth candle was lighted in all five cities in the
first high-tech global Hannukah ceremony.
   Hannukah, the eight-day festival of lights, celebrates the
victory of the Jews over the Greco-Syrian kingdom in 165 B.C. The
kingdom tried to impose its culture on the Jews and desecrated the
holy temple in Jerusalem with statues of Greek gods.
   According to legend, when the Jews entered Jerusalem and tried
to rekindle the temple's eternal flame, they found enough oil for
one day, but the oil miraculously lasted eight days.
   To commemorate the miracle, Jews light candles at sunset for
eight consecutive days.
   The Western Wall, where the candle-lighting ceremony was held,
is the sole remnant of the second Jewish temple and the holiest
site in Judaism.
   Ruth Kabakoff, a 60-year-old tourist from Orlando, Fla., watched
one of two screens facing the Western Wall with excitement. She
said she heard about the satellite ceremony in her hotel, from
announcements in the streets over loudspeakers.
   ``I think it is wonderful that Jews feel that strongly about
their faith to join together. It makes me want to cry,'' she said.
   The candle in Jerusalem was lighted by Ashkenazi Chief Rabbi
Mordehai Eliahu, one of Israel's two chief rabbis.
   The Jerusalem crowd listened to a speech in Yiddish from
Brooklyn, N.Y., by the Lubavitcher Rebbe, Menachem M. Schneerson.
The rabbi's Habad movement sponsored the satellite ceremony.
   Esther Bodzin, an 18-year-old seminary student from Detroit,
said the highlight for her was watching children in Moscow
celebrate Hannukah.
   ``I think it's amazing. Look at all the people here. This one TV
show is tying together the Jews from all over,'' she said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>