<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0276 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1749EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-StockFraud-Lewis Bjt   12-18 0711</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stock Fraud-Lewis, Bjt,0734</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Stock Speculator Gets Three Years Probation</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEFAN FATSIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former stock speculator Salim B. Lewis on Monday
was spared a prison term for stock manipulation by a federal judge
who ordered him to work in a drug rehabilitation clinic, saying
``your skills should not be wasted.''
   Lewis, 50, a prominent Wall Street veteran whose downfall
resulted indirectly from the Ivan Boesky insider trading scandal,
was placed on three years probation and fined $250,000 after
pleading guilty to three counts for illegally inflating the price
of Fireman's Fund Corp. stock in May 1986.
   U.S. District Judge Mary Johnson Lowe also fined Lewis' firm,
S.B. Lewis &amp; Co., $400,000 for violating federal securities laws.
   Lewis faced up to 15 years in prison and a fine of $750,000 and
the firm a maximum $1 million fine for the manipulation, which
raised the value of Fireman's Fund stock immediately before a Lewis
client, American Express Co., sold a large amount of shares in a
new public offering.
   American Express was never charged, and there is no proof that
it or Lewis profited from the manipulation. But under federal
securities laws, profit is not necessary for a crime to have been
committed.
   ``I recognize my conduct was wrong,'' Lewis told the court.
``For this I am deeply sorry.''
   He said he was not motivated by greed but by a desire to punish
rival speculators attempting to bid down the price of Fireman's
Fund. The government said his version of events was ``simply not
supported by the facts.''
   Lewis pleaded guilty in Manhattan federal court in August,
reversing his assertions of innocence nine months after he was
indicted.
   The charges stemmed from a 1987 guilty plea by former Los
Angeles stockbroker Boyd Jefferies, who testified against several
Wall Street figures in the government's criminal fraud crackdown.
   Jefferies was implicated in the scandal by Boesky, the convicted
inside trader now in a New York halfway house finishing a
three-year prison term.
   Lewis was ordered to work 40 hours a week for one year at Daytop
Village, a Manhattan-based drug rehabilitation clinic. He must work
20 hours a week at the clinic in the second and third years of his
probation. Lewis will work at Daytop as an executive consultant,
Arkin said.
   ``You should be sentenced in such a manner that your skills
should not be wasted,'' Lowe said.
   But she added: ``I firmly believe your actions undermined the
integrity of (the financial) system. I have no problem saying that
should not be tolerated or go unpunished.''
   Prosecutors alleged Lewis requested two of Jefferies' employees
to buy more than 400,000 shares of Fireman's Fund on May 8, 1986,
in an attempt to drive its price up 12{ cents to $38 a share.
   The indictment also accused Lewis of promising to reimburse the
Jefferies employees for any losses and of hiding his role through
phony records.
   On May 9, 1986, American Express announced it would sell 8
million shares of its 41 percent owned Fireman's Fund at $41.50 a
share, a new stock offering that had been widely expected.
   Prosecutors said American Express made $88 million from the sale
but they never offered evidence that any of that profit was tainted
by what Lewis did.
   Lewis said he manipulated the stock price to foil
``short-sellers'' in Fireman's Fund stock. Short-sellers are
speculators who sell borrowed stock to push down the value,
repurchase it at a cheaper price, return the borrowed shares to the
lender and pocket the difference as profit.
   The Securities and Exchange Commission in September 1988 banned
short-selling in new stock offerings like that of Fireman's Fund,
exactly the type of activity Lewis claimed he'd tried to thwart.
Stock prices tend to fall after announcement of a new issue, which
dilutes the stock's value.
   Vincent DiBlasi, attorney for S.B. Lewis &amp; Co., said the firm
had fired all but seven of 44 employees and is liquidating.
   Lowe said the firm's demise sends ``the appropriate message to
the investment community that if a company engages in this type of
activity it will no longer be around.''
   ``In other words the death of a company is as final as the death
of a human being,'' she said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>