<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0222 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0223EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-WangChanges Bjt   12-21 0619</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Wang Changes, Bjt,0639</SECOND>
<HEAD>Wang Announces New Strategy of Compatibility</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JONATHAN YENKIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Wang Laboratories Inc., which has posted losses
and slashed its work force, has been criticized for having too
limited a product line. But the computer company says it hopes to
change its image by making equipment that uses popular,
industrywide standards.
   ``We're focusing more and more on our customers,'' said Gerry
Paul, Wang's vice president of systems, research and development.
``What they want is a wide variety of applications of software.''
   Analysts said the strategy, announced Wednesday, marks an
important departure for Wang, and it follows a recent trend in
which computer companies have been making equipment that is
compatible across the industry.
   ``Wang traditionally has been a closed, proprietary equipment
company,'' said Steven Wendler, an analyst with Gartner Group Inc.
``For a company like Wang, this movement into open systems is a
very significant philosophical change.''
   Wang said the announcement was part of a general strategy
outlined by company President Richard Miller last month, in which
the Lowell-based firm is trying to pay closer attention to the
needs of its customers.
   In a statement Wednesday, Miller said that by ``adopting
openness both as a product strategy and a state of mind, and
constantly listening to and heeding our customers' directions, Wang
will succeed in its efforts to grow and remain competitive in the
1990s and beyond.''
   Wang's strategy calls for integrating standardized technologies
into its existing product lines and developing new sets of hardware
and software based on popular industry standards such as UNIX and
DOS.
   For the past two years, Wang has been making personal computers
that are compatible with equipment from industry leader
International Business Machines Corp., Paul said.
   But, he added, ``We didn't move as quickly as we should have in
opening up our products.''
   Wang posted a loss of $62.1 million in the quarter that ended
Sept. 30. As part of the company's new focus, Miller announced last
month that Wang would cut 2,000 jobs, in addition to about 5,000
jobs that were eliminated earlier in the year.
   Part of Wang's rebuilding strategy has been to develop so-called
imaging systems, in which documents such as payroll forms or
insurance claims are electronically ``scanned'' and stored in a
computer.
   The documents can be retrieved on a computer screen much as a
VCR reproduces the images of a movie. The technology is aimed at
reducing the time and cost associated with manually filing,
collating and retrieving documents.
   Wang said its focus on openness is being blended with the
imaging technology to ``enable the broadest possible range of
users'' to take advantage of the product.
   Wang said it hoped to further broaden the use of imaging systems
through a licensing agreement, also announced Wednesday, with
Novell Inc., a Provo, Utah, company that makes personal computer
networking systems.
   ``Our goal is to provide universal access to Wang imaging and
integration of information and applications,'' Miller said.
   But while Wang continues to build its market in image
processing, more important is the company's movement away from its
proprietary systems, Wendler said.
   In the next four years, he said, the image processing market is
expected to grow to $3 billion, but open system technologies are
expected to represent a $60 billion market.
   ``The prospects for image processing are bright,'' he said,
``but the prospects for open systems are much brighter.''
   Wang also said Wednesday it had reached an agreement to sell up
to 30 percent of the shares it holds in its Taiwan manufacturing
subsidiary. The buyer was not announced. Wang said the sale of a
full 30 percent of the shares would bring it about $120 million
after taxes.
</TEXT>

</DOC>