<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0752EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Israel-Shootings     12-29 0439</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Israel-Shootings,0453</SECOND>
<HEAD>Army Acknowledges Accidental Shooting of 12-Year-Olds</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Retransmitting to correct slugline.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EILEEN ALT POWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The army today ordered an investigation into
the shooting of two 12-year-old Palestinians in an assault on
masked Arabs a day earlier in the occupied Gaza Strip.
   The army said the shootings were accidental. Both boys were
reported in good condition today at Gaza City's Shifa Hospital.
   Also today, a Palestinian suspected of collaborating with Israel
was hacked to death by masked Arabs in Gaza's Khan Yunis refugee
camp, Arab reports said.
   The slaying of Ahmad Mohammed Abu Shahmeh, 56, came a day after
PLO leader Yasser Arafat's mainstream Fatah faction called for
restraining slayings of alleged collaborators in a leaflet
distributed in Nablus in the occupied West Bank.
   Today's death raised to at least 164 the number of Palestinians
killed by fellow Arabs during the 2-year-old Palestinian uprising
against Israeli rule of the occupied lands. Most were suspected of
collaboration.
   A total of 640 Palestinians have been killed by Israelis in the
uprising, and 43 Israelis also have died.
   The army said in a statement issued today about the 12-year-olds
tthat soldiers detected four masked Arab youths in Gaza City and
``fired according to regulations.''
   ``Apparently children were near the group of masked people and
therefore injured by gunfire,'' it added. One masked youth also was
wounded.
   Under army firing rules, troops can shoot at the legs of masked
Palestinians who flee despite soldiers' orders to halt and warning
shots fired in the air.
   Palestinian reporters on Thursday quoted one of the wounded
Palestinians as saying none of the victims wore masks but that one
ran away in fear when soldiers approached.
   The house of a 41-year-old Palestinian arrested on suspicion of
killing suspected collaborators was demolished today by the army.
The four-room house of Hamdi Sheikh Khalil in Gaza City was home to
seven people, Arab reports said.
   The army has demolished or sealed more than 360 Palestinian
homes since the start of the uprising.
   A hand-grenade was thrown into a restaurant early today in the
town of Petah Tikva near Tel Aviv, wounding one Palestinian and
leaving another hospitalized with shock, police said.
   Police said one man was taken into custody in the incident,
adding they suspected ``criminal motives'' in the case. The Itim
national news agency said the man arrested was wearing the skull
cap of an observant Jew.
   Tension in Petah Tikva involving Arab day laborers led the town
earlier this year to set up a ``holding area'' to segregate
Palestinians waiting for rides to and from the occupied territories.
</TEXT>

</DOC>