<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0326EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Names     12-30 0678</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Names,0705</SECOND>
<HEAD>Names in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY14</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hope for world peace was the New Year's
message from former President Ronald Reagan and wife Nancy as they
headed for the desert bash that has become a 22-year tradition.
   ``Their hope for 1990 is that all peoples of the world will live
in peace and freedom,'' Mark Weinberg, spokesman for the Reagans,
said Friday.
   The Reagans were spending the weekend at the estate of friend
and former ambassador Walter Annenberg. The annual pilgrimage to
the estate near Palm Springs has become a New Year's ritual for the
Reagans.
   Weinberg said the Reagans will socialize with friends, play golf
and watch football games on television during their stay at the
Annenberg compound 110 miles east of Los Angeles.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>OSLO, Norway (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Helge Ingstad, the Norwegian scientist and
explorer who discovered Leif Erikson's settlement in Newfoundland,
was honored on the eve of his 90th birthday.
   Television, radio and newspapers on Friday extolled Ingstad's
exploits. During excavations from 1960 to 1968, Ingstad and his
wife, archeologist Anne Stine Ingstad, found a concentration of
Norse homesteads at L'Anse aux Meadows in northern Newfoundland.
   Their findings showed that Norse people had sailed via Greenland
to settle in North America about the year 1000, or 500 years before
Columbus reached America.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Author V.S. Naipaul was given knighthod, and
Maggie Smith was made a dame commander in honors announced today.
   The pair made Queen Elizabeth II's semiannual honors list, which
the government compiles. The queen actually bestows the honors at a
later ceremony.
   Naipaul, 57, a Trinidad-born writer, was made a Knight Bachelor.
The author of ``In a Free State,'' ``A Bend in the River'' and
``Enigma of Arrival'' came to Britain at age 17 on a scholarship to
Oxford University and has become one of the country's most
important writers.
   The honor entitles him to call himself Sir Vidiadhar, but his
work always appears with his initials.
   Maggie Smith, 55, one of Britain's finest stage actresses and an
Oscar-winner for ``The Prime of Miss Jean Brodie,'' was made a Dame
Commander of the Order of British Empire, the equivalent of a
knighthood for a woman.
   Many of the 947 awards made in the New Year's list went to
emergency service staff who worked at Lockerbie, Scotland, after a
bomb exploded on Flight 103 and the plane crashed Dec. 21, 1988,
killing 270 people.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After an ill-fated attempt to have multiple
hosts this year, the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences
has selected comedian Billy Crystal as sole host for the 1990
Academy Awards broadcast.
   ``We are extremely pleased to have Billy host the show,''
Gilbert Cates, producer of the 1990 telecast, said Friday. ``His
unique talents and his ability to handle the unexpected will be
important assets this year.''
   It will mark the third consecutive awards show appearance for
Crystal and his first as host.
   Nominations for the 62nd Annual Academy Awards will be announced
Feb. 14. Among the films in contention is the comedy ``When Harry
Met Sally...,'' in which Crystal co-stars. The Oscar trophies will
be presented in Los Angeles on March 26.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CORPUS CHRISTI, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush and Soviet leader
Mikhail S. Gorbachev would prefer to be left out in the cold when
it comes to advertisements for a decongestant.
   ``Heads of state don't endorse cold medicine,'' Bush spokesman
Marlin Fitzwater said Friday.
   Fitzwater objected to ads for Drixoral, an over-the-counter head
cold remedy manufactured by Schering-Plough Corp. The ads show
Gorbachev and Bush shaking hands at the superpower summit in Malta
earlier this month.
   ``In the New Year, may the only cold war in the world be the one
we're fighting,'' assert the advertisements.
   But the ads clearly are giving the White House a headache.
   ``We do not approve or sanction or acknowledge any of these
commercial endorsements and we appreciate the two television
networks that declined to run them,'' said Fitzwater.
   ABC and CBS have refused to carry the spot.
</TEXT>

</DOC>