<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0137 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1957EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Bush-Barbara     12-27 0362</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Barbara,320</SECOND>
<HEAD>President Assures Crowd Wife Is OK</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CRISTOPHER CONNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEEVILLE, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush assured the folks back
home Wednesday that his wife is ``in very good health,''
notwithstanding what the they may have read in a supermarket
tabloid.
   Bush, addressing more than 800 people at a barbeque dinner in
his home state, said he left Mrs. Bush back at the White House
``winding down her responsibilities as a grandparent'' over the
Christmas holidays.
   ``She is in good health. I get asked that all the time,'' said
Bush about his wife of 44 years who has been undergoing treatment
for Graves disease.
   Graves disease is the result of an overactive thyroid gland and
has caused teary eyes and double vision in Mrs. Bush, according to
her doctors.
   The National Enquirer recently ran an article claiming her
condition was worse than the White House has let on and that the
first lady was in severe pain at times.
   The White House says Mrs. Bush is responding to treatment. She
visited the Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minn., last month, where
specialists decided to vary her medication, prednisone.
   ``You know, there is a magazine that I'm sure nobody here is too
familiar with called the National Enquirer. But apparently they
printed a story about her on their front page and we've had more
crazy letters and inquiries'' about her health, said the president.
   ``She's in very good health. She feels just great,'' said Bush.
   Barbara Bush will join her husband on Friday in Houston, where
they will ring in the new year. They also plan to visit soldiers
wounded in Panama at two military hospitals in San Antonio on
Sunday.
   Bush is spending three days in South Texas without his wife,
hunting for quail at the ranch of a friend, Will Farish, as he has
during Christmas week for years.
   The crowd gave a vigorous round of applause when Bush concluded
his remarks on his wife's health by saying, ``I think Bar's doing a
fantastic job for our country.'
   The Bushes celebrated Christmas with their five children and 11
grandchildren at Camp David, the presidential retreat in Maryland.
</TEXT>

</DOC>