<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0216EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Names     12-21 0736</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Names,0762</SECOND>
<HEAD>Names in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY14</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BONN, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Leonard Bernstein will conduct
Beethoven's ``Ninth Symphony'' in East and West Berlin in two
concerts to celebrate recent historic events in Germany.
   Musicians from the United States, Britain, France, West Germany,
East Germany and the Soviet Union will play under Bernstein's
baton, said Justuz Frantz, director of the Schleswig-Holstein Music
Festival and coordinator of the Berlin performances. He announced
the concerts Wednesday.
   The first concert will be Saturday at the Berlin Philharmonic in
West Berlin, the second on Christmas Day at the East Berlin
Schauspielhaus theater.
   The performance in West Berlin will be broadcast live on a giant
screen near the city's Kaiser Wilhelm Memorial Church so people can
see it free, he said.
   Bernstein put together the international orchestra to
``symbolize the four Allies,'' as well as the two German states,
Frantz said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jack Nicholson concedes he's never been
Hollywood's top box office attraction, but he says, ``That's all by
design.''
   ``I like being in that second or third spot,'' the actor, who
stands to make $60 million for his role in ``Batman,'' said in
January's issue of Gentleman's Quarterly.
   ``Just let some other lunatic do this stuff and move up behind
him, and nobody gets too excited about it,'' Nicholson said. ``I've
had creative autonomy from `Easy Rider' on, with a few exceptions,
and that's all you get out of being the Number One box office star
anyway.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tom Cruise, although familiar with ``The Color
of Money,'' says he's never done a film just for the cash.
   ``I don't know how many times I have to say this, but having
clout in the business has never been a huge concern of mine,''
Cruise said in Rolling Stone magazine's Jan. 11 issue.
   ``And I have never done a film for money. ... That's not what
acting is for me. I love doing it, and I want to try different
things,'' said Cruise, who co-starred with Dustin Hoffman in ``Rain
Man'' and Paul Newman in ``The Color of Money.''
   His most recent different thing: the role of disabled Vietnam
veteran Ron Kovic in the just-released ``Born on the Fourth of
July.'' Cruise said he ignored the advice of studio executives and
others who felt he should steer clear of the role.
   ``People want to limit things,'' Cruise said. ``They say, `God,
you're going to lose everything? Aren't you afraid?' ... Somewhere
I guess you want to find out, how far can I fall? How deep is the
well? When am I going to hit? I want to know that.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Judith Jamison, a former dancer in the Alvin
Ailey American Dance Theater, will succeed Ailey as the company's
artistic director.
   Miss Jamison said Wednesday that earlier this year, Ailey told
her he wanted her to succeed him. ``He said, `You're going in
another direction now.'''
   Ailey, who founded the company 31 years ago, died Dec. 1.
   Miss Jamison joined the company in 1965, leaving 15 years later
to be one of the stars of ``Duke Ellington's Sophisticated Ladies''
on Broadway.
   Last year, she started the Jamison Project, for which she
choreographs and dances. The Jamison Project will continue through
June and some dancers and some dance works will enter the Ailey
company.
   The future of the Ailey company, Miss Jamison said, ``will
reflect his vision and mine. They're not one and the same.'' She
said changes will be ``a creative process we will be working on the
entire time I'm here.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Saudi financier Adnan Khashoggi may take a
vacation to Colorado and Florida as he awaits trial on charges that
he helped Ferdinand and Imelda Marcos in the alleged plunder of the
Philippine treasury.
   Khashoggi has been free on $10 million bail since he was
extradited to this country from Switzerland in July. Conditions on
his bail include that he remain in New York and that his movements
be monitored by an electronic bracelet.
   Khashoggi, who has pleaded innocent to the charges, has been
living in a Fifth Avenue penthouse. His trial with Mrs. Marcos is
scheduled to begin March 14.
   U.S. District Judge John Keenan on Wednesday granted his request
for the three-week vacation to visit family after Khashoggi's
lawyer, Robert Morvillo, said in a letter that prosecutors had
consented to it.
</TEXT>

</DOC>