<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1453EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-TechnologyExports     12-17 0379</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Technology Exports,360</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mosbacher Says US Negotiating Controls With Hungary, Poland</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BARTON REPPERT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United States has started negotiations
with Poland and Hungary aimed at preventing diversion to the Soviet
Union of U.S. high-technology exports to those two East European
countries, Commerce Secretary Robert Mosbacher said Sunday
   Mosbacher's remarks came a day after President Bush signaled
that his administration is ready to consider a major relaxation of
export controls with regard to Warsaw Pact nations.
   ``I think it is timely that we take a new look at the commercial
restraints,'' Bush said Saturday at a news conference on the
Caribbean island of St. Martin after meeting with French President
Francois Mitterrand.
   Mosbacher, appearing on NBC's ``Meet the Press'' program, was
asked about a pending request by the Control Data Corp. to sell
several high-powered computers to the Soviet Union.
   The commerce secretary responded that ``we'll have to look at
each item on a case-by-case basis.''
   ``We released middle technology and we're going to look to see
whether it should go higher than that,'' Mosbacher said. ``Eastern
European countries, yes; the Soviet Union, we'd have to be very
careful.''
   Later in the program, Mosbacher was asked how the United States
could be confident that high-technology items exported to Poland
and Hungary, which remain members of the Warsaw Pact, would not end
up in Soviet hands.
   He replied: ``Well, because both of them have started
negotiations with us on verification and continuing observation on
what they do with whatever we send them. And it would be on that
condition and that we make that negotiation a reality that we would
send them these things so that there couldn't be transshipment.''
   Mosbacher also was questioned about the announcement Friday that
the U.S. merchandise trade deficit had surged to $10.2 billion in
October, the biggest deficit in 10 months.
   The commerce secretary replied that he did not believe the
October figure spelled bad news for longer-term efforts to help
reduce the trade deficit.
   Mosbacher said he expects the U.S. trade imbalance for all of
1989 will total about $110 billion, down from approximately $120
billion last year.
   ``We're chipping away at it _ not fast enough, but we're working
on it,'' he said.
 
</TEXT>

</DOC>