<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 2358EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Martin 5thLd-Writethru a0670 12-25 0885</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Martin, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0670,0904</SECOND>
<HEAD>Billy Martin, Former Yankee Manager, Dies in Alcohol-Related Wreck</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Add son and daughter to survivors in final graf. Adds byline.
Version moving on sports wires.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY28, NY29, LaserColor NY28C</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM KATES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BINGHAMTON, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Billy Martin, the pugnacious five-time
manager of the New York Yankees baseball team who was repeatedly
fired after bouts of drinking and brawling, was killed Monday in an
alcohol-related traffic accident, authorities said. He was 61.
   Martin was riding in a pickup that skidded off a road in the
Town of Fenton, near his suburban home, at 5:45 p.m., when roads
were icy, authorities said. The truck skidded 300 feet down an
embankment and stopped at the foot of Martin's driveway, Port Crane
Fire Chief John Eldrid said.
   The driver, William Reedy, 53, of Detroit, was charged with
driving while intoxicated, Broome County Sheriff Anthony Ruffo said.
   Efforts to revive Martin at Wilson Memorial Hospital failed and
he died there about 7 p.m. of severe internal injuries and possible
head injuries, hospital spokesman Michael Doll said. Reedy, a
long-time friend of Martin's, suffered a broken hip and possible
broken ribs and was listed in serious condition, Doll said.
   An autopsy was scheduled to be performed on Martin Tuesday, Doll
said.
   ``It's like losing part of my own family,'' Yankees owner George
Steinbrenner said in a statement. ``I was just with him last
Wednesday when he came down to entertain 2,000 underprivileged kids
in Tampa. Billy said this meant so much to him because he never had
anything like this when he was a kid.''
   ``Baseball has lost one of its most unique and colorful
personalities and Oakland has lost a friend,'' said a statement
issued by the Haas family, owners of the Oakland Athletics, whom
Martin managed from 1980-82.
   Born Alfred Manuel Martin, he played second base for the Yankees
from 1950-57, including five World Series championship teams.
   He was honored with a plaque in Yankee Stadium's monument park,
a place reserved for the likes of Lou Gehrig, Babe Ruth and Joe
DiMaggio. His plaque proclaims Martin ``A Yankee Forever.''
   ``It was a big loss. He was a dear friend and I will miss him.
He was a great little guy,'' DiMaggio said in San Francisco.
   Martin was first hired to manage the team in 1975. His latest
firing was on June 23, 1988, when he was replaced by Lou Piniella,
the man he replaced at the end of the 1987 season. Steinbrenner
kept Martin on as a consultant.
   Martin brought his combative style to the manager's bench,
arguing with players and umpires and getting his teams to play a
hard-running game dubbed ``Billy ball.''
   But his exploits off the field clouded his later career. He got
into a fight in a topless bar in Texas on May 6, 1988, hours after
being ejected from a game for arguing a call with an umpire. Six
weeks later he was fired by Steinbrenner.
   ``In on-the-field management, he was the best field general I
ever played for. Off the field, he was all of those things and a
lot more,'' said Wayne Gross, who played under Martin in Oakland.
   His first managing stint typified his love-hate relationship
with the Yankees. He guided the team to a World Series title in
1977, a season marked by his shoving match with slugger Reggie
Jackson in the Boston stadium that June.
   The next season, Jackson was suspended for five days on July 18,
1978, after ignoring Martin's instruction to bunt. Five days later,
Martin blasted out at Jackson and Steinbrenner saying, ``One's a
born liar; the other's convicted.'' (Steinbrenner pleaded guilty to
conspiring to violate federal elections laws in a contribution to
Richard Nixon's 1972 campaign. Former President Reagan pardoned him
in January.)
   Martin resigned in tears the next day. Only five days later,
however, Steinbrenner announced he would bring Martin back, a
promise he fulfilled the next year.
   Martin married his fourth wife, the former Jill Guiver, in
January 1988. They had been living on a large farm in Port Crane.
   In an interview in July 1989, Martin said he was enjoying life
out of the spotlight of baseball and the publicity he earned with
numerous barroom altercations.
   ``I have sheep, cattle, ducks, geese and a few horses,'' he
said. ``I like it because we also have an 80-acre lake. I do
everything. I raise pheasants and turn them loose.''
   In his career as a major-league manager, Martin had 1,258
victories and 1,018 losses in 16 seasons. In addition to the
Yankees, he managed the Minnesota, Detroit, Texas and Oakland
teams. He led the Minnesota Twins to an American League West title
in 1969 and the Detroit Tigers to an AL East title in 1970. He led
the Yankees to AL pennants in 1976 and 1977 and the Oakland
Athletics to an AL West title in 1981.
   In 11 major-league seasons as a player, Martin batted .257 with
64 home runs and 333 runs batted in.
   Besides his wife, Martin is survived by a son, Billy Joe, and a
daughter, Kelly, both from previous marriages; two brothers and two
sisters _ Frank Pisani of Vacaville, Calif.; Jack Downey of
Clearlake, Calif.; Patricia Irvine of Berkeley, Calif.; and Joan R.
Holland of Berkeley.
</TEXT>

</DOC>