<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 2248EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SecretTaping     12-17 0496</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Secret Taping,0508</SECOND>
<HEAD>Secret Taping Raises Questions On Reaccreditation of Conn. Police</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARTFORD, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A national commission is reconsidering
its accreditation of Connecticut's state police because the
department secretly taped telephone calls between suspects and
their attorneys, The Hartford Courant reported Sunday.
   The Commission on Accreditation of Law Enforcement Agencies Inc.
has given the police until the end of the month to document that
its policies in 1988 complied with a requirement that suspects be
given confidential access to lawyers, the newspaper said.
   The commission also called on the department to explain its
taping operations, the Courant said.
   The issue of secret taping arose in a manslaughter trial in
October, and controversy snowballed last month when the Courant
reported that the state police routinely tape-recorded telephone
conversations at state police barracks, including calls between
suspects and lawyers.
   The disclosures led to the forced resignation of the
department's head, Lester J. Forst. A federal grand jury is
investigating the practice, and Congress is scheduled to begin
hearings on the issue Monday. A group of attorneys has sued the
state on behalf of prisoners.
   Tape-recording telephone calls is legal in certain
circumstances, such as with a judge's permission or when one of the
people talking knows the call is being recorded. But recording
calls between lawyers and clients is forbidden under federal law.
   The Courant reported earlier this month that it found evidence
that suspect-attorney phone calls may have been monitored in
several other states, including West Virginia and Utah.
   The newspaper reported Sunday that state police officials
assured the accrediting commission more than a year ago that they
guaranteed privacy for suspects talking to lawyers. The paper cited
a February 1988 report from the non-profit commission, which
accredits police departments across the country.
   The Connecticut department is one of only nine state forces in
the country to win full accreditation. The department prepared 18
months for the evaluation and paid the commission $14,620 for it.
   Bernard R. Sullivan, who replaced Forst as the state's public
safety commissioner and head of the state police, said he wrote the
commission recently to suggest it consider setting a specific
standard on police taping.
   After problems caused by taping in Connecticut and elsewhere
were solved, Sullivan said, ``This may turn out to be a very
positive thing for policing.''
   As part of the accreditation process, four commission inspectors
pored over documents, scrutinized equipment and interviewed
department members for five days.
   Police who knew of the secret taping did not tell commission
inspectors, said Ken Medeiros, executive director of the
commission. Commission inspectors rely mainly on police cooperation
and integrity rather than any investigation of their own, he said.
   Accreditation is considered a seal of approval for a department.
It immediately reduced the Connecticut department's liability
insurance costs by 10 percent. It also enhanced the department's
reputation in law enforcement circles and was supposed to assure
the public that the agency was complying with public safety laws
and regulations.
</TEXT>

</DOC>