<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0111 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1650EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Long-DistanceRates     12-19 0454</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Long-Distance Rates,430</SECOND>
<HEAD>AT&amp;T Cutting Rates Slightly</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By W. DALE NELSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation's dominant long-distance telephone
company, the American Telephone &amp; Telegraph Co., announced Tuesday
that it will cut basic, daytime interstate rates an average of 1.3
percent Jan. 1. Evening rates will drop an average of 2.0 percent.
   AT&amp;T spokesman Herb Linnen said the reductions were necessary
under changes earlier this year in the Federal Communications
Commission's regulation of long-distance charges.
   The FCC now imposes caps on AT&amp;T's long-distance rates based on
the company's long-distance expenses, as opposed to a preset rate
of return.
   AT&amp;T said the lowered rates reflect reduced expenses, mainly
from reduced fees that AT&amp;T will pay in 1990 to local telephone
companies for access to local exchanges.
   John Hauser, a spokesman for AT&amp;T's principal competitor, MCI
Communications Corp., said MCI would also pass on savings in local
telephone company access charges. ``We will remain competitive with
them,'' he said.
   Hauser's counterpart at US Sprint, Robin Pence, said, ``We are
reviewing the filing and we intend to remain competitive.''
   AT&amp;T says it has about 70 percent of the long-distance market,
as measured by interstate and intrastate revenues. MCI is No. 2
with more than 10 percent. US Sprint claims 7 to 8 percent.
   In filing notice with the FCC of its intent to lower rates, AT&amp;T
estimated that the reductions would save customers $300 million a
year on interstate and international long-distance services used
primarily by residential and small business customers.
   A 10-minute AT&amp;T call during daytime hours on a weekday, to
anywhere in the United States, will cost $2.50 or less, an average
decrease of 1.3 percent.
   Linnen said a 10-minute daytime call from Washington to New
York, which now costs $2.30, would decline to $2.20, a drop of 4.3
percent. An evening call from Washington to San Francisco, Los
Angeles or Dallas, which now costs $1.67 for 10 minutes, would drop
5.3 percent to $1.58. Many of the reductions would be less for
other calls.
   The Monday-Friday ``day'' calling period is 8 a.m. to 5 p.m.
local time. The ``evening'' period is 5 p.m. to 11 p.m. Sunday
through Friday.
   The ``night'' calling period, for which rates will not change,
is from 11 p.m. to 8 a.m. Sunday through Friday. ``Weekend''
calling rates, identical to the night rates and also unaffected,
are in effect all day Saturday and until 5 p.m. Sunday.
   International calls from the 48 contiguous states to 25 of the
most frequently called countries will be slashed by $104 million.
The reductions will vary from country to country; the countries
will include Canada, Mexico, Japan, the United Kingdom, France,
Italy, Israel, Brazil, Australia, the Philippines, Taiwan and Korea.
</TEXT>

</DOC>