<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0739EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Goetz-Cancer 1stLd-Writethru a0477 12-19 0322</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Goetz-Cancer, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0477,0329</SECOND>
<HEAD>Subway Gunman Reportedly Has Cancer</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 7th graf, `The shootings ...' to RESTORE dropped `and';
SUBS 11th graf, `The documents ...' to fix typo in `Bronx.'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Subway gunman Bernhard Goetz reportedly is being
treated for cancer.
   Goetz _ who became a symbol of crime fears in the city when he
shot four unarmed youths he said were threatening him on a subway
train _ revealed in court papers Monday he underwent ``major
surgery'' last month.
   The surgery and subsequent radiation treatments were for
testicular cancer, sources familiar with the case told the New York
Daily News and the New York Post. One testicle was removed, the
newspapers reported today.
   Goetz's attorney, Barry Slotnick, refused to give details of his
client's illness.
   ``Obviously, you can assume that he is not well,'' Slotnick
said, but added that Goetz was in good spirits after the operation.
   ``He is a very strong individual who has gone through a lot in
the past five years and will not allow his present unfortunate
physical condition to get him down,'' the attorney said.
   The shootings Dec. 22, 1984, ignited controversy over racial
tension and the rights of crime victims to defend themselves.
   Goetz, who is white, claimed the four black youths were trying
to rob him; the youths said they were panhandling.
   Goetz, 41, served eight months in prison for a weapons
conviction stemming from the shootings. He was acquitted of
attempted murder and assault.
   Darrell Cabey, who is paralyzed from the waist down from the
shooting, is suing Goetz for $50 million.
   The documents revealing Goetz's surgery were filed in court in
the Bronx to explain why he failed to appear for a deposition Dec.
1 with Cabey's attorneys.
   William Kunstler, one of Cabey's attorneys, said the news Goetz
had cancer didn't make him feel sympathy.
   ``It possibly makes me believe in God,'' Kunstler said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>