<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 2110EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HuntBankruptcy 1stLd-Writethru a0773 12-17 0319</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hunt Bankruptcy, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0773,0323</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge Approves Bunker Hunt Bankruptcy Protection Plan</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 7th graf to CORRECT amount to be paid to IRS to 80 percent,
sted 70 percent.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal bankruptcy judge has approved a
reorganization plan for ex-billionaire Nelson Bunker Hunt, paving
the way for him to emerge from bankruptcy protection next month.
   Under the plan approved Friday by U.S. Bankruptcy Judge Harold
Abramson, the $222 million left of Hunt's multibillion-dollar
fortune will be transferred to a trust next month and proceeds from
the trust will be used to repay debts.
   The plan was jointly proposed by Hunt and a group of his major
creditors.
   Hunt's bankruptcy attorney, Russell Munsch, said his client was
``very glad to be out of bankruptcy, but bitter at what bankruptcy
has cost.''
   In September 1988, Hunt and his wife, Caroline _ who owed more
than $1 billion to creditors _ filed for protection under Chapter
11 of federal bankruptcy law.
   The smaller estate of his brother, William Herbert Hunt, still
remains under Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection, but is expected to
be closed next week. William Hunt's plan faces challenge from two
creditors who have about $25 million in claims.
   About 80 percent of the money raised under the liquidation of
Bunker Hunt's trust is to be used to repay the Internal Revenue
Service. Minpeco S.A., a Peruvian mining concern that won a $132
million court judgment against the brothers stemming from their
alleged attempt in 1979-80 to corner the silver market, will also
receive a large share of the liquidated estates.
   Under terms of the settlement, Hunt lost his real estate
holdings, including the largest cattle ranch in Australia and the
Bronco Bowl recreation center in Dallas.
   He will be allowed to keep his $1.8 million Dallas mansion, his
Cadillac, household furnishings, clothing and 50 percent of the
proceeds from non-producing gas and oil properties.
</TEXT>

</DOC>