<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1208EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SovietWatch     12-23 0307</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet Watch,0316</SECOND>
<HEAD>Counterfeiters Beat Soviet Army Watch In Battle for Thai Market</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID BRUNNSTROM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BANGKOK, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For $110.89, you can watch a Russian
revolution once a minute in Bangkok.
   You can also do pretty much the same for less _ $97.27 less to
be precise _ but your version of the Soviet Army Watch will come
from Taiwan and not Moscow.
   Billed by its promoters as the most exciting fashion accessory
of 1989, the genuine Soviet Army Watch arrived in Bangkok on Dec.
1, but counterfeit versions have been on open street sale for
several months now.
   Charnchai Kheangprakhong, manager of Zur-Ton International,
which markets the real Soviet Army Watch in Thailand, said he is
not worried by the flood of cheap imitations.
   ``It is not a problem _ you can tell which is genuine and which
is not _ there is a big difference in quality,'' he said, adding
that he expects sales of the real watch to surpass 10,000 in the
first year.
   ``It is a hot fashion item,'' he said.
   The fake watches came to Thailand partly because of the big
demand for them after the Soviet Army Watch was launched in Europe
and the United States, he said.
   ``People couldn't get the real one here so they brought in the
fake ones,'' he said.
   The latest symbol of glasnost is also the latest counterfeit
item to be found on the streets of Bangkok. It vies with cheap
imitations of Rolex and Cartier watches as well as hundreds of
other products including old favorites like Luis Vuitton luggage
and Lacoste polo shirts.
   Most counterfeit products are made domestically, but some
imitation watches or watch parts are smuggled in from Taiwan.
   As one Western businessman living in Thailand remarked:
``Copyright here basically means `the right to copy.'''
</TEXT>

</DOC>