<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1252EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Europe Bjt   12-27 0915</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Europe, Bjt,0941</SECOND>
<HEAD>In the West, Regrets About Past Favors to Ceausescu</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHARLES CAMPBELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Now that he's been toppled and executed, Nicolae
Ceausescu has few defenders, his rank secure among the century's
most brutal and despised dictators.
   But it wasn't so long ago the Romanian president was the West's
favorite Communist, showered with kind words and economic benefits
for his role as a maverick in the East bloc.
   France was especially friendly toward Ceausescu's Romania for
many years, seeing a people with cultural affinities as well as a
country whose independence from the Soviet Union could be a
mirror-image for French refusal to follow U.S. foreign policy leads.
   In the aftermath of the Romanian revolution, France is now
seeing apologies and recriminations, as politicians and parties
accuse each other of being slow to realize the scope of Ceausescu's
abuses of power.
   Elsewhere, the change of heart has taken a different form. Queen
Elizabeth II stripped Ceausescu of his honorary knighthood ``as a
mark of revulsion at the abuse of human rights in Romania.''
   King Olav V of Norway took away his honorary Grand Cross of St.
Olav Order and, by action of Queen Margrethe II of Denmark, the
Romanian leader was no longer a Knight of the Elephant Order when
he went before the firing squad.
   All three monarchs acted after Ceausescu was driven from power
Friday, wiping out honors that had been awarded about a decade
earlier, when Romania's reputation was at its height.
   The process occurring in the aftermath of Ceausescu's ouster is
similar to those that followed the demise of other dictators this
century, such as Josef Stalin in the Soviet Union, Ferdinand Marcos
of the Philippines, Idi Amin in Uganda and Jean-Bedel Bokassa of
the Central African Republic.
   It was not until early this year that the United States withdrew
Romania's valuable status as ``Most Favored Nation'' for trade
purposes, on grounds of human rights violations.
   As recently as 1986, Reagan administration officials were
defending Romania's Most Favored Nation status, with Edward J.
Derwinski, counselor of the State Department, telling a hostile
congressional committee that Romania had an ``overall reasonably
good record'' on allowing people to leave the country.
   Ceausescu's reputation for free-thinking was earned in foreign
affairs.
   He condemned the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan in 1979 and
refused to join the 1968 invasion of Czechoslovakia that ended the
``Prague Spring'' liberalization movement.
   Ceausescu also stood apart from the other Communist countries
when he maintained links with Israel after the 1967 Middle East
War, eventually serving as mediator between Israel and Egypt in the
talks that led to their peace treaty.
   The gratitude won as the Jewish state's only ally in a hostile
Communist bloc has survived, although Israel condemned massive
killings by the secret police and pledged support for Romania's new
leadership.
   ``Speaking as Jews and Israelis we cannot forget the general
point, we cannot remember our enemies and forget our friends,''
Israel's former ambassador to Bucharest, Abba Geffen, said
Wednesday on Israel radio. ``We must not enter into the
anti-Ceausescu hysteria.''
   Anti-Ceausescu sentiment was mostly to be found in Moscow back
in 1969, when Richard Nixon chose Romania for the first visit by a
U.S. president to a Warsaw Pact country.
   Nixon and Ceausescu delighted crowds by joining in a traditional
Romanian peasant dance, with a Romanian girl dancing between them.
Their joint statement talked of a ``spirit of cordiality, sincerity
and mutual respect.''
   Earlier in the 1960s, French President Charles de Gaulle blazed
the trail of ties between the West and Romania.
   ``De Gaulle was following a policy of independence vis-a-vis the
United States. France was seeking an ally in the East. Ceausescu
was following a similar path in the Warsaw Pact,'' said Ewa
Kulesza, an expert on Eastern Europe at the French Institute for
International Relations in Paris.
   ``There was a kind of identification between De Gaulle's France
and Ceausescu's Romania. It was an illusion,'' she said in an
interview.
   The illusion, based in part on cultural associations between
France and Romania, whose languages are similar, was long-lasting.
   Claude Cheysson, former French foreign minister who visited
Romania in 1983, apologized for his role in an interview published
Monday in the leftist daily newspaper Liberation.
   ``We should have been more clear in our denunciations of what we
knew, of what we guessed about Romania, so that perhaps we could
have precipitated the movements that we see now,'' Cheysson was
quoted as saying.
   Former President Valery Giscard d'Estaing accused the current
Socialist government of not doing enough to call attention to
Ceausescu's misdeeds.
   Socialist leaders criticized Giscard d'Estaing for exchanging
visits with Ceausescu _ while Mitterrand at least scrapped a
planned visit to Romania in 1982, although he cited scheduling
problems rather than human rights abuses. The trip was never
rescheduled.
   Giscard d'Estaing replied, in an interview in the rightist
newspaper Le Figaro, that he ``personally felt a strong antipathy''
for Ceausescu after their 1980 encounter in France, and said the
translator at their session could confirm it.
   The heaviest fire has focused on Georges Marchais, the hard-line
French Communist Party leader, who vacationed on Ceausescu's yacht
in 1984. Dissidents in the party called this week on Marchais and
the entire Politburo to resign because of their past support for
Ceausescu.
   The Politburo replied that Marchais had not seen Ceausescu in
five years, and had made many quiet appeals to the Romanian leader
for respect of human rights.
</TEXT>

</DOC>