<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0143 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1557EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-SmugglingHearing     12-20 0358</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Smuggling Hearing,0371</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prosecutors Seek to Keep Family Jailed on Pot Smuggling Charges</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BETH HARRIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>INDIANAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The former president of the Indianapolis
League of Women Voters and her two sons were behind bars today
after being extradited from Austria on charges of running a major
marijuana smuggling ring.
   Less than 24 hours after their extradition, Linda Leary and
Richard and Paul Heilbrunn appeared in shackles Tuesday before a
U.S. magistrate and were then jailed for a hearing Friday on
whether to free them on bail before trial Feb. 13.
   ``The evidence we'll present will likely keep them detained,''
U.S. Attorney Deborah said.
   A 1987 indictment named them among 34 people charged with
operating an 11-state ring that moved at least 250,000 pounds of
marijuana _ one of the biggest such drug operations ever uncovered.
They were arrested in May in Austria.
   Before leaving the United States in 1985, Leary, 58, was
president of the Indianapolis League of Women Voters and the local
chapter of the National Council of Jewish Women.
   Paul Heilbrunn, 35, was a commodities broker and columnist for a
local business journal. Richard Heilbrunn, 38, lived with his wife
and two children on a farm outside Indianapolis.
   ``This is a major milestone,'' Daniels said. ``Though we had
felt confident that they would be home by the end of the year, it's
good to see that process complete.''
   Daniels and her staff waited for months while Justice Department
officials in Washington processed hundreds of pages of documents,
translated them into German and moved them through the State
Department to Austria.
   Of those indicted, 20 have been convicted, five are awaiting
trial, five remain at large, and two have been acquitted, Assistant
U.S. Attorney Jack Thar said. Charges against two were dismissed.
   Paul Heilbrunn, the alleged ringleader, faces possible life
imprisonment on charges including conspiracy to import and
distribute marijuana and running a continual criminal enterprise.
   Richard Heilbrunn faces up to 60 years in prison and Leary as
much as 30.
   The indictment says the ring operated in Indiana, California,
Connecticut, Washington, Alabama, Mississippi, Georgia, South
Carolina, Florida, Michigan and Virginia.
</TEXT>

</DOC>