<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0130 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1845EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Reax 1stLd-Writethru   12-27 0974</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Reax, 1st Ld - Writethru,a0610,1004</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nations Urge Support for New Government, End to Retribution</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS throughout to UPDATE relief efforts, former king saying
government won't last; no pickup</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By COTTEN TIMBERLAKE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Arab League on Wednesday urged Romania's new
government to prevent attacks on Arabs following reports that Arab
mercenaries fought for its executed dictator. Britain cautioned
Romanian reformers to refrain from revenge attacks.
   Civic Forum, the Czechoslovak opposition group, said Wednesday
the Czechoslovak consulate in Bucharest had confirmed reports of
2,000 foreign mercenaries fighting with those loyal to executed
dictator Nicolae Ceausescu.
   ``They were positive about Libyans and indicated Syrians and
Palestinians'' were involved, Civic Forum spokesman Michael
Zantovsky said in Prague after returning from Bucharest. He added
that the number of mercenaries could be even higher.
   Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev spoke by telephone with
Ion Iliescu, the new interim president, who thanked his old college
chum for his support.
   For the first time, Israel criticized Ceausescu, who had been
highly regarded for his support of the Jewish state in the face of
East bloc opposition.
   Romania's former King Michael, who said he would be willing to
return, said the new government may collapse.
   Emergency aid poured into the country and relief agencies said
they needed money and blood rather than more food, clothing and
other supplies.
   The list of nations recognizing the new government grew longer.
   U.N. Secretary-General Javier Perez de Cuellar promised all
possible humanitarian asssistance to Romania and said he hoped the
transition to democracy would be peaceful.
   Some countries, including Czecholsovakia and Norway, the first
nation to recognize the new government, arranged for diplomats to
travel to Romania.
   The provisional government, called the National Salvation
Committee, took power after Ceausescu's ouster Friday, saying it
will hold power until elections can be held in April. Ceausescu and
his wife, Elena, were executed by a firing squad Monday, the
government said.
   President Bush said he was ``amazed'' at the changes that have
taken place in Romania. ``We did say we were concerned that the
trial of Ceausescu should have been more open, but that's their
matter,'' he said, adding that army seemed to be bringing the
remaining pro-Ceausescu forces under control.
   China's Premier Li Peng and President Yang Shangkun on Wednesday
sent congratulations to Romania's new leaders and expressed hope
for continued friendship between the countries.
   Ceausescu's government had close ties with Beijing and Ceausescu
was one of the few world leaders to praise China's military
crackdown of the student democracy movement in June.
   British Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher praised ``the
extraordinary courage'' of the Romanian people in a warm message of
support to Iliescu.
   But Foreign Office Minister William Waldegrave said: ``There
mustn't be a bloodbath of revenge now.''
   Egypt, although expressing support for the new Romania
government, criticized the Ceausescus' execution without a public
trial.
   Officials from the 22-member Arab League met with the Romanian
ambassador in Tunis, Tunisia, to demand that Romanian officials
promise that Arabs living in Romania not be subjected to ``bad
treatment,'' a statement said.
   The Palestine Liberation Organization alleged Tuesday its
diplomatic staff and Palestinian students in Romania have been
attacked in recent days.
   Several Eastern European news agencies have accused
Palestinians, Libyans and Syrians of fighting alongside security
forces loyal to Ceausescu. Libya, Syria and the PLO have denied the
reports.
   In Jerusalem, a statement by Foreign Minister Moshe Arens to
Parliament was the first time Israel openly criticized Ceausescu.
   Referring to the thousands of victims of the anti-Ceausescu
rebellion, Arens said, ``Israel condemns the terrible massacres
carried out by Ceausescu's security forces.''
   Ceausescu was the only East bloc leader to maintain ties with
Israel after the 1967 Middle East War, when the others sided with
the Arabs.
   Joining the United States and a score of states recognizing the
new Romanian leadership were Denmark, Czechoslovakia, Malaysia and
North Korea, whose hard-line Communist government, led by Kim Il
Sung, was often compared to Ceausescu's.
   However, King Michael, who was deposed in 1947 when the
Communists took over and now lives in Switzerland, said he did not
expect the new government to last.
   ``The crowds do not accept what's there now, because they (the
government) have communist backgrounds. They have come from
Ceausescu's party, they worked with him before. So I don't think
the people will accept this,'' he said in a BBC television
interview broadcast Wednesday night.
   The king, who said he would return home immediately if he was
wanted, called the plan to hold elections in April ``a little
premature'' because Romania's political system had been destroyed
over the past 40 years.
   ``So there is actually no political groundwork to have elections
so soon,'' he said.
   Countries and charities sent or pledged millions of dollars,
food, tons of medical supplies and equipment and doctors and nurses
to help Romanians.
   Rony Brauman, president of the non-governmental aid agency
Doctors Without Borders which has 43 people working in 13 Romanian
cities, said in Paris the most pressing need is money.
   ``The urgent needs of Romania for drugs and medical and surgical
material are now covered,'' said Brauman. ``The problem now is
forwarding and distributing this aid as it's needed.''
   A Red Cross official told relief workers in Prague that blood is
the most urgent necessity.
   A committee has been set up in Bucharest under the auspices of
the Red Cross and the United Nations to coordinate assistance
arriving in Bucharest, the Red Cross said.
   In Washington, The American Red Cross urged people to send
money, not goods. It said 500 tons of food, clothing, blankets and
medical supplies have arrived or are en route.
   The Red Cross said it has received information that one
Hungarian Red Cross volunteer was fatally shot Friday while
bringing relief supplies to the western city of Timisoara.
</TEXT>

</DOC>