<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0649EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ToHalveAndHalveNot 1stLd-Writethru a0456 12-28 0635</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-To Halve And Halve Not, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0456,0646</SECOND>
<HEAD>Winning The Lottery: Testing The Ties That Bind</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Subs 5th graf, `The case ...' and 22nd graf, `David R. .. .'
to move up first reference to Ellis.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALLISON J. PUGH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   State lotteries may create millionaires overnight,
but the newfound wealth brings with it stresses that can make or
break even family ties.
   In two contrasting cases in the past week, a disabled New
Hampshire man gave his brother a lottery ticket worth millions,
while a hospitalized Massachusetts man and his wife lost their
legal battle over winnings they say his sister promised to share.
   ``Even in the most stable families, there's lots of things that
have to be renegotiated when someone gets a lot of money. But
chances are, the problems did exist before,'' said Dr. Lyn
Styczynski, who works at a family counseling center in Boston.
``It's not all a godsend.
   ``It's very stressful, and it's a strange stress, not one we get
a lot of preparation for.''
   The case of Earl and Elwood Havlock was extraordinary, however,
said David R. Ellis, a spokesman for the Massachusetts State
Lottery Commission.
   ``That's very unusual, very, very unusual, and very nice,'' he
said.
   Earl Havlock, who is disabled and unable to work, was buying his
brother a series of lottery tickets for Christmas when he hit a
$8.94 million jackpot.
   The 42-year-old man lives alone in the central New Hampshire
town of Ashland, on his Social Security checks and his brother's
generosity. He said he never considered holding the ticket for
himself, and he handed over the multimillion-dollar present to his
brother without qualms.
   ``Why not?'' Earl Havlock said. ``Ain't goin' back on my word.''
   Earl bought the winning tri-state lottery ticket for northern
New England on Saturday, a few minutes before the drawing.
   Elwood, who makes about $31,000 a year working for the Plymouth
Highway Department, said he plans to quit his job in three weeks.
   As for Earl, Elwood said he would continue to help care for him.
   ``Anything he needs or wants, I get him,'' Elwood said.
   In contrast, the gift of money served to rend the bonds between
Toni Ann Lydon and her sister-in-law, Catherine Beauregard. The
pair ran a beauty salon together until Beauregard and her husband,
Francis, bought a winning ticket in 1985.
   Last week, a Middlesex County Superior Court jury refused to
award Lydon and her husband, Thomas, half of a $2.8 million
Megabucks jackpot the Beauregards won. The jury found that previous
agreements the couples used to split ticket winnings were
unenforceable.
   Lydon and her husband, who is Catherine Beauregard's brother,
said the couples had plans to share the earnings as they had done
before.
   The day before the jury verdict, Thomas Lydon was admitted to
the hospital, his son, Bobby, said Wednesday.
   ``That's our main concern,'' said Bobby Lydon, who would not
comment on whether the family was seeking an appeal of the
decision. He would not comment on his father's illness.
   The Lydons suit said that after the Beauregards bought their
winning ticket, they told the Lydons they would pick them up to
drive to get their checks together. The Beauregards never showed
up, according to court papers.
   Edward Sokoloff, the Lydons' attorney, said the Beauregards
thereafter began denying there had ever been an agreement. He said
they claimed the splitting of previous smaller winnings with the
Lydons was simply a nice gesture on their part.
   Ellis said the Massachusetts State Lottery Commission does not
get involved in such disputes, which are rare.
   ``We cannot be involved in this. How could we get involved?'' he
said. ``We try to give them guidance, but it's up to them to
protect themselves. These are legal, voting-age adults.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>