<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0158 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1656EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Czech-Church     12-22 0651</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Czech-Church,0673</SECOND>
<HEAD>Czechoslovaks to Celebrate Christmas Mass in Freedom</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SYDNEY RUBIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For the Roman Catholic Church,
crippled and corrupted by the Communist state, Christmas will be a
joyous reawakening of hope after more than four decades of
persecution.
   ``It will be a Christmas in freedom,'' said Cardinal Frantisek
Tomasek, who will say Mass in Prague's gothic St. Vitus Cathedral
on Christmas Day. ``It is now possible for our priests to speak
freely.''
   Mass was said in churches last Christmas, but only by priests
licensed by the state. Authorities discouraged attendance by the
nation's estimated 9.3 million Catholics, 60 percent of the
population.
   Many believers stayed away while an unknown number of others met
secretly in cramped apartments for Christmas Mass performed by
banned priests.
   Now, everything is different. The peaceful revolution that began
in November bringing an end to Communist domination has opened
unlimited possiblities for the church.
   On Sunday, Mass will be said in virtually every church to
hundreds of thousands of faithful. Millions more will watch it
broadcast live on state TV, an event unimaginable a year ago.
   Last Christmas, the Rev. Vaclav Maly was shunned as a dissident.
Ducking secret police, he said Mass for about a dozen people who
gathered around him at great risk.
   This year, Maly will stand before hundreds on the altar of
Strahovsky Klaster, a 13th century monastery overlooking to Vltava
River.
   Jailed for joining the human rights group Charter 77, Maly
worked between stints in jail as a night watchman and coal stoaker
while ministering secretly. On Jan 1, he will begin leading his own
church.
   ``The 11 years I could not work in public were not in vain. I
met all levels of society and learned to talk to atheists as well
as believers. I was thrown into life with my faith as my only
support,'' said Maly, 39, whose name is being mentioned to replace
Tomasek as primate of Czechoslovakia.
   Tomasek, 90, said he plans to discuss his retirement with Pope
John Paul II when he visits Czechoslovakia, possibly next year.
   Tomasek himself spent three years in jail in the 1950s for being
named a bishop without state approval. Dozens of others shared his
fate.
   Monastic orders were dissolved, religious associations banned.
An estimated 8,000 of the country's 12,000 monks disappeared into
labor camps.
   Clergy became employees of the state, receiving their salaries
from the government who had veto power over all church appointments.
   As a result of this power, Bishoprics fell vacant while the
Vatican and Communist state argued over who should fill them. As
recently as a year ago, 10 of the nation's 13 bishoprics were empty.
   On Thursday, three of these were filled. By the end of next
month, Tomasek hopes they will all be full.
   ``We've waited 30 years for this,'' Tomasek said in an
interview. ``Now it seems the freedom of the church is certain and
will be fully respected.''
   The reform government announced last week that freedom of
religion will no longer be limited. The 1949 law requiring the
licensing of priest will be stricken from the books.
   But forbidden fruit is sweetest, and some fear that after the
first flush of religious freedom, believers may stray.
   ``Before it was a simple, the powerful against the powerless,''
Maly said. ``The church was attractive because it embodied values
denied or oppressed by Marxist ideology.''
   But in the pluralistic society being built, the church will have
to compete.
   ``There will be a richness of values, and the church's role is
an open question,'' Maly said. ``But I believe the church will
succeed in attracting more people than ever if it has the internal
strength to preach tolerance and help society remember forgotten
values like forgiveness, trust, love, faithfulness, respect for the
individual.''
   ``The church has an excellent chance. People are spiritually
hungry after such a long time.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>