<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0198 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1852EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-EastGermany 1stLd-Writethru a0791 12-20 0724</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0791,0742</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kohl Ends Visit With Appeal for Aid and Patience</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS grafs 2 `At the;' graf 9 `Kohl, who;' and graf 13 `Bild,
a' to restore dropped words. Picks up 14th, `Kohl and '</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NESHA STARCEVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DRESDEN, East Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chancellor Helmut Kohl of West
Germany recommended Wednesday that East Germany become stronger
economically before considering reunion with its rich and powerful
neighbor.
   At the end of an emotional visit to the East, he also discounted
fears of a ``Fourth Reich,'' an increasingly used term that raises
the specter of Adolf Hitler.
   President Francois Mitterrand of France, who arrived in East
Berlin for a three-day official visit hours after Kohl returned to
the West, cautioned against changing borders in Europe.
   ``For the whole of Europe, it would not be good _ indeed it
would be very dangerous _ to reopen the issue of the existing
borders,'' he said.
   Before returning to Bonn, Kohl said ``the economic potential of
the German Democratic Republic must be strengthened'' before
reunification became a possibility. He said he expected a treaty
expanding relations to be completed before East Germany's first
free elections, scheduled for May 6.
   Mitterrand, in an interview with East German TV before leaving
Paris, said relations between the two German states have ``very
special characteristics.''
   He was the first head of state or government of the three
western World War II Allies to visit East Berlin. Aides said his
trip should not be viewed as recognition of East Berlin as the East
German capital, which the Western Allies reject.
   The United States, Soviet Union, France and Britain still have
authority over Berlin as a result of postwar occupation of Hitler's
Third Reich.
   Kohl, who spent two days in East Germany, said at a final news
conference his government would address the concerns of other
European countries as the two Germanys move closer together.
   ``It's the most natural thing that Germans want to live
together, but we all know it cannot come immediately,'' he said.
   East Germany's parliament scheduled a session for Jan. 11-12 to
debate a new travel law and legislation to promote joint ventures
with Western companies.
   A draft law providing alternatives to military service for
conscientious objectors also will be on the agenda, the official
news agency ADN reported.
   Bild, a West German newspaper, said another passage through the
Berlin Wall would be opened Friday at the historic Brandenburg
Gate, a symbol of German unity.
   Kohl and Premier Hans Modrow agreed at their summit Tuesday that
East Germany woulds open a pedestrian crossing at the gate before
Christmas and would lift travel restrictions for West Germans on
Christmas Eve.
   They also signed several agreements and pledged to negotiate a
treaty bringing them closer together, especially by expanding
economic links.
   In a commentary Wednesday, ADN said the summit was a success,
but ``anyone who hoped'' Kohl would arrive ``with a sack full of
Rhine gold rejoiced too early.''
   Kohl told reporters inter-German issues that could be discussed
soon included improving traffic connections and solving joint
telecommunications and pollution problems.
   ``We will have to work intensively'' on a common German
currency, he said, and acknowledged that as ``one of the most
difficult questions.''
   Kohl said the aim of a common currency was to allow West Germans
to buy goods in East Germany. East Germany restricts such purchases
because state subsidies make many goods much cheaper than in West
Germany, and shortages are feared.
   In a sign of the rapidly increasing economic links, East Germany
announced Wednesday the first joint venture with a West German firm
had been signed. A compact disc manufacturing plant is to be built
by the Pilz company, based outside Munich, and the East German
state conglomerate Robotron.
   In Bonn, a working group of both nations on promoting tourism
held its first meeting.
   Kohl said West Germany will support reform in East Germany and
``not only talk, but act.'' He pledged, however, to avoid
``destabilization,'' an apparent reference to the power vacuum
created by the collapse of Communist Party control over the past
two months.
   Addressing the concerns of neighboring countries, Kohl said:
``Fears based in the past are understandable, but there is nothing
to be feared from the future. It's absurd to talk about a Fourth
Reich.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>