<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0113 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 2051EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Baltics     12-23 0364</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Baltics,0377</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gorbachev Denounces Separatist Sentiments</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Mikhail S. Gorbachev lashed out Saturday
at secessionist sentiments threatening to pull his country apart,
charging that they were leading to ``conflict and blood and death.''
   Gorbachev, jabbing his hands in the air, spoke to the Congress
of People's Deputies. A Communist Party Central Committee was
expected Sunday to discuss the Lithuanian party decision to break
with the national party.
   ``To realize the right to self-determination through secession
means to blow up the union, set people against each other and sow
conflict and blood and death,'' Gorbachev told the Congress.
``That's what separatists are pushing us toward.''
   The Congress broke into applause.
   Gorbachev has tried hard over the last several months to prevent
the Lithuanians from abandoning the national Communist Party. He
reacted with anger when it made its decision Wednesday.
   The Lithuanian party move is part of a long-range program to
restore the independence that the small Baltic republic enjoyed
between the world wars.
   Later Saturday, the Congress balked at a declaration denouncing
the 1939 Nazi-Soviet pact that led to the absorption of Lithuania
and two other Baltic lands, Latvia and Estonia, into the Soviet
Union.
   The declaration received 1,052 votes _ 70 short of the majority
required for approval. A total of 678 deputies voted ``no.''
   Supporters said they would try to win approval once more on
Sunday, the final day of the Congress.
   With its vote, the Congress ``demonstrated its conservatism,''
said Estonian deputy Marju Lauristen. ``Fifty years later, they
prefer to sleep with Stalin's dreams.''
   The resolution was supported by Baltic deputies who claim their
homelands were victims of dictator Josef Stalin's aggression. It
would condemn as invalid the secret protocol of the Soviet-Nazi
non-aggression pact on the eve of World War II.
   In Lithuania, activists reported that the republic's Communist
Party had split in two, one party professing loyalty to its mother
party in Moscow and another, larger party that has declared its
independence from Moscow.
   The activist Lithuanian people's front, known as Sajudis,
reported that party members who had opposed breaking off from
Moscow had formed their own leadership in a ``factual split'' from
the independent party.
</TEXT>

</DOC>