<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0085 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1405EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-StelloNomination 1stLd-Writethru a0448 12-19 0793</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Stello Nomination, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0448,800</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stello Nomination Attacked</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Top 8 grafs new with hearing; picks up 3rd graf pvs, A committee
vote.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A former Justice Department investigator said
today Victor Stello Jr., nominated by President Bush to head the
nation's nuclear arms production, lied to him during a probe of the
Three Mile Island nuclear accident.
   Julian Greenspun also told the Senate Armed Services Committee
that Stello had been ``a total bully'' when he worked at the
Nuclear Regulatory Commission.
   Greenspun said Stello, as the chief of staff at the NRC, ``lied
to me'' during Greenspun's investigation of the 1979 Three Mile
Island nuclear reactor accident in Pennsylvania.
   The former investigator said Stello had told him the power
plant's owner was not required to keep records of tests conducted
on cooling pipes. Greenspun said he later learned the records were,
in fact, required and were central to the Justice Department
investigation.
   Stello was scheduled to appear later in the day to respond to
the allegations by Greenspun and other witnesses called by the
committee.
   ``A number of things occurred that gave me great pause as a
prosecutor and as civil servant ... in terms of his candor and his
being a total bully at the NRC for people who had differences of
opinion,'' Greenspun told the committee.
   One of Stello's supporters on the committee, Sen. John Warner,
R-Va., asked Greenspun if he knew of any instances in which Stello
had broken the law.
   Greenspun responded, ``That's sort of like a politician saying,
`I ought to be elected because I haven't been indicted yet.'''
Greenspun did not charge that Stello had broken any laws in his
dealings with the investigator.
   Stello was apperaing before the panel for the second time in
little more than a month in his effort to become assistant energy
secretary for defense programs, the chief manager of the nation's
nuclear weapons program.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   A committee vote on the nomination is not expected before
Congress reconvenes Jan. 23.
   Energy Secretary James D. Watkins made a highly unusual personal
plea to the committee last month to confirm Stello, saying the
department urgently needed him in the post in order to carry out
major safety improvements at the arms plants. Many of the
facilities are closed down for safety and technical reasons.
   The committee on Nov. 17 deferred a decision on Stello, saying
it wanted to hear from additional witnesses, including officials
who worked with him during his 26 years at the Nuclear Regulatory
Commission, which governs civilian uses of nuclear power.
   Former NRC chairmen John Ahearne and Joseph Hendrie were to be
among those testifying today. Ahearne has said he believes Stello
is fully qualified for the weapons job.
   In a related development, Watkins told the House and Senate
armed services committees in letters sent last Friday that he
decided, at Stello's recommendation, to put off a decision on when
to restart the Savannah River nuclear production reactors until a
study of environmental impacts is completed.
   It was not clear whether the decision could mean a delay in
resuming Savannah River production of tritium, a man-made gas
needed to make nuclear warheads. Copies of Watkins' letter were
made public Monday by a member of the House panel.
   Stello was nominated for the Energy Department job in July. He
then began working as an adviser to Watkins on the Savannah River
restart project pending a Senate decision on his nomination. Last
month Watkins decided to give Stello a second-level appointment in
the weapons office, which does not require Senate confirmation.
   Three Democratic members of the committee _ Sens. John Glenn of
Ohio, Timothy Wirth of Colorado and Edward Kennedy of Massachusetts
_ have led the fight against Stello. They contend he is ill-suited
to improve safety conditions at the plants.
   Most members of the committee have not publicly said whether
they will vote for Stello.
   While serving as the chief staff official at the NRC, Stello was
accused of altering agency regulations at the request of utilities
that operate nuclear rectors, and authorizing cash payments to an
informant as part of a vendetta within the NRC.
   At his first confirmation hearing in November, Stello strongly
defended his professional record and said he was being unfairly
attacked by anti-nuclear forces and political opponents of
controversial decisions he made at the NRC.
   In a development that could stiffen resistance to Stello's
nomination, an outside investigator concluded in a report made
public Dec. 9 that the cash payments to an informant were made
because of personal conflicts within the NRC. That contradicts
Stello's assertion that the payments were made in order to obtain
information about wrongdoing that could affect safety at a nuclear
power plant.
</TEXT>

</DOC>