<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0032EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Romania-Ceausescu     12-27 0943</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Ceausescu,0975</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dictator's Rule Left 60,000 Dead, Romanians Say</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Wednesday AMs report.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIOREL URMA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nicolae Ceausescu reportedly killed
60,000 Romanians during his terrible reign, some sent to
Transylvanian torture chambers so horrible that the dead leader is
being compared to the monsters of myth.
   State media in post-Ceausescu Romania have begun to paint a
horrific portrait of a man who killed with the epic blood lust of
Count Dracula and the cavalier conscience of a real monster: Adolf
Hitler.
   His son, Nicu, was described as a drunk who ran down and killed
two pedestrians with his car and had a special room where he used
to rape women.
   Ceausescu's execution and the new revelations about his 24-year
rule has Romanians careening between revulsion and exultation.
   ``Oh, what wonderful news. The anti-Christ died on Christmas,''
a Bucharest radio announcer said after an announcement that the
former Communist leader and his wife, Elena, were executed.
Christmas carols then filled the air.
   A secret military tribunal in Monday convicted Ceausescu and his
wife of genocide, undermining the economy and attempting to flee
with more than $1 billion stashed in foreign banks.
   Romanian state television Tuesday broadcast a videotape of
Ceausescu and his wife after they were executed by a firing squad,
their bloody bodies slumped in front of a wall.
   In an official announcement, the television said the charge of
genocide covered the deaths of 60,000 people.
   ``This is the moment of truth. We got rid of the monsters who
mutilated our history. Let these tyrants be cursed. Romania's soil
should not accept their bodies,'' anchorman Viorel Popescu said on
TV and national radio. The broadcasts were monitored in Vienna.
   ``The name of Ceausescu should never be pronounced and written
again. It should be replaced with Dracula from Scornicesti,'' an
unidentified painter in the southern Transylvania city of Sibiu
told national radio. Scornicesti is the village where Ceausescu was
born Jan. 26, 1918, into a peasant's family.
   Even when he was alive, the iron-fisted Ceausescu had earned the
nickname of Vampirescu for his harsh rule, an allusion to Count
Dracula's horror tales set in 19th century Transylvania by Bram
Stoker.
   The United States and some other nations appeared critical of
the decision to try, convict and execute the Ceausescus so quickly.
   On Monday, a U.S. statement announcing the establishment of
diplomatic relations with Romania said: ``We regret the trial did
not take place in an open and public fashion.''
   But Silviu Brucan, a former Romanian ambassador to Washington
and leading dissident who is on the 37-member revolutionary
governing council, said the reason behind the Ceausescus' rapid
execution was to ``crush any hopes for a lethal coup'' by his hated
secret police, the Securitate.
   ``He was probably executed on Christmas Day to show that a new
hope, the hope of freedom, was born in Romania. Ceausescu was the
anti-Christ,'' an unidentified poet told the radio.
   During the Ceausescu reign, dissent was ruthlessly repressed by
the Securitate, a huge and sinister network of tens of thousands of
people.
   Debt repayment and mismanaged industrialization programs
triggered widespread food and energy shortages and dissidents faced
prison, commitment to mental hospitals, internal exile or house
arrest.
   Laws mandated the reporting of every unauthorized conversation
with a foreigner. Every typewriter had to be registered with the
police and censorship was far tighter than anywhere in the Soviet
bloc.
   Romanian TV monitored in Vienna showed a former ``torture
chamber'' ran by the Securitate in the western Romanian city of
Timisoara, where more then 12,000 protesters, including children
and women, were killed by the security forces when local riots
erupted Dec. 17.
   The revolution actually began in Timisoara two days earlier,
when small protests began eventually blossomed into the nationwide
uprising that toppled Ceausescu on Friday.
   ``It's terrifying what we see in this torture room,'' a
commentator said. ``Calcinated bodies, pieces of hairy scalps,
blood and tortured bodies lying on the floor. The victims were
brought here naked.
   ``How small were Hitler's lackeys. They were genuine angels (by
comparison). These are nightmarish images,'' the unidentified
commentator said.
   Tearful residents looking for missing loved ones congregated at
freshly unearthed mass graves containing the bodies of hundreds of
summarily executed people, some mutilated.
   One gruesome picture showed the body of an unborn baby whose
mother had been cut open by a bayonet.
   The army and revolutionaries who ransacked the Communist Party
office of Ceausescu's youngest son, Nicu, in Sibiu, southern
Transylvania, found hundreds of Kent cigarette packs and bottles of
whiskey and ``tuica,'' Romanian plum brandy.
   The television showed a back room where, according to the
commentator, Nicu, party chief of the Sibiu county, ``used to rape
women.'' Also displayed were stockings, makeup and underwear of his
purported victims.
   Nicu, 39, was known as a womanizer, heavy drinker and a fan of
Western fast cars who killed at least two people in traffic
accidents, Romanian officials said. He was arrested Dec. 22.
   ``Hitler had more dignity,'' the radio and TV commentator said.
   Romanian TV also showed pictures of the apartment of Ceausescu's
daughter, Zoia-Elena, where she was arrested.
   Among the items displayed were seven expensive watches, jewelry,
$95,000 in cash, valuable paintings taken from Romanian art museums
and pearls ``which we don't think are false.''
   ``Such a `modest' baggage for such a long trip (to jail),'' the
commentator said sarcastically.
   The TV also showed meat supposedly shipped in from Vienna for
her dogs.
   The media reported that Zoia, trained as a mathematician, asked
officers before being taken away by arresting officers: ``Is there
enough room for my two pets?''
</TEXT>

</DOC>