<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0145 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1937EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a PM-BusinessMirror Adv27   12-26 0562</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Business Mirror, Adv 27,0577</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv27</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release PMs Wednesday, Dec. 27</HEAD>
<HEAD>Upcoming: The Big Experiment With Market Economies</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN CUNNIFF</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Analyst</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Perhaps no decade this century has begun amid
greater economic unpheaval, challenge and potential than the 1990s,
and it isn't due solely to the fall of Communist regimes in Eastern
Europe.
   Western Europe too is in the midst of historic changes scheduled
to begin in little more than a year with integration of the
European Economic Community. Japan is facing adjustments because of
competition.
   The American challenge is as big as any of them. It must
solidify the great accomplishments of the 1980s, bring down
inflation, steer the way through an economic downturn, reduce the
trade deficit and balance budgets.
   Japan, which ascended to economic dominance in many trade areas
during the 1980s, is faced with demands to make its economy more
receptive to imports, to reduce its trade surplus and perhaps to
develop its infrastructure.
   China is trying to lift itself to world economic standards in
the production of goods. Hong Kong faces a change of sponsorship
from Britain to China. Taiwan, South Korea, Singapore and other
small Asian nations face the challenge of remaining competitive
while lifting living standards.
   Confronted with evidence of superior lifestyles in more highly
developed countries, much of Africa, Latin America and the Mideast
are in political and economic ferment that no longer can be
repressed.
   Amid the confusion, there are few blueprints for the future so
carefully defined as that of the European Economic Community. There
is no clear procedure for turning centrally planned economies into
market economies.
   Nor is there time to develop plans. Instant communication
produces instant change, but contributes little toward identifying
programs for carrying out the changes. The demands for change are
swift, the implementation remains slow.
   Through all of the changes, however, there is at least one
constant factor, opportunity.
   For major trading nations it means new markets. For
underdeveloped nations it means the chance to radically lift
depressed living standards. For all nations it means a more
productive allocation of resources and skills.
   Managed well, the changes could be a great leap forward for the
world community. Prospects for Western Europe, for example, already
had brightened with the scheduled removal of trade barriers among
12 nations in 1992.
   Now, says Albert Cox Jr., economic analyst with the investment
counseling firm Bil, Trainer Wortham Inc., ``there is the
possibility of massive growth in international trade in the next 10
years.''
   If that happens, he concludes, ``history tells us that greatly
enhanced world economic prosperity will be the end result.''
   No matter what economic changes occur throughout the world, they
are bound to have an impact on domestic politics and economic
direction within the United States.
   Already Washington is debating the possibilities of the
so-called peace dividend, or billions of dollars in funds that
supposedly will be available as a result of a cutback in defense
programs. But that is only the beginning.
   If the world's experimentation with market economies continues,
it will provide a showcase for those seeking to direct the American
economy toward the most efficient ends.
   Conceivably, it could even mean an approach to that long-sought
American goal of shrinking the federal government while maintaining
and even improving services to the public.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End advance PMs Wednesday, Dec. 27.</NOTE>

</DOC>