<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0158 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1530EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-Color     12-20 0548</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Color,0564</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bombs Shake The Night, Looting Rules the Day</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. helicopter gunships and fighter
jets thundered through the hot, moonlit night toward the caldron of
light surrounding Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega's headquarters.
   They whined overhead before diving toward the strongman's
compound two miles east of the Diablo Heights promontory
overlooking the Panama Canal.
   Armored personnel carriers and truckloads of soldiers roared out
of U.S. army bases on the roads below, surrounding the compound
with the crackle of machine guns, the cough of mortars and the
heavy thump of cannon.
   The sky blazed with tracer fire and, eventually, glowed with the
light of a giant fire.
   Daybreak revealed the compound reduced to rubble with only
scattered shots still being fired. A pall of acrid smoke spread
slowly over the city, as scores of dazed survivors fled their homes
in surrounding residential neighborhoods.
   Hundreds of refugees _ men, women, and children _ could be seen
in the street, walking in the tropical morning to churches,
hospitals, and schools, in search of safety.
   During the day the city turned into a scene of chaos. Armed
toughs who support Noriega took to the streets, some of them
commandeering cars. One resident said her car was stolen when a man
put a gun to her head and demanded the keys.
   Shortly before noon, the looting began. Even though sporadic
shooting continued all over the Panamanian capital, there were
dozens of people breaking into supermarkets and stores and making
off with whatever they could lay their hands on.
   Most of the looters were just poor people from the slums. Off
they went with stacks of food, cameras, home appliances, TV sets,
mattresses and clothes.
   Although a few scattered shots could be heard here and there, a
festive atmosphere reigned as people walked away with food, tires,
even refrigerators and stoves carried by four or five people at a
time.
   The major afternoon fighting, however, came in the San Miguelito
neighborhood to the northeast, a stronghold of the civilian
``Dignity Battalions'' that Noriega had set up to help enforce his
rule.
   Attack jets bombed and helicopters strafed a Defense Forces
barracks on top of San Miguelito, and once again came the refugees,
fleeing on foot or in their cars, if they could.
   At dozens of U.S. Army checkpoints, those who wanted to pass had
to get out of their cars and drop to their knees while the vehicle
was thoroughly searched.
   U.S. soldiers herded together about 300 Panamanian prisoners in
a field near Albrook Air Base, at the foot of Diablo Heights.
Relatives and friends of the captives waited across the street.
   Many of the prisoners had been taken in raids on houses in
Diablo Heights, a Panamanian neighborhood. Jeeps with mounted
machine guns had swept through the neighborhood during the night,
stopping at certain houses and taking the men prisoner.
   In one house, where four reporters were hiding along with the
residents, the owner said he had nothing to fear until his wife
noticed an 8-by-10 color photo of her husband as a student shaking
hands with none other than Cuban President Fidel Castro.
   She swiftly hid the photo, potentially offensive to American
eyes, in their bedroom.
</TEXT>

</DOC>