<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1237EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Top10Stories 1stAdd   12-28 0949</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Top 10 Stories, 1st Add,0966</SECOND>
<HEAD>UNDATED: traffic jams.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The earthquake, centered 75 miles south of San Francisco,
measured 7.1 on the Richter scale, the strongest to hit the United
States since the Alaska quake of 1964. It lasted 15 seconds, killed
67 people and injured 3,000 others. Property damage was placed at
$7 billion.
   A 50-foot section of the Bay Bridge collapsed, as did a few
apartment buildings, and a 1.5-mile stretch of double-decker
Interstate 880 toppled onto the lower roadway, crushing cars and
trapping motorists.
   Among the safest places during the quake: San Francisco's high
rises, built to strict building codes adopted after the San
Fernando quake of 1971.
   5. When the Supreme Court opened the door for states to regulate
the standards for abortions within their borders, limiting the 1975
Roe vs. Wade decision, it also moved the battleground between
pro-choice and anti-abortion advocates to state legislatures and
state elections.
   The anti-abortion side wanted to require teen-agers to seek
permission from their parents for abortions, or married women to
seek their husband's OK. Other questions focused on the use of
federal funds for abortions.
   Pennsylvania passed the most restrictive abortion statute in the
nation. Illinois settled a suit that would have limited abortions
in that state. Virginia and New Jersey elected governors who drew
considerable support from pro-choice voters. Pro-choice advocates
in Congress were readying a federal statute to broaden abortion
rights along the lines of Roe vs. Wade.
   The issue was sure to affect state and congressional elections
in 1990.
   6. The Colombian government declared war on the druglords in
August, in response to the assassination of a leading presidential
candidate.
   Within four months, 10 middle-level drug suspects had been
extradited to the United States. Drug traffickers retaliated with a
campaign of bombings and shootings that included a Dec. 8 car-bomb
attack that killed 63 people. The government also blamed the
druglords for the Nov. 27 bombing of an Avianca jetliner near
Bogota, which killed 107.
   The government claimed a major victory in December with the
killing by security forces of Gonzalo Rodriguez Gacha, a
billionaire leader of Colombia's biggest cocaine gang, the Medellin
cartel, and the man accused of directing the campaign of terror.
But the euphoria over Gacha's death was tempered by fears that his
reputed partner, Pablo Escobar Gaviria, would seek retribution.
   In the United States, a record 21.4 tons of cocaine was seized
near Los Angeles and near-record amounts intercepted elsewhere.
President Bush unveiled a $7.9 billion drug control strategy, and
planned to meet with South American leaders in Colombia in February
1990.
   7. For a week in September, Hurricane Hugo cut a wide swath of
destruction along a 2,300-mile path from the Caribbean to the
Carolinas. The storm killed 56 people in the Caribbean and 40 more
on the mainland, despite an exodus of residents along the Southeast
coast.
   In hard-hit St. Croix, 90 percent of the houses and buildings
were destroyed by Hugo's 200-mph winds. Hundreds of looters
plundered stores of everything from food and clothing to VCRs and
jewelry in the aftermath of the storm, prompting President Bush to
send Army troops, FBI agents and federal marshals to restore order
in the U.S. territory. Officials say it could be spring before
power is restored. Full recovery could take years.
   In South Carolina, the storm did nearly $6 billion in damage.
Hugo demolished downtown Charleston, which had not been hit by a
major hurricane in 30 years. It also left homeless an estimated
16,000 South Carolinans, many of them beach residents who vowed to
rebuild.
   8. The scandals that rocked Congress, the Defense Department and
the Department of Housing and Urban Development seemed endless. A
congressman admitted to a brief sexual relationship with a man who
claimed to run a male prostitution ring. The speaker of the House
resigned after being cited for ethics violations. Five senators
were to be investigated for intervening with federal regulators on
behalf of a scandal-ridden savings and loan. Pentagon procurement
irregularities led to indictments, and HUD influence peddling
became a running national story.
   In three separate cases, congressmen were convicted of
money-laundering, perjury and contributing to the delinquency of a
minor.
   Finally Congress passed the Ethics Reform Act of 1989 that would
bar congressmen, but not senators, from accepting fees for
speeches, starting in 1991. In return, congressmen, but not
senators, would receive a $24,000-plus pay raise. The act also
provided substantial raises for other top executive and judicial
branch officials.
   9. The so-called thrift institutions _ the nation's savings and
loans _ turned out not to be thrifty at all. When the failures
piled up, Congress passed a $159 billion bailout bill in August and
established the Resolution Trust Corp. to oversee the rescue of the
pillaged S&amp;Ls, which had grown to 280 by the end of the year. In
December the RTC was pressing the S&amp;Ls under its control to begin
selling more than $300 billion in assets.
   The RTC had disposed of 33 of the ailing thrifts and had its eye
on 220 more.
   10. Hampered by the non-availability of secret documents, the
Iran-Contra investigation ground on, trying to unravel the scheme
by which the United States sold arms to Iran and used the proceeds
to finance pro-American guerillas in Nicaragua.
   Marine Lt. Col. Oliver North, the former National Security
Council aide who won national prominence in dramatic congressional
hearings probing the arms deals, was convicted of three of 12
felony counts, including destroying or falsifying government
documents and receipt of an illegal gratuity. Punishment totaled
over $500,000 in fines and more than five years in prison.
   At year's end there were still cases pending in the Iran-Contra
investigation.
</TEXT>

</DOC>