<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1234EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India     12-21 0360</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India,0370</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Government Wins Confidence Vote</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RAJU GOPALAKRISHNAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister V.P. Singh's minority
government passed its first test of support Thursday, winning a
vote of confidence in Parliament as expected.
   A chorus of ``Yes!'' arose when the vote was called and Speaker
Rabi Ray of Singh's People's Party declared the motion carried. The
Congress Party of former Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi abstained.
   Singh, who led a broad coalition in the November elections,
presented the confidence motion. He had pledges of support from
several parties that would have given him more half the votes if a
roll- call vote had been necessary.
   He took office Dec. 2, ending Gandhi's five-year tenure as prime
minister, and named his Cabinet three days later. Under a deadline
set by President Ramaswamy Venkataraman, he had until Jan. 1 to
obtain approval from the legislators.
   Shortly before the vote was taken, Singh told Parliament his
government showed India could turn from personalities to issues in
choosing a leader.
   ``The delicate balance of political forces may turn out to be
the most glorious occasion for our democracy,'' said the new prime
minister, whose victory ended a hold on power by the Congress Party
that extended back through Gandhi's mother, Indira, to his
grandfather, Jawaharlal Nehru.
   It is only the second time since independence from Britain in
1947 that the Congress Party has not controlled the government.
   This also was the first time a prime minister or his party had
initiated a confidence motion.
   The constitution does not require a confidence vote for a new
government, but neither does it prohibit one. President
Venkataraman felt a vote was the best way to determine whether
Singh's government could function.
   In the elections, Gandhi's Congress Party won 193 of the 525
seats in the lower house of Parliament, making it the largest
single party. The People's Party won 137 seats and its partners in
the National Front alliance won three.
   Venkataraman asked Singh, 58, to form a government after he had
obtained pledges of support from a Hindu nationalist party, with 86
seats, and a leftist alliance with 52.
</TEXT>

</DOC>