<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0263 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1805EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-WallStreet 2ndLd-Writethru   12-21 0488</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Wall Street, 2nd Ld-Writethru,0508</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stocks Post Small Gain</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS last graf to CORRECT Amex close and change.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHET CURRIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The stock market struggled to a small gain
Thursday, halting a week-long slide.
   Analysts said traders drew some mild encouragement from signs
that the Federal Reserve was continuing little by little to relax
its credit policy.
   The Dow Jones average of 30 industrials, down 73.16 points in
the five preceding sessions, gained 3.20 to 2,691.13.
   Advancing issues outnumbered declines by about 3 to 2 in
nationwide trading of New York Stock Exchange-listed stocks, with
932 up, 627 down and 460 unchanged.
   With five trading days left in 1989, the Dow Jones industrial
average shows a net gain of 522.56 points, or 24.1 percent, since
the start of the year.
   Analysts said evidence of a new move Wednesday toward easier
credit by the Federal Reserve encouraged buyers to nibble warily at
stocks that have lately suffered from worries about a possible
recession in 1990.
   Brokers also said traders remained hopeful that stock prices
might benefit from the so-called January effect, a historical
tendency for the market _ and especially smaller stocks _ to show
greater-than-usual strength in the first few weeks of a new year.
   One explanation often offered for the January effect is the
lifting of yearend selling pressures from investing institutions
cleaning losers out of their portfolios and individual investors
realizing losses for tax purposes.
   Stride Rite jumped 3] to 27~. Late Wednesday an investor group
proposed a bid for the company at $32 a share.
   Among recently depressed stocks, Walt Disney rose 2\ to 114\;
Federal National Mortgage [ to 34{; General Motors ~ to 42], and
International Business Machines { to 95[.
   Boston Edison dropped 1{ to 20[. The company cut its quarterly
dividend from 45.5 cents to 38 cents a share.
   Caterpillar, which projected a decline in fourth-quarter
earnings from the previous three months, fell 1~ to 57|.
   Magnetek lost 1 to 8| in one of the day's biggest percentage
declines. The company said a jury ruled against its Universal
Manufacturing subsidiary in a breach-of-contract case involving
L.M.P. Corp.
   Volume on the floor of the Big Board came to 175.15 million
shares, against 176.52 million in the previous session. Nationwide,
consolidated volume in NYSE-listed issues, including trades in
those stocks on regional exchanges and in the over-the-counter
market, totaled 212.70 million shares.
   As measured by Wilshire Associates' index of more than 5,000
actively traded stocks, the market increased $18.18 billion, or
0.55 percent, in value.
   The NYSE's composite index of all its listed common stocks
gained .96 to 190.50.
   Standard &amp; Poor's industrial index rose 1.95 to 393.81, and
S&amp;P's 500-stock composite index was up 1.94 at 344.78.
   The NASDAQ composite index for the over-the-counter market
climbed 4.15 to 441.14. At the American Stock Exchange, the market
value index closed at 369.55, up 1.37.
</TEXT>

</DOC>