<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0169 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1940EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-Panama-Americans-Thumbnails     12-22 1050</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Panama-Americans-Thumbnails,1102</SECOND>
<HEAD>Brief Look at Those Who Died in Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY89</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a glimpse at some of the Americans killed during the
Panama invasion. The Pentagon has released only these names thus
far.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Staff Sgt. Larry R. Barnard</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Barnard, who had just turned 29, was a nine-year veteran Army
infantryman and Ranger. He was the son of a Methodist minister, the
Rev. Marilyn Barnard, and her husband Raymond, of Hallstead, Pa.
   Barnard married his high-school sweetheart, Tammy, and they had
a 10-year-old daughter and a younger set of twins.
   ``Larry was a fine kid,'' said Jerry Thomson, athletic director
at Blue Ridge High School, where Barnard played football and other
sports.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Pfc. Roy Dennis Brown Jr.</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The 19-year-old infantryman was a native of Buena Park, Calif.
Brown's mother, Julie Otto, also of Buena Park, said her son had
phoned the family a week before his death, saying his unit had been
put on alert and was preparing to go into combat.
   Friends and relatives described the blond, blue-eyed young man
as a classic ``California boy'' who had looked forward to joining
the Armed Forces when he was still a student at Magnolia High
School in Anaheim. He had played trombone in the marching band.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Pfc. Vance T. Coates</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Travel was one of the reasons the 18-year-old Coates joined the
Army, said a friend who attended high school with the Great Falls,
Mont., native. Coates dropped out of Great Falls High School to
enter the service in February. He completed infantry training at
Fort Benning, Ga., last summer.
   ``He liked survival sorts of stuff and hunting and fishing,''
said the friend, 17-year-old Sung Kokko. Julie Martin, mother of
another of Coats' friends, said that Coats wanted to make a career
of the Army and possibly become a Green Beret.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Lt. j.g. John Patrick Connors</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Connors, 25, was a member of the elite Navy operations unit
known as the SEALS. Officials said he died during an assault on a
Panamanian airfield.
   The Arlington, Mass., resident was a 1987 graduate of Worcester
Polytechnical Institute, in Worcester, which he attended on Naval
ROTC scholarship. Paul Bennett, Connors' ROTC commander, described
him as ``a quiet kid, not the kind of kid who walks around with
Soldier of Fortune in his back pocket. But he loved his country,
and had a strong sense of value and freedom.''
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Pfc. Jerry Scott Daves</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A member of the 1st Battalion of the 504th Parachute Infantry
Regiment, the 20-year-old Daves flew out of Pope Air Force Base in
North Carolina late Tuesday for Panama.
   ``He wanted to be a soldier all through high school,'' said Ray
Parnell, a longtime friend. ``He got his chance. I'm sure he went
wanting to go.''
   Daves joined the Army in August 1988 shortly after graduating
from Southview High School in Hope Mills, N.C.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Pfc. Martin D. Denson</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Denson, 21, was a native of Abilene, Texas. He entered the Army
in January and was stationed at Fort Bragg, N.C., as an infantryman.
   His father, Jerry, had put an ``Airborne Emblem'' in front of
his home as a show of support just 15 minutes before learning his
son was dead. ``He lived and breathed football. He was my best
friend,'' said the elder Denson.
   At Jim Ned High School in Tuscola, near Abilene, Denson had been
president of his senior class and was involved in Future Farmers of
America, the science club, dairy judging and worked on the
yearbook. ``He was really sharp and a real good writer and very
creative,'' said his English teacher, Carol Hughes.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Spc. William D. Gibbs</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Gibbs, 22, is survived by his wife, Kimberley, who is pregnant
with the couple's first child, due in March.
   ``He had just talked to his wife Sunday,'' his stepmother, Erika
Gibbs, said Thursday. ``He said he was OK. He told Kimberly not to
worry. The next thing we heard was that he had been killed.''
   It was the second trip to Panama this year for the Modesto,
Calif., native. His infantry unit was part of a hihly mobile combat
division involved in a six-month training exercise staged in the
Central American nation that began in January.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Candy Helin</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Candy Helin was the only civilian reported killed. The
43-year-old teacher had spent most of her adult life in Panama,
where she taught gifted students. Neither the State Department nor
her sister-in-law knew her U.S. hometown.
   Mrs. Helin was killed early Wednesday when a uniformed man
jumped from the grass and fired at her vehicle as she and her
husband, Steve, drove home from dinner with friends.
   Steve Helin, who was not injured, works as a civilian financial
analyst for an organization that oversees operation of the Panama
Canal. The couple have two children, Stephanie, 16, and Tracey, 20.
   ``She was a very creative, intelligent person,'' Jane Sheaffer,
of Dixon, Ill., said of her sister-in-law. ``It's quite a waste of
a life that was making a lot of contributions for our country and
to their country.''
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Cpl. Garreth C. Isaak</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The Marine corporal had been in Panama since October and was
shot in the neck and right arm an hour after the invasion began. He
died eight days shy of his 23rd birthday.
   Isaak was a native of Greenville, S.C., and had attended Bob
Jones Academy, a Christian prep school affiliated with Bob Jones
University in Greenville, until the 10th grade, but graduated from
a high school in Harvey, N.D. His father, Albert, is a biology
professor at Bob Jones University, and his mother, JoAnn, is a
librarian there. Isaak had two older sisters.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Spec. Phillip S. Lear</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Lear, 21, of Westminster, S.C., was with the Army's 2nd Ranger
Batallion stationed at Fort Lewis, Wash. He planned to wed a Port
Orchard, Wash., woman and study architecture at the University of
Washington or University of Puget Sound after his enlistment was to
end next summer.
   When he joined the airborne Rangers in 1987 he fulfilled a
long-held dream to be a paratrooper with the elite infantry unit.
While at West-Oak High School in Westminster he participated in
Junior ROTC, winning three awards in his senior year. He is
survived by his parents, Harold and Miriam, four brothers and a
sister.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>