<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0935EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DogEyes     12-22 0358</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Dog Eyes,0369</SECOND>
<HEAD>World Not Just Black and White To Dogs, Study Concludes</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SANTA BARBARA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The world isn't all black and white
for man's best friend, but pooches are better at spotting Blue and
Big Red than Old Yeller, a research study concluded.
   Three dogs named Flip, Gypsy and Retina helped scientists at the
University of California, Santa Barbara, dispel the belief that
dogs live a colorless life, according to a study published in
January's Scientific American and in the journal Visual
Neuroscience.
   The yearlong study found that dogs do distinguish colors, but it
also showed the animals have limited color vision, similar to men
who suffer from a type of colorblindness once known as ``green
blindness.''
   The dogs could not distinguish yellow, green, orange and some
other shades, the study said.
   Psychologists Jay Neitz and Gerald H. Jacobs and technician
Timothy Geist used greyhounds Flip and Gypsy and toy poodle Retina
in the studies exploring photopigments, the molecules in the eye's
receptor cells that help differentiate colors.
   The researchers trained the dogs to respond to colored lights on
a display panel, the study said.
   In each test, two lights would be of the same color, while a
third would be different. The dogs were trained to push the
different light with their noses, and they got a snack if they
pushed the correct one.
   The dogs had no trouble distinguishing red and blue _ the colors
at the opposite end of the spectrum. They could even tell more
subtle differences in the similar hues of blue and violet.
   But the dogs ``could not discriminate among colors from
greenish-yellow through orange to red,'' the account in Scientific
American said.
   The study was partly funded by the National Eye Institute.
   Jacobs, interviewed by telephone Thursday, said the research
team was careful to make sure the dogs weren't simply
distinguishing between shades of gray.
   ``We went to elaborate lengths to make sure they could not go on
brightness cues,'' he said.
   Besides disproving the popular notion that dogs see in black and
white, the study gives insight into the eye's mechanisms for
differentiating color, he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>