<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0154EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Students-Drugs     12-19 0716</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Students-Drugs,710</SECOND>
<HEAD>Survey: White Students More Likely Than Blacks to Use Drugs</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAROLYN SKORNECK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   White students are more likely than black
students to use all kinds of drugs _ from liquor to cocaine and
hallucinogens _ according to a nationwide survey of drug use by
sixth to 12th grade students.
   ``For all too long, this problem has been portrayed as a black
problem, and I think the end result has been that there are some
people who have not really cared a lot about it because of that,''
said Judge Reggie Walton, associate director of the Office of
National Drug Control Policy.
   ``This is an American problem, not just a black problem, and all
of us have to get on with the business of dealing with this
problem, because I believe that if we do that, that we can, in
fact, prevail,'' Walton said.
   The figures from the Parents' Resource Institute for Drug
Education Inc. were released Monday.
   Fifteen percent of the 58,898 black students surveyed nationwide
said cocaine was ``very easy to get,'' compared with 8 percent of
the 296,180 white students surveyed, according to the PRIDE results.
   However, totals for cocaine use _ and for use of liquor,
marijuana, hallucinogens and stimulants as well _ in junior high
schools, senior high schools and the senior year of high school
showed that across the board, a higher percentage of white students
than black students were using drugs.
   ``It goes against conventional wisdom _ particularly television
has portrayed the problem of drug abuse in the United States as a
black, inner city problem,'' said Doug Hall, vice president of
PRIDE.
   The focus on inner-city drug use by blacks ``feeds the
increasing expressions of racism that surface daily in our
country,'' PRIDE co-founder Marsha Keith Schuchard said at a news
conference Monday.
   Atlanta-based PRIDE surveyed the students at 958 schools in 38
states during the 1988-89 school year, including students in
inner-city areas in Atlanta, Chicago, Dallas, Houston, New York and
Washington D.C., Hall said.
   Of the 40,000 high school seniors surveyed, only 4 percent of
the black students said they had used cocaine at least once in the
previous year, while 7 percent of the white students said they had
done so.
   Meanwhile, 11 percent of black male seniors and 12 percent of
white male seniors said they used marijuana very frequently,
meaning at least once a week. Fourteen percent of black male
seniors and 17 percent of white male seniors said they used liquor
very frequently.
   The students surveyed filled out anonymous questionnaires that
were spot checked internally with somewhat duplicated questions to
determine the truthfulness of responses. There also were occasional
re-tests of groups of students, Hall said. There was no overall
margin of error because the results were based on actual responses
and the survey was not a scientific, random poll.
   The survey's findings for overall drug use by seniors in high
school, totals for senior high school students including 12th
graders and junior high school students were:
   _Cocaine: 7 percent of white seniors, 4 percent of black
seniors; 5 percent of white high school students, 3 percent of
black high school students; 2 percent of white junior high
students, 1 percent of black junior high students.
   _Liquor: 65 percent of white seniors; 37 percent of black
seniors; 57 percent of white high school students, 29 percent of
black high school students; 28 percent of white junior high
students; 13 percent of black junior high students.
   _Marijuana: 29 percent of white seniors; 17 percent of black
seniors; 24 percent of white high school students, 13 percent of
black high school students; 8 percent of white junior high
students; 5 percent of black junior high students.
   _Hallucinogens: 6 percent of white seniors; 2 percent of black
seniors; 5 percent of white high school students; 2 percent of
black high school students; 2 percent of white junior high
students; 1 percent of black junior high students.
   _Stimulants: 11 percent of white seniors; 3 percent of black
seniors; 11 percent of white high school students, 2 percent of
black high school students; 4 percent of white junior high
students; 2 percent of black junior high students.
   PRIDE was founded by a group of parents to fight drug abuse.
</TEXT>

</DOC>