<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0262 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1157EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-Eastern-American 1stLd-Writethru   12-18 0331</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Eastern-American, 1st Ld-Writethru,0341</SECOND>
<HEAD>Accord Near on Sale of Eastern Routes, Report Says</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Recasts grafs 1-2. Lead prospects uncertain</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eastern Airlines agreed over the weekend to sell
its prized South American routes and other assets to American
Airlines as part of a plan to restructure from a 9-month-old
strike, a published report said today.
   Eastern was scheduled to meet with its creditors committee in
New York before releasing a statement, a company spokeswoman said.
   Eastern spokeswoman Karen Ceremsak wouldn't comment directly
about The Wall Street Journal story, which said a tentative
agreement in the months-long negotiations had been reached over the
weekend. The report said the transaction will total $450 million to
$500 million.
   American Airlines spokesman Ed Stewart said the company had no
comment.
   Eastern, which entered Chapter 11 bankruptcy reorganization on
March 9, five days after being crippled by a strike of its three
unions, had planned to sell its South American routes as part of
plans to emerge as a smaller carrier. Negotiations with American,
which has coveted the South American routes for its expansion of
Miami regional operations, stalled in August.
   Eastern initiated new talks some two months ago, amid concerns
about cash shortfalls in Eastern's rebuilding plan.
   Eastern has delayed presenting a new reorganization plan to
creditors while the negotiations have continued. Eastern hopes to
emerge from Chapter 11 in early 1990.
   The Journal report today, citing unidentified sources, said
American would get Eastern's South American and Caribbean routes,
plus gates and landing sites at various airports. American also
would obtain some other assets of Eastern's parent Texas Air Corp.,
including Continental Airlines' Miami-London route, the report said.
   The Journal reported that the agreement came about after
Continental agreed to settle a long-standing lawsuit against AMR
Corp., American's parent company. That suit sought as much as $1
billion in damages and alleged that American's computer
reservations system gave American an unfair advantage.
   The sale of international routes must receive government
approval.
</TEXT>

</DOC>