<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0636EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-HongKong     12-21 0576</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hong Kong,0590</SECOND>
<HEAD>Reaction Mixed to British Nationality Package for Hong Kong</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAN BIERS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HONG KONG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A plan in Britain to give residency rights to
225,000 people from Hong Kong received mixed reviews today, with
some arguing it would be too narrow to be of much help to the
colony before China takes over in 1997.
   ``A little that will not go very far,'' read the headline over
The Hong Kong Standard newspaper's editorial on the package.
   The nationality plan, announced Wednesday by British Foreign
Secretary Douglas Hurd, is designed to prevent 50,000 key Hong Kong
residents and their families from emigrating before the colony
reverts to China.
   He argued that giving important people in the civil service,
business and the professions the right to live in Britain was
essential to persuade them to not join the ``brain drain'' of top
white-collar workers leaving because of concern over impending
Communist Chinese rule.
   China's promise that Hong Kong can maintain its capitalist
system for 50 years and enjoy a high degree of autonomy has met
with widespread skepticism here, particularly after the bloody
suppression of spring pro-democracy protests in Beijing.
   Hong Kong's governor, Sir David Wilson, praised the plan as
helping ``create the sort of stability and the reassurances for a
substantial number of people which we have been looking for.''
   Honor Hong Kong, a group of top business leaders formed to press
for right of residency in Britain, also welcomed the package as
encouraging key white-collar staff to remain in the territory.
   ``We argued for more, we should have been given more; but this
figure - we believe _ is a basis on which to rebuild confidence in
our economy,'' said Simon Murray, the group's chairman.
   Murray noted that a private study released last week estimated
as many as 315,000 key workers were essential to maintaining Hong
Kong's vibrant economy.
   Community leaders on the colony's Legislative Council who have
long argued that the right of residency should be granted to all
3.25 million Hong Kong Chinese eligible for British passports vowed
to pressure London to broaden the program.
   Some expressed worries the plan will divide the community as
only 4 percent of the colony's 5.7 million people will qualify.
Fears also were voiced that the offer will not stop the brain drain.
   The lobbying group British Citizens for Hong Kong issued a
statement saying the plan ``will have no effect in stemming the
outflow and ... is a divisive and dishonorable gesture of dismissal
by Britain ...''
   Wong-hyo, vice chairman of the Hong Kong Chinese Civil Servants'
Association, was quoted by the Standard as saying the package was
``inadequate to keep up morale and retain staff.''
   Although the Xinhua News Agency, China's official representative
in the colony, refused to comment on the package, a newspaper that
often reflects Beijing's thinking was critical of the plan.
   The Chinese-language Wen Wei Po argued that the package showed
Britain was only concerned with maintaining the territory's
prosperity until 1997.
   ``If the society is divided into two types of people who have
different futures and benefits, it would be very difficult for them
to unite and live through the transitional period and the years
after,'' the paper said in an editorial.
   ``To solve Hong Kong's confidence crisis, Hong Kong people
should develop trust in themselves'' and put into effect the ``one
country, two systems'' policy China has promised for the territory,
it said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>