<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0650EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     12-26 0579</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0598</SECOND>
<HEAD>Most of Nation Gets Break From Cold _ But Southeast Still Frozen</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Michigan and Wisconsin braced for heavy snow and the Deep South
shivered early today, but much of the nation basked in a winter
break from an arctic front.
   In Michigan, a cold front produced squalls with heavy snow
Christmas night and early today. Wakefield received 10 inches of
snow, Ironwood had 6 inches and Marquette measured 5 inches.
   In northwest Wisconsin, forecasters predicted up to a foot of
snow tonight. Strong winds also were expected for all five of the
Great Lakes, where gale warnings were in effect.
   A warm front, meanwhile, produced scattered snow showers late
Monday from Tennessee and the Ohio Valley to New York and the
middle Atlantic coast region.
   Among the cities getting fresh snow this morning were
Louisville, Ky., Indianapolis, Cincinnati, Cleveland, Detroit,
Albany, N.Y., and Portland, Maine.
   Monday's storm produced enough new snow at Erie, Pa., to push
their snowfall total for the month past the previous December
record of 59.9 inches set in 1985.
   It was a cold Christmas day in Florida. Afternoon highs across
the state were 44 to 56 degrees, following morning lows which
dipped to 17 at Crestview and Tallahassee.
   The cold continued today in the South, with freezing
temperatures this morning in Jacksonville, Fla., Macon, Ga., and
Atlanta.
   Parts of California also were cold on Monday. The high
temperature Monday at Bakersfield was 38 degrees, a record for the
coldest high on the date.
   Temperatures warmed into the 50s in the central Plains and the
lower Mississippi Valley.
   The hot spot in the nation Monday was the Southern California
town of San Juan Capistrano, with a high of 84 degrees.
   The nation's coldest spot was Milo, Maine, at 22 degrees below
zero.
   Record lows for Christmas Day: Fort Lauderdale, Fla., 29
degrees; Key West Fla., 46; Miami, 30; Miami Beach, Fla., 33; and
Wilmington, N.C., 0, an all-time record.
   Other reports at 6 a.m. EST today:
   _EAST: Albany, N.Y., 22 snow; Atlanta 28 partly cloudy; Boston
28 cloudy; Buffalo 22; Charleston, S.C., 32 fair; Chattanooga 24
fair; Cincinnati 29 snow; Cleveland 21 snow; Detroit 13 blowing
snow; Hatteras 34 windy; Jacksonville 30 fair; Key West 52 fair;
Knoxville 29 cloudy; Macon 31 fair; Miami 39 fair; New York 26
snow; Philadelphia 26 cloudy; Pittsburgh 22 snow; Portland, Maine,
24 cloudy; Richmond 31 cloudy; Tampa 43 partly cloudy; Washington,
D.C., 25 foggy.
   _CENTRAL: Birmingham 26 fair; Bismarck 12; Denver 28 fair; Des
Moines 08 fair; Fort Worth 35; Indianapolis 23 snow; Kansas City 22
fair; Little Rock 35 fair; Louisville 34 cloudy; Memphis 31 fair;
Nashville 33 fair; New Orleans 39 fair; North Platte 20 fair;
Oklahoma City 37 fair; Omaha 11 fair; Rapid City 29 fair; St. Louis
29 partly cloudy; Minneapolis-St. Paul 02 fair; Sault Ste. Marie 10
fair; San Antonio 34 fair.
   _WEST: Albuquerque 28 fair; Anchorage 23 cloudy; Boise 19 foggy;
Casper 32 fair; Fairbanks 02 fair; Great Falls 47 windy; Honolulu
68 fair; Las Vegas 42 partly cloudy; Los Angeles 58 foggy; Medford
25 foggy; Pendleton 27 foggy; Phoenix 48 partly cloudy; Portland,
Ore., 33 foggy; Reno 22 fair; Salt Lake City 21 snow; San Diego 57
cloudy; San Francisco 45 fair; Seattle 39 foggy; Spokane 31 foggy.
   _INTERNATIONAL: Calgary 48 fair; Montreal 19 snow; Ottawa 19
snow; Regina 25 partly cloudy; Toronto 21 cloudy; Winnipeg 07
partly cloudy; Merida 59; San Juan 71.
</TEXT>

</DOC>