<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0351EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BusCrash-Chronology     12-22 0331</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bus Crash-Chronology,0346</SECOND>
<HEAD>Key Events in Drunken-Driving Crash That Killed 27</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Bus Crash Trial, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOUISVILLE, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a chronology of key events in the
nation's worst drunken-driving disaster:
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>1988</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   May 14 _ Church bus from Radcliff, Ky., carrying 67 people
collides with pickup traveling the wrong way on Interstate 71 near
Carrollton, Ky. Fiery crash kills 27 people _ 24 of them children.
   May 16 _ Larry Mahoney, a chemical plant worker who drove the
pickup, is charged with 27 counts of capital murder. Authorities
say Mahoney had a blood-alcohol level nearly 2{ times the legal
limit.
   May 19 _ Thousands gather on high school football field in
Radcliff to mourn victims; funerals begin.
   May 20 _ Mahoney pleads innocent to charges; Kentucky begins
crackdown on drunken drivers and offers free safety inspection of
private buses.
   July 22 _ Carroll County grand jury indicts Mahoney on 27 counts
of wanton murder.
   Aug. 2-4 _ National Transportation Safety Board holds hearing on
bus crash in Louisville.
   Oct. 10 _ Mahoney released from jail on $540,000 property and
cash bond.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>1989</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   March 29 _ National Transportation Safety Board releases
findings, saying Kentucky needs tougher drunken driving laws and
that states should set a date for school buses not meeting 1977
federal standards.
   May 14 _ First anniversary of bus crash marked by ceremonies
held in memory of the victims. Monument in their honor unveiled at
Radcliff cemetery.
   June 3 _ Federal officials approve highway signs marking the
crash site on I-71.
   Nov. 8 _ Mahoney's trial begins with jury selection.
   Nov. 20 _ Testimony begins.
   Dec. 14 _ Mahoney takes the stand, says he's sorry for the bus
crash and deaths he is accused of causing.
   Dec. 21 _ After deliberating for 11 hours, jury convicts Mahoney
of 27 counts of second-degree manslaughter, one count of drunken
driving, 12 counts of assault and 41 counts of wanton endangerment.
Jury begins deliberating what sentence to recommend.
</TEXT>

</DOC>