<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0099 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1940EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BurkinaFaso 1stLd-Writethru a0594 12-25 0296</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Burkina Faso, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0594,0300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Burkina Faso Reports Coup Foiled</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: ADDS 2 grafs on no details known.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OUAGADOUGOU, Burkina Faso (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government said Monday it
foiled an attempted coup against the 2-year-old government of
President Blaise Compaore, but denied reports that it executed
seven of those arrested.
   Justice Minister Antoine Komi Sambo told a news conference
``foreign mercenaries'' were among those arrested, but he refused
to provide any details.
   He said those arrested would be brought before the courts of
this landlocked West African former French colony, once known as
Upper Volta.
   Burkina Faso, with a population of more than 8.5 million, gained
independence in 1960.
   In Paris, the Burkinabe League of Human Rights issued a
statement protesting the arrests and what it called repression by
the country's ``military dictatorship.''
   ``As of Dec. 25, more than 50 people have been arrested, and
their number is likely to double in the days to come, according to
disquieting information coming from Burkina Faso,'' it said.
   Earlier Monday, the French news agency Agence France-Presse
quoted what it called well-informed sources in Ouagadougou as
saying seven people were executed Sunday night and Monday morning,
and about 30 others, mostly soldiers, were arrested.
   Compaore took power Oct. 15, 1987, in a military coup that left
President Thomas Sankara among those slain. Officials reported
another aborted coup last September and said four alleged plotters
were executed summarily, including the men who were No. 2 and No. 3
in Compaore's government.
   The justice minister did not disclose on Monday when any of the
latest events took place, nor did he disclose any details of the
coup attempt.
   The League of Human Rights, a Paris-based group of Burkina Faso
exiles, said it had no further specifics on the attempt.

</TEXT>

</DOC>