<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0718EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AlaskaVolcano     12-19 0545</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Alaska Volcano,0566</SECOND>
<HEAD>Volcano Snarls Mail, Air Travel</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL JENKINS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Redoubt Volcano's frequent eruptions
pumped tons of steam and ash into the air, covering parts of
south-central Alaska with a fine layer of gray grit and stranding
holiday mail and travelers.
   Variable winds spread ash clouds east, north and south, but
Anchorage, with almost half the state's population, was spared the
fallout. The heaviest ash concentrations were seen over the Kenai
Peninsula and Prince William Sound.
   Ash clouds were seen rising to 31,000 feet from Redoubt's
10,197-foot summit.
   ``The volcano is still very active,'' said Steve Brantley, a
geologist with the Alaska Volcano Observatory on Monday. ``We are
continuing to observe a high level of earthquake activity on the
mountain.''
   The swirling clouds of ash delayed or detoured air traffic in
and out of Anchorage, stacking up thousands of travelers and tons
of mail.
   The Anchorage International Airport was open Monday, but service
was irregular, with some airlines grounding aircraft and others
offering limited service. Some domestic airlines canceled flights
and international carriers routed their aircraft around Anchorage.
   At the Seattle-Tacoma International Airport, hundreds of people
trying to get to Alaska were stranded.
   ``I guess my wife and I will be sleeping at the airport,'' said
Anchorage resident John Stout, 67, on Monday. The couple has been
stuck in Seattle since Saturday. They learned Monday that Delta Air
Lines would no longer pay for their hotel room.
   ``We can't go on indefinitely supplying people all over the
country with hotels and meals,'' Delta spokesman Ron Tansey said.
`` ... We're fairly optimistic we can get these people home.''
   Nancy Schmitt, a spokeswoman for the U.S. Postal Service, said
the ash clouds were ``playing havoc with us. ... This is the
largest backup we've ever had.''
   About 22,000 pounds of mail was stacked in Anchorage on Monday
for shipment out of Alaska. Another 130,000 pounds waited in
Seattle for shipment to Alaska, she said.
   The postal service depends on commercial jets to move the mail,
but has resorted to chartering propeller aircraft, she said.
   ``The mail's moving, but slowly,'' she said.
   The Alaska Railroad added a train between Anchorage and
Fairbanks for travelers, said spokeswoman Vivian Hamilton.
   While some were trying to get on planes, a group of Korean Air
Line passengers refused to reboard their flight Monday, saying they
were concerned whether it was safe to fly.
   Flight 25 was en route from New York to Seoul on Saturday when
it landed in Anchorage. The flight was delayed and passengers were
taken to hotels.
   ``Then all these rumors started about the safety of the plane;
the volcanic ash,'' said Christine Lee, a Korean national with a
home in the United States. ``It's hard to tell what's really true.''
   Redoubt rumbled awake Thursday after two decades of slumber. It
has sent ash and steam skyward intermittently since. It is located
in a sparsely populated area 115 miles southwest of Anchorage in
the Lake Clark National Park and Preserve.
   Last Friday, dust from Redoubt shut down all four engines of a
KLM Royal Dutch Airlines 747, causing the plane to plunge from
25,000 feet to 12,000 feet in 12 minutes before the crew could
restart the clogged engines.
</TEXT>

</DOC>