<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0097 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1340EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Korea-Europe     12-29 0369</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Korea-Europe,0379</SECOND>
<HEAD>Emergency Meeting of North Korean Envoys to East Europe Reported</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   North Korea has called home its
ambassadors from its Communist allies for an emergency meeting,
apparently because of the changes in Eastern Europe, a South Korean
government official said Thursday.
   North Korea appeared to have convened a meeting of its
ambassadors to 30 countries, including China and the Soviet Union,
one month ahead of schedule to discuss the radical liberalization
in many of its allies, said South Korean Unification Minister Lee
Hong-ku.
   The Korea Times quoted a South Korean government source as
saying: ``There is a high probability that the North will seek
gradual openness ... to escape from political isolation and to
boost the economy.''
   On Tuesday, North Korean President Kim Il Sung, who has built up
a massive personality cult in his four decades of hard-line rule,
recognized the new Romanian government.
   North Korea has called for the Communist countries to increase
vigilance against ``imperialist'' efforts to undermine socialism.
   Rodong Shinmun, the official newspaper of North Korea's
Communist Party, urged intensifying ``revolutionary education'' in
the country in the face of ``the ever more malicious anti-socialist
moves of the imperialists.''
   All people should be encouraged to establish a correct outlook
by ``carrying into effect the idea and intentions of the party and
the leader, deeply trusting them as the mainstay,'' said the
paper's editorial, carried by Pyongyang's official Korean Central
News Agency, monitored in Tokyo.
   ``In our country today, the superiority of socialism is fully
displayed, the entire people are closely united behind the party
and the leader, and a healthy, revolutionary trait is pervading the
whole society,'' it said.
   But, it added, ``the imperialists are craftily maneuvering to
break the people's conviction of socialism and undermine socialism
from within.''
   Under these conditions, the editorial added, only when
revolutionary education is intensified ``is it possible to enhance
the anti-imperialist revolutionary spirit and class consciousness
of the people still further and prevent the infiltration of the
corrupt bourgeois ideology and mode of life.''
   The official news agency also said Kim's message to new Romanian
leader Ion Iliescu expressed hope for strengthening friendly and
cooperative relations, and wished the Romanian people success.
</TEXT>

</DOC>