<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1250EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Lithuania     12-25 0304</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lithuania,0313</SECOND>
<HEAD>Party Fails to Reach Agreement on How to Deal with Lithuanian Schism</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Communist Party leadership met Monday but
failed to agree on how to deal with the Lithuanian party's
unprecedented declaration of independence from the Kremlin, a
source said.
   The source, one of the more than 250 members of the party's
policy-making Central Committee, said the committee would resume
its plenary meeting on the question Tuesday.
   ``They decided to think it over and start again,'' said the
high-ranking party official, who spoke on condition he not be
identified.
   Lithuanian Communists voted Wednesday at a special congress in
their capital of Vilnius to form their own party, rejecting appeals
for unity from President Mikhail S. Gorbachev and other top Soviet
officials.
   The Lithuanians' break is serious because it is without
precedent in the history of the party founded by Vladimir I. Lenin,
who demanded and forged a unitary party across the Soviet Union.
   Moreover, Lithuanian reformers predict local party organizations
in many of the other 14 constituent Soviet republics will rapidly
follow their example, which would present Gorbachev with a
fractured party as he prepares for a nationwide party congress in
October 1990.
   The Central Committee convened in Moscow on Monday ``to consider
the situation in the Lithuanian party branch,'' state-run Radio
Moscow said. Other official media did not immediately report on the
closed-door session.
   Algirdas Brazauskas, the Lithuanian party leader, said the
break, which included drafting a separate party program, was
necessary for Lithuanian Communists to compete successfully in
local elections Feb. 24.
   However, a group of Lithuanian Communists who opposed the break
countered by forming their own leadership, and pledged continuing
loyalty to Moscow.
   The Central Committee invited both Brazauskas and the leaders of
the anti-separatist faction to Moscow to attend its meeting, Radio
Moscow said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>