<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0137 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2104EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AlaskaVolcano     12-19 0667</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Alaska Volcano,0685</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eruption Continues To Slow Airline Flights, Scientists Get Close
Look</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto AG1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL JENKINS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scientists have gotten their first good
look at Redoubt Volcano and say most of its steam and volcanic ash
seems to be erupting from a single small vent about two-thirds of
the way up the mountain.
   The abrasive airborne ash, which could clog aircraft engines,
delayed or detoured air traffic in and out of Anchorage, stacking
up thousands of travelers and tons of mail. Among the stranded
travelers were 70 Korean Air Lines passengers who have refused
since Saturday to get on a plane.
   Anchorage International Airport was open Tuesday, but service
was irregular, with some airlines grounding aircraft and others
offering limited service. Some domestic airlines canceled flights
and international carriers routed their aircraft around Anchorage.
   Hunreds of stranded passengers were camping out in airports in
Anchorage and Seattle and the backlog began to affect airports as
far away as Salt Lake City.
   The sky cleared enough Monday to allow airborne scientists to
get close to the 10,197-foot mountain for the first time since it
began erupting Thursday.
   The Alaska Volcano Observatory, a joint center for state and
federal scientists, reported that the hot, gritty material was
coming from a vent less than 600 feet in diameter between the
8,000- and 8,500-foot level of the mountain.
   No lava was observed in the vent or elsewhere in the volcano's
crater, scientists reported.
   While the mountain continued to blow spectacular plumes up to
30,000 feet, scientists said most of the material was steam. They
said volcanic ash blanketed the volcano's southeast flank.
   They also observed a curtain of steam rising from a glacier on
the north side of the volcano. They said the steam appeared to be
the result of water flowing from the vent down the glacier and into
the Drift River.
   Water from melting snow and ice is contained in the normal
channel of the river, which flooded extensively when the volcano
last erupted more than two decades ago.
   While emissions from the mountain appeared to contain less ash
than before, the Federal Aviation Administration continued to warn
pilots of the hazards of additional volcanic activity because of
the abrasive ash. A notice advised that suitable alternative
airports may not be available should aircraft be forced to divert
from Anchorage.
   About 70 Korean Air Lines passengers remained in Anchorage on
Tuesday because of flight safety, said Lee Steiner, KAL's customer
relations manager in Los Angeles.
   Flight 25 with 240 passengers was en route from New York to
Seoul on Saturday when it landed in Anchorage. The flight was
delayed and passengers were taken to hotels.
   Then rumors started about the danger of flying near the ash
clouds and about half the passengers refused to reboard their plane.
   All but the 70 stay-behinds got on a KAL flight early Tuesday,
Steiner said. He said the airline was paying their bills.
   Steiner said those staying in Anchorage would be put aboard the
next available flight to Korea. ``But we don't know when that will
be at this point,'' he said. ``It depends on the climatic
conditions.''
   Last Friday, volcanic ash from Redoubt shut down all four
engines of a KLM Royal Dutch Airlines 747, causing the plane to
glide from 25,000 feet to 12,000 feet in 12 minutes before the crew
could restart the clogged engines.
   Anchorage, with almost half the state's population, has escaped
most of the ash settling to the ground in a fine, gray layer. The
heaviest ash concentrations were reported over the Kenai Peninsula
and Prince William Sound.
   Redoubt is located in a sparsely populated area 115 miles
southwest of Anchorage in the Lake Clark National Park and Preserve.
   No injuries have been reported in the eruptions, but one family
was removed Sunday from a lodge in the shadow of the volcano. They
were in no immediate danger. Another couple remains at a lodge
north of the peak.
</TEXT>

</DOC>