<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0085 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1236EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-US-Panama 2ndLd-Writethru a0544-a0431 12-18 0764</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-Panama, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0544-a0431,750</SECOND>
<HEAD>Administration Condemns `Climate of Aggression' in Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Combines pvs, editing throughout to tighten.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM RAUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bush administration said today that
Panamanian Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega's declaration of war seems
to have become a ``license for harassment'' against Americans.
   White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater, citing the weekend
killing of a U.S. officer in Panama and other incidents of
violence, condemned ``a climate of aggression that is very
disturbing.''
   And President Bush, in an interview today with reporters from
The Associated Press and three other news agencies, called the
slaying ``an enormous outrage.''
   Bush said he is reviewing a range of options in response, and
pointedly did not rule out military action.
   ``I think a president, all presidents, have options, but they
don't discuss what they might be,'' Bush said. He repeated the
answer when asked if military action was among the options
available.
   The Defense Department said four American servicemen were trying
to flee a crowd of Panamanian troopers and civilians Saturday night
when the Panamanian soldiers opened fire, fatally wounding one
American.
   Another U.S. officer's ankle was grazed with a bullet, the
statement said. The Americans were traveling in a private car and
were off-duty and unarmed, it added.
   The weekend violence came after Noriega had himself installed as
the country's supreme ruler on Friday and declared his country in a
state of war with the United States.
   ``We are monitoring the situation there on a continung basis,
but we are very concerned that the declaration of war that was
stated ...may have been a license for harassment and threats and in
this case murder,'' Fitzwater said.
   ``Other members of the U.S. military were detained, their
weapons and radios taken away from them after questioning, and then
released. The attack on the naval officer's wife certainly goes
beyond any previous experience. And the murder is outrageous in
itself,'' Fitzwater said.
   The Defense Department said a Navy lieutenant and his wife had
been stopped at the same roadblock as the four servicemen.
Panamanian soldiers blindfolded the Navy officer and his wife and
took them to a different location where they were interrogated for
about four hours, the department said.
   During the interrogation, the Navy officer was repeatedly beaten
and kicked in the groin, the statement said. His wife was slammed
against a wall and sexually threatened, it said.
   Fitzwater defended his characterization of the slaying as
``murder,'' saying the U.S. officer ``was unarmed and he was
killed.''
   He said most U.S. dependents have left the country or have been
moved onto the U.S. military base there, a 9:50 p.m. curfew had
been imposed over the weekend on U.S. military personnel, and the
base put on a high state of alert.
   ``There's no question that it's a dangerous situation,''
Fitzwater said.
   Earlier, deputy White House press secretary Roman Popadiuk said
the Noriega regime ``is isolated both domestically and
internationally and has been using force and intimidation to thwart
the will of the Panamanian people. Acts such as those of last
evening are the consequence of such a regime.''
   Defense Secretary Dick Cheney met Sunday with senior officials
at the Pentagon and issued a statement afterward saying, ``We've
seen General Noriega brutalize the people of Panama, crack down on
his own civilians and military alike after the last coup attempt,
designate himself the leader of the country and declare a state of
war with the United States.''
   ``These actions have created an atmosphere in which Panamanian
Defense Forces feel free to fire on unarmed Americans. We fully
expect that those responsible will be brought to justice,'' Cheney
said.
   ``Ultimately, it is General Noriega himself who has encouraged
this kind of lawlessness. His own conduct sets an example of
cruelty and brutality. The lack of discipline and control in the
Panamanian Defense Forces is further evidence that Panama is a
country without a government,'' Cheney said.
   The names of Americans involved in the Panamanian violence were
withheld pending notification of relatives.
   The Panamanian Defense Forces charged that the servicemen had
fired several shots at Noriega's military headquarters, wounding
three Panamanians, including a soldier and an infant.
   Noriega, who is wanted in the United States on drug trafficking
charges, was declared Panama's chief of government Friday by a
rubber-stamp legislature, which declared Panama in a ``state of
war'' with the United States.
   The United States has imposed severe economic sanctions on
Panama in a bid to force the ouster of Noriega. It recently
announced it is banning Panamanian-flag commercial vessels from
entering U.S. ports.
</TEXT>

</DOC>