<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0221 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1546EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-US-SovietAccounting     12-19 0289</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-US-Soviet Accounting,0298</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S., Soviet Accounting Venture Launched</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   American numbers crunchers are the latest
capitalists to exploit the budding U.S.-Soviet business romance.
   Ernst &amp; Young, a leading U.S. accounting and professional
services company, said Tuesday it had signed an agreement with
Vneshconsult, the Soviet management consulting firm, creating what
was described as the first Western-Soviet accounting company, based
in Moscow.
   The American partners will provide training in their worldwide
audit methodology for Vneshaudit's Soviet personnel, Ernst &amp; Young
said in a news release.
   ``There is no public accounting profession in the Soviet Union
since there has been, until recently, no need for one,'' said James
Searing, Ernst &amp; Young's director for international business
services.
   ``Concepts such as the Western understanding of profit
measurement and the differences between external and internal
auditing and reporting are new for them,'' Searing said. ``Setting
up business there requires far more than just adapting one
country's accounting standards to another's.''
   Ray Groves, co-chief executive of Ernst &amp; Young, said the firm's
entry into the Soviet market ``is both a tangible symbol of the new
cooperation and a highly practical advance movement for American
commerce.''
   A number of highly visible American companies have been signing
business deals and exploring opportunities in the Soviet Union
because of the liberalization encouraged by President Mikhail
Gorbachev, who is trying to revitalize his nation's stagnant
economy and reduce the state's role.
   U.S. ventures now range from importing Soviet watches to
building the world's largest McDonald's restaurant in Moscow.
   Ernst &amp; Young, one of the largest accounting firms in the world,
was established by the merger of Arthur Young and Ernst &amp; Whinney
earlier this year. The company has offices in more than 100
countries.
</TEXT>

</DOC>