<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0059EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-India-Bofors     12-27 0469</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-India-Bofors,0484</SECOND>
<HEAD>Singh Government Halts Future Contracts With Swedish Firm Bofors</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The new government of Prime Minister
V.P. Singh says it will temporarily stop buying weapons from a
Swedish armaments firm accused of paying huge bribes to secure a
1986 contract with the Indian army.
   The alleged impropriety in AB Bofors' $1.4 billion Howitzer gun
deal was a key campaign issue for Singh, whose centrist coalition
ousted Rajiv Gandhi and the Congress Party from power in last
month's elections.
   Singh, who is also the country's defense minister, announced in
Parliament on Tuesday that Bofors will be barred from future
contracts until ``they satisfy us in their conduct in regard to
(the) Howitzer guns.''
   At least two newspaper investigations have sought to prove that
Bofors paid as much as $50 million in bribes and commissions to yet
unnamed persons.
   The allegations have not been proved since they surfaced in
April 1987, but one newspaper, The Hindu, has published purported
documents that it said established Gandhi's links with recipients
of the alleged bribes and commissions.
   The Hindu, and another newspaper, Indian Express, said senior
officials in Gandhi's cabinet and persons close to him received the
bribes. Gandhi has also been accused of covering up the
investigation by handing it over to pliant officers.
   Gandhi has denied the charges and maintained that his actions
have been above board.
   Singh's National Front coalition government said in its election
manifesto that it will unearth and disclose the names of the
commission recipients within 15 days of taking office. Singh was
sworn in Dec. 2.
   On Tuesday, Singh denied that he is not longer keen on probing
the Bofors deal now that his coalition is power.
   Singh said the government order Tuesday covers ``supply of names
of recipients and return of money paid in regard to Bofors gun
transactions.''
   ``This shows there is no lack of enthusiasm. We are determined.
There is no question of compromise on anything.
   ``We will do everything to get the names and come to the
truth,'' Singh said. His colleagues in Parliament loudly thumped
desks.
   Singh was interrupted by Gandhi's Congress Party members when he
continued with the statement. House chairman Shankar Dayal Sharma
adjourned the session amid the uproar triggered by angry shouts
from Singh's colleagues.
   Hours after Singh's truncated statement, the Defense Ministry
said it had been directed by the prime minister to stop all future
contracts with Bofors.
   It was the new government's first major policy decision on the
Bofors deal since taking office.
   ``The embargo will be till such time as the company satisfied
the government of India about their previous conduct,'' the Defense
Ministry said in a statement.
   The current Howitzer gun deal apparently remained unaffected by
the decision as neither Singh nor the Defense Ministry referred to
it.
</TEXT>

</DOC>