<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1017EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CardboardCops     12-28 0312</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Cardboard Cops,0322</SECOND>
<HEAD>Food Store Chain Hopes Police Cutouts Will Cut Out Crime</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A food store chain is hoping that the unblinking
stares of three police officers will deter shoplifting, even if the
cops are only 6-foot cardboard cutouts.
   The police officers stationed in Kroger stores this week are
life-size and look pretty real. But they're scarecrooks, operating
on the same principle as scarecrows.
   Police in London noticed a decrease in shoplifting after they
put up cardboard bobbies in stores, Dallas Police Lt. A.J.
D'Alessandro said Wednesday.
   Kroger put officer cutouts _ made from photos of three Dallas
police officers _ in three stores in Dallas, and move them around
each month. After three months, Kroger plans to review the campaign
to see whether it has been as successful as its British inspiration.
   ``I'm pretty sure we'll have some success,'' D'Alessandro said.
``This campaign can be a limited-time success, but we'll move the
officers around to other stores. The people will be faced with a
different officer, and they'll be startled again.''
   The cutouts portray officers in uniform in natural poses. A sign
at the cutouts' feet reads: ``Shoplifting is a Crime.''
   Police Cpl. Chip Bulin appeared satisfied with the life-size
cardboard photograph of himself. Also pictured are Cpls. Robert
Garcia and Rodney Woods.
   The cutouts are placed in areas conducive to theft, Tyner said.
Bulin's likeness was in the cosmetics department, Woods' guarded
cigarette cartons, batteries and the automated teller machine.
Garcia's cutout was placed near soda machines.
   The photos, at D'Alessandro's request, were shot straight on,
``to make it appear that wherever you move, they are looking at
you.''
   Charlie Tyner, security supervisor for Kroger, said the store is
not trying to fool anyone with the cardboard cops.
   ``But it's a startling way to say the same old message, that
shoplifting is a crime,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>