<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0190 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0053EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-S&amp;Ls-MailingLists     12-19 0266</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-S&amp;Ls-Mailing Lists,0275</SECOND>
<HEAD>Trade Group Complains About Mailing List Rule</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-S&amp;L Bailouts, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A trade group representing savings and loan
holding companies is complaining about new rules that prohibit S&amp;Ls
from releasing mailing lists of their customers' names without
permission from their customers.
   The rules imposed by the Office of Thrift Supervision provide
that a name and address may be given out only if the customer is
first notified and does not object within 15 days. After two years,
the customer must be asked to renew the permission.
   The prohibition took effect Friday.
   The Association of Thrift Holding Companies, in a suit filed in
U.S. District Court seeking to overturn the regulations, complained
that the rules make it difficult for thrift parent companies, such
as insurance companies and banks, to cross-market their products to
the thrift's customers.
   Banks do not operate under similar restrictions and imposing the
limits on S&amp;Ls likely will hurt the government's efforts to dispose
of failed thrifts, the trade group said. Financial institutions
earn money by selling their mailing lists to others.
   However, thrift office director M. Danny Wall said in a
statement the regulation ``strikes a reasonable balance between
customers' expectations of privacy and legitimate business
interests of thrift institutions.''
   He acknowledged that in most states the rules will now be
tougher for S&amp;Ls than for banks, but said, ``We think that's a
positive step, and gives the public an incentive to place their
business with thrifts.''
   The regulation has exemptions allowing customer information to
be disclosed to regulatory officials, law enforcement officials and
credit-reporting agencies.
</TEXT>

</DOC>