<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0152 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1516EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-PanamaAnalysis 1stLd-Writethru a0739 12-20 1053</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama Analysis, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0739,1030</SECOND>
<HEAD>After a Year of Taunting Bush, Noriega Is Attacked</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Updates with Baker comments, subbing 3 grafs for 16th graf pvs,
At least</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WALTER R. MEARS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In another time, another president said he
would not see the United States made into ``a pitiful, helpless
giant.'' The phrase echoed as President Bush ordered American
troops to crush and capture Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega, whose
Panamanian regime had withstood an arsenal of American sanctions
short of force.
   Part of the mission was reported accomplished within eight hours
on Wednesday with the Pentagon declaring that Noriega had been
decapitated as the strongarm leader of Panama.
   But he escaped and supporters claimed he was still directing his
loyalist forces. The United States called him a fugitive, and said
he would be tracked and taken, to stand trial on U.S. drug
trafficking indictments.
   For more than two years, Noriega had taunted and incited the
giant, while his foes at home and in Washington tried futilely to
dislodge his grip on power. Bush, whose watchword is prudence, said
it was an enormous frustration. But he took it for nearly a year,
for lack of an acceptable alternative.
   Then he took a risk, and went to war. ``Fellow citizens, last
night I ordered U.S. military forces to Panama,'' he told the
nation Wednesday. ``...I took this action only after reaching the
conclusion that every other avenue was closed and the lives of
American citizens were in grave danger.''
   Bush gained prompt and predictable support at home, from
Democrats as well as Republicans. He had briefed congressional
leaders just before U.S. forces went into combat against Noriega's
loyalists in the Panama Defense Forces.
   Presidents seldom face much political dissent when American
forces are in combat, especially with the kind of provocations
Noriega provided. His puppet assembly had declared a state of war
with the United States, and an off-duty American officer was shot
and killed by his forces on Saturday.
   Bush recounted the killing, the wounding of another American
serviceman, the capture and beating of a third and threats against
his wife.
   ``That was enough,'' the president said.
   ``Gen. Noriega's reckless threats and attacks upon Americans in
Panama created an eminent danger to the 35,000 American citizens in
Panama,'' Bush said. ``...And that is why I directed our armed
forces to protect the lives of American citizens in Panama, and to
bring Gen. Noriega to justice in the United States.''
   Bush had repeatedly encouraged Noriega's opponents to kick him
out of power. He had said that Noriega was the problem, that the
United States quarrel was with the general, not with the Panama
Defense Forces, and that his ouster would instantly restore normal
diplomatic and economic relations.
   Yet when dissident PDF officers attempted a coup on Oct. 3 and
briefly held Noriega, American forces stood by, inactive. U.S.
forces had blocked two roads and had conferred with coup leaders,
but the administration decided against intervention.
   That drew protests from left and right, although some
Republicans complained that dovish Democrats who opposed
intervention in other crises were endorsing it retroactively in
Panama.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III said U.S. commanders had
been told they could offer support for the coup ``if there were an
opportunity to do this without risking bloodshed and significant
loss of American life and to do so without open military
involvement...''
   Those instructions ring with irony now that U.S. forces have
been sent into open combat.
   On Wednesday, Baker recalled his October testimony, and the
administration explanation of U.S. inaction at the time of the coup
attempt.
   ``I said if this administration chose to use force, it would
make its own decisions,'' he told a news conference. ``It would not
act based on some unknown coup plotters' strategy or rationale.''
   At least 11 American soldiers were killed in action early
Wednesday, others wounded.
   That is the price of using military power. It was Richard M.
Nixon who spoke of the price of shrinking from its use, 19 years
ago. ``If, when the chips are down, the world's most powerful
nation, the United States of America, acts like a pitiful, helpless
giant, the forces of totalitarianism and anarchy will threaten free
nations and free institutions throughout the world,'' he said,
announcing he had sent forces to attack Communist North Vietnamese
sanctuaries in Cambodia.
   Bush ordered about 7,000 troops into Panama to join some 12,000
already stationed there as the Panama Canal garrison. Another 2,500
reinforcements were being deployed Wednesday.
   Later, there are sure to be told-you-so comments from those who
argued the administration should have sent forces to join the
October coup.
   And Noriega's purge of dissident PDF officers after that coup
could make it more difficult for the United States to quickly
complete operations and withdraw the additional troops, which Bush
said he wants to do as quickly as possible.
   The newly-installed government of Panama _ led by Guillermo
Endara, thought to have won the May election Noriega annulled _
will need reliable new leaders to take control of the military in
place of his henchmen.
   Stability under an elected government will be the real test of
success, whatever happens to Noriega. The administration has been
wagering all along that his support was thin and brittle. American
intervention puts that to the tes: if the theory is correct and he
is powerless, Noriega is irrelevant.
   But if Noriega or his lieutenants are capable of holding out and
running continuing operations against U.S. forces and the Endara
government, the administration will have a major problem on its
hands.
   When President Ronald Reagan ordered American forces into action
in the 1983 invasion of Grenada and the 1986 air raid on Libya, the
operations were swift and brief. The Bush administration wants
intervention in Panama to be a mission accomplished and quickly
ended. Prolonged involvement would stir political opposition at
home and intensify the inevitable Latin American resentment against
Yankee intervention, no matter the cause.
   Bush sought to ease that backlash by saying he wants to get out
swiftly, by lifting economic sanctions against Panama under the new
Endara government, and by promising anew that the United States
will turn the canal over to Panama at the end of the century.
</TEXT>

</DOC>