<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1108EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MansionMurders     12-17 0672</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mansion Murders,0692</SECOND>
<HEAD>Motive Still Unknown in Beverly Hills Slayings, Police Say</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By E. SCOTT RECKARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEVERLY HILLS, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four months after a Hollywood
executive and his wife were slain in their mansion, the motive is
unclear although police say they suspect the shootings were
``message'' murders.
   Relatives have maintained that Jose Enrique Menendez,
hard-driving chairman of Live Entertainment Inc., was killed for a
reason related to his video and music distribution business.
   Nothing was stolen from the Spanish-style, $5 million home.
There were no signs the killers forced their way in. No clues were
left at the scene. The couple were killed the night of Aug. 20 by
multiple shotgun blasts at close range. Their sons said they found
the bodies after a night out.
   Police say they are continuing to investigate possible mob links
to the death of Menendez, 45, and his wife Mary Louise ``Kitty''
Menendez, 44. But detectives have pursued many other angles,
including questioning the Menendez couple's sons, Erik, 19, and
Lyle, 21, about the night of the deaths.
   The sons did not reply to an interview request relayed by
probate lawyer Stephen B. Goldberg.
   Police also are looking into the disappearance of an apparent
reference to Menendez's plans to write a new will.
   Under terms of the parents' 9-year-old wills, the sons will
share a $10 million estate that Goldberg estimates will exceed $5
million after debts and taxes are paid _ ``next summer if all goes
smoothly.''
   They also were beneficiaries of a $400,000 life insurance policy.
   Goldberg said he tried to determine a few weeks ago whether the
boys had been ruled out as suspects, but the answer was
inconclusive. ``The only thing I have been able to confirm is that
there are no prime suspects,'' Goldberg said last week.
   Police won't rule out anybody or anything, at least not
publicly. A $25,000 reward posted by family friends had brought in
some leads, police said.
   ``There has been no specific motive determined,'' said Lt.
Robert Curtis, a spokesman for the department. ``It's fair to say
some progress has been made, but that's about all I can say.''
   He refused to comment on the disappearance of an apparent
reference to a new will in the Menendez home computer.
   Family members, speaking on condition of anonymity, said a
relative tried to read a computer file named ``will'' after the
murders, but was unable to do so. Before a computer expert was
brought in, the file disappeared.
   The relatives would not say who could have erased the file.
   No new will has been found. The family and Goldberg say they are
convinced none was made, although Menendez had discussed drawing
one up to replace the wills made in 1980 in New Jersey, when he was
far less wealthy.
   Menendez had little money when his parents sent him out of Cuba
after Castro took power. Smart and a perfectionist, he was an
executive for RCA and Hertz before joining Live Entertainment.
   Companies operated by Live had been linked to organized crime
and pornography before Live bought them, but company officials have
vehemently rejected suggestions that the deaths may have a mob link.
   Curtis said that was still considered possible, and Menendez's
sister, Marta Menendez-Cano of West Palm Beach, Fla., said not long
after the slayings that the family blamed organized crime.
   ``We think he made the mistake of buying a business that had
been used before by the Mafia, and we think he was trying to run it
straight,'' she said.
   Richard Stavin, former head of a federal task force into
organized crime's influence in Hollywood, noted that vast amounts
of money are at stake in the booming video business, and said,
``It's conceivable that this could be a mob hit.''
   Meanwhile, the family says the sons have tried to get on with
their lives. Talented tennis players, they practice obsessively
nowadays and talk of getting into the real estate business. It's
unclear if Lyle will return to Princeton University in January.
</TEXT>

</DOC>