<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0270 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1300EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-American-Eastern 1stLd-Writethru   12-20 0863</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-American-Eastern, 1st Ld-Writethru,0889</SECOND>
<HEAD>American Jumps Into Latin America Through Eastern Purchase</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 8 grafs with American news conference; picks up 7th
graf, ``The purchase ....</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN A. BOLT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In one stroke, American Airlines has become a
significant international carrier through the $471 million purchase
of Latin American and European routes and other assets from
struggling Eastern Airlines and its parent, Texas Air Corp.
   The long-anticipated deal, announced Tuesday, increases
American's Central and South American destinations from one city in
Venezuela to 20 in 15 countries. It also gives American its second
London route in two days and Eastern's unused route authority from
Miami to Madrid, Spain.
   American Chairman Robert L. Crandall said today the deal will
allow American to ``fully realize our aspirations'' in Latin
America and Eastern to gain badly needed cash as it tries to emerge
from Chapter 11 bankruptcy reorganization.
   In a news conference in Miami today, noted that the deal must be
approved by the U.S. Department of Transportation, but added, ``We
certainly think it should be (approved) ... This is a very good
transaction.''
   American, besides being the No. 1 domestic airline, serves seven
Mexican destinations and about 20 in the Caribbean, plus has a
growing presence in Europe, where it has 5 percent of the market,
and the Pacific.
   The agreement followed by one day American's $195 million
purchase from Trans World Airlines Inc. of a Chicago-London route,
plus facilities at Chicago's O'Hare International Airport. In
addition, American paid $400,000 Monday for Braniff's landing
rights at Chicago and New York.
   All the purchases require approval by various government
agencies. In addition, the Eastern transactions must be approved by
a U.S. Bankruptcy Court judge in New York.
   ``American has been pursuing the expansion of its international
operations from some time,'' Crandall said Tuesday. ``This
transaction will allow our company to continue building its
international network, and it will make the United States a
stronger competitor in Central and South America by linking that
region to American's extensive domestic route system.''
   The purchase includes gates at several U.S. airports currently
held by Eastern and sister carrier Continental Airlines, plus
Eastern facilities at U.S., Puerto Rican and South American
airports.
   As part of the agreement, Continental will drop a $1 billion
antitrust lawsuit against Sabre, the computer reservation system
owned by American's parent, AMR Corp. of Fort Worth.
   Texas Air, based in Houston, said the deal would pump $349
million into Eastern, which is struggling to emerge from bankruptcy
court protection next year.
   Continental, which is selling is Miami-London route, will
realize $102.5 million; System One, Texas Air's computer
reservations system, will net $19.5 million through the sale of
telecommunication and data processing systems needed to service the
Latin American routes.
   ``The sale of these assets will enable Eastern Airlines to
continue on its course of successfully rebuilding as a smaller and
stronger airline for the future, with its operations centered at
its Atlanta hub,'' Texas Air said in a statement.
   Eastern also said it would sell the 14 Lockheed-1011s it uses on
the Latin American routes. The planes, which are an older, smaller
version of the widebody jet, could bring in about $200 million,
according to analysts' estimates.
   American, which has spent billions this year buying new aircraft
to serve its expansion plans, says it is not interested in the jets.
   Analysts generally applauded American's purchases of the routes.
They say the carrier's expansion beyond U.S. borders is necessary
if it is to become a ``player'' internationally.
   The deals also could have the pleasant side effect of making AMR
less attractive to a corporate raider by decreasing cash and
depressing earnings.
   ``These are good long-term moves, and if they affect earnings in
the short term, they can deal with that,'' said analyst Mark
Daugherty at Dean Witter Reynolds Inc. in New York.
   Analyst Helane Becker of Shearson Lehman Hutton Inc. sounded a
warning note, however.
   ``I really think that you don't necessarily want to take $500
million or $200 million cash and give it to a competitor that would
be out of business in a year,'' she said, referring to Eastern and
TWA. ``You sort of have to wonder if they could buy these assets
out of bankruptcy at a cheaper price than they're doing today.''
   AMR shares closed Tuesday at $60, up $2.75, in New York Stock
Exchange trading.
   American has been expanding vigorously this year, buying
airplanes to fly its newly acquired, or sought-after routes;
beginning work on a $400 million maintenance facility; expanding
domestic operations; and fighting off a takeover from billionaire
Donald Trump.
   American has broadened its European service significantly this
year, and already has approval for more routes next year, when it
will reach about 165 flights weekly to 18 European cities.
   Six years ago, it flew to none.
   Expansion also is under way in the Pacific, where American next
year will begin flying to Sydney, Australia and Auckland, New
Zealand. The airline also is trying to add a second Tokyo flight.
   The growth has been financed through record profits, although
Crandall has warned the performance won't continue this quarter or
next year.
</TEXT>

</DOC>