<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0219 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 2017EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Eastern 1stLd-Writethru   12-28 0698</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Eastern, 1st Ld-Writethru,0719</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eastern Cutting 600 Jobs, Salaries</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: ADDS final graf to UPDATE with Eastern getting extension on
deadline for reorganization plan; No pickup</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD COLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eastern Airlines announced Thursday it will cut 600
jobs and temporarily trim salaries for about 10,000 workers as the
retrenching carrier prepares to sell its Latin American routes and
shrink its home base.
   The downsizing is part of Eastern's plan for reorganization in
the wake of the strike that idled the Miami-based carrier for
several months early this year.
   Eastern President Phil Bakes said the pay and benefit reductions
were ``something we wanted to avoid,'' but large losses are
expected to continue in the first half of the new year.
   The belt-tightening package is expected to save $100 million
next year for Eastern, which posted a net loss of $185.2 million in
this year's third quarter.
   The announcement reflects Eastern's intention to return to its
original reorganization plan cutting its pre-strike operations by a
third. In August, dogged by failure to sell the profitable Latin
American routes, Eastern had decided to pare operations by only 10
percent.
   Attrition and early retirement will blunt the effects of the
cutbacks, but a number of operational employees will be out of work
Jan. 31 as Miami operations are reduced from 75 daily flights to 50.
   Job cuts also will come July 1 when rival American Airlines
plans to take over the Latin American routes, Eastern Senior Vice
President Tom Matthews told a news conference in Miami.
   After months of negotiations, American said Dec. 19 it would buy
Eastern's Latin American routes and certain other assets from
Eastern's parent Texas Air Corp. for $471 million.
   Federal officials and the U.S. bankruptcy judge overseeing
Eastern's Chapter 11 reorganization must approve the deal.
   Separately Thursday, Pan Am Corp. said it intends to protest to
the government American's planned purchase of the Latin American
routes. Pan Am contends that the route transfer from ailing Eastern
to the nation's largest airline will hinder competition.
   Eastern said pilots, flight attendants and Machinists will not
be affected by the job cuts. The airline has hired thousands of
employees in those categories, mostly non-union, to replace members
of the striking unions.
   But half of Eastern's 20,000 employees _ including management,
pilots and flight attendants working at the higher pre-strike wage
levels _ will have their wages reduced by 10 percent to 20 percent
for a year, beginning Jan. 16.
   About 850 pilots will see their $72,000-a-year salaries slashed
by 20 percent for six months. Half of the cut will be restored
after six months, and pay will return to normal after a year. About
950 newly hired pilots are working for $27,500 a year and will not
be affected.
   Flight attendants earning a pre-strike salary of $30,000 a year
also will take cuts, but those hired under the new wage levels of
$15,000 will not.
   The wage cuts are subject to union negotiations, Matthews said.
Officials of the Air Line Pilots Association were not immediately
available for comment on Eastern's action. Mary Jane Barry, head of
the Eastern flight attendants union, said she couldn't comment
since contract negotiations are ongoing.
   The pilots and flight attendants unions, which walked out in
sympathy with the Machinists' strike, called off their actions just
before Thanksgiving but few got their jobs back.
   Matthews said he expects the latest round of cuts to be the last
necessary to achieve the reorganization plan.
   Eastern employed about 32,000 before the strike began March 4.
The airline filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection from
creditors five days later.
   Eastern plans to reshape itself at about two-thirds of its
pre-strike size with its major hub in Atlanta. Matthews denied
speculation that Eastern plans eventually to move its headquarters
from Miami to that city.
   Rising fuel prices and the prospect of only modest growth in air
travel in 1990 also were factors in the decision to cut jobs, the
airline said.
   Also Thursday, U.S. Bankruptcy Judge Burton R. Lifland extended
until Feb. 12 Friday's deadline for Eastern to submit its revised
reorganization plan. The judge already has given the airline
several such extensions.
</TEXT>

</DOC>