<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0645EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Panama-DrugCase     12-21 0457</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Drug Case,0471</SECOND>
<HEAD>Preparations Under Way For Possible Extradition of Noriega</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL WARREN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gen. Manuel Noriego would be treated as any other
criminal defendant _ ``no more, no less,'' said the federal judge
handling the ousted Panamanian leader's drug trial.
   But 80 miles to the north, in West Palm Beach, another federal
judge on Wednesday postponed the cocaine importation trial of three
men after agreeing with defense attorneys' contention that the trio
could not receive a fair trial because of the U.S. military action
in Panama.
   Noriega and 16 associates face federal drug-trafficking
indictments returned last year by grand juries in Miami and Tampa.
   ``If General Noriega is apprehended and brought here for
trial,'' U.S. District Judge William M. Hoeveler said Wednesday,
``he would be given the same treatment as any other person accused
of a crime _ no more, no less.
   ``All his rights will be protected,'' the Miami trial judge said
in the February 1988 Miami indictment against Noriega.
   In West Palm Beach, Judge James C. Paine postponed the trial of
two U.S. citizens and a Colombian national charged with smuggling
more than 25 pounds of cocaine into south Florida.
   Paine agreed with defense arguments that accused drug
traffickers cannot receive a fair trial when the United States has
just invaded a country to apprehend someone accused of the same
crime.
   Paine said it might be ``difficult, if not impossible, to get a
jury seated that would give (the three) a fair trial.''
   Noriega remained at large today. The United States has issued a
$1 million reward for information leading to his arrest. If he is
caught, federal officials confirmed that extremely tight security
has been included in plans drawn up to handle his arrival.
Officials spoke on the condition of anonymity.
   After being flown to an unspecified military base in south
Florida, Noriega would be transferred to a ``secure location'' to
await the Miami trial, according to an official for the U.S.
Marshals Service.
   Two Noriega attorneys in Miami said if their client was
cornered, he would rather die than surrender.
   ``He's a fighter,'' said Miami attorney Raymond Takiff. The
attorney said he last spoke with Noriega Monday evening, and
remained in touch with the general's aides on Wednesday.
   Attorney Frank Rubino agreed.
   ``The general is alive, well and somewhere in Panama,'' Rubino
said, ``and he is on top of the situation, as far as leading his
forces.''
   Noriega is charged in the indictments with accepting bribes of
$10 million from drug traffickers of Colombia's Medellin Cartel to
protect smugglers and cocaine shipments, launder cash and supply
drug laboratories.
   If convicted, he faces up to 145 years in prison and more than
$1.1 million in fines.
</TEXT>

</DOC>