<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0354EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Romania-Convoy 1stLd-Writethru   12-29 0694</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Convoy, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0462,0710</SECOND>
<HEAD>Despite Dangers, Convoys Brave Romanian Route</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS grafs 3, 6 to CORRECT to Ceausescu sted Ceauescu; pickup
7th graf pvs, `Hungarian radio...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE JAHN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ZIMANU NOU, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The bent old woman, head scarved and
feet clad in clumsy felt slippers against the cold, smiled
toothlessly as she surveyed the ragtag relief convoy of cars, vans
and taxis loaded with supplies.
   ``There is an old Romanian saying: `First servings for everyone
else, last dregs for the Romanians,' she exclaimed. ``Now that the
devil is dead, maybe that will change.''
   Toppled and executed, President Nicolae Ceausescu remains
``Dracul'' _ the Devil _ to many who suffered under his hard hand
for 24 years.
   As the army tries to crush die-hard units of his special police,
humanitarian aid is pouring in from abroad.
   Scores of hastily organized convoys with Hungarians, Germans,
Americans, Brits and Belgians behind the wheel have braved poor
roads and the threat of ambush to help, assembling in neighboring
Bulgaria, Yugoslavia and Hungary and then heading for the border.
   Several aid volunteers have been reported killed or wounded by
Ceausescu's henchmen.
   Hungarian radio said Thursday that close to 1,000 trucks and
countless autos made the dangerous trek from Hungary alone since
Dec. 22.
   Typical was a 16-vehicle convoy assembled early one morning by
the Free Democratic Party of Hungary.
   Some highlights of its 16-hour voyage betweeen Budapest, the
Hungarian capital, and Timisoara, Romania, 300 miles to the
southeast:
   _ Budapest, 2:12 a.m. Wednesday. As the convoy forms, Jozsef
Kovacs, who helped put together the shipment of food, clothing and
medicine, relates the case of a driver in another convoy, shot in
Timisoara by a member of Ceausescu's Securitate police posing as a
hospital worker. Faces turn glum and one volunteer begs off.
   _ Varsand, Romania, 9:20 a.m. Processing of entry papers comes
to a halt as border guards and other Romanians crowd to watch the
videotaped trial of Ceausescu and his wife, Elena. As the
71-year-old dictator grimaces, a woman in a fur hat hisses: ``Ah,
the devil.'' Others laugh and nudge each other.
   _ Varsand, 11:30 a.m. A grinning man hoists a hand in a victory
sign. Hundreds of others follow suit along the route, including
children, old women and peasants on horse-drawn carriages. ``God
has sent you!,'' yells one woman. ``Victory!,'' cries another.
   _ On the road to Zindanu Nou, 11:40 a.m. Two smiling soldiers
armed with machine guns loom from the white fog _ the first of
numerous road checks. A three-mile line of cars waits for service
at two gas pumps, but there are smiles and waves to the passing
caravan with Red Cross emblems displayed on car hoods and
fluttering from antennae.
   _ Zindanu Nou, 12:30 p.m. Not everyone is happy in the village.
A neighbor of the old woman with the toothless grin waves down one
of the cars in the caravan and pleads for bandages, sobbing that
her husband, a recent amputee, has been dismissed from hospital for
lack of space.
   _ Arad, 1:07 p.m. A man drops his bicycle to blow kisses as the
convoy enters the city, the site of heavy fighting just days
before. Romanian flags, their Communist emblems cut from the
middle, flutter from hundreds of buildings. While some volunteers
help unload medical supplies, others visit a post-surgical ward.
   _ Ortisoara, 1:57 p.m. A boy no more than 7 years old, a toy
machine gun slung over his shoulder, waves a Romanian flag and
makes the V sign as the convoy moves by.
   _ Timisoara, 2:12 p.m. Much of the convoy's goods have
disappeared inside a main depot at the city's Central Hospital, but
some non-medical supplies _ bread, tinned goods, powdered soup _
are spread out on the front lawn for the taking. Several young
soldiers, rifles slung, are busy helping themselves.
   John Haydok, a Hungarian who now lives in Yonkers, N.Y., is
tired but happy. The 42-year-old man temporarily shut his land
developing business to help here.
   ``This is my first convoy,'' he says, beaming and wiping his
brow. ``I'm sure it won't be my last.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>