<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0103 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1828EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Sit-InAnniversary     12-30 0520</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sit-In Anniversary,0538</SECOND>
<HEAD>Participants To Mark 30th Anniversary of Greensboro Sit-In</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GREENSBORO, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Part of David Richmond's 1990 vacation
will be spent drinking orange juice at a lunch counter in downtown
Greensboro. It should be a lot easier than it was 30 years ago.
   On Feb. 1, 1960, Richmond was one of four black freshmen at
North Carolina A&amp;T State University who walked into the downtown
Woolworth, sat down at the whites-only lunch counter and demanded
service.
   The lunch counter manager said no, and the store manager said
no, but the students refused to leave.
   Thus began a movement.
   In the weeks ahead, sit-ins would spread to lunch counters in 54
cities across nine southern states. They eventually shattered one
of the more visible racial barriers of everyday life and achieved
one of the earliest victories of the budding civil rights movement.
   ``What happened in 1960 served to launch people of the city and
nation on a relentless pursuit of human dignity,'' said Claudette
Burroughs-White, co-chairperson of the Greensboro Sit-in 30th
Anniversary Committee.
   The committee is leading several biracial groups in celebrating
the actions of Richmond and fellow students Ezell Blair, Franklin
McCain and Joseph McNeil.
   The commemorative events from Jan. 31 to Feb. 3 include
banquets, symposiums, a student march from the A&amp;T campus and the
unveiling of a plaque outside the store. The four former students
also will have their bronzed footsteps set in the sidewalk.
   Richmond and his three sit-in colleagues once again will take
seats at the lunch counter, as they have done at previous
anniversary celebrations.
   ``We didn't do it for the glory or heroics,'' Richmond said.
``It was just something that was spontaneous, something we talked
about collectively. I don't think any one of us singularly would
have done it. The four of us were like a unit. We have remained
close through the years.''
   Today, he quietly goes about his duties as housekeeping
supervisor at a Greensboro health care center.
   The others have left the area. McCain is an executive with the
Celanese Corp. in Charlotte. Blair, who has changed his name to
Jibreel Khazan, lives in New Bedford, Mass. McNeil is a stockbroker
in New York.
   The re-enactments give Richmond a chance to chat with Ima Evans,
the lunch counter manager who was working at the bakery counter the
day the students came in.
   ``We are very good friends,'' Richmond said. ``We have appeared
on a couple of programs together.''
   Ms. Evans, who is white, said the sit-in put Woolworth employees
in an awkward situation. The black employees were sympathetic to
the students, as were some of the white workers, but they weren't
allowed to serve blacks.
   ``I felt they deserved to be served as much as anyone,'' Ms.
Evans said, ``but it was policy all over.''
   The Greensboro sit-ins eventually involved hundreds of students.
Each day, they showed up at Woolworth and at the Kress
five-and-dime store down the street, causing an uproar at City Hall
and in the business community.
   After months of sit-ins, meetings and negotiations, Woolworth
and later Kress agreed to integrate their lunch counters.
</TEXT>

</DOC>