<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0110EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Names     12-23 0688</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Names,0714</SECOND>
<HEAD>Names in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY14</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Country music star Clint Black said he got the
audience at Carnegie Hall in New York to loosen up at a recent
concert, but there was one small snag.
   the crowd at the stately concert hall seemed to enjoy his
singing and made it seem ``like Austin on a Saturday night,'' he
said.
   One man even left a note on the window of his private bus that
was parked on the street just outside Carnegie Hall. It read: ``Yo,
Clint, loved the show.''
   One problem though: The man was a city policeman, and he also
left behind a ticket for illegal parking, Black told The Dallas
Morning News in an interview published Friday.
   Black is the first country male artist in 15 years to have his
debut single reach the No. 1 spot. His third single, ``Nobody's
Home,'' was released in November.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>SALT LAKE CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chemists B. Stanley Pons and Martin
Fleischmann, who concocted a controversial cold fusion experiment
in a kitchen, are at it again.
   This time, the results won't be questioned. Neither will they be
the subject of a new race to harness the power of the sun and stars.
   Pons and Fleischmann, who earlier this year rocked the
scientific community with claims they'd achieved a sustained fusion
reaction in a flask, annually turn their attention from laboratory
research to the kitchen.
   The menu at their holiday open house this year consisted of
nearly 60 different foods and beverages.
   The offerings included tortellini in sausage pesto; antipasto
misto; pate with green peppercorns and truffles; and avocado-lemon
mousse.
   Fleischmann said he looks ``askance at a scientist who doesn't
like to cook. Chemists, on the whole, take up cooking as a hobby.
Some study history or music, but I'd say cooking is the first
choice.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The daughter of Mayor Tom Bradley has been
charged with drunken driving and faces up to a year in jail if
convicted, an official said.
   Phyllis Bradley, 44, was charged Thursday with driving under the
influence and driving with a blood alcohol content of more than .10
percent following her arrest on Dec. 15, said Mike Qualls, a
spokesman for the city attorney's office.
   Bradley has a history of drug and alcohol abuse and has been
convicted of drunken driving before. Because of her prior
conviction, she faces a maximum sentence of one year in county
jail, a fine of $1,000 and five years probation, Qualls said. The
minimum term is 48 hours in jail, he said.
   Bradley was stopped by police in Los Angeles after making an
illegal U-turn.
   In a statement after her arrest, Ms. Bradley acknowledeged
having been arrested for such offenses in the past and didn't
contest the police allegation.
   The mayor has declined to comment on his daughter's arrest.
   She is scheduled to be arraigned Jan. 5, Qualls said.
 
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chinese pingpong star Jiao Zhimin
married a South Korean national pingpong player in an opulent
traditional Korean wedding ceremony at Olympic Park.
   Zhimin, 25, of China wed Ahn Jae-hyung, 24, on Friday,
celebrating the end of a five-year courtship started after the two
met at an international pingpong tournament in Pakistan in 1984.
They had married in a civil ceremony in Stockholm last month.
   The wedding procession included musicians playing flutes. The
bride was carried on attendants' shoulders in a litter and the
groom led the procession on a pony.
   Jiao covered her face from the groom during the ceremony, as is
tradition, and bowed many times toward her new husband. On the
wedding table beside candles and fruit, a live rooster and hen
clucked quietly, wrapped in cloth as a symbol of matrimonial
harmony.
   The two have said their love bloomed despite language
difficulties, bureaucratic problems and the lack of diplomatic
relations between their two nations. They plan to live in Seoul.
   Ahn was the bronze medalist in the men's doubles in the 1988
Summer Olympics in Seoul and Jiao won the silver in women's doubles
and a bronze medal in singles.
</TEXT>

</DOC>