<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1352EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ColdRdp     12-26 0639</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cold Rdp,0658</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands Of Water Pipes Busted In Wake Of Cold Wave</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Citrus Freeze</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Temperatures rose and snow melted Tuesday in the South, but
thousands of people had no water or little pressure because of
pipes cracked by the record cold wave.
   Temperatures stayed below the freezing point overnight
throughout much of the South, but were expected to reach the 60s in
the Carolinas by the end of the week, the National Weather Service
said.
   Airlines resumed normal schedules Tuesday at Charleston, S.C.,
after reducing flights because of snow, which piled up 15 inches
deep in places along the coast Sunday. The Myrtle Beach Jetport,
closed for a third straight day Monday, was able to operate only
during daylight because runway lights were covered by snow, said
Todd Crawford, deputy airport director.
   At least 96 deaths from the Plains to the East Coast had been
blamed on the cold since Dec. 15.
   The worst of the water problems was at Jackson, Miss., where an
estimated 60,000 homes and businesses were without water or had
greatly reduced pressure. Frozen pipes had cracked but the biggest
problem was that the Pearl River had frozen around intakes for the
municipal water system.
   Jackson's city government closed Tuesday because of the water
problem and several businesses that normally use a lot of water
agreed to close Tuesday or reduce operations. Mayor Kane Ditto said
that with luck, water could restored to all areas by late Wednesday.
   Texas cities also had broken water pipes, with more than 6,000
leaks reported in Houston. Some people had been without water since
Friday.
   Plumbers were besieged with calls.
   ``The wait could be a week, if not longer,'' said Billy Duncan,
owner of Duncan's A-1 Redi Rooter Plumbing in San Antonio. ``It
depends on how fast we can get to them and how fast we can get
parts in.''
   ``We're sitting here with about 300 calls, and there's no way we
can get to all of them,'' Duncan said.
   Hotels in Houston offered discount rates for people who only
wanted to take showers.
   Taps also ran dry in Charleston. ``There's got to be thousands
of broken lines out there,'' said Steve Kinard, manager of
Charleston's public works department, which supplies water to
400,000 people.
   And in Norfolk, Va., Fire Chief George A. Ingram said: ``We've
got water mains and pipes bursting all over the city, everything
from hotels to businesses to homes.''
   In New Orleans, water pressure dropped to dangerous levels and
the Sewerage &amp; Water Board issued urgent pleas for homeowners to
find broken pipes and turn off the water. Firefighters battling a
major fire Monday were hindered by the low water pressure, Fire
Department spokesman Bob Whitman said.
   The cold caused substantial damage to Florida's $3.5 billion
citrus crop and hurt other important winter crops, agriculture
officials said Tuesday.
   Although Florida officials hadn't released citrus loss figures,
the freeze damage was likely to be substantial since much of the
crop was still on the trees when freezing temperatures began
Saturday.
   Texas state officials estimated 70 percent of their citrus crop
and 80 percent of the winter vegetable crop were destroyed. Losses
were estimated at $200 million. But some Texas officials and
growers predicted they would be higher because warming temperatures
ruined any hopes of salvaging the frozen fruit for juice.
   In North Carolina, power had been restored Tuesday morning to
nearly knocked by Sunday's blizzard, officials said.
   Of the 500 Cape Hatteras Electric Membership Cooperative
customers who had been without power Monday night, only the Coast
Guard station at Hatteras Inlet remained in the dark, said Sandy
Gray, a staff assistant for the cooperative.
   North Carolina Power, which had reported 5,000 people without
electricity at the height of the storm, had ``zero customers out''
Wednesday, said spokeswoman Cindy Odom.
</TEXT>

</DOC>