<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0208 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0745EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a w PM-WalterMears ADV19   12-18 0727</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Walter Mears, ADV19,0742</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv 19</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release PMs Tues Dec 19 and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Retransmitting to correct category code.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Political Pay Raise Deal Will be Hard to Enforce</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WALTER R. MEARS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In theory, the House has shelved the oldest of
issues _ congressional pay _ with the political pact that is
supposed to keep candidates quiet on the subject next year. In
practice, that's going to be a very difficult deal to enforce.
   A conservative think tank already is denouncing both the raise
and the political pact. Stephen Moore of the Heritage Foundation
said congressional tactics on the pay raise were dictatorial if not
criminal.
   The prospect of loopholes that may yet make the pay raise a 1990
campaign issue does not dismay Republican political strategists,
who signed the campaign truce reluctantly in the first place. They
figure that the pay raise could have been the basic issue for GOP
challengers in their campaign to whittle at the House majority the
Democrats have held for 35 years.
   House leaders of both parties wanted the political truce to open
the way to passage of a cost of living increase next year followed
by a 25 percent raise and a ban on honoraria, both effective in
1991. President Bush wanted what they wanted.
   And attack-minded Republicans couldn't buck that lineup. So
party chairman Lee Atwater swallowed his misgivings and signed away
an issue that cuts against incumbents. The agreement was signed by
the two national party chairmen and by the chairmen of the national
House campaign committees.
   Shelving the issue works to the advantage of House Democrats
because they are the majority, with more incumbents at risk,
although one early application of the truce is said to have been a
reminder to a would-be Democratic challenger for a Republican seat
that the pay raise is not supposed to be used as an issue.
   That's not always going to work, in either party, even if
accompanied by sanctions such as the withholding of money and
manpower the parties customarily supply to their candidates. To
some challengers, the issue is likely to be worth more than the
support, especially when criticism of the pay raise could be
coupled with a denunciation of the national party truce as an
attempt at gag rule.
   One reason the issue will won't die in 1990 is that it will come
up again in the Senate, which shunned the full pay raise and voted
itself a cost of living increase without matching the House ban on
honoraria.
   Another is the newfound clout of the radio talk show hosts and
producers who stirred the outcry against the big pay raise Congress
decided to forgo early in 1989.
   Political use of that episode, notably by Atwater, who sent out
a Republican fundraising letter denouncing the pay raise even
though Ronald Reagan recommended it and President Bush endorsed it,
figured in the negotiations that led to the attempt to keep the
subject out of the 1990 campaign.
   Atwater signed, and there'll be no replay. He plans to observe
the pay raise truce to the letter, but not beyond. He does not feel
bound to monitor or enforce the truce, or to punish GOP challengers
who don't observe it.
   In his Heritage Foundation paper, Moore argues that Congress
should get a raise only if it meets deficit reduction targets.
Otherwise, he said, pay should be frozen or perhaps even cut. ``It
seems inconceivable that any corporation wallowing in billions of
dollars in debt would reward its management with a 40 percent
across-the-board raise,'' Moore says.
   Moore called the raise a bipartisan, midnight raid on the
Treasury, and said if the executive branch of a private business
handled its affairs that way, ``they would be universally denounced
and probably tossed into jail.''
   He said the political truce is even worse. ``In effect, the two
parties are conspiring to choke off any political opposition to the
pay raise,'' Moore said.
   Truce or no truce, complaints like that are likely to rekindle
the pay raise issue and put it on the political agenda next year.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Walter R. Mears, vice president and columnist
for The Associated Press, has reported on Washington and national
politics for more than 25 years.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>For Release PMs Tues Dec 19 and Thereafter</NOTE>

</DOC>