<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1125EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Flight103     12-23 0615</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Flight 103,0631</SECOND>
<HEAD>Friendships Rise From Ashes of Pan Am Flight 103</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LESLIE SHEPHERD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOCKERBIE, Scotland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tucked away in the hills of southern
Scotland, Lockerbie is the kind of small market town that few
American tourists would ever have known about had it not been for
the bombing of Pan Am Flight 103.
   Now, many know its quiet streets, verdant fields dotted with
grazing sheep and family-run shops as well as they know their own
neighborhoods in New York, Detroit and the many other cities the
victims called home.
   Because of the disaster, close ties have been forged between
many of the town's 3,500 residents and bereaved American relatives.
   ``There was a bond created that will last forever,'' said Joe
Horgan, a Philadelphia contractor whose brother-in-law was on the
doomed flight on Dec. 21, 1988.
   ``There were times when we lost our faith in our fellow man, but
you only have to come here to have it restored. These people
reached out in the midst of their own devastation and guided us.''
   All 259 passengers and crew members died when a bomb concealed
inside a radio-cassette player exploded in the plane's forward
cargo hold. Eleven townspeople were killed by fiery wreckage that
plummeted 31,000 feet from the winter sky.
   Local residents, grieving for their friends and neighbors and
still shocked by the destruction of their homes and streets, did
yeoman duty in the following days recovering bodies and wreckage.
   Later, they laundered victims' bloodstained clothing to be
returned to relatives.
   They formed a Lockerbie Friendship Group to help anyone who
needed to make the pilgrimage to the fields, churchyards and farms
where their loved ones fell. They welcomed them, provided
transportation and as often as not, lent an ear to listen or a
shoulder to cry on.
   Members of the group refuse to give interviews but issued a
statement saying: ``For some relatives, one visit is enough. In any
cases lasting friendships have been formed.''
   Paul and Eleanor Hudson, whose 16-year-old daughter, Melina, was
on Flight 103, stayed in the home of the local Church of England
vicar for last week's anniversary services. Earlier this year, they
welcomed a Scottish journalist into their Albany, N.Y., home.
   The local Roman Catholic priest, the Rev. Patrick Keegans, whose
neighbors died when the plane's fuel-laden fuselage struck their
home, became close to Bert Ammerman of New Jersey whose brother,
Tom, was killed.
   At an ecumenical service in the town square marking the first
anniversary of the bombing, the Keegans read aloud a letter from an
unidentified American relative who said: ``I shall return each year
to walk the streets of Lockerbie and visit with the gentle people.''
   ``Whether we like it or not, Lockerbie has become a place of
pilgrimage,'' said retired doctor Alistair Cameron. ``We have got
to be able to meet these people now and in the future and help them
express their grief.''
   Permanent memorials small and large have been erected in several
parts of Lockerbie, from a four-ton granite slab inscribed with all
270 names to a gallery of photographs in front of the alter of Holy
Trinity Catholic church.
   The night before the first anniversary of the bombing, Horgan
presented the town with an engraved plaque of appreciation.
   ``Our dear friends of Lockerbie, we feel bound to you by a chain
of grief and love so strong that it can never be broken,'' its
message says.
   ``Please accept out heartfelt gratitude for your kindness,
compassion, sympathy and kinship. We are all refreshed by your
goodness.''
   The plaque is to hang in the refurbished town hall, which served
as a morgue in the days after the disaster.
</TEXT>

</DOC>