<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0142 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1427EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama Bjt-1stAdd   12-20 0503</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama, Bjt - 1st Add,0517</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT ^PANAMA CITY: two hours.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The Soviet Union condemned the U.S. attack as ``gunboat
diplomacy'' while Britain offered support. Peru expressed outrage
and recalled its Washington ambassador.
   Venezeula summed up many reactions by saying it opposed
Noriega's regime but condemned the U.S. military intervention.
   The U.N. Security Council was considering Nicaragua's request
for an emergency meeting to consider the U.S. intervention. At the
U.N. meeting, Panama ``will demand that the United States withdraw
its invading troops immediately,'' Rodriguez said.
   The U.S. assault began about midnight Tuesday as forces attacked
Panamanian military headquarters, which witnesses said was
destroyed.
   Fighting also was reported at a Panamanian cavalry unit about
seven miles east of the Defense Forces headquarters; and at the
Panamanian base Fort Cimarron, about 20 miles from the capital.
   About 9,500 American troops from bases in the United States were
flown in to augment the 12,000 soldiers based in Panama.
   Panama's Defense Forces has 15,000 men. Noriega also has armed
citizen ``Dignity Battalions.''
   Noriega's main bodyguard, Lt. Asuncion Gaitan, spoke on national
radio after dawn to say that Noriega was ``well and in a safe
place.''
   ``Don't anyone give up your positions,'' he said. Gaitan then
gave a series of messages using code names and instructions.
   Fighting continued after dawn in Old Panama, just east of the
Marriott, and in San Miguelito, a poor district northeast of the
city center.
   The Panama Canal was closed at 1 a.m. because of the fighting,
said Panama Canal Commission spokesman Franklin Castrellon. He said
landslides had caused the only previous closings in the waterway's
75-year history.
   Panamanian forces attacked the U.S. Embassy, causing light
damage, and the area was secured by U.S. military personnel and
vehicles about 4:30 a.m., said a U.S. Embassy spokesman speaking on
condition of anonymity.
   The only TV channels operating were the U.S. military network
and a Panamanian station that displayed a Department of Defense
shield. Radio Nacional claimed that Defense Forces had shot down a
U.S. helicopter.
   The United States has tried to oust Noriega with economic and
political pressure since he was indicted on federal drug
trafficking charges in February 1988.
   Bush was criticized for not ordering U.S. troops to help the
mutineers during the October coup attempt. American soldiers
blocked some routes to Defense Forces headquarters, but not all,
and Noriega loyalists rescued him.
   On Friday, Noriega's rubber-stamp government declared the
country was in a ``state of war'' with the United States and named
the general head of state to deal with the threat. A day later, a
U.S. Marine lieutenant was shot to death by Panamanians in what
American officials called an unprovoked attack.
   American troops in Panama had been on maximum alert and
restricted to base since the lieutenant was killed Saturday and an
American Navy couple was held and the woman threatened sexually.
   On Monday, a U.S. Army officer wounded a Panamanian policeman
because he thought the man was about to draw a weapon, according to
the U.S. Southern Command.
</TEXT>

</DOC>