<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0230EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-MasterGene     12-22 0605</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Master Gene,0619</SECOND>
<HEAD>Scientists Discover Master Builder Gene of Immune System</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DANIEL Q. HANEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAMBRIDGE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scientists delving into one of the
immune system's deepest mysteries reported today they have
discovered the genetic trigger that equips the body to hunt down a
bewildering array of invading germs.
   One expert described the discovery as one of the most important
ever made in the young field of immunology, the study of the body's
built-in defenses against disease.
   Researchers from the Whitehead Institute for Biomedical Research
said they found a gene that ceaselessly reshuffles the genetic
library inside newly made white blood cells. This lets the body use
a limited amount of genetic material, or DNA, to concoct an endless
assortment of antibodies capable of zeroing in on bacteria and
viruses that it has never before encountered.
   Their discovery should improve understanding of how the body
arms itself against infection. While it doesn't immediately open up
new ways to treat disease, it may someday let medicine fine-tune
the body's weapons to improve health.
   The gene _ dubbed the recombination activating gene, or RAG-1 _
was discovered by graduate students David G. Schatz and Marjorie
Oettinger. They described their work in today's issue of the
journal Cell.
   ``It's one of the top 10 or 20 discoveries in the history of
immunology,'' commented Dr. Michael Lieber of Stanford University.
``It deals with the basic way that our bodies make antibodies in
the most fundamental sense.''
   The researchers believe the gene makes all or part of an enzyme
called recombinase, which cuts and splices bits of DNA. These
scraps of genetic material are assembled into new genes, which in
turn provide the danger-sensing radar for B cells and T cells, the
body's principal warriers against invading microbes and cancer.
   B cells work by secreting uniquely shaped chemicals called
antibodies. Occasionally, an antibody encounters a microbe with a
spot on its surface that is a mirror image of the antibody. When
this happens, the antibody latches onto this spot, known as an
antigen. This marks the invader for destruction by other soldiers
in the immune system.
   T cells attack invaders directly, and they look for them with
uniquely shaped structures on their coats that are known as antigen
receptors.
   The body constantly pumps out B cells and T cells equipped with
an ever-changing assortment of these unique shapes, and each unique
form requires the work of a unique gene. The body gets these genes
by randomly piecing together scattered bits of DNA from throughout
the cell's genetic archives.
   Two years ago, Dr. Susumu Tonegawa of Japan was awarded the
Nobel prize for discovering that this shuffling explains the
diversity of antibodies.
   ``Since then, we have learned surprisingly little'' about how
the body achieves this rearrangement, said Nobel laureate David
Baltimore, a co-author of the latest work. ``This is the first step
toward finding a chemical basis of diversity.''
   Schatz compared the immune system to an automobile factory. In
this analogy, RAG-1 is the assembly line worker who puts together
the cars' engines.
   ``This reaction is the very heart of what makes the immune
system go,'' he said.
   Schatz said it may soon be possible to watch and manipulate this
assembly process in the test tube and someday even in the human
body. One potential, though distant, application is in replenishing
the ravages of AIDS.
   The AIDS virus selectively seeks out and destroys a particular
variety of blood cell called helper T cells. ``Maybe in time we
will be able to specify the production of these particular cells,''
he said, replacing those lost to the disease.
</TEXT>

</DOC>