<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0229 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0036EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-InterestRates 1stLd-Writethru f0182 12-29 0672</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Interest Rates, 1st Ld-Writethru, f0182,0687</SECOND>
<HEAD>Economists: Higher Energy, Food Prices Unlikely To Alter Fed Policy</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 12th graf, `The federal ...,' to CORRECT federal funds
rate to 9] sted 9.50 percent.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JULIA C. MARTINEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The recent weather-related jump in energy and wholesale food
prices should have a minimal impact on interest rates barring
severe crop or oil shortages, but frigid temperatures in coming
months could chill investors' inflation outlook, economists said
Thursday.
   A record-setting cold snap in the past week has heavily damaged
fruit and vegetable crops in such major growing areas as Florida
and Texas and sent heating oil prices soaring in many parts of the
country.
   The price of home heating oil and other fuels such as propane
and kerosene have nearly doubled in some areas in the last two
weeks as demand surged and supplies dwindled. Cold weather closed
some refineries in Texas and Louisiana and curtailed crude oil
shipments in some states.
   On the New York Mercantile Exchange, near-month heating oil
futures jumped more than 40 percent in two weeks _ from 70.42 cents
a gallon on December 15 for the near-term contract to 99.71 cents
on Wednesday. Prices fell 3.31 cents to 96.40 cents a gallon on
Thursday.
   But economists believe the current weather-related price rise is
temporary. As such, it is unlikely to produce a long-term change in
the inflation outlook that would prompt the Federal Reserve to
increase interest rates in an attempt to stem rising prices.
   ``The Federal Reserve would be out of its mind if it changed
economic policy because it's snowing in Florida,'' said Susan
Lakatos, economist with Kidder, Peabody &amp; Co.
   ``If the heating oil situation were so serious and widespread
that it created shortages and closed factories we could expect some
impact on interest rates. But there is no indication of that,'' she
said.
   Nevertheless, the rise in heating oil prices and the deep freeze
that has damaged citrus and other crops have confused the inflation
outlook. Prospects for a drop in interest rates in early 1990 are
being put on hold, analysts said.
   Higher energy and food prices have also altered the inflationary
psychology of the credit and financial markets, with investors less
sure the Fed would act to loosen credit and push interest rates
lower, said John Silvia, economist with Kemper Financial Services
Inc. in Chicago.
   ``Instead of expecting the Fed to ease in January as before,
people will be a lot less optimistic with respect to inflation,
even though everyone knows it's a temporary situation,'' Silvia
said, ``and the Fed will be slower to ease than it might have
been.''
   David H. Resler, chief financial economist for Nomura Securities
International Inc., said the rise in heating oil prices may have
contributed to the rise in short-term interest rates in recent days.
   The federal funds rate, the interest commercial banks charge
each other for short-term loans, surged to 9] percent on Thursday
from 8.19 percent last Friday after holding relatively steady
during the rest of December.
   ``In a thin market with relatively few players around, anxieties
run higher than normal,'' Resler said.
   But investor worries may be premature. Resler said that because
food and fuel are considered nondiscretionary items in a household
budget, higher prices for those produces could mean individuals
simply would cut back on purchases in other areas.
   ``If I get stuck with oil bills 50 percent higher than usual,
the harsh reality is that I will have to spend less on something
else,'' Resler said. ``Over time that would exert downward pressure
on other prices.''
   Peter Greenbaum, economist with Smith Barney, Harris Upham &amp;
Co., said that food and energy normally are separated from other
inflation indices because of their short-term volatility. And while
higher prices for heating oil, citrus fruit and vegetables likely
will push the December and January wholesale price indexes up, it
should not amount to a sustained rise in prices, he said.
   ``The core inflation rate should be insulated from these
effects,'' Greenbaum said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>