<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0253EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AbuseProgram Bjt   12-29 0612</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Abuse Program, Bjt,0631</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hawaii Aims to Prevent Child Abuse With Early Intervention</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEVE ELLIOTT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HONOLULU (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hawaii is trying to fight child abuse with an
ambitious program designed to screen every new parent for the
potential to commit domestic violence and offer counseling to those
at risk.
   The Healthy Start program presently reaches 60 percent of
Hawaii's new parents, and the state hopes to be screening nearly
every new parent by 1992. Those judged at risk are offered five
years of home visits and counseling on economic and emotional
problems that can lead to child abuse.
   ``What's nice about the program is they're trying to help the
family in all aspects of family life,'' said Loretta Fuddy,
supervisor of child services for the state Health Department's
maternal child health branch. The department supervises seven
private agencies that operate the program.
   Twenty percent of those surveyed are found to be at risk and are
offered the services of a home worker who makes weekly visits, said
Betsy Uohara Pratt of Hawaii Family Stress Center, which began a
pilot program in 1985 from which Healthy Start was developed. Only
5 percent of the parents decline the assistance, she said.
   Roughly 1,500 to 1,600 households have received home visits this
year. That number is expected to increase to 2,600 by 1992. The
program is expected to cost $6 million a year when fully operating.
   There were 2,215 documented cases of child abuse in Hawaii in
1988, according to the state Health Department.
   Pratt said it is difficult to locate abused children before they
reach school age.
   ``I've seen a lot of kindergarteners absolutely devastated by
the time they reach kindergarten,'' said Pratt, who supervises the
training of counselors for Healthy Start. ``We can help these kids
get off to a safe and healthy start which would help them when they
get into the school system.''
   Healthy Start begins at the hospital shortly after a baby is
born. Workers interview new parents or examine their medical charts
to spot warning signs that indicate a tendency to abuse or neglect
children.
   Workers try to determine whether the parent or parents have
financial problems, housing problems, low self-esteem, were abused
as children, or have other traits considered warning signs for
child abuse.
   About 75 percent of those helped by Healthy Start are mothers on
welfare, Pratt said.
   The home worker counsels on basic parenting skills that help a
child's development and alleviate stress on a parent. ``Many
families have astoundingly little knowledge of infants,'' she said.
   Workers also help the families attack economic and emotional
problems by putting them in touch with social service agencies.
   Most important, Pratt said, the workers help build the parents'
self-esteem.
   ``What we do for them is cheer them on,'' she said.
   Visits are made once a week until a baby is 18 months and then
are gradually scaled back to quarterly visits until the child is 5
years old.
   Fuddy said the program costs the state $1,600 a year per family.
In comparison, she said, it costs $6,000 to provide a year of
foster care for a child.
   She said she hasn't heard anyone objecting that Healthy Start
might be an invasion of privacy.
   ``It's offered as a service to the families,'' she said. ``They
ask permission to interview the families and offer them home
visitor services.''
   She said assessment workers have permission from hospitals to
screen patients' records. The patients' permission isn't required,
she said.
   Pratt said it's too early to say if Healthy Start has had an
impact on Hawaii's rate of child abuse.
   ``We can only guess that it's helping,'' she said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>