<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0214EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BostonTeaParty     12-18 0309</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Boston Tea Party,0317</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bostonians Re-enact Tea Protest</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   People dressed as early Colonists and American
Indians rushed aboard a ship and dumped boxes of ``tea'' into
Boston Harbor on the 216th anniversary of the Boston Tea Party.
   The re-enactment Sunday evening of the Colonials' protest
against British tariffs took on a modern twist as some of the 50 or
so spectators, wary of how the Legislature might try to ease
Massachusetts' budget problems, shouted, ``No new taxes!''
   Under cover of night, with temperatures in the low teens, 15 to
20 people hacked into tea boxes and threw the contents _ leaves
instead of tea _ from the brig Beaver II into the harbor, just as
Colonials did with 347 boxes in 1773.
   Nine ``Redcoats'' then boarded the ship, and escorted the
``Colonials'' off to fife and drum music.
   The Tea Party was a protest of British tariffs on the brew and
England's practice of taxing Colonial Americans without allowing
them representation in Parliament. The protest helped spark the
Revolutionary War less than two years later.
   ``I'm a loyal revolutionary believing unjust taxes shouldn't be
on something we can get for a cheaper price,'' said Joe Kolb of
Watertown, who has played a Colonist in the re-enactment since 1976.
   ``I'll be here as long as I can swing an ax,'' said Kolb, a
field investigator for a utility company.
   ``We whipped the citizens into a frenzy about the tea, and they
decided to do something about it,'' said John Vann, speaking as Sam
Adams, the ``ringleader'' of the original protest.
   Vann, chairman of the Massachusetts Council of Minutemen and
Militia, wore Colonial garb and a ponytailed wig.
   He said the tea and debris from the boxes would be removed from
the already polluted harbor by a Boston Tea Party Ship and Museum
employee in a canoe.
</TEXT>

</DOC>