<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0227 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1231EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-YE--Yearin'89 Adv00-1stAdd   12-18 0575</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-YE--Year in '89, Adv 00 - 1st Add,0588</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv00</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release in Year-End Editions</HEAD>
<HEAD>UNDATED: with grandchildren.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   This was the presidency as a perpetual motion machine _ except
that critics said Bush was dragging his athletic shoes when it came
to governing. By year's end, he still hadn't filled some important
jobs in his administration.
   Bush declared war on drugs, and Colombian drug barons declared
war on their own government. ``Narco-terrorists,'' they were
called. By year's end, both wars were stalemates, at best.
   In Virginia, the old capital of the confederacy, L. Douglas
Wilder became the first black person to be elected governor of a
U.S. state. New York City, Seattle and New Haven, Conn., elected
their first black mayors.
   ``We passed another milestone on freedom's road,'' Mayor-elect
David Dinkins of New York said in his victory speech. But the road
contained familiar detours and roadblocks.
   Racial violence raged for three days in Miami's black Overtown
neighborhood after a black motorcyclist was shot to death by a
Colombian-born policeman. In New York, a black youth went into a
white neighborhood to buy a car; he was surrounded by a white gang
and shot to death. When blacks marched through the neighborhood to
protest the killing, they were jeered.
   ``My son will never turn this corner again and it's only because
of this _ the pigment of his skin,'' said Moses Stewart, father of
the slain youth. ``This is what America has to learn _ that we no
longer are going to take this.''
   America learned something else in 1989 _ a lesson about the
price of progress.
   At 12:28 a.m. on March 24, Capt. Joseph Hazelwood picked up the
microphone on the radio of his ship, the Exxon Valdez, and called
the Coast Guard in the harbor town of Valdez, Alaska.
   ``We've fetched hard aground,'' Hazelwood said. ``We're leaking
oil.''
   The light of dawn showed that the worst oil spill in U.S.
history, almost 11 million gallons of thick crude oil, had begun
tarring the pristine shoreline of Prince William Sound.
   Hurricane Hugo's fuel was wind and water.
   The vicious storm rampaged through the Caribbean, leaving more
than 30 people dead, and reached the U.S. mainland Sept. 21 at
Charleston, S.C., where it flattened historic buildings with 135
mph winds and spun on devastatingly through the Carolinas and
Virginia. In all, 29 people died on the mainland.
   ``We're going to be a long time digging out of this and
rebuilding,'' South Carolina Gov. Carroll Campbell said.
   The same could be said of the San Francisco Bay area, where the
biggest earthquake since 1906 killed 67 people and rang up $7
billion in damage.
   The quake was tragic, but it also brought forth the resiliency
and compassion of ordinary people. Just moments after the Nimitz
Freeway collapsed in a poor section of Oakland, residents clambered
into the wreckage to search for survivors. Similar tales of heroism
were written throughout the quake-damaged region.
   The Sunday after the quake, the Rev. Joseph M. Powers of
Oakland's St. Francis de Sales Cathedral held services in a Baptist
church _ his cathedral was too badly damaged to be used.
   Powers' message could stand as a sort of epitaph for the quake,
and maybe for the year.
   ``Sometimes in life,'' he said, ``God shakes us and says, `Pay
attention.' There is something more important than the ordinary
things in our lives.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Release in Year-End Editions</NOTE>

</DOC>