<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0235 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0146EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-ComputerContract     12-22 0278</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Computer Contract,0287</SECOND>
<HEAD>AT&amp;T Gets Transportation Department Computer Contract</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Federal Aviation Administration has
awarded a contract potentially worth $853 million to a unit of
American Telephone &amp; Telegraph Co. for up to 40,000 computer
workstations at Transportation Department offices around the
country, officials said.
   AT&amp;T Computer Systems announced Thursday it had won the
``networked computing contract,'' which will provide computer
hardware, software, training and maintenance for FAA and other
government transportation offices.
   Initial value of the three-year contract is $18.8 million, but
both government and company officials said it could reach $853
million with five one-year options to install a network of
computers in all department regional, branch and local offices.
   The department now uses ``a hodgepodge'' of 56 brands of
microcomputers, several incompatable software programs and a
variety of local area computer networks, said FAA spokesman John
Leyden. He said the new contract covers desk, laptop and other
computers in a network for administrative offices and is not part
of plans to upgrade FAA air traffic control operations.
   Leyden said it was the biggest contract FAA has awarded. He said
about $534 million worth of equipment and work would be for FAA
offices and the rest for other Transportation offices.
   The system to be installed is called OATS, for Office Automation
Technology and Service.
   ``We believe this is one of the largest desktop office
automation contracts ever awarded, '' said Gordon J. Bridge,
president of AT&amp;T Computer Systems. He said it represents a major
milestone in AT&amp;T's computer company, which is six years old.
   He said the new system will save the government money by
increasing productivity with state-of-the-art computers and
software.
</TEXT>

</DOC>