<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0321EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-SavannahRiver     12-30 0448</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Savannah River,440</SECOND>
<HEAD>Engineers Report No Cracking in Military Nuclear Reactor</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Energy Department after months of study
has dismissed the possibility of any cracking in one of the three
reactors at the Savannah River nuclear weapons complex. Studies of
the two other reactors are planned for next year.
   The determination of no cracking in P reactor is a major gain
for the department, which is in the midst of a $1.66 billion
program to repair and modernize the three reactors. They have been
closed for more than a year for safety reasons.
   Discovery of cracking in any of the reactor vessels likely would
put them permanently out of service since the 35-year-old vessels
are virtually irreplaceable.
   The Savannah River reactors are the nation's only source of
tritium, a radioactive gas used in nuclear warheads. Tritium decays
at a rate of 5.5 percent a year, so supplies in warheads must be
replenished periodically or the bombs cease to function.
   Barring any unforeseen problems such as vessel cracking, Energy
Secretary James D. Watkins hopes to restart K reactor by next fall;
the second, L reactor, by December 1990, and the third, P reactor,
in the spring of 1991.
   The Savannah River complex is located near Aiken, S.C.
   Last September, engineers of Westinghouse Savannah River Co.,
which runs the plant under an Energy Department contract, began
using a sophisticated new technology called ultrasonic testing to
check for cracks in the reactor vessels.
   Westinghouse and Watkins initially said completion of the tests
was not a precondition to restarting the reactors, but Watkins
changed his mind in late September after Westinghouse reported a
potential sign of cracking in P reactor. A few days later, he
announced that the irregularity was an existing weld repair that
would not affect the reactor's safety.
   The P reactor testing was completed Oct. 30.
   In Friday's report on results of ultrasonic testing at P
reactor, Westinghouse said there were no signs of cracking,
although several irregularities were found. It said these
irregularities were determined to be weld repairs done during
manufacture of the vessel, or other harmless abnormalities.
   ``In no case do any of these findings represent a concern with
respect to the structural integrity of the tank,'' the report said.
   In ultrasonic testing, high-frequency sound waves are passed
through the reactor vessel walls, and any abnormalities, including
cracks, show up as breaks in the waves.
   Becky Apter, a Westinghouse spokeswoman, said Friday that
ultrasonic testing at K reactor was scheduled to begin in
mid-January, but that it probably would be set back a week or 10
days because of delays in other work at the reactor.
</TEXT>

</DOC>