<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0122 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1611EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-RisingTerrorism     12-18 0550</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rising Terrorism,540</SECOND>
<HEAD>Terrorists Could `Increase the Carnage' Next Year, Officials Say</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Judge-Explosion Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RUTH SINAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Terrorists pressing for more attention could
well ``increase the carnage'' in attacks on airplanes and other
targets next year, federal officials said Monday. One raised the
possibility that chemical weapons will soon be used.
   Terrorist groups appear to be moving away from hijackings and
toward airplane bombings, as evidenced by the Pan Am explosion last
December and by the bombings this year of an Avianca plane over
Colombia and a French UTA jetliner over Niger in Africa, said
Anthony Wayne of the State Department's office on counter-terrorism.
   Thus, he said, the number of terrorist incidents might decline
while the number of casualties would grow.
   In the first 10 months of the year, 410 people were killed in
international terrorist attacks, according to preliminary figures
compiled by the State Department. In the corresponding period last
year, 308 people were killed.
   Terrorism has become so pervasive ``that it's lost much of its
shock value,'' said Seth Cropsey, deputy assistant secretary of
state for special operations. ``Terrorists, to stay on the front
page and in the public eye feel they must increase the carnage,''
he said.
   As a result, ``it's likely that we'll see more efforts to bomb
planes and the appearance of new weapons and tactics previously
shunned by terrorist groups. Indeed, future concern is the possible
introduction of biochemical agents,'' he said.
   Cropsey declined to elaborate on such prospects, citing
intelligence sources.
   A third official, speaking on a seminar panel with the other
two, cautioned against any expectation that reforms in the Soviet
Union would result in a lessening of support for countries such as
Cuba, Syria and Nicaragua that have been accused of financing
terrorist groups.
   ``Until proven wrong, we should not operate'' on that
assumption, said Oliver B. Revell, associate deputy director of
investigations at the FBI.
   Revell, speaking at a George Washington University symposium on
terrorism, said terrorist organizations such as the
Marxist-oriented Japanese Red Army and the Palestine Liberation
Front-General Command will continue to pose a threat to U.S.
interests and to Americans in 1990.
   Investigations have focused on the PFLP-GC as a prime suspect in
the bombing of Pan Am flight 103 over Scotland last December in
which 270 people _ among them 200 Americans _ were killed.
   Revell also said ``a very small number of tightly disciplined''
Iranians among the 325,000 Iranians living in the United States
could present a threat to Americans. ``Anti-U.S. sentiment has
continued'' since the death of the Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini last
summer, Revell said.
   Some 10,000 Iranian students on scholarships from their
governments live in the United States and ``with this
infrastructure, the threat appears to be substantial,'' he said.
   Tehran Radio reported in recent months on several meetings
between senior Iranian officials and the leader of the PFLP-GC.
   In another development, a congressional report issued Monday
said that increased security procedures since the bombing of Flight
103 are not being carried out properly at high-risk foreign
airports due to a lack of training standards.
   The General Accounting Office report faulted the Federal
Aviation Administration for not establishing minimum training
requirements and standards for the extra security measures taken
following the Dec. 21, 1988, disaster.
</TEXT>

</DOC>