<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0164 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 2128EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Peru-Peace 1stLd-Writethru a0684 12-29 0363</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Peru-Peace, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0684,0372</SECOND>
<HEAD>National Minute of Peace Marred by Violence</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS throughout to UPDATE with extension of emergency regulations,
details, minor editing. No pickup</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LIMA, Peru (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of beleaguered Peruvians prayed for
peace Friday during a national minute of silence called by church
and government officials, but even that brief moment was marred by
violence.
   The same day, the government renewed emergency regulations for
60 days in eight departments and one province. Such regulations
have been used since 1982 to combat terrorism.
   Precisely at noon Friday, traffic stopped, factories became
quiet, and people paused for a moment of reflection as one of the
most violent years in the country's history came to a close.
   Hundreds gathered in Lima's main square to hear an address by
Cardinal Juan Landazuri, but as the minute of silence began a small
group of striking state workers clashed with riot police in the
middle of the square.
   Witnesses said police quickly surrounded the group of about 10
workers, beat them with riot clubs and hauled them away.
   As the minute of silence ended, church bells rang and horns
blared as motorists showed their support for the vigil, the third
consecutive year the minute of prayer has been observed.
   Peru is being wracked by a leftist insurgency that has taken
more than 17,000 lives since 1980. At least 2,500 people have
disappeared.
   Sen. Enrique Bernales, head of a special commission on violence,
said this week that nearly 3,000 people have been killed in
political violence this year.
   ``Ten years of violence, of terrorism, of destruction and of
death have painfully torn apart the heart of our people,''
Landazuri said.
   Witnesses said traffic proceeded normally in outlying suburbs of
the capital, as many people ignored the call to prayer.
   The government announced the extension of emergency rules in a
decree published in the official gazette, El Peruano.
   The state of emergency regulations gives broad powers to the
military to fight leftist insurgents and suspends some civil
liberties, including freedom of movement and guarantees against
search and seizure.
   Such restrictions cover about one-third of this Andean nation,
affecting more than half its 21 million residents.
</TEXT>

</DOC>