<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0031EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-China-English     12-27 0730</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-China-English,0756</SECOND>
<HEAD>Language Lovers Defy Ban, Meet to Practice English</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Wednesday AMs report.</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHY WILHELM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Young Chinese determined to learn English are
defying police orders and gathering weekly in a local park in a
dramatic display of peaceful disobedience under martial law.
   The mix of soft-spoken office and factory workers and full-time
students, few of whom would dare challenge the government in any
other way, come each Sunday to a hilltop glade in the Purple Bamboo
Park famous for five years as the English Corner.
   There, they awkwardly accost each other and launch into careful
but determined conversation in English. A well-used opening line is
``How long have you studied English?''
   The park put signs up Oct. 28, declaring the corner closed. It
said students were too busy with other studies. But still the
English lovers keep coming.
   They begin arriving shortly before 10 a.m., hovering nearby
until the numbers seem large enough for them to climb the
now-forbidden hill. Then, huddled deep in padded coats and mufflers
and stomping feet for warmth, they mingle cocktail-party style,
chatting in English.
   Two plainclothes police burst upon the gathering one recent
Sunday, grabbing elbows and trying to move the participants along.
``Hey, don't stand around here,'' one yelled. ``Can't you read the
signs? The corner is closed.''
   The crowd of about 60 people moved sluggishly down the hill to a
lakeside, where skaters glided on the frozen surface. Conversation
resumed through cold-stiffened lips.
   ``The police never come back,'' one corner veteran said
confidently. A few minutes later, one of the police gave a
frustrated shout: ``Go away! Go away!''
   There was a pause, then: ``What do you think of Beijing?''
someone asked a visitor politely.
   It is a practiced ritual. ``They come every week,'' according to
a young man who said he was a science student. So does he, although
a bit nervously. ``I learn a lot from other people. I think my
English has improved,'' he said.
   Many of those who frequent the corner study English on their
own, and it is their only opportunity to try out words they've
learned from tapes or books. They consider English their best hope
for going abroad _ to study and perhaps, whispered one man, ``to
stay for freedom.''
   Certain ground rules have prevailed since June, when the army
attacked pro-democracy protesters and he government began an
intense campaign against dissent.
   ``Before we talked about anything we wanted to,'' said the
science student. ``Now we talk about daily life, maybe about our
(work) units, or cooking.''
   ``Laundry,'' chimed in a girl in a pink parka. ``The weather,''
said a man.
   ``But not politics,'' concluded the student.
   Most believe politics is the real reason the corner was ordered
closed. The student said some people used the corner before June to
make speeches about democracy, believing that police _ who
generally lack college educations _ would not understand.
   Foreign reporters also sometimes visited, using the
conversations as one barometer of what young intellectuals were
thinking.
   But almost everything in Communist-ruled China touches on
politics, and it is hard to avoid entirely.
   ``What do you think about the economic crisis in socialist
countries?'' the girl in pink asked.
   ``Crisis?'' queried a factory technician who had somehow
acquired Australian-accented English. ``Do you mean `shizi
lukou'?'' he asked, using the Chinese for crossing or intersection.
   Someone explained, and he was quick to learn the new word. ``I
heard an interesting conversation about the crisis in East
Europe,'' he offered.
   Listeners shivered with excitement at the words ``East Europe.''
   ``Can we talk about international politics?'' asked a tall young
man. ``Is it OK to talk about Romania?''
   ``I was delighted to hear about Romania,'' whispered a man in a
pale blue jacket, referring to the overthrow of hard-line Communist
leader Nicolae Ceausescu.
   Asked what they thought of Ceausescu, the group giggled
nervously. ``I have an opinion but I cannot tell you,'' said one.
``He was a dictator,'' said someone bolder. ``Autocrat,'' supplied
a third.
   ``Freedom and democracy is the trend in the world, and it makes
me very happy,'' said the technician to general agreement.
   No one spoke of Chinese intellectuals' frustrated hopes for
democratic reform in their own country. Generations of Chinese have
learned to communicate dangerous ideas like that without words of
any language.
</TEXT>

</DOC>