<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 2349EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NuclearWaste-Lawsuit     12-28 0402</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nuclear Waste-Lawsuit,0411</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nevada Sues DOE Over Nuke Dump Plan</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRENDAN RILEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CARSON CITY, Nev. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The state of Nevada has filed suit
against U.S. Energy Secretary James Watkins over Watkins' continued
efforts to locate a high-level nuclear waste dump at Yucca Mountain.
   Brian McKay, the state's attorney general, said Wednesday he
filed the lawsuit in the 9th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals in San
Francisco, seeking the court's endorsement of the 1989
Legislature's formal rejection to Congress of the Yucca Mountain
site.
   ``Despite our notice to Congress ... and Congress' silent
acceptance of that fact, Secretary Watkins continues to pursue the
project,'' McKay said, adding that the DOE is violating terms of
the federal Nuclear Waste Policy Act.
   The state contends that Watkins has made it clear to Congress
that he is pushing for the Yucca Mountain site ``in excess of his
statutory jurisdiction and authority and contrary to constitutional
right.''
   The lawsuit asks for an order that the site is unsuitable for a
dump, and that Watkins stop all site studies and related activity.
   The suit was filed a day after Gov. Bob Miller said he had
rejected four permit requests by the DOE to study the suitability
of the proposed Nevada site for the nation's first high-level
radioactive waste dump.
   ``The Legislature has passed and I have signed bills that make
the dump illegal here,'' he said. ``We cannot issue permits
allowing the DOE to begin testing a site we have outlawed. They
can't proceed without these permits.''
   Carl Gertz, project manager for the energy department at the
proposed Yucca Mountain site agreed that Miller's action made a
court battle inevitible. He said a lawsuit would be filed early
next year to obtain the permits.
   ``It seems strange to us that state officials say Yucca Mountain
is not suitable for the repository, yet the state will not grant us
the permits needed to make that determination scientifically,''
Gertz said.
   Energy department officials maintain the state cannot ban the
repository until the president recommends a site to Congress.
Miller said Nevada's position and that of the energy department
will have to be resolved in court.
   Current plans call for a waste site to be established by the
year 2010 to store 70,000 metric tons of radioactive wastes for
10,000 years. Yucca Mountain is the only location in the country
that currently is under consideration.
</TEXT>

</DOC>