<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0275 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1744EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-CommodityRdp     12-18 0702</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Commodity Rdp,0727</SECOND>
<HEAD>Heating Oil Futures Skyrocket as Cold Snap Continues</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID DISHNEAU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Heating oil futures soared Monday on the New York Mercantile
Exchange as forecasts for more brutally cold weather attracted new
buyers to a market that has been climbing with barely a pause for
five weeks.
   On other other commodity markets Monday, precious metals were
lower; livestock futures were mixed; and grains and soybeans were
mostly lower.
   Heating oil futures settled .49 cent to 4.24 cents higher with
the contract for delivery in January up 4.24 cents at 74.66 cents a
gallon, a four-year high.
   Unleaded gasoline futures finished 1.3 cents to 1.74 cents
higher with January at 54.51 cents a gallon; crude oil futures
settled 3 cents to $1.12 higher with January at $22.22 a barrel,
the highest level since last April.
   With sub-zero temperature readings boosting domestic demand for
heating oil, the entire energy complex has become a weather market.
The cold snap that descended on the nation's midsection last week
is expected to continue into this weekend, bringing unseasonably
frigid temperatures to most of the United States east of the
Rockies.
   ``We've had weather markets in heating oil before but in my
lifetime I don't remember a weather market developing this early in
the season,'' said James Ritterbusch, a energy market analyst with
Carson Petroleum Co., a Chicago-area oil distributor.
   Weather markets can create huge profits for speculators but they
are notoriously treacherous. A hint of a change in the weather
pattern can send prices plummeting.
   The heating oil market began its climb from about 60 cents a
gallon in early November amid concerns about tight supplies of
heating oil in Europe, which also had an early run-in with Arctic
weather.
   But the European weather has since warmed and river levels there
have risen with rain, opening transportation channels that had been
problematic.
   ``A week or two ago, you saw a lot of cargoes from South America
being redirected from North America to Europe,'' Ritterbusch said.
``I think some of those ships are now going to be making a U-turn.''
   Precious metals futures fell moderately on New York's Commodity
Exchange as the dollar showed some strength. Prices opened sharply
lower but trimmed their losses by midday, with support stemming
from tension over the shooting of a U.S. soldier in Panama.
   Gold futures settled $2.10 lower across the board with December
at $411.80 a troy ounce; silver was 3.9 cents to 4.2 cents lower
with December at $5.565 a troy ounce.
   Pork futures advanced on the Chicago Mercantile Exchange on
ideas that cold weather would curtail hog marketings.
   Cattle futures settled mixed in cautious trading ahead of the
Agriculture Department's monthly cattle-on-feed report.
   The report, which was released after the close, showed 2 percent
more cattle on feedlots Dec. 1 than on the same date a year ago
compared with market expectations for no change.
   November feedlot placements were much higher than expected while
marketings off of feedlots were only slightly above expectations.
   Analysts expected the report to prompt some selling of live
cattle futures at the opening Tuesday. But the report was perceived
as bullish for the cash cattle market and gains there could
partially offset selling pressure in the futures markets.
   Live cattle futures settled .10 cent lower to .35 cent higher
with December at 78.27 cents a pound; feeder cattle were .15 cent
lower to .30 cent higher with January at 84.57 cents a pound; live
hogs were .30 cent to .55 cent higher with December at 53.45 cents
a pound; frozen pork bellies were .13 cent to .88 cent higher with
February at 52.07 cents a pound.
   Most grain and soybean futures prices fell slightly on the
Chicago Board of Trade as new snow insulated the winter wheat crop
from the cold and rain brought refief to soybean crops in southern
Brazil.
   Wheat futures settled 1{ cents lower to 2 cents higher with
December at $4.15 a bushel; corn was unchanged to 1{ cents lower
with December at $2.34{ a bushel; oats were 1{ cents to 2} cents
lower with December at $1.42 a bushel; soybeans were { cent to 2{
cents lower with January at $5.80} a bushel.
</TEXT>

</DOC>