<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0146 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1551EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Aid 1stLd-Writethru a0637 12-22 0518</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Aid, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0637,0529</SECOND>
<HEAD>Aid Pledged to Romania; Red Cross Planes Set to Depart</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: UPDATES throughout with more detail on aid. No pickup</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATRICK McDOWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The European Community foreign ministers pledged
immediate aid to Romania on Friday and saluted the people's courage
in overthrowing the Stalinist regime of President Nicolae Ceausescu.
   The International Committee of the Red Cross in Geneva sent two
planes with 4 tons of medical supplies to Bucharest. Two
non-government aid agencies based in Paris also prepared to send
doctors and medical equipment.
   After a special meeting called by Foreign Minister Roland Dumas
of France, ministers of the 12-nation European Community said
Romanians paid a ``heavy price'' in toppling Ceausescu, who ruled
for 24 years.
   ``So that Romania can reclaim its destiny, the European
Community and its member states solemnly reaffirm their will to
give it the immediate aid and cooperation of which the Ceausescu
regime has unjustly deprived it,'' said a statement released by the
ministers.
   Dumas said later the aid would be in food, but he did not
specify the type or amount. He said community officials would meet
next week to work out the details.
   In Brussels, the European Commission decided to send $1.2
million in medical aid to be distributed by the French agencies
Doctors Without Borders and Doctors of the World, the French Red
Cross, the West German Red Cross and the International Red Cross.
   It appeared the Community also would review recent sanctions
taken against Romania, including an announcement Thursday
suspending preferential trading agreements on some Romanian
products.
   ``The Community is ready to furnish emergency aid to the
Romanian people, who have suffered so much,'' Dumas said.
   In their communique, the ministers invited Romania to rejoin the
35-nation Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe that
drafted the 1975 Helsinki accords on human rights.
   The ministers saluted ``the courage of the Romanian people, who
reconquered the liberty to which, like all other people, they have
a right.''
   The ministers were in Paris for the second day of a two-day
meeting on coordinating trade policy with the 22-member Arab League.
   Juerg Bischoff, a Red Cross spokesman in Geneva said national
Red Cross and Red Crescent societies in neighboring countries were
standing by to help. The Red Crescent is the Moslem equivalent of
the Red Cross.
   He said officials in Bucharest gave permission for the two Red
Cross planes to land, he said, and ``we suspect there is very
little medical material in Romania at the moment.''
   The planes will carry seven Red Cross workers and one
representative of the World Health Organization to Romania to
establish longer-term requirements.
   Doctors Without Borders and Doctors of the World said they were
sending medical personnel to Bucharest.
   ``The Romanians are short of everything: first-aid, antibiotics,
syringes, food and clothing,'' said Jacques Lebas, president of
Doctors of the World.
   Doctors Without Borders said it would send an eight-member
medical team and 1.2 tons of equipment Friday, and more flights
Saturday with 18 tons of equipment from Paris and Brussels.
</TEXT>

</DOC>