<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1133EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AntietamLights     12-18 0415</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Antietam Lights,0427</SECOND>
<HEAD>Volunteers Light Candles in Tribute to Civil War Casualties at Antietam</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto HAG1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEB RIECHMANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SHARPSBURG, Md. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Flames from 23,110 candles illuminated
snowy Antietam battlefield, flickering in a holiday tribute to each
soldier killed, wounded or missing on the bloodiest day of the
Civil War.
   The candles, burning inside sand-filled brown paper bags,
emitted faint light at dusk Sunday. When darkness fell, a trumpeter
played taps and 2,826 automobiles began a slow procession through
4.5 miles of the battlefield of rolling hills 70 miles west of
Baltimore.
   ``You actually had a sense of beings _ spirits,'' John Gress, a
Waynesboro, Pa., retiree said. ``In one place, someone placed a
candle so somehow it glistened on a tree covered with ice. It was
unbelievable.''
   More men were killed or wounded at Antietam on Sept. 17, 1862,
than on any other single day in American military history. Union
casualties were 12,410 and Confederate 10,700.
   ``It's a memorial and Christmas is the season of lights. We just
thought it would be a good time to stop and reflect,'' said Richard
Rambur, superintendent of the national battlefield.
   ``When you were placing the candles you'd wonder who might have
fallen on the spot where you were putting one,'' said Dan Weiss of
Sharpsburg, one of an estimated 400 volunteers who distributed and
lit the candles.
   It took at least 30 minutes to drive through the park to see the
candles glowing under a starless sky. Four cannons, black
silhouettes against the sky, were embraced by the lights, many
standing in rows like the headstones at Arlington National Cemetery.
   Neither side gained a decisive victory in the Battle of
Antietam, which was the climax of the first of Gen. Robert E. Lee's
two attempts to carry the war into the North. The battle also gave
President Lincoln an opportunity to issue the Emancipation
Proclamation, which freed the slaves in 1863.
   ``I was a medical officer in Vietnam where the American casualty
count was in the mid-50,000 range, and that was over a long period
of time,'' National Park Service director James M. Ridenour said.
``When you stand here and realize 23,000-plus within eyesight in
one day _ it's breathtaking.''
   The Rev. Richard Hembrock, a Lutheran minister in Sharpsburg,
said: ``People will be able to see how more than 23,000 candles
relate to lives out here. It will be a chance to reflect what we
fought for and what we believe in.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>