<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0250 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1239EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-SPE--BrideandGroom-TheCeremony 1stLd-Writethru b1337
12-18 0798</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-SPE--Bride and Groom-The Ceremony, 1st Ld-Writethru, b1337,0806</SECOND>
<HEAD>BC-SPE--Bride &amp; Groom-The Ceremony, b1337, ^Eds: Corrects Arabic
to Aramaic in 9th graf, Other ways ... says Syme. ^SPECIAL EDITION</HEAD>
<HEAD>Bride &amp; Groom: The Ceremony</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY702</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BARBARA MAYER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Newsfeatures</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The wedding ceremony of Susan Parsons and Donald Waite expressed
their relationship with each other, their families and their
friends.
   ``And that's a what wedding should do,'' says Rev. Paul Alcorn,
co-pastor of the Bedford, N.Y., Presbyterian Church in which the
couple were married.
   Alcorn says that most couples now want the wedding ceremony to
reflect their personal histories. In this instance, the groom's
brother _ an ordained minister _ officiated in the service with
Alcorn, and the congregation was asked to consent verbally to the
union. Then anyone who wished to could speak about the couple, a
part of the ceremony known as sharing time.
   The wedding also was typical because one partner had been
divorced, says Alcorn. ``A significant proportion of couples come
from a background of divorce.''
   Some other trends noted by Alcorn and others: Premarital
counseling is taken much more seriously. Alcorn says couples are
``very interested in interpersonal dynamics,'' and ministers are
likely to initiate discussions on how relationships succeed and
fail.
   ``More couples are opting for a more traditional type of service
than five to eight years ago, but with contemporary nonsexist
language. They avoid masculine-only gender pronouns and the thees
and thous. It's not just the father of the bride giving daughters
away. In 95 percent of the services, both families give their
blessing,'' says the pastor. He says he found the same thing true
in prior pastorates in Neenah, Wis., and suburban Chicago.
   Rabbi Daniel Syme, author of the book, ``The Jewish Home'' and
vice president of the Union of American Hebrew Congregations in New
York, finds that Jewish couples in the Reform tradition ``are much
more interested in knowing the meaning of the ceremony and the
symbols that will be part of that ceremony, as opposed to passive
participation in a ceremony which is not understood.''
   Interest in restoring traditional ceremonies but updating them
to reflect a more equal role for women also is an important trend,
he said. In Jewish ceremonies, it's common for both sets of parents
to join the couple under the wedding canopy, or chupa.
   Other ways in which tradition is returning include the use of a
Jewish marriage document in Hebrew and Aramaic, known as a ketuba.
However, the ketuba (the word comes from the Hebrew word meaning
``written'') has been recast to reflect the equality of the sexes
in the marriage covenant, says Syme.
   Among a growing number of Reform Jewish couples, the groom wears
a yarmulke, or skullcap, and makes similar caps available to all
men in the temple. Reform Judaism eliminated the requirement for
the headgear many years ago.
   Donning the skullcap signifies both the re-embracing of
tradition and the fact that many of those now affiliated with
Reform congregations came from more traditional homes. ``For them
the yarmulke is an important symbol,'' says Syme.
   ``It is customary now for the couples getting married in the
Catholic faith to enter more into the planning of their wedding,''
says Bishop Patrick V. Ahern, Vicar of Staten Island. N.Y., and
pastor of the Church of the Blessed Sacrament there.
   ``In the old days, it was a fully developed ceremony which they
accepted and didn't modify,'' according to Ahern, who has been a
priest for 45 years. The changes introduced by the Vatican Council
15 years ago make it easier for couples to exercise some choices.
   ``Couples are delighted to have that opportunity to participate.
They get a pamphlet listing options and in most cases go over it
very carefully,'' says Ahern. ``Often they design very beautiful
ceremonies for themselves, selecting the readings from scripture
and using certain permissible options.'' He says a favored Biblical
reading is the section on love in First Corinthians. The Waites
chose this.
   Many Catholic couples will opt for a candle-lighting ceremony.
Each lights a taper and then together they light a third candle, to
symbolize the unifying sacrament of marriage and their equality as
man and wife. They often turn to each other in exchanging consent
vows, adds Ahern.
   Rabbi Alex Goldman, author of the novel ``The Rabbi Is A Lady''
and 12 other books and religious leader of Temple Beth El, a
conservative temple in Stamford, Conn., reports that there has been
a change in choices of ceremonial music of the wedding.
   ``Gone almost completely are traditional military marches like
`Here Comes The Bride.' Instead, music that has come out of Israel
and is drawn from the Psalms or Solomon's Song of Songs is
preferred. This gives the ceremony a more romantic and more loving
character.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>