<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1415EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Obit-Beckett Bjt   12-26 0896</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Beckett, Bjt,0924</SECOND>
<HEAD>Samuel Beckett, `Waiting For Godot' Playwright, Dies at 83</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PAR2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHARLES CAMPBELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Samuel Beckett, the shy, Irish-born author whose
despairing vision of the world in ``Waiting For Godot'' symbolized
the pessimistic strain in modern writing, has died in Paris, his
adopted home. He was 83.
   The poet, playwright and novelist died Friday but the death was
not announced until after a small, private funeral service Tuesday.
His publisher, Jerome Linden, said Beckett died of respiratory
failure.
   The model of an artist who makes no compromise for the sake of
popularity, the Nobel Prize-winning writer attributed his success
to ``an intuitive sense of despair.''
   ``There are no landmarks in my work,'' Beckett once said. ``We
are all adrift. We must invent a world in which to survive, but
even this invented world is pervaded by fear and guilt. Our
existence is hopeless.''
   After the announcement of his death, several mourners gathered
amid the neo-Gothic mausoleums of Montparnasse Cemetery to place
flowers on his simple granite marker.
   ``I admired him very much,'' said a French philosophy student
who lit a candle at the graveside but refused to give his name.
``I've read most of his works and found them very moving. I cannot
believe he's dead.''
   At first, Beckett's audience was limited to an intellectual
elite. But the reclusive writer and his plays, especially ``Waiting
for Godot,'' came to be emblematic of a difficult modern style of
literature even for people who never read or saw the works.
   ``He was in the forefront of modern literature,'' British
playwright Harold Pinter said Tuesday. ``He was totally original
and a man of great courage, not only in himself, but in his work.
His work knew no bounds.''
   Jack Lang, France's culture minister, called Beckett ``an
immense writer, exceptionally exacting, who has profoundly marked
his century.''
   Beckett lived in Paris since 1937, working with the Resistance
in Nazi-occupied France during World War II, for which he won the
Croix de Guerre with a gold star in 1945. He once said he preferred
``France in war to Ireland in peace.''
   He wrote some of his some works in French and some in English,
translating them himself into the other language.
   Beckett's last published work was an 1,801-word novella in March
called ``Stirrings Still,'' a meditation on old age. Only 200
copies were published and sold for $1,720 each.
   Beckett's world echoed with cries of agony and compassion at the
futility and loneliness of human existence, peopled with vagabond
couples caught in a never-ending master-slave dialogue.
   Critic J.D. O'Hara once called Beckett ``one of those artists
for whom the miseries of the world are misery.''
   The miseries first caught an audience's eye in 1952, when French
director Roger Blin rescued from obscurity Beckett's two-act fable
about two tramps waiting for a third, Godot.
   Their grim jokes are interrupted by a brutal fat man driving a
slave with a heavy burden. The fat man later returns blinded and
moves on. The tramps end the play still waiting for Godot.
   The play was translated and performed in more than 20 languages.
When it was staged last year at New York's Lincoln Center with
Robin Williams and Steve Martin as the two tramps, it sold out.
   The stunning triumph of the 1952 production focused attention on
Beckett's earlier works, with their recurring theme of the
despairing vagabond.
   Later plays developed Beckett's themes of man's losing battle
against destiny.
   In ``Endgame,'' a blind paralytic laments his fate while his
senile and crippled parents die of despair in garbage cans.
   In ``Krapp's Last Tape,'' first performed in 1969, a nearly
blind old man plays back a 30-year-old tape of his own voice and
realizes he no longer understands the words he used in his youth.
Beyond hope or ambition, he remains interested only in trivial
reminders of his sex life and other bodily functions.
   Beckett won the Nobel Prize for literature in 1969. Always
secretive about his personal life, he refused to attend the award
ceremonies in Stockholm, fleeing to Tunisia to avoid attention.
   Even the date of Beckett's birth was wrapped in mystery. He said
he was born in Dublin on Good Friday, April 13, 1906. But his
biographer, Deirdre Bair, suggested he was really born a month
earlier, with Beckett shifting it to the anniversary of the
crucifixion as a boost to his self-made legend.
   The son of a surveyor, Beckett was brought up in a comfortable,
upper-middle class Protestant household.
   He studied modern languages at Trinity College, Dublin, and
first came to Paris in 1928 to lecture in English at the
prestigious Ecole Normale Superieure.
   In Paris he met another Irish exile, James Joyce. ``Joyce had a
moral effect on me,'' Beckett said later. ``He made me realize the
meaning of artistic integrity.''
   After Beckett's father, William Beckett, died in Dublin in 1933,
his mother urged Beckett to drop literature and take up a serious
profession.
   To escape her and her family, Beckett settled permanently in
Paris in 1937.
   In 1938, Beckett was stabbed in a Paris street brawl. A woman
passing by on her bicycle stopped to help the gravely injured man
and have him taken to a hospital.
   That woman, Suzanne Deschevaux-Dumesnil, became his lifelong
companion and they finally married in 1961. She died in July. The
couple had no children.
</TEXT>

</DOC>