<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0123 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1522EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AwardReturn     12-29 0448</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Award Return,0459</SECOND>
<HEAD>Indian Publisher Returns H.L. Mencken Award In Wake of Racist Comments</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOSEPH KEENAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SIOUX FALLS, S.D. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Sioux publisher of the Lakota Times
said Friday he has returned the H.L. Mencken Writing Award he won
in 1985 because of racist and sexist remarks Mencken made in his
recently published diaries.
   ``I feel very strongly that everything that I have fought for in
the last 20 years to try and improve race relations ... it just
wouldn't wash if I accepted an award and kept an award from a
person that has attitudes that are so bigoted.'' said Tim Giago, a
member of the Oglala Sioux tribe.
   His weekly paper is named for the dominant Sioux language.
   ``I have a strong feeling that this kind of subtle racism, by
people that are in a position to help, is probably the worst form
of racism.
   ``We can deal with outright, blatant, redneck racism because
it's right there in front of us,'' he said. ``But it is very hard
to deal with that kind of racism by people in prominent positions,
especially in the media, that carry this silent racial attitude
with them.''
   Giago, of Rapid City, said he also will return the $2,500 prize
that came with the award.
   Mencken, the famous columnist for The Sun of Baltimore, wrote
his diaries between 1930 and 1948. Publication was withheld until
more than 25 years after his death in 1956.
   Giago writes a weekly syndicated column on Indian issues for 20
newspapers across the country. He said he doubted others who
attended the ceremony with him five years ago, such as Coretta
Scott King, the wife of slain civil rights leader Martin Luther
King Jr., would have taken part if they had known about Mencken's
attitudes toward blacks, women and Jews.
   In one entry, Mencken wrote: ``It is impossible to talk anything
resembling discretion or judgment to a colored woman. They are all
essentially child-like and even hard experience does not teach them
anything.''
   A spokesman for the Baltimore Sun, which sponsors the award,
said Friday neither Publisher Reg Murphy nor other senior
management at the newspaper were available for comment.
   Murphy wrote in Editor and Publisher recently that he had
considered ending the awards because of the diaries, but decided
against it.
   ``You don't throw away all of the wonderful work of a man like
Mencken that was in the public domain because of the private
venom,'' he wrote in the trade magazine.
   Another Mencken award recipient, Chicago Tribune columnist Mike
Royko, told the Sioux Falls Argus Leader he does not plan to return
his award because of Mencken's private thoughts.
</TEXT>

</DOC>