<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0050EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-Panama-Assessment Bjt   12-21 0633</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Assessment, Bjt,620</SECOND>
<HEAD>Invasion Off to a Rocky Start, Faces Daunting Challenges</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   If the Bush administration was counting on a
quick, surgical strike in Panama, officials can only conclude that
their surprise military action is off to a rocky start.
   While the wisdom of President Bush's decision almost certainly
will be debated at length in Congress, the massive American
military force dispatched to Panama faces daunting challenges, as
does the new U.S.-installed Panamanian government as it seeks
acceptance both at home and abroad.
   Seldom are military operations pulled off without a hitch and
Panama is no exception. The invasion dealt the Panamanian Defense
Forces a severe blow, but Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega remains on
the loose. The deaths of American soldiers tend to undercut a
primary goal of the invasion: protecting American lives in what
Bush's view was an increasingly unsafe environment in Panama.
   The 24,000 U.S. troops in Panama still face the challenge of
securing control over Panama City. They also may be confronted with
the possibility that some Americans may be held hostage and that
armed pro-Noriega partisans may be able to engage in guerrilla
warfare.
   Still, the Pentagon could take some comfort that organized
resistance dissolved within hours after the operation began
Wednesday morning.
   The acceptance both nationally and internationally of the
government the United States helped install in Panama remains
uncertain. The Bush decision will be viewed positively over time if
Panamanians accept President Guillermo Endara as their leader and
foreign governments show their approval by dispatching ambassadors
to Panama City.
   Bush is able to boast perhaps only one unqualified endorsement
from a foreign leader _ Great Britain's _ while the voices from
Latin America have been almost uniformly negative.
   At the Organization of American States, the holdover pro-Noriega
envoy was allowed to assume Panama's seat Wednesday. The envoy sent
by the newly installed government was rebuffed.
   Things have gone better for Bush on the home front, with the
strong bipartisan congressional backing standing in sharp contrast
to the widespread criticism Bush endured following the recent
disclosure of two high-level trips to China.
   A Cable News Network poll found public support for the action in
excess of 90 percent.
   And few could argue with the assessment of William J. Bennett,
the director of national drug control policy, who said of Noriega,
``I think we can safely conclude that this ends his career as a
drug trafficker. He's not running drugs. He's not running Panama.
He's just running. And that's good.''
   The administration hoped that by now Noriega would have been
hustled off to Florida to face charges of narcotics trafficking.
But when U.S. troops arrived where Noriega was thought to be on
Wednesday, he wasn't there. The White House is offering a $1
million bounty for him.
   Fairness requires that Bush's critics take into account the
consequences of doing nothing, permitting Noriega to continue what
many agree has been a corrupt one-man rule in one of the
hemisphere's most strategically placed nations.
   Bush said he had no choice but to do what he did.
   ``I took this action only after reaching the conclusion that
every other avenue was closed and the lives of American citizens
were in grave danger,'' he said.
   The wisdom of Bush's decision will be discussed well into the
winter months and beyond. The risks and rewards of his decision are
such that there may not even be a definitive judgment by the time _
according to the Panama Canal treaties _ Panama is ready to assume
full control of the waterway at midnight on Dec. 31, 1999 _ 10
years and 10 days from now.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   George Gedda has covered foreign affairs for The
Associated Press since 1968.
</TEXT>

</DOC>