<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0626EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Dollar-Gold     12-21 0314</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Dollar-Gold,0332</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar Lower Against Most Currencies, Gold also Lower</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dollar fell against most major currencies this
morning in quiet European trading.
   Gold prices were also lower.
   The developments in Panama have had only a limited impact on the
dollar and unless the crisis escalates, the dollar won't receive
much support, traders said.
   ``The dollar market is very flat,'' said a Milan trader. ``The
Panama situation could help the dollar if it aggravates, but I
don't think so.''
   Dealers said the dollar was weakened by continued bullish
sentiment for the West German mark.
   ``There's no fundamental incentive to buy dollars while the mark
is so strong,'' said a dealer at a large European bank in Frankfurt.
   Volume is very low with activity limited to some last minute
commercial orders before the end of the year, traders said.
   In Tokyo, the dollar fell 0.46 yen to a closing 143.77 yen.
Later, in London, it was quoted at a slightly higher rate of 143.80
yen.
   Other dollar rates at midmorning compared with late Wednesday:
   _1.7312 West German marks, down from 1.7355
   _1.5588 Swiss francs, up from 1.5585
   _5.9137 French francs, down from 5.9165
   _1.9543 Dutch guilders, down from 1.9720
   _1,290.50 Italian lire, up from 1,288.00
   _1.1590 Canadian dollars, down from 1.1625
   In London, the dollar fell against the British pound. It cost
$1.6095 to buy one pound, more expensive than $1.6052 late
Wednesday.
   Gold opened in London at a bid price of $412.70 a troy ounce,
down from $413.50 bid late Wednesday. At midmorning, the city's
five major bullion dealers fixed a recommended price of $413.00.
   In Zurich, the bid price was $412.80, down from $413.00 bid late
Wednesday.
   Gold in Hong Kong fell 70 cents to close at a bid $411.34.
   Silver was selling in London at a bid price of $5.57 a troy
ounce, up from late Wednesday's $5.56.
</TEXT>

</DOC>