<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0230 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1541EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WKD--RecordReviews Adv00   12-18 0324</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--Record Reviews, Adv 00,0333</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv00</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Anytime</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WEEKEND ENTERTAINMENT AND ARTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>In the Groove: Record Reviews</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KIRA L. BILLIK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   ``Dr. Feelgood'' (Elektra) _ Motley Crue
   
   Rx for feeling good? Send for Motley Crue's ``Dr. Feelgood.''
   Produced by Bob Rock, who just wrapped the Cult's ``Sonic
Temple,'' the fifth album from heavy metal vaudevillians Motley
Crue has something for everyone.
   If you're mulling over the current political disarray in the
world, there's ``Time to Change,'' the musically sappy but
lyrically stinging closing ballad.
   If you like things a bit more playful, there's ``Sticky Sweet,''
``She Goes Down'' and ``Same Old Situation (S.O.S.).''
   But the wittiest, most Aerosmith-like of these is the
down-in-the-bayou groove of ``Slice of Your Pie,'' a two-part tale
of lead singer Vince Neil leering at a female passer-by, then
getting her where he wants her via the closing grind, a steal from
the Beatles' ``I Want You (She's So Heavy).''
   Numbers such as the barroom stomp of ``Rattlesnake Shake'' and
the near-speed metal of ``Kickstart My Heart'' show off the new and
improved musicianship of guitarist Mick Mars and bassist Nikki
Sixx, who both leave behind most of the usual metal riffs they used
in 1987's ``Girls, Girls, Girls.''
   Standouts are the title track, a tale of urban blight as seen
through a drug kingpin's rise and fall, and the dark ``Without
You,'' written by Sixx for drummer Tommy Lee and his actress wife,
Heather Locklear.
   The latter, praising monogamy, is a nice break from the
relentless barrage of the sex songs on ``Feelgood,'' and the
mushiness of recent power ballads such as Warrant's ``Heaven.''
   If you want Aerosmith, buy their latest, ``Pump,'' but the
closest thing on the Motley's record is ``Don't Go Away Mad (Just
Go Away).'' It's a breakup song with a smart attitude, despite the
ending that strains to use the cute title.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Release Anytime</NOTE>

</DOC>