<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0293 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1748EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-CommodityRdp     12-20 0734</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Commodity Rdp,0760</SECOND>
<HEAD>Orange Juice Futures Climb Higher On Freeze Fears</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID DISHNEAU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Orange juice futures prices climbed higher Wednesday on the New
York Cotton Exchange as fears of a weekend freeze in the Florida
citrus belt intensified.
   On other commodity markets, sugar futures fell sharply; coffee
futures gained in reaction to the U.S. military action in Panama;
precious metals advanced; energy futures were mixed; grains and
soybeans fell; and livestock and meat futures retreated.
   Futures prices for frozen concentrated orange juice settled 1.9
cents to 3.05 cents higher with the contract for delivery in
January up 2 cents at $1.3445 a pound.
   Freezing temperatures are almost certain to reach Florida's
citrus region this weekend as one of the most powerful cold-air
masses of the decade lumbers down from Canada, said Jon Davis, a
meteorologist who tracks the impact of the weather on commodities
for Shearson Lehman Hutton Inc.
   ``This air mass is so strong that even the fringe of it has
potential to cause some damage across the citrus belt,'' Davis
said. ``Now it's just a matter of how much damage.''
   The coldest temperatures, ranging from the lower 20s in the
northern reaches of the fruit region to the lower 30s in the south,
are expected on Friday night and Saturday night, Davis said.
   With temperatures that cold for an extended period, he said,
trees could be damaged as well as fruit, which could cut into
production for years to come.
   Sugar futures prices plunged on the New York Coffee, Sugar &amp;
Cocoa Exchange in reaction to a Brazilian court ruling that could
result in a rapid movement of supplies out of Brazil.
   A Superior Court on Tuesday overturned the Brazilian
government's decision to withhold sugar export licenses from three
trade houses in a bid to divert sugar to the nation's fuel alcohol
program.
   Sugar futures finished .32 cent to 1.14 cents lower with January
at 12.76 cents a pound.
   Coffee futures prices made strong gains in New York on supply
concerns prompted in part by the U.S. military action in Panama.
   The Panama Canal was closed to traffic Wednesday as U.S. armed
forces launched a surprise assault in Panama in an attempt to
capture Panamian leader Manuel Noriega.
   The incident created uncertainty about coffee shipments from
Central America.
   Coffee futures settled 1.12 cents to 2.13 cents higher with
March at 78.14 cents a pound.
   The military action in Panama also helped boost precious metals
futures on New York's Commodity Exchange.
   Gold futures settled $1.40 to $1.70 higher with December at
$413.60 a troy ounce; silver was 1.8 cents to 2.6 cents higher with
December at $5.448 a troy ounce.
   Energy futures finished mixed after initially surging on the
Panama news. But heating oil for near-term delivery continued its
dramatic rally, rising for the 15th of the last 16 sessions on
weather-driven worries about tightening supplies.
   West Texas Intermediate crude oil settled 7 cents to 10 cents
lower with February at $21.21 a barrel; heating oil was .59 cent
lower to .75 cent higher with January at 75.76 cents a gallon;
unleaded gasoline was .20 cent to .71 cent lower with January at
53.22 cents a gallon.
   Grain and soybean futures prices closed mostly lower Wednesday
on the Chicago Board of Trade, paced by moderate losses in the
soybean market linked partly to the closing of the Panama Canal.
   Wheat futures settled unchanged to 1\ cents lower with March at
$4.13 a bushel; corn was unchanged to 1\ cents lower with March at
$2.38{ a bushel; oats were { cent to 1 cent lower with March at
$1.52\ a bushel; soybeans were 3} cents to 6 cents lower with
January at $5.73} a bushel.
   Livestock and meat futures finished lower, led by limit losses
in the pork belly market amid disappointment over the government's
slow pace in buying pork bellies to ship to Poland and expectations
that monthly USDA report due out on Thursday will show a net
increase in supplies of frozen bellies.
   Live cattle settled .10 cent to .55 cent lower with December at
78.82 cents a pound; feeder cattle were unchanged to .15 cent lower
with January at 84.55 cents a pound; live hogs were .27 cent to .85
cent lower with December at 52.67 cents a pound; frozen pork
bellies were 1.90 cents to 2 cents lower with February at 49.60
cents a pound.
</TEXT>

</DOC>