<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0100 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1729EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel 1stLd-Writethru   12-30 0746</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0545,0771</SECOND>
<HEAD>Peace Activists Form Human Chain, Police Charge Twice</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: UPDATES thruout with suspected collaborator killed, 10 Palestinians
wounded in clashes, moves up reference to alleged waving of Palestinian
flag.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By G.G. LaBELLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 15,000 Israelis, Palestinians and
Europeans joined hands Saturday to call for peace, but police fired
tear gas and rubber bullets after some chanted pro-Palestinian
slogans and allegedly waved the banned Palestinian flag.
   Hospital officials said more than 50 people were injured.
   In the occupied territories, Palestinian assailants shot and
killed a fellow Palestinian suspected of collaborating with Israel,
and hospitals said Israeli troops shot and wounded 10 Palestinians
in scattered clashes.
   The army listed one wounded and was investigating the other
reports.
   For the most part, the attempt to form a human chain around the
white stone walls of Jerusalem's Old City was as peaceful as its
intended message _ ``1990: Time for Peace.''
   Israeli youngsters with balloons held hands with monks in brown
robes and Palestinian women in traditional embroidered dresses.
Demonstrators sang ``We Shall Overcome'' and chanted ``Two states
for two peoples'' _ a wish for a Palestinian state beside Israel.
   At least twice, police and troops charged small groups of
demonstrators, swinging nightsticks and firing rubber bullets. They
used percussion bombs and a water cannon to disperse knots of
people.
   Police officials said policemen charged into the crowds because
Palestinian flags were waved and anti-Israeli slogans shouted. The
Palestinian flag is outlawed in Israel.
   Reporters covering the event saw no flags, but small groups of
Palestinians shouted slogans against Israel's occupation and in
favor of the PLO.
   ``Palestine is Arab,'' went one chant. Another was ``Intefadeh,
go ahead,'' referring to the two-year Palestinian uprising that has
killed 640 Palestinians and 43 Israelis.
   Hospital officials said they treated more than 50 people for
injuries from beatings, rubber bullets and tear gas. Police
reported about 50 arrests.
   Rita Shukair, a Palestinian-American from Kansas City, stood in
the street carrying an olive branch, trying to block the mobile
water cannon from moving toward the crowd.
   A policeman slapped her in the face and pulled her away as she
shouted: ``Do you think this is Romania? This is the land of God,
of Moses and Jesus and Mohammed.''
   About 2,000 extra police were brought in for the rally. The
violence was limited to the two clashes near Herod's Gate in Arab
east Jerusalem.
   Elsewhere, the mood was festive as hundreds of balloons were
released into the air and people linked arms in the bright sunshine.
   Salman Faroukh, 32, a Palestinian who said he was imprisoned for
11 years for belonging to Yasser Arafat's mainstream PLO faction
Fatah, held hands with an Israeli teen-ager.
   ``This is the first time I'm taking part in such an activity
because I believe we should live in peace with the Israelis,''
Faroukh said.
   The organizers _ who included Europeans groups, the Israeli
Peace Now movement and Palestinian activists _ said more than 1,200
people came from Europe.
   Police estimated the crowed at 15,000, but organizers said it
was more and complained that army roadblocks kept many Palestinians
from arriving from the occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip. Army
officials said they only kept out troublemakers.
   A women's march a day earlier, sponsored by the same groups, was
violently broken up when an outlawed Palestinian flag was raised.
   During Saturday's rally, small groups of religious Jews in
skullcaps hurled insults at the peace activists, and Israeli
right-wing political parties condemned the demonstration.
   The Italian Foreign Ministry said it protested to the Israeli
government over the detention and alleged mistreatment of Italians
involved in demonstrations Friday and Saturday.
   Among them was Dacia Valent, a deputy inthe European Parliament.
The Rome-based La Repubblica newspaper quoted her as saying police
beat her over the head, kicked her in the stomach and spit at her
after arresting her Friday.
   Arab reports said Masud Ibrahim Imadi, 28, died instantly when
three masked men shot him in his home in the Bureij refugee camp in
the Gaza Strip. The reports said Imadi, a mechanic for the U.N.
Relief and Welfare Association, was suspected of collaborating with
Israeli authorities.
   His death brought to 165 the number of Palestinians killed by
fellow Arabs during the uprising. Most were suspected of
collaborating.
   Imadi's death was also the fourth in as many days of suspected
collaborators and comes amid calls by Arafat for such slayings to
be restrained.
</TEXT>

</DOC>