<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1447EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-CoalStrike     12-30 0464</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Coal Strike,430</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bargainers Continue Marathon Coal Strike Negotiations</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: Top prospects uncertain</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bargainers for the United Mine Workers and the
Pittston Co. continued marathon negotiations Saturday as they
pushed for an end to a bitter strike that's idled coal miners in
three states since April.
   The two sides returned to the table about 9 a.m. Saturday after
meeting behind closed doors at a Washington hotel until about 2:30
a.m., said Herb Fishgold, an aide to mediator W.J. Usery.
   Saturday's daylong bargaining session was the fourth since
Christmas.
   Both sides were under a gag order imposed by Usery and it was
unclear whether the same kind of progress was made during the
latest round of negotiations as was reported during the
pre-Christmas meetings.
   Usery, a former labor secretary named by Labor Secretary
Elizabeth Dole to mediate the coal talks, said last week he'd like
to have a tentative settlement by New Year's Day for miners in
Virginia, West Virginia and Kentucky.
   At the UMW office in Castlewood, Va., District 28 President
Jackie Stump said he had been telling striking miners, ``if it does
happen it will be great, but just don't depend on it.''
   Even if Pittston miners start off the year with a new contract,
things won't be the same as before in the coalfields before the
bitter dispute, Stump said.
   ``It's going to take a while, and maybe a long time ... for the
wounds to heal,'' Stump said.
   Some 1,700 coal miners in the three states are on strike against
Pittston. The union said the company's decision to end
contributions to a United Mine Workers retirement and health plan
and job security were the main issues. The miners had worked 14
months without a contract before the strike began April 5.
   The violence-marred walkout was prompted by Pittston's refusal
to contribute to the UMW's industry-wide fund for miners'
retirement and health plans for some 130,000 pensioners. Pittston,
the nation's largest coal exporter, says it cannot afford the
payments other U.S. coal companies make because it faces greater
costs in sending coal abroad.
   Union leaders said other coal companies also would refuse to pay
into the benefit plan if Pittston's attempt to stay out held up.
   The UMW has given each striker about $200 a week in benefits,
and the union said it would give strikers a $1,250 Christmas bonus.
The union is facing fines totaling $63.5 million for violating
court orders limiting picketing and other strike activities.
   Pittston has hired replacement workers, but production has been
well below pre-strike levels. The company reported its coal
operations lost $3.6 million in the second quarter of 1989 and $9.8
million in the third quarter, compared with profits of $9 million
and $7.4 million in the respective quarters of 1988.
</TEXT>

</DOC>