<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0630EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DeadbeatDads     12-21 0396</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Deadbeat Dads,0407</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fathers' Group Demands Equal Time With Judge Using Ads To Nab Deadbeats</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE LINDER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A judge's new weapon in the war against
deadbeat dads in divorce cases has led a fathers' group to demand
equal time against mothers who violate visitation rights.
   Family Court Judge Stephen Levin spent nearly $7,000 in court
funds for a full-page ad last week in the Philadelphia Daily News,
listing 136 fathers and six mothers accused of ignoring bench
warrants for more than a year, mostly for failing to pay child
support. He warned they would go to jail if they did not respond
immediately.
   Sixty delinquent fathers and two mothers did, although they were
angry about the unexpected and unwanted publicity.
   ``They said they were petrified, angry, humiliated, and several
told me they were even afraid to show their face on the street,''
Levin said.
   While mothers congratulated the judge for his innovative
approach, it irritated a group called Fathers and Children
Equality, which claims Family Court caters far too much to mothers
and takes too long to handle child visitation violations.
   ``Why doesn't he do it to the women who are purposely keeping
their children from their fathers?'' asked Benjamin Manis, who has
experienced problems with his former wife over their 4-year-old.
``We don't get equal rights in Family Court.''
   The judge said he recognized the validity of complaints over
visitation rights, but said he was elated at the results of the ad.
   ``We got an immediate response, and we sent a strong message to
others delinquent in child support that if you don't want your name
in the paper, you better pay up,'' he said.
   Levin said he would also try to address the visitation problem.
   ``Custody is difficult to deal with and, sometimes, fathers
won't pay support because the mothers won't let them see the
children,'' the judge said.
   ``And fathers are resentful because courts don't move as swiftly
to help them as they do for mothers seeking support. In the middle,
unfortunately, are the kids, and we are there to make sure they are
taken care of.''
   What about those 76 fathers and four mothers who have ignored
the ad?
   ``I am going to get sheriff's deputies to arrest them, and I am
going to put them in prison,'' Levin said. ``I am not bluffing.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>