<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0146 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 2208EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Books 1stLd-Writethru a0630 12-27 0688</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Books, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0630,0713</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ceausescu's Books Also Have Limited Shelf Life</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERT 2 grafs after 11th graf, `The couple ...' to UPDATE with
cleanup at U.N. mission; pickup 12th graf, `For the ...' editing to trim</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MORT ROSENBLUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Romania's national library is
desperate for books, but not that desperate. The complete works of
Nicolae Ceausescu are headed for the pulping machine.
   ``Perhaps we'll keep one copy of each, somewhere,'' allowed
Angela Popescu Bradiceni, director since 1955, with a slight sniff.
``After all, we are a library.''
   A trigger of the revolution was the looming presence of the
dictator's numbing words, bound in bulk. They were stacked in the
window of every bookstore. At the national library, they filled six
long rows.
   Enthusiastic workmen have already carted off various
translations of ``On the Way of Building up the Multilaterally
Developed Socialist Society,'' all 32 volumes, 700 pages each. The
English edition was baled to go.
   Had anyone ever checked out volume 26, for example, he would
have learned: ``The visit I have paid to Somalia at the invitation
of President Mohamed Siad Barre has yielded highly good results.''
   The pile included leaflets of speeches, collected mental musings
and 12-ounce publicity packets to the glory of a man who traveled
the world ceaselessly to exchange fulsome toasts and pose for
photos.
   One collection had almost identical covers. At the left, there
was Ceausescu with slicked down jet black hair and a debonaire
mien, a photo from 1957. At the right, there was someone else:
Jimmy Carter, Brezhnev, Mengistu, or whichever of his friends he
happened to be visiting.
   But not all the purged books were his.
   There was also ``Research in the Field of Systems and
Characteristics of Macromolecules'' by his wife, Elena.
   ``No one ever read this stuff, no one,'' said Virgil Tiberiu
Spanu, director of acquisitions. ``Never.''
   The couple was ousted from power Friday. They were reported
executed Monday A new revolutionary council has promised free
elections and democracy.
   At U.N. headquarters in New York, the Romanian Mission tossed
out dozens of books by Ceausescu, cut the hammer and sickle from
its flag, and dropped ``socialist'' from its name.
   Delegation member Dino Marian said Wednesday, ``I must confess
there already was a thick layer of dust on the books.''
   For the librarians, destroying Ceausescu's books was sweet
revenge for bibliophiles forced to hide away 10 percent of their
collection under lock and key.
   Ceausescu's strict laws forbade anyone without a special permit
to see books about Romanian politics since World War I, or works of
anyone suspected to be even a mild dissident. Books by foreign
radicals or U.S. economists also were restricted.
   Romanian and foreign researchers had to apply to a cultural
council that decided whether to grant permission. Applications were
referred to the secret police.
   ``When you applied to the council, a very secret, complex
mechanism came into play,'' Spanu said. ``Most people did not
bother.'' Some books were banned altogether.
   Mostly, books were not bought because the library had no foreign
currency.
   ``We were 10 to 15 years behind the world in scientific
material,'' Spanu said. The library's latest edition of the journal
``Chemical Abstracts'' is from 1972.
   But the problem went beyond money.
   In Romania, each typewriter had to be registered with the
police, along with a sample of its characters.
   At the news agency Agerpres, editors made a careful selection of
what was truth for the general public, what would be passed along
in a single copy and what would go nowhere at all.
   At the national library, directors are confident of a sharp
shift. As one good omen, their collection survived the revolution.
   Although the nearby university library lost 500,000 books,
burned in fighting between Ceausescu loyalists and revolutionaries,
all of the national library's 1.5 million volumes survived.
   ``We were lucky because we have no building of our own, and our
books are in storage all over town,'' Mrs. Bradiceni said.
   She looked around at at the shelves purged of Ceausescu's works.
``Now we have plenty of room.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>