<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0166 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1424EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WeekendTV Adv06-07   12-27 0771</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Weekend TV, Adv 06-07,0788</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv06-07</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Weekend Editions, Jan. 6-7</HEAD>
<HEAD>Elizabeth Pena Plays Wife of Drug Agent Enrique Camarena</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JERRY BUCK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Television Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actress Elizabeth Pena said she felt
fortunate that Mika Camarena agreed to meet with her before she
began playing the wife of a U.S. agent in the NBC miniseries ``Drug
Wars: The Camarena Story.''
   The three-part, six-hour series, which NBC will telecast on
Sunday, Monday and Tuesday, tells the story of the kidnap-murder of
Drug Enforcement Administration agent Enrique ``Kiki'' Camarena
five years ago in Mexico.
   The miniseries also stars Steven Bauer as Camarena and Craig T.
Nelson and Treat Williams as DEA agents. It's based on the book
``Desperados'' by Elaine Shannon.
   ``Mika had refused to meet with anyone else,'' said Pena. ``She
obviously didn't want to talk about it anymore. We met in her
attorney's office in San Diego. I came away admiring her greatly.
She was one of the forces behind getting justice for Kiki.
   ``She's a very centered person. She has great faith in God.
Elaine Shannon's book is very detailed, but Mika told me the
domestic things. Shopping, hosting the other DEA wives. I watched
her body language and how she thought things out before speaking. I
say whatever comes to mind. She's very careful, which I think comes
from being the wife of a DEA agent.''
   Camarena and his wife grew up along the border and attended high
school together in Calexico, a border town in California's Imperial
Valley.
   Camarena was stationed in Guadalajara, Mexico, where he was
abducted on Feb. 7, 1985. He was tortured and murdered by the drug
lords. DEA agents believed the crime was covered up by high
officials of the Mexican government, according to Shannon's book.
In this country, the Reagan Administration put a gag order on any
criticism of Mexico.
   The filmmakers, headed by executive producer Michael Mann,
stayed away from Mexico for their own safety and filmed instead in
Spain.
   Pena, who starred in ``La Bamba,'' ``Down and Out in Beverly
Hills'' and ``Batteries Not Included,'' auditioned for the role in
``Drug Wars.'' She has completed starring roles in the motion
pictures ``Blue Steel'' and ``Jacob's Ladder'' and is in the
upcoming NBC series ``Shannon's Deal.''
   ``A number of actresses tried out for the role,'' she said. ``I
felt more confident about the audition after I met the director,
Brian Gibson. Usually after an audition I think I should have done
this or that. I came back four times.''
   The last thing she did before ``Drug Wars'' was ``Shannon's
Deal,'' a movie pilot about a Philadelphia lawyer that was telecast
last June. It was written by John Sayles (''Eight Men Out,''
``Matewan'' and ``Return of the Secaucus Seven'') and stars Jamey
Sheridan. It has no air date but NBC scheduled it as a series after
it got a good rating and high critical acclaim.
   ``David Mamet will write and direct the first two shows, which
makes me a very lucky person,'' she said. ``I call it a Philip
Marlowe story. It's about a retired criminal lawyer who goes back
into practice. He wants to do it easy but winds up with a big case.
   ``My character's a kind of collage. She has a photographic
memory and she becomes his secretary.''
   It will be the third series for Pena, who also starred in
``Tough Cookies'' as Robby Benson's police partner and in ``I
Married Dora'' as a Latin American nanny who is about to be
deported and marries the widowed father of the children she looks
after.
   In ``Blue Steel,'' she plays the best friend of rookie
policewoman Jamie Lee Curtis. ``I'm a nice girl and it's so hard to
play nice,'' she said. ``I become the target for a thrill killer.
It's my first screen death. I did die in a stage production of
`Romeo and Juliet.' Twice, actually, since Juliet takes poison then
stabs herself.''
   She co-stars with Tim Robbins in ``Jacob's Ladder,'' a movie
that she said is about ``dying and letting go.''
   ``I'm a manifestation of his imagination,'' she said, ``but I
turn out to be something different.''
   Pena was born in Elizabeth, N.J., which became her namesake. She
spent most of her first eight years in Cuba, then was raised in New
York. At the age of 10 she followed her parents into the theater.
   Her husband, Steve Kibler, is a teacher at a junior high school
in the inner city. ``I met a school teacher from Kentucky in a soul
food restaurant,'' she said.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Jan. 6-7</NOTE>

</DOC>