<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0090 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1230EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Romania-Ceausescu     12-29 0309</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Ceausescu,0316</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ceausescu Held Prisoner for Three Days in Moving Armored Car</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Romanian dictator Nicolae Ceausescu and his wife,
Elena, were held prisoner in a constantly moving armored car for
the last three days of their lives, Britain's Independent
Television News said today.
   The Ceausescus were executed by firing squad on Christmas Day
after a secret trial.
   ``You saw in the movie on the television that he got out of an
armored car. Now I can tell you that he lived for three days in
that armored car. And the armored car was washed and moved inside
the unit (a military area) as if nobody was inside,'' Capt. Mihail
Lupoi, identified as a senior army official, told ITN.
   Lupoi said Ceausescu was a diabetic but refused to take his
daily dose of insulin during his last three days.
   Ceausescu was handed over to the army by a mob who had
surrounded him at a checkpoint, said Lupoi, who had been called to
the scene.
   He was then constantly driven around in the armored car for the
three days in a military area outside the capital to prevent any
attempt by loyal members of his security forces to free him, Lupoi
said.
   ITN also reported that when Ceausescu addressed a crowd from the
balcony of his palace on Dec. 21, he already had an escape plan
worked out.
   When Ceausescu's speech was drowned out by the angry crowd, the
escape plan went into operation, ITN said. The Ceausescus left the
next morning by helicopter which carried them to a pre-arranged
meeting with his chauffeur-driven car, it said. That night they ran
into a road block 60 miles west of the capital. There Ceausescu was
recognized by a policeman, who told people that the president and
his wife were in the car, Lupoi said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>