<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0942EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Czechoslovakia 2ndLd-Writethru a0494 12-18 0851</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Czechoslovakia, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0494,0875</SECOND>
<HEAD>Party Leader Predicts Coalition Before Elections</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: SUBS 4th graf to restore first reference to Havel; SUBS 6th
graf, `The marchers ...' to drop now-redundant first reference.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GIRARD C. STEICHEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Communist Party chief Karel
Urbanek said his party probably will try to form a coalition with
other parties before free elections planned next year, an official
newspaper reported today.
   The state news agency CTK said Foreign Minister Jiri Dienstbier
would begin negotiations in Moscow on the possible withdrawal from
Czechoslovakia of about 80,000 Soviet troops. The soldiers were
installed here after the Soviet-led invasion that crushed a 1968
reform movement.
   And the Communist Party daily Rude Pravo today printed an
extraordinary front-page apology ``to all those who were hurt'' by
its articles in the past.
   Previous articles that attacked Vaclav Havel, Alexander Dubcek
and other proponents of democracy ``did not reflect positions of
the majority of the paper's editors,'' said the newspaper's new
editor, Zdenek Porybny.
   On Sunday, about 100,000 marchers in Prague commemorated the
one-month anniversary of their peaceful revolution, which has
toppled hard-line Communist leaders and has forced the Communists
to surrender their monopoly on power, open borders and promise free
elections.
   The marchers also chanted their support for the election of
Havel as president.
   Urbanek was quoted in Rude Pravo as saying the party must renew
itself to survive and be open to a possible coalition with other
leftist parties.
   ``It is more than probable already now that the Communist Party
should go into the (free) elections in a coalition with other
leftist parties which already exist, as well as those to be
established in the future,'' he said.
   Officials have said free elections could be held in June or
July. They would be the nation's first in 43 years.
   Urbanek did not specify which parties the Communists might try
to work with, but he likely meant the Socialist and Peoples'
parties, which have traditionally been allied with the Communists
but have recently exerted more independence.
   A main item on the agenda of an extraordinary party congress
later this week is ``to use the richness of ideas from 1968 ...
while cleansing the party on all levels,'' Urbanek said.
   Premier Marian Calfa and Dienstbier are scheduled to visit
Moscow on Wednesday to discuss the withdrawal of Soviet troops and
closer economic cooperation between Prague and the Kremlin,
government spokesman Marcel Jansen said.
   The visit was at the invitation of Soviet Premier Nikolai
Ryzhkov, Jansen said.
   A meeting between Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard Shevardnadze
and Dienstbier also is possible, ministry spokesman Vlastimil Samek
said.
   Dienstbier and other Czechoslovak officials say the agreement
allowing Soviet troops to stay after crushing the 1968 ``Prague
Spring'' reforms was made under pressure. However, government
officials say any troop cuts should run parallel with superpower
disarmament talks in Vienna.
   The latest Communists to be purged from the party in the
shake-up were Slovak Communist Party boss Ignac Janak and six other
officials, whose memberships were suspended Sunday during a Slovak
Party Congress in Bratislava.
   Janak was expelled from the Czechoslovak Communist Party's
Politburo last week.
   Sunday was the anniversary of the Nov. 17 police crackdown on
peaceful student protesters in the capital that proved the spark
for the popular revolt that has forced an end to 41 years of
Communist domination.
   Havel, a playwright and former political prisoner, has emerged
as the main contender for the presidency.
   The November crackdown galvanized Czechoslovaks, who began
pouring into the streets by the hundreds of thousands to demand an
end to authoritarian one-party rule.
   Mass protests brought the resignation of hard-line leaders,
including president Gustav Husak, and lead to the creation of the
country's first non-Communist government since 1948.
   Participants in Sunday's march carried candles and held banners
that proclaimed ``Havel for President.'' They chanted ``Long Live
Havel!''
   The students retraced the three-mile path of the Nov. 17
protest, walking up to Prague's Vysehrad Cemetery and cathedral and
winding through Prague's historic streets for a rally at Wenceslas
Square.
   The marchers paused for a moment of silence and to light candles
at the site of the violent police charges against them in November.
   The flag-waving marchers were greeted with cheers and applause
by bystanders.
   ``We are just so grateful to the students for what they did to
bring about this change,'' said an elderly woman who asked not to
be identified. ``It's such a terrible shame that our generation was
not able to do the same thing.''
   Havel, in a televised speech Saturday night, said: ``We are all
grateful to the students for having given the revolution its
beautiful, dignified, peaceful ... and affectionate face that is
now admired by the whole world.''
   Under an agreement worked out last week between the Communists
and the opposition, Parliament will elect a president who is not
affiliated with any party and is a Czech.
   That appeared to clear the way for the candidacy of Havel.
   Dubcek, leader of the crushed ``Prague Spring'' reforms, also
has been mentioned as a presidential candidate.
</TEXT>

</DOC>