<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0234 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0249EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-FrozenProfits Bjt   12-29 0623</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Frozen Profits, Bjt,0644</SECOND>
<HEAD>Freezing Weather Heats Up Market for Heating Oil, Orange Juice Futures</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID DISHNEAU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Freezing weather is putting the squeeze on
supplies of Florida orange juice and heating oil, but it's
providing hot profits for speculators who own those commodities on
paper.
   Speculative trader George Booth estimates his customers will
make $700,000 to $1 million off the Florida freeze.
   The Norwood Hyacinth Fund, a public futures fund managed by Dunn
Capital Management Inc. in Stuart, Fla., tallied profits of
$383,000 in the heating-oil futures market from Nov. 22 through
Wednesday, according to Jay Klopfenstein of Norwood Securities, the
fund's sponsor.
   The recent rallies in the prices of orange juice and heating oil
have been spectacular.
   The price of heating oil for delivery in January soared 74
percent from Nov. 22 through Wednesday, when the contract settled
at 99.71 cents a gallon on the New York Mercantile Exchange.
   During the same period, frozen concentrated orange juice for
January delivery surged 23 percent to $1.5015 a pound on the New
York Cotton Exchange, with most of those gains made in the past two
weeks.
   Commodity speculators don't deny the frequent accusation that
they make money from other people's misery, but they do defend
their gains as the hard-won rewards of an extremely risky business.
   In addition, many of them were doing poorly this year until the
record-breaking cold spell hit.
   Mort Baratz, editor of Managed Accounts Report, monitors 169
public futures funds and 129 private investors pools that provide
opportunities for investors to speculate in commodity and financial
futures.
   ``I can tell you that the great majority of them have had a very
difficult year through the end of November,'' Baratz said Thursday.
   ``Suddenly, along comes a cold wave with a substantial effect on
heating oil and orange juice,'' Baratz said in a telephone
interview from his office in Columbia, Md.
   ``Now I'm confident that many of those I follow will recoup
some, if not all, the losses they sustained in first 11 months.''
   A futures contract is the right to buy a set amount of a certain
commodity, such as oil or orange juice, at a certain price on a
certain date.
   There are two kinds of traders in the futures markets:
speculators and hedgers. Hedgers produce or use the commodities
themselves. They buy and sell in the futures markets as insurance
against price swings in the cash markets.
   For example, when a freeze hits, an orange grower can sell
futures contracts at high prices. When prices inevitably fall, he
can buy back the contracts at the lower price and use the profit
from that transaction to offset his cash loss from freeze damage.
   Speculators are not involved in industries that produce or use
the commodity. They merely buy and sell in the futures markets on
the hope of profiting from price changes.
   Booth, of Palo Alto, Calif., calls himself one of the country's
biggest orange juice speculators. His company, George Booth &amp;
Associates Inc., manages about $32 million invested by 15
individual customers and 10 funds and spread among 22 futures
markets.
   Booth said those who depict orange juice speculators as vultures
circling the devastated Florida orange groves don't understand the
realities of frozen oranges or the futures market.
   First of all, he said, freezing an orange reduces its juice
content but doesn't destroy it, so orange growers haven't been
entirely wiped out.
   And many growers are as savvy as speculators at using the
futures market, which is essentially a vehicle for transferring
risk to those willing to accept it.
   A Dec. 22 report from the Cotton Exchange showed hedgers
outnumbering speculators in the orange juice market by about 12,500
to 10,200.
</TEXT>

</DOC>