<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0110EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Fed-InterestRates     12-18 0675</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Fed-Interest Rates,670</SECOND>
<HEAD>Economists Predict Lower Interest Rates in Next Six Months</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN CRUTSINGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Economics Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A variety of business and consumer interest
rates should head down over the next six months as the Federal
Reserve continues its efforts to keep a sluggish economy from
toppling into a recession, many economists predict.
   These analysts were forecasting that banks' prime lending rate,
to which one-third of all business and consumer loans are tied, and
mortgage rates will decline in the wake of further credit easing on
the part of the Fed.
   That was the prevalent view as Federal Reserve policymakers
gathered today for a meeting of the Federal Open Market Committee,
the panel of Fed board members and regional bank presidents who
meet eight times a year to map monetary strategy.
   While the meetings are held behind closed doors with the minutes
of the sessions not released until six weeks later, many analysts
were expecting a clear-cut signal of looser credit to emerge from
the discussions, perhaps before the end of the week.
   These economists believe the central bank will decide to reduce
a key interest rate, the federal funds rate, by another 0.25
percentage point, dropping it from 8.5 percent to 8.25 percent.
   The federal funds rate is the rate banks charge each other on
overnight loans. It is the primary lever the central bank uses to
control short-term interet rates.
   When the next easing move occurs, economists were predicting
that banks will quickly follow suit by reducing their prime lending
rates to 10 percent, down from the current 10.5 percent. Analysts
said they expected at least one more cut in the prime lending rate
to 9.5 percent to occur before next summer, in response to further
Fed easing moves.
   Analysts predicted that the credit easing would have a
beneficial effect on mortgage rates as well.
   David Wyss, an economist with DRI-McGraw Hill, predicted that
fixed-rate mortgages, currently at a national average of 9.75
percent, will fall to around 9.25 percent by next summer.
   Economists say they are confident in their belief that the Fed
will ease further because economic growth has slowed significantly
while at the same time inflationary pressures have moderated.
   ``It will take additional easing steps to guarantee that we
don't go into a recession,'' said David Jones, an economist with
Aubrey G. Lanston &amp; Co. ``I think we will avoid a recession, but
just barely.''
   Jones and other economists point to the fact that unemployment
has begun rising as various manufacturing companies from autos to
computer firms have announced layoffs in the face of slumping
demand.
   At the same time that growth is slowing, inflationary pressures
are easing. The government announced Friday that prices at the
wholesale level fell in November for the third time in the past
five months, with the drop led by a big decline in gasoline costs.
   ``Inflation has decelerated enough so that the central bank has
a margin of comfort to ease interest rates to boost economic
growth,'' said Allen Sinai, chief economist of the Boston Co.
   That assessment is far different from the view as 1989 began. At
that time, the central bank was in the midst of a yearlong effort
to drive interest rates higher to dampen demand and keep
inflationary pressure in check.
   However, in May the Fed switched course and began a series of
gradual easing moves as signs mounted that economic growth was
beginning to slow in response to the earlier credit tightening.
   The Bush administration has complained that the Fed has been too
timid in its credit loosening and has brought on an undue risk of a
recession. But most economists give Federal Reserve Chairman Alan
Greenspan and his colleagues high marks for a delicate job of
balancing the threats of inflation and recession.
   Wyss said he believed the economy will escape without a
recession and that growth will begin rebounding in the second half
of next year, at which time he predicted that the declines in
interest rates will come to an end.
</TEXT>

</DOC>