<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1159EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Sakharov 3rdLd-Writethru a0512 12-18 0962</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Sakharov, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0512,0985</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gorbachev, Other Politburo Members Bid Farewell to Sakharov</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 4th graf, `Sakharov, who...' to CORRECT that he was buried
beside Bonner's mother. New grafs 11-29, `State-run television...M.S. Gorbachev,'
UPDATE with memorial rally, details of funeral service. No pickup.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto MOSB1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN-THOR DAHLBURG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Human rights champion Andrei D. Sakharov was
buried today in the cold earth of the Russia he tried so hard to
change, mourned by tens of thousands of countrymen and praised by
the leadership that once reviled him.
   ``It's over,'' Sakharov's wife and dissident comrade-in-arms,
Yelena Bonner, said as she turned to a companion during the
twilight burial in a Moscow cemetery.
   Before Sakharov's crimson- and black-trimmed coffin was lowered
into the ground at Vostryakovskoye Cemetery, its cover was removed
to allow Bonner to bid a final farewell. She removed the shroud
from his face and bent to kiss him on the forehead.
   Sakharov, who died Thursday of an apparent heart attack at the
age of 68, he was buried alongside Bonner's mother, Ruth, a
Stalin-era political prisoner who died in 1987 at age 87.
   Top party brass riding sleek black limousines and tens of
thousands of common people trudging through the slush joined in
paying their last respects to the Nobel laureate.
   President Mikhail S. Gorbachev and other ruling Politburo
members stood in icy morning rain to view the body outside the
Academy of Sciences, to which Sakharov, a creator of the Soviet
hydrogen bomb, belonged. Gorbachev spoke at length with Bonner.
   ``Now it is clear that he deserved the Nobel Prize,'' Gorbachev
told reporters. Sakharov was denied permission to travel to Norway
to accept the 1975 prize for his human rights campaign. He was
hounded for years and finally banished into internal exile by past
Soviet leaders.
   Some marchers carried protest signs demanding democratic
elections, echoing the final cause of Sakharov before he died last
week. Others hoisted the blue-red-white flag of czarist Russia, now
the symbol of the grassroots pro-democracy Russian People's Front.
   More than 8,000 grieving Soviets followed Sakharov's body,
transported in an open-ended bus that also carried Bonner along
Lenin Prospekt to outdoor funeral ceremonies at Luzhniki sports
complex. The southern Moscow facility is a favorite site for
rallies by human rights activists.
   In the Kremlin, the 2,250-member Soviet Congress to which
Sakharov belonged adjourned at midday so its members could attend
the ceremony.
   State-run television showed excerpts of the service in a special
broadcast of the kind usually reserved for the deaths of major
government figures.
   At the outdoor service, the crowd surged dangerously forward
toward Sakharov's coffin and Bonner had to plead for order. The
coffin was then transported nine miles in a bus along slush-filled
streets to the cemetery.
   In the afternoon, tens of thousands of mourners gathered at the
Luzhniki stadium parking lot for a memorial service.
   Sakharov ``did all he could,'' said Ilya Zaslavsky, a Moscow
member of the Soviet Congress. ``Now only his ideas can change
things, and only we can fulfill his ideas.''
   Other parliamentarians pledged to heed Sakharov's call to create
a full-fledged opposition in the Congress and to push for victory
for progressives in local elections.
   ``The best wreath for Andrei Dmitrievich Sakharov is to win over
conservatives in the March elections,'' said economist and deputy
Gavriil Popov.
   Lech Walesa, the leader of Poland's Solidarity movement and
winner of the 1983 Nobel Peace Prize, had been expected to attend
the funeral, but Poland's official PAP news agency reported that
his plane had to land in Leningrad because of bad weather.
   Gorbachev and other top Soviet officials, including Politburo
members Premier Nikolai I. Ryzhkov, Vitaly I. Vorotnikov, Alexander
N. Yakovlev and Vadim A. Medvedev arrived at the Academy of
Sciences building in Moscow in the morning to view Sakharov's body.
   From another direction, buses escorted by police cars arrived.
Some 20 people bore a closed casket on their shoulders from a bus,
and placed it on a platform in front of the academy. Bonner also
emerged, accompanied by her son Alexei Semenov.
   The coffin was opened in the frigid rain, and an umbrella opened
to shield Sakharov's face.
   Gorbachev walked to the foot of the casket, and stood for awhile
in silence. He then nodded, and the huddle of people around the
casket broke up.
   Sakharov's body was placed back on the bus and taken to the
Lebedev Physics Institute, where Sakharov worked.
   ``His only wish was for the state to have a human face,''
Academician Yevgeny L. Feynberg said of his fellow physicist as
colleagues at the institute filed past the casket.
   Outside the Academy of Sciences, Gorbachev and Bonner spoke
animatedly, with Bonner smiling at one point. Gorbachev and his
entourage entered the academy building to sign an official book of
condolences. The Soviet leader simply wrote ``M.S. Gorbachev.''
   He emerged, and talked briefly with repoters. ``The relations
between myself and Sakharov were always those of mutual respect,''
Gorbachev said. ``Now it is clear that he deserved the Nobel
Prize.''
   It was Gorbachev who allowed Sakharov to return to Moscow in
December 1986 after nearly seven years of internal exile in the
city of Gorky. The two men had clashed, however, over the speed and
sweep of Gorbachev's political reform program, with Sakharov
demanding the Communist Party that Gorbachev heads renounce its
constitutional monopoly on power.
   Moscow News _ an organ of the official press which once branded
Sakharov an ``utterly ignorant person'' _ took the rare step Sunday
of publishing a special edition devoted to the activist.
   It included a text of Sakharov's last public remarks, a speech
he delivered hours before his death in which he said the Soviet
hierarchy was ``leading the country to a catastrophe.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>