<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1403EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Colombia     12-23 0453</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia,0465</SECOND>
<HEAD>Leftist Guerrillas Attack Army Patrol, Kill 10 Soldiers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STAN YARBRO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Leftist guerrillas from the nation's
largest insurgent group ambushed an army patrol in southern
Colombia on Saturday, killing 10 soldiers, an army communique said.
   The attack came just hours after another leftist guerrilla
group, the April 19 Movement, announced it had suspended a
tentative peace pact after Congress failed to approved key parts of
the accord.
   Guerrillas belonging to the Revolutionary Armed Forces of
Colombia blew up part of the road south of the town of San Martin
as an army patrol traveling in three vehicles passed over it, the
communique said.
   The insurgents then opened fire on the patrol with automatic
weapons and rockets, killing 10 soldiers and injuring an
undetermined number, said the communique, read in a radio broadcast
by the Caracol network.
   The communique added that forces from the army's 7th Brigade
were still fighting the guerrillas who perpetrated the attack. San
Martin is 65 miles south of Bogota in Meta state.
   Founded about 30 years ago, the Revolutionary Armed Forces of
Colombia, with its estimated 5,000 armed rebels, is the oldest and
largest of Colombia's six main guerrilla groups.
   Another group, the April 19 Movment, said Saturday that it would
not lay down its weapons and accept a government amnesty this month
as originally planned.
   The movement cited as the reason for its decision Congress's
failure to approve key points of an official peace plan, which were
included in legislation to reform the country's constitution.
   The Senate shelved the legislation Dec. 14, after the House
attached a bill allowing a national vote on Colombia's extradition
of drug traffickers.
   The Senate apparently accepted President Virgilio Barco's
argument that the extradition referendum would lead to increased
terrorist violence by traffickers trying to pressure the public
into rejecting extradition.
   The shelving of the reform legislation was viewed as a victory
for the Barco administration's struggle against traffickers but a
blow to its efforts to make peace with the April 19 Movement and
other leftist groups.
   The legislation would have created a special electoral system
allowing the movement to elect members to Congress with fewer votes
than normally required. The group had demanded the concession in
return for its agreement to lay down its arms.
   A joint communique issued Saturday by the April 19 Movement's
leaders and government negotiators said the agreement has been
suspended but not discarded. ``Its contents are still valid, and
its negotiators have the responsibility to make it a reality,'' the
communique said.
   Both sides expressed ``the will to continue seeking dialogue and
negotiation.'' A new round of talks to save the pact is to begin in
January.
</TEXT>

</DOC>