<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1240EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r k BC-EditorialRdp 2ndAdd   12-27 0531</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Editorial Rdp, 2nd Add,0552</SECOND>
<HEAD>UNDATED: the former.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Dec. 19
   The Cedar Rapids, Iowa, Gazette on Mississippi River pollution:
   Abuse and indifference finally have caught up with the
Mississippi River. It probably shouldn't have come as too great a
shock recently when the environmental group Greenpeace pronounced
``the father of waters'' a ``soup of toxic chemicals.''...
   Iowa's contribution to the pollution is varied, although the
greatest portion comes from agricultural pesticide runoff.
Startling quantities are involved: It has been determined, for
example, that 112,000 pounds of the chemical Alachlor flows past a
test site in Louisiana each year.
   The Greenpeace report pointed a finger at specific industries,
as well, claiming they are discharging ``metals, solvents,
cancer-causing hydrocarbons,'' and assorted other toxins into the
Mississippi at Clinton, Muscatine and Riverdale. ...
   Any smugness we middle Americans may have felt toward our
countrymen in the sooty, grimy reaches of New York or California
with their debris-infested beaches is misplaced until we get to
work cleaning up after ourselves.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Dec. 25
   The Omaha (Neb.) World-Herald on the Soviets and NATO:
   After years of hating the NATO alliance and trying to weaken it,
the Kremlin now apparently sees NATO as a way of keeping Germany
from attempting to capitalize on Soviet weakness.
   American diplomats have pointed to the Warsaw Pact as a
stabilizing infuence as Eastern Europe undergoes what amounts to a
democratic revolution. Shevardnadze has made a similar point
regarding the American presence. The two Germanys are not likely to
go wobbling off on a disturbing political or military course if
Soviet and American troops are still present in the heart of Europe.
   Reducing those troops to more reasonable levels is now the work
of the Soviet-American arms negotiators in Geneva. The job should
be easier because the Soviets finally admit that the Americans are
in Europe to keep the peace, not to start another war.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Dec. 26
   The Sioux Falls (S.D.) Argus Leader:
   Under the terms of his new contract, Kirby Puckett of the
Minnesota Twins will make more in a month than President Bush will
make in a year.
   The star outfielder will make more in a month than (South
Dakota) Gov. George Mickelson will for his entire four-year term.
   At $9 million for three years, Puckett will average $250,000 a
month. And he isn't even the highest paid player in major league
baseball.
   Lately, baseball players have been grabbing the spotlight. They
have been the beneficiaries of a spectacular, new boom in salaries.
The players have shown that they can overpower team owners at the
bargaining table, as well as on the field.
   The new salary structure is almost sickening. It reflects a
skewed system of public values that has actually been in place for
decades. Don't blame the modern players for taking what they can
get. That's how free enterprise works.
   If you like, blame the owners, who publicly plead poverty, and
then get into multimillion-dollar bidding wars for mediocre
pitchers and .225 hitters.
   Mostly, though, blame those of us who are silly enough to keep
going to games, keep watching them on television, keep reading
about them and otherwise keep caring.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Editorial Rdp</NOTE>

</DOC>