<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0181 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0827EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Braniff     12-28 0428</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Braniff,0445</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dallas Entrepreneur Wants To Buy Braniff</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ORLANDO, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Dallas entrepreneur who tried last year
to found an airline for smokers now wants to purchase Braniff Inc.,
a newspaper reported.
   Kay Cohlmia was to meet with representatives of the troubled
carrier today, he told the Orlando Sentinel in a telephone
interview. He said he has arranged financing but would not give
details.
   Orlando-based Braniff filed Sept. 28 for bankruptcy protection
and has been short of cash since.
   Lawyers for the carrier's unsecured creditors said they have not
been approached by Cohlmia.
   ``We're interested to hear what his offer is,'' said attorney
Richard Levy, who represents the unsecured creditors' committee.
Levy said his office does not have an appointment to meet with
Cohlmia.
   In October, Braniff hired Merrill Lynch Capital Markets, an
investment banking company, to find sources of financing, including
possible buyers.
   Cohlmia, 54, said he worked for Braniff as a baggage handler in
the 1960s.
   ``I love that airline,'' he said. ``It could be the best _ and
will be _ if we buy it.''
   Describing himself as a ``hustler and an idea man,'' Cohlmia
said he would turn Braniff into a service-oriented airline catering
to business fliers.
   For 20 years, he operated Cohlmia Aviation Inc., which at its
peak used a fleet of more than 60 planes to ferry checks among
banks, he said. It ceased operating in December 1987.
   In 1988, Cohlmia helped found the Great American Smokers Club,
an organization based in Texas that wanted to form an airline for
smokers only. In 1986, he ran the Las Vegas, Nev., air hub for the
U.S. Postal Service, which flew mail to the city from locations in
13 states.
   ``I thought he was a good operator,'' said Joseph A. Ryan, the
Las Vegas postmaster. Cohlmia kept the contract for about 18
months, eventually losing it to a lower bidder, Ryan said.
   Cohlmia said he does not have the money to buy Braniff on his
own but has lined up financing. He and his lawyer will meet with
the airline's creditors Friday, he said, adding that they may not
like his proposal.
   ``The problems we have are with the creditors,'' he said.
``Funny thing, everybody is looking after their own self on this
thing. I'm interested in the airline going back into business. I
think people have to be put back to work.''
   Braniff returned five new jets last week because it could not
make $3 million in lease payments. The company would not comment on
the possibility of a buyout.
</TEXT>

</DOC>