<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0117EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-SECEnforcement Bjt   12-27 0663</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-SEC Enforcement, Bjt,660</SECOND>
<HEAD>SEC Creates New Fraud Unit to Protect Small Investors</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN CRUTSINGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Economics Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Securities and Exchange Commission,
catapulted into the headlines by its pursuit of multimillion-dollar
insider trading scandals, is putting out the word that it intends
to be just as aggressive in protecting small investors.
   SEC Chairman Richard Breeden is creating a new fraud unit at the
SEC designed to police the sale of securities by savings and loan
institutions.
   Investigators have charged that some small investors lost their
life savings when they bought securities sold by S&amp;L branches in
the mistaken belief that their investments were protected by
federal deposit insurance.
   ``We intend to see to it that when people are sold securities,
they are provided all the necessary information,'' Breeden said.
   Breeden also announced Tuesday that he had selected William R.
McLucas, a 12-year SEC veteran, to be the new director of
enforcement at the SEC. He will succeed Gary Lynch, who resigned in
July after supervising such landmark insider trading cases as the
investigation of Ivan Boesky and the Wall Street firm of Drexel
Burnham Lambert Inc.
   Both Breeden and McLucas stressed that insider trading still
would be a top SEC priority, but they also indicated that the SEC,
with a 20 percent increase in its budget, would devote more
resources to more low-profile crooks.
   ``Where there is an abuse of a customer's trust, those are the
kinds of cases where we are going to make sure we have an impact,''
McLucas said at a news conference where his selection was announced.
   Individual investors have been leaving the market in droves in
recent years, scared off in part by extreme trading volatility.
Many officials believe the SEC must return to its primary mission
of bolstering confidence in financial markets through protection of
the small investor.
   Breeden, who was picked for the SEC post by President Bush last
summer, said both the administration and Congress had expressed a
strong desire to crack down on abuses against individual investors.
Breeden noted that Congress approved a 20 percent increase in the
SEC budget this year, enough to allow the agency to hire 100 more
attorneys.
   Part of the increased staffing will be used, Breeden said, to
create a special 25-attorney unit to investigate overly aggressive
sales of securities by savings and loans and other financial
institutions.
   Such sales became a major focus of congressional hearings into
the activities at Lincoln Savings and Loan Association, the Irvine,
Calif.-based S&amp;L whose failure is expected to end up costing
taxpayers a record $2 billion.
   Small investors told congressional investigators they were lured
into purchasing bonds in Lincoln Savings' parent company, American
Continental Corp., in the mistaken belief that their money was
protected by federal deposit insurance.
   When American Continental, which is headed by Arizona
businessman Charles H. Keating Jr., filed for protection under the
bankruptcy law, it left some 22,000 small investors who had
purchased nearly $200 million in corporate bonds in the lurch.
   Breeden said the new SEC unit will try to prevent financially
ailing S&amp;Ls from turning to fraudulent practices in a desperate
effort to raise cash.
   McLucas, 39, joined the SEC in 1977, two years after receiving a
law degree from Temple University.
   Lynch, who resigned to join a New York law firm, served for four
years as SEC enforcement chief, taking over from John Fedders, who
was forced to resign after allegations surfaced that he had beaten
his wife.
   Lynch was credited with restoring morale at the SEC and
directing some of the agency's biggest investigations, beginning
with the exposure of Dennis Levine in May 1986. Levine's
cooperation led to a $100 million settlement with speculator Ivan
Boesky. Boesky in turn implicated Drexel Burnham, which led to a
$650 million settlement with the securities firm, the largest
securities fraud case ever brought by the government.
   Civil and criminal charges are still pending against former
Drexel junk bond pioneer Michael Milken.
</TEXT>

</DOC>