<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0220 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2006EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-Panama-KellyText 5thAdd   12-20 0806</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Panama-Kelly Text, 5th Add,a0844 et. seq.,760</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHN: air-dropped.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Q: Were those flown down yesterday?
   GEN. KELLY: No, they went down sometime earlier. We also had six
Apache helicopters in Panama. That is a modern day-night
all-weather helicopter that represented a real combat multiplier.
We had some gunships, Air Force AC-130 gunships, and other
capabilities down there, all of which stood us in very good stead.
   Q: General, how many casualties from that air drop? Did we take
any?
   GEN. KELLY: I know of no casualties that occurred as a result of
the air drop.
   Q: That's a pretty hairy thing, though, to drop, what, 20
planes' worth of airborne at night?
   GEN. KELLY: Oh, no, there was a whole lot more than 20. We
wouldn't want to give you the exact number. No, 20 aircraft came
out of Fort Bragg. A whole lot more came out of other places to
carry the Rangers. Only the airborne from the 82nd came out of
Bragg.
   Q: Well, how _ well, give us a little better idea of that
landing zone and everything, what happened there. I mean, this was
_ did you light the area with (the strips?)?
   GEN. KELLY: Yeah, they landed right on Tocumen airfield. You
know, that's nice and wide and open and all that.
   Q: General, what kind of problems do the Dignity Battalions pose
for you in Panama City tonight?
   GEN. KELLY: That's hard to say. You're asking me to predict the
future, and that's really an intelligence question, so I'll turn it
over to my colleague. (Laughter.)
   Q: Could we ask you, sir _
   ADM. SHEAFER: We've had _ there is some _ about 18 Dignity
Battalions. They vary in size from as few as a couple of dozen
people up to about 250. Their military training is generally pretty
inadequate.
   Q: Inadequate?
   ADM. SHEAFER: Inadequate. They're great with people who are
unarmed, but when it comes to fighting uniformed soldiers that are
well trained, they're not very good. And they are throughout many
parts of Panama City at this time. We have seen activity
principally between the areas that General Kelly mentioned, Rio
Hato in the west, and Fort Cimarron in the east by about roughly
nine of these 18 battalions. And we have seen nothing out of the
other nine.
   Q: Sir, General Kelly was telling us in the _ when he was
outlining the other units that were outside, and speaking of
Noriega forces, that there was a great deal of fleeing in the face
of the Americans. Does your intelligence suggest that will happen
in Panama City? Or are you expecting to get into a rough
street-to-street _
   ADM. SHEAFER: I'll answer _
   Q: _ (inaudible) _ which could lead to more casualties.
   ADM. SHEAFER: I'll answer the question the same way he did.
You're asking me to predict the future and that's very difficult to
do. We simply don't know.
   Q: _ like the rebellion for urban fighting when you said
   _ (inaudible).
   ADM. SHEAFER: I mean, you have to plan for the worst, and hope
for the best.
   Q: Are these guys armed? Aren't these more unarmed rebels? What
kind of weapons?
   ADM. SHEAFER: They have _ in this case we have reports that some
of the Dignity Batallions have been armed _
   Q: What kind of weapons?
   ADM. SHEAFER: With RPGs and AK-47s.
   Q: Can you give us an assessment of the difficulty it presents
to you that Noriega is still at large? The difficulty in terms of
stimulating the remaining pro-Noriega _
   ADM. SHEAFER: I don't think that's the right question. The right
question is the difficulty he has staying at large.
   Q: But you don't feel that having him at large presents you with
a different magnitude of problem because of what he represents? I
mean, as you yourself have said, he's a slippery fellow and _
   GEN. KELLY: He is, and right now Mr. Noriega commands nothing.
He has no payroll. He has no cronies except for possibly a small
group of people who are loyal to him personally because he pays
them. He does not present us with a military problem. His soldiers
did not fight any more bravely over the past day because he was
there or he wasn't there. I think now that the structure of the PDF
combat units has been reduced he is in deeper trouble. I don't
think he's deeply loved by the Panamanian people. I don't think _ I
do think that if they _ they get an inkling of where he is they're
going to _ they're going to let us know where he is or let the
authorities in Panama know where he is, because recall, that
they're the ones that did all the suffering while he was the
dictator.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>