<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0192 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1220EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-Florida-Citrus 1stLd-Writethru f0054 12-26 0553</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Florida-Citrus, 1st Ld-Writethru, f0054,0571</SECOND>
<HEAD>Weekend Freeze Leaves Florida Crop Damaged</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf pvs, `This freeze ..., with one graf to show Collier
County has more winter vegetables than citrus. Picks up 3rd graf pvs, In
Texas ...</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAT LEISNER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The frigid weather that swept through much of the
South over the holiday weekend has caused substantial damage to
Florida's $3.5 billion citrus crop and hurt other important winter
crops, agriculture officials say.
   ``This freeze has just devastated us,'' said Anne Goodnight,
commissioner in Collier County, which has many winter vegetable
crops and some citrus. She said she planned to ask Gov. Bob
Martinez for disaster aid this week.
   In Texas, state officials estimate 70 percent of the citrus crop
and 80 percent of the winter vegetable crop were destroyed when
temperatures plunged into the low 20s and upper teens.
   Losses there were estimated at $200 million. But some Texas
officials and growers predicted they would be higher because
warming temperatures ruined any hopes of salvaging the frozen fruit
for juice.
   Although Florida officials haven't released actual production
losses, the freeze damage is likely to be substantial since much of
the state's crop was still on the trees when temperatures dipped
blow freezing starting on Saturday.
   The plunging temperatures taxed the state's utilities over the
weekend and again today. The power companies tried to divide the
misery by cutting electricity to different areas for short periods
of time, but the moves wreaked havoc on citrus groves.
   Most growers abandoned traditional methods of protecting their
crops, such as using smudge pots or wind machines, and instead used
networks of microjets, which spray water on the trees to protect
them from freezing.
   When the power went off, the protective irrigation systems
failed.
   ``There was nothing I could do about it,'' said John Heist, a
Lake County citrus grower. ``They turned off the electricity at
about 9 a.m. (Sunday). But it was too cold and the system froze in
parts.''
   ``We would have been better off not to turn on the system at
all.''
   Immokalee, a winter vegetable production center, was hit hard by
the chill.
   Farmers said the area lost more than 90 percent of its tomatoes,
peppers and other vegetables, which are worth more than $200
million yearly.
   Among the few happy farmers were strawberry growers who came
through the hard freeze better than others.
   ``No wind, no problem,'' said Roy Parke of Parkesdale Farms, a
berry farmer in Plant City.
   A lack of wind allows irrigation systems to build an even layer
of ice on fragile plants to protect the bloom. Wind scatters the
water from sprinklers, allowing colder temperatures to get to the
plants and damage or kill them.
   Parke estimated that the $162 million berry industry likely
would suffer only half the loss expected.
   Growers were not the only agricultural workers suffering from
the freeze. Migrant workers found their livelihood endangered.
   ``If there aren't any other crops to pick, these people don't
have any other place to work,'' said Charles Esposito, program
manager for the Beth-El Mission in Plant City.
   More than 10,000 migrant workers living in Immokalee for the
picking season, which runs from November through May, may be
unemployed. Before the freeze, they earned $40 to $125 a day.
</TEXT>

</DOC>