<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0131 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1422EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Panama-Wounded 3rdLd-Writethru a0634 12-22 0868</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Wounded, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0634,0887</SECOND>
<HEAD>More than 200 Wounded Brought To San Antonio, Biggest Influx Since
Vietnam</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to UPDATE with general's visit; picking up
4th graf pvs, `On Wednesday...'. DELETES 8th graf pvs, `Army Gen...', now
outdated.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-US-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto Upcoming</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SCOTT ROTHSCHILD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN ANTONIO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Army Chief of Staff today handed out
Purple Hearts and other medals to soldiers wounded in Panama,
telling them he and the president are proud of their ``selfless
commitment to the service of this nation.''
   Gen. Carl Vuono arrived at Wilford Hall Medical Center, one of
two large military hospitals here that since Wednesday have
received more than 200 men injured in the Panama invasion, the
largest influx of casualties since the Vietnam War. Twenty soldiers
died in the assault.
   Officials said 112 men remained hospitalized at Wilford and an
additional 89 remained at nearby Brooke Army Medical Center, which
Vuono planned to visit later in the day.
   ``Right before I got on the helicopter down here I got a phone
call from the president of the United States, the
commander-in-chief,'' Vuono told the first soldiers he visited.
``He wanted me to tell you and every other troop down here how
proud he is of each and every one of you for your sacrifice.''
   Vuono first handed out Purple Hearts to Pvt. Christian Robinson,
no hometown available; Pfc. Bobby Miller of Franklin, Pa.; and
Spec. 4 Albert Harris, of Jackson, Miss. All three suffered gunshot
or shrapnel wounds. Reporters were not allowed to accompany Vuono
on the rest of his visit.
   Of the at least 210 servicemen brought here, two were recovered
enough to be released to their units this morning, while an
additional 53 would probably be released later today or Saturday, a
spokesman said. But 18 were described as ``seriously ill.''
   When American servicemen are wounded or burned overseas, they
usually are brought to San Antonio, home to four Air Force bases
and an Army post. Wilford Hall is one of the nation's main military
hospitals, and Brooke is a leading burn unit.
   On Wednesday and Thursday, military authorities said four
transport planes from Panama landed at Kelly Air Force Base
carrying 191 soldiers, along with four men who died en route or
shortly after arrival. A fifth plane, carrying 21 wounded soldiers,
arrived early this morning, bringing the reported total of wounded
brought here to 212.
   This morning, Wilford Hall and Brooke hospitals reported they
had 201 patients, and seven other wounded men had been transferred
to hospitals near their respective bases. Counting the two men
already released, that would bring the total brought here to 210.
There was no immediate explanation of the discrepancy.
   The hospitalized soldiers were in good spirits, doctors said.
   ``It is amazing what they have tolerated and they're doing it
without whimpering,'' said Lt. Col. Robert Solenberger, Brooke's
chief of surgery.
   Solenberger and his counterpart at Wilford Hall said 18 patients
could be considered ``seriously ill.'' But hospital officials had
no exact count this morning on how many were listed in critical or
serious condition.
   Injuries ranged from broken bones to gunshot and shrapnel
wounds, said Lt. Col. Johnny Whitaker, spokesman for Lackland Air
Force Base. The names of the injured, most of them Army personnel,
were not released.
   A reception center for relatives of the wounded was set up at
Fort Sam Houston. Housing was arranged for the families, and
several San Antonio hotels offered free or reduced-price rooms.
   ``This is kind of a way of life for us,'' said Caryl Hill,
executive director of the local United Service Organizations.
   ``The people of San Antonio are a little bit more aware of
military life,'' Ms. Hill said. ``When there's a war, it's not
unusual that we're going to be receiving the wounded.''
   Doctors and nurses worked extra shifts and postponed vacations
to handle the largest influx of casualties they've had since the
Vietnam War, Whitaker said.
   ``There's a lot of tired people. These have been long days.
People seem to be fairly upbeat, holding their own,'' he said.
   Richard and Linda Turner of DeSoto, Texas, were some of the
first parents to arrive. They visited their son, Pvt. Richard
Turner Jr., who suffered a concussion when a bullet grazed his
helmet.
   ``He saw one of his friends killed,'' Mrs. Turner said. ``He
cried quite a bit.''
   Her son's injury failed to shake Mrs. Turner's support for the
invasion, though.
   ``I definitely think that (Noriega) is one of the main runners
of drugs,'' the mother said. ``Because of this awful man, the drugs
are so heavy in our country.''
   Military officials said medical procedures were running
smoothly, the soldiers were in good spirits and many of them may be
cleared to return to their units today.
   ``They're taking it very well. If there's a predominant feeling
that these men have, it's that they wish that they were back there
fighting,'' said Air Force Col. William Burner III, chief of
surgery at Wilford Hall.
   Two soldiers, he said, refused to sit while they were initially
examined for leg and arm injuries. ``They basically stood at
attention while I examined them.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>