<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0119 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1846EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CommuterPlaneCrash     12-27 0436</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Commuter Plane Crash,0452</SECOND>
<HEAD>Federal Agencies Probe Air Crash That Claimed 6 Lives</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES L. ENG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASCO, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Federal investigators Wednesday began
examining the wreckage of a commuter plane for the cause of a crash
that killed all six people aboard.
   The twin-engine United Express turboprop went down in a field
and burst into flames just short of the runway late Tuesday while
en route from Seattle to Pasco via Yakima.
   At a news conference, United Express president Craig Belmondo
raised the possibility that wing icing contributed to the crash but
said it was ``much too early to speculate'' on the cause.
   Fire officials found ice at the crash scene but Belmondo said it
had not been determined whether the ice came from the British
Aerospace Jetstream 31, a 19-passenger plane.
   The crew contacted the airline's dispatch center at the Tri City
Airport here within three to five miles of landing, as is routine,
and gave no indication of a problem, Belmondo said. He did not know
if there was any communication between the plane and the airport
tower after that.
   Federal Aviation Administration spokesman Dave Duff said the
plane hit 100 feet short of the runway; Belmondo said it went in
500 to 700 feet short.
   Investigators from the National Transportation safety Board and
the FAA arrived Wednesday.
   United Express has deicing equipment at Yakima but it was not
immediately known if it was used on the plane before its departure
for Pasco, a flight of about 80 miles which usually takes about 30
minutes.
   Visibility at the time of the crash was seven miles and wind was
calm, Duff said. The plane was not equipped with voice and flight
data recorders that larger commercial airlines are required to
carry.
   The plane was built in Scotland in 1987 and delivered to United
Express in December of that year, Belmondo said. It had 5,000 hours
of flight time and had its last maintenance inspection on Dec. 20,
he said.
   The aircraft had no record of any major mechanical problems, he
said.
   The pilot, Capt. Barry Roberts, 38, had more than 11 years of
regional flying experience with more than 6,600 hours of total
flying time, including more than 660 hours in British Aerospace
Jetstream aircraft, Belmondo said.
   Co-pilot Doug McInroe, 25, joined United Express in August with
more than two years flying experience, Belmondo said.
   He said he did not know who was piloting the plane when it
crashed.
   United Express, based at Pasco, serves 15 cities in Washington,
Oregon, Idaho and Montana. It began commercial service in 1987.
</TEXT>

</DOC>