<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0330EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Poindexter     12-22 0609</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Poindexter,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Reagan and Judge in Poindexter Case at Odds</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETE YOST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former President Reagan and the judge in John
Poindexter's Iran-Contra case appear to be on a collision course
over the use of the ex-president's notes and diaries in court.
   U.S. District Judge Harold Greene on Thursday gave Reagan until
Jan. 7 to turn over to the court excerpts from those documents for
possible use at Poindexter's trial.
   Greene said he wants to review material from the ex-president
before deciding whether it should be supplied to Poindexter, who
subpoenaed documents Reagan may have relating to 67 meetings and
events. Fifty of them concern assistance to the Contras and 17
relate to the administration's secret arms sales to Iran.
   Greene said he is moving the start of the trial back a month to
Feb. 20 to deal with the subpoena and other issues.
   The former national security adviser says Reagan's documents
will bear out that the former president authorized activities for
which Poindexter now is charged with crimes.
   ``The Court will ... promptly conduct its ... review of the
Reagan documents ... and it will render a decision on the segments
of the subpoena that will be quashed and the parts of the Reagan
diary, notes and notebooks that must be made available'' for
Poindexter's defense, said the judge.
   Lawyers for Reagan and the Justice Department had offered to let
Greene see excerpts from the diary, but only if the former
president and the Bush administration were permitted to see a
proffer Poindexter filed spelling out why he believes he needs the
Reagan material.
   The judge flatly refused to let them see the proffer now.
   ``It would be going too far to accord to the attorneys for
President Reagan and for the incumbent president ... a special role
in the determination whether particular documents'' must be turned
over, said Greene. The judge noted their ``direct interest in the
outcome'' of the subpoena dispute and said transferring the court's
responsibilities to them would be ``unprecedented.''
   Greene said the Justice Department and Reagan will be permitted
to see the proffer next month, if the judge decides to turn the
material over to Poindexter and Reagan invokes executive privilege.
   Using executive privilege, presidents can shield from public
disclosure documents used in carrying out their constitutional
duties.
   Poindexter is accused of conspiracy, two counts of obstructing
Congress and two counts of making false statements. The charges
focus on his alleged lies about a November 1985 CIA-assisted
shipment of Hawk missiles to Iran and denials that North was
raising money and providing military advice to the Contras.
   Meanwhile, Iran-Contra prosecutors say Greene's restrictions on
Oliver L. North's testimony may make it impossible to use the
former White House aide as a witness against Poindexter.
   Greene said he would limit North's testimony because it might
have been tainted by Poindexter's immunized testimony on Capitol
Hill in 1987.
   The judge's decision rules out use of most of North's testimony
from his trial in April, in which North frequently mentioned his
former boss.
   But the office of the independent counsel Lawrence Walsh urged
Greene to ``permit North to testify to all events he currently
recalls ... even if his current recollection has been refreshed by
Poindexter's immunized testimony.''
   Refreshing his recollection from Poindexter's congressional
appearance ``does not constitute an impermissible use of that
immunized testimony,'' said prosecutors.
   North said last week he doesn't want to testify against
Poindexter.
   North's ``demonstrated unwillingness to answer substantively any
question posed to him by the government ... may well preclude ...
from calling this witness at all,'' Walsh's office said in court
papers.
</TEXT>

</DOC>