<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0543EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Panama-USTroops     12-20 0401</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-US Troops,0414</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soldiers Dispatched to Panama From N.C., California</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FORT ORD, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soldiers from the Rapid Deployment Force
at Fort Ord and from Fort Bragg, N.C., have been dispatched to
Panama to help apprehend Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega, Sen. Pete
Wilson said today.
   ``Elements of the 7th Light Infantry Division ... have
supplemented the 12,000 troops already in Panama,'' the California
Republican said in a telephone interview with Los Angeles radio
station KNX.
   Troops from Fort Bragg were airlifted to Panama, said Wilson,
who praised President George Bush for the decision to send to the
Central American country.
   Noriega is ``up to his eyeballs in the drug traffic,'' Wilson
said.
   Noriega, who nullified his country's May elections, was indicted
on U.S. drug trafficking charges in February 1988.
   The senator's comments followed the mobilization Tuesday night
of an undetermined number of soliders from Fort Ord, about 80 miles
south of San Francisco, and their transfer, apparently to Travis
Air Force Base in Fairfield.
   Soldiers of the 7th Infantry Division (Light), which in some
deployments includes artillery and aviation units, were ordered to
report to Fort Ord for an ``emergency deployment readiness training
exercise,'' some time Monday, said Jim Davis, public affairs
officers for the Army.
   Davis, however, said that as a matter of policy, he could not
comment on the number mobilized, their destination or their time of
departure.
   By early today, military convoys were seen heading north on
Interstate 680 toward Fairfield, according to the California
Highway Patrol.
   Nineteen buses and a truck loaded with soldiers arrived at
Travis late Tuesday, according KCRA-TV in Sacramento. More buses
and trucks were reported going into the base about 40 miles
northeast of San Francisco. But a base spokesman said he could not
say where the soliders came from or where they were going.
   ``We cannot comment on any military operations at this time,''
said Sgt. Jerry Taranto. ``We can't comment on anything on the
operation.''
   Travis was enveloped in heavy fog, making flights difficult.
   Earlier Tuesday, C-141 planes were seen in the air around Fort
Bragg, home of the Army's 82nd Airborne division.
   Fort Bragg spokesmen would say only that Army units there were
participating in a routine ``emergency deployment readiness
exercise.'' Sgt. Bobby Feibel, a spokesman for the division, said
he had no information on reports that some of the division had left
Fort Bragg.
</TEXT>

</DOC>