<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0154 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 2007EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Czechoslovakia-Reax     12-29 0507</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Czechoslovakia-Reax,0530</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nations Praise Havel's Election</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JEFF DONN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Both Communist and non-Communist leaders of Poland, the country
at the vanguard of the East bloc's democratic revolution, joined in
cheering Vaclav Havel's election as president of Czechoslovakia on
Friday.
   Western European leaders hailed the move as another step in
Czechoslovakia's march toward democracy.
   The Bush administration said the election of the playwright,
once a jailed dissident, ``marks a fitting end to a year of
astonishing change in Eastern Europe.''
   Havel, an internationally acclaimed playwright and opposition
leader, was elected in a unanimous vote of his nation's Parliament
as the first non-Communist president of Czechoslovakia in 41 years.
   Solidarity leader Lech Walesa in Poland welcomed the choice of
Havel ``with great joy'' and wished him strength in carrying out
his new responsibilities, according to the official Polish PAP news
agency.
   In his telegram, Walesa said: ``Czechoslovakia needs people like
you. The duty of a continuation of the chosen path of new reforms
will rest with them.''
   Communist President Wojciech Jaruzelski and Prime Minister
Tadeusz Mazowiecki, a former activist in the Solidarity labor
union, also sent cables of congratulations to Havel, PAP reported.
   Mazowiecki was elected as the East Bloc's first non-Cmmunist
head of government on Aug. 24, paving the way for a wave of reform
elsewhere in Eastern Europe.
   Chancellor Helmut Kohl of West Germany sent a telegram to Havel
promising that West Germany is ready to support Czechoslovakia in
its pursuit of reforms.
   ``The new Europe of freedom needs a democratic and dynamic
Czechoslovakia,'' Kohl said.
   West German President Richard von Weizsaecker said in a message:
``Dialogue and cooperation should accompany us in the future
emergence of a united Europe.''
   Havel's first foreign visit, announced Friday, will be to East
Germany and West Germany on Jan. 2.
   In London, a Foreign Office spokesman said of Havel's election:
``We greatly welcome it. His commitment to the ideals of democracy
has been repeatedly and courageously demonstrated.''
   ``We are confident that he will promote Czechoslovakia's
peaceful transition towards a truly democratic society, a process
in which Mr. Havel has already played a crucial part,'' the
spokesman said on condition of anonymity.
   He described Havel's assumption of power as ``a momentous step
in the postwar history of our continent.''
   In Paris, President Francois Mitterrand also offered
congratulations.
   ``Knowing the eminent role you have played in the struggle for
reestablishment of democratic institutions in Czechoslovakia, I am
convinced you will be able to carry out successfully the heavy
responsibility confided in you,'' Mitterrand's telegram said.
   President Francesco Cossiga of Italy said: ``The Parliament's
choice ... represents a symbolic stage in the glorious march that
the peoples of the Czechoslovak republic have embarked on toward
ever higher goals of freedom, democracy and political pluralism.''
   In Texas on holiday, President Bush pledged U.S. support for the
changes in Czechoslovakia.
   Bush said Havel's election ``is living proof of what Mr. Havel
has called the `power of the powerless' to bring about peaceful
democratic change,'' according to White House spokesman Marlin
Fitzwater.

</TEXT>

</DOC>