<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2343EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Panama-Resistance     12-20 0723</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Panama-Resistance,0746</SECOND>
<HEAD>Defense Forces, Noriega Resist; Loyalty Remains Strong Enough</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Instead of collapsing when the United
States threw its military might against Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noriega, his Defense Forces stubbornly resisted.
   The elusive general the Bush administration had hoped to put
before a federal judge in Florida on drug charges remains at large
and in hiding despite an attack Wednesday by thousands of American
troops.
   Many in Panama had thought the Defense Forces would simply
``throw down their guns as soon as an American helicopter appeared
over the barracks,'' as a Noriega opponent once put it.
   In interviews prior to the attack, U.S. military leaders had
claimed Defense Forces troops would refuse to shed their blood for
Noriega. Part of their evidence stemmed from the fact that disloyal
officers mounted two coups against him.
   But the general, who sometimes seemed to escape by magic,
apparently retained enough loyalty for his men to put up a fight
when the U.S. stroke came. From Defense Forces posts all over
Panama came reports of stubborn fighting that lasted for hours.
   With their garrisons destroyed or under siege, many Panamanian
officers left and joined small paramilitary groups in urban
guerrilla warfare.
   While U.S. forces had heavy artillery and air power to use
against installations and sent their armored personnel carriers
rolling over fences and cars, Panamanian armed groups fought a
delaying action.
   ``We are acting as urban guerrillas, although we have lost some
positions, some garrisons,'' said Enrique Thompson, the second in
command in the paramilitary groups, known as Dignity Battalions.
   Thompson spoke with an Associated Press reporter as the five men
with him took up positions in the bushes with Soviet-made AK-47
rifles near the Tinajitas garrison, taken over Wednesday morning by
the Americans.
   ``The people are joining the struggle for national
sovereignty,'' he said.
   The Noriega forces marshalled resistance with appeals over the
National Radio, broadcasting in a national network.
   Announcers called on Panamanians to organize neighborhood armed
resistance and guerrilla war. The station played Panamanian
patriotic songs that taunt Americans. Officers even used it to
broadcast instructions to troops and messages to each other, often
in code.
   U.S. forces finally did slowly close down the radio stations
that made up the chain, but it was a slow process.
   ``Incredible,'' said a sweaty U.S. Army sergeant as he listened
to the exhortations. ``That was the first thing we should have
silenced.''
   Unlike the armed forces in other parts of Latin America, the
Defense Forces officer corps is made up largely of men from poor
backgrounds and became the vehicle dictator Omar Torrijos used in
the late 1960s to topple the ruling oligarchy.
   Noriega, a Torrijos disciple, once observed that the upper-class
had only itself to blame when they complained about the Defense
Forces' dominance, because they preferred to make money.
   He openly mocked the upper-class and his supporters frequently
refer to the opposition election victory on May 7 as an effort by
the oligarchy to return to power.
   Noriega promoted officers with poor backgrounds, often from
discriminated-against black and Chinese minorities, and worked hard
to retain their loyalty with lucrative slices of the corruption pie
in Panama.
   But when that loyalty slipped, it did in coup attempts in 1988
and 1989, he reacted brutally, and reports that he personally beat
or shot coup instigators circulated.
   Accused of domestic repression by the U.S. government, he
whipped up nationalistic feelings showing himself as a Panamanian
wrongly accused by the large country that wanted to renege on the
the Panama Canal treaties.
   The invasion was a slap in the face to Panamanians who have
considered themselves friends and allies of the Americans since the
two countries joined hands in the construction of the Panama Canal
at the beginning of the century.
   As the armored personnel carriers rolled out of Fort Clayton
after midnight Wednesday past the Panamanian town of Diablo
Heights, some men and women watching them cursed them or cried.
   ``Whey are they doing this?'' a housewife asked a reporter.
``Are they going to kill our people just for one man?''
   ``The Americans have no control of the situation,'' said Dr.
Leonardo Diaz of the Santo Tomas hospital. ``Their strength is in
their personnel carriers and their Cobras (helicopters), but the
people are angry.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>