<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0745EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Israel-Journalists     12-18 0379</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Israel-Journalists,0389</SECOND>
<HEAD>Journalists Charged for Entering Closed Military Zone</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARIEH O'SULLIVAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For the first time in the 2-year-old
Palestinian uprising, police have charged journalists with entering
an area declared closed by the military, police said today.
   The charges were brought against three Israeli reporters, Joel
Greenberg of the English-language Jerusalem Post, Ori Nir of
Haaretz and Oren Cohen of Hadashot.
   Shaul Naim, police prosecutor, said the three would not be
jailed during legal proceedings but could be sentenced to up to two
years in prison if convicted of the charges. He said he was
uncertain when the trial would be held.
   The charges were presented Sunday before the Jerusalem
Magistrate's court, Naim said.
   During the uprising, soldiers have regularly blocked reporters
from entering troubled towns or villages by declaring them closed
military areas. While reporters have been detained several times
for entering such areas, no charges had been brought.
   Greenberg, Nir and Cohen were found by army troops in the West
Bank city of Nablus on Nov. 15, 1988, after the city of 120,000 had
been closed by the army.
   The incident occurred on the day that the PLO declared an
independent Palestinian state. To prevent trouble, the army put the
entire Gaza Strip under curfew and declared Nablus and several
other West Bank towns and villages closed areas.
   The Jerusalem Post quoted the charge sheet as saying the
journalists ``stayed for a long time inside Nablus after it was
declared a closed area ... although they heard at 7 a.m. on the
radio that the area was declared closed.''
   Greenberg claimed at the time that the three were unaware Nablus
had been closed when they entered the city.
   ``We didn't know it was a closed military area because we left
early in the morning and they didn't say anything about closure the
day before,'' he said.
   The three were detained by soldiers in Al-Ittihad Hospital, and
said they had remained there for fear of endangering themselves
after the closure order was announced.
   The Hebrew daily Hadashot, whose reporter Cohen was among those
accused, said in an editorial that the police charge ``is just
another, and exceptionally bitter, expression of the decline of our
democracy due to pressure from the uprising.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>