<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1145EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-EastGermany 5thLd-Writethru a0530 12-19 0898</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-East Germany, 5th Ld - Writethru, a0530,0922</SECOND>
<HEAD>Wall To Be Opened At Brandenburg Gate; Summit Puts Focus On Reunification</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: CORRECTS dateline to East Germany, sted West; SUBS grafs 9-30,
`Kohl was...financial ties' with 17 to add comments from Kohl and Modrow,
color from scene. Trims and deletes outdated material. Pickup 31st graf,
`Kohl has...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NESHA STARCEVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DRESDEN, East Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Berlin Wall will be opened
before Christmas at the Brandenburg Gate, the towering monument
viewed by many as a symbol of German unity, East German Premier
Hans Modrow said today.
   The announcement followed a meeting between Modrow and West
German Chancellor Helmut Kohl, during which the two leaders
discussed the thorny issue of how to bring the long-divided nations
closer together.
   Since the Berlin Wall started crumbling early last month,
Germans in both East and West have demanded an opening at the gate
to demonstrate the new era of improved relations between the
countries.
   Modrow told reporters the new opening for pedestrians will be
created before Monday. And the date for visa-free travel by West
Germans and West Berliners to East Germany will be moved up from
Jan. 1 to Dec. 24, in time for Christmas and New Year.
   Elsewhere in Eastern Europe today:
   _Former Czechoslovak dissident Vaclav Havel received an
endorsement for president from the Communist premier, Marian Calfa.
   _Hungarian radio reported that gunfire rang out early today in
the streets of the Romanian city of Timisoara, where bloody clashes
between security forces and anti-government protesters reportedly
left dozens dead last weekend.
   _Yugoslavia's premier suffered a blow after the nation's largest
republic, Serbia, flatly rejected his key reform program that would
introduce market mechanisms into the ailing economy.
   The summit highlighted the debate raging over German
reunification, which Kohl supports and Modrow opposes.
   Chants of ``Helmut! Helmut!'' and ``Germany, united
fatherland!'' rose from the crowd of at least 5,000 that lined the
streets as Kohl's motorcade of black Mercedes limousines carried
him to the meeting at the Hotel Bellevue.
   Workers in hard hats left work to catch a glimpse of the
chancellor, and West German flags and banners calling for German
unity formed a sea of red, black and gold.
   But there were signs of opposition to Kohl's pro-reunification
stance.
   ``A Fourth Reich _ Is that why you stayed behind?'' said one
poster on a fence in the city center. It referred to those East
Germans who have declined to emigrate to wealthy West Germany,
choosing instead to stay behind and help rebuild their troubled
socialist state.
   With the ruins of war-ravaged buildings visible in the distance,
Modrow told reporters his first talks with Kohl marked a ``new
beginning'' in relations between the countries. Kohl accepted an
offer to start negotiations on a treaty to improve relations, and
negotiations will start ``immediately,'' Modrow said.
   Kohl told reporters he hopes such a treaty can be signed by late
spring.
   He later walked through a crowd of several thousand people.
Several signs called for German reunification, with one saying
``Helmut and Hans, make us into one Germany.''
   At an outdoor rally, Kohl drew wild cheers when he referred to
the crowd as ``compatriots'' and said, ``We will not abandon you.''
   ``The emotions are nice, but we have to see what the reality
is,'' he said on West Germany's ZDF television.
   Kohl said he and Modrow would meet again at the end of January
or the beginning of February.
   He said the two sides ``got closer on some issues,'' citing the
East German push for a more formal relationship between the two
states.
   The summit was held in Dresden because West Germany refuses to
acknowledge East Berlin as the capital of a separate and sovereign
East German state.
   East Germany has been seeking a ``Treaty Community,''
establishing fuller ties between East and West Germany, rather than
working to join them.
   Kohl has proposed a 10-point plan aimed at eventual German
reunification.
   Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard A. Shevardnadze today reiterated
Soviet concerns about reunification during a speech to members of
the European Parliament in Belgium, saying there are two good
reasons to oppose it:
   ``We (the Soviet Union) paid the price of 20 million lives for
the existing European stability,'' he said of World War II.
``Furthermore, can the German people themselves forget the national
tragedy brought onto them by Hitlerism?''
   Kohl has made clear that his conservative-led government seeks
eventual reunification of the two German states that have been
divided since 1945.
   But Modrow and many other East Germans active in the
increasingly fragmented political arena have said joining the two
states would be destabilizing for Europe and would result in a
``sellout'' of East German land and industry.
   Reunification has become a major topic of public debate and a
political football in both Germanies ever since a massive popular
uprising forced East Germany to open its borders Nov. 9 and led to
a crumbling of Communist control.
   East Germany's first free elections are now set for May 6.
   Chants of ``Germany, united fatherland'' occasionally disrupted
a candlelight vigil in Leipzig on Monday night. The silent march
was called by church and reform leaders in memory of the victims of
Stalinism.
   The words ``Germany, united fatherland'' were originally part of
the East German national anthem but have been excised since the
early 1970s when Communist officials dropped reunification as a
goal.
</TEXT>

</DOC>