<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0123 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1657EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Flight103 1stLd-Writethru a0677 12-21 0795</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Flight 103, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0677,0813</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tiny Flare-Path Lights Up Memorial As Lockerbie Remembers</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs with later service, picks up 7th graf pvs,
``While this ...''; SUBS 17th graf pvs, ``Wreaths heaped ...'' with 1 graf
to CORRECT number of dead Syracuse students to 35, sted 25.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LON4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LESLIE SHEPHERD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOCKERBIE, Scotland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A path of lanterns flickered against
a granite memorial Thursday as grieving relatives and local
residents marked the first anniversary of the Pan Am Flight 103
bombing over this Scottish town.
   The 270 lights _ one for each victim killed _ shone in the night
after local clergymen dedicated the memorial in a 19th century
graveyard during a day of somber and poignant commemoration.
   At least 20 American relatives joined in the services,
culminating in an open-air ecumenical gathering at night outside
the town hall that on Dec. 21, 1988, became a makeshift morgue.
   More than one-third of Lockerbie 3,500 people turned out in
freezing temperatures to hear the local Roman Catholic priest
declare, ``from this disaster there is no complete recovery.''
   ``The honest answer is that ... quite simply, life cannot be the
same again,'' said the Rev. Patrick Keegan. ``It has changed, we
have changed.''
   In the early evening, relatives _ some sobbing _ packed an
isolated stone church, Tundergarth, overlooking the field where the
cockpit fell from the jumbo jet. It was blown apart by terrorist
bomb in a radio cassette player.
   Earlier, about 500 people gathered in biting cold at a simple
dedication of the memorial in the Dryfesdale Cemetery, one mile
outside Lockerbie.
   ``While this might be a traumatic experience for us, the worst
has already happened,'' said George Williams of Joppa, Md. His only
child, a 24-year-old U.S. Army lieutenant, was on the flight.
   ``When we go home we'll feel a whole lot better,'' added
Williams, 58, who came with his wife, Judy.
   Vapor trailing from two aircraft overhead formed a cross in what
appeared to be a coincidental tribute.
   All 259 people aboard the New York-bound Pan Am jet died and 11
others died on the ground as the jet exploded over this small town
in southern Scotland.
   After a year of painstaking investigation, the bomber has not
been identified. But suspicion points to an extremist Middle East
terrorist group, the Popular Front for the Liberation of
Palestine-General Command.
   As darkness fell, an American couple, Paul and Eleanor Hudson,
lighted 270 lanterns along a path leading to the memorial and in a
circle before it. Their 16-year-old daughter, Melina, was aboard
the flight.
   Classmates at Melina's school, the Albany Academy for Girls, in
Albany, N.Y., made the lanterns, which were sand-filled bags with
candles inside. Each was inscribed with a dove and the name of a
victim.
   ``It's the greatest honor I can think of,'' said Mrs. Hudson,
from Albany.
   On the light polished granite of the 6-foot memorial, names of
the victims are carved in roughly alphabetical order, with families
grouped together, in three panels.
   ``When you actually see the names, that's when it really hits
you _ 270 is just a number,'' said Briton Barry Flick, whose
brother, Clayton, boarded Flight 103. Clayton Flick and his fiancee
had been going on a three-day sightseeing trip.
   Wreaths heaped at the foot of the memorial included one from
Syracuse University, to its 35 students who perished on Flight 103
as they flew home for Christmas from an exchange program.
   ``I thought it was very appropriate and very respectful ... an
extension of the people of Lockerbie. They've given us faith and
hope throughout the year,'' said Joe Horgan, of Philadelphia, a
member of the board of Victims of Pan Am Flight 103. It represents
American victims.
   British families of victims sent a 3-foot wreath of evergreen
sprigs and carnations carrying the inscription, ``Their spirit
lives on.''
   The Stars and Stripes, sodden from rain that stopped only as the
service in the cemetery began, drooped in front of the granite
memorial.
   No formal invitations were issued to what the local member of
Parliament, Sir Hector Monro, called ``a family affair.'' But the
U.S. ambassador, Henry Catto, attended and Queen Elizabeth II sent
a representative.
   In the heart of the garden is a grave containing a single casket
symbolizing the 17 victims whose bodies were never found, 10 from
the aircraft and seven from Lockerbie.
   At the back of the cemetery, a memorial plaque presented
Wednesday night by American relatives was attached to a rock wall
where other relatives can affix individual plaques.
   Earlier, Britain announced that following recommendations of a
security study, inspectors with inert explosives will begin posing
as terrorists to test airport security, following the practice of
Israel's El Al airline.
</TEXT>

</DOC>