<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0108 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1944EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Grain-Soviets     12-19 0303</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Grain-Soviets,300</SECOND>
<HEAD>More U.S. Wheat for Soviets</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Soviet Union will be able to buy an
additional 2 million metric tons of U.S. wheat at subsidized
prices, the Agriculture Department said Tuesday.
   Undersecretary Richard T. Crowder said the wheat will be made
available under the department's Export Enhancement Program, or
EEP. The new amount is in addition to 14,200 tons Moscow had
remaining under a previous allocation announced last May 2.
   The Soviet Union is committed to buy minimum quantities of wheat
and corn under a long-term grain agreement, which began its seventh
year on Oct. 1 and will expire Dec. 31, 1990. Moscow has bought
about 800,000 tons of wheat for delivery in 1989-90, according to
USDA records.
   Nearly 11 million tons of corn have been sold for 1989-90
delivery, along with soybeans and soybean meal.
   In 1988-89, the sixth period under the agreement, the Soviet
Union bought about 5.4 million tons of wheat and more than 16.3
million tons of corn, plus soybeans, soybean meal and grain
sorghums.
   A metric ton is about 2,205 pounds and is equal to 36.7 bushels
of wheat.
   The EEP arrangement allows private exporters to sell wheat and
other designated commodities to specified countries at reduced
prices in order to meet foreign competition. The exporters then
collect free government surpluses of grain or other products as
bonuses, or subsidies.
   Since EEP began in 1985, more than $2.6 billion in subsidies has
been paid to exporters to ship a variety of commodities to overseas
customers. As of Nov. 30, sales totaled 87.2 million tons of grain,
including 64.4 million tons of wheat.
   The Soviet Union, as the largest EEP beneficiary, has bought
more than 17.5 million tons of wheat. China is second at 13.2
million tons of wheat, plus 185 head of cattle.
</TEXT>

</DOC>