<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1614EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Violent 1stLd-Writethru a0569 12-25 1092</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Violent, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0569,1118</SECOND>
<HEAD>Repressed Hatred Explodes in Violence In Romania</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 21st graf, ``Knowing of ...'' to change wording to Warsaw
Pact, sted Eastern Europe.</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALISON SMALE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Romania's revolution against Communism,
unlike others in Eastern Europe, has exploded in volatile emotions
and violence against the repression enforced by the 24-year
dictatorship of Nicolae Ceausescu.
   Ceausescu and his wife, Elena, were reported to be executed on
Monday after a secret trial on charges of particularly grave crimes
against the people.
   No other East European country revolting in the name of
democracy has reacted in this way. But no other East European
country had a Ceausescu, whose unparalleled personality cult
trumpeted his ``golden era'' while imposing more and more hardship.
   As mandated debt repayment and industrialization programs
brought hardship to every Romanian, dissent was largely repressed
by his dreaded Securitate, a massive network of at least 700,000
people.
   Workers who dared to protest disappeared mysteriously.
Intellectuals, with a higher profile in society, faced prison,
mental hospital, internal exile or house arrest.
   Laws mandated the reporting of every unauthorized conversation
with a foreigner, the registration of every typewriter _ potential
weapons in the war of words against Ceausescu's rule _ and
censorship far more draconian than any other in the Soviet bloc.
   Everywhere in Eastern Europe, the existence of the censor lent
weight even to words written with little intention of riling
against the Communist rule despised across half a continent.
   In Romania, this was taken to the extreme. Dissident poet Ana
Blandiana, a member of the National Salvation Committee that is now
trying to run the Balkan country, had a book banned last year
simply for a poem about a ``Scallion.''
   For this ``Scallion,'' she wrote: ``Poems have been written, And
portraits painted.'' The regime assumed she was referring to
Ceausescu.
   Such actions revealed the near-paranoia of the Ceausescu regime,
a government headed by peasants turned revolutionaries then
dictators, whose total control knew none of the limits imposed on
aristocrats or monarchs by generations of breeding and sense of the
possible.
   Thus the Ceausescus and their children, reportedly drank,
gambled and lived the high life at will. Ion Pacepa, former chief
of counterintelligence who defected to the United States in 1978,
wrote in memoirs published last year that Elena Ceausescu listened
every week to tapes made at her children's apartments and the homes
of high officials.
   The Ceausescus regarded every aspect of public life as their
private property. In 1966, Ceausescu decreed that every Romanian
family should have four children _ a norm increased two years ago
to five kids per family.
   Few complied. But women were regularly subjected to
gynecological examinations at work to ensure that they were not
hiding any pregnancy they might try to abort for fear they could
not feed their own children.
   Blandiana once talked of the Romanians as an ``entire people
still unborn, yet condemned to be born ... through women's bodies
... never asked if they consented.''
   Citizens everywhere feared tight surveillance. On a flight out
of Romania in 1987, a Romanian exile living in Sweden talked
non-stop of the privations he had found on his first visit home in
five years, apologizing for burbling because he had been unable to
speak the truth for 10 days.
   The barefaced lies of officials in Romania angered even
Westerners who visited just for a few days. For citizens, it was
much worse.
   A Romanian now living abroad recalls, for instance, that one of
her closest friends once confided in a whisper in a private house
that her husband, a state official, would take her into the
bathroom and run water, speaking in a soft voice if he wanted to
tell her about anything _ however harmless _ at the office.
   Such repression was bound to explode in a cascade of words once
Ceausescu went. This is happening now all over Romania, where
makeshift committees in each town repeatedly denounce the regime.
   But the unparalleled repression, akin only to Josef Stalin's
Soviet Union, and not to any other East European country in 1989,
also bred the violence now seen on the streets of Bucharest.
   The revolt against Ceausescu was bred of that violence, and of
despair. The thousands of anti-government protesters who took to
the streets of Timisoara on Dec. 17, mown down by the gunfire of
security forces, braved death because despair had overcome fear in
their quest for bread and freedom.
   Knowing of the massacre, and the other revolutions that had left
their land the last bastion of Stalinism in the Warsaw Pact,
Romanians in several other cities also revolted.
   More carnage by the security forces convinced the army to come
over to their side early Friday. Then, desperation switched sides.
   Knowing that popular hatred of the dictator they once served
will suffice to kill them or put them behind bars, Ceausescu's
security forces began to draw arms caches and safe houses to shoot,
destroy and kill in a murderous last show of their power.
   It is as if the clock had turned back 44 years to the dying days
of World War II in Europe, when Soviet troops had to fight street
for street to gain control of Berlin from diehard Nazis who knew
they had only death to face if they surrendered.
   The National Salvation Committee is issuing repeated appeals to
the population not to take retribution for the years of privation
they suffered at the hands of Ceausescu and the Securitate.
   But a discussion of the most suitable punishment for the
captured dictator on Bucharest Radio Sunday, before the execution,
reflected the bitter hatred of a population that felt even a death
sentence would not pay them back for what they have endured.
   ``Ceausescu was a bastard,'' said Maria Stoica, a worker in
Bucharest. ``He shouldn't die quickly. He must pay for all the
crimes with which he poisoned us.''
   ``He killed us for 24 years,'' said Dumitru Grunea, a car
worker. ``Let him be tried before the people and executed the way
(18th century prince Constantin) Brincoveanu was killed.''
   Brincoveanu was beheaded by the Turks in Constantinople after
being forced to witness the executions of his own sons.
   Alluding to the meager supplies for which Romanians had to queue
six hours a day, an unidentified woman added, ``Ceausescu should
eat the meatless bones we were given as food.''
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Alison Smale, chief of bureau for The Associated Press in
Vienna, has reported extensive from throughout Eastern Europe.
</TEXT>

</DOC>