<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1203EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Shevardnadze 3rdLd-Writethru a0514 12-19 0744</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Shevardnadze, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0514,0765</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Foreign Minister Makes Unprecedented Visit To NATO Headquarters</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 15 grafs to UPDATE with further Shevardnadze comments
to European Parliament, U.S. official's comment on Eastern Europe; Picks
up 15th graf, `Shevardnadze's visit ...'; SUBS grafs 21-31, `The report
...' with 5 grafs to tighten, include further comments.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT J. WIELAARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRUSSELS, Belgium (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard A.
Shevardnadze made an unprecedented visit to NATO headquarters today
and said the Warsaw Pact and NATO must remain in place despite
sharply reduced East-West tensions.
   Later, he reiterated Soviet concerns about German reunification
and warned Western nations not to pressure the German states to
come together.
   ``We do believe the Warsaw Treaty and NATO at this crucial stage
in European development ... are able to play a very important
stabilizing role to become a stabilizing factor in Europe,''
Shevardnadze told reporters after meeting NATO Secretary-General
Manfred Woerner.
   Woerner said Shevardnadze ``mentioned the very essential role of
the Americans here in Europe'' and that the Soviet envoy expressed
interest in setting up formal links between the two military
alliances.
   Woerner said he told Shevardnadze the Warsaw Pact would have to
make further changes before such a move could be considered.
   It was the first time such a high Soviet official has been to
NATO headquarters. His visit came a day after the Western alliance
issued a report saying the Soviet Union appears to be cutting
defense spending.
   Both officials said they agreed that an accord could be wrapped
up next year on reducing conventional weapons in Europe.
   They also agreed a superpower agreement could be worked out next
year on reducing long-range nuclear weapons.
   ``My impression is that the Cold War is, indeed, over,''
Shevardnadze said later during a speech to members of the European
Parliament.
   During the speech, he welcomed the fact that Western leaders
have endorsed reunification if favored by both East and West
Germany but added, ``Any appeals or advice `to exercise
self-determination' or prescriptions as to how and when to change
the ... system of government are not only inappropriate, but may
raise doubts about the authenticity of the eventual allegedly free
choice.''
   Shevardnadze said there are two good reasons to oppose
reunification:
   ``We (the Soviet Union) paid the price of 20 million lives for
the existing European stability,'' he said of World War II.
   ``Furthermore, can the German people themselves forget the
national tragedy brought onto them by Hitlerism?''
   Separately, U.S. Gen. John Galvin, NATO's military commander in
Europe, called events in Eastern Europe an ``enormous transition
(that) is fraught with potential dangers of instability and
uncertainty.''
   ``In the face of this, a unified NATO can be very helpful, and
it appears the Soviets recognize this as well,'' Galvin said in a
statement.
   Shevardnadze's visit to NATO was viewed as carrying great
symbolic importance at a time of a rapidly changing East-West
climate.
   On Monday, NATO released a study that said the Soviet Union
appears to have begun cutting its defense expenditures, including
in the critical area of conventional forces.
   The analysis offers new evidence that the Kremlin is trying to
pare down its massive military industry.
   A year ago, Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev went before
the United Nations and promised to unilaterally cut Soviet forces
by 500,000 troops and reduce conventional arms substantially.
   A month later, he called for a 14.2 percent cut in military
spending and a 19.5 percent reduction in military production.
   ``A number of major procurement programs, particularly in the
land armaments area, are being scaled back,'' the NATO report says.
It adds, however, that it is too early to tell whether all of
Gorbachev's promises will be carried out.
   To the European Parliament, Shevardnadze outlined at length his
concerns about German reunification.
   ``Where are the political, legal and material guarantees that
German unity would not eventually create a threat to the national
security of other states and to peace in Europe?'' he asked.
   ``Will such a hypothetical Germany ... be ready to accept the
existing borders in Europe and renounce any territorial claims? As
we know, the government of the Federal republic of Germany has
avoided answering that question.''
   Europe, he said, must have two ``sovereign German states ... A
retreat from that is fraught with destabilization in Europe.''
   Shevardnadze later flew to London for talks with Prime Minister
Margaret Thatcher. He made no statement upon arriving at the
airport.
</TEXT>

</DOC>