<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0149 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1457EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Lithuania Bjt   12-20 0657</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lithuania, Bjt,0677</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lithuanian Communists Approve Break with National Party</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK J. PORUBCANSKY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VILNIUS, U.S.S.R. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lithuanian Communists voted
overwhelmingly Wednesday to form an independent party, breaking
Moscow's iron political unity for the first time in Soviet history.
   The Lithuanian party's congress of 1,038 delegates voted to
declare themselves an ``equal partner,'' rather than a subordinate,
of the Soviet Communist Party.
   Delegates at the Vilnius Opera and Ballet Theater stood for a
sustained ovation after the vote result was announced: 855 voted
for independence, with 160 for retaining subordination to the
Moscow party.
   Party chief Algirdas Brazauskas congratulated the congress and
expressed the ``hope and wish that our party will always be
resolute, rejuvinated and ready for new battles.''
   The party declared in a resolution it would ``maintain relations
of equal partnership with the Soviet Communist Party, other
progressive parties, public organizations and movements.''
   ``The major goals of the Lithuanian Communist Party are an
independent, democratic Lithuanian state, implementation of the
ideals of humanistic socialism, liberty and social justice,
creation of adequate living conditions for the Lithuanian people
and all the inhabitants of Lithuania,'' the resolution said.
   The break runs counter to more than 80 years of Communist Party
practice and polcy. Since before the 1917 Russian Revolution,
Vladimir I. Lenin demanded a unified party covering the entire
territory of the czarist empire. In 1921, the party formally
outlawed the existence of factions.
   The vote came after two days of tough exchanges between the
majority seeking a break with Moscow and the minority, mostly
ethnic Slavs, who opposed it.
   ``I believe that the formation of this kind of independent party
leads practically to its annihilation,'' said Stefanya
Serzhantovich, a tractor driver from rural Vilnius who is a
congress delegate.
   But Brazauskas and other party leaders said such a split,
including drafting a separate party program, was necessary for
Lithuanian Communists to compete in Feb. 24 elections.
   The Communists, who supported a legislative move Dec. 7 to
strike the leading role of the party from the Baltic republic's
Constitution, will have to compete with the grassroots political
movement Sajudis and other newly formed parties in the local
elections.
   President Mikhail S. Gorbachev had appealed to the Lithuanians,
most recently through party ideology chief Vadim A. Medvedev, not
to split, saying doing so would hurt his reform effort.
   Yegor K. Ligachev, a conservative member of the ruling
Politburo, said in Moscow the Lithuanian party's action ``is great
trouble for the people and for the Communists.''
   He said the Lithuanians ``just do not realize yet what grief
will descend.''
   Lithuanian party documents set a goal of restoring the
republic's complete political independence, something Gorbachev has
warned could upset the balance of a rapidly changing era.
   Lithuania's action was the latest in a series of radical steps
taken by Communist parties in Eastern Europe, which have ended
their monopoly on political power and allowed other parties to form.
   Writer Raimondas Kasauskas told the delegates that an
independent Lithuania was no danger to the Soviet Union, ``just
like the existence of a peaceful Finland or Denmark is not bad,
just like the changes in Hungary don't mean anything bad.''
   ``It would be a disaster if the results of the voting would not
meet the aspirations of the people,'' he said.
   Arvydas Matulionis, of Lithuania's Institute of Society,
Philosophy and Law, told delegates 56 percent of local residents
polled Nov. 30 approved of a separate Communist Party.
   He said 61 percent of the party members polled approved of the
idea.
   Sajudis observers say local Communist Parties in other republics
such as Latvia, Estonia, Georgia and Armenia could follow
Lithuania's example soon and present Gorbachev with a splintered
party when he convenes the 28th national party congress next fall.
   Ethnic Lithuanians make up about 80 percent of its 3.7 million
people. Russians make up about 10 percent, and there are smaller
populations of Poles and other ethnic groups.
</TEXT>

</DOC>