<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1346EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-HolidayinSpace Bjt   12-17 0720</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Holiday in Space, Bjt,0737</SECOND>
<HEAD>Astronauts Ready to Grab a Giant Christmas Present in Space</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HOWARD BENEDICT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Aerospace Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Five astronauts are ready to rocket
into orbit on a holiday voyage to capture a prized Christmas
present for eager scientists.
   The treasure is a satellite the size of a small school bus that
has orbited for nearly six years and will crash to Earth in March
if it is not corraled.
   It is called LDEF, for Long Duration Exposure Facility, and is
packed with 57 experiments containing a wealth of scientific and
technological information.
   The astronauts are to ride the shuttle Columbia into space later
this week to track down and retrieve LDEF, which is 30 feet long,
14 feet in diameter and weighs 21,400 pounds.
   They had been scheduled for liftoff Monday, but lagging work at
the launch pad last week forced a delay until Thursday. Sources
reported Saturday the work remained behind schedule and that a new
date, possibly Friday or Saturday, would be set Monday at a meeting
of shuttle managers.
   On Day 2 of the 10-day mission, the space travelers are to
deploy a Navy communications satellite and start several medical
and scientific experiments as commander Dan Brandenstein and pilot
Jim Wetherbee maneuver Columbia toward their target.
   They will rendezvous with LDEF on Day 4, 5 or 6, depending on
the time and day they lift off.
   ``We hope that even though we'll be gone from our families and
loved ones at Christmas, that we'll be able to bring back a great
big Christmas present for all the scientists who are working on
LDEF,'' Brandenstein said in an interview. ``We'll celebrate
Christmas when we get back.''
   Brandenstein will steer to within 35 feet of LDEF and mission
specialist Bonnie Dunbar will extend the spacecraft's 50-foot robot
arm to snare the satellite.
   ``It will be like hunting a speck in the sky,'' Brandenstein
said. ``But NASA has had plenty experience doing this type of
rendezvous, and Jim and I have practiced it to perfection in the
simulator.''
   Once Dunbar has grasped the satellite, she will hold it on the
end of the arm, turning it frequently, for as long as five hours
while mission specialists Marsha Ivins and David Low photograph
each of its exterior experiments.
   ``Some might have become so eroded or weakened by the long
exposure to space and bombardment by micrometeoroids and atomic
oxygen that they could fall apart during the stress of atmospheric
re-entry or a return to Earth's gravity,'' Dunbar explained. ``So
we want good documentary photos in case that happens.''
   Then she will load LDEF into the cargo bay and the astronauts
will concentrate on experiments for the remainder of the flight,
the second longest planned so far in 33 shuttle missions.
   The flight will be a stepping stone for even longer missions as
Columbia gradually is being modified to stay aloft for 16 days in
1992 and eventually for 28 days.
   Scientists are eager to examine LDEF to learn how various
materials and systems have withstood the long exposure to the space
environment, information that will help in designing permanent
space stations and other long-term spacecraft such as those planned
for a ``Star Wars'' missile defense system.
   ``LDEF is invaluable to us,'' said the mission's flight
director, Al Pennington. ``It is chock full of every material we
use in space flight.''
   LDEF has been in space nearly five years longer than it was
supposed to.
   It was launched by a shuttle crew in April 1984 and was to have
been retrieved 10 months later. But scheduling problems and the
1986 Challenger disaster delayed the rescue.
   ``If LDEF is not recovered, the loss would be tremendous,'' said
Robert M. Walker, director of the McDonnell Center for the Space
Sciences at Washington University in St. Louis, who is
co-investigator of one of the experiments.
   ``We would not only lose experiments that could provide clues to
the origin of our sun and planets but, more importantly, we will
lose valuable information about the changes and damage to
spacecraft after long exposure to the space environment.''
   Also aboard are 12.5 million tomato seeds, which will be
distributed to American students in grades 5 through university
level for research into such things as germination rates and
genetics.
</TEXT>

</DOC>