<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1006EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Romania 5thLd-Writethru   12-24 1291</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Romania, 5th Ld-Writethru,a0693,1329</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Government Calls Cease-Fire, Halt Civilian Vigilantes</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 11 grafs with Ceausescu reportedly found in secret
bunker, vast network of secret tunnels filled with army under the city;
picks up 10th pvs: Fighting was ...</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DUSAN STOJANOVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Buildings burned out of control and
bodies littered the capital Sunday as citizens and allied soldiers
fought savage battles with secret police units loyal to deposed
President Nicolae Ceausescu.
   Some of Europe's most brutal street fighting since World War II
continued for a third day in Bucharest and at least four other
major cities nationwide.
   Romanian radio, in the hands of the revolutionaries, called a
cease-fire, but heavy fighting continued in the center of the city
and at the airport. Revenge-minded vigilante groups who plucked
weapons off the dead were adding a new element to the carnage.
   Supporters of Ceausescu penetrated the headquarters of Romania's
revolutionary leaders, shooting and stabbing at random before they
were subdued by armed forces.
   The National Salvation Committee is trying to lead the chaotic
country from inside the television station building, and the army
said the building remained secure after the attack, which
reportedly killed three people.
   Heavily armed secret police forces loyal to the ousted ruler
were fighting fierce battles with army units who joined the popular
uprising on Friday after a week of protests nationwide.
   Fighting eased briefly in the capital after daybreak Sunday, and
some citizens were seen lugging Christmas trees and carrying
shopping bags, as some merchants briefly opened their shops. But
renewed sniping and hit-and-run attacks by Ceausescu loyalists
cleared the streets again.
   Romanian radio said Sunday that soldiers had found a vast
network of safe houses and secret tunnels criss-crossing the city
that Ceausescu forces stocked with arms, ammunition and electronic
monitoring equipment in recent years.
   The tunnels, some with entrances masked by nondescript panels in
subway stations, run for miles, linking Ceausescu's palace with
party headquarters and extending as far as a lake in the northern
part of the city, said the radio.
   The provisional government said Saturday that Ceausescu his
wife, Elena, and other members of the ruling family were captured
by the army.
   Soviet state television said without elaboration Sunday that
Ceausescu and his wife were captured Saturday while hiding in an
underground bunker. Romanian radio said later Sunday that
Ceausescu's daughter, Zoia, also was captured.
   The revolutionary coalition, trying to halt the anarchy in the
streets and disarm civilians as well as Ceausescu loyalists,
ordered a cease-fire and told all non-army personnel to turn in
their weapons by Monday at 5 p.m. local time.
   People violating the cease-fire ``are committing crimes against
the Romanian people and will receive the strictest punishment,''
said the National Salvation Committee decree.
   Fighting was heavy through the night in and around Bucharest and
in the cities of Brasov, Szeben, Sibiu and Timisoara.
   The revolution began Dec. 15 with protests in Timisoara.
Thousands of people were killed when Ceausescu tried to staunch the
massive protests, and hundreds, perhaps thousands more have died in
the armed struggles for control since Ceausescu fled his palace on
Friday.
   Ceausescu's security forces are elite, heavily armed police who
are essentially fighting for their lives against the
revolutionaries, many of whom have vowed revenge for the massacres
of unarmed citizens during the massive pro-reform protests.
   The East Germany news agency ADN said 5,000 people have died in
the fighting Friday and Saturday. That could not be confirmed, but
a head count at one of 14 Bucharest hospital's tallied 100 dead.
   Army units have formed a cordon around the television building,
a focal point of the struggle for the country and headquarters of
the newly formed National Salvation Committee. The committee is a
hastily formed provisional government of officials ousted by
Ceaucescu through the years, dissidents and sympathetic army
officers.
   During the night, witness said that at one point fanatic
Ceausescu supporters appeared in the TV building's corridors,
shooting and stabbing randomly before being subdued.
   People at the TV building said nobody knew where the attackers,
dressed in civilian clothes, had come from. It was unclear whether
they had penetrated army defenses from the outside or if they had
been in hiding within.
   The assault left one woman dead and two men wounded.
   The U.S. Embassy in Bucharest on Sunday was evacuating
dependents and some staff in a convoy to Sofia, said spokeswoman
Agi Kuperman.
   The army claimed control of all major strategic points across
the nation on Romanian radio. But it was difficult to tell how
secure was the revolutionaries' hold on the country.
   In Timisoara, Associated Press correspondent John Daniszewski
was shot and wounded by uniformed men who stopped his car and
robbed him Saturday night, the Yugoslav Consulate said. He was
hospitalized in satisfactory condition. It could not immediately be
determined whom his assailants were.
   The Yugoslav news agency Tanjug said fighting had moved to the
outskirts of Timisoara, with army units apparently engaging fleeing
Ceausescu loyalists.
   Youths armed with clubs or iron bars assumed control in the city
and were directing traffic and performing other routine functions,
said Tanjug.
   Romanian radio also reported fighting in Sibiu and Brasov, both
about 60 miles north of Bucharest.
   In Bucharest, sporadic machine gun and sniper fire could be
heard near the downtown Intercontinental Hotel, and at least two
snipers were believed positioned on the hotel's roof, from where
fire could be heard before noon.
   Firefights raged well into Saturday night in Bucharest, with the
routes once traveled by Ceausescu between his guarded private villa
and the Communist Party headquarters the scene of intense battles.
   The university library and nearby buildings, believed to be the
stronghold of the Ceausescu loyalist forces, were burning out of
control on Sunday, and there were no attempts to put out the fires.
   Groups of teen-agers armed with automatic rifles and pistols
which they took from the dead ``are trying to carry out a vendetta
against the (Securitate) terrorists,'' Stephan Andreescu, spokesman
for the National Salvation Committee, said, referring to the
security forces.
   ``These ... forces are trying to escape and are extremely
dangerous,'' Andreescu told The Associated Press. But he claimed
the army was in ``complete control of the situation in the
country.''
   ``The terrorists are believed to be hiding in the subway and in
secret underground passages below the former presidential palace,''
Andreescu said. ``It will take days before it is all over.''
   The Soviet news agency Tass, reporting from Bucharest, said the
resisting Securitate units were retreating to cemeteries where
there are rumored to be ``hideouts among burial vaults and
entrances to a system of secret underground tunnels.''
   Ceausescu ruled Romania with an iron fist for 24 years, refusing
the Soviet bloc reforms that this year swept through Hungary,
Poland, Czechoslovakia, Bulgaria and East Germany with relatively
little violence.
   In Switzerland, the Justice Minister said Sunday that a
``precautionary'' freeze has been placed on any assets that may be
held in Switzerland by Ceausescu and his family. The action came
after Romanian exile groups claimed the ousted dictator had stashed
millions of dollars of gold in Zurich banks.
   Thousands of people have been killed since Dec. 15, when the
defense by a few hundred people of a defiant pastor threatened with
arrest in Timisoara turned into a mass protests that swirled the
nation.
   Ion Iliescu, a leading figure in the National Salvation
Committee, said in a national broadcast early Saturday evening that
Ceausescu would be tried.
   A committee communique Sunday said courts would mete out
punishments of the ``greatest severity'' to ``the dictator and his
former lackeys.''
   Several aid shipments sent from abroad were said by Hungarian,
Austrian and other media to be tied up at the airport.
</TEXT>

</DOC>