<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0104EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Christmas-Jesus'KinIII     12-22 1225</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Christmas-Jesus' Kin III,1262</SECOND>
<HEAD>Part III: Family in Galilee Put Pressures on Jesus</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Friday AMs report.</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   This final part of a three-part Christmas series
is about the big Galilean family of which Jesus was a part.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE W. CORNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Religion Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Baffled and sometimes upset by Jesus' independent streak, his
family tried to curb him. ``Even his brothers did not believe
him,'' the record says. But they stuck by him, eventually becoming
pillars of his cause.
   A putative aunt sought to curry preferential status for her
sons, supposed cousins, but he wouldn't play favorites. When still
a boy of l2, he distressed his elders by quitting them to converse
with Temple scholars.
   ``Son, why have you treated us so?'' his mother remonstrated,
noting that she and her husband, Joseph, had hunted him for three
days. They did not understand his explanation about being drawn to
God's house.
   The push-and-pull of those closest and dearest is a common
experience in the best of families. That sort of pressure rimmed
Jesus' life _ the chafing, caring concern of relatives. He had many
in that small close-knit enclave of Israel, bound together by its
belief in one God in a pagan world.
   Relationships, near and distant, pervaded that tiny, insulated
society. It was a hemmed-off, connected household, especially in
Jesus' rural hometown of Nazareth in upland Galilee.
   ``A prophet is not without honor, except in his own country, and
among his own kin, and in his own house,'' he said, indicating the
negative reactions of ``kin'' to his newly launched ministry.
   He ``marveled because of their disbelief,'' Mark's gospel notes.
   His family must have been aghast when Nazareth townspeople
dragged him angrily from the synagogue after his first sermon about
liberty for captives and the oppressed and ``good news to the
poor.''
   Neighors intended to hurl him from a cliff, but stopped at the
last moment, hesitating. His gaze burned into them, and they shrank
back, opening a path for him. He walked away, never going home
again.
   He ``who loves father or mother'' or ``son or daughter more than
me is not worthy of me,'' he said, adding that his truth requires
greater devotion than to parents, wife, children, brothers, sisters
or even to one's ``own life.''
   His immediate family included a flock of ``brothers and
sisters,'' the record says, naming James, Joses, Judas and Simon,
plus an unspecified number of sisters.
   Differences exist about their exact relationship because of
Catholic belief in Mary's perpetual virginity. Some hold that the
brothers and sisters were offspring of Joseph by a previous
marriage, though this is without biblical support.
   It also has been claimed they were cousins in the loose
terminology of ancient times. In any case, a batch of them were
linked in Scripture with Joseph and Mary and obviously shared an
upbringing with Jesus.
   Scripture, in saying Jesus was Mary's ``first-born son,''
implies she later had others, and in saying Joseph ``knew her not
until she had borne a son,'' implies subsequent marital relations.
Whichever, it was a big family.
   It tried to deter Jesus' ministry at the outset. Distressed by
talk that he was ``beside himself,'' his family descended on a
synagogue where he was preaching, intending to seize him.
   When word reached him that ``your mother and your brothers are
outside, asking for you,'' the personal pain of it must have torn
him. He lowered his head momentatily, then spread his arms wide and
said:
   ``Who are my mother and my brothers?'' His gesture embraced
everyone. ``Here are my mother and my brothers! Whoever does the
will of God is my brother, and sister and mother.''
   A poignant interlude, it projected Jesus' work beyond intimate
bonds to humanity at large. But it must have hurt. Such steps are
never without pain, said the late theologian Paul Tillich.
   Noting that the ``depth of the gap'' between him and his family
became acute only with the start of his public ministry, Tillich
added:
   ``Something unconditional breaks into the conditional relations
of the natural family and creates a community which is as intimate
and strong as the family relations, and at the same time infinitely
superior to it.''
   Jesus' apparently rich aunt is identified in three of the
gospels _ John referring to ``his mother's sister,'' Mark to
``Salome'' and Matthew to the ``mother of the sons of Zebedee.''
   Zebedee ran a properous fishing fleet on the Sea of Galilee and
two of his sons, James and John, quit the business to become
disciples of Jesus, presumably also cousins. Salome evidently was
among wealthy women who supported Jesus ``out of their means.''
   That James and John were cousins is further indicated when
Jesus, on the cross, assigned care of his mother to John, a family
responsibility not likely to be placed outside blood ties.
   Salome was a strong-minded, practical woman, something of a
firebrand like her sons, whom Jesus nicknamed ``sons of thunder.''
She also was ambitious, and she saw majestic prospects for Jesus.
   While some relatives doubted his course, she felt sure of it,
even though misconstruing his goal as a restored Jewish kingdom.
She wanted some key places reserved for family.
   She put it bluntly, a senior to a younger clan member. ``Command
that these two sons of mine may sit, one at your right hand and one
at your left, in your kingdom.''
   Jesus looked fondly at his aunt and slowly shook his head. ``You
do not know what you are asking.'' It aroused jealousy among his
apostles. He told them his domain would not be run like the Roman
occupation _ by force and domination.
   Impatience also was registered by Jesus' ``brothers.'' His
growing impact in rural Galilee impressed them, John 7 notes, and
they proposed he go to Jerusalem for a coming festival to establish
himself at the heart of Judaism if he could.
   ``Leave here and go to Judea,'' they urged, suggesting somewhat
skeptically that if his works were genuine he could gain greater
fame. ``For no man works in secret if he seeks to be known openly.
If you do these things, show yourself to the world.''
   He looked at them affectionately, reading their doubts. ``My
time has not yet come, but your time is always here ... Go to the
feast yourselves.''
   Later, however, he went. Curious crowds besieged him, leading to
his crucifixion by Roman authorities, and his resurrection.
   That event transformed his brothers, binding them to him in
unwavering loyalty. The oldest brother, called James the Just,
became head of the church in Jerusalem, his leadership ranked above
the 12 apostles.
   He presided over the church's first council, which widened doors
of the new faith beyond Jews to Gentiles, to all the world. Many
scholars ascribe to him the biblical epistle of James with its call
to apply Jesus' teachings in deeds.
   ``Be doers of the word,'' he wrote. ``Faith, if it has no works,
is dead.''
   After James was slain in rising revolutionary tides of the early
A.D. 60s, church historian Eusebius says, another brother of Jesus,
Simon, took over church leadership in Jerusalem.
   Initially unresponsive, relatives became mainstays of the
world-girdling faith Jesus started. However, he says the principle
relationship extends beyond blood to all believers.
   ``I am the vine,'' he said, ``you are the branches.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>