<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0194 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1421EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-WallStreet2pm     12-26 0336</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Wall Street 2pm,0354</SECOND>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prices moved marginally higher in extremely
light trading on Wall Street today with bargain-hunting responsible
for the gains.
   The Dow Jones average of 30 industrials was up 7.68 at 2,719.07
as of 2 p.m. EST after have been down about seven points in earlier
trading.
   The broader market was also slightly higher. Advancing issues
were ahead of decliners by a margin of about 10 to 9, with 701
stocks rising, 626 falling and 532 unchanged on the New York Stock
Exchange.
   Volume on the Big Board came to a light 53.64 million shares
with two hours of trading left. Many traders were extending their
Christmas holiday into this week.
   Stocks declined early in the session as bond prices slumped in
response to an increase Monday in Japan's discount rate from 3.75
percent to 4.25 percent.
   The Treasury's 30-year bond was down about } point, or $6.25 per
$1,000 in face amount, while its yield rose to 7.95 from 7.88 late
Friday.
   Analysts said some of the drop in bonds also was attributable to
traders adjusting yearend portfolios and to concerns about
inflation. Prices for heating oil and orange juice futures rose
sharply today because of the cold weather, and traders speculated
that inflation might accelerate.
   But as the session progressed on Wall Street, traders decided
that there was little cause for concern, said Michael Metz, an
analyst with Oppenheimer &amp; Co.
   Investors had available cash and were in the market picking up
bargains, Metz said.
   The most-actively traded stock on the NYSE was Bank of New
England, which rose ] to 7~.
   Exxon was down \ to 50] after a weekend explosion shut down a
major refinery in Texas. American Express was up 1 to 32~, IBM was
off ] to 95 and Sears, Roebuck was up | to 37].
   The NYSE's composite index of all its listed common stocks rose
0.22 to 192.17. On the American Stock Exchange, the market value
index rose 0.15 to 370.99.
</TEXT>

</DOC>