<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0109 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1459EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Schools-Television     12-18 0568</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Schools-Television,590</SECOND>
<HEAD>Education Groups Back TBS School Program</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By W. DALE NELSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four national education groups said Monday
that they support Turner Broadcasting Co.'s commercial-free news
program for classroom use, denouncing rival Channel One because it
carries commercials.
   ``Exploitation of a captive audience in the classroom, using the
classroom and the curriculum as a marketplace for products rather
than a marketplace for ideas, and selling or trading students in a
classroom for a satellite dish or a television monitor are
outrageous breaches of ethical practice,'' Gary Marx, associate
executive director of the American Association of School
Administrators, said about Channel One.
   Marx joined representatives of the National PTA, the National
Association of Secondary School Principals and the National
Education Association at a news conference with Ted Turner,
president of Turner Broadcasting.
   Channel One, produced by Whittle Communications of Knoxville,
Tenn., envisions making and installing up to 300,000 television
sets, 16,000 videocasette recorders and 8,000 satellite dishes at
participating schools. The Turner program does not, and would be
delivered at schools via cable or tape rather than satellite.
   Scott Thompson, executive director of the organization of
principals, said Channel One producers are telling schools, ```You
are going to have to sell the time of your students in your
classroom in order to get this.'''
   ``We think this is ethically wrong,'' Thompson said.
   Thompson said his group had written to all of the companies that
advertise on Channel One explaining its objections. He said some
companies decided not to continue their sponsorship, but he did not
name them.
   Whittle spokesman David Gerard disagreed with the criticism of
the commercials.
   ``We are not introducing advertising to schools,'' Gerard said,
arguing that newspapers and magazines that carry ads long have been
used as teaching tools.
   Jeremiah Floyd, associate executive director of the National
School Boards Association, which announced its support of Turner
Broadcasting's CNN Newsroom in April, reaffirmed its backing but
did not criticize Channel One.
   ``It is a local proposition, and if that's the only game in town
and the local people decide they want to go with that game, then
that's their prerogative,'' Lloyd said.
   Turner said CNN Newsroom, launched in August, had an initial
enrollment of 1,000 schools. That has risen to 5,000, 2{ times the
figure Turner Broadcasting had expected to have by now, he said.
   He said he expected to have 10,000 schools by September.
   Whittle, which plans to launch Channel One nationally in March,
said in November that it had 1,050 schools lined up. The company
has said it hoped to expand to 8,000 schools by the end of 1990.
   Gerard said Whittle will have raised about $200 million in
advertising support for Channel One by the end of the year.
   ``We think the Turner program is pretty good, it's pretty
well-produced, but like the vast majority of great educational
programming, it's not watched. It goes unseen by most students in
this country and the technology is not there to watch it,'' Gerard
said.
   ``When a school signs up for Channel One, they are committed to
showing the program about 90 percent of the time in virtually every
classroom every day,'' he said.
   Turner said about 50 percent to 60 percent of high schools have
cable television available and, in those that don't, teachers can
tape the program, at home when it is broadcast in the early morning
hours.
</TEXT>

</DOC>