<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0221 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0512EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a PM-BusinessMirror Adv22   12-22 0876</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Business Mirror, Adv 22,0898</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv22</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release PMs Friday, Dec. 22</HEAD>
<HEAD>Flower Power In The Book Industry</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN CUNNIFF</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Analyst</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   One of the more successful books of the
Christmas selling season is a work of art, ``In The West,'' a bound
portfolio of some of artist Georgia O'Keeffe's best work. It costs
$100.
   While that in itself is a story, since book publishing has had
its woes, the saga behind the book is a rare one of
entrepreneurship involving a young publisher guided by heart and
soul rather than a business degree.
   Nicholas Callaway was a Harvard classics student in 1973 when
the artist came to the school to receive an honorary degree. ``I
wanted to see the person I had admired in the photographs (by her
husband, Alfred Stieglitz),'' he said.
   A junior, Callaway wasn't involved in the ceremony, so he had to
improvise. O'Keeffe loved flowers. ``I went to a florist in Harvard
Square and bought a peony,'' he said, and then worked his way
through the crowd in the yard.
   ``There she was,'' he said, ``the woman in the photographs.'' As
she passed in procession he held out the peony, saying ``This is
for you Mrs. O'Keeffe.'' She took it, instinctively, it seemed, and
held it throughout the ceremony.
   O'Keeffe, then 85, seldom corresponded with admirers, but
Callaway had been mesmerized. He wrote to her the following year.
She replied, saying she had always wondered who gave her the peony.
She invited him for a visit.
   Callaway spent a day with O'Keeffe at Ghost Ranch, her studio
near Abiquiu, N.M. It intensified his feelings. At the time, he had
no thought of publishing, but the classics scholar felt drawn more
intensely toward studio arts.
   He recalled the flower episode a few days ago, and briefly dwelt
on its meaning in his life, and perhaps in the lives of would-be
entrepreneurs.
   ``When you are drawn to something you must seize the
opportunity. There is no reason to hesitate in pursuing an
intuition, attraction or interest,'' he said.
   ``Had I not handed her the flower,'' he reflected, ``a lot of
other things might not have happened.''
   Callaway experimented with photography before he left Harvard,
traveled to Europe on a fellowship, studied art, apprenticed
himself to a fine printer in Paris and then was asked by a friend
to run an art gallery there.
   The experiences were revealing. Callaway, 23, found he could
combine art and business _ that, in fact, he was a good
businessman. The elements were coming together, he said, and
convinced him to have his own operation.
   Back in America, his brother, like his father, an entrepreneur,
lent him money to publish his first book, ``Brancusi: The Sculptor
as Photographer.'' He sold 3,000 copies at $19.95.
   He went to see O'Keeffe again, found she wanted to publish a
book of her husband's photographs, couldn't resist the challenge
and daringly won the right to co-publish the work with The National
Gallery of Art. He had four employees.
   The book was a huge success, critically and commercially. He was
on his way, working from a Greenwich Village studio but printing in
Kyoto, Japan.
   Callaway Editions, Inc. still has only eight people, but
smallness is its strength. Big up-front costs, typical in book
publishing, are not easily met by small companies, so Callaway
restructured and focused his efforts.
   That restructuring seems to have defined the way fine books are
published in the future. Callaway and similarly small companies now
often co-publish with large, established houses, combining the
strengths of each.
   The small company specializes in concepts, editorial matter and
production. ``We concentrate on making the book, and they (bigger
publishers) do what they do best: financing, marketing, sales and
distribution,'' he says.
   The Callaway staff is intense, perfectionist, dedicated,
creative. And enterprising: They must, for instance, develop leads
from decades-old telephone books to find owners of paintings, and
then seek permission to photograph.
   ``In The West'' is the second of four O'Keeffe volumes scheduled
for co-publishing with the esteemed house of Alfred Knopf, part of
Random House, and edited by Callaway and Doris Bry, an O'Keeffe
associate and scholar.
   The first, ``One Hundred Flowers,'' in two years sold nearly
75,000 hardbound copies at $100, and more than 100,000 in a $29.95
softcover edition. Previously, no $100 trade art book had sold more
than about 15,000 copies.
   That's just part of the commercial success. Callaway and Knopf
have found that O'Keeffe, an American icon, is a world industry.
About 150,000 ``One Hundred Flowers'' calendars sold at $12.95,
with another edition out for 1990.
   Parts of ``In The West'' also will take multiple forms: a wall
calendar to be sure; a $16.95 engagement desk book (75,000 copies),
a $9.95 post card book with two images of 12 paintings (30,000),
and an $18.95 address book (35,000).
   The works will be published in Canada, the United Kingdom,
France, Germany, Italy, Japan and Scandinavia, again with partners
in each country. ``We could not do what we do without larger
companies,'' says Callaway.
   But what they do is what they love to do, eight intense people
in a small Greenwich Village studio. It makes a difference.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv PMs Friday, Dec. 22.</NOTE>

</DOC>