<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0152 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1457EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s e BC-APN--TVWeek Adv07   12-26 0808</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--TV Week, Adv 07,0824</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv07</HEAD>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Jan. 7</HEAD>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<HEAD>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 1 b&amp;w photo.)</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JERRY BUCK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Television Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tall and powerful Craig T. Nelson seems right
for the role as the tough federal agent in the forthcoming NBC
miniseries ``Drug Wars: The Camarena Story.''
   But Nelson is equally at home doing comedy. He's also currently
starring in the comedy series ``Coach,'' which ABC recently
returned to its hit Tuesday schedule. ``Coach'' had previously
aired in the spring and summer.
   In ``Coach,'' Nelson plays Hayden Fox, who at 45 clings to a
coaching job in a small college that a younger man would regard
only as a steppingstone. His old-fashioned ideas bring him into
conflict with the women in his life, a coed daughter he had not
seen in years, his longtime girlfriend and a new college president
who has some feminist ideas about sports.
   Curiously enough, Nelson began as a stand-up comic and comedy
writer-performer. But ``Coach'' is the first comedy he's done after
years of dramatic roles in feature motion pictures, frequently as
the heavy, and in such series as ``Chicago Story'' and ``Call To
Glory.''
   At one time, no producer would even consider him for a dramatic
role. In 1972, he got so discouraged he packed up his family and
moved into a log cabin with no electricity and no running water in
a wilderness area.
   After five years, he hitchhiked back to Los Angeles and found a
company willing to back a documentary series on people who drop out
of society. He tried to interest his former comedy partner, Barry
Levinson, in helping him edit the series.
   Instead, he found Levinson had just written a movie called
``...And Justice For All.'' Levinson asked him to audition for a
role and he was cast as the calculating prosecutor.
   Suddenly, Nelson became a much sought-after actor for movies and
television. After a time, people forgot he had done comedy.
   ``Drug Wars,'' which NBC will broadcast in three parts Sunday,
Monday and Tuesday, tells of the 1985 kidnap-murder of U.S. Drug
Enforcement Administration agent Enrique Camarena in Guadalajara,
Mexico, and its aftermath. DEA agents believe Camarena was killed
with the knowledge of Mexican police and that a cover-up reached
the top levels of the Mexican government. The story is based on the
book ``Desperados'' by Elaine Shannon.
   ``I play James `Jaime' Kuykendall, the agent in charge of the
Guadalajara office, although the name is changed to Harley
Steinmetz,'' Nelson says. ``He's a big Texan, soft-spoken, with a
drawl. I talked with him several times because I needed to know how
he reacted during certain situations.
   ``He was reaching into areas that weren't accessible to him and
it was frustrating to him. In one scene he watches the police
question one of the men who interrogated Camarena after his
abduction. He goes berserk because the questions are so absurd.
Jaime confirmed that it was a very difficult time and some punches
were thrown.''
   Nelson's new show, ``Coach,'' began with a call from
producer-creator Barry Kemp.
   ``The idea of doing a comedy again really intrigued me,'' he
says. ``People no longer thought of me as a comedy actor. I liked
what Barry had in mind for the character. He's a guy in a midlife
crisis. He's not necessarily a nice guy. As a coach, he hasn't been
exposed to a lot of other values.
   ``One of the things I liked is they wanted to bring him to a
confrontation of his values and have him change through his
daughter and girlfriend. The ladies in his life have certain ideas
of how he should be adapting to what they bring him, but he doesn't
see it that way.''
   Nelson came to Los Angeles from Arizona in 1967 after he
received a scholarship to the Oxford Theater from the Eddie Cantor
Foundation.
   ``I had a baby and a wife and a car that was falling apart,'' he
says. ``I met Barry, who was also on a scholarship. He was living
in his car. It smelled like cologne and cigarettes. We teamed up
and did a comedy act at various clubs and trade fairs. It was a way
to get into the business, but at first I also had a job as a
security guard and later as a security analyst.''
   During that time they worked as writers and performers on a
Lohman and Barkley television variety series, ``The Tim Conway
Comedy Hour,'' an Alan King special and ``The John Byner Comedy
Hour.''
   Nelson has not written any ``Coach'' episodes, but says he has a
lot of input. He is writing ideas for movies and other stories.
   ``I'm doing right now exactly what I want to be doing,'' he says.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>

</DOC>