<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0188 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1837EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     12-22 0386</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0397</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cold Spell One of Worst On Record</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Record low temperatures were reported in more than 125 cities
across the nation Friday while readings above freezing were limited
to Florida, the Pacific Coast and southwestern deserts.
   More records were expected to fall Friday night. The National
Weather Service said the number of record lows makes the cold snap
one of the most severe on record for nation's central and eastern
region.
   Morning lows of 23 degrees below zero at Kansas City, Mo., 26
below zero at Concordia, Kan., and 27 below zero at Goodland, Kan.,
were the coldest for any day or month of the year on record for
those three locations.
   A reading of minus 23 in Indianapolis was the coldest of the
century.
   By sunrise Friday, subzero readings extended from the High
Plains region to the Great Lakes region, the Ohio Valley and
Tennessee Valley to New England.
   Arctic cold continued to push across the Gulf Coast and into
Florida. Strong northerly winds kept temperatures dropping during
the day across parts of the south-central and southeastern United
States.
   Temperatures in the single digits were was far south as northern
Mississippi and northern Alabama.
   Snow, sleet and freezing rain made travel hazardous across
southern Texas and southern Louisiana. Rain was expected to change
to snow in parts of the Southeast overnight.
   Fair weather prevailed across most of the West with fog west of
the Rockies.
   A warm front was beginning to bring more moderate temperatures
to the northern High Plains but it was accompanied by snow and
strong winds.
   Some of the cities with record low temperatures for the date:
Atlantic City, N.J., 7; Billings, Mont., minus 26; Birmingham,
Ala., 5; Burlington, Iowa, minus 18; Cape Hatteras, N.C., 22; Cedar
Rapids, Iowa, minus 19; Cleveland, minus 15; Conway, Ark., 1;
Duluth, Minn., minus 22;
   Evansville, Ind., minus 15; Fayetteville, Ark., minus 8; Grand
Rapids, Mich., below 11; Huron, S.D., minus 28; Jackson, Miss., 8;
Louisville, Ky., minus 15; Lubbock, Texas, minus 2; La Crosse,
Wis., minus 24; Nashville, Tenn., minus 10; Omaha, Neb., minus 25;
Philadelphia 6; Rapid City, S.D., minus 29; Tulsa, Okla., minus 6;
Wilmington, Del., 5; Youngstown, Ohio., minus 12.
   The low in the Lower 48 states was 47 degrees below zero at
Broadus, Mont.
</TEXT>

</DOC>