<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 1129EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WalleyeLimit     12-31 0352</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Walleye Limit,0362</SECOND>
<HEAD>South Dakota Walleye Limit Reduced One-Third</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOE KAFKA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PIERRE, S.D. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Anglers will find it easier to catch their
limit of South Dakota walleye in 1990, but not because the finicky
game fish is suddenly more willing to take the bait.
   The legal daily catch has been cut from six to four as of
Monday, annoying fishermen and prompting warnings that tourism may
suffer.
   The problem is that anglers are getting too good at catching the
tasty fish.
   While fishermen once had to guess where the elusive and feisty
walleyes were lurking, many now rely on electronic sonar units to
locate them, said Dennis Unkenholz, a biologist for the Game, Fish
and Parks Department.
   ``There's more people fishing more hours,'' Unkenholz said.
``They're using bigger boats and sophisticated fishing equipment.''
   ``Walleyes are a renewable resource, but they can only sustain
so much harvest,'' he added.
   The Game, Fish and Parks Commission made the unexpected cut Nov.
6 and reaffirmed its decision Dec. 8. The agency said that in some
places, heavy fishing has caused a ``noticeable decline in the
quality of the fishery and places the future of the fishery in
serious jeopardy.''
   Unkenholz said that the reduced limit won't affect many people
because few anglers catch the limit anyway.
   South Dakota will see fewer non-resident anglers because of the
change, said Larry Atkinson, chairman of the Tourism Advisory
Board. Fishing contributes $70 million a year to South Dakota's
economy, he said.
   ``It will have a severe impact on especially the businesses that
are hanging on by a thread now,'' he said.
   Bait shops and campgrounds catering to anglers dot the shoreline
along the four Missouri River reservoirs in South Dakota. Walleyes
also are the main fare in natural lakes in eastern South Dakota.
   Since fishing licenses are not issued specifically for walleyes,
it's not possible to say exactly how many people cast their lines
for walleyes each year in South Dakota. The state record for
walleyes is about 15 pounds, although most of those caught range
between one-half pound and three pounds.
</TEXT>

</DOC>