<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0153EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-US-EasternEurope     12-29 0454</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-Eastern Europe,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Congressman Urges Most Favored Nation Status for Czechoslovakia</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RUTH SINAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The author of a law that discriminates against
trade with Communist countries is asking President Bush to remove
all tariff restrictions from the ``revitalized nation'' of
Czechoslovakia.
   Charles A. Vanik wrote Bush this week saying the official
decrees published by the pro-democracy reformists running
Czechoslovakia have ``clearly met all conditions'' of the law he
co-sponsored with the late Senator Henry Jackson in 1974.
   The Jackson-Vanik amendment, which in essence imposes high
tariffs on countries that forbid free emigration, was designed to
pressure the Communist bloc into allowing Jews and other minorities
to emigrate. It forbids granting such countries Most Favored Nation
trade status that significantly reduces tariffs on imports into the
United States.
   Czechoslovakia has been actively seeking Most Favored Nation
status since early this year, but was told by the administration
that dramatic improvements would have to be made in its human
rights record.
   A State Department official said Thursday that consideration is
being given to granting Czechoslovakia's wish in light of the
fast-paced reforms away from totalitarian Communist rule.
   The two new Czechoslovak leaders, Vaclav Havel and Alexander
Dubcek, were subjected to severe human rights violations under the
Communists who ran the country until two months ago, Vanik said.
Dubcek was elected speaker of Parliament on Thursday and Havel was
scheduled for swearing-in as president today. New elections are
expected next year.
   The new leadership has amended Czechoslovakia's constitution to
remove the Communist Party's monopoly on power and the predominance
of Marxist-Leninist teachings in the school system. In addition,
lawmakers voted Thursday to amend the presidential oath to be taken
by Havel to eliminate the pledge of allegiance to socialism.
   ``The most important thing America can do is provide an
immediate fair and equal access to our markets,'' said Vanik, a
lawyer in private practice here who was a Democrat representing an
Ohio district when the law was passed.
   ``I urge that you declare this revitalized nation eligible for
Most Favored Nation status and the same tariff benefits we extend
to all our other trading partners,'' he asked Bush.
   Bush recently lifted the Jackson-Vanik restrictions from
Hungary, granting it Most Favored Nation status in response to
moves in that country toward democratic rule.
   ``He could do the same for Czechoslovakia,'' Vanik said. ``It
wouldn't cost him anything and would be a great way to tell them we
support what they're doing.''
   Bush also has indicated he would be willing to grant Most
Favored Nation status to the Soviet Union if it adopts laws, now
under consideration, permitting free emigration.
   Czechoslovakia exports glass products, machine tools and other
light industrial goods.
</TEXT>

</DOC>