<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1038EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Panama-Guns 1stLd-Writethru a0426 12-28 0727</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Guns, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0426,0745</SECOND>
<HEAD>Panamanian Turn In Guns Galore To U.S. Forces _ Even Valuable Antiques</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 12th pvs, `An army...' to UPDATE with latest weapons figures.
DELETES 13th pvs as OUTDATED and picks up 14th pvs, `Harper said...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DORALISA PILARTE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The gun collection program set up by
U.S. armed forces to sweep Panama City clean of illegal weapons has
been a huge success _ maybe too much so.
   One person turned in a beautiful antique flintlock musket _ at
least 150 years old _ with brass handle, hand-carved wooden stock
and loading tools, including what looked like a wooden mallet.
   All of it fit snugly in special compartments of a soft leather
case lined with red velvet.
   ``I tell them that this kind of stuff is worth far more than the
$100 we give them for a pistol,'' said Army Sgt. Tim Harper of the
193rd Brigade stationed at Fort Clayton on the outskirts of Panama
City near the canal.
   But apparently, the people would rather have the cash than an
old, odd-looking musket that shoots lead balls, which in any case
may just have been acquired in the looting that destroyed the
city's main shopping avenue.
   Most Panamanians, however, have been bringing in regular stuff _
Soviet designed AK-47 automatic rifles, Belgian-made FAL assault
rifles (``The sniper's weapon,'' Harper said), hand and
rocket-propelled grenades as well as light anti-tank weapons,
dynamite and even tear-gas grenades.
   That doesn't include the ``exotic'' guns that Harper said he
wasn't actually expecting to get _ Uzi submachine guns,
American-made M-60 machine guns, ``and lots and lots of
ammunition.''
   ``It's a gun lover's paradise,'' said Harper, of Allen Park,
Mich., as he surveyed hundreds of weapons in small piles lying on
exercise mats covering the entire floor of Ancon Gym.
   By paying cash for weapons brought in to four special collection
points, the U.S. military is trying to lessen the chances that they
could fall into the hands of diehards from Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noriega's disbanded Defense Forces.
   Authorities pay $25 for each hand grenade brought in; $100 for
pistols; $125 for shotguns; $150 for automatic rifles; $150 for
mines. On items not outlined in the payoff schedule, Harper
bargains.
   Bazookas, for example, go for about the same as an automatic
rifle; tear-gas grenades are negotiable, but closer to the price
for regular hand grenades.
   An Army official said today that $150,000 had been paid for
2,208 weapons turned in by 721 people.
   Harper said the weapons would eventually probably be returned to
Panama's new government, which was sworn in Dec. 20 when the United
States invaded to oust Noriega. Members of the Defense Forces who
surrender are screened and incorporated into a new armed force that
includes police and security.
   Already, some are performing tasks alongside U.S. troops and
taking over police duties, such as directing traffic.
   Armed with their regular weapons, the Panamanian forces also are
patrolling streets and guarding government buildings, looking for
looters and the occassional sniper.
   At Ancon Gym, about 100 Panamanians lined up late Wednesday
afternoon to collect their money. Some said they had been there
since morning, when they turned in weapons.
   Most people interviewed said they had ``found them in the
trash.'' One man said he found his weapon ``in the bushes.''
   When asked why they were looking through the trash, or in the
bushes, those interviewed tended to want to change the topic of
conversation.
   One man, 23-year-old Luis Reyes, admitted he was a former
Defense Forces sergeant and had been in the Panamanian military for
nearly five years.
   A native of the central provincial town of Los Santos, Reyes
said he was a high school dropout and had joined the Defense Forces
as just a quick way to start earning a living.
   He said he has a wife and two toddlers. He brought in a
.38-caliber handgun, for which he was to get $100.
   ``I'll use it to buy food and other things that are needed in my
house, what else?'' Reyes said.
   He said he would like to form part of the new armed force, but
if there are civilian jobs available, then he'd rather have one of
those.
   ``I would be more at rest and closer to my family,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>