<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0155EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Names     12-28 0687</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Names,0715</SECOND>
<HEAD>Names in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY14</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWPORT BEACH, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former President Reagan regaled the
University of Southern California football team with tales of his
portrayal of George Gipp, but the role didn't impress Michigan
coach Bo Schembechler.
   Reagan, a Bel-Air resident, showed up at a recent practice to
watch the 12th-ranked Trojans prepare for their Rose Bowl contest
with No. 3 Michigan on New Year's Day.
   Reagan told the team a story about the filming of ``Knute
Rockne, All-American,'' in which he played the legendary Notre Dame
running back.
   ``I saw him play in the movie, and he didn't look good enough to
beat us,'' Schembechler said Wednesday. ``And he should be down in
Miami, supporting the Gipper's team, Notre Dame.''
   The Fighting Irish play No. 1 Colorado in the Orange Bowl on New
Year's Day.
   Reagan and his wife, Nancy, planned to visit the Palm Springs
desert estate of friend Walter Annenberg on their annual New Year's
pilgrimage.
   The Reagans are scheduled to leave Friday for the 110-mile trip
to the luxurious walled estate of the former ambassador to Great
Britain. It will be their 22nd annual New Year's holiday at the
Annenberg compound.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>ST. CHARLES, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rock 'n' roll legend Chuck Berry has
been accused in a lawsuit of secretly videotaping women using a
restaurant restroom.
   Hosana A. Huck, 48, a former cook at a restaurant owned by
Berry, filed the lawsuit Tuesday in St. Charles County Circuit
Court seeking unspecified damages.
   Huck, who worked at the Southern Air in Wentzville, about 30
miles from St. Louis, said she and other employees and customers
were taped and that it humiliated her and caused her distress.
   Berry, 63, who lives near Wentzville, was unavailable for
comment. Calls to his restaurant went unanswered Wednesday.
   The lawsuit says the videotapes ``were created for the improper
purpose of the entertainment and gratification'' of Berry's
``sexual fetishes and sexual predilections.''
   The duck-walking guitarist is known for such hits as ``Roll Over
Beethoven'' and ``Johnny B. Goode.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>DUNLEWY, Ireland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Irish lawmaker Pat Gallagher has married
a woman who served nine years in prison after being convicted of
Irish Republican Army activities in Britain.
   Anne Gallagher, 38, and her sister Eileen Gillespie, were
sentenced to 15 years in prison for conspiring to cause explosions
and possessing explosives. They were released in 1983.
   The trial judge described the sisters as ``sinister and evil IRA
bombers.''
   Gallagher, 41, said earlier this year that his wife deserves a
chance of a normal life.
   ``I know my constituents do not think any the worse of me,''
said the junior minister in Irish Prime Minister Charles Haughey's
government.
   The couple married Wednesday in Dunlewy, County Donegal, 140
miles northwest of Dublin.
   The IRA is fighting British rule in Northern Ireland. It wants
to unite the predominantly Protestant province with the 95 percent
Roman Catholic Republic of Ireland under socialist rule.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PECOS, N.M. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actress Greer Garson Fogelson is
reconsidering the sale of her 10,000-acre ranch after learning the
proposed buyer would convert it into a resort, her representatives
said.
   Although the 81-year-old Mrs. Fogelson had decided at one point
to sell the ranch, she no longer is certain after learning of the
extent of the proposed development, spokeswoman Jean Carpenter said
Wednesday in Dallas, where the actress lives.
   Pecos National Monument Superintendent Linda Stoll said last
week that Indian ruins at the monument could be damaged by air
traffic and housing if the adjacent 10,000-acre Forked Lightning
Ranch along the Pecos River in central New Mexico became a resort.
   Capital Developers International Inc. of Orlando, Fla., is
negotiating to buy the property. Stoll said plans for the resort
include an airfield, private hunting reserve, two golf courses, a
454-acre shopping center, a race track for cars and motorcycles and
housing developments.
   Capital's answering service said Wednesday nobody from the
company would be available to comment until Jan. 10.
   The actress starred in such films as ``Mrs. Miniver,''
``Goodbye, Mr. Chips,'' ``Pride and Prejudice'' and ``Sunrise at
Campobello'' in a career that spanned 40 years.
</TEXT>

</DOC>