<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1056EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Israel     12-30 0411</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Israel,0423</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Human Chain' Almost Surrounds City, Police Charge Twice</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EILEEN ALT POWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police and border troops used nightsticks and
fired rubber bullets, tear gas and water cannons to disperse some
of the thousands of people demonstrating for peace in Jerusalem's
Old City today.
   At least 13 people were injured. Police arrested 50 people,
according to Israel radio.
   Police said some demonstrators shouted pro-Palestinian slogans,
setting off two charges by policemen into largely Palestinian
groups. Some demonstrators shouted ``Palestine is Arab!'' and the
Moslem rallying cry ``Allahu Akbar'' _ ``God is great!''
   For the most part, however, the Israeli, European and
Palestinian participants in the peace chain joined in chants of
``We want peace'' and carried balloons with the rally's slogan,
``1990 _ Time for Peace.''
   Some 15,000 people, about a third more than organizers had
expected, turned out for the ``human chain'' around the stone walls
of Jerusalem's Old City. Twelve hundred people came from Europe for
the rally, most of them Italians.
   The crowd probably could have encircled the wall of the Old
City, a distance of more than 4,000 yards. But participants were
unevenly distributed, with the activists five deep in some areas
and up to a dozen yards apart in others.
   After the activists linked hands, thousands of balloons were
released into the air to drift over the city.
   People stood silently for about 15 minutes, then some
participants broke into a rousing version of ``We Shall Overcome''
and chanted ``two states for two people.''
   Rally organizers said the goal was to prove that dialogue
between Israelis and Palestinians can lead to peace in the Middle
East. The rally was sponsored by Italian peace groups, Israel's
Peace Now and Palestinian activists.
   Faisal Husseini, a Palestinian leader in Jerusalem, complained
that army roadblocks on the outskirts of Jerusalem kept many
Palestinian from attending.
   ``I know that if the road were opened, we would have had double
or triple the number you are seeing,'' Husseini told reporters as
he joined the gathering.
   He described it as ``a very historic moment'' and added that it
should be a message for Israelis to look at the Palestinian as an
individual and ``learn that you can build peace with him.''
   A woman's peace march on Friday, also part of the ``1990 _ Time
for Peace'' program, was broken up by police firing tear gas and
swinging nightsticks after an outlawed Palestinian flag was raised.
</TEXT>

</DOC>