<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0171 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 2036EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WKD--Richler Adv05-07   12-26 0729</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--Richler, Adv 05-07,0750</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv05-07</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Weekend Editions, Jan. 5-7, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WEEKEND ENTERTAINMENT AND ARTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Books and Authors: Mordecai Richler's Most Ambitious Work</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SOLL SUSSMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TORONTO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mordecai Richler has a standard answer ready for
those who wonder about the apparent similarities between the
fictional Gursky family in his new novel and a certain real-life
Canadian dynasty that soared to wealth and prominence in the
whiskey business.
   ``My reply will be that I wouldn't want five years' work reduced
to the level of prurient gossip,'' he says.
   Indeed, Richler closes the lively new book, ``Solomon Gursky Was
Here,'' with an author's note that simply states: ``I made the
Gurskys up out of my own head.''
   The Montreal-based writer is frequently repeating his answer on
the promotional tour that is helping to make the novel, his first
since ``Joshua Then and Now'' in 1980, one of the big books of the
Canadian fall publishing season. It will appear next spring in the
United States and a short while later in Britain.
   ``I think there are two or three superficial resemblances in
their early careers, but it's not about that family at all,''
Richler, 58, said of the Bronfman family, who built Seagram's into
the world's largest distilling company.
   He noted that the novel not only includes those ``superficial
resemblances'' to the Bronfmans in Montreal but also ranges over
Canadian territory from the Prairies to the Arctic and covers
subjects from anti-Semitism to the search for the Northwest Passage.
   ``You write a novel, and it's very difficult to follow it around
with explanations,'' Richler said. ``I feel I've had my say.''
   The atmosphere of Montreal's prominent Jewish community has
served Richler well in his past novels, such as ``The
Apprenticeship of Duddy Kravitz'' and ``St. Urbain's Horsemen.''
   ``It's certainly the most complex novel I've ever attempted,''
Richler said of his new work. He was interviewed, looking slightly
rumpled and smoking small Dutch cigars, at breakfast during his
visit to Toronto for an authors' festival.
   ``It's his longest novel yet, and by far his most ambitious and
imaginative,'' reviewer William French wrote in Toronto's Globe and
Mail newspaper. ``Whether it's his most satisfying is open to
debate.''
   Richler works regularly as a journalist and is one of the
Canadian writers turned to frequently by foreign publications
seeking a home-grown view of the country.
   He has been working lately on an article about the
English-French language tensions in Quebec. The province's English
minority lives for the most part in Montreal, the largest city in
Quebec.
   ``It's a quarrel more appropriate to a schoolyard. Whichever
side you're on, it's somewhat embarrassing to be quarreling about
signs,'' Richler said.
   Quebec provincial laws restrict the language on all outdoor
commercial signs to French.
   ``It's a very wasting tribal quarrel. It has little to do with
the real problems of the country,'' he said.
   During the hard-fought 1988 campaign over whether Canada should
go ahead with a free-trade agreement with the United States, he
lined up not with such writing heavyweights as Robertson Davies and
Margaret Atwood against the pact but with a lesser known group
supporting it.
   ``I just felt that it was a trade deal,'' Richler said. ``I hope
it will work out well. The test will be if it creates more jobs.''
   The opponents of the pact, which took effect last Jan. 1, argued
that Canadian culture could be overwhelmed if trade barriers were
lowered with the United States.
   ``I thought there was a certain amount of hysteria,'' Richler
said. ``I don't think the free trade deal is going to destroy the
CBC (Canadian Broadcasting Corp.) or Canadian publishing; if I
thought so, I would be against it.''
   Richler sees an ironic touch to his having taken positions that
made him anathema to hard-core Canadian nationalists and his now
having written ``a resoundingly Canadian novel.''
   He said his publishers seem to believe the material will be
considered exotic elsewhere and not be harmed by readers' lack of
knowledge about Canada. ``They think it's a very commercial
novel,'' he said.
   Richler lived in Europe, mostly in London, for two decades,
returning to his native Montreal in 1972.
   He also has worked as a screenwriter, including the screenplay
for ``The Apprenticeship of Duddy Kravitz,'' and written two
well-received children's books.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Weekend Editions, Jan. 5-7</NOTE>

</DOC>