<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0239 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0752EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-AutoLayoffs     12-22 0388</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Auto Layoffs,0401</SECOND>
<HEAD>Half of GM's Linden Plant Shutting Down Indefinitely in February</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FREDERICK STANDISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Auto Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   General Motors Corp. is eliminating one of two
shifts at a New Jersey car assembly plant, adding to the production
woes of the nation's auto industry.
   On Thursday, GM spokesman Phil Workman in Lansing said the
second shift at the automaker's Linden plant would stop production
Feb. 26 and about 1,600 workers would be laid off indefinitely. The
first shift will continue producing Chevrolet Corsica and Beretta
automobiles.
   Also on Thursday, GM and Chrysler Corp. added to their lists of
factories temporarily suspending production in January. That brings
to 42 of the Big Three's 53 U.S. assembly plants which will be down
for at least one week each next month.
   More than 127,000 workers will be affected.
   In addition to state unemployment benefits, laid-off workers can
draw on special funds that can boost their pay during factory
shutdowns to as much as 95 percent of their straight-time wages.
   The effect of the shutdowns on the country's auto industry
supply community is difficult to measure, and it's likely that
thousands of other workers could face temporary layoffs next month.
   All the assembly plant closings are caused by slumping sales and
high new-vehicle inventories.
   Demand for Corsica and Beretta cars, which are also produced in
Wilmington, Del., has been slipping. Sales this year through Dec.
10 were 12.7 percent behind last year's pace. GM's domestic car
sales, meantime, were off 8.3 percent for the same time.
   Combined inventory of the two cars _ essentially the same except
Beretta has two doors and Corsica has four _ stood at 123 days at
the end of November, based on the current selling pace according to
Ward's Automotive Reports, a weekly industry newsletter.
   Inventory for the eight major U.S. automakers stood at 88 days,
Ward's said.
   News of the Linden shutdown hit workers hard.
   ``It's no Merry Christmas when a person has been trying to dig
in with the company, working twice as hard, working with the
management, trying to sell the cars ourselves, putting our heart
into it,'' said United Auto Workers union Local 595 President
Charlie Marshall.
   ``To hear there's only one shift is a big letdown for
everybody,'' he added. ``We all feel like we've been had.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>