<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1559EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-WorldReax     12-24 0867</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-World Reax,0897</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hearts and Wallets Open For Romanian People; Soviet Intervention
Backed</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EDITH M. LEDERER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hearts and wallets opened all over the world for
the embattled Romanian people Sunday, and the United States and
France said they would not oppose Soviet bloc military intervention.
   The International Red Cross led new efforts to send in food and
medical aid, but fighting prevented most relief flights from
landing in Bucharest and many convoys were stalled at the borders.
   France said it was willing to help muster a ``brigade of
volunteers'' if asked to aid Romanians fighting security forces
loyal to ousted dictator Nicolae Ceausescu.
   Foreign Minister Roland Dumas said on radio station RTL that he
told Soviet officials if Moscow decided to intervene, France ``not
only would not object to it, but would support this action.''
   U.S. Secretary of State James Baker III said in a television
interview that the Romanians were fighting a ``repressive
dictatorship, so I think that we would be inclined probably to
follow the lead, follow the example of France, who today has said
that if the Warsaw Pact felt it necessary to intervene on behalf of
the opposition that it would support that.''
   The Dutch government said military intervention would ``support
the aspirations of the Romanian people,'' but it recognized the
``enormous dilemma'' over the issue, given the bitter memories of
past Soviet interventions in East bloc countries.
   But Soviet Premier Nikolai Ryzhkov on Saturday all but ruled out
military Soviet intervention. Moscow has mobilized humanitarian
aid, and the Soviet news agency Tass reported Sunday that trains
were massing on the Soviet-Romanian border with medical supplies,
food and clothes.
   Hungarian radio said 250 trucks and an equal number of cars
loaded with medicine, bandages and food reached Romania from
neighboring Hungary but that little was getting through the
country's other borders.
   An East German aircraft carrying medical supplies landed at an
unidentified Romanian airport Sunday, the East German news agency
ADN reported.
   Public collections went up in virtually every country of Eastern
and Western Europe.
   In Sofia, the Bulgarian capital, Communist Party officials
donated party membership fees for the month of December to
suffering Romanian families.
   The British Red Cross said it collected $80,000 in just 24 hours.
   Sweden pledged $3.1 million in assistance.
   The Portuguese Red Cross said it collected donations over the
weekend and would send 30 aid workers with a planeload of food and
medicine to Romania.
   Queen Margrethe II of Denmark decided to return decorations she
received from Ceausescu, news reports said. On Friday, Britain's
Queen Elizabeth II stripped Ceausescu of his honorary knighthood.
   In Tripoli, Libya, students marched ``in support for and
solidarity with the Romanian people's revolution,'' the official
news agency JANA said.
   They handed a petition to the Romanian Embassy saying events in
Romania ``show the falsehood and failure of the goverment idea,
parties, the tyranny and oppression as well as dictatorship,'' JANA
said.
   Grigor Gysi, the East German Communist leader, welcomed the
Ceausescu government's ouster, saying in a statement carried by
ADN: ``Its monstrous anti-human terrorism, slaughter and bloodshed
prove once again that the regime of the Ceausescu clan has nothing,
absolutely nothing to do with socialism.''
   At least 23 Romanian embassies switched allegiance to the new
provisional government, and three states recognized the National
Salvation Committee that claimed to control Romania.
   Romania's first deputy prime minister, Gheorghe Oprea, who was
in Turkey on an official visit when Ceausescu was toppled, told
reporters in Istanbul Saturday night that he rejoiced in Romania's
liberation.
   ``As a Romanian citizen, I will do everything I can for my
country. I support the freedom movement and will return to my
country to fight and work for the success of the new system,'' the
Anatolia news agency quoted him as saying.
   Archbishop of Canterbury Robert Runcie, spiritual leader of the
Church of England and head of the 70 million member Anglican
Communion, asked all congregations to pray for the Romanian people
at Christmas services.
   Prince Carol of Romania, half-brother of King Michael of Romania
who lives in Switzerland, was in the congregation at a special
service for London's Romanian community at the Russian Orthodox
Church in Kensington.
   ``We are here to remember those who have fallen,'' he said.
   ``It hurt me to see the pictures of violence coming out of
Romania, where they are trying to get rid of a madman who is only
there for his own benefit.''
   In Hong Kong, hundreds of people put wreaths in a downtown park
on Saturday to mourn Romania's dead and held a candle-lit rally.
   The Geneva-Based International Committee of the Red Cross said
an eight-member team that flew to Bucharest on Friday night
remained trapped in the airport vicinity with four tons of urgently
neeeded medical supplies. Spokesman Joerg Bischof said members have
cared for at least 600 wounded civilians and military since their
arrival.
   On Christmas Day, a DC-10 chartered by the Netherlands Red Cross
was to stop over at Geneva to pick up 60 tons of medical supplies
provided by the Swiss Red Cross.
   The French government sent two planeloads of medical supplies
and emergency medical teams to Romania.
</TEXT>

</DOC>