<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1200EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-DiplomaticMinuet     12-17 0484</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Diplomatic Minuet,480</SECOND>
<HEAD>Power Struggle Spills Over to Embassy in US</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RUTH SINAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Would Lebanon's real ambassador please stand
up?
   The request reflects the anomalous situation at the Lebanese
Embassy, where the battle for control of Lebanon is being
re-enacted between loyalists of embattled Christian Gen. Michel
Aoun and supporters of newly elected Lebanese President Elias Hrawi.
   Hrawi, who has fired Aoun from all his posts, last week removed
Lebanon's veteran ambassador to Washington, Abdallah Bouhabib, and
handed control of the embassy to the No. 2 diplomat, Sleiman Rassi.
   On Wednesday, the State Department said it had been informed by
Lebanon's new government that Bouhabib had resigned effective Dec.
11 and Rassi was now in charge. The Department said that since it
recognizes the Hrawi government as the legitimate ruler of Lebanon,
it would now deal only with Rassi.
   So far, so good.
   But Aoun _ who is holding out with 20,000 troops at the
presidential palace in Beirut and refuses to recognize the Hrawi
government _ sent Bouhabib a telex ordering him to stay put.
   ``Aoun says Bouhabib is the legitimate ambassador because he,
Aoun, is the legitimate ruler,'' said embassy spokesman Yousef
Sayah.
   So Bouhabib, a staunch Aoun backer, continues to occupy the
ambassador's office and residence.
   He argues that under foreign service regulations he is entitled
to a two-month transition period to put his affairs in order and
transfer the embassy to his successor.
   ``Even from a humanitarian point of view, you can't just tell
someone who has been in office six years to just leave
immediately,'' said Sayah.
   But Lebanon's Prime Minister, Salim al-Hoss, decided he could.
In recent months Bouhabib had made derogatory statements about
al-Hoss, and the Moslem leader demanded he cede his job
immediately, said Lebanese sources.
   Bouhabib, who owns a house in Washington and whose wife and
children are Americans, turned to his American and Arab friends for
help.
   He asked Ambassador Clovis Maksoud, the envoy of the 22-nation
Arab League, to intercede on his behalf with al-Hoss.
   Maksoud, a skilled diplomat, urged the new Lebanese government
to grant Bouhabib a two-month transition and avoid public
embarrassment, said the Lebanese sources.
   Bouhabib also controls the embassy's bank accounts and has
insisted he will retain control unless he is guaranteed a graceful
transition, they said.
   ``Then, too, he could be hoping that within two months Aoun may
gain control and he (Bouhabib) could stay,'' said one official who
spoke on condition of anonymity.
   All this leaves the State Department in a bind.
   The U.S. Embassy in Beirut has been shut for several months for
security reasons, and the main channel of communications with the
Hrawi government is through its ambassador here.
   ``We will deal with Rassi,'' said one American official, adding,
``We're not looking to chase Bouhabib out, but we have to go with
what the new government says.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>