<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0274 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1324EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-GNP 3rdLd-Writethru   12-20 0819</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-GNP, 3rd Ld-Writethru,0847</SECOND>
<HEAD>Economy Grew At an Annual Rate of 3 Percent July Through September</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Top 11 grafs new to include Fed actions; picks up at pvs 10th
graf, In a</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN D. McCLAIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.S. economy grew at an annual rate of 3
percent from July through September, the government said today, but
analysts say it has slowed dramatically during the fourth quarter.
   The economic deterioration has led many anlaysts to urge the
Federal Reserve to lower interest rates to stimulate the economy.
The central bank did add money to the banking system late Tuesday,
leading to the belief that it might permit interest rates to fall
again.
   In its final report on third-quarter economic activity, the
Commerce Department said the gross national product was revised
upward 0.3 percentage point from the 2.7 percent rate reported last
month.
   Many economists had predicted no change from November in the
figure released today.
   The change was attributed to another upward revision in net
exports and a downward revision in personal consumption.
   The GNP is the nation's total output of goods and services and
its broadest measure of economic health.
   The report bore good news for the Fed's goal of restraining
inflation. A price index tied to the GNP rose at an annual rate of
2.9 percent during the July-September period, unchanged from last
month's report.
   It is the Fed's high-interest policy that is blamed, in part,
for the fourth-quarter sluggishness, particularly in the automobile
and other manufacturing industries.
   The Federal Open Market Committee, the central bank's
policymaking arm, met privately Monday and Tuesday to consider
monetary policy but, as usual, did not announce whether it would
permit rates to continue to fall.
   However, the key federal funds rate, the interest banks charge
each other for overnight loans, dropped to 8 7-16 percent from
about 8{ percent late Tueday. Analysts said they expected a target
of 8\ percent for the rate.
   Besides manufacturing sluggishness, other disruptions in
fourth-quarter growth are expected from the Boeing aircraft strike,
the lingering effects of Hurricane Hugo and the San Francisco
Bay-area earthquake.
   In a companion report, the Commerce Department said after-tax
profits of U.S. corporations fell 5.4 percent in the third quarter.
That was a revision from the 7.2 percent decline reported last
month.
   Corporate profits have dropped for three consecutive quarters.
They were down 0.3 percent in the first quarter and 1.1 percent in
the second.
   Consumer spending, which accounts for two-thirds of all economic
activity, was revised to show a 5.6 percent growth rate compared to
the 6.2 percent gain reported last month.
   The various changes left the GNP expanding in the third quarter
at a seasonally adjusted annual rate of $4.16 trillion.
   Today's report was the third on the July-September GNP. In its
initial estimate in October, the Commerce Department said the
third-quarter economy would grow at a 2.5 percent annual rate.
   Last month's initial revision was due mainly to
better-than-expected trade performance. The September trade
deficit, which hit a five-year low, was not available when the
advance estimate was made in October.
   Today's revision reflects additional data that has become
available.
   While the economy surprised many analysts with its 3 percent
growth durin the first nine months of the year, it has declined
significantly this quarter and some economists fear it will drop
below 1 percent and perhaps even trip into a recession.
   The administration is forecasting a 2.7 percent growth rate for
all of 1989. The fourth-quarter GNP would have to advance 1.6
percent to meet that goal.
   Much of the growth in the third quarter was attributed to robust
automobile sales that were driven by sales incentives. Automakers
dropped the incentives with the introduction of 1990 models in
October and sales plummeted.
   But David Berson, chief economist for the Federal National
Mortgage Association, noted that incentives are being restored and
predicted a pickup in sales starting in January.
   The Fed's high-interest policy is intended to curb inflation. As
inflation appeared to moderate, the central bank has gradually
eased interest rates since last June.
   But many economists say rates still are too high and are
stifling growth, even threatening an end to an unprecedented seven
years of peacetime growth.
   ``Fourth-quarter growth is about 0.8 percent,'' said Donald
Ratajczak, economic forecasting director at Georgia State
University. He said growth in the first three months of 1990 will
be about 1 percent.
   ``But I'm expecting a couple of prime rate cuts, and if we don't
see them we might turn our forecast to the negative,'' he said.
   Robert Brusca, chief financial economist for Nikko Securities
Co. International Inc., also suggested the Fed should consider
further easing interest rates.
   ``I think the Fed will have to move to reduce interest rates in
order to keep the economy going next year, but I think they're
going to have to do it slowly,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>