<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0237 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0314EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-AirFares     12-29 0401</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Air Fares,0416</SECOND>
<HEAD>Major Airlines Cut Fares in Selected Markets</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCY GORDON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   In an effort to lure passengers during the slow winter months,
the nation's big airlines are lowering fares as much as 30 percent
in selected markets.
   The fare reductions, in effect through early March, only apply
to about 10 percent of the airlines' route networks _ but they
involve densely traveled routes. The move was started by Midway
Airlines, which announced last Saturday one-way fares ranging from
$19 to $99 across its 50-city route system within the continental
United States.
   United Airlines followed suit Wednesday, and United's cuts were
quickly matched in the same markets by Northwest Airlines and Trans
World Airlines. Spokesmen for American Airlines, Delta Air Lines
and Continental Airlines said Thursday those carriers have matched
the move.
   ``We've got to be competitive,'' said Ed Stewart, a spokesman
for American at its headquarters outside Fort Worth, Texas.
   American, the nation's largest airline, will cut fares to about
40 cities from Chicago. That compares with its total network of
about 1,200 markets.
   American's round-trip fares between Los Angeles and New York,
for example, will be cut to $278-$318 from $398-$438. Between
Boston and Nashville, Tenn., fares will drop to $178-$198 from
$238-$278.
   The discounts affect flights between New York, Boston and Los
Angeles and other cities in the continental United States. Arizona,
Florida and Nevada are excluded.
   Analysts said the historical winter slowdown in air travel,
which is expected to be worse than usual this year, motivated the
fare discounts. They are aimed mostly at vacationers, who can meet
the requirements for advance purchase and minimum stays.
   ``We knew that the fourth (1989) and the first (1990) quarters
were going to be very sloppy for this industry,'' said Edward
Starkman, an airline analyst at PaineWebber Inc. in New York.
   The last major change in fares was in early December, when the
big airlines raised discount MaxSaver fares _ but softened the blow
by eliminating advance-purchase requirements for the popular
tickets during the holiday period.
   Last week, Southwest Airlines cut prices on its longer routes, a
move other carriers followed on a limited basis.
   The new fare reductions require a 14-day advance purchase and a
Saturday night stay.
   Passengers wanting to use the lower fares must make reservations
by Jan. 31. The fares are available only on a round-trip basis and
aren't refundable.
</TEXT>

</DOC>