<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1335EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Panama-delCid 2ndLd-Writethru a0533 12-26 0531</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-del Cid, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0533,0541</SECOND>
<HEAD>Panamanian Officer Called One of Noreiga's `Righthand Men' Pleads
Innocent</HEAD>
<BYLINE>Eds: LEADS with 6 grafs to UPDATE with del Cid pleading innocent,
quote, Jan. 2 hearing scheduled. Pickup 4th graf, `We are...' ^By MICHAEL
WARREN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Panamanian officer accused of helping deposed
dictator Manuel Antonio Noriega smuggle cocaine for the Medellin
cartel was jailed in Florida today after surrendering in Panama,
the Justice Department said.
   Lt. Col. Luis del Cid, who commanded a Panama Defense Forces
unit in the province of Chiriqui, was placed in the custody of U.S.
Drug Enforcement Administration agents after he surrendered
Saturday, said Deborah Burstion-Wade, an agency spokeswoman in
Washington.
   He was flown to the United States under tight security Monday
and held at the federal Metropolitan Correctional Center south of
Miami, Ms. Burstion-Wade said.
   Del Cid pleaded innocent to drug-related charges today before
U.S. District Judge William Hoeveler and was ordered held without
bond pending a Jan. 2 hearing.
   Del Cid, 46, repeated his claim that he turned himself in to
fight the charges. ``I surrender myself. I wanted to be brought
here,'' he told the judge through a translator.
   Frank Rubino, one of Noriega's attorneys, said he came to the
court session today to monitor the situation and arrange to speak
with del Cid, who is now represented by a public defender. Rubino
said he does not think he will defend del Cid.
   ``We are confident that we have the evidence to convict him,''
U.S. Attorney Dexter Lehtenin said at a news conference this
morning before heading to del Cid's first court appearance.
   Lehtenin described del Cid as one of Noriega's ``righthand men''
and said he was the ousted Panamanian leader's liaison, courier and
emissary in drug trafficking deals with Colombian drug lords.
   Del Cid was one of 15 Noriega associates named in an indictment
unsealed Feb. 5, 1988, by a federal grand jury in Miami. He was
wanted on four counts related to cocaine possession and laundering
drug profits, the spokeswoman said.
   According to the indictment, del Cid acted as a liaison and
money courier between Colombia's Medellin cartel and Noriega. The
indictment accused Noriega of accepting a $4.6 million bribe from
the organization to protect shipments of cocaine, launder money,
supply drug laboratories and shield drug traffickers from the law.
   A federal grand jury in Tampa indicted Noriega on charges of
taking a separate $5.4 million bribe from the Colombia drug cartel.
   If convicted on all counts, del Cid could be sentenced to 70
years in prison and fined $550,000, according to Lehtinen's office.
   After del Cid's surrender, he declared loyalty to the government
of Guillermo Endara, installed as president last week after U.S.
troops invaded Panama to remove Noriega from power.
   He remained in custody in the Central American country until DEA
agents escorted him to Miami.
   ``Normally he would have been flown in by U.S. marshals, but
this was not an ordinary case,'' Ms. Burstion-Wade said.
   The Justice Department has said that if Noriega is brought to
the United States, he would be tried first in Miami because the
prosecutors' case there was stronger than in Tampa.
</TEXT>

</DOC>