<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0157 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1819EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-SavannahRiver     12-18 0343</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Savannah River,340</SECOND>
<HEAD>Watkins Adds New Condition to Restarting Nuclear Reactors</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In a concession to environmentalists, the
Energy Department will not restart its Savannah River defense
nuclear reactors until an environmental impact study is completed,
according to a department letter obtained Monday.
   It was not immediately clear whether the decision would mean a
further delay in restarting the three reactors, which were shut
down last year to undergo massive safety upgrades, worker
retraining and management restructuring.
   The first of the reactors, the nation's only source of tritium
needed to make nuclear warheads, is tentatively scheduled to resume
production next fall.
   Energy Secretary James D. Watkins told members of the House and
Senate armed services committees in letters sent Friday that he
decided to drop the department's objection to completing the
environmental study before restarting the reactors.
   The department had agreed a study was needed, but maintained
there was no legal requirement to finish it before resuming tritium
production.
   ``Because the decision-making process will be enhanced by the
information and opportunity for public comment presented by the EIS
(environmental impact study), the department will complete the EIS
before it makes any decision to resume'' production, Watkins wrote.
   A copy of the letter was released by the office of Rep. James
Hansen, R-Utah, a committee member.
   Department spokesman Will Callicott said he could not
immediately comment on the decision except to say an environmental
impact statement is being developed and is tentatively scheduled
for completion in August.
   Three national environmental groups _ Greenpeace, the Natural
Resources Defense Council and the Energy Research Foundation _ sued
the Energy Department in December 1988 seeking to force completion
of the study before restart.
   Dan Reicher, an attorney for the Natural Resources Defense
Council, said his group had not seen details of Watkins' decision
but that it appeared the Energy Department had conceded defeat.
   ``It appears to us we've had a major victory,'' Reicher said.
``It looks as though the Energy Department has seen the error of
its ways.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>