<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0164 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1859EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-AirControllers     12-20 0511</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Air Controllers,490</SECOND>
<HEAD>Air Controllers Give 14 Facilities Low Marks for Safety</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID BRISCOE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Air traffic controllers at 14 facilities near
the East and West coasts give their operations the lowest marks for
safety and other concerns, a congressional report said Wednesday.
   The report, by the General Accounting Office, ranked controller
operations around the country according to responses from Federal
Aviation Administration controllers to an extensive 1988 survey.
The survey showed widespread concern over operations of the system
that guides all aircraft over the United States.
   A significant number of the 5,000 FAA controllers who responded
anonymously saw problems. Eighty-five percent perceived a shortage
of fully qualified controllers, 65 percent said they handled too
much traffic in peak hours, a majority were concerned about the
quality of training and 43 percent said their morale was low.
   The aggregate results of the survey had been previously
released, but the new report ranked 84 facilities according to the
percentage of employees giving negative responses on each of
several key questions.
   It says Boston and Washington FAA centers had the most negative
responses on key questions of workload, facility staffing,
overtime, training, safety and morale, while centers in
Albuquerque, Houston and Minneapolis had the fewest.
   Twelve airport facilities with the most negative responses were:
Baltimore-Washington; Boston; Burbank, Calif.; Kennedy Tower, N.Y.;
Miami; New York traffic control center; Oakland, Calif.; Ontario,
Calif., traffic control center; Orlando, Fla.; Philadelphia;
Phoenix traffic control center, and Washington National.
   Those with the fewest negative responses were Cleveland; Hebron,
Ky.; Jacksonville, Fla.; Lubbock, Texas; Milwaukee; Minneapolis;
Phoenix airport; Sacramento, Calif.; St. Louis traffic control
center; Tampa, Fla., and West Palm Beach, Fla.
   All other surveyed facilities fell into a middle category, with
a mix of negative and positive responses to the six key questions.
   ``The FAA should be asking people (at the lowest-rated centers)
why they think their center is performing so poorly,'' said Rep.
Guy Molinari, R-N.Y., who released the GAO rankings.
   Molinari, who is leaving Congress at the end of the year to
become borough president in Staten Island, N.Y., said controllers's
views should be ``key to resolving the chronic problems in the air
traffic control system.''
   He said high-ranking centers and terminals also should be
studied to see why employees rate them so well.
   Kenneth Mead, GAO director for transportation issues, said the
report has been well received by the FAA and should be a useful
tool in improving operations.
   In response to the report, the FAA said its system is safe and
improvements have been made since the survey was taken, including
an increase in the number of controllers by about 400 to 14,822 as
of Nov. 30.
   ``The GAO data is not fully consistent with results of our own
surveys which show continuing improvements in job satisfaction
areas,'' spokesman John Leyden said. The FAA surveyed employees in
1984, 1986 and 1988, he said.
   Leyden said, however, the agency would use the GAO data ``to see
if there's any new information here to help us improve the system.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>