<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0088 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1407EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-MailBombs 1stLd-Writethru a0482 12-21 0731</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mail Bombs, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0482,0746</SECOND>
<HEAD>Precede MOUNTAIN BROOK</HEAD>
<HEAD>FBI Looks at Civil Rights Litigation in Investigating Mail Bombs</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 14 grafs to UPDATE with Georgia lawyers questioned,
possible link to Air Force bias case. PICKS UP 4th graf, `Vance, a....'
DELETES final 10 grafs to tighten. Changes byline.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto XBM4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATRICIA WALSH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The FBI pressed the search for links between a
series a parcel bombs in the South and civil rights litigation,
reportedly questioning a Georgia lawyer about a 14-year-old racial
discrimination case.
   The FBI emphasized its investigation of the mail bombs that
killed a federal judge and a civil rights lawyer remained
open-ended.
   In Macon, attorney Charles A. Mathis said Wednesday that the FBI
questioned one of his associates about a case in which his firm's
clients won a $3.75 million settlement over discrimination at
Robins Air Force Base in Warner Robins. Mathis declined to name the
fellow lawyer or detail what he was asked.
   Another lawyer, Henry Grady Smith of Warner Robins, said he was
surprised to learn that his name was on the return address of a
package bomb sent to the NAACP office in Jacksonville, Fla. That
bomb was defused Tuesday.
   ``I've never represented their organization. I'm not a civil
rights attorney,'' he said, adding that he was interviewed by the
FBI about the package Tuesday.
   ``I've never dealt with anybody in Jacksonville. I can't figure
out why anybody would use my name.''
   Earlier this week, a government source said the bomb that killed
U.S. Circuit Judge Robert S. Vance in Birmingham, Ala., on Saturday
bore the return address of a fellow judge who regularly sent Vance
packages.
   FBI spokesman Diader Rosario in Atlanta said agents have
interviewed everyone whose name appeared on the parcels, but ``we
do not consider them suspects or involved in any way, shape or
form.''
   FBI agent Jerry Shockley of Montgomery, Ala., said the bombs _
the two fatal bombs plus unexploded ones found at the 11th U.S.
Circuit Court of Appeals in Atlanta and a NAACP office in
Jacksonville, Fla. _ may have been sent by a racist group in
response to NAACP school desegregation lawsuits.
   Mississippi lawyer Richard Barrett, leader of a white
supremacist group called the Nationalist Movement, said he does not
think anyone in his or similar groups is to blame.
   ``I believe them to be the work of a deranged lunatic, that is
my first impression,'' Barrett said. ``I think that the American
people should not be stampeded by the liberal knee-jerk hysteria
that seems to be emanating from various quarters, including the
FBI.''
   The FBI today said it was installing 24-hour tip lines in
Birmingham, Ala., Jacksonville, Fla., and Atlanta to seek clues in
the investigation.
   In Birmingham, a telephoned bomb threat today forced evacuation
of a building that includes the office of the U.S. Bankruptcy Court
judge who gave the eulogy for Vance on Wednesday. No explosive was
found, U.S. Marshal Tom Greene said.
   National and local judicial figures were among more than 700
mourners at a memorial service for Vance in a church guarded by
dozens of police officers and checked by dogs trained to smell for
bombs.
   Vance, a member of the 11th Circuit and a former chairman of the
Alabama Democratic Party, was killed instantly Saturday in his home
when he opened a package and the bomb exploded, sending finishing
nails into his lower abdomen. The bomb also wounded his wife.
   Two days later, another package bomb killed Robert E. Robinson,
a black lawyer in Savannah, Ga. A third bomb was found was found in
the court building that houses the 11th Circuit in Atlanta and a
fourth in the headquarters of the NAACP in Jacksonsville, Fla.
Those two bombs were defused.
   U.S. Bankruptcy Judge Clifford Fulford of Birmingham delivered
the eulogy for his close friend. He asked the mourners to ``put
aside our outrage for a while'' to honor Vance.
   ``The assassins were cheated if they thought that Bob Vance was
afraid to die,'' Fulford said.
   Vance's life, Fulford said, ``was the antithesis of our grief, a
life of fullness and gusto.''
   He described Vance as a strong believer in the law and a man
``who stood up for the underdog and the oppressed. ... No wonder
his assassins could not stand such a man in their presence.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>