<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0203 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1741EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-LincolnAccountant 2ndLd-Writethru f0190 12-26 0880</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lincoln Accountant, 2nd Ld-Writethru, f0190,0904</SECOND>
<HEAD>Account Hired By Thrift After Vouching for S&amp;L's Solvency</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 5th graf pvs, `Atchison could... with lawyer saying Atchison
won't speak to reporters; SUBS 6th graf pvs, `By a 2-1... to fix typo in
`few'; PICKS UP 7th graf pvs, `By the...; Version moved on general news
wires</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LARRY MARGASAK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three days before federal bank regulators
approved a delay in seizing Lincoln Savings and Loan in May 1988,
the private accountant whose audits influenced the decision
switched jobs and went to work for the thrift's owner, according to
documents and interviews.
   The two regulators whose votes delayed the seizure for a year
say they did not know at the time that the accountant, Jack D.
Atchison, had taken the new job _ said by one member of Congress to
pay $900,000 annually.
   But in recent statements, former Federal Home Loan Bank Board
chairman M. Danny Wall and board member Roger F. Martin said their
decision concerning the fate of Lincoln _ the nation's costliest
thrift failure _ might have been different if they had been
informed.
   ``Certainly, it would have had an effect on the decision had he
known,'' said Karl Hoyle, an aide to Wall. ``Could it have swung
the other way (in favor of immediate seizure)? Maybe.''
   Attempts to reach Atchison for comment proved futile. His lawyer
also declined to discuss the matter, first reported by The Arizona
Republic, and said that Atchison would not talk about it with
reporters.
   By a 2-1 vote on May 5, 1988, the three-member bank board
decided against a recommendation from San Francisco regulators to
seize the troubled savings and loan. The group decided instead to
launch a new federal examination of the thrift's books. The effect
of the decision was to permit the bank to continue operating for an
additional year under the ownership of Charles H. Keating Jr.
   By the time the regulators ousted Keating and took control on
April 14, 1989, the cost of protecting depositors had soared, and
may now total more than $2 billion.
   Wall earlier this month resigned as head of the bank board's
single-administrator agency, the Office of Thrift Supervision,
under pressure from Congress because of his handling of the Lincoln
case. He remains in the job until a successor is named.
   The delay in seizing Lincoln generated a barrage of news stories
about Keating, especially the $1.3 million he and associates
contributed to campaigns and causes of five senators who intervened
with the regulators on his behalf.
   The Senate Ethics Committee has begun a formal investigation to
determine whether the intervention was linked to the money. All the
senators have denied any wrongdoing.
   Since 1986, favorable audit reports on Lincoln had been written
by Atchison, who was managing partner in the Phoenix office of the
large accounting firm of Arthur Young _ now Ernst &amp; Young.
   Bradley Boland, Keating's spokesman, said Atchison began working
for Lincoln's parent firm _ American Continental Corp. of Phoenix _
on May 2, 1988, three days before the crucial meeting of the bank
board. House Banking Committee Chairman Henry B. Gonzalez, D-Texas,
said Atchison's salary with American Continental was $900,000 a
year.
   An Arthur Young memo confirmed the timing of the job change,
saying that Atchison ``decided to accept a position with American
Continental Corp. effective May 1, 1988.''
   Last Nov. 7, Atchison refused to answer questions before
Gonzalez' committee, claiming a Fifth Amendment constitutional
right against self-incrimination.
   At the time Atchison switched jobs, the San Francisco-based
regulators were telling the bank board that Lincoln was in such
serious trouble that it should be taken over by the government.
   But Atchison's audits, according to a transcript of the bank
board's May 5, 1988 meeting, concluded that the thrift had enough
reserves to cover losses and had met net worth requirements.
   Faced with the differing opinions, the bank board conducted its
2-1 vote to freeze Lincoln's level of investments, transfer the
bank board investigation from San Franciso to Washington and begin
a new probe of the Irvine, Calif. thrift.
   Wall and Martin voted in the majority, while board member
Lawrence J. White constituted a single-vote minority who favored
immediate government seizure.
   Martin said in an interview that he didn't know that Atchison
had gone to work for American Continental three days before the
meeting. He said he ``would have been concerned'' had he known, and
``absolutely'' would have raised questions about the impartiality
of the audits.
   ``We were were very dependent on the accountant's opinion,'' he
said.
   Wall spokesman Hoyle said his boss ``did not have any
knowledge'' of the job change.
   ``At a minimum, he would have wanted to go back and check with
Arthur Young,'' Hoyle said. ``No doubt we would have looked at
things differently, because it would have made the data suspect.
It's a significant factor if you knew perhaps these numbers were
tainted.''
   D. Jeffrey Hirschberg, associate general counsel for Ernst &amp;
Young, said, ``We clearly have no evidence (Atchison) committed any
impropriety when he was a partner at Arthur Young.''
   ``We have partners that leave all the time for better-paying
jobs in industry,'' he said. ``It's not unusual. Just because Jack
left does not mean the audit was improper.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>