<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0228 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2209EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CarnegieHeroes     12-20 0689</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Carnegie Heroes,0711</SECOND>
<HEAD>Carnegie Hero Commission Honors 20 Heroes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM STRADER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Phoenix police officer Russell E. Dean was
staring down the barrel of his own revolver, held by a 16-year-old
who threatened to kill him after being stopped for speeding, when a
passerby intervened.
   John W. Basey stopped his car, grabbed the assailant, pulled him
off the policeman and then found himself facing the cocked and
loaded gun.
   Basey, a 40-year-old window washer, was one of 20 people honored
Wednesday by the Pittsburgh-based Carnegie Hero Fund Commission for
risking their lives attempting to save others. Unlike Basey, some
of them were honored posthumously.
   Those honored, each of whom receives a $2,500 cash reward and a
medal, bring to 111 the number recognized this year. The
organization has honored 7,405 Americans and Canadians since
industrialist Andrew Carnegie established the commission in 1904.
   Dean said Wednesday the 16-year-old he chased last July reached
speeds of 80 mph on Phoenix's streets before crashing his car into
a tree.
   When Dean stopped to apprehend the boy, the youth turned on the
motorcycle officer and fell on him. The boy pulled Dean's
.38-caliber pistol from his holster.
   ``He put the gun right to my left eye and he said he was going
to kill me,'' Dean said.
   Then Basey arrived. ``Mr. Basey walked right up in the face of
that gun that could have gone off at any time,'' Dean said. ``I
believe Mr. Basey saved my life.''
   Basey talked the 16-year-old into releasing the gun, and Dean
handcuffed the boy and arrested him. Dean suffered only a sprained
knee and scrapes.
   Also recognized Wednesday were:
   _Derek Lambert, 16, of Andrews, S.C., who saved a man who had
fallen from a boat and severely cut his hands on the propeller on
Oct. 9, 1988.
   _Milton E. Bradford, 32, of Newport, N.J., who died saving a
co-worker who was overcome by gas in a sewer shaft on Sept. 6, 1988.
   _Shirley Belle Viscusi, 58, Howick, Quebec, a nurse who died
trying to save a woman who suffocated in a home for the elderly
that had caught fire on July, 25, 1988.
   _Michael B. LaRiviere, 18, Rockaway, Ore., who died while
swimming to save a man caught in an ocean current on July 30.
   _Martin A. Benfield, 27, Lenoir, N.C., who nearly drowned
pulling two young boys out of the ocean after they had gotten into
water over the heads on June 14, 1988.
   _Leonard A. Theroux, 65, Chepachet, R.I., who pulled a man from
his burning auto before the vehicle became engulfed in flames on
Feb. 18.
   _Aaron Lorne Clark, 25, Magdalen Islands, Quebec, who drowned
while helping to save a 13-year-old girl in the Gulf of St.
Lawrence on Aug. 21, 1986.
   _Jerry L. Conrad, 35, Toledo, Ohio, who leaped into a moving car
to save a 2-year-old girl on Sept. 23, 1987.
   _Jerry O. Anderson, 35, Tulsa, Okla., who drowned while saving a
12-year-old boy who had fallen from a dam into deep water on May 27.
   _Allen N. Davidson, 13, Gaffney, S.C., who crawled into a
burning house and dragged an elderly woman to safety on Nov. 19,
1988.
   _Michael Ollins, 33, Chicago, a bus driver who left his vehicle
and stopped a group of young men from beating a man on a crowded
city street on Aug. 20, 1987.
   _Claude Cleroux, 50, Montreal; Serge Perron, 38, Repentigny,
Quebec; and Robert K. Myles, 37, St. Hillaire, Quebec, all of whom
helped save a co-worker trapped beneath a crumbling wall after an
explosion in an oil refinery on December 16, 1986.
   _Scott Walter Asson, 20, Burley, Idaho, who broke a car window
and pulled a woman free just before the car was submerged in a
flooded wash in Scottsdale, Ariz., on Oct. 14, 1988.
   _Donat Pelletier, 43, and Guy Bernier, 41, both of Ste.
Felicite, Quebec; and Denis Blanchet, 42, and Rejean Miville, 35,
both of St. Pamphile, Quebec, who crossed the partially frozen
surface of the St. John River to rescue a co-worker trapped in a
bridge that was carried downstream April 1, 1986.
</TEXT>

</DOC>