<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0159 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 2011EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Bush 3rdLd-Writethru a0638 12-29 0957</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0638,890</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fitzwater Refuses To Get Into Argument With Vatican Over Noriega</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS penultimate graf with two grafs to tupdate with Bush arrival
in Houston</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER CONNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CORPUS CHRISTI, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bush administration on Friday
rejected a Vatican claim that the United States is ``an occupying
power'' in Panama, while acknowledging that the diplomatic standoff
over deposed dictator Manuel Antonio Noriega is likely to persist.
   Presidential press secretary Marlin Fitzwater said the Vatican
was ``doing a fine job'' in handling the Noriega situation. He said
the United States must ``calmly go along'' while Roman Catholic
Church officials decide what do about Noriega, who has been holed
up at the Vatican Embassy in Panama City since Christmas Eve.
   But State Department spokesman Richard Boucher, reflecting
mounting tensions between Washington and Vatican City, took issue
with a Vatican description of the United States as an occupation
force in Panama.
   ``We are down there with the consent of the government of
Panama, the legitimately elected leaders of Panama,'' Boucher said.
``That means we're not an occupying power.''
   Fitzwater, however, said talks with Roman Catholic Church
officials were proceeding in ``a positive vein.'' He declined to
get into an argument with Vatican City about U.S. actions in and
around the embassy where Noriega has been holed up.
   The press secretary answered questions about the diplomatic and
legal jockeying as Bush, some 60 miles away in Beeville, Texas,
wound up three days of hunting and fishing.
   Fitzwater's remarks appeared aimed at soothing increasingly
harsh exchanges between the Vatican and the United States over
Noriega, who took refuge in the Vatican Embassy on Christmas Eve.
That was five days after Bush ordered U.S. military invasion forces
into Panama.
   Fitzwater said he did not know whether U.S. troops, ringing the
Vatican embassy where Noriega is hiding in Panama City, would stop
bombarding the building with nerve-shattering rock-and-roll music.
   At the Vatican earlier, spokesman Joaquin Navarro had complained
about the activities of U.S. troops who have surrounded the Panama
City embassy to prevent Noriega from slipping away.
   ``An occupying power cannot interfere with the works of a
diplomatic mission nor can it demand that a person seeking asylum
in that mission be handed over to it,'' Navarro said.
   Asked about this Friday, Fitzwater said, ``The Vatican's doing a
fine job. ... We appreciate their efforts. We continue to work with
them in a very positive way. We think that they've taken a very
serious and constructive role in this episode.''
   Navarro did say the papal nuncio in Panama City was trying to
convince Noriega to quit his refuge.
   The United States wants Noriega handed over to stand trial on
two drug trafficking indictments. The decision to militarily
intervene on Dec. 20 ended a two-year standoff in which the U.S.
government had sought with words and economic sanctions to topple
Noriega, who had thwarted efforts to restore democratic rule in the
Central American country.
   Fitzwater also said he wasn't upset about a report in The
Washington Times Friday, which said an errant phone call from the
State Department to the U.S. Embassy in Panama City could have
tipped eavesdropping Panamanians to the U.S. invasion 48 hours in
advance.
   ``No one seems to know whether it's true or not,'' he said.
Fitzwater said that Noriega had ``an extensive intelligence
operation.'' But he added that ``it's history now.''
   Summing up where things stood nearly a week after the United
States and the Vatican commenced talks about Noriega, Fitzwater
said, ``We can't predict how long it will take'' to resolve the
custody issue.
   ``This matter has to play out,'' he said. `` ... We'll just
calmly go along.''
   ``It's a very difficult situation, very tense circumstances,''
Fitzwater added. ``They are managing a difficult situation on the
ground there in Panama. They have been very cooperative with us
certainly and with other countries in trying to resolve the issue.''
   ``So our interest is in establishing a harmonious
relationship,'' the spokesman said.
   Asked whether the United States would seek to physically prevent
Noriega's removal to a third country, Fitzwater said, ``We won't
speculate. We'd like to have him in the United States.''
   Fitzwater also would disclose nothing about which of Noriega's
cronies have left the Vatican embassy. ``There's just not much that
we have to say or want to say while this is going on,'' he said.
   ``There are some things we don't know and there's some things we
know and just won't tell you. We just don't think it's helpful,''
the spokesman said.
   Earlier, Bush sent ``warm'' congratulations from Beeville to
Vaclav Havel on his election as president of Czechoslovakia, and
pledged U.S. support for the rebirth of democracy in the East
European nation.
   The White House said the election of the once dissident
playwright ``marks a fitting end to a year of astonishing change in
Eastern Europe.''
   Later the president flew to Houston, where he will remain
through New Year's Day, and dined with national security adviser
Brent Scowcroft and first lady Barbara Bush. Fitzwater said the
president had nothing to report on Panama but likely would get a
full briefing from Scowcroft.
   Bush and his party bagged 20 quail during his 2{-day hunting
vacation onb the Lazy F ranch owned by his long-time friend Will
Farish, Fiztwater said. Secretary of State James A. Baker III
caught a 19-pound turkey which, cleaned and dressed, Bush and Baker
brought with them on the flight to Houston.
   The Bushes will make a sidetrip Sunday to two military hospitals
in San Antonio to visit servicemen wounded in Panama. The president
will stop in Montgomery, Ala., to go bass fishing on New Year's Day
before returning to the White House late Monday.
</TEXT>

</DOC>