<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0115 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1702EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-HairyQueenMary Bjt   12-27 0583</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hairy Queen Mary, Bjt,0596</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mustache Wearers Rock the Boat at the Queen Mary</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL FLEEMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Disney let Captain Hook and Captain Nemo wear
mustaches, but First Officer John Magness of the Queen Mary _ the
only real-life seaman of the three _ was ordered Wednesday to shave
it off or ship out.
   Magness, the No. 3 officer on the Disney-operated ship, was sent
home on a one-day suspension for violating the Walt Disney Co.'s
grooming policy, which forbids beards and mustaches.
   If Magness goes ahead with plans to keep his mustache, by next
week he will have run out of suspensions and will join three other
crew members _ two waiters and a busboy _ who were fired for
wearing mustaches.
   ``It's a matter of principle,'' said Magness, 65, whose mustache
is little more than a thin grey tuft. ``I've had that mustache for
42 years now. My wife wants me to keep it. My kids have not seen me
without it. So there it stays.''
   The policy is so strict that company founder, the mustachioed
Walt Disney, would be in violation, along with many famous Disney
characters, from Uncle Remus to six of the seven dwarfs. Much of
Minnie Mouse's wardrobe would be too gaudy for Disney.
   Magness, who wore his mustache in the Navy through 13
engagements in World War II and three engagements in the Korean
War, summed up his feelings for the policy in two words:
   ``It stinks.''
   The flap was the latest in several disputes over what critics
have called Disney's overly conservative practices. The
Burbank-based company, for instance, lost its battle to ban
homosexuals from dancing together at Disneyland.
   The 35-year-old grooming policy just went into effect his month
at the Disney-operated Queen Mary, permanently docked in Long Beach
Harbor, 25 miles south of Los Angeles. Two of the employees were
fired Christmas Eve.
   Disney bought the leasehold to the Queen Mary two years ago,
along with the adjacent Spruce Goose plane, built by Howard Hughes,
a billionaire with a mustache. The ship is run as an attraction,
and officers such as Magness basically are in charge of answering
visitors' questions.
   The grooming policy, which applies to all park and hotel
employees, bans mustaches, beards and long hair on men. Bright eye
shadow, red fingernails or two-toned hair on women are also
forbidden.
   Queen Mary spokesman Rich Kerlin said that enforcing the policy
was a matter of keeping the Disney empire consistent, although he
would not say why the company was so strict on facial hair.
   ``It's just that it's been a policy for 35 years,'' he remarked,
adding that Disney himself instituted the policy.
   ``If we allowed the Queen Mary employees to have mustaches, we'd
have to let the entire theme park and resort employees do the
same,'' the spokesman said.
   Kerlin said that the only exceptions to the no-mustache rule
were if an employee needed one for ``medical reasons.''
   So far, 90 of the 100 men with mustaches agreed to shave them
off. Others, like Reza Nazertehrani and Tom Nicolai, refused. They
were fired Dec. 24 from their jobs as waiters and plan to protest
the policy with their union.
   ``I feel I have a right as a person to live in the United States
_ a free country _ and to not shave my mustache,'' said
Nazertehrani. ``I am Iranian. It is part of my culture. We are very
proud to have a mustache.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>