<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0008EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-US-Panama Bjt   12-25 0984</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-Panama, Bjt,980</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Still Wants to Bring Noriega to Justice</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WX6</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER CONNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The hunt for Manuel Antonio Noriega is over,
but President Bush still is searching for ways to bring the
ex-Panamanian dictator to justice even though he is now closeted in
the Vatican ambassador's home, a White House spokesman says.
   Bush learned at Camp David late Sunday afternoon, shortly after
returning from a Pentagon briefing, that Noriega had surfaced
seeking asylum at the residence of the papal nuncio in Panama City
after five days on the run.
   The first reaction from White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater
was that Noriega's ``reign of terror is over.''
   But drug-trafficking indictments still hang over Noriega's head,
and U.S. authorities are weighing options for dealing with the
fugitive ex-dictator.
   Under international law, if the Vatican grants Noriega asylum,
U.S. forces cannot legally enter the papal embassy to arrest him.
   ``President Bush is gratified that General Noriega has been
located. ... The president is pleased that `Operation Just Cause'
is on course. The United States will continue to pursue avenues for
bringing General Noriega, now located, to justice,'' Fitzwater said.
   The Italian news agency ANSA quoted the papal nuncio in Panama
City, Monsignor Sebastiano Laboa, as indicating he would not hand
over Noriega to the United States or the new U.S.-backed government
in Panama.
   Sen. Jesse Helms, R-N.C., said late Sunday that sources in
Panama told him Noriega ``is seeking to be permitted to leave and
go to one of two or three countries, including Cuba.''
   Sources in Panama familiar with the situation told The
Associated Press that the papal nuncio had mentioned to other
diplomats the possibility of Noriega going to Spain or Cuba.
   Helms said he spoke to White House chief of staff John Sununu,
who ``tells me that they are in strenuous negotiations with the
Vatican, pointing out that he is not there for political reasons.
... I asked him if the prospects look good and he says they don't
look bad, because the church realizes how the people feel in
Panama.''
   Fitzwater said a high-ranking ``Deputies Committee'' led by
deputy national security adviser Robert Gates met Sunday afternoon
and night to discuss the options.
   ``We just can't speculate on any course of action for the
present,'' said Fitzwater. ``We still are pursuing ways to bring
him to justice.''
   Asked if anyone now would get the $1 million reward the United
States had offered for Noriega's capture, Fitzwater said, ``No, I
don't think so.''
   Defense Secretary Dick Cheney, who traveled to Panama on
Christmas Eve, learned en route that Noriega had sought asylum.
   ``I am delighted that General Noriega has finally been run to
ground,'' he said on arrival at Howard Air Force Base, four miles
west of Panama City.
   ``Now it is up to the lawyers and the diplomats to figure out
what is next,'' Cheney said. ``As far as I'm concerned, the
military has done its job.''
   Earlier, before getting the news, Bush promised stepped up
humanitarian aid for the beleaguered population of Panama City and
praised the performance of the 26,000 U.S. troops there as
``outstanding.''
   Bush had interrupted his own holiday weekend at Camp David, Md.,
to huddle with military chiefs at the Pentagon.
   He also delivered a radio address to U.S. armed forces around
the world, saying Americans possess ``the strength to confront
tyranny when we must. General Noriega is the latest one to learn
that lesson.''
   Bush departed the Pentagon flashing a thumbs-up sign and telling
reporters he sensed ``a real turnaround.''
   Even before Noriega surfaced, Bush and other U.S. officials were
cheered by the return of a semblance of order to Panama City's
streets and the surrender of four of Noriega's top military
commanders.
   Fitzwater said more than 20,000 weapons had been captured and
thousands of other arms turned in by members of the army Noriega
used to lead, the Panama Defense Forces. He said more than 1,000
former PDF soldiers have returned to duty in the country's new
security force. ``Law and order is being successfully restored and
signs of normal commercial life are beginning to emerge,'' said
Fitzwater.
   The shelves of stores across Panama City had been stripped bare
by looters in the lawless days after the Dec. 20 invasion that
toppled Noriega.
   Bush told reporters, ``The emphasis now is on cleaning up the
last parts of resistance, seeing that civilian government takes
over. Tranquility in the city is an important goal.''
   He said American troops are ``now putting a great deal of proper
emphasis on humanitarian concerns,'' including getting food and
medicine to the populace.
   Cheney said earlier Sunday on ABC's ``This Week with David
Brinkley'' that the U.S. forces ``still have a lot of work to do''
to restore order and put down the last resistance in Panama.
   But Noriega's decision to seek asylum removed Bush's biggest
worry: the fear that ``the crafty devil,'' as one U.S. general
called him, might be able to wage a prolonged guerilla war against
U.S. troops and the fledgling government of President Guillermo
Endara.
   Bush was staying at Camp David until Wednesday with his five
children and their families, including 11 grandchildren. He leaves
then for a five-day hunting and fishing trip to Texas and Alabama.
   He also planned to spend part of Sunday, New Year's Eve,
visiting servicemen wounded in Panama at military hospitals in San
Antonio, Texas.
   This Christmas Eve was the 45th anniversary of Bush's own return
home from the Pacific war front as a decorated Navy combat pilot
during World War II.
   Then, as now, he said, there are ``times when America must
sacrifice in the cause of peace.''
   ``In Panama, as in every other such test in our history,
Americans put their lives on the line for the basic values of
liberty and decency on which our nation is founded,'' the president
said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>