<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0814EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Lebanon     12-27 0435</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lebanon,0448</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lebanon Complains to U.N. About Israeli Attacks</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RIMA SALAMEH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lebanon said today it was lodging an
urgent complaint with the U.N. Security Council about Israel's
latest ground and air attacks that reportedly killed 12 people and
wounded 31.
   The attacks, which occurred 12 hours apart on Tuesday, destroyed
two guerrilla bases of the Communist Party in central and southern
Lebanon.
   Prime Minister Salim Hoss' office said instructions were being
transmitted to Lebanon's U.N. mission to complain of ``this blatant
aggression.'' The office said Lebanon would not ask for a council
debate.
   Israeli paratroopers backed by tanks and helicopter gunships
destroyed one guerrilla base in southeast Lebanon before dawn, and
warplanes blasted a command post of the same group at sunset
further to the north.
   Rescuers worked under spotlights overnight to dig out victims
from the rubble of the two-story command post in the coastal town
of Rmeile, 20 miles south of Beirut.
   Police said the final casualty toll of the Rmeile attack stood
at 10 killed and 28 wounded, the heaviest among Israel's 18 air
raids into Lebanon this year. Twenty-eight people have been killed
and 137 wounded in the 18 air strikes since Jan. 11.
   Two Communist guerrillas were killed and three wounded in the
earlier ground assault on the base in the southeastern village of
Nabi Safi.
   The assault, staged by 100 paratroopers backed by four tanks and
eight armored personnel carriers, was the Israeli army's heaviest
ground advance into Lebanon since an assault on the Syrian-backed
Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine-General Command on
Dec. 9, 1988.
   The attack force advanced from Israel's self-proclaimed border
zone, a two- to 15-mile wide buffer zone north of the Israeli
border, which Israel and the Israeli-allied South Lebanese Army
have controlled since 1982.
   The Communists have been blamed for several terrorist attacks in
Israel as well as the attempted assassination in November 1988 of
the South Lebanese Army commander.
   Elsewhere in southern Lebanon, rival Shiite Moslem militias
battled into a fifth day today in southern Lebanon.
   Police said eight people were killed and 37 wounded in artillery
and tank fire duels Tuesday and early today between the
fundamentalist Hezbollah and the Syrian-backed Amal militia. That
raised the overall toll to 46 killed and 187 wounded since the
current round of fighting began Saturday.
   The two factions have been vying for mastery of Lebanon's 1.2
million Shiites, the country's largest sect, for more than two
years.
   The overall toll of the intermittent power struggle since May
1987 stands at 617 killed and 1,766 wounded.
</TEXT>

</DOC>