<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0179 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1249EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-YE--Deaths1989 Adv00-2Takes   12-19 1110</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-YE--Deaths 1989, Adv 00 - 2 Takes,1166</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv00</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release in Year-End Editions</HEAD>
<HEAD>They Helped Shape Our World</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhotos</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Their many different worlds seldom intersected _ the worlds of
music and baseball, of letters and law, of the surreal and the
slapstick, of political struggle and science, of spies and
prizefights and quiet poetry.
   But together these people from many worlds helped shape our
world, for good or ill, and then they departed.
   Here, month by month, is a roll of notables who died in 1989:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>JANUARY</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   EMPEROR HIROHITO, once venerated as a living god by the
Japanese, he reigned for 62 years. As the last survivor among World
War II-era leaders, he saw his nation progress from ruin to riches.
At age 87.
   BRUCE CHATWIN, British novelist and travel writer whose
obsession with nomads took him to some of the most remote places on
Earth. At age 48 of a rare disease of the bone marrow contracted on
a 1986 visit to China.
   BEATRICE LILLIE, pearl-swinging comedienne whose improvisational
skills and mastery of the elegant putdown delighted theatergoers in
dozens of Broadway and London shows. Age 94.
   SALVADOR DALI, flamboyant painter and founder of the surrealist
movement whose celebrated dreamscapes, particularly ``Persistence
of Memory,'' made an indelible impression on contemporary culture.
Age 84.
   SIR WILLIAM STEPHENSON, British spymaster, the ``man called
Intrepid,'' whose vast intelligence web snared German spies in the
United States during World War II. Age 93.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>FEBRUARY</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   JOHN CASSAVETES, actor and filmmaker known for his innovative,
unconventional works, such as ``A Woman Under the Influence'' and
``Faces.'' At age 59 of cirrhosis.
   JOE RAPOSO, Grammy-winning songwriter and co-creator of the
children's television program ``Sesame Street.'' Age 51.
   BARBARA TUCHMAN, Pulitzer Prize-winning historian whose 1962
book ``The Guns of August,'' chronicling the beginning of World War
I, offered nuclear-age leaders lessons in how man's fate can too
easily elude man's control. Age 77.
   WAYNE L. HAYS, powerful Ohio congressman who destroyed his
14-term career with the Elizabeth Ray congressional sex and payroll
scandal. Age 77.
   GUY LAROCHE, French fashion designer whose sophisticated styles
were renowned for their quality, beautiful fabrics and arresting
colors. Age 67.
   KONRAD LORENZ, scientist and author whose pioneering behavioral
studies of humans and animals earned him the Nobel Prize for
medicine. At age 85.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MARCH</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   MAURICE EVANS, actor and producer who starred in Shakepeare on
television and the London stage, played lighter roles on U.S.
television and produced several Broadway hits, including ``Teahouse
of the August Moon'' and ``No Time for Sergeants.'' Age 87.
   EDWARD ABBEY, ardent environmentalist and author (``The Monkey
Wrench Gang,'' ``Desert Solitude'') who dreamed of returning the
West to a pristine state and wrote of its ruination by the cement
of civilization. Age 62.
   STEPHEN DAVISON BECHTEL SR., international engineering and
construction giant whose accomplishments included Hoover Dam. Age
88.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>APRIL</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   SUGAR RAY ROBINSON, widely regarded as ``pound for pound'' the
greatest boxer ever. Generations of fighters, including future
champ Muhammad Ali, copied his style. At age 67.
   ABBIE HOFFMAN, life-long political and environmental activist
and 1960s radical who rose to prominence with the Chicago Seven and
founded the Yippie movement. At age 52, suicide.
   DAME DAPHNE DU MAURIER, author of ``Rebecca,'' ``My Cousin
Rachel'' and other celebrated novels of romance and the
supernatural. Age 81.
   LUCILLE BALL, daffy redheaded comedienne whose wide-mouthed
wails, extravagant pratfalls and harebrained schemes delighted
television viewers for four decades. Age 77.
   KONOSUKE MATSUSHITA, inventor who founded Matsushita Electric
Industrial Co., one of the world's largest manufacturers of
consumer electronics. Age 94.
   ROY LEE WILLIAMS, rose from trucker to become president of the
International Teamsters union but finished his career serving a
prison term for bribery. Age 74.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MAY</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   CHRISTINE JORGENSEN, born George, shocked the world by becoming
the first person to undergo a sex-change operation. Age 62.
   GILDA RADNER, effervescent comedian, one of the original stars
of ``Saturday Night Live'' and creator of such memorable characters
as Roseanne Roseannadanna and Emily Latella. At age 42 of cancer.
   CLAUDE PEPPER, oldest member of Congress, champion of the
elderly, liberal crusader and an architect of Social Security, the
minimum wage and medical programs. Age 88.
   OWEN LATTIMORE, China scholar who Sen. Joseph McCarthy once
accused of being ``the top Soviet espionage agent in the United
States.'' A Senate committee concluded there was no basis for
McCarthy's accusation. Age 88.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>JUNE</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   AYATOLLAH RUHOLLAH KHOMEINI, clergyman who, from exile, rallied
Moslem fundamentalist passions in Iran, overthrew the U.S.-backed
shah and ruled as revolutionary religious ``guide'' for 10 years.
Age 86.
   FRAN ALLISON, the warm-hearted foil for two goofy puppets on the
pioneering children's television show ``Kukla, Fran and Ollie.''
Age 81.
   HONOR TRACY, travel writer, columnist and author of novels that
satirized Irish and English society. Age 75.
   I.F. STONE, anti-establishment commentator and publisher whose
fiery dissent inspired a generation of journalists. Age 81.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>JULY</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   ANDREI A. GROMYKO, longtime Soviet foreign minister known as
``Grim Grom'' or ``Mr. Nyet.'' Served every Soviet leader in the
era from Stalin to Gorbachev. Age 79.
   JIM BACKUS, character actor who played the wealthy Thurston
Howell III on ``Gilligan's Island'' and provided the piercing,
ever-perplexed voice for cartoon character Mr. Magoo. Age 76.
   JANOS KADAR, took power in Hungary after the Soviets crushed the
1956 revolt and steered his country through relative prosperity
until Communist moderates forced him out last year. Age 77.
   MEL BLANC, the ``Man of a Thousand Voices'' who entranced
generations of cartoon viewers with voices ranging from Bugs Bunny
and Porky Pig to Barney Rubble and Tweety Pie. Age 81.
   LAURENCE OLIVIER, the foremost actor of his generation and
leader of the giants of the English-speaking theater. Age 82.
   HERBERT VON KARAJAN, world-renowned and controversial conductor,
led the Berlin Philharmonic for 34 years. Age 81.
   DONALD BARTHELME, innovative writer of modern fiction. Age 58 of
cancer.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>AUGUST</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   MICKEY LELAND, veteran congressman who made world hunger a
legislative priority. At age 44 in plane crash while visiting
famine relief camps in Ethiopia.
   WILLIAM SHOCKLEY, Nobel Prize winner in physics, one of the
inventors of the transistor and controversial advocate of theories
of genetically based intelligence. Age 79.
   AMANDA BLAKE, actress who played saloonkeeper Miss Kitty on
television's long-running series ``Gunsmoke.'' Age 60.
   GEORGE ADAMSON, conservationist who, with his wife Joy, devoted
his life to returning lions born in captivity to the wild, a story
detailed in the books and movies ``Born Free'' and ``Living Free.''
At age 83, shot to death by animal poachers.
   HUEY NEWTON, articulate leader of black militancy in the 1960s,
co-founder of the Black Panther Party. At age 46, killed in a
street shooting.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>