<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1625EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Philippines-Coup     12-17 0665</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines-Coup,0688</SECOND>
<HEAD>Response To Coup Attempt Shows The Strengths, Weakness Of Democracy</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT H. REID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government's efforts to rebound
after the recent failed coup have largely consisted of rhetoric,
partly because of a political system designed to check presidential
action.
   It is widely assumed that President Corazon Aquino must make
sweeping changes in her administration and leadership style if the
nation is to recover from the political, economic and social damage
caused by the Dec. 1-9 military mutiny that nearly ousted her.
   More than a week after the last rebel surrendered, there have
been no Cabinet changes. She seems to have delayed action so it
does not appear that she bowed to the mutineers' demands for
change, including an end to government corruption and inefficiency.
   There also have been no major domestic policy reforms. But the
Philippine political system, which Mrs. Aquino proudly describes as
a ``restored democracy,'' is not designed for speedy action.
   It was designed to divide power among the executive, legislative
and judicial branches after 20 years of strongman rule under the
late President Ferdinand Marcos. For better or worse, the Aquino
administration and citizens are discovering what that means in time
of crisis.
   In a bid to restore public confidence, Mrs. Aquino declared a
state of national emergency on Dec. 6. The declaration exists in
name only, however, because Congress has not ratified the final
version of a bill spelling out what Ms. Aquino would be empowered
to do during a state of emergency.
   The Senate and House of Representatives planned to take up the
legislation on Monday.
   It would grant few new powers beyond price controls, state
operation of public utilities and recovery of ``loose firearms.''
   Congress amended the original proposal to require adherence to
the constitution, language that virtually guarantees court
challenges if the legislation passes.
   For example, the compromise bill would not allow the government
to arrest suspects without warrants or circumvent other legal
restraints. Lawmakers also have weakened proposed curbs on the
right to strike and media reporting.
   The idea of emergency powers has been severely criticized by
people with bitter memories of martial law, which Marcos imposed
from 1972 until 1981.
   ``We see a repeat of the Marcos regime,'' wrote columnist Neal
Cruz in the Philippine Daily Globe. ``Marcos refused to heed
appeals for reform. Instead, he declared a state of emergency, then
imposed martial law. ... Now that housewife is turning out to be
another Marcos.''
   In the heady days after the 1986 ``people power revolution''
that toppled the Marcos administration, Mrs. Aquino appointed a
commission to draft a new constitution to guarantee no more
one-person rule.
   The commission restored the two-house legislature precisely
because Marcos had been successful in transforming a single-house
National Assembly into a rubber-stamp chamber.
   Last week, the system seemed to work: Congress refused to give
the administration everything it wanted.
   The president is constitutionally empowered to declare a state
of emergency ``and under reasonable terms ... temporarily take over
or direct the operations of any privately owned public utility or
business affected by the public interest.'' No other specific
powers are cited.
   Even if she declared martial law, Mrs. Aquino would hardly have
a free legal hand.
   The constitution stipulates that martial law ``does not suspend
the operation of the constitution'' or the operations of Congress
and the courts.
   Mrs Aquino could order arrest without warrants for 60 days but
Congress is empowered to overrule such a decree after 48 hours.
   One step that she could take would be to dismiss her Cabinet,
which had been widely criticized as ineffective months before the
coup attempt.
   Presidential staff sources, speaking on condition of anonymity,
say Mrs. Aquino was preparing to drop some Cabinet members but did
not plan a massive shake-up because she believes much of the
criticism is unfair.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   EDITOR'S NOTE: Robert Reid has been The Associated Press bureau
chief in Manila since September 1986.
</TEXT>

</DOC>