<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0209 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1204EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--SubmarineTesting Adv25   12-21 0534</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Submarine Testing, Adv 25,0546</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv25</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Monday, Dec. 25, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Tiny Base Conducts Research for Navy's Newest Attack Submarine</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN K. WILEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BAYVIEW, Idaho (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Beneath the surface of Lake Pend Oreille,
scientists are testing technology the Navy hopes will make the new
Seawolf class attack submarines the world's fastest and quietest.
   General Dynamics Corp. last month laid the keel for the first of
the $1.4 billion SSN-21 submarines at its Groton, Conn., shipyard,
said Navy spokesman Lt. Greg Smith. Asked about specifics of the
work here of the Acoustic Research Detachment, he said, ``Nearly
all that information is classified.''
   The civilian contractor, Tracor Inc. of Austin, Texas, tests
one-fifth and one-quarter scale models of hulls and propellers
here. In general, researchers want to know how much noise is made
by the special steel hull as water flows past and how much the
steel dampens noise made by machinery inside, said George A.
Guedel, the civilian manager.
   ``We are trying to develop technologies for allowing the
submarine to go faster, quieter and still hear others before they
hear it,'' Guedel said.
   A key piece of equipment is the $64 million Kokanee, a
quarter-scale model steered by computer as it sails through an
underwater course. The model is used to test propeller designs
intended to reduce noise, said Jim Scott, a spokesman for the David
Taylor Research Center at Annapolis and Carderock, Md.
   The Acoustic Research Detachment at Bayview is a unit of the
David Taylor Center and is one of six such laboratories for ship
research.
   The base is designated classified, the lowest of three levels of
security. Unarmed guards from a private security company patrol the
grounds. Signs posted on fences and buoys in the lake tell people
not to trespass.
   Bayview, a quiet fishing resort community of about 237 full-time
residents, surrounds the 22-acre base, which is behind a chain link
fence with concertina wire. Otherwise, there is not much to
indicate that the collection of aluminum buildings is a center of
classified research.
   Inside a metal drydock _ its ceiling covered with insulation to
prevent snooping by Soviet infrared satellites _ modifications are
made to the Kokanee and other test models named for Northwest fish
species. Although the Kokanee is inside the building, its aft and
propeller are always covered by a shroud.
   In the middle of the bay, a large, floating metal building is
used to refit hull designs and conduct noise experiments on a
110-ton full-scale model.
   In one series of tests, buoyant hulls called ``vertical flying
models'' are pulled to the bottom of the 1,300-foot-deep lake then
released. As they rise to the surface, technicians using
computer-assisted listening devices learn how much noise they make
as they cruise through the water.
   There are several reasons why the glacier-carved lake is in some
ways better than seawater for testing the acoustic properties of
various metals and equipment, Guedel said. In the middle of the
lake there are 23 square miles of water 1,000 feet deep or more.
The sub-surface temperature stays a chilly 39.5 degrees year-round
and there is less corrosion than in saltwater tests.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Dec. 25</NOTE>

</DOC>