<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0558EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather     12-20 0654</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather,0670</SECOND>
<HEAD>Arctic Air Freezes Upper Midwest</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Polar air dropped temperatures as low as 40 below zero and
powered piercing gusts across the northern Plains today, spawning
deadly wind chills of 80 below on the day before the official start
of winter.
   Snow was falling on either side of the arctic front gripping the
nation's midsection. Northwestern Montana expected 4 to 8 inches of
new snow today in the valleys and a foot or more in the mountains.
   Another round of lake effect snow in New York state was expected
east of Lake Ontario and Lake Erie today. Lake squalls have dumped
more than 2 feet of snow from Oswego to Pulaski, N.Y., over the
past few days.
   Life-threatening wind chills were predicted for Minnesota, the
Dakotas, Illinois and Iowa today and Thursday as gusts of up to 30
mph combined with increasingly frigid air.
   ``This is way below normal for December,'' said Richard May, a
National Weather Service meteorologist at Bismarck, N.D., which
recorded Tuesday's coldest reading for the Lower 48 states at 35
below. ``It will be the worst cold we've had this season.''
Tuesday's temperatures ranged between 30 and 40 degrees below
normal statewide.
   Snow advisories were in effect today over north-central Indiana
and northwestern Upper Michigan and for western Lower Michigan
along Lake Michigan.
   A winter storm watch was posted over Upper Michigan for late
today and Thursday.
   Michigan was on track for its coldest December on record. The
state's average mean temperature for the first 18 days in the month
was 14.1 degrees, according to the National Weather Service. The
normal for the month is 23.5 degrees.
   Rain reached across the Carolina coasts through Georgia to
northern Florida Tuesday. A winter weather advisory for snow,
freezing rain and sleet was posted for South Carolina, except the
southern coast.
   A heavy snow warning for northwest Indiana was canceled, but a
snow advisory remained in effect from near La Porte to the Elkhart
area. By today, as much as 10 inches of snow had fallen near South
Bend and La Porte, which has received up to 3 feet of new snow over
the past few days.
   Three Florida cities reached record high temperatures Tuesday
for the date. Hollywood's 84 degrees and Miami's 85 bested marks
set in 1986.
   West Palm Beach hit 88 degrees to break a 28-year-old record and
set Tuesday's high temperature in the nation.
   Other reports at 4 a.m. EST today:
   _EAST: Albany, N.Y., 12 snow; Atlanta 31 cloudy; Boston 20 snow;
Buffalo 16; Charleston, S.C., 35 foggy; Chattanooga 23 fair;
Cincinnati 04 fair; Cleveland 15 foggy; Detroit 10 fair; Hatteras
37 foggy; Jacksonville 43 rain; Key West 72 foggy; Knoxville 23
partly cloudy; Macon 35 cloudy; Miami 70 foggy; New York 24 partly
cloudy; Philadelphia 18 fair; Pittsburgh 15 snow; Portland, Maine,
13 cloudy; Richmond 21 foggy; Tampa 64 foggy; Washington, D.C., 19
fair.
   _CENTRAL: Birmingham 29 foggy; Bismarck 12 snow; Chicago 2
partly cloudy; Denver 20 fair; Des Moines 2 snow; Fort Worth 19;
Indianapolis 5 fair; Kansas City 9 hazy; Little Rock 19 fair;
Louisville 11 partly cloudy; Memphis 17 fair; Nashville 12 fair;
New Orleans 40 foggy; North Platte 3 fair; Oklahoma City 16 fair;
Omaha 3 foggy; Rapid City 1 partly cloudy; St. Louis 4 fair;
Minneapolis-St. Paul 17 fair; Sault Ste. Marie 2 snow; San Antonio
29 fair.
   _WEST: Albuquerque 32 fair; Anchorage 20 partly cloudy; Boise 19
fair; Casper 27 windy; Fairbanks 8 fair; Great Falls 0; Las Vegas
34 fair; Los Angeles 52 fair; Medford 24 snow; Pendleton 33 partly
cloudy; Phoenix 47 fair; Portland, Ore., 32 foggy; Reno 21 fair;
Salt Lake City 29 fair; San Diego 53 fair; San Francisco 46 foggy;
Seattle 45 rain; Spokane 30 foggy.
   _INTERNATIONAL: Calgary 12 snow; Montreal 3 snow; Ottawa 5 snow;
Regina 32 fair; Toronto 12 partly cloudy; Winnipeg 32 partly
cloudy; San Juan 72.
</TEXT>

</DOC>