<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0190 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0929EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APArts:MaxFactor Adv22   12-21 1028</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP Arts: Max Factor, Adv 22,1052</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv 22</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Fri PMs, Dec 22 and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>From the Czar's Wigmaker to Beauty Guru to Stars</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By THERESE LEE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When Technicolor was first tested in the
1930s, the on-screen results raised some well-penciled eyebrows:
The hills were green, the grass was green and the actors' faces ..
. were green.
   Max Factor, Hollywood's beauty guru, realized makeup was
reflecting the color of the scenery. So he headed to his shop,
experimented and delivered a makeup that dried to a dull finish. He
packaged the new product in round, flat containers. For lack of a
better name, Factor called it Pan-Cake makeup.
   It was one in a series of innovations offered by the Russian
immigrant during a Hollywood career that spanned 29 years.
   The name Max Factor was synonymous with movie glamour for
decades, but his true gift to Hollywood was to make actors appear
natural instead of glamorous.
   Factor's contributions to good looks can be seen at the Max
Factor Makeup Museum in Hollywood, founded in 1984 by curator Bob
Salvatore, a 23-year employee of Max Factor &amp; Co.
   ``Max saved Technicolor. And at the same time he invented modern
makeup,'' Salvatore said. ``Max knew he had something when the
actresses started stealing the Pan-Cake for their own use.''
   Salvatore admits the museum is part historical preservation and
part publicity for the company, now owned by Revlon Inc. Admission
is free and the ``museum shop'' is a Max Factor retail outlet.
   Unlike the tourist-oriented Hollywood Wax Museum or the
Fredericks of Hollywood Bra Museum with its exhibit of celebrity
undergarments, the Factor museum is notable for its quiet elegance.
   The main lobby has antique glass and wood cases displaying
powder, lipstick and perfume containers from past decades. Four
``color'' rooms, where beauty treatments were once given, branch
off from the lobby.
   When the rooms were added to the salon in 1935, each was
dedicated by an actress. The blonde room painted in shades of blue
was dedicated by Jean Harlow; the redhead room, in green hues, by
Ginger Rogers; the brunette room, in rose colors, by Claudette
Colbert; and the brownette room, in peach, by Rochelle Hudson.
   ``A woman could walk into the room for her color and immediately
be surrounded by a flattering environment,'' Salvatore said.
   For Factor, applying makeup was as much science as art. The
``beauty calibrator'' is a reminder of his search for the perfect
face, a quest, Salvatore said, that was never satisfied.
   The contraption, a mass of metal bands and pointers circling a
mannequin's head, was patented by Factor in 1932 to measure the
distance between the eyes, the length of the chin and other aspects
of a woman's face. With that information, Factor would apply makeup
to camouflage nature's imperfections.
   Another Factor invention on display is the kissing machine. He
wanted his lipsticks to withstand a perfect ``10-pound kiss.''
That, Salvatore said, is a ``respectable goodbye kiss between a
husband and wife. Any more than that and they are on their own.''
   Factor hired a man and woman to test the indelibility of new
lipsticks. But the pair, who were married to other people, soon
tired of the work and quit. Factor had rubber molds made of the
kissers lips and attached them to a hand-operated machine that
pressed the fake lips together.
   The Factor saga in America began in 1904, when he arrived in St.
Louis to run his display at the World's Fair. After the fair, he
stayed on, operating a barber shop for five years. Factor had
$40,000 in gold when he arrived in the United States but lost most
of it through bad business deals.
   After moving to Los Angeles in 1909, he opened a barber shop in
the theater district and made wigs and makeup for stage clientele.
Filmmakers soon sought him out with makeup problems.
   One early problem he tackled was converting stage greasepaint to
film makeup. The early film, monochromatic, did not register red,
so cheeks and lips looked black on the screen. Factor mixed up
colors that would look natural.
   ``Max Factor was not only the most important force in Hollywood
makeup, he was the only source that was interested in movie
makeup,'' said Howard Smit, a 30-year veteran of the Makeup and
Hairstylists union. ``This wasn't a product that you could make for
the masses.''
   The first film for which Factor had a contract to do all the
makeup and hair was ``Vogues of 1938.''
   Factor's sons, Max Jr. and Davis, carried on the legacy when he
died in 1938. The family sold the company in the 1970s. It was
owned by Beatrice Corp. and others until 1985 when Revlon purchased
it.
   During that time, the company expanded into a
multimillion-dollar international cosmetics firm. That prosperity
was fueled by the use of dozens of stars such as Loretta Young and
Bette Davis in celebrity ad campaigns unequaled before or since. A
few of the ads, appearing in international publications between
1928-47 are on display at the museum.
   It was not love of Factor's makeup that attracted the big names;
the actresses had little choice. They were told by the studios to
pose for Factor ads, Salvatore said. It was a relationship that
benefited both Factor and the studios.
   ``At the time he was shipping his makeup all over the world and
European sales for movies were even more lucrative than American,''
Salvatore said. ``The ads would say `Barbara Stanwyck in ``Double
Indemnity,''' and it would be like advance advertising for the
movie. And Max got to use a very recognizable face in his ads here.
No money ever changed hands, not a penny.''
   Hollywood recently knocked on Max Factor's door again. Director
Jack Nicholson wanted to use the museum to film a scene for the
movie ``The Two Jakes,'' a sequel to ``Chinatown,'' set in the late
1940s.
   In the scene, actress Meg Tilly, a brunette, comes to the salon
to have a facial.
   ``They filmed it in the blonde room,'' Salvatore said. ``Max
would have been appalled.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv PM Fri Dec. 22</NOTE>

</DOC>