<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0134 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1937EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Brazil-PriestSlain     12-27 0421</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil-Priest Slain,0431</SECOND>
<HEAD>Archbishop Says Priest's Slaying May Have Been Politically Motivated</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RIO DE JANEIRO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The slaying of a French priest in
southeastern Brazil may have been politically motivated and not the
work of robbers, a Brazilian archbishop said Wednesday.
   The Rev. Gabriel Felix Roger Maire ``had been receiving death
threats for the past several months due to his work on behalf of
justice and human rights for the poor,'' Archbishop Silvestre
Scandian said by phone from Vitoria.
   Police found Maire, 53, shot in the chest and slumped over the
wheel of his car Saturday on the outskirts of Vitoria, 310 miles
northeast of Rio. Police arrested two suspects and charged them
with shooting Maire during an attempted robbery.
   Scandian disputed the police report, saying Maire's wristwatch
and other personal items were left in the car. A bag containing his
cassock and empty wallet was found about 100 yards from the scene.
   The Rev. Mauricio de Mattos Pereira, of the Archdiocese's
Justice and Peace Commission, said three other politically
motivated killings occurred in nearby towns since June.
   ``When you try to raise the consciousness of the small, the big
react,'' said Pereira. ``They want to silence all those trying to
show the poor the roots of injustice.''
   Maire arrived in Brazil in 1980 and worked in the lower-class
parish of Vila Velha, eight miles south of Vitoria.
   Thousands of people attended a wake for Maire on Tuesday. The
priest's body will be flown to France on Thursday, maccording to
Maria Beatrice de Seixas Correa, a spokeswoman at the French
consulate in Rio.
   The Roman Catholic Church here estimates more than 800 people
have been assassinated for political reasons since Brazil returned
to civilian rule after a right-wing military dictatorship ruled
from 1964 to 1985.
   Many of the victims have been rural union leaders involved in
land disputes and church activists who advise them.
   In only three cases, two involving the murder of priests, have
the killers been brought to justice, according to Amnesty
International, the human rights group.
   The most famous case involved the slaying of Chico Mendes, a
world-renowned union leader and environmentalist who led peaceful
protests to stop the clearing of Amazon rain forest by cattle
ranchers.
   Mendes, 44, was shot in his home in the backwoods Amazon town of
Xapuri on Dec. 22, 1988. Although a cattle rancher and his son have
been arrested and charged in the case, a judge last week announced
that the earliest possible trial date would be April 1990.
</TEXT>

</DOC>