<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0171 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1324EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i AM-Britain-PigeonRacing Adv22-1stLd-Writethru   12-19 0772</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Pigeon Racing, Adv 22-1st Ld-Writethru,b0422,0793</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv22</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Friday AMs, Dec. 22, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pigeon Racing Is Popular Sport in Britain</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: CORRECTS 6th graf, Camelleri, a ... million people, to fix spelling
of name to Camilleri.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LESLIE SHEPHERD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHELTENHAM, England (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   From the blue-collar housing projects
of cockney east London to the gardens of the gentry, grown men scan
the skies for hours most weekends, waiting for their pigeons to
race home.
   They rhapsodize about pigeon racing, the sport known as ``the
fancy'' and now one of Britain's more popular pastimes.
   ``All you see is a pinprick in the sky,'' said Maj. Edward
Camilleri. ``They fly toward you and you hope its yours. Then they
fold their wings, they drop out of the sky, they literally do. They
come straight down like bullets.''
   Says Bernie Bennett, who has 60 pigeons: ``Unless you're a
pigeon fancier, you just find it very hard to understand, to see a
person out in the garden, like me yesterday, bucketing down with
rain, looking for pigeons to come from 100 miles.
   ``With pigeons I find one thing and one thing only: You're the
jury, you're the prosecution, you are the judge. All that happens
down in your backyard is down to you.''
   Camilleri, a retired soldier who runs the Royal Pigeon Racing
Association, estimates Britain has more than 200,000 pigeon
breeders and racers among its 56 million people.
   Nearly 2 million pigeons, many with meticulously documented
pedigrees dating back several avian generations, are registered
with Camilleri's association alone.
   The sport has an honorable history: The ancient Egyptians kept
pigeons; Hannibal took them over the Alps; they served in both
world wars, carrying messages for the Allied intelligence forces in
Europe. Thirty-one pigeons were awarded the Dickens Medal, the
``Animal Victoria Cross,'' in World War II.
   In Britain, pigeons were traditionally associated with
beer-drinking, cloth-capped men, but it has moved upmarket in
recent years, attracting lawyers, actors and titans of industry. At
the top end of the scale, Queen Elizabeth II maintains a pigeon
loft.
   Britain's largest pigeon breeder, Louella Pigeon World, is a
high-tech enterprise that paid a world record 77,000 pounds
($120,120) in 1988 for the racing pigeon Emerald II.
   ``That, pound for pound, makes it more valuable than the Derby
winner,'' Camilleri said, referring to Britain's most prestigious
horse race.
   Emerald II is moved from one secret location to another, because
with the large sums sometimes at stake in bets and prize money,
sabotage and pigeon-napping are not unheard of.
   However, high prices don't always guarantee success, Camilleri
said, and a good racing pigeon can start as low as 20 pounds ($32).
   ``Stockmanship comes into it, knowing and understanding
pigeons,'' he explained. ``They all have their individual
characters and what you've got to do is understand their character
well enough and encourage them to come home quicker than the next
pigeon.''
   No one knows exactly how pigeons they find their way home after
being released, sometimes hundreds of miles away.
   ``The sun is definitely one (factor) and magnetic field is
definitely a second,'' Camilleri said. Research in Europe indicates
the sense of smell also may help.
   There's also a very basic urge.
   Most pigeons in Britain are kept on the ``widowhood system.'' As
soon as a hen and cock produce a pair of young, or squeakers,
they're separated. Only the males are raced, and the only time they
get to see their hens is when they return to the loft at the end of
a race.
   Each fancier's loft is registered and the distance between it
and any of the 200 official British ``liberation sites'' measured
to the nearest yard.
   Pigeons are bundled into baskets, sometimes the night before a
race, and taken to the liberation site in air-conditioned trucks.
Each wears a rubber band about the size of a wedding ring on its
leg with the details of where it came from.
   The pigeons are all released at the same time. They ascend
rapidly, quickly become oriented and head for home.
   When they land, the fancier removes the rubber band and puts it
in a timeclock that is sealed and taken to the local racing club.
The flight distance is divided by the time it took to determine who
won the race.
   What is it about pigeons that engenders such passion and loyalty?
   ``The fascination about it: you get a few pigeons, you start
winning races, and from then on it's a lot like horse racing, only
cheaper,'' Camilleri said.
   ``You can pit your wits against nature.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Friday AMs, Dec. 22</NOTE>

</DOC>