<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0293 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 2022EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-HuntBankruptcy     12-22 0486</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hunt Bankruptcy,0503</SECOND>
<HEAD>Herbert Hunt Bankruptcy Concludes</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A chapter in the turbulent financial saga of the
Hunt brothers _ once among the richest men in the world _ drew to a
close this week as William Herbert Hunt relinquished his estate to
a liquidating trustee.
   Hunt's resolution of one of the biggest personal bankruptcies in
history came on the heels of his brother Nelson Bunker Hunt's
settlement last week.
   It brings an end to the more than $3 billion fortune received
from their father, famed oil wildcatter H.L. Hunt.
   Both brothers will formally emerge from bankruptcy in early
January.
   ``I don't plan to sit on my fanny,'' Herbert Hunt said when
asked about his plans.
   On Thursday, U.S. Bankruptcy Judge Harold Abramson signed the
order that will transfer the fallen oilman's estate to a
liquidating trust within 10 days. Herbert Hunt's $169 million
estate will be liquidated to pay creditors over the next six years,
absolving him of nearly $1 billion in debt.
   Missing from Thursday's hearing were the television cameras,
crowds or fanfare that dominated the end of Bunker Hunt's
bankruptcy case.
   ``Bunker got much more attention because he is much more
interesting, but this was the harder of the two cases to resolve,''
said Hugh Ray, attorney for Manufacturers Hanover Trust Co., a
creditor in both bankruptcies. He noted that Herbert's assets are
less liquid.
   ``Bunker had a lot more cash,'' he said.
   Ray said it was ``miraculous'' to have two such sizable
bankruptcy cases resolved within 15 months.
   Under the plan confirmed Thursday, Herbert will be stripped of
his assets, which are concentrated heavily in depressed Texas and
Arizona real estate. His largest holding is a $50.5 million
interest in a 4,000-acre Phoenix housing development.
   Herbert will lose his $400,000 salary, but he will keep his
Cadillac, $1.2 million Dallas mansion, personal effects totaling
$50,000 and a 50 percent interest in non-producing oil and natural
gas properties.
   In addition, if Hunt can enhance the selling price of his
Byzantine coins and bronze statues, he will receive a portion of
those proceeds. Herbert's children will be given a chance to buy
his one-half interest in his Vail, Colo., home as well as his wife
Nancy's English pottery collection.
   Seventy percent of Herbert's holdings will go to the Internal
Revenue Service and the other 30 percent will be divided among the
remaining creditors, including Manufacturers Hanover and Minpeco
SA, a Peruvian mining company.
   In addition, the IRS will be paid $75 million out of future
gifts, income and inheritances.
   Herbert's financial problems began in 1980 when he and his
brother lost $1.5 billion speculating in the silver futures
markets. The silver losses were compounded by falling real estate
prices and the collapse of the oil market.
   The brothers filed for bankruptcy protection in September 1988,
shortly after a New York jury found the Hunts had conspired to
corner the silver market.
</TEXT>

</DOC>