<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1130EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Poland     12-29 0308</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Poland,0316</SECOND>
<HEAD>Glemp Wishes Lawmakers Strength During First Parliament Visit</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH G. SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Primate Jozef Glemp today paid tribute to
lawmakers of all political persuasions during the first visit by a
Poland's Roman Catholic leader to Parliament in the country's
postwar history.
   Lawmakers greeted Glemp with Christmas carols. His visit was
another sign of the changes in Poland's government since
Solidarity-backed candidates trounced Communist parliamentary
candidates and joined with other parties to form the East bloc's
first government led by non-Communists.
   Similar changes occurred in recent months in East Germany and
Czechoslovakia, and democratic reforms have spread through
Bulgaria, Hungary and Romania.
   Glemp met with senators and members of the Sejm, as the lower
house of Parliament is called, during a break in a heated debate
over amendments to the constitution and an eventual change in the
country's national emblem.
   ``I wish you enough strength for the coming year and that the
link between the nation and the Parliament will become stronger and
meet with greater understanding,'' he said.
   Throughout the morning, lawmakers debated the constitutional
amendments, especially one that would eliminate a clause giving the
Communist Party the leading role in state affairs as well as a
proposed change that would add a crown to the national emblem.
   The package of constitutional amendments would also restore the
historical name of the country to the prewar Republic of Poland
instead of the Communist-imposed People's Republic of Poland.
   ``We shall soon say goodbye to 1989,'' said Edward Rzepa, a
deputy from the Solidarity caucus. ``It seems it is the most
appropriate moment to give society a long-expected gift _ a new
constitution.''
   The constitutional amendments, proposed by the Solidarity
caucus, are designed to eliminate or change sections inconsistent
with new democratic reforms until a completely new constitution can
be written.
</TEXT>

</DOC>