<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0218EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-HomicideRecords Bjt   12-28 0562</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Homicide Records, Bjt,0580</SECOND>
<HEAD>Drugs Blamed for Making '89 a Record Year for Homicide</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MITCHELL LANDSBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Murder rates soared to new highs in some of the nation's largest
cities in 1989, but at least eight cities saw a surprising drop in
homicides.
   Police were quick to blame crack for homicide records that were
set in at least seven cities, but they were less certain about why
there was less killing elsewhere.
   One official suggested that violence may have ebbed in cities
where drug dealers have already won their turf wars by killing off
rivals and dividing up territory.
   Final 1989 statistics in most cities won't be prepared for at
least several weeks, but a preliminary survey by The Associated
Press of police departments in more than 30 cities shows that the
number of homicides rose in most of them.
   ``A large amount of the increase has to do with the violence
associated with the drug trade,'' said Hubert Williams, executive
director of the Police Foundation.
   Police officials across the nation echoed his statement.
   More homicides were committed this year than ever before in
Washington, Philadelphia, New Orleans, Kansas City, Milwaukee,
Charlotte, N.C., and New Haven, Conn.
   Several other cities, including New York City, are likely to
have set records when final 1989 statistics are compiled.
   In some big cities _ Chicago, Los Angeles and Baltimore, among
them _ the number of killings is up from last year but nowhere near
the all-time high.
   At least eight cities, including Miami, Dallas and Denver,
expect to end the year with a slight decline in homicides. The
other cities: Minneapolis; Indianapolis; Portland, Ore.; Virginia
Beach, Va.; and Newark, N.J.
   Police offered no explanations for the decline, but Williams of
the Police Foundation said those cities might just be ahead of
others in the sophistication of their drug kingpins.
   ``It's my sense, at least, that the homicides related to drug
trafficking begin to peak as the turf battles begin to break out,
and diminish as someone gains control,'' he said.
   In New York, which always has the largest number of homicides in
the nation, killings totaled 1,773 as of Nov. 24. That is 19 more
than were committed in the same period of 1988.
   In September alone, 197 people were killed, making it one of the
bloodiest months in the city's history.
   Assistant Police Chief Raymond Kelly attributed the rise to
crack, the smokeable form of cocaine. He noted that in 1978, there
were 1,504 homicides in New York.
   ``What's different now than in the late '70s and early '80s? The
answer is crack,'' Kelly said.
   Although New York claims the largest number of violent deaths,
Washington is the most murderous big city on a per capita basis.
   A police spokesman there, Lt. Reginald Smith, estimated that 60
percent of this year's homicides were drug-related.
   Through Dec. 21, 419 people had been killed in the District of
Columbia in 1989, compared with the previous all-time high of 369
set last year.
   In Philadelphia, there were 481 killings by Dec. 21, well above
the 15-year-old record of 444. Police blamed not just drugs but the
fact that today's drug dealers are far better armed than their
counterparts in the past.
   ``Before they had zip guns and homemade weapons. Now they have
automatic weapons, Uzis,'' said Sgt. Robert Snyder, a 32-year
police veteran.
</TEXT>

</DOC>