<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0112 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1442EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PauleyFarewell     12-29 0471</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pauley Farewell,0485</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Today' Co-Host Leaves After 13 Years</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY24</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RAYNER PIKE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jane Pauley took leave of the ``Today'' show
Friday after 13 years as co-host, fighting back tears and promising
to keep up friendships with the program's regulars, including her
successor, Deborah Norville.
   ``I have to thank NBC for giving me this incredible front-row
seat for the last 13 years, and my colleagues for being more like
family and for making this studio feel like home,'' she said.
   Pauley announced in October that she intended to leave
television's longest-running network morning show. The announcement
came amid published speculation that she was being pushed out for
the younger, flashier Norville.
   Pauley said then and reiterated Friday that she and her
successor would continue to be friends. Pauley has extended her
contract with NBC to 1992 and will be involved in prime-time
programs beginning in March.
   Bryant Gumbel, ``Today'' co-host for the past eight years, said
to Pauley at the end of her final program: ``Consistency's a
treasured thing. You know where I stand.''
   ``Class act,'' was the parting comment from weatherman Willard
Scott.
   ``I never knew we'd be such good friends and I never knew I
would get the chance to continue the legacy that you've begun,''
Norville said.
   Tom Brokaw, who shared the spotlight with Pauley the first five
years of her run, said in a farewell film clip that her great
ability was ``that she can reach everyone from Robert DeNiro across
the middle of America into the heartland.''
   ``All the cliches about Jane are true _ she is the young woman
that you'd like to have as your daughter,'' Brokaw said.
   The film clips that took up much of the program's final
half-hour included Pauley in some of the estimated 12,000
interviews she conducted over the years, mugging with a fat cigar
and a bulbous clown's nose and taking a ribbing about her ballooned
shape late in a pregnancy.
   There also was a cavalcade of her coiffures during her ``Today''
career. A fan was shown saying that she could really identify with
Pauley because ``sometimes her hair really doesn't look too good.''
   But anthropologist Helen Fisher said each hairstyle showed
Pauley ``really senses her audience. It's not too sexy; she knows
this is a morning program. It's not too cute; she knows this is an
important program.''
   ``I look like Alice in Wonderland,'' a maturer and more assured
Pauley commented after watching her first appearance on the show in
1976 in which she acknowledged that ``one-and-a-half years ago Jane
Pauley was a second-string news reader in Indianapolis.''
   The 25-year-old Pauley was brought to New York to replace
Barbara Walters, the first woman host of the show.
   ``Today'' began in 1952 with Dave Garroway and Jack Lescoulie as
hosts.
</TEXT>

</DOC>