<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1356EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-ThirdWorldDebt     12-25 0679</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Third World Debt,700</SECOND>
<HEAD>East Europe, Third World Debt Seen Rising</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CARL HARTMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Debts of East European and Third World
countries are due to rise next year despite the plan of Treasury
Secretary Nicholas F. Brady to ease some of the heaviest burdens on
debtor countries.
   ``When you have a vibrant, growing economy -- like Indonesia,
for example -- debt can be a good thing if it doesn't grow too
fast,'' said John M. Underwood of the World Bank.
   ``It's a sign that foreigners have confidence that it's a good
place to put their money.''
   Indonesia's debt rose from $43 billion in 1986 to $52 billion
last year, according to figures the bank issued this week.
Indonesia had to pay out nearly $8.5 billion in principal and
interest to its creditors in 1988.
   Third World leaders complain that such outflows leave them litle
to build the schools and buy the equipment to create jobs for their
growing populations. The bank calculated the total outflow at more
than $51 billion this year.
   Until 1983, new loans to developing countries brought them more
money than they had to pay out on the old ones.
   Despite the cost, Third World governments still seek more loans,
if only to help pay the interest on the old loans.
   Underwood is top economist in the International Economics
Department of the World Bank, the largest source of aid to Third
World countries. The aid is also in the form of loans, over $21
billion in the year that ended June 30.
   The bank plans to provide as much as $1.35 billion to Poland,
which got nothing last year but already owes more than $42 billion.
Its new non-Communist leadership is hoping to borrow an additional
$4 billion or more in the coming year.
   Brady's strategy seeks to ease the burden for 39 debtor
countries, by combining debt and interest reduction with new loans
from banks. So far, plans have been developed for three countries:
Mexico, the Philippines and Costa Rica.
   The World Bank estimated that his strategy could save as much as
$6 billion a year for 19 ``severely indebted middle-income
countries'' like Argentina and the Philippines, which owe much of
their debt to private banks. He made his proposal last March,
before the big changes in eastern European countries which now have
better prospects for getting the new loans they want.
   For the poorest countries, governments are the main creditors
rather than banks. During the 1980s, 10 creditor governments have
forgiven $2.3 billion owed to them. The United States, which was
not among the 10, has promised to forgive another billion. New aid
to these countries, most of them in Africa, is now largely in the
form of grants.
   Two officials of Resources for the Future, a private study group
in Washington, said that the United States has an interest in
easing the debt burden: the heaviest debtors are among the biggest
buyers of U.S. goods. The less they have to pay out to banks, the
more they have left over to buy the products of U.S. farms and
industries, they pointed out.
   ``The net result of easing debt burdens would be more robust
economies that would support more stable political systems and
create stronger markets for U.S. exports,'' wrote Elaine M. Koerner
and George E. Rossmiller in the fall issue of ``Resource for the
Future,'' the organization's quarterly publication.
   The World Bank predicted that the debt of 111 countries will
rise to $1.189 trillion in 1990 from $1.165 trillion this year.
Underwood said that the Institute of International Finance, which
collects figures for major private banks, adds another $188 billion
for 10 countries, including the Soviet Union, that the bank does
not count. The Central Intelligence Agency estimated that the
Soviets owed $42.3 billion to western banks last year.
   That would bring the current total to $1.353 trillion. The
figure could be raised in 1990 by new lending to help East European
governments as they switch to something more like the market
economies of the west.
</TEXT>

</DOC>