<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0123EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-SpaceShuttle     12-19 0523</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Space Shuttle,0534</SECOND>
<HEAD>Space Shuttle Delay Sets up Heavy 1990 Launch Schedule</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HOWARD BENEDICT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Aerospace Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The delay of Columbia's satellite
rescue mission until after the holidays sets up 10 space shuttle
flights in 1990, NASA's heaviest schedule ever.
   ``Columbia is essentially ready to fly, so if we get it off
early next year, we don't believe there will be any added pressure
on the rest of the schedule,'' Kennedy Space Center Director
Forrest S. McCartney said Monday after the postponement was
announced.
   The launch had been scheduled for Thursday but was put off until
Jan. 8 to allow more time to correct launch pad problems and to let
most of the center's 16,000 workers go home for the holidays.
   The most shuttle flights conducted in one year was nine, in
1985, before the 1986 Challenger explosion that grounded the
program for 32 months.
   Two missions were flown in 1988. There were five this year as
the National Aeronautics and Space Administration has been
gradually building toward 12 a year by 1992.
   Shuttle managers decided to postpone Columbia's liftoff after
assessing progress on lagging work at renovated pad 39A, which has
not been used since before the Challenger accident. A series of pad
problems, mainly with the fueling systems, caused two previous
short postponements of the mission, which is to deploy one
satellite and retrieve another that is falling to Earth.
   ``The team worked very hard to get Columbia off before
Christmas, but the added work of going off a refurbished launch pad
and a new mobile launch platform really slowed us down,'' said
William B. Lenoir, NASA's associate administrator for space flight.
   The long delay also will enable the agency to essentially shut
down the center as it usually does the last week of each year to
allow employees to take long-planned vacations and to permit an
annual electrical power shutdown so that aging computer and other
systems and components can be overhauled.
   A launch attempt next week would have cost NASA considerable
overtime pay and would have pushed off the power shutdown to 1990,
possibly disrupting work on other shuttle flights.
   ``The launch crews have worked hard this year, and they have
earned a Christmas vacation,'' McCartney said.
   Astronaut Dan Brandenstein, who will command Columbia, said he
and his crew were disappointed about the delay, ``but we are happy
to know we will be spending Christmas with our loved ones. ...
We'll get a good running start at launch after the holidays, and we
can't think of a better way to start a promising new decade.''
   The five astronauts are to spend 10 days in space. They will
release a Navy communications satellite and then track down and
recover the science satellite, a 21,400-pound laboratory that has
orbited the globe nearly six years.
   Columbia's launch is not as urgent as it once was. A few months
ago, it was believed that the science satellite the astronauts will
retrieve, the Long Duration Exposure Facility, would fall back to
Earth in January. That estimate later was revised to mid-February
and just last week to mid-March.
</TEXT>

</DOC>