<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1233EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Congress-Defense Bjt   12-30 0960</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Congress-Defense, Bjt,870</SECOND>
<HEAD>Last Year's Defense Budget Battle Was Just a Warmup</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DONNA CASSATA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fierce fighting between Congress and President
Bush this year over cancellation of a handful of conventional
weapons is a harbinger of the battles expected over the next
military budget, lawmakers say.
   ``Secretary (Dick) Cheney opened an ugly door,'' said Rep. John
Rowland, R-Conn., looking ahead to the certain strife when the
Pentagon chief delivers his fiscal 1991 defense budget to Congress
in late January.
   Cheney touched off a tidal wave of dire predictions in the
Pentagon and concern in Congress when he directed the military
services to consider possible cuts amounting to $140 billion to
$180 billion for fiscal 1992 to 1994.
   On closer examination, the potential cuts in a 1992-94 Defense
Department wish list reflected a Pentagon realization that its
future spending levels would not differ significantly from the
amounts Congress approved during the past five years, defense
analysts and lawmakers say.
   White House budget planners have told Cheney he can spend a
little more than $292 billion in fiscal 1991, which begins Oct. 1.
That means the budget would not keep pace with inflation, which the
administration estimates is averaging 4.1 percent. Congress
approved $286 billion in fiscal 1990.
   When Congress weighs the new budget, it will have to consider
whether to reduce military spending even further.
   Lawmakers balked this year when Cheney proposed a military plan
for fiscal 1990 that eliminated 10 conventional weapons programs,
including the Marine Corps' V-22 Osprey and the Navy's F-14D jet
fighter, but left strategic programs such as the B-2 stealth bomber
relatively intact.
   The fiscal 1990 defense budget that emerged from Congress
restored some of the money for the conventional weapons, cut funds
significantly for the Strategic Defense Initiative and trimmed the
budget for other high-tech programs.
   The nearly two-month process left some lawmakers shaking their
heads in disgust.
   ``In my roughly 20 years involved in this, I've never seen such
forceful, if not ruthless, lobbying,'' Sen. John Warner of
Virginia, ranking Republican on the Senate Armed Services
Committee, said of the wrangling over the F-14D jet fighter.
   But those skirmishes will seem like child's play when Congress
tackles the next budget, most observers say.
   The chairman of the House Armed Services Committee took a swipe
at the Bush administration on Thursday, charging that it bungled
the announcement of future defense cuts by failing to spell out a
military strategy.
   Rep. Les Aspin, D-Wis., said that without a strategy, the
administration faces the likelihood of lawmakers concerned with
parochial interests crafting the defense budget.
   ``I think it will be the most contentious in years ...
especially with the shrinking budget and in light of what's going
on in Eastern Europe,'' said Rep. Ike Skelton, D-Mo., an Armed
Services Committee member.
   ``It will definitely be bloodier,'' said John Isaacs of the
liberal group, Council for a Livable World.
   Although all the budget numbers and possible weapons cuts have
not been hammered out _ and won't be officially until the budget
arrives on Capitol Hill _ likely reductions in the fiscal 1991
budget have emerged in recent weeks.
   To date, they include:
   _Slightly more than $292 billion in Pentagon spending, which
would mean the military budget won't keep pace with inflation,
according to Defense Department sources, who requested anonymity.
   _Stretching out production of the B-2 stealth bomber program,
which could raise the per plane cost of the radar-evading aircraft
from $530 million to as high as $1 billion.
   _Cancellation of the Army's M-1 tank, according to congressional
sources, who asked not to be identified.
   _Reduction of the current troop strength of 2.1 million by about
275,000 and elimination of three Army combat divisions, five and a
fraction Air Force fighter wings and about 60 naval vessels from a
fleet of 562.
   The defense budget for fiscal 1990 requires Cheney to consider
substantial troop cuts by reducing the military personnel account
by $461 million. Cheney must report to Congress by Jan. 1 to
explain how he will meet the cut.
   Also on the chopping block again is the V-22 Osprey, which
Congress delayed a decision on by approving $255 million in
research and development money for the tilt-rotor aircraft in
fiscal 1990.
   The Pentagon recently ordered the Navy to cancel production
contracts for the Osprey, although Congress had freed up more than
$300 million in production money for the aircraft that had been
appropriated in fiscal 1989.
   And The Associated Press reported Friday that the Navy is
seriously considering limiting purchases of its $1.2 billion
Trident submarine to every other year.
   The battle lines being drawn between Congress and the
administration are obvious, according to lawmakers and defense
analysts interviewed in the last two weeks. In the past, the
administration has trimmed the defense budget by eliminating or
stretching out conventional programs popular in many districts
while continuing funds for research and development of strategic
programs.
   During the peacetime buildup of the Reagan administration, when
few programs suffered, there were few complaints.
   ``In the last six to eight years, there was a lot to go
around,'' said Rowland, a member of the House Armed Services
Committee. ``Who got the dough was making the pie.''
   But without a clear threat from Eastern Europe and pressure to
reduce the defense budget, parochial interests in Congress will
clash with administration attempts to maintain a significant budget
for strategic programs.
   ``Our military priorities are wacky,'' said Sen. Carl Levin,
D-Mich., a member of the Senate Armed Services Committee. ``Where
we're eliminating or prematurely terminating or stretching the
production of useful, modern conventional weapons systems in order
to produce an MX missile, the fight will go on. The battle will go
on. This will not be easy.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>