<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0171 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0745EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-HughesLawsuit     12-27 0338</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hughes Lawsuit,0352</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Employee Says Firm Covered Up Microchip Defects</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FULLERTON, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A former employee of the Hughes
Aircraft Co. division here sued the company for $9.6 billion,
contending it covered up a potential defect in more than 4 million
computer chips used in defense systems.
   The suit was filed in June in U.S. District Court in Santa Ana
and was unsealed and served Tuesday, said Frank Barbaro, an
attorney for plaintiff Michael C. Denlinger.
   ``We think our national security is compromised,'' Barbaro said.
   The suit was brought under the federal False Claims Act, which
allows so-called ``whistleblowers'' to share in damage awards in
defense fraud cases.
   Denlinger, a former senior staff engineer at the Hughes
division, alleged that defective chips installed since 1984 caused
two failures in the Navy's submarine-launched Advance Capability
torpedo system.
   While routine screening found two defective chips in torpedoes,
but the suit's allegations are wrong, said Dan Reeder, a spokesman
for Hughes' Ground Systems Group here.
   ``Erroneous,'' Reeder said. ``We have never had any failure of
the test torpedoes due to hardware problems during any of the
hundreds of runs we have gone through.''
   The microchips were used in several defense systems, including
an information-processing system for the radar on board the U.S.S.
Vincennes, which mistakenly shot down an Iranian commercial
jetliner in 1988, the Los Angeles Times reported today.
   In his suit, Denlinger said his repeated memos about possible
cracking of the chips because of a soldering process were ignored.
He resigned in November 1988.
   The basis for the unusually large multibillion-dollar damage
request was not immediately available.
   Hughes said Tuesday that it has inspected every chip since
becoming aware of a cracking problem in 1985, and said it was an
industrywide problem, the Times said.
   Hughes already is the target of another defense-related lawsuit.
It alleges that the Radar Systems Group in El Segundo overcharged
the government $50 million on four radar programs, including one
for the B-2 stealth bomber.
   That suit seeks $120 million in damages.
</TEXT>

</DOC>