<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0602EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-BoatPeople     12-30 0387</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Boat People,0397</SECOND>
<HEAD>Officials Say Other Protests Loom; Police Could Use Gunfire To Quell
Violence</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CINTY LI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HONG KONG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police said today they believe Vietnamese boat
people may torch their detention centers or take hostages to
prevent authorities from forcibly repatriating them to their
impoverished homeland.
   Police also said officers may have to open fire on boat people
if violence in the squalid camps worsens.
   The comments came one day after boat people in the Chi Ma Wan
Detention Center armed with Molotov cocktails, homemade swords and
stones attacked security forces sent to conduct a weapons search.
   ``If police are attacked in closed quarters, police will be
justified to open fire,'' Barry Deegan, deputy Regional Commander
of the Marine Police, said at a news conference on the riot.
   About half of the 3,227 boat people at the camp already have
been denied refugee status and are considered illegal immigrants
facing forced repatriation.
   The Hong Kong government claims they do not qualify for refugee
status because they did not flee persecution but instead sailed
into this British colony to seek a better life.
   Since a first group of 51 boat people were forcibly repatriated
earlier this month, there have been several demonstrations against
the program at Chi Ma Wan and other camps.
   Police issued a statement today that said: ``Male inmates are
believed to have prepared a number of contingency plans to counter
any moves by the authorities to remove them.''
   ``Such plans include lighting fires inside the camps, stoning
the authorities, arming themselves with homemade weapons and
possible hostage- taking,'' the statement said.
   Deegan said some of these tactics were used Friday by boat
people who threw stones, 40 Molotov cocktails and burning blankets
at police and prison officers. Other Vietnamese used swords and
lances.
   Police fired more than 140 tear gas cannisters to disperse the
mob, Deegan said. Fourteen boat people and 24 police officers and
guards were injured. Twenty-five Vietnamese were arrested.
   Prison officers found more than 700 weapons, many made from
water pipes, laundry racks and bed posts.
   About 44,000 Vietnamese who sailed into Hong Kong after mid-June
1988 face repatriation if they cannot prove they fled persecution.
Some 12,000 others in the camps who arrived earlier were
automatically granted refugee status and can be resettled overseas.
</TEXT>

</DOC>