<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1826EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather 1stLd-Writethru a0806 12-24 0363</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0806,0371</SECOND>
<HEAD>Winter Retains Icy Grip On Eastern States</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf to CORRECT number of cities with record lows to
56, sted 57.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The persistent cold wave gave Florida record lows Sunday, and
stirred up a snowstorm that piled snow in 8-foot drifts in the
Carolinas, but a slight warming trend moved onto the Plains
   Record or record-tying lows were reported for 56 cities from
Texas to Florida and north to New England.
   Temperatures dipped below zero as far south as Tennessee and
freezing temperatures were reported as far south as southern
Florida, where Miami cooled to a record 31 degrees.
   The Florida Keys was the only place in the eastern half of the
country without freezing temperatures from late Saturday into
Sunday morning.
   Sunday's official low for the Lower 48 states was 27 degrees
below zero at Houlton, Maine, with unofficial lows of 33 below zero
reported in the West Virginia mountain valley communities of Glady
and Cheat Bridge.
   Wind blew at 40 to 50 mph along the Outer Banks of North
Carolina, causing considerable blowing and drifting snow and
knocking down power lines. In Hyde County, on the coast of the
mainland, the wind created snow drifts up to 8 feet high.
   Snowfall totals in eastern South Carolina ranged up to 14 inches
at Myrtle Beach, with 8 inches at Charleston.
   Light snow dusted northern Florida, but much of the state got
ice on roads and crops.
   Light snow also dusted the southeastern corner of New England.
   In the central part of the nation, temperatures rose rapidly.
   The temperature hit 40 degrees at Chamberlain, S.D., and
Minneapolis warmed into the 20s after nearly five straight days
below zero. Kansas City, Mo., had a December record of 16 below
zero Saturday, but highs in the 30s and 40s were predicted for
Monday in the region.
   Temperatures even remained above freezing overnight across parts
of the northern Plains. Sunday's low of 33 at Dickinson, N.D., was
66 degrees higher than the city's morning low on Friday.
   Clouds and light snow accompanied the warmer weather from Kansas
and Arkansas to Minnesota and Michigan.
</TEXT>

</DOC>