<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0810EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-India     12-30 0416</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-India,0428</SECOND>
<HEAD>Indian Parliament Repeals Punjab Law</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Parliament has repealed a constitutional
amendment that allowed the government to suspend basic human rights
in Punjab state where Sikh extremists have killed more than 7,500
people in the past seven years.
   The decision, taken late Friday night in the final hours of the
first Parliament session convened under Prime Minister V.P. Singh,
was largely a goodwill gesture.
   The amendment, passed in March 1988 when Rajiv Gandhi was prime
minister, would have expired March 30, 1990. Many of the measures
imposed under it had already been lifted earlier by the Gandhi
government in hopes of easing the Punjab situation.
   Singh has promised to seek a political solution to the Punjab
problem and has already traveled to the rich northern farming state
in hope of opening new talks with Sikh militants.
   Sikh extremists, advocating creation of an independent nation
for their faith in Punjab, have killed at least 1,806 people in the
state this year, including 25 since Singh took office Dec. 2.
   The victims include Hindus, the country's largest religious
group, as well as fellow Sikhs considered traitors or
non-supportive of the militant movement.
   Parliament's lower house voted 360-1 to repeal the 59th
amendment to the Constitution, and the upper house cast a unanimous
140 votes in favor of repeal. The repeal will become effective as
soon as it is accepted by President Ramaswamy Venkataraman, whose
post is primarily ceremonial.
   Gandhi, who is now the opposition leader in Parliament, said
earlier his Congress Party would not oppose repeal.
   The policy-making lower house, of which Singh and Gandhi are
members, had 525 seats at stake in the November election. Singh's
National Front and its allies have 277 seats, while the Congress
Party has 193.
   The 59th amendment had allowed the government to declare a state
of emergency in parts or all of Punjab, thereby enabling the
government to invoke other anti-terrorism laws that permit arrest
without charge and indefinite detention. These laws remain on the
books.
   Singh, who is a Hindu like all of his predecessors as prime
minister, led his National Front coalition through the November
election with pledges to seek a political solution to Punjab.
   Sikhs, who have a slight majority in Punjab, have complained of
discrimination against their faith and culture by Hindus.
   Nationally, Sikhs comprise only 2 percent of India's 880 million
people, while Hindus account more about 80 percent.
   The Sikh faith has roots in both Hinduism and Islam.
</TEXT>

</DOC>