<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0922EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WaterWoes     12-18 0317</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Water Woes,0328</SECOND>
<HEAD>Water Restrictions Start in South Florida</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WEST PALM BEACH, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Water restrictions prompted by
South Florida's worst drought in 27 years took effect today,
forcing the shutoff of decorative fountains and raising the
prospect of brown golf courses and dirty cars.
   About 4 million people from the Florida Keys to the
sprinkler-equipped estates of Palm Beach, more than 200 miles to
the north, must reduce water consumption 15 percent under the first
regional restrictions in nine years.
   The rules were adopted Thursday by the South Florida Water
Management District. Violators can be fined $25.
   Environmentalists charge the Everglades are being shortchanged,
and golf course operators worry that the winter tourist season may
wither along with their greens. Golf is a $5 billion-a-year
business in Florida.
   ``The aesthetics are going to suffer,'' said Steve Kuhn, greens
superintendent at Miami's famous Doral Country Club. ``Things won't
be as lush.''
   Lawn watering and car washing are permitted only between 4 a.m.
and 8 a.m., three days a week, on alternating days according to
whether the house is odd- or even-numbered. No outdoor water use is
allowed on Fridays.
   Golf-course watering, pool filling and washing of boats, streets
and walks have been restricted or banned. Fountains have been
ordered shut off.
   South Florida is in its worst dry spell since 1962. Some areas
have gotten 33 inches less rain than normal during the past 14
months, and the area is heading into the dry season, which runs
through May.
   Environmentalists complained that 6.1 billion gallons of
Everglades water had been diverted in November for drinking and
farming. ``In times of water shortage, wildlife interests suffer
first and benefit last,'' said Paul Parks of the Florida Wildlife
Federation.
   District officials say golf courses are among the biggest water
users, consuming 250,000 to 1 million gallons a night. An average
household uses about 250 gallons a day.
</TEXT>

</DOC>