<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1027EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Brazil 1stLd-Writethru a0458 12-19 0720</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Brazil, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0458,0738</SECOND>
<HEAD>Unofficial Count Calls Collor de Mello Winner in Brazilian Election</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to UPDATE vote totals, unofficial winner
might be announced today, current president offering to resign early; Picks
up 6th graf, `Globo TV ...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TODD LEWAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRASILIA, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Supporters of socialist presidential
candidate Luis Inacio da Silva refused to concede defeat and
accused the nation's biggest television network and private bus
companies of sabotaging their campaign.
   The official tally today had conservative free-market advocate
Fernando Collor de Mello leading da Silva by 2.46 million votes,
with 90.36 percent of the ballots counted in Brazil's first direct
presidential election in 29 years.
   The winner could be announced this afternoon, Superior Electoral
Court spokesman Irineu Tamanini said. Final results will be known
by Wednesday, he said.
   Out-going President Jose Sarney said he would step down from
office early if Congress voted to shorten his five-year mandate.
   ``If the Congress wishes, I won't be an obstacle,'' said Sarney,
a civilian who took office in 1985 to end a 21-year right-wing
military regime. Sarney was chosen in an Electoral College vote
coordinated by Brazil's top generals.
   The new president is scheduled to succeed Sarney for a five-year
term March 15. However, pressure is mounting for Sarney to resign
early to allow the new president to adopt emergency economic
measures.
   News of Collor de Mello's lead stabilized financial markets
Monday and triggered a plunge of the dollar on the illegal, but
tolerated, black market.
   Globo TV, the nation's biggest network, on Monday projected
Collor de Mello would defeat da Silva by 6.27 percent of total
votes cast.
   The conservative candidate led by 3 million votes, or 5.1
percent of valid ballots, in the network's unofficial tally, which
was based on 86.8 percent of returns announced by state election
officials.
   The owner of Globo TV, media tycoon Roberto Marinho, supported
Collor de Mello during the campaign.
   Officials of da Silva's Workers Party said they would sue the
network, accusing it of giving Collor de Mello more television time
in news broadcasts in the days leading up to the vote.
   The party officials also accused the network of portraying the
conservative candidate in a more favorable light than his leftist
adversary.
   All TV time during Brazilian elections is strictly controlled by
the Supreme Electoral Court.
   ``We'll follow this to the last vote and show the Court how much
Globo TV influenced the election's outcome,'' said Workers Party
President Luiz Gushiken.
   Federal Police Chief Romeu Tuma said officials were
investigating charges by the Workers Party that voters couldn't
reach polling stations in the states of Bahia and Ceara _ both
strong da Silva regions _ because private bus companies pulled
their vehicles off the streets.
   Collor de Mello, 40, advocates free-market policies and moral
cleanup in government. He says Brazil's $110 billion foreign debt,
the largest in the Third World, should be paid, but under less
burdensome conditions.
   Brazil's business, military and media establishments have closed
ranks behind Collor de Mello, who comes from a prominent family in
the northeastern state of Alagoas, long established in politics.
   The Marxist-oriented de Silva, 44, has ured immediate suspension
of payments on the foreign debt, and advocates sweeping land, urban
reform and the redistribution of income.
   Brazilians on Sunday cast ballots to choose a successor to
President Jose Sarney for a five-year term in a historic vote
marking the return of democratic rights after 21 years of military
rule. The country of 150 million people has 82 million registered
voters.
   Sarney is a civilian but gained office through a
military-coordinated Electoral College vote in 1985.
   Da Silva was bouyed early in the official count by returns from
the major southern cities of Porto Alegre and Rio de Janeiro, his
main strongholds.
   But Collor de Mello overtook da Silva when returns came in from
remote central and northern regions, where the conservative had an
edge.
   Collor de Mello appeared briefly Monday afternoon outside his
Brasilia mansion, waving and making a victory sign. He made no
comment on the count to reporters.
   Da Silva and Collor de Mello were the top vote-getters in a
field of 21 candidates in first-round balloting Nov. 15. Neither
obtained a majority needed to win so the runoff was held.
</TEXT>

</DOC>