<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0959EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-EastGermany 1stLd-Writethru   12-21 0647</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-East Germany, 1st Ld - Writethru,a0533,0662</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mitterrand Meets East German Leaders; United Germany on Agenda</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 4 grafs to UPDATE with Mitterrand condemning Romanian
leader. Pickup 2nd pvs, `His visit...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH G. SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Francois Mitterrand of France said
today that the days of Romanian leader Nicolae Ceausescu are
numbered and called for his replacement.
   ``It is a regime of personal, family power that has no honest
reason to remain,'' Mitterrand said at a news conference during his
three-day visit to East Germany. ``I think that the days of this
regime, in a Europe in full movement, are numbered. But at what
price!''
   In his first condemnation of the bloody suppression of protests
in Romania, Mitterrand ruled out foreign intervention to topple
Ceausescu. He said ``the response has to come from Romania.''
   Mitterrand also met with East German political leaders today to
express the concerns of the West about the possibility of German
unification.
   His visit came as West German Chancellor Helmut Kohl told West
German lawmakers that the Germanys plan to strengthen all economic
and political ties.
   But Kohl also tried to ease the concerns of European nations
worried about a united Germany, saying the growing closeness of the
two countries can only help the continent.
   Meanwhile, the West German government said East Germany would
open Berlin's Brandenburg Gate on Friday. The gate is a historic
portion of the Berlin Wall viewed by many as a symbol of German
unity.
   Kohl, East German Premier Hans Modrow, West Berlin Walter
Momper, and East Berlin Mayor Erhard Krack will participate in the
historic ceremonies, said government spokesman Hans Klein.
   The official East German news agency ADN said Mitterrand met
with Modrow and that the ``joint responsibility for balance in
Europe'' was the main topic.
   Mitterrand and Modrow also discussed the possibility of
expanding ties, while the East German premier expressed interest in
a trade and cooperation agreement with the European Economic
Community, ADN said.
   It added that Mitterrand had reacted ``positively'' to the idea
of closer East German ties to the EEC.
   But before leaving Paris on Wednesday, Mitterrand said: ``For
the whole of Europe, it would not be good _ indeed it would be very
dangerous _ to reopen the issue of the existing borders.''
   In an interview with East German television, he also said the
``two paths open for the Germans are the democratic path and the
peaceful path.''
   The possibility of reunification was raised after the
pro-democracy movement recently forced the Communist Party in East
Germany to oust its hard-line leaders, lift travel restrictions and
open the Berlin Wall.
   Mitterrand arrived Wednesday, a few hours after Kohl Germany
ended an emotionally charged visit to East Germany that brought out
thousands advocating reunification.
   During Mitterrand's visit, French and East German officials are
to sign several agreements, including a five-year project for
closer economic and technical cooperation.
   At a state dinner Wednesday hosted by East Germany's interim
president Manfred Gerlach, a non-Communist, Mitterrand paid tribute
to the East German pro-democracy movement and said the Germans
should determine their own future.
   But he stressed that ``no country may impose its political
system on another.'' He said closer German ties would result in the
context of a strengthened European Community and a general
overcoming of the continent's division. Mitterrand is representing
the 12-nation EC, whose rotating presidency France holds until Dec.
31.
   He is also the first head of state from the three western World
War II Allies to visit East Berlin.
   The United States, Soviet Union, France and Britain have
ultimate authority over Berlin, a result of the postwar occupation
of Hitler's defeated Third Reich.
   While relations between Kohl and Mitterrand are close, the
French leader's statements before his trip highlighted traditional
French wariness of a strong Germany at the heart of Europe.
</TEXT>

</DOC>