<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1112EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Brazil-Election 2ndLd-Writethru   12-18 0779</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Brazil-Election, 2nd Ld-Writethru,a0488,0802</SECOND>
<HEAD>Unofficial Results Show Rightist Leading in Presidential Race</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 8 graf to UPDATE vote totals, TV network declaring
Collor de Mello the winner; Picks up 7th graf, `Brazilians went ...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY10</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TODD LEWAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRASILIA, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Conservative Fernando Collor de Mello
held a slim lead over his socialist adversary in Brazil's first
popular presidential election since 1960, according to partial
returns today.
   Sunday's runoff was seen as a referendum on two decades of rapid
but unequal growth that has brought 1,500 percent annual inflation,
sinking real wages and corruption, and the Third World's biggest
foreign debt, $110 billion.
   Voters could choose between two kinds of reform to attack the
problems _ Collor de Mello's free-market policies or the platform
of Luis Inacio Lula da Silva that includes redistribution of land
and wealth, reform in education and health care and a moratorium on
Brazil's foreign debt.
   The Supreme Electoral Court had Collor de Mello leading da Silva
by 1 percentage point, after counting 33.8 percent of the returns.
   Globo TV, the nation's largest network, had Collor de Mello
ahead by 2.9 million votes, or 4.9 percent of the total, with 85.7
percent of the votes counted in an unofficial tally.
   The network, which used its computers to tally the returns from
individual states, today projected Collor de Mello as the winner.
   Electoral Court spokesman Irineu Tamanini said Collor de Mello's
lead was expected to grow as returns came in from the candidate's
strongholds in remote central and northern regions. The official
count was slower because state returns were doublechecked to avoid
error.
   Officials said the final tally would not be ready until
Wednesday.
   Brazilians went to the polls on a jubilant, peaceful election
day in a historic vote hailed as a huge step toward the return of
civilian rule after a rightist military regime ruled from 1964 to
1985.
   Many waved banners, honked horns and sported T-shirts and
buttons favoring one or the other candidate for the five-year
presidential term.
   Brazil, with 150 million people, is the world's third-most
populous democracy, after India and the United States. Brazil has
82 million registered voters, but turnout was reported lower than
expected in some regions.
   Two exit polls predicted Collor de Mello, an athletic
40-year-old former governor from a wealthy and powerful political
clan, would win by between 3 percent and 4 percent.
   One survey, by the Brazilian Institute of Public Opinion and
Statistics, the country's biggest private polling company, gave
Collor de Mello 52 percent of the vote and da Silva 48 percent.
   A second exit poll, by the respected DataFolha polling
institute, gave Collor de Mello 51.5 percent of the electorate. It
forecast 48.5 percent for da Silva, a bearded gravel-voiced labor
leader who grew up in poverty.
   The surveys buoyed officials of the Collor de Mello camp.
   ``We are not celebrating yet, but we are relieved because the
polls are confirming our expectations of victory,'' Claudio
Humberto Rosa e Silva, spokesman for Collor de Mello's rightist
National Reconstruction Party, said Sunday.
   Officials of the 44-year-old da Silva's Workers Party said it
was too early to concede defeat.
   Collor de Mello, a former governor of Alagoas who advocates
free-market policies and battling corruption in government, is
backed by Brazil's business, military and media establishments.
   The coalition behind da Silva, called the Brazil Popular Front,
includes Marxists, unionists, top singers, soap opera stars, former
leftist guerillas and the dominant liberal wing of Brazil's
powerful Roman Catholic Church.
   The new president is to replace lame-duck President Jose Sarney
on March 15. However, there is growing sentiment for Sarney to
resign before then. Two of Sarney's Cabinet ministers said Sunday
the president-elect should take office soon to save Brazil's ailing
economy.
   Heavy rains in central, northeastern and far southern Brazil
reduced voter turnout on Sunday.
   A number of voters wrote personal messages to the candidates on
the ballots, which nullified their votes.
   One voter in Belem, capital of the northern Amazon state of
Para, wrote on a ballot, ``Please do something to help the young
people in Brazil who are taking drugs.''
   Collor de Mello and da Silva were the top vote-getters in a
field of 21 candidates in first-round balloting Nov. 15. Neither
obtained a majority needed to win, and the two went to a runoff
election.
   The last popularly elected president of Brazil was Janio
Quadros. He resigned in 1961 after seven months in office citing
``occult forces.'' A right-wing military regime overthrew Quadros'
successor, his vice-president, Joao Goulart, and ruled until 1985.
   Sarney is a civilian but gained office through a
military-coordinated Electoral College vote in 1985.
</TEXT>

</DOC>