<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0183 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1935EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-PRI--Briefs Adv28   12-26 0767</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-PRI--Briefs, Adv 28,0790</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv28</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Thursday, Dec. 28, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Complaint Seeks to Ban Senior Banking Discounts</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PLANTATION, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 45-year-old businessman is seeking to
outlaw the widespread practice of offering banking discounts to
older customers.
   Peter Levine, in a complaint filed with Broward County's Human
Relations Division, asks that county banks cease the deals to those
55 or older.
   ``I don't have anything against older people,'' said Levin,
owner of a tote bag manufacturing business in Hialeah. ``I just
think it's discrimination.''
   ``We believe it is proper,'' said William Darby, a vice
president at C&amp;S Bank, where Levine has an account. ``A lot of
restaurants, banks and movie theaters have done it for years.''
   If the Human Relations Division is unable to resolve the
complaint it will go to the county's Human Rights Board.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Actor David Keith Envisions United Elders In `Grand Corp'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KNOXVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor David Keith wants America to stop
wasting a precious resource _ the wisdom of its aged.
   ``To harness this power of experience and challenge the energies
of youth, to put the power back in the hands of experience, I
proposed the Grand Corps,'' said Keith, who envisions building an
organization of people 60 and older to speak out on the issues from
pornography to ecology.
   ``When I look around the country, I see young people pushing
their grandparents and the older people into a corner, putting them
in front of the TV and saying, `Here, keep your mouth shut,'''
Keith said.
   ``And I don't see the older people fighting back. I don't see
them saying, `My mind is still alive. I've got good ideas that you
ought to listen too.'''
   Keith, 35, who most recently played Oliver North in a TV
miniseries and Elvis Presley on the big screen, hopes to form the
first Grand Corps chapter in his hometown of Knoxville. He thinks
senior citizens, once unified, could carry tremendous clout both
locally and nationally because of their sheer numbers.
   Noting the growing percentage of elderly Americans, he said,
``Imagine 52 million letters arriving in Congress on the same day
to get a pornography bill put through. They are going to listen.''
   Keith said he didn't expect to get anything more from the Grand
Corps than a chance to honor the love he received from his late
grandparents.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Fear of Crime Makes Elderly Prisoners in Own Homes</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TALLAHASSEE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Many of the retirees who move to
Florida to enjoy their ``golden years'' wind up prisoners in their
homes because of their fear of crime, a state task force on crime
and the elderly reported.
   The 65-page report concluded that people over 60 are victimized
less often than younger people, but ``the resulting injuries or
incurred damages are more devastating'' for the older victims.
``Older persons live in abject terror of such every-day occurrences
as going to the grocery store or merely stepping outside to pick up
their Social Security checks,'' it said.
   Florida has the oldest population in the United States; by next
year, more than 2.4 million people 65 and older will live in the
Sunshine State.
   ``The high concentration of the aged in one environmental
setting acts as a magnet to criminals,'' said the report by the
Attorney General's Task Force on Crimes and the Elderly. ``Public
housing, especially for the elderly, is a prime target for purse
snatchings, robberies and burglaries.''
   Additionally, the elderly are more likely to be harmed or held
hostage during a burglary attempt as failing vision or hearing
leave them unaware there is someone in the house. And ``the elderly
are perceived by juveniles as easy targets for violence and
crime,'' said the report.
   In addition to threats from unknown criminals, the elderly are
particularly vulnerable to smooth-talkers. It is extremely easy to
control someone's assets, merely by having them sign a power of
attorney, and some unscrupulous funeral homes are adept at catching
the elderly at vulnerable times, the report said.
   Among its recommendations, the task force urged creating a
Department of Elderly Affairs, a measure already approved by voters
in 1988. The report said the Department of Health and
Rehabilitative Services had become too large and bureaucratic to
function efficiently and that the agency's Division of Aging and
Adult Services appeared to be the poor stepchild of a cumbersome
system.
   The report, based on research and testimony gathered during four
months last winter, also noted that the state has begun revising
its guardianship laws and imposing tougher penalties for crimes
committed against elderly citizens.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Dec. 28</NOTE>

</DOC>