<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1345EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Christmas-Germany     12-25 0437</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Christmas-Germany,0451</SECOND>
<HEAD>West and East Berliners Celebrate Christmas Together</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH G. SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Leonard Bernstein transformed a Christmas
performance of Beethoven's Ninth Symphony into an appeal for
brotherhood as West and East Berliners mingled freely in the
divided city for the first Christmas in 28 years.
   ``I am experiencing a historical moment _ incomparable with
others in my long, long life,'' the American conductor said during
the nationally televised performance Monday.
   Bernstein conducted an international group of musicians in the
Schauspielhaus, capping three days of performances that celebrated
the demise of the Berlin Wall and the struggle for freedom
throughout Eastern Europe.
   The Ninth Symphony was inspired by German writer Friedrich
Schiller's 18th century poem ``Ode to Joy.'' In the concert,
Bernstein substituted the word ``freedom'' for ``joy'' in the
chorus to reflect his personal message.
   The 71-year-old musician conducted the same symphony at the
Philharmonic in West Berlin in a performance timed to end at
midnight Saturday, when West Germans were allowed to travel without
visas into East Germany for the first time.
   More than 1,000 people poured into the Schauspielhaus for the
10:30 a.m. Christmas concert, while hundreds more packed the square
in front of the concert hall to watch the performance on a giant
television monitor.
   The concert was also broadcast live in more than 20 countries by
satellite.
   Bernstein united an international group of musicians from East
and West Germany as well as the United States, Britain, France and
the Soviet Union _ the four victorious World War II allies still
technically responsible for governing Berlin.
   The East German government presented Bernstein the ``Star of
People's Friendship.''
   In the city, hundreds of thousands of Berliners passed freely
through the wall via crossings created in the concrete barrier
after East Germany threw open its borders six weeks ago.
   West Berliners had to wait up to three hours to cross into East
Berlin by car and there were long lines at two new crossings at the
Brandenburg Gate.
   One West Berliner riding a bicycle and dressed up as Santa Claus
failed to persuade border guards to let him through ahead of the
rest of the crowd.
   Berliners packed cafes and restaurants on Unter den Linden, East
Berlin's most elegant boulevard, while in West Berlin, street
vendors did a brisk business selling sausages on a cold, sunny day.
   East German border police reported that 274,500 East Germans had
crossed into West Germany, while 268,000 West Germans went into
East Germany.
   It was busier in Berlin, however, where 220,000 East Berliners
went West and 257,000 West Berliners went East.
</TEXT>

</DOC>