<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0210 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1143EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-BoardofTrade Open   12-19 0302</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Board of Trade, Open,0315</SECOND>
<HEAD>Grain Futures Drift Lower</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Most grain and soybean futures prices drifted
lower in light early trading today on the Chicago Board of Trade.
   Trading volume was thin and activity slow, typical for a
pre-holiday period.
   ``The main characteristic of the market today is its quiet, dull
trade _ it's directionless,'' said Victor Lespinasse, a floor
trader with Dean Witter Reynolds Inc.
   Rainfall overnight in Brazil, the world's second-largest soybean
producer, kept pressure on soybean futures prices.
   Traders seemed to ignore the continuing frigid weather in the
Great Plains and Midwest, which helped commodity prices last week.
   The Agriculture Department's rejection of wheat export bids from
Morocco and Egypt added another bearish factor while indications
that India is in the market for palm oil were perceived as helpful
to the soybean oil market.
   In early trading, wheat futures were \ cent lower to { cent
higher with the contract for delivery in December at $4.14} a
bushel; corn was { cent to } cent lower with December at $2.34 a
bushel; oats were 1{ cents to 2 cents lower with December at $1.40
a bushel; soybeans were { cent to 1{ cents lower with January at
$5.79} a bushel.
   Cattle futures were mixed while pork futures were lower in early
trading on the Chicago Mercantile Exchange.
   Live cattle were .32 cent lower to .18 cent higher with December
at 78.45 cents a pound; feeder cattle were .23 cent lower to .08
cent higher with January at 84.40 cents a pound; live hog futures
were .10 cent to .35 cent lower with December at 53.10 cents a
pound; frozen pork bellies were .05 cent to .70 cent lower with
February at 51.65 cents a pound.
   Cattle futures settled mixed on Monday while pork futures
advanced.
</TEXT>

</DOC>