<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0343EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Japan-Markets     12-22 0466</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Japan-Markets,0479</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar, Yen Slip</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Uncertain prospects over interest rates in Japan
and the United States, coupled with the Panama situation, slumped
the dollar against the Japanese yen and share prices on the Tokyo
Stock Exchange today.
   The dollar closed at 143.67 yen, down 0.10 yen from Thursday's
close of 143.77 yen. After opening at 143.67 yen, the currency
ranged between 143.65 yen and 143.79 yen.
   The Nikkei Stock Average of 225 selected issues, a 296.52-point
loser Thursday, lost 175.11 points, or 0.45 percent, closing the
week at 38,040.37.
   Masahiko Sahara, a dealer with Industrial Bank of Japan Ltd.,
said the market was ``unable to find the dollar's direction,''
squeezed by the issues of Japan's official discount rate and signs
of easing U.S. monetary credit.
   Finance Minister Ryutaro Hashimoto, reiterating his earlier
stance of three days ago, told a news conference this morning that
current price and monetary conditions in Japan do not require
changes in monetary policy.
   But Hashimoto added monetary authorities will look at movements
in currency and money markets in determining when to raise the key
lending rate.
   Lower interest rates make a country's currency less attractive
to investors.
   Yasushi Mieno, the new governor of the Bank of Japan, said in an
interview with the Nihon Keizai Shimbun, Japan's largest economic
newspaper, that a discount-rate hike would be needed to stem
excessive price rises and stabilize the foreign exchange rate, the
paper reported today.
   During a briefing Thursday on wholesale price trends, central
bank officials said upward price pressures have been increasing
over the last few months.
   A Bank of Japan official, briefing reporters on condition of
anonymity, said higher prices for oil and natural gas, the yen's
continued weakness and the effect of higher wages on prices in
certain sectors, such as machinery, were threatening price
stability.
   Earlier this week, news reports said the Bank of Japan planned
to raise its official discount rate by 0.5 percentage points from
the current 3.75 percent points some time this week. The Finance
Ministry and central bank officials have denied any central bank
action would be taken in the near future.
   The official discount rate, the rate the Bank of Japan charges
on loans to commercial banks, influences other domestic interest
rates.
   ``Speculation that the central bank now is considering to hike
its key lending rate next year, probably in January or early
February'' sent many investors reteating to the sidelines, said
Sachiko Hata, a dealer with Nikko Securities Co.
   Investors were wary how the situation in Panama following
Wednesday's U.S. military intervention in that Central American
country would develop, she said.
   Ms. Hata said prospects that the U.S. monetary authorities would
lower the nation's discount rate early next year also worked as a
negative factor in the day's securities market.
</TEXT>

</DOC>