<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0180 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1819EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Graves 2ndLd-Writethru a0785 12-22 0466</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Graves, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0785,0477</SECOND>
<HEAD>People Digging Up Mass Graves to Find Relatives</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 1 grafs after 5th graf, ``All had ...'' with quote.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DUSAN STOJANOVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TIMISOARA, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of people Friday were digging
up mass graves discovered in the forest district of Timisoara,
trying to find the remains of their friends and relatives killed in
last weekend's crackdown.
   Three such mass graves are believed to be holding as many as
4,500 corpses of people massacred by the dreaded security forces on
Saturday, Sunday and Monday. There was no independent confirmation
of the number of dead.
   Timisoara, 500 miles from Bucharest near the Yugoslav and
Hungarian border, was the center of protests that were brutally
suppressed by the regime of President Ceausescu, who was reported
overthrown Thursday.
   West German television, apparently showing footage provided by
Romanian TV, showed muddied, naked corpses being dug out and placed
on white sheets, one after the other.
   All had their feet tied together with wire. A dead boy, about
three or four years old, was shown lying on the ground.
   ``Not even Hitler killed his own children, and here they used
automatic machine gun bursts to strafe them down,'' said Slavomir
Gvozdenovic, editor of a literary review in Timisoara.
   The situation in this city of 350,000 people was chaotic, and
there did not seem any authority at all beyond the downtown opera
square.
   Vasile Todorescu, an electrician, said he was trying to find his
20-year-old son, who disappeared during the unrest.
   He said the corpses had been transported by garbage trucks to
the area and the drivers were later shot by the police so no
witnesses whould be left.
   Sorin Oprea, head of the Democratic Front of Romania, which
seems to be at least in partial control of Timisoara, said his
group does not recognize the new national leadership being set up
in Bucharest.
   ``We want all Romanian citizens to elect the country's new
leadership,'' said Oprea, a mechanic. ``In Bucharest they only
fought for two days while our struggle was much longer.''
   Oprea, 37, was interviewed at the downtown opera house which is
currently being used as the headquarters of the provisional
municipal leadership.
   He was wounded in the leg during clashes with the police and has
not slept for three days, he said.
   ``Our struggle is not yet over,'' Oprea said.
   People approaching the opera house were being searched by
plainclothes volunteers, some of whom were armed with automatic
rifles.
   The people's militia, as the volunteers call themselves,
captured their weapons from troops during the weekend fighting,
they said.
   About 1,000 activists were occupying the opera building Friday
night in front of which more than 20,000 people were still
rejoicing over the ouster of Ceausescu.
</TEXT>

</DOC>