<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0103 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1851EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SriLanka     12-26 0478</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sri Lanka,0489</SECOND>
<HEAD>Guerrillas Surrender to Sri Lankan Army</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEXTER CRUEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>COLOMBO, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 150 members of an outlawed
Tamil militia surrendered to the Sri Lankan army Tuesday after
trekking through the jungle for three days to escape rival Tamil
guerrillas.
   The weary members of the outlawed Tamil National Army contacted
the Sri Lankan army Monday in northeastern Nidamwela town and were
brought to a makeshift detention center 30 miles away, military
officials said.
   They surrendered a few hours after guerrillas of the Liberation
Tigers of Tamil Eelam attacked a Tamil National Army camp, killing
44 militants in the Batticaloa district, the officials said on
condition of anonymity.
   The Tigers, the strongest guerrilla group in Sri Lanka's Tamil
ethnic minority, have intensified their power struggle with rival
Tamil militants as Indian peacekeeping troops wind down their
2{-year effort to pacify the northeastern part of the island.
   The Tigers and the Sri Lankan government claim the departing
Indians have armed and trained 4,000 members of the Tamil National
Army. India has repeatedly insisted it only trained a volunteer
force sanctioned by the Sri Lankan government _ and not the Tamil
National Army, which has been outlawed by President Ranasinghe
Premadasa's government.
   Indian troops started arriving in Sri Lanka July 30, 1987, under
an accord with India in an effort to settle the insurrection. But
the Tigers reneged on the accord and attacked the Indians, who were
supposed to oversee a surrender of arms.
   India agreed in September to withdraw its last troops by Dec. 31
but later said it was unlikely to meet that deadline. An estimated
25,000 Indian soldiers remain.
   Tamils, who make up 18 percent of the island's 16 million
people, claim discrimination by the majority Sinhalese, and Tamil
militants want a separate homeland. The revolt has claimed 11,000
lives since it started in 1983.
   The 155 militants had slipped out of the camp Friday in search
of food but had been spotted and pursued by the Tamil Tigers, one
of the militants told reporters who were flown to Polonnarywa, 100
miles northeast of Colombo.
   ``We do not want to go back, we will be killed,'' said a young
Tamil in the abandoned warehouse housing the militants.
   The military officials said the guerrillas, most aged 18 to 24,
were being held in protective custody in the barbed wire-fenced
warehouse. He said the militants would be flown to Colombo soon.
   The officials displayed an array of weapons they said had been
seized from the militants. Officials in Colombo said the arms
included 83 Soviet-designed AK47 assault rifles, a light machine
gun, four submachine guns, five mortars, two rocket launchers, five
hand grenades and a cache of ammunition.
   On Monday, soldiers killed seven Sinhalese militants in separate
battles in north central Anuradhapura and central Kandy districts,
a government statement said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>