<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 0020EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-China-HongKong     12-31 0309</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Hong Kong,0318</SECOND>
<HEAD>China Blasts Britain Over Right Of Abode Plan</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM ABRAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   China on Saturday said a British plan to give
special residence rights to 50,000 Hong Kong families was a ``gross
violation'' of Sino-British agreements on the return of Hong Kong
to Chinese sovereignty in 1997.
   The Foreign Ministry said in a statement it was ``greatly
surprised'' at the British plan and threatened to take unspecified
retaliatory action.
   Britain on Dec. 20 announced it will give residence rights to
50,000 households, about 225,000 Hong Kong Chinese, to help prevent
a brain drain of the colony's most talented people before 1997.
   The British government has argued that guarantees of right of
abode will ease concerns about Chinese rule after 1997 and will
encourage people to remain in Hong Kong.
   An estimated 42,000 people, many frightened by China's bloody
suppression of the pro-democracy movement this spring, have
emigrated this year, and 55,000 are expected to leave in 1990.
   The Foreign Ministry statement, carried by the official Xinhua
News Agency, said the British plan ``is a gross violation of
(Britain's) own solemn commitment'' made in 1984 when the two
countries agreed on the reversion of Hong Kong.
   It quoted a 1984 memorandum stating that Hong Kong citizens with
British passports can use the passports after July 1, 1997
``without conferring the right of abode in the United Kingdom.''
   Some 3.25 million Hong Kong Chinese in the territory of 6
million people now have British passports but no residence rights.
   The Foreign Ministry demanded that Britain reverse its position
on residence rights. ``Otherwise, it will have to bear a series of
consequences arising therefrom. The Chinese side reserves the right
to take corresponding measures thereby.''
   It was not clear why it took the Chinese side 10 days to respond
to the British proposal.
</TEXT>

</DOC>