<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0095 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1215EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CDC-DrunkenDriving 1stLd-Writethru a0443 12-22 0458</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-CDC-Drunken Driving, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0443,0463</SECOND>
<HEAD>Drunken Driving Problem Worst Over Holidays, CDC Reports</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS one graf after 4th graf, `The National...' to incorporate
another estimate reported in Chicago-dated a0488.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BYRD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Federal health officials have a grim holiday
message for the nation: 1,770 Americans are going to die in highway
crashes in the next 11 days, half in wrecks where somebody was
drinking.
   Alcohol-related highway deaths seem to be declining slightly,
the national Centers for Disease Control said Thursday. But
statistics show a higher rate of highway deaths _ and a higher rate
of drunken-driving wrecks _ during the year-end holiday period.
   ``This is not to say don't travel,'' said Dr. Terence L. Chorba,
a CDC researcher. ``This is to say don't travel drunk, particularly
if you're the one behind the wheel.''
   The National Highway Traffic and Safety Administration projects
that 1,770 highway deaths and 48,000 injuries will occur on the
roads over the Hanukkah-Christmas-New Year's holiday travel season,
which began Thursday and extends to Jan. 2.
   Statisticians at the National Safety Council in Chicago came up
with a lower projection of as many as 770 lives deaths over the
long Christmas and New Year's weekends. The estimate was based on
data compiled during the holidays in previous years, seasonal
weather factors and national driving safety trends.
   The worst day of the season is expected to be Saturday, when the
highway administration predicts 235 traffic deaths. Friday is
second, with 197, followed by Sunday _ Christmas Eve _ with 176 and
New Year's Day with 165.
   ``Over the holidays we see more ... miles traveled, and you have
an increase in the number of fatalities _ but you also have an
increase in the number involving drunk driving,'' Chorba said.
   Last year, 50 percent of the deaths on Christmas involved
drunken driving, compared to 39 percent on non-holiday days. For
the day of New Year's Eve, it was 36 percent, but for New Year's
Day, including the hours after midnight, it was 58 percent.
   In 1988 overall, 47,093 deaths were reported in U.S.
motor-vehicle crashes; 18,503, or 39 percent, involved drunken
driving _ someone with a blood-alcohol count of 0.10 or more,
legally drunk in most states.
   That percentage is down somewhat from 1987, when 18,529 drunken
driving crashes were reported, 40 percent of the 46,386 traffic
deaths. The figure was 46 percent in 1982.
   Chorba noted, however, that fully half of the fatal crashes
still involve someone who has been drinking, even if the person is
not legally drunk.
   ``Fifty percent of the fatalities on the roads have some alcohol
component to them, whether it's a driver or a bicyclist or a
pedestrian,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>