<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0254 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0739EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Lincoln-Researcher     12-18 0434</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lincoln-Researcher,0452</SECOND>
<HEAD>Researcher Stands By 1984 Report Supporting S&amp;L That Later Failed</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The researcher whose 1984 report said a
controversial investment strategy posed no danger to Lincoln
Savings and Loan says he stands by his evaluation even though those
investments have been blamed in the S&amp;L's subsequent failure.
   George J. Benston, now a professor at Emory University, was with
the University of Rochester in New York when he issued the study,
paid for by Lincoln Savings of Irvine, Calif.
   ``I stand by the conclusions I drew from the data I had,''
Benston said last week.
   The report was used by Lincoln to battle regulators who sought
to block it from increasing its ``direct investments'' in real
estate and undeveloped land.
   In a direct investment an S&amp;L becomes an owner _ not merely a
lender _ in a project, putting off income from loan payments in
favor of a hoped-for profit when the project is sold. For Lincoln,
many of those deals went sour and have been blamed in part for
Lincoln's collapse.
   Benston's report was endorsed by Alan Greenspan, then a private
economist paid by Lincoln and now chairman of the Federal Reserve
Board.
   Greenspan has been criticized for his role, as have five U.S.
senators _ all beneficiaries of campaign contributions from Lincoln
Savings' owner _ who held a special meeting with S&amp;L examiners to
ask why the thrift was the subject of federal scrutiny.
   Fifteen of the top 17 S&amp;Ls Benston cited in his report to show
that direct investments were profitable have since failed.
   Benston argues direct investments were not the main reason.
   ``They had big losses on their loan portfolios, not their direct
investments,'' he said.
   Edwin Gray, chairman of the Federal Home Loan Bank Board and the
nation's top S&amp;L regulator from 1983 to 1987, counters that direct
investments played a major role.
   ``I think he (Benston) made a disastrous mistake,'' said Gray,
now president of Chase Federal Bank in Miami. ``I don't know how
much he was paid by Lincoln, but his advice was as wrong as wrong
can be.''
   Benston's report delayed early attacks on direct investments,
Gray said, and ``in significant part, that led to the thrift
crisis.''
   This year Congress voted to phase out S&amp;L authority to make
direct investments.
   Benston, now promoted by Emory University as a thrift industry
expert, said his report merely provided an accurate analysis of
contemporary data.
   ``I'm a researcher,'' he said. ``If it turns out that the world
has changed, I'll change my conclusions. But I still don't know for
sure what happened at Lincoln.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>