<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0219 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2001EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-Panama-KellyText 4thAdd   12-20 0934</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Panama-Kelly Text, 4th Add,a0844 et. seq.,770</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHN: been hurt.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   And the people who were there who may harm them know that we're
present and we're armed and we'll come after them.
   Q: General, do you plan to get dependents or other U.S.
personnel out of Panama now?
   GEN. KELLY: Not immediately. We have not implemented any plan
along those lines.
   Q: General, with some of your goals accomplished, are there any
thought _ is there any thought being given now to withdrawing some
U.S. troops?
   GEN. KELLY: My boss indicated, I think this morning, that there
were no timelines, that we were going to stay there long enough to
get the job done. I don't think I see this as a long, long-term
effort, U.S. troops in Panama, combat troops for months or years,
but I think that it's going to take a little while to help the
country get back on its feet. You've got to realize they've gone
through an awful time over the last couple of years with Noriega,
who has done a great deal to break down the social fabric of the
country, and we've got to try and help them rebuild it.
   Q: General _
   Q: Can you give an update on casualties _ an update on casualty
numbers?
   GEN. KELLY: Yeah, I can. Okay, we've lost so far four
helicopters, but three of those four will probably be _ and this is
an assertion on my part _ repairable, and the fourth one, if we get
it back _ it's in the water _ may be. And that was one Apache and
three observation helicopters. We have had 11 military people _ one
Marine, I believe, the rest soldiers _ killed, 59 wounded, and one
missing, and I mentioned the one dependent who was dead. You know,
one _ one dead American is too many, but, thank God, the numbers
don't appear too high right now.
   Q: Do you know how many of those were accidental, General?
   GEN. KELLY: To my knowledge, none of them were accidental.
   Q: General, on a scale of one to ten, how successful would you
say this operation has been so far?
   GEN. KELLY: Oh, ten. And you're asking the wrong guy.
(Laughter.) I think that it is among the most professionally
executed operations that I have seen in 33 years of military
service. Recall that the _ that the so-called war status was
declared on Friday, the Marine was killed on Saturday, the family
beating and harrassment occurred on Saturday. We made a decision,
and in almost no time at all we were putting our paratroopers and
our Rangers on airplanes and sending them down there. I don't know
that there's another country in the world that can do that. I do
know that I'm a pretty biased guy when it comes to the U.S.
military, and I think that we have the finest leaders we have
available running things in Panama.
   Q: General Kelly, following that if I could sir, in the
aftermath of Grenada, can you tell us, do you have any reports yet
of perhaps communications gear that couldn't communicate back and
forth, men dropped in the wrong place, those kinds of problems
repeating?
   GEN. KELLY: We have indications that human beings in Panama have
made mistakes, you know, history is replete with that. As far as
major glitches are concerned, Ted and I have been on the _ in the
NMCC on the communications. There has never been a second that we
haven't had direct voice communications with the commander and his
staff. In Panama, there's never been a second that they haven't
been in communication with Gen. Steiner, the Southern Task Force
Commander, JTF South, Joint Task Force South. And, no, we have not
had those kind of glitches.
   Q: Did you have any problems with any kind of weather?
   GEN. KELLY: No, no. We had weather problems, of course, up in
Fort Bragg and Pope Air Force Base trying to get out yesterday. We
had an ice storm, and we had one heck of a time getting the
airplanes de-iced, and we had problems out of Travis today with
fog; that slowed us down getting out.
   Q: General, on that point _
   GEN. KELLY: But we still made the TOTs (Time Over Target).
   Q: _ would you like to have started this operation sooner? Would
you like to have had it conducted sooner than one this morning?
   GEN. KELLY: If you could wave a magic wand and get the MAC
(Military Airlift Command) aircraft together and do all those kinds
of things, I would like it to have started just the second the
President said we could go. We were in a position where we had to
tell him that it takes so many hours to get that many airplanes
together, because they're all around the world, and we don't have
an excess number of those aircraft.
   Q: General _
   Q: General, on the amount of equipment we've thrown into this
fight in the way of planes, tanks, helicopters, what force, in
addition to manpower, are we actually bringing to bear here?
   GEN. KELLY: Reasonable force. I am a tanker. We have four tanks
in Panama, and they're Sheridans, which, as you may recall, are
light vehicles that have a 152mm gun and were originally designed
primarily to fire a Shillelagh missile. They came out of the 82nd
Airborne Division, and that's the only TO&amp;E battalion in the Army
left with the Sheridans because the M1 tanks are too heavy to be
air-dropped.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>