<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1257EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Panama 4thLd-Writethru a0520 12-28 0885</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama, 4th Ld - Writethru, a0520,0908</SECOND>
<HEAD>Banks Reopen, Canal Resumes Full Operations</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 5 grafs to UPDATE with Justice Department reax to
report Noriega's associates have left embassy; picks up 4th pvs, `Army
Lt...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PAN1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DOUGLAS GRANT MINE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Banks reopened today, the Panama
Canal resumed 24-hour operations, and a U.S. spokesman said nearly
$6 million in confiscated funds had been turned over to the new
government of President Guillermo Endara.
   The former strongman, Manuel Antonio Noriega, remained inside
the Vatican Embassy. Panama's archbishop, the Rev. Marcos McGrath,
said several of Noriega's associates left the embassy voluntarily.
   ``In general, the number has been getting lower and it will
continue to do so,'' McGrath told reporters outside the Vatican
Embassy. He said some were leaving because there were no charges
against them, and others were negotiating with the new Panamanian
government.
   A U.S. Justice Department spokesman in Washington, when asked
about the report that some had surrendered, said, ``I don't believe
so.''
   But the spokesman, David Runkel, said it's possible ``there may
have been one or more people who have left ... that may include
children.''
   Army Lt. Col. Jerry Murguia, a spokesman for the U.S. Southern
Command, said $5.82 million belonging to Noriega had been
confiscated and released to the Panamanian government.
   Officials said the Panama Canal had returned to its regular
24-hour schedule and worked through the night. The Panama Canal
Commission said 21 ships passed through Wednesday, 35 were
scheduled to go through today and another 150 were waiting for
transit.
   The canal was closed for 48 hours after the United States
invaded Dec. 20, and has been gradually increasing the hours of
operation since then.
   Murguia also said Panama City's international airport should be
reopened by Saturday. It has been closed to commercial aviation
since the invasion.
   Banks in this international financial center reopened throughout
the nation, with First Vice President Ricardo Arias Calderon
appearing at a ceremony at the Central Bank.
   Endara, in a news conference Wednesday, had appealed again to
the Vatican Embassy to surrender Noriega for trial on drug
trafficking charges, but the Vatican today said it had received no
formal request from the Panamanian government and would not simply
push Noriega out and hand him over to U.S. authorities.
   ``We have not received any letter,'' said Joaquin Navarro, the
Vatican's chief spokesman.
   In Texas, President Bush said his administration was determined
to bring Noriega to the United States to stand trial, but admitted
that the Vatican's stand ``complicated things.''
   The U.S. invasion began Dec. 20 and Noriega was on the run until
appearing at the Vatican Embassy on Sunday.
   U.S. troops, armored cars and helicopters have stood watch
outside around the clock to ensure he doesn't escape or get
spirited away.
   Navarro said the Vatican still hoped to resolve the crisis
within days but he gave no details about negotiations.
   He also declined to comment about a story in today's Los Angeles
Times in which the Vatican Embassy in Panama reportedly authorized
U.S. forces to take necessary measures in the event that Noriega or
his associates take the Vatican envoy or any other staff hostage.
   The newspaper said the authorization has been interpreted by
some U.S. officials as an invitation to the United States to seize
the ousted Panamanian dictator from the embassy, while others have
said that isn't the case.
   Navarro said he couldn't comment on the report because he didn't
know the source of information for the report.
   Panama's new government hustled to restore order, screening
members of Noriega's disbanded Defense Forces and incorporating a
growing number of them into a new armed force that includes police.
   Murguia told reporters today that Lt. Col. Arnulfo Castrejon
left the embassy and was detained by U.S. forces. Castrejon was the
officer on duty at Defense Forces headquarters when Panamanian
forces fatally shot a U.S. Marine officer Dec. 16 in one of the
principal incidents leading to the U.S. invasion.
   The U.S. Southern Command said all but a few hundred of the
15,000 members of the Defense Forces had surrendered or been
arrested.
   The U.S. Justice Department asked France, Switzerland,
Luxembourg and Britain to freeze bank accounts in which Noriega is
believed to have stashed more than $10 million in ``illegal drug
money.''
   France froze accounts in two banks holding $3.3 million and
Swiss officials placed a ``precautionary'' freeze on two accounts.
   The United States and the Endara government, which was elected
in May balloting that Noriega nullified, renewed their pleas to the
Vatican to turn over the ousted military ruler.
   U.S. troops cannot go after Noriega, who was thought to be
trying to negotiate safe passage to a third country, because
embassies are inviolable under international law.
   Noriega was indicted by two federal grand juries in Florida in
February 1988 on charges of trafficking in Colombian cocaine and
money laundering.
   The Southern Command said Wednesday 23 American servicemen and
two dependents have been killed and 322 Americans wounded since the
United States invaded. It said 297 Panamanians troops were killed
and 123 wounded.
   Murguia cited an army surgeon as saying at least 250 civilians
were killed. That figure did not include others who were quickly
buried in the first days of the invasion, Murguia said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>