<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0308EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-PanamaStatement 2ndAdd   12-20 0479</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Panama Statement, 2nd Add,480</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHN: American countries.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Q. Is the fact that a step toward handing over the canal to the
Panamanians is scheduled to occur on Jan. 1 have anything to do
with the timing of this operation now?
   A. I don't think is has to do with the timing, but it certainly
has to do with the substance. We do have a responsibilty under the
Panama Canal Treaty for its safety and security, and we do believe
there have been threats that jeopardize the security of the treaty.
And that is one of the aspects of our purpose here.
   Q. Can you give us any details of A, how it's going, B, what the
size of the U.S. force that was amassed for this was and how long
you think this operation might take?
   A. I really can't answer any of those questions in any great
detail. The United States is committing forces we believe are
adequate to the task. It is a major undertaking. There are numbers
of troops and equipment that have been dedicated to this task. But
I just want to wait until some later point to give any kind of
logistical characterization of the size.
   The president has been considering this matter for several days.
As you all know, he was quite disturbed by the events of last
weekend involving the killing of the United States Marine and the
harassment and threats to the naval officer and his wife. The
president reviewed this issue with his national security adivsers
on Sunday afternoon. They considered options, developed a plan and
the president made the basic decision to proceed with this action.
Since then there have been any number of meetings. I will not go
into details of when and how they were conducted. But the president
has been reviewing this matter on a continual basis since Sunday.
And there really has not been any question about our willingness or
our readiness to proceed since that time.
   Q. What are the troops' orders with regard to Noriega? Were they
ordered to try to take him alive? And if they do, what do you want
them to do with him?
   A. Their orders are to apprhenend Gen. Noriega and our purpose
is to return him to the United States for prosecution under our
laws regarding drug trafficking. Gen. Noriega was indicted in the
southern district of Florida in Miami and the northern district in
Tampa for drug trafficking. And we want to bring him to the United
States for prosecution under that indictment.
   Q. Who swore in Endara, under what legal authority and where is
he now?
   A. I don't know who swore him in. The legal authority of course
was that they are the freely and openly elected leaders in the May
elections and they are assuming office on that basis.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>