<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0168 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2147EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ConvictionReversed 1stLd-Writethru a0716 12-21 0564</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Conviction Reversed, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0716,0571</SECOND>
<HEAD>Court Orders Innocent Verdict For `Soldier of The Year'</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 4th graf, `Henderson and ..., to UPDATE
with prosecutor's reaction; picks up 5th graf pvs, `Cox was..</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CURT ANDERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TALLAHASSEE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Florida Supreme Court on Thursday
ordered an innocent verdict for a former Army ``Soldier of the
Year'' sentenced to die in the 1978 murder of a young Walt Disney
World worker.
   The court, in a unanimous ruling, said there was insufficient
evidence to convict Robert Craig Cox, 30, a former Army Ranger. The
ruling vacated Cox's death sentence, reversed his conviction and
ordered the trial court to acquit him of all charges.
   ``The state showed the possibility that he might have been one
of several people who could have done it. That's not enough in a
criminal case,'' said Larry B. Henderson, an assistant public
defender in Daytona Beach who handled Cox's appeal.
   Henderson and the state attorney general's office said it was
rare for the Supreme Court to order an innocent verdict. Usually,
the court sends such cases back for new trials or sentencing
hearings.
   ``We may ask them to rehear it,'' said Richard Doran, the
prosecutor in the case. ``For a court to reverse a case and direct
an aquittal is very rare. Within my memory, there's been maybe one
or two cases where that's happened since the death penalty was
reinstated'' in 1976.
   Cox was convicted in 1988 of the killing 10 years earlier of
Sharon Zellers, 19. She disappeared after leaving work Dec. 30, and
her badly beaten body was found several days later in an orange
grove near Orlando.
   Police questioned Cox, who was in central Florida visiting his
parents, but brought no charges. He became a suspect because he was
staying in a motel adjacent to the grove and part of his tongue had
been bitten off the night before, indicating a possible struggle.
   The case went unsolved for a decade. In the meantime, Cox was
named the Army's ``Soldier of the Year'' in 1979, Henderson said,
and took part in the invasion of Grenada in 1983.
   In 1986, Cox ran into trouble in California and pleaded guilty
to kidnapping and assault with a deadly weapon. He was sentenced to
nine years in prison and dishonorably discharged from the Army.
   Florida authorities then charged Cox with Ms. Zeller's murder,
and he was convicted in 1988. Cox contended throughout that
prosecutors had only circumstantial evidence, and on Thursday the
Supreme Court agreed.
   The state's case hinged on hair, O-type blood and a boot print
found in the victim's car. Expert testimony about the hair and
blood type, while saying both could be linked to Cox, was not
conclusive, the court said.
   Cox's boots were never compared with the print found in Ms.
Zeller's car, the court said, the missing piece of tongue was never
found and no witnesses had seen the two together.
   ``Circumstances that create nothing more than a strong suspicion
that the defendant committed the crime are not sufficient to
support a conviction,'' the justices wrote.
   Henderson said Cox would likely be transferred from death row at
the Starke prison to Orange County, where a formal aquittal hearing
would be held. Cox then would go to California to finish serving
his prison term there, he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>