<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0249 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1001EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-PhoneRegulation 1stLd-Writethru f0017 12-22 0580</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Phone Regulation, 1st Ld-Writethru, f0017,0595</SECOND>
<HEAD>FCC Has Plan for Better Phone Service, Lower Costs</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: Leads with 4 grafs to CORRECT that price caps apply only to
interstate portion of local phone company revenues. Picks up 5th graf pvs,
`When the ...' This also moved on general news wires.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAY ARNOLD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Local telephone companies will lose their
guaranteed profit margins on interstate revenues in 1991 under a
regulatory plan for better service at lower costs, the chairman of
the Federal Communications Commission said.
   New FCC Chairman Alfred Sikes, fulfilling the promises of his
predecessor, Dennis Patrick, said Thursday that beginning Jan. 1,
1991, many local phone companies will switch from the current
``rate-of-return'' pricing system to an incentive-based regulation
known as price caps.
   In the meantime, these companies will continue under the
rate-of-return formula that allows them to earn 12 percent above
their investments, the FCC decided in a 4-0 vote.
   Price caps will apply to the revenues local phone companies
collect from connecting their callers with long-distance companies.
Local phone companies with more than $100 million in annual
revenues will fall under price caps, which the FCC says is designed
to lower phone rates.
   When the FCC imposed price caps on the American Telephone &amp;
Telegraph Co. this year after two decades of rate-of-return
regulation, it said consumers would reap $900 million in savings
over the next four years as AT&amp;T raised or lowered rates within
certain inflation-based price bands.
   Rate of return for the local companies, which was due to expire
Dec. 31, will continue into next year pending completion of a more
comprehensive study of the process.
   Sikes said the price cap ``is the best available means of
ensuring the United States the kind of efficient and effective
telecommunications system that it needs.''
   Local phone companies have been earning 12 percent since 1986,
which a consumer advocate said was too high under current market
conditions.
   ``The record clearly shows the rate of return should be
reduced,'' Gene Kimmelman of the Consumer Federation of America
said following the commission's vote. ``Consumers ought to be
seeing rates coming down because the companies' earnings are
excessive. ... Here was a chance to cut out the fat.''
   But the commission said the 12 percent rate was still ``just and
reasonable.''
   Patrick, the former FCC chairman, had said earlier this year he
wanted price caps for the local phone companies, but his aggressive
deregulatory approach ruffled many feathers in Congress.
   Richard Firestone, chief of the FCC's common carrier bureau,
said Thursday he had ``every expectation of being able to work
successfully with Congress.''
   Sikes made clear he was unsatisfied with the amount of
investment the local phone companies have been making in new
facilities and equipment under the current rate-of-return process.
   ``This past fall, when I addressed the U.S. Telephone
Association convention in San Francisco, I questioned the level of
industry investment in new plant and facilities,'' Sikes said.
``Since then, many companies have assured me that their plans for
1990 and beyond involve stepped-up modernization programs.''
   Sikes, noting his previous experience as overseer of the
Missouri Public Service Commission, said the cost-plus approach to
pricing used there ``ill-served the consumer.''
   Firestone said the FCC expected to adopt a price cap scheme by
the fall of next year, while also completing its rate-of-return
study at about the same time.
   Local phone companies must file comments on the present
rate-of-return scheme by Feb. 16.
</TEXT>

</DOC>