<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0122 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 2017EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Jacobson     12-26 0471</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Jacobson,0483</SECOND>
<HEAD>Joel Jacobson, Former Casino Control Commissioner, Dies</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HENRY STERN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LIVINGSTON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Joel Jacobson, a no-nonsense former New
Jersey casino regulator who once called Frank Sinatra ``an
obnoxious bully'' and was later appointed court trustee of a
scandal-ridden Teamsters local, died Tuesday. He was 71.
   Jacobson, a South Orange resident, died about 3:25 a.m. at Saint
Barnabas Hospital in Livingston, said a hospital spokeswoman who
asked that her name not be used. She said she could not release a
cause of death.
   ``I am saddened at the death of Joel Jacobson,'' Gov. Thomas H.
Kean said in a statement. ``He was an individual of strong and
firmly held positions and possessed a willingness to express them
forcefully and articulately. He fought for his beliefs, both as a
public servant and as a private citizen.''
   Jacobson, a longtime labor union official, joined the state
Casino Control commission in 1981. His tenure was marked by his
vote against issuing a gaming license to Hilton Corp. and his
run-in with Sinatra.
   In 1984, he characterized the singer as someone who ``walks into
a casino and exhibits himself like an obnoxious bully, forcing men
and women to commit infractions because of the fear of losing their
jobs.''
   The comment came after Sinatra and fellow entertainer Dean
Martin forced a blackjack dealer at the former Golden Nugget casino
to deal from her hand instead of a plastic ``shoe'' which holds the
cards. Jacobson's remark so angered Sinatra that he refused to
perform in the state for a time.
   Outgoing Casino Control Commission Chairman Walter N. Read said
Jacobson never feared letting others know what he thought.
   ``Joel had a lot of influence in a lot of areas for a long
period of time,'' Read said.
   Jacobson resigned from the commission in June 1986 and was
appointed by U.S. District Judge Harold Ackerman to run Union
City-based Teamsters Local 560. Ackerman had ruled in February 1984
that the 8,000-member Local 560 had suffered under ``an orgy of
criminal activity'' for 25 years.
   In May 1987, Ackerman removed Jacobson, saying ``more needs to
be done in order to insure that the documented egregious pattern of
racketeering activity does not re-emerge the moment that the
trusteeship is ended.''
   Jacobson later accused the government of trying to bust the
union with the appointment of Edwin H. Stier, a former assistant
U.S. attorney and director of the state Division of Criminal
Justice. The union in 1988 held a government monitored election and
returned to self-administration.
   In 1974, Jacobson became a member of the state Board of Public
Utilities and its president in 1976.
   He became the first commissioner of the state Department of
Energy _ now part of the state Department of Commerce, Energy and
Economic Development _ upon its creation in 1977.
</TEXT>

</DOC>