<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0217EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Boston-IrelandProject     12-22 0308</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Boston-Ireland Project,0313</SECOND>
<HEAD>Boston Launches Huge Shopping Center in Northern Ireland</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DANA KENNEDY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In what was billed as the largest American
investment in Northern Ireland, Mayor Raymond Flynn announced the
development of a $100 million shopping center in the economically
troubled city of Londonderry.
   ``We're all keenly aware of the trouble in Northern Ireland,''
Flynn said at a news conference Thursday with British and Irish
officials and Cardinal Bernard Law. ``But today, what is happening
in America is very special. We're reaching out and bringing a new
kind of hope, one that transcends words. It brings jobs and
economic opportunity.''
   Groundbreaking will begin next fall on the 300,000-square-foot
complex, which should provide about 1,400 jobs in office, service
and construction, Flynn said. The shopping center, funded by a
Quincy-based developer, is expected to open in 1992.
   The project stems from Boston Ireland Ventures, a non-profit
group founded in 1987 by Flynn and Northern Irish political leader
John Hume to spur economic growth in the north and west of Ireland.
Hume leads the Social Democratic and Labor Party, representing
moderate Catholics in Northern Ireland.
   Londonderry, also known as Derry, the second largest city in
Northern Ireland, is in one of the poorest areas in the country,
with unemployment rates of up to 45 percent.
   After 18 months of negotiations with the British government,
which rules Northern Ireland, O'Connell Development Co. agreed to
build the complex. The company's other projects include waterfront
complexes such as the World Trade Center and Bayside Exposition
Center in Boston and the Marina Bay complex in Quincy.
   ``This is the essence of cooperation,'' said Liam Canniffe,
consulate general of Ireland. ``They are welcoming you on the
streets of Derry. There are great ties between America and Ireland
and now there are great ties between Derry and America.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>