<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0216 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1758EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Soviet-Miners     12-29 0401</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Miners,0416</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Mine Strike Leader Barred From Travel to U.S.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: also on general news wires.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANN IMSE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Airport border guards abruptly revoked the
passport and exit visa of a Soviet strike leader Friday as he was
to board a flight to the United States to meet American union
leaders. The U.S. Embassy filed a strong protest.
   Embassy spokesman Jim Bullock said the United States considered
the action a violation of what U.S. officials have been told would
be the new free-exit policy.
   Soviet officials previously had authorized the U.S.
government-sponsored trip by 10 leaders of last summer's national
coal strike. Soviet citizens must obtain an exit visa for each trip
out of the country.
   But permission was refused at the last minute for Sergei V.
Masalovich, a strike leader from Vorkuta in the Soviet Arctic,
Bullock said.
   Soviet Foreign Ministry spokesman Sergei Komolov said
Masalovich's visa was canceled because the trade union committee in
Vorkuta had stripped him of his duties on the strike committee.
   ``So he cannot be part of the official delegation,'' but may
re-apply for a visa for a private visit, Komolov said.
   The miners were chosen for the trip by their strike committees.
   Bullock responded that Masalovich was traveling on the personal
invitation of the U.S. ambassador and ``an organization cannot
cancel an invitation to a private individual,'' he said.
   Bullock said embassy officials did not know if Masalovich had
been removed from the strike committee, and that it was irrelevant,
even if true.
   Bullock also denied the Foreign Ministry's claim that the
embassy had been notified. ``We find the Foreign Ministry statement
to be false and incomprehensible,'' he said.
   Hundreds of thousands of coal miners went on strike in July in
the Soviet Union's first nationwide work stoppage in decades. The
government quickly gave in, saying complaints of poor social and
economic conditions were justified. But the struggling Soviet
economy has been hard-pressed to fulfill those promises of more
soap, food and social programs.
   Miners in Vorkuta _ famed in the Soviet Union as the site of
harsh prison camps under former leader Josef Stalin _ struck again
in October for five weeks, saying the government failed to keep its
promises to increase pensions and wages and to improve living
conditions.
   The miners are scheduled to meet with U.S. labor leaders,
including AFL-CIO head Lane Kirkland.
</TEXT>

</DOC>