<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0530EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Panama-US-Chronology 1stLd-Writethru   12-20 0786</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Panama-US-Chronology, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0478,0827</SECOND>
<HEAD>Key Events During Noriega's Rule of Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Subs last item to UPDATE. No pickup.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a chronology of key events
related to Gen. Manuel Noriega's rule of Panama:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>___</NOTE>
<NOTE>1981</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Armed forces chief Gen. Omar Torrijos dies in plane crash.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>1982</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   March _ Three of Torrijos' colonels, Manuel Antonio Noriega,
Ruben Dario Paredes and Roberto Diaz Herrera cut a deal to resolve
power struggle. Paredes takes over as armed forces chief and agrees
to retire in August 1983, leaving Noriega to take over, with Diaz
Herrara as second-in-command. Noriega promises to deliver 1984
presidential election to Paredes.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>1983</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   August _ Noriega takes over as commander of the armed forces.
The Panamanian legislature passes a law creating the Panamanian
Defense Forces with control over National Guard, other Panamanian
military and police forces, canal matters and functions such as
immigration control and regulation of civilian aircraft. Noriega
reneges on Paredes deal and installs his own president in 1984
election.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>1987</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   June _ Diaz Herrera, retiring as second-in-command, accuses
Noriega of drug-related activities, rigging 1984 election and
murdering Dr. Hugo Spadafora, former vice minister of health who
accused Noriega of drug trafficking.
   June 9 _ Protest movement demands probe into Diaz Herrera's
allegations and return to democracy. Street protests are crushed
brutally.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>1988</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Feb. 4 _ Federal grand jury in Miami indicts Noriega on
drug-running charges. Grand jury in Tampa returns similar
indictments.
   Feb. 25 _ President Eric Delvalle, who was put in place by
Noriega, announces he has fired his patron.
   Feb. 26 _ Noriega-dominated National Assembly ousts Delvalle,
who goes into hiding. Washington continues to recognize him as head
of state. Education Minister Manuel Solis Palma named minister in
charge of presidency. Noriega opponents call general strike.
Government closes opposition news media.
   March 3 _ U.S. courts block withdrawal of Panama funds from U.S.
banks.
   March 11 _ President Reagan imposes sanctions, including
eliminating trade preferences for Panama and withholding Panama
Canal fees.
   March 14 _ Public employees riot after government is unable to
pay wages.
   March 16 _ Coup organized by Defense Forces officers against
Noriega fails. Demonstrations erupt in capital and power outage
blacks out nation.
   March 28 _ Troops disperse thousands of anti-government marchers
and storm Marriot Hotel, beating and arresting opposition activists
and journalists. Several are injured and dozens arrested in one of
biggest protests in months.
   April 9 _ United States announces economic sanctions prohibiting
American companies and government from making payments to
Panamanian government. Some $56 million in Panamanian funds in
American banks are frozen. United States tries to negotiate
Noriega's departure without success.
   May 9 _ Banks reopen but with severe restrictions, including a
freeze on savings accounts.
   Aug. 21 _ U.S. accuses Panamanian authorities of 240 incidents
of harassment of American military personnel in 1988.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>1989</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   May 7-9 _ Presidential election pits Noriega candidate against
opposition candidate Guillermo Endara. Noriega's victory claim
countered by rioters as well as international observers who say
ballots were rigged. Former President Carter, a U.S. observer,
denounces Noriega for stealing election. White House says
independent exit polling showed Noriega's slate losing by 3-to-1
margin.
   May 10 _ Government nullifies election before final results
released, citing fraud and international interference. Endara and
his two running mates beaten and a bodyguard killed by civilian
thugs as defense forces look on. Police break up opposition
demonstration with gunfire and tear gas.
   May 11 _ President Bush orders 2,000 additional U.S. troops to
Panama, joining 10,000 already there.
   Sept. 1 _ Provisional President Francisco Rodriguez takes
office, but Noriega remains de facto leader.
   Oct. 3 _ Attempted U.S.-backed coup against Noriega fails.
   Dec. 15 _ Noriega says Panama is in a ``state of war'' with the
United States and his rubber-stamp legislature appoints him chief
executive officer of the government to respond.
   Dec. 16 _ Panamania soldiers kill a U.S. Marine lieutenant.
Panamanian officials say the American officer was killed when he
and three others drove a car past checkpoints, then fired at
Noriega's military headquarters building, wounding two civilians
and a soldier. The United States says the four were unarmed, in
civilian clothes, when they got lost near the headquarters.
   Dec. 18 _ A U.S. Army officer wounds a Panamanian police
corporal because he thought the man was about to draw a weapon,
according to Southern Command.
   Dec. 20 _ President Bush orders U.S. troops into combat in
Panama City on a mission to seize Noriega to face federal drug
charges in the United States. The White House says the mission also
is intended to protect American lives, restore democraty to Panama
and preserve the integrity of the Panama Canal.
</TEXT>

</DOC>