<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0091 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1132EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-EastGermany 3rdLd-Writethru a0577 12-22 0860</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-East Germany, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0577,0882</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands Surge Through as Berlin Wall Opens at Brandenburg Gate</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 9 grafs to ADD quotes from revelers. Pickup 8th pvs,
`The crowd...' Delete 19th graf pvs, `Others held...' to remove reference
to Ceausescu.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BER19</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH G. SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of jubilant Berliners surged
through new openings in the Berlin Wall at the Brandenburg Gate
today for the first time in 28 years.
   The celebrants braved an intermittent rain as they filled the
square in front of the towering symbol of the postwar division of
Germany that is becoming a monument to the rapprochement of East
Germany and West Germany.
   East German Premier Hans Modrow met West Germany Chancellor
Helmut Kohl at the border for the 3 p.m. (9 a.m. EST) ceremony,
then they walked together into East Germany. They were nearly
mobbed by the crowd as they walked to a platform in front of the
gate to address the exulting Berliners.
   Kohl called the occasion ``a fantastic thing.''
   Thousands drenched by the rain uncorked champagne and danced
atop the Berlin Wall, the once impregnable concrete barrier that is
quickly crumbling.
   The opening was televised live in both countries. ``This is
where the heart of Berlin pounds,'' said a commentator for West
Germany's ZDF network.
   Two banners were unfurled near the new crossings to protest the
killings of demonstrators in Romania.
   ``The last time I was here was as a kid when I used to play on
this very spot. I never thought I'd come here again, it's really
wonderful,'' said Peter Rebachmann, 42, of East Berlin.
   ``What a beautiful Christmas present. I am so elated that I can
experience this,'' said a middle-aged woman.
   The crowd cheered and set off firecrackers when East German
workers started dismantling the wall Thursday night. The workers
used a crane to remove the rounded top of the wall.
   ``This is an experience that will go down in history. The gate
was a symbol of division of Germany,'' said Jozef Polak, a West
Berlin mechanic.
   More than 10,000 people had jammed the western side for the two
sections of the wall to fall down. Some climbed on trees to get a
better view. More people kept arriving throughout the night.
   A loud cheer sounded through the night air as the East German
crane lifted a 3{-foot-wide segment of the concrete to make the
first hole in that part of the wall shortly after midnight.
   The two new crossing points are 15 feet wide each. One is for
Westerners going into East Berlin, the other for East Germans going
to West Berlin.
   Although more than 20 border crossings have been made at the
wall since East Germany opened its borders to the West on Nov. 9,
the Brandenburg Gate has the most symbolic meaning for Berliners.
   The 200-year-old gate, Berlin's most famous landmark, remained
on the eastern side when East Germany's Communist authorities built
the Berlin Wall in 1961.
   Graffiti on the western side at one of the segments to be
removed said, ``One day every wall must fall down.''
   Friedhelm Brinkman, a salesman from Dortmund, West Germany, said
he drove 360 miles to see the event.
   ``This was the central place in Berlin where everything happened
(before the war). I always thought this place would be opened again
and that's why I came tonight,'' he said late Thursday.
   Some people in the crowd shouted, ``Germany, United
Fatherland,'' _ the rallying call of East German supporters of
German unification.
   
   The crowd was kept well away from the wall by barricades and
cordons of West Berlin police to prevent them from possibly trying
to cross the wall.
   After East Germany's dramatic opening of the borders, thousands
of people danced on the section of the Berlin Wall at Brandenburg
Gate.
   Crowds pulled down one segment of the wall in unforgettable
scenes seen on television worldwide. Thousands of people had waited
in vain for the gate to be opened in the first few days after the
Berlin Wall started crumbling down in the wake of East Germany's
peaceful revolution.
   Kohl and Modrow announced the agreement to open the two
crossings when Kohl visited Dresden on Wednesday.
   The gate, the size of a five-story building on top of which is a
bronze chariot with the goddess Victoria, was the backdrop for
Hitler's rise to power and his last stand. It was also where East
German workers began a 1953 uprising that was crushed by Soviet
tanks.
   In East Berlin, the famous Unter den Linden boulevard ends at
the gate. On the Western side, the sprawling avenue that leads to
the gate was renamed June 17 Street, after the date of the uprising.
   Nazi brown shirts staged a triumphant torch parade through the
gate when Adolf Hitler was named chancellor on Jan. 30, 1933.
   In the final days of World War II, the six-column sandstone gate
was heavily damaged as Soviet tanks closed in on Hitler's bunker in
the chancellory. It marked the border between the Soviet and
British sectors when the victorious allies divided conquered Berlin
into four sectors.
</TEXT>

</DOC>