<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0140 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1808EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Lithuania 1stLd-Writethru a0632 12-21 0711</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lithuania, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0632,0737</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gorbachev Blasts Lithuania's Break, Party Calls Meeting</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS throughout to UPDATE with Politburo criticism of Lithuania,
background, Lithuania reinforces break, Brazauskas quotes. No pickup</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANDREW KATELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Mikhail S. Gorbachev blasted Lithuania's
Communists on Thursday for breaking with the national Communist
Party in their drive to restore their republic's sovereignty.
   The national Communist Party Central Committee scheduled an
emergency meeting to discuss the historic defiance.
   Rimantas Kanapenes, a spokesman for Lithuania's political group
Sajudis, said Gorbachev summoned Lithuanian members of the national
parliament to protest Wednesday's decision by the Lithuanian
Communist Party Congress to end subordination to the national party
and declare itself independent, with its own rules and program.
   The Kremlin had warned of ``great trouble'' ahead for the
Lithuanians, and it came fast.
   ``This decision should be assessed only as a step aimed at the
split of the Lithuanian Communist Party from the Soviet Communist
Party,'' the ruling Politburo said in a message to the Lithuanian
Communists.
   ``This concerns not only the Lithuanian Communist Party but the
entire party.''
   The message was signed by Gorbachev and reported by the official
news agency Tass.
   Gorbachev told the Congress he shared the ``concern and alarm''
of many Communists about Lithuania's action and said the Politburo
decided to call an emergency meeting of the Central Committee, its
parent body, on the issue ``in a few days.''
   He said dozens of Communist members wrote him notes calling
Lithuania's action ``very sad for all Communists'' and describing
it as ``a new step in a separatist tendency in the country, a new
enormous danger for the Soviet Communist Party and our
multi-national state.''
   ``The alarm is growing, the chain reaction has started,'' the
notes read.
   A Sajudis official has predicted the Communist parties of
neighboring Latvia and Estonia in the Baltics, and Armenia and
Georgia in the Caucasus, would follow Lithuania's lead and break
off from the national party.
   Kanapenes said Gorbachev telephoned Lithuanian party chief
Algirdas Brazauskas in Vilnius, the republic's capital, shortly
after the 855-160 vote to break away from the national party.
   ``Brazauskas said it was a very difficult conversation,''
Kanapenes said. ``Gorbachev said he was very sorry'' about the
decision.
   Brazauskas told a news conference in Vilnius Thursday night he
had a ``very correct talk'' with Gorbachev and denied rumors that
Gorbachev threatened to declare martial law in Lithuania.
   ``It's a great anecdote, but there was no such talk,'' he said.
   He said he understood why some orthodox Communists were upset.
   ``I think it's a very important step toward perestroika, but for
someone who can't imagine such profound restructuring it must be a
real shock.''
   The Lithuanian Congress reinforced its stand Thursday by
approving statutes implementing the break with the national party
and re-electing the 57-year-old Brazauskas as its first secretary.
   Kanapenes said Gorbachev aides also called in the head of
Sajudis, Vytautas Landsbergis.
   A resolution approved by Lithuania's legislature declares the
republic's party an ``equal partner with the Soviet Communist
Party, other progressive parties, public organizations and
movements.''
   That position runs counter to more than 80 years of party
policy. Before the 1917 Bolshevik Revolution, Vladimir I. Lenin
demanded unity, and a 1921 party congress formally ruled out any
factions.
   Tass said about 160 Lithuanian congress delegates who voted
against the breakoff met in Vilnius on Thursday. It said the
dissident group, claiming to represent a quarter of the republic's
Communists, pledged to work to maintain ties with the national
party.
   Politburo member Yegor K. Ligachev had said Wednesday that
Lithuania's move ``is great trouble for the people and for
Communists.''
   Lithuanians ``just do not realize yet what grief will descend.''
   Lithuanian leaders on Dec. 7 supported a move by the legislature
to create a multiparty political system, striking from the Baltic
republic's constitution language making the Communist Party the
leading force in society.
   The Communists' new program also supports eventual restoration
of the independence Lithuania enjoyed between the world wars. The
Soviet Union absorbed the region in 1940 under secret agreements
with Nazi Germany.
   Several small political parties already have formed to challenge
the Communists in Feb. 24 local elections, and Lithuanian Communist
leaders say they need an independent structure to compete in the
balloting.
</TEXT>

</DOC>