<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0212 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1221EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-WallStreetNoon     12-19 0309</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Wall Street Noon,0324</SECOND>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The stock market showed a broad loss again today
amid persistent worries about the future course of the economy.
   The Dow Jones average of 30 industrials, down 56.10 points in
the past two sessions, dropped 10.46 to 2,687.07 by noontime on
Wall Street.
   Losers outnumbered gainers by more than 3 to 1 in nationwide
trading of New York Stock Exchange-listed issues, with 333 up,
1,044 down and 489 unchanged.
   Analysts said the latest economic reports from the government
hadn't done much to pull the market out of its recent slide,
induced to a great extent by worries about the real estate market
and mortgage debt.
   The Labor Department reported that the consumer price index rose
0.4 percent in November, or at an annual rate of 4.9 percent. That
appeared to put a new obstacle before any fresh moves by the
Federal Reserve to relax its credit policy.
   Separate government figures showed a 4.7 percent decline in
housing starts last month.
   Brokers said that left stocks in the grip of recession fears and
of talk that a slump in business conditions might be exacerbated by
a weak market for homes and other real-estate properties.
   A few recently depressed mortgage and regional banking stocks
staged a rebound. Federal National Mortgage rose | to 31}, and Bank
of New England gained ] to 7~.
   But most other bank stocks remained on the defensive. Citicorp
fell ~ to 26; Chase Manhattan { to 31]; J.P. Morgan } to 39~, and
Chemical Banking { to 28}.
   The NYSE's composite index of all its listed common stocks
dropped 1.29 to 188.88. At the American Stock Exchange, the market
value index was down 2.64 at 368.22.
   Volume on the Big Board came to 99.24 million shares at
noontime, up from 74.84 million at the same point Monday.
</TEXT>

</DOC>