<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0109 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1901EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-UN-Romania     12-26 0363</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-UN-Romania,0373</SECOND>
<HEAD>China Blocking Meeting on Romania to Prevent Comparisons, Diplomats
Say</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania</HEAD>
<DATELINE>UNITED NATIONS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   China is blocking Security Council debate
on the revolt in Romania because it fears comparisons with
Beijing's own violent encounter with pro-democracy protests,
diplomats said Tuesday.
   The Security Council put off discussion on Romania on Tuesday
because of resistance by China, the diplomats said, speaking on
condition of anonymity.
   A U.N. spokesman said only that the Romanian question, which had
been placed on the agenda, had not been taken up. There was no
comment from Chinese diplomats.
   Weeks of pro-democracy protests in China earlier this year were
crushed by troops in Beijing. China says about 300 people died, 200
of them civilians. Witnesses and Western security sources say the
toll may range from 500 to 3,000.
   In Romania, the new revolutionary government says more than
12,000 people were believed slain during a week of protests against
the rule of ousted leader Nicolae Ceausescu, who ordered troops to
shoot demonstrators. Mass graves were found in the western city of
Timisoara.
   U.N. diplomats said China government wants to avoid any
comparison with Romania. China has reacted sharply to international
criticism to its crackdown.
   U.N. diplomats familiar with council proceedings said China,
with the support of some developing nations, argued that the
situation in Romania was strictly an internal affair and the
international community should not become involved.
   Other diplomats argued, however, that the instability in Romania
threatens Europe, and that maintaining international peace and
stability is a legitimate concern of the 15-nation Security Council.
   Austria, Hungary, West Germany and Italy last week requested
that the issue a statement about the crisis in Romania. They
suggested the council could deplore the violence among the
demonstrators, army and security forces and call for an orderly
transition to democracy.
   China, however, refused Saturday to permit Security Council
President Enrique Penalosa of Colombia to read an informal
statement of concern to reporters.
   China is one of the five permanent council members with veto
power and can block a statement. A council statement requires a
concensus. The five permanent members are the United States,
Britain, China, France and the Soviet Union.
</TEXT>

</DOC>