<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0912EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-US-Panama 3rdLd-Writethru a0521 12-21 0773</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-Panama, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0521, 2 Takes,750-1,300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cheney Holds Out Prospect of Partial Withdrawal By Christmas</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Breaks into 2 takes; new material throughout on Smithsonian
Institution hostages, further congressional, Cheney and Noriega comment;
combat reports from Panama</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM RAUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Defense Secretary Dick Cheney raised the
prospect today that some American forces could be withdrawn from
Panama by Christmas even though Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega, a $1
million bounty on his head, evaded a huge military manhunt.
   The Pentagon issued a new report on casualties from the massive
invasion intended to usher in a ``new democratic government'' in
Panama and wipe out Noriega: 18 U.S. servicemen killed, 117 wounded
and one missing. There was also one American civilian death, that
of a woman teacher.
   At least a dozen Americans were held hostage by Noriega's forces
and the Smithsonian Institution said 11 scientists and technicians
were missing from a research institute and believed taken hostage.
   ``Given the size of the operation and its complexity, and the
opposition that's been encountered, the level of casualties is
probably lower than would have been expected,'' the defense
secretary said on CNN.
   ``I think within the next few weeks we'll be able to return the
situation back to where we're relying only on those (U.S.) forces
that were in the country prior to the intervention,'' he added.
   Gen. Colin Powell, chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, said
most of the military objectives had been accomplished. ``We are
seeing a mopping up-type activity,'' he said.
   Powell said reports of Noriega's whereabouts had been received
throughout the night and were chased down _ but without results.
   ``We do not know where he is,'' Powell said on ABC-TV's ``Good
Morning America.''
   While President Bush drew broad support from Congress, there
were hints that the political backing might erode if the military
deployment turns out to be a prolonged one.
   ``Both the president and the Congress, I think, assume that this
is going to be an operation that will be concluded as soon as
possible,'' said House Speaker Tom Foley, D-Wash., on CBS-TV's
``This Morning.''
   Deep skepticism about the operation came from Rep. Charles B.
Rangel, D-N.Y.: ``We've been waiting for some darn excuse to invade
Panama.''
   But Sen. Richard Lugar, R-Ind., said, ``Things had reached the
edge. The president had to act.''
   In all, Bush ordered 9,500 soldiers and Marines into Panama to
bolster the 13,000 already based there.
   Cheney said the Americans were beginning to get telephone calls
in response to the $1 million reward for the capture of Noriega
that was posted Wednesday night at the end of the first day of the
American intervention.
   ``So hopefully we'll be able to wrap up Mr. Noriega in the near
future and return him to the United States for trial,'' Cheney said.
   He expressed the belief that Noriega had not left Panama.
   Noriega and 16 associates were indicted in Miami and Tampa,
Fla., last year on drug-trafficking charges.
   Powell said he was not worried about Noriega still being ``at
liberty'' since he wielded no power any longer. ``He no longer
controls the drug money and he no longer is in a position to give
out his favors or his punishments,'' the general said.
   Reports from Panama said American forces had met stiff
resistance during the night, with heavy fighting raging just before
dawn in the middle-class suburb of San Miguelito but by daybreak,
the fighting had ceased. U.S. army troops patrolled the streets of
Panama City, but were unable to prevent widespread looting.
   In an interview on ``CBS This Morning,'' Cheney was pressed
about when U.S. units might be withdrawn.
   ``I wouldn't want to make a hard and fast projection,'' he
replied.
   ``I would guess that some of the units may be out by Christmas
but I think the key thing is for us to make certain that the
situation's under control, that the new government of Panama, the
democratic government, is well established, and a lot of that we
can do with forces that are permanently in Panama.
   ``But we won't take anybody out until we're confident that in
fact the situation's under control,'' Cheney added.
   In Panama, Noriega said on a government-run FM radio station
that he will now lead a guerrilla war against the United States.
``We're in trench warfare now and we will maintain the
resistance,'' he said. ``Our slogan is to win or die, not one step
back.''
   Powell said the chief U.S. goal today would be to locate
Americans who were taken hostage by forces loyal to Noriega in the
chaotic opening hours of the operation.
</TEXT>

</DOC>