<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0135 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 2320EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Colombia-Prison     12-26 0450</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia-Prison,0463</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police End Prison Disturbance, Free Hostages, Kill 5 Inmates</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STAN YARBRO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police attacked a prison cell block
controlled by jailed drug traffickers and rescued 18 hostages held
for two days, a Justice Department spokesman said Tuesday.
   Six traffickers died and five hostages were injured in the
bloody rescue operation Monday night.
   Also Monday in Salgar, a town 167 miles north of Bogota, a group
of unidentified men massacred six farmers, the Antioquia state
governor's office reported Tuesday.
   An official communique said authorities still had not determined
the motive for the mass killing, and that no arrests had been made.
Right-wing death squads have killed scores of other peasants in the
same part of Colombia the last year.
   Later Monday, two police officers were assassinated, apparently
by members of Colombia's largest and oldest guerrilla group in La
Vega, a town 260 miles south of Bogota, the Cauca state governor's
office reported.
   The assassinations apparently were carried out by the
Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia, the communique said. The
leftist guerrilla group has increased its activity in recent
months. Last Saturday, members of the group ambushed an army patrol
and killed 10 soldiers in rural eastern Colombia.
   The Bogota prison takeover ended Monday when police gained the
release of all the hostages, including two children. A Justice
Department spokesman told The Associated Press the situation at La
Picota jail in southern Bogota had returned to normal.
   Authorities had been negotiating for two days with the
prisoners, who took the hostages after a failed jailbreak Sunday.
   After subduing guards during visiting hours, the inmates, all
jailed on drug trafficking charges, put on guards' uniforms in an
attempt to escape, Bogota's El Tiempo newspaper reported Tuesday.
   Authorities discovered the plan and sealed off the cell block
before the prisoners could flee, El Tiempo said, citing prison
sources.
   The paper added that the cornered criminals then took hostages,
including civilians who had been visiting their jailed family
members.
   The prisoners initially protested the killing by police of
Gonzalo Rodriguez Gacha, El Tiempo said. The Medellin cartel leader
was slain Dec. 15 in a gunfight with police on Colombia's northern
coast.
   As a condition for the hostages' release, the inmates demanded
that the administration of President Virgilio Barco end its
extradition of drug traffickers, El Tiempo said.
   The administration has sent 11 drug suspects to the United
States since last August when it decreed the policy.
   The uprising is the second by drug traffickers at a Bogota jail
in less than a week. Five prisoners died last Tuesday in a knife
battle between rival groups of convicted traffickers at another
prison facility in the capital.
</TEXT>

</DOC>