<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0353EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BoobyTrapFatal     12-28 0307</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Booby Trap Fatal,0316</SECOND>
<HEAD>Homeowner's Booby Trap Fatally Wounds Intruder</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GARRY MITCHELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOBILE, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A suspected burglar was killed after setting
off a booby trap rigged by a homeowner who complained of frequent
break-ins.
   Police said Wednesday that 37-year-old Leroy (or Lee Roy)
Woodard of Mobile was shot in the neck and killed about 11:30 p.m.
Tuesday when he stepped into a trap laid by the homeowner.
   Police spokesman Tom Jennings said the booby trap included two
hunting rifles in separate locations, one pointing down a
staircase. He said one rifle fired when Woodard stepped on a wire
rigged to the rifle trigger.
   The homeowner, 29-year-old Mark McClammy, was questioned and
released. But Jennings said the case would be presented to a county
grand jury.
   Joy Patterson, a spokeswoman for the state attorney general,
said, ``It's illegal to take a life to protect property, but it
could be legal where someone is defending their own life or someone
else's life.''
   McClammy told police he lived alone in the house that was under
renovation. He said he was in Mississippi when the shooting
occurred.
   A neighbor called McClammy and told him he had heard a shot from
inside the house. McClammy and the neighbor went inside and found
the man on the floor at the foot of the stairwell.
   Woodard had three prior arrests, Jennings said.
   James Miller, who has lived in the downtown neighorhood for 26
years, said he has a burglar alarm, but would not rig a booby trap.
   ``That sounds like a cruel thing to do,'' Miller said.
   But a woman who owns a store near the house said the
neighborhood has a problem with burglaries.
   ``I'm glad it happened,'' said the woman, who spoke on condition
of anonymity. ``People break into places out here all the time.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>