<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1330EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mandela     12-19 0502</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mandela,0517</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mandela Holds Six-Hour Talks With Militant Labor Leaders</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SAHM VENTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PAARL, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nelson Mandela wants to be leave
prison immediately but won't beg for his freedom, said one of five
militant union officials who had a long meeting with the black
nationalist leader Tuesday.
   Mandela, whose release is widely expected in the next six weeks,
has been allowed a series of meetings at his prison quarters with
anti-apartheid leaders.
   Tuesday's six-hour encounter was his first with a delegation
from the Congress of South African Trade Unions, the country's
largest labor federation and a powerful force within the
anti-apartheid movement.
   Syndey Mufamadi, the federation's assistant secretary-general,
said Mandela wants to be freed now, but in the meantime had decided
to continue periodic talks with government officials.
   ``He is not a go-between, but is in a position to meet
government officials and to convey their views to our movement,''
Mufamadi said. ``Mr. Mandela sees himself as a prisoner and not in
any position to enter negotiations at this stage.''
   President F.W. de Klerk met with Mandela last week at the
presidential office in Cape Town.
   The meeting prompted press speculation that some members and
supporters of Mandela' African National Congress guerrilla movement
were worried that he was opening talks with the government before
it met the ANC's preconditions. These include release of all
political prisoners, lifting of the state of emergency and lifting
a ban on the ANC.
   ``Mandela does not see any possibility of negotiations unless
the proper climate is created,'' Mufamadi said. ``His release is
just one of these issues. ... He is not prepared to beg for his
release.''
   Mufamadi said Mandela sees himself as a ``disciplined member of
the ANC'' who would not act in conflict with the organization's
exiled leadership in Zambia.
   Mufamadi said the main purpose of Tuesday's meeting was to brief
Mandela, 71, on developments in the anti-apartheid movement.
   ``Comrade Mandela's message to the people is that the struggle
must continue,'' Mufamadi said.
   The five-man delegation included prominent activists who head
two of the labor federation's biggest affiliates: Cyril Ramaphosa
of the National Union of Mineworkers and Moses Mayekiso of the
National Union of Metalworkers.
   Mandela, the most popular leader among South Africa's black
majority, has been jailed since 1962 and is serving a life sentence
for plotting anti-government sabotage. Virtually all prominent
black leaders have said they won't enter negotiations until he is
freed.
   Foreign Minister Pik Botha met Tuesday with Britain's
ambassador, Robin Renwick, to discuss media reports that British
Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher had made a formal appeal for
Mandela to be released before Christmas.
   Mrs. Thatcher's office denied this, saying she had not set any
new time frame for her standing request that Mandela be freed ``as
soon as possible.''
   De Klerk has offered to negotiate a new Constitution that would
extend political rights to blacks. He opposes a one-person,
one-vote system and wants whites to retain veto power over major
policy decisions.
</TEXT>

</DOC>