<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0145 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1723EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     12-22 0586</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0604</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright and Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Folks in the Midwest and East got more snow
and cold than they wanted, but at least it was free. In sunny
Southern California, residents can buy artificial snow for their
yard, but it sets 'em back $100 a ton plus labor and delivery
charges.
   Maurice Gonzalez, 32, of suburban Canoga Park was one of more
than two dozen customers who paid an ice company to pretend they
were having a white Christmas for a couple of days this season. His
5-inch ``snowfall,'' really pulverized ice, was put down Wednesday.
   ``We had a lot of people stopping by with kids,'' Gonzalez said
Thursday. ``They play with it, grab a little bit to show their
parents. It's fun just watching them.'' With daytime temperatures
around 70, the snow was down to a few patches by late Thursday.
   Gonzales said the fun factor made it worth the cost, which came
out to about $100 per inch on his size yard. The family also has
put up such decorations as a Santa Claus with reindeer, a Nativity
scene and figures of a boy and girl sledding.
   ``I didn't really plan to do all this, this year _ it just kind
of happens,'' Gonzalez said. ``If you have kids, you just start
doing things and you get in the spirit of Christmas.''
   Jeff Lucas, a driver for North Hollywood Ice Co., said the
company uses mobile ice crushers to pulverize 300-pound blocks of
ice, and blowers to spray the fine particles across the yard.
   ``It's the same grade as snow,'' said Lucas. ``We lay it on so
thick, it'll last a while even in the sun.''
   The company has delivered yuletide snow-on-demand since the
1970s and got more than 25 residential orders this year, manager
Fred Rymond said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>COLORADO SPRINGS, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A listing in the local telephone
book for Rudolph Reindeer is actually an unlisted phone number at
nearby Fort Carson, an apparent Christmas prank that has gone
little noticed for seven years.
   The telephone number _ complete with non-existent address _ was
assigned to Rudolph on Dec. 16, 1982, said Abel Chavez, a spokesman
for U S West Communications. The number is one of thousands
assigned to Fort Carson.
   ``It was a humorous stunt, I would guess,'' Chavez said. ``It's
kind of amazing that it's lasted this long and was not brought to
our attention.''
   It was also kind of amazing to Fort Carson officials, who said
few people called the number asking for ``Rudolph'' until a news
story about it was published Friday.
   ``It was supposed to be unlisted,'' said spokeswoman Ann Smith.
``How it got in the phone book, we don't know. I think there's
somebody with a silly sense of humor.''
   The base has nearly 6,000 telephone numbers, assigned to
different departments as needed. Smith said ``Rudolph's'' number
has been assigned to a weather station in a trailer on the base
since 1987, Smith said. She was not sure which department had the
number in 1982.
   A newspaper story about the listing Friday prompted a flurry of
calls to the weather trailer, said Sgt. Mike Howard, base spokesman.
   ``They have received about 100 calls, from children to
grandparents. The people who work in the trailer provide
meteorological information (for Fort Carson units). This morning,
they spent their morning answering the telephone.''
   Chavez said it's too late to get it out of the 1990 phone book,
but it will be pulled from future editions.
</TEXT>

</DOC>