<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0205EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-CanadianLimits Bjt   12-18 0878</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Canadian Limits, Bjt,0899</SECOND>
<HEAD>Canadian Scallopers See U.S. Poachers Move in on Their Catch</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LESLIE DREYFOUS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HALIFAX, Nova Scotia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A cat and mouse game played out for
the past five years on Georges Bank is driving Canadians toward a
tougher stand against Americans poaching on their rich fishing
grounds, officials said.
   ``I'd equate it with a small boy teasing a dog. The dog will go
along with it for only so long and then he'll bite,'' says Jeremy
D. Conway, chief of investigations for the Canadian Department of
Fisheries and Oceans.
   When the World Court divided the territory about 120 miles off
Cape Cod in 1984, American scallopers learned fast that their
two-thirds couldn't match the Canadians' rich portion. Periodic
incursions became the norm.
   But the raids have more than tripled in recent weeks, according
to Canadian and U.S. officials, who report as many as 20 U.S. boats
now cluster at the international line each night.
   Last week, a Canadian navy destroyer tailed a Fairhaven,
Mass.-based scalloper for 12 hours, during which a collision was
reported and warning shots were fired.
   Canadian scallopers, who have observed government-imposed
fishing quotas, are near despair. Their industry is losing more
than a $1 million a month to poachers even as 1,500 factory workers
in the outpost town of Canso are losing their jobs and skippers are
missing boat payments, officials said.
   ``We wouldn't allow American citizens to come up and raid our
shopping malls or banks,'' said Carl Goodwin, chief of surveillance
operations at the Canadian fisheries department. ``Why let them
raid our natural resources? We have to stop this before someone
gets hurt.''
   Radar and patrol records indicate a clear pattern. As soon as
the lone naval destroyer patrolling the boundary starts moving out
of sight, intruders steam in and haul out as many scallops as
possible. When the patrol ship comes back into view, the violators
take off.
   The incursions have become easier because Nova Scotia's
scallopers have been ashore since October, when they filled their
quotas. At the same time, Canada's Coast Guard, which usually
patrols the Hague Line, has been on strike.
   Robert Prier, the fishing department's director of conservation
and protection, said ``the flagrant disregard for Canadian
boundaries and authorities'' has worn very thin and warships have
been more frequently giving chase.
   ``They have been tolerant in the past, but this latest action
signifies a new direction in Canadian policy,'' said Lt. Craig
Lloyd, who is based at Coast Guard headquarters in Boston. ``We
will not interfere with their law enforcement efforts in
international waters.''
   Lloyd said no Canadians have been reported poaching in U.S.
waters, but, ``if we had Canadian fishing vessels over on our side
of the line we would take action to stop them.''
   The Fairhaven-based Concordia's captain said his charts
indicated he was in international waters. He compared the ``hot
pursuit'' to a wartime assault.
   ``Even if they see a boat fishing a half-mile over the line and
chase them out, isn't that good enough? Why do they want to start
sinking boats?'' William Furey Jr. asked Sunday.
   ``You're talking about a small boat and a few scallops or a few
fish. Is that serious enough to have 10 families burying their son
or husband a Christmas time?''
   But Canadian officials and fishermen, who note the high tech
navigation equipment virtually all scallopers use, rejected the
scenario.
   ``If you don't want war then don't break the rules,'' Goodwin
said. ``And if you want to take the risk ... then don't cry when
the shots are fired, or say we're too aggressive.''
   For the Canadian scallopers moored along these craggy shores,
the violations provoke a particularly bitter reaction. They stuck
to the government quotas imposed to protect against overfishing and
tied up their boats more than two months ago.
   Now it's Christmas time. Their savings are stretched and the
community's frustration mounts daily with second-hand reports of
how American poachers are illegally hauling in a hefty holiday
catch.
   ``Our boats are tied up and men are out of work while these
American guys are catching our scallops,'' said Albert Eisner, who
started fishing as a teen-ager. ``They're making fools of us. It's
an insult.''
   The story was different for the generations of scallopers from
New England and Canada who fished Georges Bank side by side, but
the brothers bound by sea have turned to battle since the Hague
Line was drawn.
   ``These guys have so many common bonds in the maritime
environment. They've often helped each other out through the
years,'' said Fred Greene, who runs several Nova Scotia-area
fishing enterprises. ``But our fishermen are being pushed to
desperation.''
   The problem defies easy solution. Canada lacks a treaty to
extradite Americans for fishing violations. Lloyd said the U.S.
Coast Guard planned to step up patrols and officials from both
countries have been discussing stiffer penalties for U.S.
intruders, but so far they're still paying less than 1 percent of
the $700,000 fines Canadian violators pay.
   ``You can't go out and solve this with warships. There's got to
be a better way,'' said Paul Allen, who has been scalloping for 34
years. ``But we better do something soon because I've no doubt it's
going to get worse.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>