<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0204 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0918EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-HousingStarts 1stLd-Writethru f0036 12-19 0338</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Housing Starts, 1st Ld-Writethru, f0036,0347</SECOND>
<HEAD>Housing Starts Fell 4.7 Percent in November</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Subs graf 2, The Commerce, to CORRECT `up' to `down.' This also
moved on general news wires.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN D. McCLAIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Housing starts fell 4.7 percent in November
after rising 13 percent a month earlier, the government reported
today.
   The Commerce Department said new homes and apartments were built
at a seasonally adjusted annual rate of 1.36 million units last
month, down from a revised 1.43 million units in October.
   The October increase was the largest since December 1986. Starts
had fallen 4.9 percent in September.
   The report was fresh evidence of the sluggishness in the housing
industry. Construction has been one of the economic sectors slowed
by high interest rates resulting from the Federal Reserve's grip on
credit as it strives to curtail inflation.
   In addition to its effect on construction jobs and the building
materials industries, the housing industry has an impact on other,
related industries, such as home appliances and furnishings.
   Interest rates ranged from 9.82 percent to 9.74 percent in
November, according to surveys by the Federal Home Loan Mortgage
Corp. Total housing starts during the first 11 months of the year
were down 6.5 percent from the same period of 1988.
   Construction of single-family homes in November dropped 0.9
percent to an annual rate of 1.02 million units. Single-family
starts had risen 5.5 percent in October.
   Apartment construction fell 14.4 percent in November to an
annual rate of 346,000 units after jumping 37.9 percent in October.
It had fallen 13.6 percent in September.
   The South had the steepest decline, down 11.3 percent to 495,000
units after rising 14.8 percent in October. Starts in the West also
fell, down 5.3 percent to 375,000 units.
   Starts increased 3.7 percent to 305,000 units in the Midwest and
3.3 percent to 295,000 units in the Northeast.
   Applications for building permits, a barometer of future housing
activity, edged down 1.7 percent after rising 2.8 percent in
October.
</TEXT>

</DOC>