<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0173 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 2315EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-NuclearWasteDump     12-29 0680</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nuclear Waste Dump,0705</SECOND>
<HEAD>Developer Picks Northern Nebraska For Nuclear Waste Dump</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By J.L. SCHMIDT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUTTE, Neb. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A builder announced Friday the selection of a
site near this tiny community for a low-level nuclear waste dump
for Nebraska, Kansas, Oklahoma, Arkansas and Louisiana.
   Opponents and a senator from neighboring South Dakota said they
would fight the selection, but others hailed the $40 million
project for the jobs and money it would bring to Boyd County in
northern Nebraska.
   The 320-acre site about two miles west of this community of
about 530 people and five miles from the South Dakota line was
chosen for its geology, said US Ecology Vice President Rich Paton.
   Gov. Kay Orr cautioned that it would be premature to conclude
that the site was acceptable until the licensing process is
completed.
   ``A license will not be issued unless US Ecology can convince us
that Nebraska's environment, and the health and safety of the
citizens of Boyd County will be protected,'' Mrs. Orr said.
   The application won't be made before July 1990, said US Ecology
spokesman Jim Neal.
   The reinforced, above-ground concrete vault system is expected
to begin operating in 1993 and to employ 25 to 30 people.
   It will have a 30-year lifespan and capacity for up to 5 million
cubic feet of radioactive waste, but officials estimate there will
be only 50,000 to 70,000 cubic feet, Neal said. The waste, gloves
and other radioactive garbage from nuclear power plants or
hospitals, will come from the five states.
   ``I don't think we have a whole lot of people who are afraid of
this thing,'' said Butte Mayor Ron Schroetlin.
   Schroetlin said the five-state waste compact commission had
promised $300,000 a year to the area chosen until the disposal site
is built and up to $2 million each year it is used.
   ``If that's used wisely it can help the whole county,'' he said.
   The site was one of three US Ecology was considering. The others
were in Nuckolls and Nemaha counties in southeast Nebraska.
   The 500 to 1,000 feet of impermeable shale bedrock beneath the
Boyd County site ``will provide a sound, natural barrier'' between
it and the Dakota Sandstone aquifer, Paton said said.
   US Ecology is developing the site for the Central Interstate
Low-Level Radioactive Waste Compact Commission. Member states voted
two years ago to make Nebraska the host state.
   In November 1988, Nebraska voters rejected an initiative
petition question to remove the state from the compact.
   Boyd County opponents had argued that their area contains
wetlands that should be protected, but Paton said US Ecology could
build without disturbing them.
   Harold Pierce, an area geologist who worked for the county
Low-Level Radioactive Waste Monitoring Committee, said US Ecology's
choice was a wise decision. ``There's not much question in my mind
that that's the best site, geologically and hydrologically,''
Pierce said.
   Actions over the years by local opponents included boycotting
businesses owned by supporters, and trying to recall a county
supervisor.
   Last month, a jury acquitted four Boyd County men accused of
confronting security guards at the gate of the proposed site, and
charges were dropped against a fifth.
   Schroetlin said things have calmed down. ``Maybe it will fire up
again,'' he said.
   U.S. Sen. Thomas A. Daschle, D-S.D., said he would ask the Army
Corps of Engineers and the Nuclear Regulatory Commission to review
the decision.
   ``I find it incredible that the state of Nebraska can determine
that a site that contains numerous federal wetlands would be
acceptable for a low-level nuclear waste site,'' the senator said.
   Lowell Fisher, head of the Save Boyd County anti-dump group,
said, ``We're going to do everything we can think of. We'll attack
it legally and every other way possible. I firmly believe it won't
be built here.''
   Boyd County's People for Progress, a group formed about a year
ago to support the waste site, welcomed US Ecology's choice.
   ``Now is the time for everyone to come together to work for the
good of our county,'' said Ken Reiser, the group's vice chairman.
</TEXT>

</DOC>