<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0047EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Lawyer-Explosion 3rdLd-Writethru a0722 12-19 0497</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lawyer-Explosion, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0722,0508</SECOND>
<HEAD>Black Activist Killed By Mail Bomb</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Rewrites throughout to UPDATE with FBI comment linking `similarities'
of bomb attacks and link to Atlanta tear-gas bombing in August; tightens;
no pickup.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Judge Explosion, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAVANNAH, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A lawyer was killed when a mail bomb
exploded in his office Monday, and federal agents said there were
``strong similarities'' to the mail bomb found at an Atlanta
courthouse and the mail bomb killing death of a federal judge in
Alabama.
   Robert Robinson, a city alderman and civil rights activist, died
of his wounds at 8:25 p.m. while undergoing surgery at Memorial
Medical Center about 3{ hours after the 5 p.m. bomb blast, said
hospital spokesman Michael Rowan.
   ``He lost his right arm, his left hand and some upper body
tissue and (suffered) severe damage to his legs,'' fellow alderman
Floyd Adams said earlier.
   Robinson was not able to communicate with doctors when he was
brought in to the hospital after the blast around 5 p.m., said
Jeryl Davis, another hospital spokesman.
   A mail bomb killed 11th U.S. Circuit of Appeals Judge Robert
Vance in Mountain Brook, Ala., on Saturday. Earlier Monday, a bomb
mailed to the 11th Circuit in Atlanta was discovered and removed
safely.
   At a news conference late Monday, FBI Special Agent Bob DeLoach
said it was ``definitely a possibility'' that white supremacists
sent the bomb that killed Robinson.
   DeLoach and Special Agent William Hinshaw said the FBI is
warning lawyers, judges and NAACP activists in Georgia and Alabama
to beware of strange packages.
   Hinshaw also said the FBI has warned the NAACP that the attacks
apparently are related to the Aug. 22, 1989, tear-gas bomb mailed
to NAACP's Atlanta offices, in which eight people, including a
4-month old child, were injured.
   Postal Inspector John Paul confirmed that the Postal Service is
investigating the Robinson slaying as well as Vance's because
Robinson was killed by a bomb that was in a package mailed to his
office.
   Police told the mayor's office that Robinson had ``received a
package, similar to what's been happening in Atlanta and
Birmingham,'' said Clerk of Council Dyanne Reese.
   ``The preliminary investigation indicates strong similarities to
the other explosive devices,'' FBI Agent Tom Moore said in
Birmingham, Ala., where authorities were investigating Vance's
assassination.
   ``The explosive and incendiary device experts from the FBI and
postal authorities who were in Birmingham yesterday and in Atlanta
today are being flown into Savannah,'' Moore said.
   Robinson represented the National Association for the
Advancement of Colored People in a long-running desegregation case
against the Savannah school system, said state Rep. Jim Pannell of
Savannah.
   Pannell, who attended the University of Georgia Law School with
Robinson, said Robinson was one of the first black students to
attend Savannah High School in the 1960s.
   He said Robinson handled many criminal defense and personal
injury cases, but he said he could not recall any which would have
supplied a motive for the bombing.
</TEXT>

</DOC>