<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0171 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1934EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Cuba     12-18 0497</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Cuba,1st Ld-Writethru,a0589,500</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Calls Cuba a ``Renegade Nation''</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDs: ADDS 9 grafs, State Department comment on terrorism and Cuban
view; Add byline</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The State Department renewed its criticism on
Monday of Cuban arms shipments to Central America and said ``it is
time for Cuba to stop acting like a renegade nation.''
   Department spokeswoman Margaret Tutwiler said Cuba should stop
sending weapons to Nicaragua's leftist government and Nicaragua
should stop sending such arms on to Salvadoran rebels.
   She said that Cuba must begin shouldering more responsibility
than before because it will soon become a member of the U.N.
Security Council.
   ``It needs now to begin acting in a way consistent with the
great responsibility it will bear in the council,'' she said.
   Her statement suggested a shift in emphasis about the U.S. view
of who is to blame for the continuing upheaval in Central America.
   The administration previously had said the Soviet Union had a
duty to persuade Cuba and Nicaragua to block the transfer of Soviet
bloc weapons to the Salvadoran insurgency.
   In her remarks on Monday, Ms. Tutwiler seemed to play down
Soviet responsibility for the continuing violence in Central
America. But, under questioning, she said that the administration
has not backed away from its previous view and that Central America
continues to be a divisive issue for Moscow and Washington.
   The administration does not challenge Moscow's contention that
it has ceased direct arms deliveries to Central America. But
officials say they are convinced that some Soviet weapons arrive in
Central America via third countries, especially Cuba.
   Monday evening, in response to a press question, the State
Department said that Cuba continues to be one of six countries on a
U.S. government list of countries that support international
terrorism.
   ``Cuba continues to provide safe haven, weapons and political
and financial support to a wide range of leftist and insurgent
organizations that use terrorism,'' the department said.
   It said Cuba supports a Colombian leftist group that has
attacked western economic interests.
   In addition, it said that the Salvadoran rebel group backed by
Cuba has publicly threatened Americans assisting the Salvadoran
government as ``legitimate targets of assassination.''
   Also, Cuba has supported a leftist group in Chile believed
responsible for several international terrorist incidents in recent
years, the department said.
   Joining Cuba on the State Department terrorism list are Iran,
Syria, Libya, South Yemen and North Korea.
   Cuba, in turn, regards the United States as the country most
prone to international adventurism worldwide. It has cited repeated
U.S.-sponsored assassination attempts against President Fidel
Castro and large-scale American military involvement in Central
America.
   Castro recently accused the United States of directly
intervening in the internal affairs of the Philippines by lending
air support to President Corazon Aquino during the recent coup
attempt.
   Beyond that, Castro said that the worldwide U.S. network of
military bases gives the United States the capability to intervene
in virtually any region on short notice.
</TEXT>

</DOC>