<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0130 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1939EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Peru-Rebels     12-28 0533</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Peru-Rebels,0551</SECOND>
<HEAD>Peruvian Rebels Attack Police; U.S. Helicopters Reported Involved</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANDREW SCOTT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LIMA, Peru (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Maoist guerrillas attacked a jungle police
post at dawn Thursday in the coca-rich Upper Huallaga Valley but
were repelled with the help of U.S. helicopters stationed in the
area for drug raids, officials said.
   One policeman was killed and four were wounded, they reported.
   At about 6:45 a.m., about 100 Shining Path rebels with
submachine guns and bazookas attacked the police post in Nuevo
Progreso, a jungle area 260 miles northeast of Lima, according to
Interior Minister Agustin Mantilla.
   Mantilla said the guerrillas fled after three Peruvian police
helicopters attacked them.
   A government anti-narcotics official, who spoke on condition of
anonymity, said the three helicopters were dispatched from the
U.S.-built antidrug base at Santa Lucia, about six miles from Nuevo
Progreso.
   Eight helicopters on loan to Peruvian police from the U.S. State
Department are stationed at the base for use in antidrug
operations. The helicopters are flown by American contract pilots
but are officially under police command _ the only police
helicopters that operate in the area.
   U.S. Embassy spokesman Gene Bigler said no U.S. helicopters or
personnel were involved in the battle.
   He told The Associated Press two helicopters piloted by
Americans flew a reconnaissance mission Thursday morning from the
base. He said base personnel received a request for assistance from
the police post at Nuevo Progreso, but said he did not know if the
reconnaissance flight was related to the attack.
   Bigler said three Peruvian army helicopters stationed in nearby
Uchiza picked up the police casualties and took them to Santa Lucia
so they could be flown to Lima.
   A military spokesman in Lima had no comment.
   The Peruvian drug official said three helicopters from the base
flown by Peruvians took part in the Thursday fray and pursued
retreating rebels.
   Bigler said no Peruvian pilots or co-pilots currently are at the
base.
   Santa Lucia is the operations center for U.S. drug agents
working with Peruvian police to attack clandestine airstrips and
coca-processing laboratories used by cocaine smugglers.
   Twenty to 40 Americans, including agents, contract pilots and
mechanics, work out of the base, where eight UH-1 (Huey)
helicopters are stationed. The helicopters have door-mounted M-60
machine guns.
   Huallaga Valley is the world's single largest source of the coca
leaf. Most of the leaf is made into coca paste and sent to Colombia
to be refined into cocaine.
   Joint operations began in September. Peru suspended them Dec. 21
to protest the U.S. invasion of Panama. The government lifted the
suspension and operations resumed Tuesday.
   Valley drug traffickers operate in league with Shining Path
rebels, who protect them from police for a share of drug profits.
   Bigler said U.S. law bars U.S. personnel and helicopters from
being used to fight the guerrillas. U.S. officials have
acknowledged, however, that antidrug operations could result in
confrontations with the rebels.
   The Shining Path began its insurgency in 1980 near Ayacucho, 235
miles southeast of Lima in the Andes Mountains. The rebels now
operate throughout the highlands and in the coca-producing jungles
of the northeast.
   The government says more than 17,000 people have died in the
violence.
</TEXT>

</DOC>