<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0181 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2235EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania 4thLd-Writethru a0810 12-21 1217</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0810,1254</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romanian Security Forces Fire on Crowds in Bucharest</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 2 grafs to UPDATE with U.S. statement. Pick up 2nd,
`Petar Tomic...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos BEL1,3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIOREL URMA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Nicolae Ceausescu sent tanks
into the streets of Bucharest Thursday and security forces with
submachine guns fired on young demonstrators protesting his iron
rule, killing at least 13 people.
   In Washington, the State Department said a ``massacre of
undetermined proportions'' was believed to have taken place the
last few days. Officials said the Bush administration was preparing
to reduce ties with Romania and hinted at possible sanctions.
   Petar Tomic, a Yugoslav journalist in the closed country, said
an armored vehicle crushed two students, other students rushed to
their aid and security forces opened fire, killing or wounding
about 20 people. He said other people were shot down, but he did
not have a casualty count.
   Clashes were reported in at least two other cities Thursday. A
Polish couple interviewed by Hungarian television said that in the
eastern city of Arad, soldiers fired on about 3,000 demonstrators.
   They said they saw some students ordered out of a college, made
to stand up against a wall and shot dead. When the alleged shooting
occurred was not clear.
   American diplomats counted at least 13 people felled by
automatic weapons fire and said more were possible, according to
State Department spokesman Richard Boucher.
   Jonathan Lamb, first secretary at the British Embassy in
Bucharest, told British Broadcasting Corp. TV that two of his
colleagues had seen the bloodied bodies of eight or nine young
people with head wounds, and guessed there could be many more.
   ``One of my colleagues stepped over a dead body,'' he said.
``Two of my colleagues have been towards another demonstration near
the American Embassy and they have found bodies in the streets.''
   He said he had ``no doubt'' security forces had fired on
protesters.
   It was the first violence in the capital since hundreds,
possibly thousands, of anti-Ceausescu demonstrators reportedly were
shot and killed by security forces last weekend in the
Transylvanian city of Timisoara, 500 miles from Bucharest.
   By 3 p.m., the official Yugoslav news agency Tanjug and the
Bulgarian state news agency BTA said from Bucharest, firing had
stopped. Elderly people urged troops not to act against the
protesters, BTA said.
   By early evening, however, Yugoslav radio and Tass reported more
bursts of automatic weapons fire.
   ``The streets are becoming more and more animated,'' Tass said,
adding that Romanian state TV had not begun its customary broadcast
at 8:00 p.m.
   The demonstators ``are surrounded by Romanian army soldiers,
special troops armed with truncheons and plastic shields and
security forces,'' Tass said. ``Choppers are patrolling over the
city.''
   The Tass correspondent said he was told by a man in plain
clothes, who identified himself as ``a representative of the
working people who helps to preserve order,'' that there was no
loss of life.
   The man said people who were seen being carried to ambulances
``had no time to dine, got overexcited and fainted.''
   Mass protests began after Ceausescu was shouted down while
addressing an official rally in a downtown square in the capital,
an occurrence unheard of in the nation he has treated like a feudal
fiefdom for 24 years. Official media switched off live coverage
when the jeering started.
   Last weekend in Timisoara, 30 miles from the Hungarian and
Yugoslav borders, police and soldiers opened fire on crowds
shouting ``Bread!'' and ``Down with Ceausescu!'' Estimates of
deaths there range from hundreds to 4,000.
   Resistance to Ceausescu, who on Wednesday returned from a
three-day official visit to Iran, spread to other cities in
Transylvania, to Moldavia in the north and on Thursday to Bucharest.
   Clashes were also reported Thursday in Arad and Cluj in
Transylvania. General strikes were reported in Timisora and Arad.
   Ceausescu, 71, faces his most serious challenge, with no support
and much criticism from Warsaw Pact allies whose societies are
being transformed by a democratic tide. The downfall of the old
guard elsewhere in Eastern Europe has made Ceausescu the
longest-serving Communist ruler.
   Journalists have not been admitted to Romania since the weekend,
and the travel of those already in the country is severely
restricted.
   Hungarian radio said in an early evening broadcast that
protesters chanted, ``The army is with us!'' _ indicating some
soldiers were unwilling to fire at demonstrators _ but also quoted
Hungarian Defense Ministry spokesman Gyoergy Keleti as saying
Romanian security forces wore military uniforms.
   Yugoslav media, quoting witnesses, reported that soldiers and
police who refused to fire on anti-government protesters in
Timisoara were executed. They did not say when the executions
occurred.
   Yugoslav radio said there were unconfirmed reports of strikes in
factories and that students were promoting a general strike.
   Hungarian radio said the Communist Party's ruling Politburo was
meeting in unannounced session, probably discussing the unrest.
   Timisoara was reported near open revolt.
   ``According to accounts coming from journalistic circles,
enterprises, plants and factories aren't working in Timisoara,''
Tass reported. ``They have been occupied by workers, who have
warned that if their conditions aren't met, they will blow up these
enterprises.
   ``The conditions ... include a demand for the government's
resignation and a demand that party officials, military and other
leaders who allowed loss of life in the town be called to account.''
   It said the workers demanded withdrawal of the army and,
``according to the latest information, the military units have
started to leave.''
   A Romanian who crossed to Yugoslavia said tanks were withdrawn
from Timisoara after workers occupying a large petrochemical plant
and threatened to blow it up.
   A Romanian traveler arriving in Yugoslavia said he also had
heard of protests Thursday in Craiova in the south and Suceava in
the north.
   Reports of continuing trouble in Timisoara suggested Ceausescu
obtained little effect by declaring a state of emergency in the
region Wednesday night that set an 11 p.m. curfew and banned
gatherings of more than five people.
   Foreign Minister Gyula Horn of Hungary said he had heard of
clashes ``between security forces'' and some army units and that
there was ``a serious political movement'' against Ceausescu.
   French President Francois Mitterrand said Ceausescu's days in
power ``are numbered.''
   A French radio station said Romanian exiles in Rome had
announced the desire to form a government-in-exile.
   At the official rally at which Ceausescu spoke, hundreds of
people began to boo and jeer, and thousands more soon joined in,
Tomic journalist said.
   Live radio transmission was interrupted for about three minutes
as the protesters approached and booed and jeered Ceausescu, whose
austerity programs and other harsh policies have imposed rationing
and other hardships on his 23 million people.
   Suddenly, there was a high-pitched noise on the radio, then
patriotic music was played for about three minutes before
Ceausescu's speech resumed in midsentence. Later broadcasts of the
speech were edited to omit the jeers.
   About 25 minutes after the scene at the rally, a Western
diplomat said, street protesters could be heard chanting ``Down
With Ceausescu!'' ``Freedom!'' and ``Timisoara, Timisoara!''
   Late in the afternoon, Hungarian radio said ``tens of thousands
of people'' were in the streets of Bucharest, some cutting the
Communist emblem out of the national flag after burning banners
made for the official rally.
</TEXT>

</DOC>