<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1310EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Flight103 2ndLd-Writethru   12-21 0538</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Flight 103, 2nd Ld - Writethru,a0583,0549</SECOND>
<HEAD>Friends, Relatives Gather For Flight 103 Anniversary</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Inserts two grafs after 5th, `Names of...' to UPDATE with New
York couple lighting luminaries. Pickup 6th pvs, `Wreaths heaped...</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LON1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LESLIE SHEPHERD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOCKERBIE, Scotland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As grieving relatives watched,
clergymen today dedicated a granite memorial etched with the names
of 270 people killed when their plane blew up over this once
obscure Scottish town.
   The somber dedication under leaden skies marked the first
anniversary of the terrorist bombing of Pan Am Flight 103.
   Two light aircraft trailing smoke to form a cross flew overhead
during the simple ceremony in a 19th century graveyard attended by
500 people, including at least 20 American relatives of victims.
   ``This is a family occasion,'' the local member of Parliament,
Sir Hector Monro, said before the group joined in singing ``The
Lord Is My Shepherd'' at the end of the 10-minute ceremony.
   Names of the victims are carved in roughly alphabetical order _
family members are grouped together _ in the light polished granite
of the 6-foot memorial consisting of three panels.
   As darkness fell, an American couple, Paul and Eleanor Hudson,
whose 16-year-old daughter, Melina, was killed, lit 270 luminarias
_ candles in sand-filled bags _ along a path leading to the
memorial and in a circle before it.
   ``It's the greatest honor I can think of,'' said Mrs. Hudson,
from Albany, N.Y. The luminarias were made by students at Melina's
school, the Albany Academy for Girls.
   Wreaths heaped at the foot of the memorial included one from
Syracuse University in New York, dedicated to its 25 students who
died on Flight 103 as they flew home for Christmas from an exchange
program.
   Relatives stood with heads bowed during the dedication.
Drizzling rain stopped as the service began in the Dryfesdale
Cemetery, one mile outside Lockerbie.
   No formal invitations were issued, but the U.S. ambassador,
Henry Catto, attended and Queen Elizabeth II sent a representative.
   Later today, American relatives were attending another service
at an isolated stone church outside the village near where the nose
cone crashed. To end the somber and poignant day, an ecumenical
service was being held in front of the Town Hall which a year ago
was turned into a makeshift morgue.
   ``I thought it was very appropriate and very respectful ... an
extension of the people of Lockerbie. They've given us faith and
hope throughout the year,'' said Joe Horgan of Philadelphia, a
member of the board of Victims of Pan Am flight 103. It represents
American victims.
   Horgan's brother-in-law, Michael Doyle, was on the flight.
   George Williams, 58, a real estate agent from Joppa, Md., said:
``While this might be a traumatic experience for us, the worst has
already happened.''
   Scottish investigators say the bomb that brought down Flight 103
was made of powerful plastic explosives concealed in a
radio-cassette player.
   Police heading the international manhunt for the bombers have
confirmed that one focus of their investigation is the Popular
Front for the Liberation of Palestine-General Command, Ahmed
Jibril's radical Syria-based faction.
   Jibril has denied involvement, but acknowledged his group has
used devices similar to the bomb that blew the jumbo jet apart.
</TEXT>

</DOC>