<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0234 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1732EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-McDonald's-Chairman     12-19 0457</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-McDonald's-Chairman,0475</SECOND>
<HEAD>Michael Quinlan Named McDonald's Chairman</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID DISHNEAU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Michael R. Quinlan, president and chief executive
of McDonald's Corp., will succeed Fred L. Turner as chairman of the
world's largest restaurant chain on March 31, the company announced
Tuesday.
   Quinlan, 45, said in an interview that he wants to put the
Golden Arches in China and that McDonald's customers will likely
see more dinner-type entrees added to the menu in coming years.
   ``The challenge to McDonald's is to be more things to more
people, the same philosophy we've been following for many years
now,'' Quinlan said.
   Turner, 56, will become senior chairman and continue as chairman
of the board's executive committee, McDonald's said in a statement.
   The post of senior chairman was previously held by company
founder Ray Kroc from 1977 _ when Turner succeeded Kroc as chairman
_ until Kroc's death in 1984.
   Quinlan joined McDonald's in 1963 as a part-time mailroom
employee. He served as a McDonald's restaurant manager, field
service manager, district and regional manager before being named a
vice president in 1974.
   He rose quickly through the executive ranks and was named in
1980 to the newly created position of president of McDonald's
U.S.A., in charge of domestic operations. Quinlan was named
president and chief operating officer of the corporation in 1982
and became chief executive officer in 1987.
   Quinlan will continue as CEO after assuming the chairmanship but
the position of corporate president will be eliminated.
   Industry analysts said Quinlan has been largely in charge of
operations since the mid-80s while Turner has been more involved in
strategic decisions.
   Among Quinlan's goals are further expansion of McDonald's into
Eastern Europe. The company has restaurants in Yugoslavia and
Hungary and plans to open one in Moscow on Jan. 31.
   The company also hopes to put a restaurant in Beijing, Quinlan
said.
   ``We've made some preliminary inquiries, we're studying the
infrastructure and we're searching for a partner over there,'' he
said. ``We're bullish on it.''
   The fast-food giant, based in the Chicago suburb of Oak Brook,
has 11,000 restaurants in more than 50 countries. International
business accounts for about 30 percent of McDonald's earnings,
which totaled $646 million last year.
   Analysts see foreign expansion and successful implementation of
an eat-in dinner menu as two keys to continued growth at
McDonald's, since the markets for fast-food breakfast, lunch and
take-out food are crowded with competitors.
   McDonald's has been test-marketing pizza and fried chicken, and
the company reportedly is considering low lighting, music and
platter-type dinners for suppertime customers.
   Quinlan will head a relatively youthful senior management team
which also includes Ed Rensi, 45, president of McDonald's U.S.A.,
and Jim Cantalupo, 46, president of the company's international
operations.
</TEXT>

</DOC>