<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0191 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1818EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Panama-Woerner 300   12-20 0289</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Woerner, 300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Southern Command Chief Says Military Attack `Well-Planned'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-US-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The former head of the U.S. Southern Command
in Panama, said Wednesday that the military strike against Panama
was ``well-planned and well-executed'' even though he has long
opposed the use of force there.
   Retired Gen. Fred Woerner, who left the Southern Command on
Sept. 30, also said the operation would be judged ``a disaster, an
absolute catastrophe'' if Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega returns to
power.
   Woerner had opposed military intervention in Panama, advocating
diplomatic and other peaceful options to dislodge Noriega. The
Panamanian leader has been indicted on drug charges in the United
States.
   Various U.S. administrations failed to deal successfully with
Noriega, ultimately pushing President Bush into a corner where he
could do nothing except send in the military, Woerner said.
   ``Bush had no other options. It had reached a point where an
American was killed,'' he said.
   Woerner, in a telephone interview from San Jose, Calif., said
Bush called for the military strike to protect the lives of
Americans and ensure freedom of movement in the Panama Canal.
   Although he did not have inside knowledge of the military
operation, Woerner said it appeared from news reports that it was
handled professionally and competently.
   ``The military operation looked well-planned and
well-executed,'' Woerner said, adding, however, that it apparently
took longer than expected.
   Woerner described Noriega as ``a clever, clever guy.'' The U.S.
operation won't be considered successful unless Noriega is either
captured or driven from Panama and never returns, Woerner said.
   He said he did not think Bush would call off the operation until
it was certain that Noriega could never return to Panama.
</TEXT>

</DOC>