<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0824EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p PM-PesticideFight     12-22 0407</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Pesticide Fight,0420</SECOND>
<HEAD>Farmers Offer Initiative to Counter Proposed Pesticide Ban</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   State farming and grocers' groups hope to
weed out an anti-pesticide ballot initiative sponsored by
environmentalists with a countermeasure aimed at cultivating more
trust in food safety.
   A coalition of agricultural groups Thursday unveiled a proposed
59-page ``wholesome food'' initiative that would double the amount
of food tested by the state for pesticide residues.
   But advocates of the anti-pesticide measure, which would phase
out the use of suspected cancer-causing pesticides over six years,
say the farming groups' countermeasure was designed to enhance its
image without eliminating toxic bug-killers.
   ``This is not to protect food, this is to protect their
privileged position, their status quo,'' said Assemblyman Tom
Hayden, who is co-sponsoring the anti-pesticide initiative with
Attorney General John Van de Kamp for the November 1990 ballot.
   The measure promoted by Hayden, Van de Kamp and environmental
groups deals with a variety of issues, including global warming and
offshore oil spills.
   But to farmers, the important part is the provision to phase out
the use of known cancer-causing pesticides. Opponents say that
would eliminate 70 percent to 80 percent of the registered
chemicals now used on California-grown food, reducing quality and
quantity.
   ``The Hayden-Van de Kamp measure is irresponsible. It takes a
sledgehammer approach rather than a common-sense approach to the
food safety issue,'' said Jasper Hempel, vice president of
government affairs for Western Growers Association.
   ``We've come up with a better mousetrap to reassure, or assure,
the public that our California-grown food is in fact safe,'' he
said.
   The farmers' measure is being pushed by a coalition calling
itself Californians for Responsible Food Laws, or CAREFUL.
   It would, among other things, double the amount of food tested
for pesticide residue, mandate a state review of children's health
protection laws and increase Mediterranean fruit fly eradication
research.
   But Hempel said the main goal of the measure was to forestall
the ``radical'' pesticide phase-out proposed in the environmental
bill.
   The coalition, which plans to begin gathering signatures for the
ballot measure in February, has hired a political consulting firm,
the Dolphin Group, and is prepared to spend $3 million to $5
million on the initiative campaign, said Lee Stitzenberger, a
political consultant with Dolphin.
   Signatures to qualify the anti-pesticide measure for the
November ballot already were being collected.
   Each bill needs 372,178 signatures of registered voters to
secure a place on the ballot.
</TEXT>

</DOC>