<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0279 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2218EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s f BC-China-OfficeGlut Adv24   12-20 1001</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-China-Office Glut, Adv 24,1030</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv24</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Sunday Dec. 24</HEAD>
<HEAD>Boom to Bust For Beijing Office Real Estate</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>BY JIM ABRAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Political instability and a staggering economy
are threatening to bust Beijing's booming market for foreign-office
space.
   Dozens of highrise office buildings are opening in the capital
this year and next, at a time when many overseas companies are
reducing operations in China or putting off new investment.
   ``It's going to be survival of the fittest,'' said James R.
Pitchon of Richard Ellis, property consultant for the World Trade
Center, Beijing's biggest building project. ``We have a baby market
here, and things have been made worse by the current economic
situation.''
   Pitchon estimated that by the end of 1990 there will be nearly
double the amount of office space currently required by the 1,100
foreign companies with offices in Beijing.
   It will be a drastic turnaround from even a year ago, when more
than half of all foreigners were working out of Chinese hotel rooms
with peeling paint, antiquated telephones and stalled elevators.
   Foreign companies began moving representatives into Beijing
around 1980 with the advent of Deng Xiaoping's economic reforms and
open door policy. But it was not until 1985, with the opening of
the 29-story China International Trust and Investment Corp. (CITIC)
building, that a select few companies had their first access to
modern office space.
   In 1986 the Holiday Inn Lido complex of hotel, apartments and
offices opened for businessmen and the next year the 23-story Noble
Tower, a project marked by bitter disputes between its Chinese and
Canadian partners, began taking in tenants.
   But that still provided only about 57,000 square yards of office
space. By next year, the figure will be five times as great.
   Heading the newcomers is the World Trade Center, a joint venture
with Hong Kong-based Kerry Industrial Co. That features a 38-story
tower with 61,000 square yards of office space, two 30-story luxury
apartment buildings and two hotels with more than 1,000 rooms.
   Among the competition is the Jing Guang Center, a 51-story
office-apartment-hotel built with Hong Kong and Japanese
participation; the 20-story Fortune Building financed by Japan's
Nomura Securities Group; the Hua Wei Center, a Norwegian-Chinese
apartment-business project with 23,000 square yards of office
space; and Capital Mansion, a CITIC undertaking with a 52-story
office-apartment building.
   Their openings, however, are clouded by the June military
crackdown on the pro-democracy movement and an austerity policy
that has stalled the economy and left in doubt the future direction
of China's market-oriented reforms. Few companies have left China,
but many have trimmed expatriate staff or canceled plans for
further investment.
   Many foreign businesses likely will wait one or two years before
deciding the extent of their commitment to China, some real estate
experts say, and investing in costly new office quarters will not
be a top priority.
   Most of the projects are months behind schedule because of
typical construction delays in China compounded by work stoppages
during the political turmoil of this spring. The World Trade,
originally slated to cost $380 million, now will require $450
million due to expense overruns.
   Many projects, such as the two-tower Asia-Pacific Building
financed partly by Singaporean and Japanese funds, have asked for
rescheduling of loans and extensions of joint venture contracts
because of expected slow returns on investment.
   The Chinese partner in the World Trade Center, the Ministry of
Foreign Economic Relations and Trade, has already agreed to extend
the life of the joint venture from 20 to 30 years.
   At least one major project, a planned 17-story hotel and office
building involving the Japanese builder Takenaka Komuten,
Mitsubishi Bank and Japan Air Lines, halted construction after June.
   ``We haven't abandoned the project,'' Takenaka spokesman Fujio
Takeuchi said in Tokyo. But he said the project team is waiting for
the domestic situation in China to return to normal.
   Another project, CITIC's Capital Mansion, has been hit by
construction delays and financing problems and, according to some
foreign real estate experts, is a ``white elephant.''
   Capital Mansion Deputy General Manager Yang Long said the
building will not open until the end of 1990. He expressed
confidence the project would succeed, but said it isn't signing
contracts yet and ``we face serious competition.''
   ``It's a race against time,'' said George P. Maier, chief
operations officer of the Jing Guang Center. Those already taking
in tenants have a big advantage, he said.
   The Jing Guang began filling its offices and apartments in
December and the World Trade Center will have 115 tenants, about 60
percent occupancy, by the end of January.
   The Fortune Building, promoted by its Japanese managers as a
high-technology office complex with a satellite transmission
network, has about 40 mostly Japanese tenants and foresees
occupancy of about 65 percent next year.
   The Norwegian Hua Wei Center, which won't open until next
summer, has leased only 20 percent of its office space and like
many others is offering ``flexible terms'' to attract customers.
   The center is asking $35 per square yard a month, but Sales
Manager Dorophy Leung said ``this price is negotiable and we will
offer discounts.''
   The World Trade Center has also cut its rates from near $40 to
about $35 a square yard.
   Office buildings also may face competition from newly built
hotels, which face an even greater glut in the near future because
of the post-June collapse of the tourist market. The State
Council-owned Capital Hotel, with an occupancy rate of 30 percent,
recently began advertising guest suites for use as offices.
   According to one survey, there will be about 24,000 rooms in
Western-style hotels in Beijing by 1991, double that of 1988 and
seven times the figure in 1983.
   Developers said the oversupply problem should eventually work
itself out, but much depends on China's political stability and
economic health. ``It could be a boom town,'' said the World Trade
Center's Pitchon. ``And it could be a ghost town.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End adv for Sunday Dec. 24</NOTE>

</DOC>