<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1452EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-AgriculturalIntrigue     12-25 0760</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Agricultural Intrigue,750</SECOND>
<HEAD>Texan's Off-The-Record Conversation Sparks Furor In International
Agriculture</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JENNIFER DIXON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When Texan John Baize, a vice president for
the American Soybean Association, criticized the United States'
controversial sugar program in an interview with a graduate
student, he thought he was speaking off the record.
   But after copies of an alleged transcript were leaked on Capitol
Hill, Baize found himself out of a job and at the center of an
international intrigue that has touched Minnesota's agriculture
commissioner _ and apparently angered Agriculture Secretary Clayton
Yeutter.
   At a yearend news conference Thursday, Yeutter appealed for
broad support of liberalized trade policies being advocated in
Geneva in ongoing negotiations under the General Agreement on
Tariffs and Trade.
   Yeutter said he believes there is broad support for the Bush
administration's proposals but noted that ``we have seen some
evidence of undercutting here and there by particular groups,''
which he did not identify.
   Kelly Shipp, his press secretary, later told The Associated
Press that Yeutter referred mostly to Minnesota Agriculture
Commissioner Jim Nichols, a Democrat, and not specifically to any
farm organizations.
   Pressed about Nichols, she said only that Nichols was ``the one
that's on his mind.''
   In an interview Friday, Nichols said the ``Baize incident'' and
Yeutter's complaints are linked, and he is not Yeutter's only
opponent on GATT issues.
   Nichols' farm policy analyst, Mark Ritchie, is responsible for
circulating copies of Baize's interview with the European student
to Minnesota sugar beet growers _ who have a stake in protecting
the government's strict quotas on sugar imports. Those comments
ended up on Capitol Hill and sparked the furor that led to Baize's
resignation on Nov. 10 from the job he had held since 1979.
   As Baize's comments were circulated anonymously on Capitol Hill,
Ritchie also was circulating GATT documents in Congress from the
U.S. Trade Representative, which Nichols contended pitted soybean
farmers against sugar producers.
   Baize believes the student who taped the August interview _
which he thought was to be an academic discussion to help her write
a thesis on agricultural trade _ turned the tape over to an
organization in France.
   Baize said the French group apparently gave the interview to
Ritchie, who acknowledges providing summaries to Minnesota sugar
beet growers.
   Those growers contacted others in the sugar industry and the
transcript was suddenly being ``faxed all over the Hill,'' Baize
said.
   Marlyn Jorgensen, president of the American Soybean Association,
moved to assure Rep. Kika de la Garza, D-Texas, chairman of the
House Agriculture Committee, that the ASA does not oppose the U.S.
sugar program.
   In a letter dated Oct. 25, Jorgensen told de la Garza, whose
district includes Texas' sugar cane growers, that Baize's comments
had been taken out of context and ``it appears that ASA has been
used for purposes that many of us do not know.''
   `I cant' believe John lost his job over this deal,'' Nichols
said. ``John's said it for years.''
   Said Baize: ``I had a frank, academic discussion and I
understood and was told it was to be off the record. I resent
anyone using an off-the-record interview, taking things out of
context, with a malicious intent to injure me. But so be it.''
   Baize, a Gatesville, Texas, native, said his sources say the
student was told before she left Europe to specifically interview
him, and that when she returned, the group asked for only one
interview tape out of 25 or 30 _ his.
   Baize said he may have been singled out because he was the
architect of the Soybean Association's charge that the European
Community's oilseed subsidies were illegal under international
trading rules.
   A dispute settlement panel of GATT ruled ``the U.S. position was
100 percent correct,'' Baize said.
   ``The fact that we filed the case and were very aggressive in
persuing it here and in Europe, angered a lot of people in the
oilseed industry in France and Europe,'' Baize said.
   Ritchie, the farm policy analyst, claims Baize knew the
interview was on the record and that the student's report would be
published in Europe.
   Ritchie, who is on a technical review committee for the
student's thesis, said Baize's comments put his state's $370
million sugar beet industry at risk by giving Europe more
ammunition to fight the U.S. sugar program in GATT.
   Baize, meanwhile, said he has ``other irons in the fire,'' and
is not bitter at his former employer.
   ``I guess I've always been a sucker for these students who come
in and want to learn something,'' Baize said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>