<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0218 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1448EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Trump-Pilots 1stLd-Writethru   12-19 0350</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Trump-Pilots, 1st Ld-Writethru,0359</SECOND>
<HEAD>Trump Shuttle Reaches Contract Agreement with Pilots</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: New grafs 3-6 to UPDATE with head of pilots union predicting
ratification, noting difference from Eastern contract talks; picks up 5th
graf pvs bg'ng, The Trump ...; ADDS byline</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCY GORDON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Trump Shuttle, the northeast airline service
named after the billionaire developer who bought it six months ago,
has reached a collective bargaining agreement with the pilots union.
   The 4-year agreement, which must be ratified by the rank and
file, provides for improvements in wages, benefits and work rules,
the airline said Tuesday. Trump Shuttle spokeswoman Joan Fudala
declined to give any details.
   ``I don't think there's any doubt that it will be ratified,''
Les Robinson, head of the pilots union at the airline, said in a
telephone interview. He also declined to disclose details of the
tentative agreement.
   Ray Grebey, the shuttle's chief labor negotiator, said in a
statement the new agreement ``recognizes the unique nature of
hourly shuttle operations''.
   Most of the 225 pilots at Trump Shuttle, which links New York
with Boston and Washington, formerly worked for Eastern Airlines.
Wealthy property developer Donald Trump bought the shuttle service
from Miami-based Eastern for $365 million in early June.
   ``We are not any longer working for a have-not airline,''
Robinson said. Calling the brief contract negotiations ``a real
love-in,'' he said they were markedly different from the ``Eastern
tradition'' of adversarial relations between employees and
management.
   The Trump Shuttle pilots are members of the Air Line Pilots
Association, one of three unions that struck Eastern last March,
forcing it to seek bankruptcy court reorganization. The Eastern
pilots and flight attendants halted their strikes shortly before
Thanksgiving, but the Machinists union is continuing its walkout.
   Contract negotiations covering the 280 flight attendants at
Trump Shuttle are due to start in the first quarter of next year,
Ms. Fudala said. Talks with the Machinists union have been
postponed pending a challenge from a rival group, the Aircraft
Mechanics Fraternal Association, which is seeking to represent
mechanics at the shuttle.
</TEXT>

</DOC>