<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0236 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0154EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-HolidaySales Bjt   12-22 0800</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Holiday Sales, Bjt,0830</SECOND>
<HEAD>Last-Minute Buyers Boost Business But Retailers Still Under Pressure</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARYBETH NIBLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Bargain-hunting Christmas shoppers have had a field day this
year, with sale signs competing with holiday decorations for
attention at many of the nation's department stores as troubled
retailers scrap to pay their debts.
   But some industry analysts say the lower prices may have hurt
the traditional last-minute buying spree.
   ``I think that we're seeing a moderate increase in retail
momentum in the last week,'' Morgan Stanley &amp; Co. Inc. analyst
Walter Loeb said Thursday. Sales of coats, sweaters and other warm
clothing have been better than expected because of bitterly cold
weather around the country, he said.
   However, Loeb said, ``some of the excitement of the last-minute
shopping was undermined.''
   As the days tick down toward Christmas, retailers are counting
on down-to-the-wire buyers to boost business and bolster profits at
this crucial time of year.
   Several store executives said Thursday said they noticed a
pickup in sales heading into a final weekend that could decide if
this is a ho-hum or ho-ho-ho holiday season.
   Bargain hunters have been enjoying a jolly time since
Thanksgiving, finding plenty of prices marked down _ particularly
at department stores owned by cash-starved Campeau Corp. and their
competitors.
   In the dog-eat-dog New York market, Campeau-owned Bloomingdale's
as well as rivals Macy's and Lord &amp; Taylor have been advertising
price cuts of 20 percent or more on dresses, sweaters and other
apparel. Bloomingdale's, which is being sold by Campeau, is under
extra pressure to pump up sales so that it will fetch the best
possible bid.
   The price competition isn't as fierce in all metropolitan areas
as it is in New York but analysts say that this year generally has
been more promotional than normal.
   Retailers offering enhanced services, such as personal shoppers
and pre-wrapped presents, say the effort is paying off. Many
retailers are pleased with their results so far.
   John Buller, senior vice president of marketing at The Bon
Marche, said the Seattle-based department store chain, owned by
Campeau, is having one of its best years ever.
   Sales at The Bon Marche's 43 stores mostly in the Pacific
Northwest have been running in the ``high single digits'' above
last year, spurred by numerous merchandising ideas, Buller said.
Every floor of each store has displays of gifts wrapped and ready
to be put under Christmas trees.
   Luxury gifts and accommodating service have pulled in customers.
Kenneth Watson, chairman and chief executive officer of Gump's,
said that in addition to providing personal shoppers _ staff who
act as elves for customers _ Gump's is offering free delivery in
the San Francisco Bay area and direct telephone lines to make it
easier for shoppers to place orders.
   Watson said holiday business at the upscale specialty chain is
about 12 percent ahead of year ago. ``I would say in our case it's
much better than expected or anticipated,'' he said.
   Crystal, watches, pens, travelers' clocks and leather bags have
been fast sellers at the tony Cartier jewelry stores, said Thierry
Chaunu, vice president of marketing.
   In addition to discounted apparel and accessories, moderately
priced home furnishings appear to be selling well, store executives
and analysts said.
   Clark A. Johnson, chairman and chief executive officer of Pier I
Imports Inc., a specialty furnishings chain of 511 stores, said
Christmas sales are running about 20 percent above 1988. The
strongest regions have been Florida, northern California and the
Pacific Northwest, while Texas and the Boston area have been the
weakest.
   Spending on consumer electronics seems to have held up despite
overall sluggish sales of expensive durable merchandise, such as
home appliances.
   The 90-plus franchisees of Software City have reported ``pretty
brisk'' business since Thanksgiving, president Shep Altshuler said.
   Maria Cirino, marketing vice president for the New Jersey-based
discounter, said sophisticated computer systems previously
associated with businesses are being bought for home use.
   Programs that help people organize budgets or tax information
and educate children are hot sellers, she said. Broder Bund's
software including ``Where in the World is Carmen Sandiego'' or
``Where in Time is Carmen Sandiego,'' intended to teach geography
and history, are two sought-after programs.
   Many retailers were reluctant to assess their performance
knowing that the next few days could be crucial. A late rally last
year salvaged the holiday season, which typically accounts for half
or more of a retailer's annual profits.
   ``The question is: `What happened this week?''' said Rosalind
Wells, chief economist of the National Retail Merchants Association.
   Even if it meets retailers' most optimistic dreams, there will
be stores stuck with slow-moving merchandise that will have to
slash prices to unload seasonal goods.
   Said Loeb of Morgan Stanley: ``There will be heavy clearance
markdowns. You've got to get rid of seasonal merchandise.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>