<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0116EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-USReaction     12-23 0515</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-US Reaction,0531</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Occupiers Get Mixed Reaction in Panama City</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALINA GUERRERO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Panamanians greeted occupying U.S.
forces with some cheers and some sneers but mostly fear, and many
remained at home rather than risk exposure in glass-littered
streets swarming with looters.
   Some of those who did venture out expressed hopes only that the
bloodshed and destruction would cease.
   Businessman Moises Levi pointed at his looted store and then at
an American soldier standing atop a nearby armored personnel
carrier.
   ``How many soldiers are there here, 20,000, 40,000? Where are
they?'' he asked.
   Mayhem and destruction have descended on the city since U.S.
troops began their invasion at midnight Tuesday. Knots of fighters
backing ousted Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega have attacked, then
disappeared, while shopkeepers trade shots with swarms of looters.
   ``They really screwed me up as a businessman,'' said bicycle
shop owner Ivan Rios. ``As a Panamanian, I am opposed to this type
of military action against my country, but I am also glad that at
last we are going to have democracy.''
   Many Panamanians were too frightened to come out of their homes
and display any emotion about the events that rocked their Central
American country, but some did cheer Americans stationed around the
Nicaraguan Embassy.
   Streets in this city of 1 million people were layered with
broken glass, overturned trash cans and fallen light poles. Plumes
of smoke darkened the sky where gunfire and mortar attacks were
launched.
   Two American officers escorted by a dozen American GIs in battle
gear toured the Santo Tomas Hospital. Deputy director Dr. Elmer
Miranda said they were ``on an inspection'' of the building.
   Miranda criticized the Americans because, in addition to dead
and wounded, the assault created a shortage of food and all types
of medicines. He said the closing of airports was preventing aid
from entering the country.
   One administrative employee hurrying along a corridor also
chastized the American action.
   ``They are butchering us. We don't want any help from them,''
she said. ``The United States are courageous with Panama, but they
do not dare meddle with Russia or Japan.''
   Out on the streets, though, a busload of civilians passing by
the Nicaraguan Embassy on Friday morning waved white handkerchiefs
and cheered the U.S. soldiers standing by their armored cars.
   The Americans, who cordoned off the embassy following rumors
that Noriega was there, smiled and waved back.
   Marine Lance Cpl. Tracy Scott Jones of Dallas said that after
the shock of the first day's battle, ``People were cheering us on.
They are on our side. They clapped as we rolled through the
streets. There was no hostility.''
   Lance Cpl. William Young of Seattle said civilians were
``friendly. They give us the thumbs up sign.''
   ``When you go out on a mission at night the situation is pretty
tense. You just look at the darkness and all you can see are the
shapes of people,'' said Young. ``But, then when you go out in the
day, people are pretty friendly.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>