<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0241 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1858EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-AmericanExpansion 1stLd-Writethru   12-19 0777</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-American Expansion, 1st Ld-Writethru,0799</SECOND>
<HEAD>American Airlines Pushing Beyond U.S. Borders</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS one graf for grafs 7-8 to UPDATE with confirmation of American
purchase of Eastern routes. Edit to conform. Also SUBS 11th graf to CORRECT
spelling of Lyon, France.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-American-Eastern</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN A. BOLT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   American Airlines Inc., which became the No. 1
domestic carrier this year, is taking advantage of sales by
competitors and expected industry weakness next year to push its
international expansion and become more than an American airline.
   The moves are necessary, analysts say, if American is to become
a ``player'' internationally. It currently has 5 percent of the
European market.
   Fast and furious dealmaking could also have the pleasant side
effect of making parent AMR Corp. less attractive to a corporate
raider by decreasing cash and depressing earnings.
   ``We have developed at American Airlines a very wide-ranging
growth plan that we have been pursuing for five years that is long
range in nature and will carry us into the next century,'' said
company spokesman Al Becker.
   ``One piece of it is international expansion. That includes
Europe, the Pacific Rim and eventually Latin America.'' American
also has talked to Aeroflot about gaining entrance to the Soviet
Union, Becker said.
   ``These are good long-term moves and if they affect earnings in
the short term, they can deal with that,'' said analyst Mark
Daugherty at Dean Witter Reynolds in New York.
   American, based in Fort Worth, took the Latin American plunge in
one move Tuesday, saying it would pay Eastern Airlines $471 million
for its 20 Central and South American routes, plus the rights to
some other European cities and some domestic facilities.
   Just Monday, American announced a $195 million deal with Trans
World Airlines Inc. for its Chicago-London route, plus four gates
and a maintenance hangar at Chicago O'Hare International Airport.
Also a bankruptcy court judge approved American's $400,000 purchase
of Braniff landing rights at Chicago and New York.
   By the middle of next year, American will have about 165 flights
weekly to 18 European cities. Six years ago, it flew to none.
   American has been expanding vigorously this year, spending
billions on new airplanes to fly its newly acquired, or
sought-after routes; beginning work on a $400 million maintenance
facility to service the jets; expanding its operations at domestic
hubs; and fighting off billionaire Donald Trump, aided in large
degree by the collapse of another airline buyout.
   This year alone, American has begun service to Stockholm,
Sweden; Lyon, France, Brussels, Belgium; Hamburg, Dusseldorf and
Stuttgart, West Germany; and Zurich, Switzerland. In addition, next
year, American will add service to Barcelona, Spain; Helsinki,
Finland; Warsaw, Poland; and Glasgow, Scotland.
   In the Pacific, American next year will begin flying to Sydney,
Australia and Auckland, New Zealand. Also, independent of any deal
with Eastern, American has announced increased service to
Monterrey, Cancun and Cozumel, Mexico.
   The airline also is trying to add a second Tokyo flight, and is
investigating flights to Seoul, Korea; Taipei, Taiwan; Hong Kong;
Singapore; and Manila.
   Additionally, American is considering expanding service in
Canada, which it does not consider among its international
destinations.
   The growth has been financed through record profits, although
Chairman Robert Crandall has warned the performance won't continue
this quarter or next year.
   But the company has plenty of cash, and an appetite for spending.
   ``There's a good deal of expansion we still want to do in
Europe,'' Becker said. ``Our basic feeling is that some of the
opportunities that are out there may not be as readily available in
1992'' when many interior European trade barriers fall.
   ``Part of our strategy is to build as much of our route system
before 1992 as we can,'' he said because of fears outsiders will
have difficulty competing in a unified European market.
   American had no international service in 1982 after jettisoning
unprofitable Pacific service in the mid-70s. An old subsidiary,
American Overseas Airways, was sold to Pan American in the early
'50s.
   American is not endangering its financial health through the
expansion, the analysts said.
   ``They're not going out and buying assets willy nilly,'' said
Edward Starkman at PaineWebber. ``It's one of the best-run
companies in this industry.''
   But analyst Helane Becker of Shearson Lehman Hutton sounded a
warning note.
   ``I really think that you don't necessarily want to take $500
million or $200 million cash and give it to a competitor that would
be out of business in a year,'' she said, referring to Eastern and
TWA. ``You sort of have to wonder if they could buy these assets
out of bankruptcy at a cheaper price than they're doing today.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>