<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0312EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-US-PanamaStatement 3rdAdd   12-20 0520</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-US-Panama Statement, 3rd Add,520</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHN: that basis.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Q. Where are they now?
   A. I don't have their exact location.
   Q. Since this is a declaration of war, why didn't the president
come out and announce it himself?
   A. The declaration of war was set by Panama, not by the United
States, so don't get that confused. The president is acting here to
safeguard American lives, to protect the Panama Canal treaty, to
secure the person who is under indictment for drug trafficking. But
the only declaration of war has been on the side of the Panamanians.
   Q. Casualties.
   A. I have no information.
   Q. What's the legal basis here in terms of a declaration of war
... and how had Congress been informed?
   A. We are basing this on the actions outlined in this statement,
which is a pattern of agression in recent days which we think is
quite threatening to American citizens in Panama. There are some
35,000 Americans there as I recall, roughly 35,000 Americans in
Panama _ in a pattern of harassment and threats going back almost a
year that involves literally hundreds of cases. I'll try to provide
you some details on that later. And on the president's strong
feeling that we need to uphold the indictment and to move in this
fashion.
   Q. How has Congress been informed?
   A. The president has telephoned earlier this evening the
leadership of the Congress, Michel, Foley, Mitchell, Dole. Other
members of the Armed Services Committee, Foreign Affairs Committee,
intelligence committees are being called this evening. And they are
all receiving briefings and information on the actions being taken.
   Q. What is their reaction?
   A. Their initial reaction has been supportive. The president has
talked to them briefly, but did outline our purposes in much the
same words that I have used here, and we have only heard support.
   Q. Any final ultimatum, directly or indirectly, to Noriega in
the last few hours?
   A. Our ultimatum is as stated, that we are there to apprehend
him and bring him back to America for prosecution.
   Q. Any attempt to communicate with him or warn him what's going
to happen if you don't quit?
   A. No.
   Q. Where is the president monitoring the events and who is with
him now?
   Q. The president is in the Oval Office and also in his study
which is right off the Oval Office. Governor Sununu has been with
him much of the evening. General Scowcroft has been there much of
the evening. Secretary Baker was there for a short time. Robert
Gates, the deputy national security adviser has convened the
deputies group. He did that earlier this evening. They are meeting
continually through this crisis and will continue to do that. Mr.
Gates is providing minute-by-minute updates as he receives them and
the president is monitoring this through other channels that are
associated with the presence of General Scowcroft.
   Q. The vice president, was he here?
   A. The vice president is here. He is in his office and he is
making phone calls at this time to various world leaders.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>