<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0218 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0213EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Ms.Magazine     12-21 0480</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Ms. Magazine,0499</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lang Plans To Make Ms. an Ad-Free Bimonthly Magazine, Names New Editor</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SKIP WOLLENBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ms. magazine is going to be back next spring
without ads and will appear once every other month rather than
monthly, its new owner says.
   Dale W. Lang, whose Lang Communications Inc. assumed control of
Ms. in mid-October, also said Wednesday he had selected a new
editor in chief for the magazine, feminist activist and author
Robin Morgan.
   The magazine, founded in 1972, had not been profitable and often
found itself at odds with advertisers over its editorial content.
   Lang had said publishing the magazine without ads would relieve
it from ``external pressures'' and enable its editorial staff to
concentrate on pursuing issues important to women without concerns
about advertiser backlash.
   The last issue of Ms. magazine was dated November. No specific
date was set for resumption of publication as a bimonthly.
   Lang was said to be unavailable for comment on the le sent a
letter of explanation from Gloria Steinem, a co-founder of the
magazine who remains a consultant to the publication.
   Spokeswoman Andrea Kaplan said Ms. Steinem would outline the
plans for Ms. and offer readers a chance to get issues of Working
Woman, Working Mother or similar magazines in the months remaining
before Ms. resumes publication.
   Lang Communications owns Working Woman and Working Mother as
well as the teen magazine Sassy and Success, a magazine for
entrepreneurs.
   Ms. Morgan, the new editor, replaces Anne Summers, who had held
that post since November 1987 and remains as editor-at-large of the
magazine.
   Ms. Summers had been part of a group including management that
bought Ms. and Sassy in July 1988 from the Australian media company
John Fairfax Ltd. Terms of Lang's acquisition of a controlling
interest in that company have not been disclosed.
   Ms. Morgan has written 12 books, including ``The Demon Lover: On
the Sexuality of Terrorism,'' ``Sisterhood is Powerful'' and
``Sisterhood is Global.'' She was a contributing editor to Ms. from
1974 to 1987.
   She was also described as a founder and leader of the feminist
movement in the United States and was a creator of the Sisterhood
is Global Institute, a feminist research organization.
   She was said to be unavailable for comment on her new job.
   Asked why Lang felt a new editor was needed for the magazine,
Ms. Kaplan said he felt ``a new editor will have a fresh
perspective on the magazine.''
   The last issue of Ms. had actress Glenn Close on the cover, but
Ms. Kaplan said the new Ms. would no longer rely on celebrity
interviews or profiles.
   ``It's going to be a hard-hitting, journalistic magazine,'' she
said.
   Industry observers have said they expect Ms. will scale back its
circulation base of 550,000 when it resumes publication.
</TEXT>

</DOC>