<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0705EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Hostages     12-25 0501</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hostages,0522</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lebanese TV, Newspapers Release Christmas Messages To Hostages</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FAROUK NASSAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Newspapers, radio and television stations
today released morale-boosting messages to eight Americans held
hostage in Lebanon, including two marking a fifth Christimas in
captivity.
   But there was no way to ascertain whether Terry Anderson and
Thomas Sutherland, kidnapped in 1985, or any of the other American
captives who are believed held by Shiite Moslem extremists were
allowed to hear or read the messages.
   ``I can hardly believe that your fifth Christmas season in
captivity is approaching,'' said Anderson's sister, Peggy Say, in a
letter written in advance to coincide with Christmas.
   ``Despite having no valid reason for believing that you might
celebrate this season as a free man, my faith prompts me to pray
very hard for a Christmas miracle,'' she wrote.
   The English text of her letter was published by the newspaper
An-Nahar along with an Arabic translation.
   The conservative Al-Anwar, the pro-Syrian Ash-Sharq and the
Moslem Al-Liwa published the Arabic translation of the letter, and
radio and television stations broadcast the message in English.
   ``We are counting on you to hold yourself together physically,
spiritually and emotionally until your day of freedom comes,'' Mrs.
Say wrote to Anderson, chief Middle East correspondent for The
Associated Press.
   ``Until then, stay strong and know that neither you nor those
held with you are alone or forgotten. Your daughters are as always,
well and beautiful.''
   Anderson has two daughters, Gabrielle, 13, and Sulome, 4. The
younger daughter was born three months after he was kidnapped on
March 16, 1985.
   Anderson, 42, of Lorain, Ohio, is the longest-held of the 18
Western captives in Lebanon.
   He and Sutherland, 58, of Fort Collins, Colo., are held by
Islamic Jihad, or Holy War, an extremist group seeking the release
of 15 comrades jailed in Kuwait on terrorist charges.
   Sutherland, acting dean of agriculture at the American
University of Beirut, was kidnapped June 9, 1985.
   One newspaper, the leftist As-Safir, published a paid
advertisement in Arabic and English carrying the message to
Sutherland.
   It was signed by his wife, Jean, his daughters Ann, Simone, Kit,
and Joan and the Murray and Sutherland families.
   ``May this find you and bring all the gifts we have of love,
hope, comfort, and spirit,'' the letter said. ``We wait for you _
we exist, we do not live without you.''
   The newspapers also published a letter from the Journalists
Committee to Free Terry Anderson that was addressed to all eight
Americans.
   The six others are Frank Reed, Joseph Cicippio, Edward Austin
Tracy, Alann Steen, Jesse Turner and Robert Polhill.
   ``We had hoped and prayed that this Christmas would be different
from the others and we'd see you all home,'' said the letter signed
by Bill Foley and Cary Vaughan for the committee.
   It concluded: ``Someday, someway, you will come home.''
   The other foreign hostages in Lebanon include four Britons, two
West Germans, two Swiss, an Italian and an Irishman.
</TEXT>

</DOC>