<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0155 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1918EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Panama-American 2ndLd-Writethru a0663 12-29 0340</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-American, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0663,330</SECOND>
<HEAD>Third American Civilian Reported Dead in Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDs: SUBS 3rd graf: ``Dragseth was,'' to CORRECT last name of earlier
victim from Helen to Helin</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The remains of an American teacher were
discovered in Panama on Friday, and his daughter blamed Panamanians
for his death.
   The American _ the third U.S. civilian to die since the conflict
began _ was identified by his daughter as Raymond Dragseth, a
teacher at the Panama Canal College, a Defense Department facility.
   Dragseth was reported to be the uncle of Richard Paul, a Defense
Department dependent who was killed a week ago. An American who was
working in Panama as a school teacher, Candy Helin, was killed
shortly after the invasion began.
   The Pentagon has said previously that 23 servicemen have died
since the Dec. 20 U.S. military intervention in Panama.
   Carolyn Dragseth, appearing at a news conference from Panama
broadcast by CNN, blamed Panamanians for the abduction of her
father, saying ``They just took my father _ I don't know why.''
   ``They came here looking for Americans,'' she said. CNN said
Raymond Dragseth was abducted from the family's apartment several
hours after the American invasion began.
   ``They just took my father. I don't know why. There's no
apparent reason why my father should have died.'' CNN said that
Dragseth's wife told them she had tried to convince the Panamanians
who abducted her husband that he was European.
   When asked whether her family had been contacted by the U.S.
Embassy, Carolyn Dragseth said, ``They've been keeping in touch
with us, especially since we, my family, located the body.''
   The Pentagon said the remains of ``an individual'' have been
recovered and once autopsy and identification efforts are complete
additional details will be provided.
   At the State Department, an official said U.S. authorities were
informed that Panamanian officials are in the process of exhuming a
person whose description would fit that of a private American
citizen. The official had no additional information.
</TEXT>

</DOC>