<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0131 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1821EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NYCPolice     12-18 0493</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-NYC Police,0505</SECOND>
<HEAD>Brown of Houston Named Police Commissioner</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto HT1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN SHANAHAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lee Brown, credited with easing racial tensions
as Houston police chief, was named Monday as police commissioner
for New York City, where he faces a drug-fueled crime wave.
   ``We need the best police commissioner we could find. Of all the
finalists, he seemed to be the absolute best in the country,''
Mayor-elect David Dinkins said at a news conference to announce his
choice to run America's biggest police force.
   Brown, chief in Houston since 1982 and one of four finalists for
the New York job, takes over Jan. 22. He will head a department
with 26,000 officers and 7,200 civilian employees, seven times
larger than Houston's.
   ``I made a difficult decision, something I didn't feel I would
be making when I was first talked to,'' Brown, 52, said at a news
conference Monday in Houston. ``I talked about it and pondered,
agonized and prayed.''
   Brown was Houston's first black police chief, and has been
credited for easing racial friction there. But Houston's force
recently has been hit with allegations of racism and corruption, as
well as controversy over shootings by officers.
   As New York's 36th police commissioner, Brown will face a city
convulsed with drug-related crime. The murder rate is at a record
level, and crack cocaine has been the main cause.
   ``The thing that will hit him immediately is the drug-crime
problem,'' said Thomas Reppetto, head of the independent watchdog
Citizens Crime Commission and a member of the search committee that
interviewed Brown.
   Brown has said that each city's crime solutions are different,
but he is a champion of community policing, with close cooperation
between police and neighborhoods, Reppetto said.
   Before taking the Houston job, Brown was chief of public safety
and chief of public safety for metropolitan Portland, Ore. He holds
a doctorate in criminology from the University of California at
Berkeley and is first vice president of the International
Association of Chiefs of Police.
   Brown will become president of the association next year, said
Reppetto. ``That's like an open door to the White House'' as an
expert on police affairs, Reppetto said.
   Brown began his career as a policeman in San Jose, Calif., in
1960. He established Portland State University's criminal justice
program eight years later and in 1972 joined Howard University,
where he was associate director of the Institute for Urban Affairs
and Research and director of the Criminal Justice Program. He went
to Portland in 1975.
   Brown succeeds Commissioner Richard Condon, who took over Oct.
22 when longtime Commissioner Benjamin Ward retired. Ward was New
York's first black police commissioner.
   Condon was one of the four finalists, and both Gov. Mario Cuomo
and outgoing Mayor Edward I. Koch had urged Dinkins to keep Condon
on. But Dinkins, who takes office Jan. 1, said he was swayed by the
strong support Brown received from law enforcement experts.
</TEXT>

</DOC>