<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0105 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1818EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Philippines     12-28 0417</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines,0432</SECOND>
<HEAD>Enrile Recommended For Prosecution in Coup</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By OLIVER TEVES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Government investigators recommended
Thursday that opposition Sen. Juan Ponce Enrile be prosecuted for
alleged involvement in the latest attempt to overthrow President
Corazon Aquino, an official said.
   Enrile, a former Aquino supporter, denied involvement in the
coup attempt, saying the accusations wer meant to harass the
opposition. He said he welcomed the opportunity to face his
accusers in court.
   Fernando de Leon, the chief state prosecutor, said the National
Bureau of Investigation recommended prosecution after witnesses
claimed to have seen Enrile with mutiny leaders Dec. 1, when
thousands of troops launched the sixth and strongest attempt to
topple Mrs. Aquino.
   De Leon said government prosecutors would review the
recommendation to decide whether charges would be filed.
   Enrile joined with Mrs. Aquino in the military-civilian uprising
that swept her to power in February 1986. He was named as defense
minister but fired from the post that November after a failed coup
by his followers.
   De Leon said those reportedly seen with Enrile at his home
included former Lt. Col. Gregorio ``Gringo'' Honasan, believed to
have been a key leader in the failed coup attempt.
   De Leon said the witnesses were hotel waiters catering a meal at
Enrile's Makati residence.
   Enrile denied that there were soldiers at his residence. He said
he had ``not more than 20'' bodyguards, all in civilian dress.
   He said there also were some guests attending a Mass customarily
held at his house on the first Friday of every month.
   ``I know that I have not done anything that is criminal under
our laws,'' Enrile said. ``I am not part of the rebellion. I have
not seen any of the participants in this military rebellion.''
   He called the accusations a ``machination'' of the presidential
palace.
   ``They want to seal the lips of the opposition in the country
and to threaten them, but I will tell them now ... that they cannot
silence me,'' Enrile said. ``This government is like a wounded
tiger flailing its paws.''
   In all, 113 people were killed and more than 500 wounded in the
Dec. 1-9 coup attempt.
   Many of the coup leaders, including Honasan, are at large.
   Government institutions bought stocks Thursday to ease
panic-selling on the Manila Stock Exchange. Dealers blamed a
statement Wednesday by Maj. Gen. Ramon Montano, chief of the
Philippine Constabulary, that intelligence reports indicated a coup
attempt may be launched between Jan. 17 and Jan. 30.
</TEXT>

</DOC>