<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0136 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0509EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DigestBriefs     12-26 0795</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Digest Briefs,0827</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United States is extending diplomatic
recognition to Romania's provisional government but expressing
regret that the trial of executed dictator Nicolae Ceausescu and
his wife Elena was conducted in secret.
   U.S. officials also are discussing how best to send emergency
aid to Romania, which has been devastated by bitter street battles
between the army and security forces loyal to Ceausescu.
   A hot line is being set up today at the State Department to
handle the many calls from Americans and Romanians wanting to
donate food and medicine.
   ``The U.S. government today established diplomatic relations
with the new legitimate government of Romania, the National
Salvation Front,'' said a statement issued by the White House on
Monday. The National Salvation Front is the name adopted by the
reform-minded leadership which assumed control of Romania after
Ceausescu was deposed last week.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Millions of Christians jammed churches in
Eastern Europe to celebrate their first Christmas in freedom after
four decades of Communist rule, but their thoughts also went to the
brave Romanian people.
   In Prague, Leipzig, East Berlin and even in battle-ravaged
Bucharest, the spirit of defiance that had guided Eastern Europeans
to their remarkable revolutions turned into hope for a brighter
future.
   The change was striking in Berlin as people from both sides of
the technically still divided city mingled freely, attending joint
church services for the first time since the Berlin Wall was built
28 years ago.
   East Germany on Sunday began allowing visa-free travel by West
Germans and thousands used the opportunity to cross to East Berlin
to join relatives for a Christmas service.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Taxpayers receive their annual holiday
greetings from Uncle Sam starting today, as the Internal Revenue
Service mails out more than 107 million tax forms and instruction
packages.
   The forms, which have been waiting at post offices across the
nation for weeks, should be in most taxpayers' hands before Jan. 1.
   The IRS always times the mailing, which costs $26 million for
postage and printing, to come right after the crush of Christmas
mail but soon enough to give taxpayers as much time as possible to
complete their returns before the filing deadline, which falls this
year on April 16.
   For taxpayers still reeling from the sweeping changes wrought by
the 1986 Tax Reform Act, the IRS has reassuring words: the new
forms look very much like last year's forms.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PORT CRANE, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Billy Martin, the hard drinking,
hard-nosed former Yankee manager whose on- and off-field brawls
overshadowed his accomplishments on the baseball diamond, died in
an alcohol-related traffic accident.
   He was 61.
   Martin was a passenger in a pickup truck that skidded off an icy
road in front of his farm Christmas night. The driver, longtime
friend William Reedy, 53, of Detroit, was charged with driving
while intoxicated, Broome County Sheriff Anthony Ruffo said.
   ``It's like losing part of my own family,'' said New York
Yankees' principal owner George Steinbrenner, who hired and fired
Martin five times as manager. ``He was one of a kind.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>JOHNSON CITY, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Owners of a high-rise retirement home
where a Christmas Eve fire killed 16 people had planned to install
a sprinkler system in the spring, the manager says.
   ``We didn't feel uncomfortable with the safety of the building.
We just had seen fires, basically on TV and other places. The
comment was made that the sprinkler system would have been a
benefit,'' Grant Trivett of M&amp;M Properties, which manages the John
Sevier Retirement Center, said Monday night.
   Trivett says the John Sevier Partnership, which owns the
11-story building, was going to have sprinklers put in at a cost of
$100,000.
   The 5-decade-old building did have water hoses on each floor and
met the fire code in effect in 1977, when it was converted from a
hotel into apartments for retirees, according to Lt. George
Leonard, fire marshal for this eastern Tennessee city of 40,000.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Most states have some sort of law restricting liquor sales on
Sundays. So when New Year's Eve falls on a Sunday, as it does this
year, it's a less-than-festive holiday for those who make a living
selling alcohol.
   ``I think it will hurt the industry,'' said Ray Brezzo, who owns
a liquor store in Glastonbury, Conn. ``We're very, very
pessimistic.''
   In Connecticut, as in many Northeastern states, bars and
restaurants can serve alcohol on Sundays but liquor stores can't
sell it. For New Year's Eve, Brezzo is hoping his customers will
buy what they need on Saturday _ but he's far from confident.
   ``Nobody knows what to expect,'' he said. ``Everybody's sort of
sitting on the edge of their seat.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>