<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0230 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0823EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-StrideRite     12-21 0401</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Stride Rite,0415</SECOND>
<HEAD>Connecticut Company to Seek Stride Rite</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAMBRIDGE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Connecticut investment company has
offered to buy the Stride Rite Corp. shoe manufacturer for about
$900 million.
   Stride Rite officials declined comment on the unsolicited
$32-a-share offer.
   Walsh, Greenwood &amp; Co. of Greenwich, and FS Champ Associates,
representing the Minda Bronfman de Gunzburg family trusts as a
limited partner, made the offer Wednesday, asked for nonpublic
information and for a reply by Dec. 28.
   In its offer, Walsh, Greenwood, which has owned 4.9 percent of
Stride Rite since last February, said it would consider options
after Dec. 28 and might go directly to stockholders with the same
or a modified offer.
   The offer was made as some analysts lowered their estimates of
Stride Rite earnings, partly because of the volume of shoes the
company sells to Campeau Corp., which owns department store chains
and which may file for Chapter 11 federal bankruptcy protection.
   On the New York Stock Exchange Wednesday, Stride Rite stock
closed at $23.50, down $3.75, on heavy trading of 1.3 million
shares.
   The Walsh, Greenwood offer was disclosed just before the market
closed, and the drop in price reportedly reflected earlier news
that industry analyst Barry Rothberg of Mabon Nugent recommended
selling Stride Rite stock.
   Stride Rite reported earnings of $34.7 million, or $1.27 a
share, for the fiscal year ended Nov. 30, 1988.
   John J. Phelan, treasurer and chief financial officer of Stride
Rite, predicted Wednesday that the company's earnings for the 1989
fiscal year will be at the lower end of estimates, from $1.70 to
$1.80 per share, and for the 1990 fiscal year from $2 to $2.20 per
share.
   Phelan said the company has lowered its predicted growth in the
sales of Keds from 30 percent to 10 percent for the 1990 fiscal
year. Keds sales rose 40 percent during the 1989 fiscal year.
   In its purchase offer, Walsh, Greenwood said, ``We have no plans
to change the manner of the company's operation or the location of
its headquarters and principal facilities.''
   In a telephone interview, Paul R. Greenwood, managing partner of
Walsh, Greenwood, told The Boston Globe it was too early to tell
whether he would install his own management team if his company
takes over Stride Rite.
   ``We like the company a lot,'' he said. ``We just think it can
be a lot more than what it is.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>