<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0434EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WoodBridges     12-26 0676</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Wood Bridges,0694</SECOND>
<HEAD>A Bridge-Building Material Comes to the Fore _ Wood</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOEL STASHENKO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW SCOTLAND, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   With thousands of its bridges in need
of repairs, New York is turning to a building material that's
strong and durable, relatively cheap, easy to work with and
pleasant to look at.
   It's wood.
   Far from being a way to cut corners, engineers say wood is in
many respects better than the traditional steel and concrete in the
kind of short, lightly traveled, rural bridges most in need of
repair.
   ``Using wood is really our best shot at building the
longest-lasting bridge with minimal maintenance,'' said Stan
Bishop, a road engineer for Cattaraugus County, in western New
York. Nearly a fifth of the 270 bridges maintained by the county
have some wood.
   The issue is significant in New York, because the state is faced
with billions of dollars in repair costs for 7,650 state- and
locally-owned spans that aren't up to standards.
   The deficiencies were discovered after a bridge on the New York
State Thruway collapsed in April 1987 in an accident that claimed
10 lives.
   If properly pressure-treated and preserved, wood is virtually
impervious to the enemy that rots out conventional
steel-and-concrete bridges _ road salt _ said William Smith, a
professor of wood products engineering at the State University of
New York in Syracuse.
   ``There's no reason wood shouldn't last 50 or 100 years or more
from a strength and durability standpoint,'' Smith said.
   Steel and concrete bridges, on the other hand, can show serious
deterioration after just 10 or 12 years on roads that are heavily
salted in the winter, Bishop said.
   Proponents of wood point to covered bridges, some of which more
than a century old, as evidence of the longevity of wooden spans.
Some elm pilings examined when the London Bridge was dismantled and
shipped to the United States as a tourist attraction had been in
service for 400 years.
   The cost savings achieved by using wood can vary considerably,
according to the length of the span, design, location, and other
factors, said Thomas Quinn, a structural engineer with the New York
state Department of Transportation. Costs can drop 20 percent or
more when wood is used instead of concrete and steel for a bridge's
superstructure, Quinn said.
   Paul Cooney, an engineer for Albany County, said many road
workers prefer working with wood to concrete.
   ``Workers tend to have more of a familiarity with wood, they
feel more comfortable with it,'' Cooney said. ``Instead of hiring
expert welders and elaborate equipment you don't have in normal
inventory, with the wood you have workers drilling holes, attaching
bolts and using tools and equipment they're used to.''
   Despite the potential cost savings, timber is seldom used in
bridges around the country, said Clellon Lovall, chief engineer in
Tennessee's transportation department and chairman of the
subcommittee on bridges and structures for the American Association
of State Highway and Transportation Officials.
   Wood has probably become attractive to New York highway
officials, he said, because it sometimes costs two or three times
more to build a bridge in New York than in other states due to high
labor, contracting and material expenses.
   ``It is limited in strength and connection capabilities,'' said
T.Y. Lin, founder and honorary board chairman of the T.Y. Lin
International engineering firm in San Francisco. ``However, there
are certainly places where it can be profitably or economically
used.''
   Generally, timber bridge experts say wood should be used only in
spans shorter than 50 feet.
   There are other potential drawbacks: beams can split, especially
under high pressure, and once that happens they must be replaced.
Wood can shrink and swell in varying moisture and temperature
conditions, possibly causing weaknesses in footings.
   In New York, wood is most often used in construction of the
superstructure _ that portion of the bridge placed atop pilings to
support the deck _ or to build the deck itself. In
steel-and-concrete spans, both parts are highly susceptible to
corrosion due to road salt and rust.
</TEXT>

</DOC>