<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0161 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1538EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Panama-Witness     12-20 0490</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Witness,0505</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Helicopters Gave Warning, Then Sent Residents Scurrying</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: ``plenty people'' cq in 10th graf</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EVE EPSTEIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Rolando Diaz learned of the battle to oust Manuel Noriega when
he heard the buzz of U.S. helicopters over his neighborhood, which
then broadcast warnings to soldiers at a nearby military
headquarters to leave the building.
   ``They were shouting down over the PA system. ... They said they
had no problem with them, they just wanted Noriega,'' he said in a
telephone interview from Panama, through an interpreter.
   Then the shooting began in Panama City. Fires triggered by the
battle leveled turn-of-the century wooden homes in a three-block
area. Diaz, who escaped with 11 members of his extended family,
said he counted six bodies of those loyal to Noriega lying dead in
the streets as he and others fled the immediate area.
   Many ended up at the nearby Salvation Army office.
   ``They were carrying TVs and their belongings on their heads,''
Marjorie Wiltshire, whose husband heads the office, said in a
telephone interview.
   The Salvation Army offered refugees from the fighting cookies
and punch _ the only food available _ then began cooking lentils
and rice for a midday meal. ``That's all we have. We can't get out
to get to a store,'' Mrs. Wiltshire said.
   Diaz and his family were escorted by U.S. soldiers to a church,
where they took shelter for about five hours until the church was
hit by an incendiary device.
   ``The church also burned down,'' said Diaz, 32.
   Diaz, a clerk in the ministry of education, sought shelter along
with about 100 other people at the Salvation Army office near the
entrance to the Panama Canal. He escaped with a few extra pants and
shirts. Everything else was destroyed.
   ``They burned everything down,'' Manuel Backalt, another
civilian who fled from the area of Noriega's headquarters with his
wife and three children, said in English. ``I see plenty people
dead in the street.''
   The fires in the houses resulted from the intense fighting; they
were not targets, eyewitnesses said.
   Backalt said the bodies _ he did not know how many _ were mainly
members of the Dignity Battalion, a paramilitary group loyal to
Noriega.
   Backalt, a self-employed stove repairman, said he was sleeping
when he heard gunfire. He said his house caught fire, and he and
his family went out into the street. None of his family was injured.
   As they walked the streets, he said, they saw a helicopter
crash. He said he didn't know if it was American or a Panamanian
helicopter.
   Although he lost his home, Diaz said he was glad the U.S.
decided to attack. ``This is the best thing that could have
happened,'' he said.
   Because Noriega's headquarters was located in a slum section of
the city, most of those left homeless are poor, said Maj. Allan
Wiltshire, who runs the Salvation Army office.
</TEXT>

</DOC>