<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0185 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 2310EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-PanamaAssembly 2ndLd-Writethru   12-21 1094</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama Assembly, 2nd Ld-Writethru,a0817,1,010</SECOND>
<HEAD>Leaders Meet Assembly</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS graf 10: ``At the,'' and graf 12: ``The two,'' to CORRECT
Tuesday to Wednesday.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   EDITOR'S NOTE: Steven Komarow is a member of the Pentagon press
pool covering military operations in Panama.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By STEVEN KOMAROW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Panama's newly installed leaders met
with members of the last legislative assembly and other public
figures under heavy U.S. guard Thursday, trying to gain control of
the country and declaring a dusk-to-dawn curfew.
   Gunshots echoed in the streets outside as President Guillermo
Endara and Vice Presidents Ricardo Arias Calderon and Guillermo
Ford presided over the meeting, which contained the incongruous
spectacle of U.S. soldiers in jeans, sweatshirts and other civilian
clothes sprinkled throughout it.
   In his speech to an audience of about 200, Endara held out an
olive branch to followers of deposed dictator Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noriega.
   Endara, his vice presidents and members of the audience sang
with special feeling their national anthem and one line in it, ``We
have finally achieved our victory.''
   Endara ordered a 6 p.m. to 6 a.m. curfew in hopes of maintaining
law and order as thousands of looters roamed the streets smashing
in windows and hauling away goods from virtually every shop in the
city.
   U.S. troops were too busy with snipers and small bands of armed
Noriega loyalists to challenge the looters.
   The new government, by the accounts of most foreign observers,
overwhelmingly won an election on May 7, but Noriega cancelled it
and continued his rule.
   At the time, Endara and Ford were beaten by members of one of
Noriega's ``Dignity Battalions,'' units who are still wrecking
havoc in the aftermath of the U.S. military takeover that started
early Wednesday morning.
   Two close aides to Endara, jailed by Noriega over a month ago
and feared by opposition members to have been tortured or killed,
appeared suddenly at the podium at the start of the session and
were embraced by Endara and his two vice presidents to a warm
ovation.
   The two men, Miguel Batista and Ivan Mojica, were spirited away
by Noriega's police and had not been heard from since. They were
freed from a jail by U.S. troops on Wednesday.
   Several people attending the session said they were grateful for
the U.S. intervention.
   ``The United States is responsible for delivering the dream we
have had since 1968,'' said cattleman Felix Espansona, an assembly
member in 1952-1956.
   ``We have had a dictatorship for 20 years and now we feel
liberated.''
   Endara called the new leadership ``The National Reconstruction
Government.'' In a brief speech he made no threats of retaliation
against followers of Noriega, now the subject of a nationwide
manhunt by the U.S. military and with a $1 million reward offered
by the White House for his capture.
   In a bid for unity, Endara said he would welcome back members of
Noriega's defense forces ``who can show they support our
democracy.''
   Vice President Ford said it will take some time to restore
order, but U.S. troops should leave ``the sooner the better'' .
   He also said, ``It is highly important for our country that
General Noriega be caught and be brought to justice.''
   A top U.S. military official agreed that Noriega's capture is
critical in restoring law and order.
   ``It's a problem because as long as you have the head of the
snake and you have parts of the snake's body, and he can make the
tapes like he did yesterday'' then you'll `have some number of
hard-core loyalists,'' said Lt. Col. Bill Bennett, chief of
contingency operations plans in U.S. Southern Command.
   The Endara government, strongly backed by President Bush, met
amid tight security provided by dozens of U.S. troops who were all
dressed in civilian clothes.
   Panamanian politicians did not want to give the impression of
total dependence on U.S. supports, so the soldiers were asked not
to wear their uniforms, several of them told reporters.
   Looking out of place with their crewcuts and bluejeans, they sat
in the audience to prevent trouble in the National Assembly
building.
   While the speeches were being delivered inside the government
building, shots rang out across the street, scattering scores of
looters and curiosity seekers from outside the wrought-iron gates
around the Assembly.
   A U.S. officer in charge of security dismissed it as a minor
incident. ``Only some shopkeeper firing shots into the air to scare
away a looter,'' the officer told a reporter.
   Government officials said all public offices and buildings would
be closed for the next two days _ virtually everything in Panama
has been closed
   since the U.S. attack _ and it was unclear when they might
reopen.
   The major exception was the Panama Canal, which resumed full
operations at dawn Thursday, military officials said. Dozens of
cargo ships were offshore awaiting a chance to go through the canal.
   The opposition to the American military takeover in the capital
city was mostly disorganized, said Bennett, but some Noriega
military units remained in the countryside and would have to be
dealt with.
   With the operation more than 30 hours old, the U.S. completed
taking control of the national assembly building, demolished
Noriega's former headquarters and took control of other key points
in the city.
   Late Wednesday, soldiers from the 82nd Airborne Division swept
through the downtown Marriott hotel where some Americans were
trapped.
   Bennett estimated that some 3,000 of the 24,000 U.S. troops
involved in the operations were military police, who would be
taking over police duties formerly carried out by Noriega's forces.
   ``Their mission will be to re-establish law and order in Panama
City,'' he said.
   One of the primary duties will be to identify and hand over
duties to Panamanian police officers who ``will be loyal to a
democratic government,'' he said.
   As the police units take over downtown, attack units would turn
their attention to routing out the remaining Noriega loyalists
elsewhere _ a job which would be made easier if Noriega is found
and captured.
   ``Without Noriega as a rallying point, a lot of the units out
there that have been sitting on the fence will be calling to tell
us that they will support the democratic government,'' he said.
   U.S. officers reported that there was a mortar fired overnight
near Fort Clayton, a major U.S. military installation, but had no
details of any damage.
   They also reported that a special unit seized a 65-foot
Panamanian boat near the Bridge of the Americas spanning the Panama
Canal. They captured 18 armed men aboard but found no explosives.
</TEXT>

</DOC>