<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0654EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Legislators'Trials     12-21 0391</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Legislators' Trials,0403</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jury Convicts Alabama Legislator of Bribery, Acquits Two Others</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HOYT HARWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BIRMINGHAM, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal jury convicted an Alabama
state legislator of taking money to influence legislation, but
acquitted two others of accepting bribes from a union official.
   After almost three days of deliberations, jurors on Wednesday
found Rep. Pat Davis guilty of four counts and innocent of four
others. Reps. John Rogers and Jim Wright were found innocent on two
counts each. All three are Democrats.
   Mrs. Davis refused to comment after the verdict, and friends
rushed her away from the federal courthouse.
   But Rogers was jubilant after the verdict. ``Yes, there is a
Santa Claus. It's the best Christmas present in my life,'' he said.
   The lawmaker said he would return immediately to work in the
Legislature, which is meeting in special session.
   Wright declined to comment after being acquitted.
   So far this year, six Jefferson County legislators have been
indicted, but five have been acquitted. A jury at Montgomery
several weeks ago acquitted three other legislators of extortion
charges in connection with an attempt to establish a dog track.
   U.S. District Judge James Hancock set sentencing for Mrs. Davis
on Jan. 25. The maximum possible penalty is 20 years and $250,000
on each of the four counts.
   The jury convicted her of taking $12,000 from a union official,
$1,200 for her hotel expenses during legislative sessions in
Montgomery, $1,000 in ``appreciation'' money, and $5,000 to
reintroduce a failed coal bill.
   Mrs. Davis, as were Rogers and Wright, was acquitted of a
conspiracy count, and she was cleared of charges she took $400 to
pay for a barbecue, $500 as a Christmas gift and $500 in
fund-raising money.
   Rogers and Wright also were acquitted of charges they accepted
$5,000 payments.
   The government contended the three lawmakers accepted about
$30,000 for their support of a bill that would have required
Alabama utilities and state agencies to buy coal mined within the
state.
   A United Mine Workers Union official, John W. Stewart, testified
that Mrs. Davis solicited a bribe from him. Stewart became an FBI
informant and, he said, set up various meetings with the lawmakers,
paying them with money provided by the FBI in its sting operation.
   Defense attorneys said the defendants accepted the cash only as
legal campaign contributions.
</TEXT>

</DOC>