<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1241EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Cambodia     12-25 0499</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cambodia,0513</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cambodians Pray on Christmas, 11 Years After Invasion</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-World Christmas, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER ENG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SITE B, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 200 Cambodians prayed for peace on
Christmas Day in their refugee camp in Thailand, exactly 11 years
after Vietnam invaded their homeland and sparked the civil war that
forced them to flee.
   ``I pray to God that I can go back to my country,'' said Sau
Rany, 22, a religion teacher who wants to be a nun.
   Inside a church of bamboo and palm leaves, she and other
refugees paid respect at an altar with a traditional Cambodian
greeting: hands folded before their faces. Besides the altar
drooped a Christmas tree with a cellophane star and plastic
flowers. No Mass was offered since there are no priests among the
refugees, and the foreign priests were away.
   Sau Rany's father and her brother were killed by the Khmer
Rouge, and she fled to the U.N.-aided guerrilla camp in 1984
because of food shortages and other hardships. She said God allows
her suffering ``probably to test my endurance.''
   Vietnamese divisions invaded Cambodia on Dec. 25, 1978, ending
nearly four years of Khmer Rouge rule and installing another
communist government. The U.N. border camps hold more than 300,000
refugees from the conflict.
   The war between the Phnom Penh government and a three-party
guerrilla coalition dominated by the Khmer Rouge has intensified
since Vietnam's troop pullout in late September.
   Almost all those at the church were women and their children.
``Usually we have more men here but today they are carrying weapons
and food at the border,'' Sau Rany explained.
   One soldier, Bith Phonn, 42, made it to church after taking
leave to look after his wife, eight months pregnant with their
ninth child.
   Bith Phonn displayed the scars from bullet wounds in both thighs
and the back of his head. He said he has killed about 10 enemy
soldiers in six years of fighting.
   ``I know it is a sin, but if I don't kill him, he will kill
me,'' he said.
   Relief officials and diplomats say that Prince Norodom
Sihanouk's group, which controls Site B, has stepped up
conscription because the United States and other countries are
supplying aid to the guerrilla armies depending on their size.
   The U.N. Border Relief Operation and the International
commuittee of the Red Cross have told Sihanouk officials they
oppose what appear to be efforts to conscript minors.
   One aid officials, speaking on condition of anonymity, said a
large group of students, some as young as 14, were taken out of the
camp in August and earlier this month for military help.
   The deputy Sihanouk administrator at Site B, Kun Kim Teng,
claimed Sunday that all those involved were 18 or older. He said
the students went for political, not military, training in August,
and those who left this month were carrying food to civilians in
newly liberated areas near the Thai border.
   All were volunteers, he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>