<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0195 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0101EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Westmark-Inman     12-27 0410</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Westmark-Inman,0426</SECOND>
<HEAD>Inman Resigns as Westmark Head</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AUSTIN, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bobby Ray Inman, a former intelligence
chief, has resigned as head of Westmark Systems Inc., a defense
electronics contractor striving to pay for its $867 million buyout
of Tracor Holdings Inc.
   Westmark, whose sole holding is Tracor, said Inman ``initiated
the action after concluding that a transition in management would
facilitate the long-term financial and organizational decisions
which will be made at Westmark and Tracor.''
   Inman, who submitted his resignation Friday, said Tuesday he
made the decision nine days ago and ``the offers have begun to
flow.''
   He said his future probably would involve technology
investments, and that he will make a decision within six weeks.
   Earlier, Inman told Business Week magazine he planned to write a
book about leveraged buyouts, the practice of using cash flow or
asset sales to pay off money borrowed to buy a company.
   Inman has held the positions of chairman, president and chief
executive officer at both Tracor and Westmark since 1987.
   Austin-based Westmark announced that Elvis Mason, managing
partner of Mason Best Co., was elected chairman and chief executive
of Westmark on an interim basis.
   Mason Best is a Dallas-based merchant bank that founded Westmark
and is its largest shareholder. Mason served as chairman and chief
executive officer of Westmark during its formation and as a
director until two years ago.
   William Moyer has been named acting president and chief
executive officer of Tracor Holdings.
   Westmark was created in 1986 to purchase electronics companies,
and bought Tracor the following year.
   But the Tracor purchase was funded with high-yield bonds,
loading the company with high-cost debt. Declining margins have
further squeezed the company, which announced this month it was
seeking to sell off assets to pay down the debt. Westmark has a $16
million interest payment on the junk bonds due Feb. 1.
   Tracor, based in Austin, produces advanced defense electronics
systems. It also modifies commercial and government aircraft and
makes analytical instruments and electrical components.
   Inman joined Westmark in 1986. Prior to that, he was the first
director of Microelectronics and Computer Technology Corp. in
Austin. MCC was the first government-approved consortium to help
the U.S. computer industry regain competitive advantages.
   Inman spent 30 years in the Navy, and rose to the rank of
admiral. He became director of naval intelligence in 1974, deputy
director of the Defense Intelligence Agency in 1976 and head of the
National Security Agency in 1977.
</TEXT>

</DOC>