<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1117EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Israel 2ndLd-Writethru a0493-a0490 12-29 0609</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Israel, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0493-a0490,0623</SECOND>
<HEAD>Peace Activists Believe Israel Intends to Thwart Rally Plans</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 9 grafs to UPDATE with women's peace march, clash
with police, arrests; picks up 5th pvs, `Organizers of...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EILEEN ALT POWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A peace march by about 3,000 European, Israeli
and Palestinian women ended today in a violent confrontation with
police after an outlawed Palestinian flag was raised in protest.
   Police said 16 women were detained, most of them Palestinians.
Police sprayed the area with tear gas, and reporters saw women
kicked, struck with nightsticks and dragged to police wagons.
   One women shouted ``Peace! Peace! Peace!'' as police dragged her
by her hair.
   Among those detained was Dacia Valent, an Italian citizen who is
a member of the European Parliament. She was taken into custody
after protesting the arrests to police.
   The women's peace march, which wound through city streets from
Jewish west Jerusalem to Arab east Jerusalem, was one of several
major events planned to precede Saturday's ``human chain'' around
the old, walled city.
   Police moved in to disperse the demonstrators after a
Palestinian flag was raised in the courtyard of a theater in east
Jerusalem.
   It was unclear who raised the flag, but Palestinian women in the
courtyard immediately took up chanting ``Israel No, PLO!'' and
other anti-Israeli slogans.
   This morning, soldiers set up checkpoints on roads from the West
Bank, increasing rally organizers' fears that the army intended to
block Palestinians from joining with Israelis and the 1,200
Europeans in Saturday's ``human chain.''
   Authorities have denied visas, barred visits to Palestinian
refugee camps and blocked tour buses from traveling to West Bank
cities.
   Army spokesmen said the checkpoints were not intended to close
off the occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip, they have refused
comment on Israeli news reports they will do so Saturday.
   Organizers of the ``1990 _ Time for Peace'' rally say their goal
is to foster dialogue between Arabs and Jews.
   ``We have emphasized that we are here to support the peace
voices on both sides,'' said Chiara Ingrao, an organizer from the
Italian Peace Association.
   Israeli officials said, however, that they fear the activists'
visit could spark more violence in the 2-year-old Palestinian
uprising against Israel's occupation of the West Bank and Gaza
Strip.
   ``The army frowns on people trying to make political statements,
especially those who are not citizens of the country, in the
territories,'' said one army official, who insisted on anonymity.
   The activists' vision of peace is at odds with the Israeli
government's view on three points; the activists call for
negotiations with the PLO, an international Middle East peace
conference and establishment of a Palestinian state alongside
Israel.
   Janet Aviad, a spokeswoman for the Israeli group Peace Now, a
sponsor of the rally, said the government is ``afraid of European
pressure and American pressure, and this event covered by the press
has potential for international pressure.''
   The Europeans include about 900 from Italy and smaller
delegations from Great Britain, West Germany, the Netherlands and
Switzerland, as well as some Palestinian-Americans. Other sponsors
include groups from Italy, Holland and Britain, and local
Palestinian activists.
   Late Wednesday night, police searched the corridors of the
Europeans' headquarters hotel. Police spokesman Avi Zelba said the
searches ``in principle were not related to their visit'' but were
aimed at apprehending a wanted Palestinian.
   Israel radio reported Thursday that Moslem fundamentalists from
the Islamic Jihad group issued threats in Sweden and Italy for
people not to participate in a rally that encouraged Jewish-Arab
cooperation.
   However, rally organizers issued a statement saying they
consider the threats ``untrustworthy and unfounded.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>