<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0142EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-FarmScene     12-26 0700</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Farm Scene,660</SECOND>
<HEAD>China Faces Growing Demand for Imported Wheat</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   China is the world's largest wheat producer
but is not keeping pace with its own consumer demand for more
bread, noodles and dumplings.
   As a result, China has been buying huge amounts of wheat from
other countries, including the United States. An Agriculture
Department analyst says import demand will continue to grow, at
least through the turn of the century.
   ``Even though it is the world's largest producer of wheat,
China's domestic demand exceeds supplies,'' says Frederick W. Crook
of the department's Economic Research Service. ``Wheat output has
risen steadily as farmers have boosted yields because of greater
irrigation and use of improved varieties.''
   Crook, in a report on China's wheat economy, said population
growth and ``consumer preference for wheat products'' such as
noodles, steamed dumplings, bread and pastries have spurred demand.
   As the world's most populous country with 1.1 billion people,
even slight changes in per capita use can translate into large
numbers.
   Crook said per capita wheat consumption rose steadily from 29
kilograms in 1960 to 48 kilos in 1978. Then, as supplies increased
because of import and production gains, the average jumped to 90
kilograms per person in 1987.
   A kilogram is about 2.2 pounds. Ninety kilos would be about 198
pounds, or approximately 3.3 bushels of wheat, allowing 60 pounds
per bushel.
   China has been at peaks and valleys as a customer of U.S. wheat
farmers since the early 1970s. Lately, Beijing has been a large and
consistent buyer of U.S. wheat, rivaling the Soviet Union at times.
   In the 1988-89 wheat marketing year that ran through last May
31, China imported almost 8.1 million metric tons of U.S. wheat and
became the largest foreign customer of American growers. The Soviet
Union, by comparison, imported 4.96 million tons in the same period.
   So far in 1989-90, China has bought about 4.7 million tons
against the Soviet Union's purchases as of Dec. 14 of less than 2
million tons.
   A metric ton, the unit favored in world grain trade, is about
2,205 pounds and is equal to 36.7 bushels of wheat. It also is
equal to 1,000 kilograms.
   Both China and the Soviet Union have bought large amounts of
wheat under a U.S. price subsidy arrangement, the Export
Enhancement Program. Under EEP, private exporters can sell to
designated foreign countries at reduced prices and then collect
USDA-owned commodities as ``bonuses'' or subsidies to make up the
price difference.
   From a production standpoint, China has been the world's largest
wheat producer in four of the last five years, according to USDA
statistics.
   China's wheat output this year, for example, is estimated at 91
million tons, compared with 89 million for the Soviet Union and
55.6 million for the United States.
   Other major producers this year include: Canada, 24.4 million
tons; Australia, 12.5 million; Argentina, 10.7 million; India, 53
million; Eastern Europe, 42.3 million; and the European Economic
Community, 79.3 million.
   Crook said that by world standards China has achieved ``fairly
high wheat yields'' and is surpassing those in India, Pakistan and
countries which have large areas of non-irrigated wheat, such as
Canada, Australia, the Soviet Union and the United States.
   On the other hand, Crook said wheat yields are higher in Mexico,
France, Poland and Japan.
   Crook said that Chinese experts predict wheat yields will climb
an average of about 1.65 percent a year and that by the year 2000
there will be some decrease in total wheat area. But they claim
that total output by then will increase to between 100 million and
105 million tons.
   ``China's population will continue to grow in the next decade,
and if per capita income continues to rise, demand for wheat will
also increase,'' Crook said. ``However, prospects for rapid gains
in domestic wheat output are dim because little arable (land) can
be shifted to wheat production, and yields are already high.''
   As a result, he added, the outlook for wheat exports to China
``looks promising in the near future.'' But the rate of growth will
depend mostly on the ability of the rest of China's economy to earn
foreign exchange.
</TEXT>

</DOC>