<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0091 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1035EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-PoliceProbe     12-20 0328</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Police Probe,0342</SECOND>
<HEAD>Important Records Missing in Detroit Police Fund Probe</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Investigators looking into what happened to $1
million paid out of a Police Department undercover operations fund
said important documents on a former deputy chief suspected of
stealing from the account have vanished.
   The missing documents detail Kenneth Weiner's involvement with
the fund, Executive Deputy Chief James Bannon said Tuesday.
   ``He's gone. The records are gone. ... He was last known to be
the custodian'' of most of the documents, Bannon said.
   Police Chief William Hart has said Weiner, a former civilian
deputy police chief, stole from the fund, which finances undercover
operations of the narcotics division.
   Weiner was in charge of sensitive security work for the police
from 1980 to 1986. He resigned in 1986 after an investigation into
a precious-metals investments deal in which several Detroit-area
investors lost several thousand dollars.
   Weiner has not been seen or heard from publicly since the
federal and city investigations began several weeks ago. The FBI
has refused to discuss the scope or any other details of its
investigation into the fund.
   The FBI and U.S. attorney's office are trying to determine
whether Weiner diverted hundreds of thousands of dollars from the
fund for personal use.
   Bannon said a substantial number of documents were gone,
including some subpoenaed under federal and city orders. He said a
theft report was filed.
   The City Council subpoenaed financial records from 1985 to 1987,
and city auditors began examining documents Tuesday.
   Release of the records averted a court battle between Mayor
Coleman Young and the council, which had issued a subpoena
demanding a chance to review the records.
   ``The mayor's concern all along was to protect the integrity of
the grand jury process and the integrity of the secret service
fund,'' said spokesman Bob Berg.
   Young, who initially said he never would give the documents to
city auditors and the council, refused to say why he changed his
mind.
</TEXT>

</DOC>