<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0245EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CovenantHouse Bjt   12-18 0750</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Covenant House, Bjt,0773</SECOND>
<HEAD>A Child-Welfare Charity's Nightmare</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY12</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BARBARA ROSEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Rev. Bruce Ritter has long been synonymous
with Covenant House, the Times Square shelter that grew into a
world-renowned refuge for street kids through the Franciscan's
vision, savvy and tenaciousness.
   Now, Ritter is faced with allegations that threaten not only his
reputation but also the very viability of the institution he
created.
   Last week, Ritter was forced to call a news conference to deny
reports that he had sex with a young man he had helped, and that he
improperly spent Covenant House funds on the man.
   ``It's every organization's nightmare,'' said E. Jeff Baron,
executive director of Emergency Shelter, which also helps runaway
youths. ``It basically strikes at the very heart of what you're
trying to accomplish.''
   Since 1968, when Ritter took some runaways into his Greenwich
Village apartment, he has fought bureaucracy, the limits of
government aid and competition from other charities to make
Covenant House grow.
   It is now an $85 million-a-year operation that manages 17
shelters with more than 2,000 beds in the United States, Toronto
and Latin America, and directly serves about 25,000 kids a year.
   Critics have said Covenant House is too big to be properly
supervised, and so good at raising money that it squeezes out
smaller sophisticated programs. But until last week, Ritter's
publicity had been almost all good.
   Presidents Reagan and Bush and their first ladies visited
Covenant House; Attorney General Edwin Meese III appointed Ritter
to his commission on pornography; Reagan called him ``an unsung
hero.''
   On Wednesday, the Manhattan district attorney confirmed he is
investigating charges of financial improprieties by Ritter, charges
made by a 20-year-old former male prostitute who also reportedly
claimed he had a sexual relationship with the 62-year-old priest.
   Cardinal John J. O'Connor said Sunday he has complete trust in
Ritter.
   ``In all of our dealings and in all of his work in this
archdiocese, he has demonstrated himself to be a soul of goodness
and of integrity,'' O'Connor said during Mass at St. Patrick's
Cathedral. ``Certainly I have been given no reason to believe that
that goodness or integrity has been violated.''
   Baron and others noted the vulnerability of a charitable
organization whose image is so closely identified with that of one
person such as Ritter, a master of public relations. Covenant House
depends on private sources for 95 percent of its funding.
   ``People don't always hear the `not guilty.' What they hear is
the accusation,'' said Baron, adding: ``If something happens to
Covenant House there's a major void in the system and there are
just not that many beds in the city.''
   More than 80 percent of Covenant House's funds come via a
sophisticated direct-mail operation from individual donors, the
rest from corporations and foundations. Ritter's signed, carefully
targeted letters to donors tell stories of ``my kids'' in familiar
tones and ask for financial help.
   Hours after the prosecutor's statement, supporters showed up at
a glitzy fund-raiser Wednesday night.
   ``You've got thousands of kids depending on Covenant House for a
roof, for a bed, for food, and we're not going to diminish our
efforts to help these kids, no matter what,'' said Jack Shea,
president of Spiegel Inc., which organized the event with artist
Peter Max.
   Patrick Kennedy, a Covenant House vice president, said donors
have voiced concern as well as support since the allegations
surfaced in the New York Post. He said the agency, whose weekly
costs average about $1.4 million, would be able to carry on even if
a cloud _ legal or perceived _ were to persist over Ritter's name.
   ``There might be a period when even more belt-tightening than
usual might go on, but I doubt very seriously that the agency
itself would be in any danger of folding, simply because it has
been functioning as long as it has,'' Kennedy said.
   Under an existing plan for Covenant House after Ritter, the
national board would choose a new chief executive officer from
among several Franciscans who will have ``understudied,'' Kennedy
said. The board itself would be responsible for running the agency.
   District Attorney Robert Morgenthau said the investigation was
in its ``earliest stages,'' and that Covenant House was cooperating.
   Ritter said Thursday he doesn't plan to resign or temporarily
step aside. ``I am so identified with Covenant House I think that
without me presently in this leadership role the work we do would
suffer very much,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>