<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0183 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1822EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-UN 1stLd-Writethru a0745 12-22 0538</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-UN, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0745,0555</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 12 grafs to UPDATE with U.S. condemnation considered,
new government's representative trying to claim mission; RESTORES first
reference to Noriega; pickup up graf 7 pvs `During discussion....' TRIMS
thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER JAMES SPIELMANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>UNITED NATIONS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Security Council began considering a
resolution Friday that would condemn the U.S. invasion of Panama
and demand the immediate withdrawal of American troops.
   Nearly all nations on the council have denounced the United
States for its military action in Panama. The United States,
possibly joined by Britain, was considered certain to veto a
resolution condemning the invasion.
   The council scheduled a vote for Saturday afternoon on the
resolution introduced by the group of nations that profess
non-alignment.
   Council members wrestled with another dilemma Friday after
inviting Panama to speak on the invasion but disagreeing over which
of the rival ambassadors should be given the floor.
   On Thursday night, the council voted 14-0, with the United
States abstaining, to hear Panama's views but did not decide who
was the legitimate ambassador. The council then met in private
Friday to continue arguing the issue.
   The United States attacked to oust Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega
as Panama's leader.
   His supporters have demanded that Mirla Bellavita, Noriega's
choice for ambassador, be allowed to speak for Panama. President
Guillermo Endara, installed during the U.S. assault, appointed
Eduardo Vallarino ambassador and asked that he speak for the
country.
   The council will confer a degree of legitimacy on the government
of whichever representative it allows to speak.
   Panama had no U.N. ambassador when the invasion occurred.
Leonardo Kam, who had held the position, was promoted to foreign
minister in September and no replacement had been accredited.
   Vallarino attempted a peaceful takeover of Panama's U.N. Mission
on Friday, but Mrs. Bellavita told him her group will continue to
be the sole occupants of the office just north of U.N. headquarters
in New York.
   Vallarino left after the polite discussion with Mrs. Bellavita,
but said he would pursue his claim.
   ``We intend to take possession of these offices; we will do it
in a very orderly process,'' he said. ``However, we will not do
anything rash or violent.''
   During discussion Thursday, U.S. Ambassador Thomas R. Pickering
said ``there is only one legal representative of Panama, and that
representative is here,'' meaning Vallarino.
   Soviet Ambassador Alexander M. Belonogov said: ``I have quite an
opposite opinion on who exactly should represent Panama on the
Security Council.
   ``We cannot be a party to any exercise which will add legality,
any legality in the United Nations at this moment, to the
government which has been ... installed by the United States in
Panama.''
   U.S. officials said privately they were hoping to stall the
issue until Endara's government was firmly in control of Panama.
   Endara is widely believed to have been the winner in
presidential elections May 7, but the balloting was rejected and
nullified by Noriega.
   Of the 15 Security Council members, only Britain has
wholeheartedly endorsed the U.S. action.
   Canada criticized the invasion but said Noriega provoked it;
France condemned both Noriega's dictatorship and the invasion.
   The other council members were highly critical of the U.S.
action.
</TEXT>

</DOC>