<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0320EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     12-30 0299</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0311</SECOND>
<HEAD>On the Light Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Had the Alamo been built according to Charles
Allen's blueprints, Davy Crockett and Jim Bowie would have fired on
Mexican troops from ramparts of peanut butter cookies.
   Allen is one of seven chefs and bakers who are fashioning
sculptures out of Girl Scout cookies to promote the organization's
annual cookie sale.
   ``This is more of an architect's job than it is an artist's,''
said Allen as he pasted Girl Scout cookies, and a pinch of
chocolate and applied an apricot glaze to the cardboard frame of
his 4-foot-tall model of the historic Texas fort.
   Allen said he had one big problem assembling his entry: hungry
co-workers.
   Other planned cookie sculptures include a model of the winged
mythological winged horse Pegasus.
   ``It's a new twist to selling cookies,'' Meg Cadigan, a
spokeswoman for the Texas Girl Scout Council, said Thursday.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>JEFFERSONVILLE, Ind. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Clark Superior Court Judge George A.
Jacobs is inviting children and adults to ``adopt'' their new
Christmas dolls at his court today.
   The sixth annual special session of Jacobs' court will present
adoption papers to owners of dolls, teddy bears or other stuffed
animals.
   Jacobs started the program in 1984. About 700 people, most of
them children toting new Cabbage Patch dolls, showed up at the
courtroom in southern Indiana. About 75 to 100 people have
participated in subsequent years.
   ``We started it just to give the kids a sense that the courts
are there to help them, not to hurt them,'' Jacobs said.
   Jacobs said he also hopes lessons taught at a young age will
carry over for the children.
   ``They say they will be loving parents and we hope that will
carry over when they do have children of their own,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>