<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 2105EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Yugoslavia 1stLd-Writethru a0688 12-17 0647</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Yugoslavia, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0688,0663</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government to Unveil Sweeping Reform Program</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: ADDS 3 grafs on Yugoslav paper publishing greetings from exiled
prince</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Czechoslovakia, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SLOBODAN LEKIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BELGRADE, Yugoslavia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Communist premier has warned
that his government will resign if Parliament rejects a package of
austerity measures he plans to submit Monday to contain
hyperinflation.
   The three-day parliamentary session has already been billed in
the media as ``D-day'' for Yugoslavia, with a sharp clash expected
between liberals and conservatives representing the country's
different regions.
   Premier Ante Markovic's government, which took over in March,
has moved fast to introduce market mechanisms as a way out of
Yugoslavia's worst-ever economic crisis, marked by a 2,000 percent
annual inflation rate, a $17 billion foreign debt and a 17 percent
unemployment rate.
   His reform program has been criticized by conservatives in
Yugoslavia's Communist leadership, especially in the republic of
Serbia, who oppose his market-oriented efforts and the promotion of
greater political pluralism.
   Several key government-sponsored reforms have been blocked by
the conservatives, and Markovic is expected to demand urgent
changes in Yugoslavia's constitution that would give more power to
the federal government to implement its program.
   The new austerity package has been kept under strict secrecy,
and speculation about the measures have caused a huge shopping
spree by Yugoslavs fearing their effect.
   ``Never before in (postwar) parliaments have there been so many
expectations and so much guesswork,'' about a session of
Parliament, the state-run Tanjug news agency said Sunday.
   Last week, the U.S. State Department said it was worried by
rising tensions in Yugoslavia and urged the people to unite in
support of Markovic's reform program.
   The tough reform measures are expected to include a substantial
devaluation of the national currency, the dinar, and tight monetary
and budgetary controls accompanied by stiff wage and price
discipline. But government spokesmen have denied rumors of a wage
and price freeze.
   The government has already announced that if the package is
passed, the country would receive ``substantial financial aid,''
including a loan of up to $1 billion from the International
Monetary Fund and some Western countries.
   In Serbia, the largest of the country's six member republics,
the opposition to Markovic's reforms is centered on claims that he
has done nothing to curb rampant inflation.
   Fearing popular discontent that could be sparked by the
austerity program and the economic reforms, Serbian authorities
have instead proposed short-term measures designed to bring down
inflation.
   In an apparent attempt to pressure the government, the state-run
trade unions of Serbia and its ally Montenegro have announced short
general warning strikes for next week to coincide with the
parliamentary session.
   Some delegates at the current Serbian Communist Party congress
have demanded that the Serbian parliamentary deputies not even vote
on Markovic's package, saying they should demand his immediate
resignation.
   Markovic has repeatedly stressed that if his program is not
approved in Parliament he will tender the Cabinet's resignation.
   A prolonged dispute between the leaderships of Yugoslavia's
constituent states over the country's political and economic future
came to a head in November, when Serbia broke off all business and
government ties with the northern region of Slovenia.
   Janez Drnovsek, head of Yugoslavia's collective state
presidency, was expected to address the parliamentary session with
a report on the deep splits that have developed between the
constituent regions and on measures to curb the crisis.
   In another development, a Christmas message from Crown Prince
Alexander, now a London resident, was published in the Sunday
edition of the Vjesnik daily newspaper in Zagreb.
   It was the first time such a thing has been done in the
country's 44-year Communist history.
   Alexander's father, the late Peter II, was Yugoslavia's last
king. The monarchy was abolished when the Communists came to power
after World War II and male members of the exiled royal family were
banned from returning.
</TEXT>

</DOC>