<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0000EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Romania-Aid     12-24 0501</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Aid,0514</SECOND>
<HEAD>Humanitarian Aid Arrives in Romania; France Offers to Help Fight</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Romania's provisional government thanked those nations who have
sent humanitarian aid to the besieged country and said it would
welcome more.
   The National Salvation Committee, which has set itself up as the
leadership in Romania, said Sunday night that medical assistance,
drugs and food already have arrived from France, the Soviet Union,
Bulgaria, Czechoslovakia and Hungary.
   But as offers of aid poured in, East bloc media said few
supplies were able to get through because of the heavy fighting
that continued in the streets.
   In terms of military aid, France's foreign minister offered
Sunday to help put together a ``brigade of volunteers'' to help
Romanians fight security forces loyal to ousted Communist dictator
Nicolae Ceausescu.
   Foreign Minister Roland Dumas said that if the Soviet Union
believed it necessary to intervene in Romania on the side of the
anti-Ceausescu forces, France ``not only would not object to it,
but would support this action.''
   U.S. Secretary of State James A. Baker III said the Bush
administration would not object if the Soviets or other Warsaw Pact
nations used their armed forces to assist the anti-Ceausescu forces.
   ``They are attempting to put off the yoke of a very, very
oppressive and repressive dictatorship, so I think that we would be
inclined probably to follow the lead, follow the example of France,
who today has said that if the Warsaw Pact felt it necessary to
intervene on behalf of the opposition that it would support that.''
   Asked directly whether the United States would not object to a
Warsaw Pact military intervention in Romania, where bloody street
fighting has followed the ouster of Ceausescu, Baker said on NBC's
``Meet The Press'': ``That would be my view, yes.''
   There was no indication of imminent military intervention by
Soviet forces. Soviet Premier Nikolai I. Ryzhkov said Saturday that
sending the Red Army to Romania would be ``impermissible'' and a
repetition of past mistakes.
   Romanian-born playwright Eugene Ionesco, who lives in France,
urged the West ``to provide military aid in arms and ammunition to
the regular Romanian army so it can defend the people against the
agents of the security police.''
   France has sent two planeloads of medical supplies and emergency
medical teams to Romania in a mission led by Bernard Kouchner,
minister for humanitarian action in the Socialist government.
   Romania's Agerpres news agency said the National Salvation
Committee thanked ``all governments that have offered humanitarian
assistance to Romania'' at a time when the people were fighting to
``liquidate the terrorist gangs of the deposed dictator.''
   It added that the provisional government ``welcomes with
gratitude any humanitarian help.''
   Cuba's Radio Reloj reported Sunday night that it had sent blood
plasma and food to Bucharest.
   ``Taking into account the high number of injured people and
victims that have been caused by the recent tragic events in
Romania, the Cuban government has sent humanitarian aid to that
country,'' the report said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>