<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0330EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Japan-Markets     12-25 0379</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Japan-Markets,0389</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar Lower, Stocks Bounce Back</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TETSUO JIMBO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dollar slipped against the Japanese yen today,
while share prices on the Tokyo Stock Exchange rebounded sharply
following the Bank of Japan's decision to raise its discount rate
by a half percentage point.
   The dollar closed at 142.72 yen, down 0.95 yen from Friday's
close of 143.67 yen. After opening at 142.72 yen, the currency
never moved higher, changing hands between 141.95-142.72 yen in
mixed trading.
   Currency dealers said the dollar's fall followed its weakness in
the New York market Friday, affected by factors such as the
weakening U.S. economy and expectations of further easing of U.S.
interest rates.
   ``There is a sense in the market that the yen is too weak
despite Japan's trade surplus,'' said a dealer at a major Japanese
bank, speaking on condition of anonymity.
   Another dealer with the Bank of Tokyo said there was little
movement on the exchange market in early trading, as many overseas
markets, including those in the United States, were to stay closed
Monday for the Christmas holiday.
   The Bank of Japan, the nation's central bank, said it decided to
raise the discount rate to 4.25 percent from its current level at
3.75 percent. The hike would be put into effect immediately, the
bank said.
   The discount rate is the rate the central bank charges on its
loans to commercial banks.
   The Yomiuri Shimbun, the largest mass-circulation newspaper in
Japan, said the central bank's policy board decided to strike a
pre-emptive blow against inflationary pressures, stemming from
continued high growth in the money supply, upward pressure on land
prices and tightness in the labor market.
   On the Tokyo Stock Exchange, the Nikkei Stock Average of 225
selected issues, which lost 175.11 points Friday, won back 383.25
points, or 0.99 percent, to close at 38,423.62.
   Securities dealers said share prices were moving in a narrow
range during the morning session as investors remained on the
sidelines in response to yet unconfirmed reports of the interest
rate hike.
   But once the discount rate hike was announced in the early
afternoon, investors enthusiastically placed buy orders.
   ``The market welcomed the discount rate hike,'' said a dealer at
Nikko Securities Co., speaking on condition of anonymity.
</TEXT>

</DOC>