<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0186 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0931EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Japan-Daiwa     12-26 0292</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Japan-Daiwa,0305</SECOND>
<HEAD>Daiwa Securities Acknowledges Unfair Stock Transactions</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Daiwa Securities Co. has been punished for
compensating a customer for losses in stock transactions, a company
official said Tuesday.
   The official said the company had not violated any laws, but
quoted Daiwa President Masahiro Dozen as apologizing for unfairness
to other investors.
   The Finance Ministry has prohibited Daiwa, one of four major
Japanese securities firms, from raising capital through public
share offerings for the time being, said the official, who spoke on
condition of anonymity.
   The ministry also ordered the company to refrain from corporate
customer business for two days, he added.
   Finance Ministry officials were not available for comment after
office hours Tuesday.
   Kyodo News Service said the ministry had discovered that Daiwa
Securities compensated for a corporate customer's losses in stock
transactions between 1975 and 1980, but could not find out whether
Daiwa had entered into a contract guaranteeing the customer against
losses in stock transactions, a violation of the Securities and
Exchange Law.
   Kyodo said the ministry's investigation showed Daiwa had
obtained about 12 billion yen, or $84 million, from selling a
subsidiary's stock and paid 11.3 billion yen to a customer that had
lost in stock transactions and 700 million yen as a commission to a
company that settled the matter.
   The Daiwa official confirmed such transactions, but declined to
give figures.
   He said four former Daiwa employees involved in the affair would
resign.
   The pay of Dozen and 11 other executives would be cut by 10
percent for periods of three months to one year, the official said.
   Kyodo said the ministry investigated after press reports alleged
that Daiwa had filed false business reports to cover up losses it
incurred in compensating the customer.
</TEXT>

</DOC>