<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0134 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0207EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f BC-JunkBonds Adv26   12-23 0761</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Junk Bonds, Adv 26,0789</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv26</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Tuesday Dec. 26</HEAD>
<HEAD>Defaults Soar to $6 Billion in Junk Bond Market's Worst Year</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEFAN FATSIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Junk bond defaults soared to $6 billion in 1989
as the number and value of new issues sank to four-year lows in a
market battered by a weak economy and sagging corporate profits,
industry data show.
   While the $200 billion market appeared to stabilize toward
yearend, it didn't recover from an autumn bruising that sent prices
plummeting, investors fleeing and companies scrambling to meet
hefty interest payments.
   Junk bonds are so called because they are considered below
investment grade and therefore offer high yields to investors in
exchange for the higher risk of default. They have been one of the
most important tools for financing takeovers and corporate growth.
   Moody's Investors Service Inc., a credit-rating agency,
downgraded 152 junk bond issuing companies in the first 11 months
of the year, compared with 110 for all of 1988. The ratio of
downgrades to upgrades through November was 2.8, sharply higher
than 1.6 last year.
   Meanwhile, the average net asset value of junk-bond mutual funds
declined 10 percent on average this year, according to Moody's.
   ``The troubling fact is it occurred while the economy was still
growing,'' Moody's senior economist John Lonski said. ``This begs
the question of what the deterioration of junk bond credit will
look like in the event of a recession.''
   Lower credit ratings mean companies have to pay higher interest
rates to borrow money. The lower a company's credit rating, the
riskier its securities are considered.
   A Moody's report estimates that a total of $6 billion in junk
bond debt belonging to 50 companies will have entered default in
1989. That compares with an annual average of about $4 billion in
recent years.
   Among the most publicized defaults in the market that dates only
to the late-1970s were Integrated Resources Inc. at close to $1
billion and Southmark Corp. at about $700 million.
   ``The situation shows no sign of getting much better,'' Lonski
said. ``We expect that in 1990 the default rate will climb to its
1989 pace.''
   The junk bond market hit the skids in September when Campeau
Corp., which used $3 billion in junk financing to create a
retailing empire, missed some interest payments because of a cash
squeeze.
   Dollar volume of junk bond issues this year through last
Wednesday totaled $5.3 billion, down 8.6 percent from 1988 and 21
percent from the peak year of 1986, according to Securities Data Co.
   There were 131 new issues for the 1989 period, vs. 160 in 1988,
190 in 1987 and 226 in 1986, the data showed. It was the lowest
since 131 new issues in 1984.
   Lonski said RJR Nabisco Inc.'s single $4 billion issue of the
securities, used to complete the company's record $25 billion
debt-financed takeover, accounted for the biggest chunk of the new
issue value.
   He said junk bonds in 1989 were used less frequently than in
past years for traditional financing purposes such as the expansion
of business.
   Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc. remained atop the junk bond charts,
though its market share fell below 40 percent for the first time
ever. Drexel underwrote $9.7 billion in high-yield bonds through
Wednesday, Securities Data reported.
   In its ``High-Yield Review'' for December, Drexel acknowledged
the market's problems but said the difference in yields between
junk bonds and government-issued Treasury securities remained wide.
   Drexel said junk bond yields, often as much as 17 percent, still
outweighs the risk of default. Drexel long has maintained that a
diversified portfolio of junk bonds compensates for defaults.
   The firm, which pioneered the bonds through its now-indicted
former executive Michael Milken, said the government-mandated
withdrawal of savings and loans and redemptions by mutual funds
amid bad publicity hurt the market most this year.
   ``Individual investors decided to withdraw not so much on sound
credit analysis as on herd instinct,'' the Drexel report said.
   ``The general perception that there was something wrong with
`junk' bonds (the identity of the securities was now completely
separate from the companies that issued them) sank deeper into the
public consciousness,'' it said.
   The Wall Street firm, hurt by the weakness and its settlement of
unprecedented federal insider trading charges, said bad press about
high-yield defaults hurt liquidity and led mutual funds to pull out.
   ``On the other hand, these stories helped create market
imperfections from which astute investors can profit,'' Drexel
said. ``We believe that is the case today.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End advance Tuesday Dec. 26</NOTE>

</DOC>