<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0033EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-Scene     12-28 0623</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Scene,0640</SECOND>
<HEAD>Embassies Ringed by Troops, Barbed Wire and Rock Music</HEAD>
<BYLINE>With PM-Panama, Bjt ^By DOUGLAS GRANT MINE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega was
rocked by a special hit list as Armed Forces radio played through
loudspeakers pointed at his refuge, the Vatican Embassy.
   ``Baby You're No Good,'' by Linda Ronstadt, ``Voodoo Child'' by
Jimi Hendrix and Bobby Fuller's ``I Fought the Law and the Law
Won'' were some of tunes that appeared on the radio playlist
Wednesday afternoon.
   The olive-green loudspeakers were set up by some of the 100
soldiers who ringed the embassy compound to keep Noriega from
getting away.
   Standing by their armored cars, the soldiers first heard David
Bowie's ``Modern Love,'' played so loudly it easily reached the top
of the nearby Holiday Inn, where reporters kept a vigil on the
embassy.
   The radio then played a string of rap songs, which shook the
building, before switching to the news.
   If Noriega wasn't wearing earplugs, he heard that the United
States is trying to freeze millions in his alleged cocaine earnings
in foreign countries.
   He also heard newly installed President Guillermo Endara call
him ``a common criminal of the worst kind ... accused of homicides
and narcotraffic and very, very horrendous crimes.''
   Later in the day, the troops moved up a tank with a 152mm cannon
next to the embassy's west wall, although the cannon was not
pointed at the embassy.
   The Cuban Embassy, in downtown Panama City, was surrounded by
coils of barbed wire. And along the street leading to the Cuban
ambassador's residence in the plush San Francisco district,
American troops manned roadblocks and allowed only people who live
in the street to go in.
   The embassies of Nicaragua, Spain and Libya were also surrounded
to prevent Noriega henchmen from seeking refuge there.
   American diplomats have declined comment on the legality of the
actions in a swift little war in which the rules seemed to have
vanished with the first puff of gunsmoke.
   On Tuesday, the Vatican ambassador, Monsignor Sebastian Laboa,
was frisked and his car searched by American troops as he left the
embassy, a rare if not unheard of occurrence because accredited
diplomats carry immunity rights that are especially valued in Latin
America.
   Noriega's ouster and capture were among the top goals of the
U.S. invasion. The Vatican Embassy, which Endara once used for
sanctuary when he was in the opposition and Noriega ran the
country, was one of the likely places of refuge the Americans
didn't stake out.
   But now that he is in there, it is vigilantly guarded.
   A few troops in sandbagged positions remain around the Cuban
Embassy, which is close to that of Spain. Nobody answers the
embassy doorbell.
   At the residence, Cuban Ambassador Lazaro Mora was apparently
inside with a considerable number of other people, but polite U.S.
soldiers told inquiring reporters, ``You can't come here.''
   Neighbors said that in the days immediately after the American
troops invaded there was a flurry of activity outside the home.
``Cars were going in and out three and five at a time and they
looked like they were full of food,`` said a woman who lives nearby.
   ``A man in that house over there can see into the courtyard and
he said he saw 14 cars. There is never that much activity there,''
she said.
   Speculation about who may be inside varies. A call went out for
a pediatrician a couple of nights ago. On Wednesday, one resident
said she saw a man crawl over the compound wall and run.
   ``We told him the Americans would shoot him if he ran. He told
us, `The Americans will shoot me if they catch me,''' she said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>