<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0211 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 2309EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-VietReunion     12-22 0398</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Viet Reunion,0408</SECOND>
<HEAD>Vietnamese Family Back Together After More Than a Decade</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WENDY E. LANE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than a decade of separation was all but
forgotten when six members of a Vietnamese family joyously reunited
with their parents, three brothers and a sister Friday at Los
Angeles International Airport.
   Sobs and screams greeted the long-awaited arrival of 65-year-old
Nguyen Van Nhu, his wife Yen and three of their children, who were
seeing the rest of their family for the first time since the
Vietnam War tore them apart.
   ``Thank you, America, thank you!'' shouted Barry Nguyen, 29, one
of six members of the family who reside in the United States.
``This is the greatest day of my life.''
   Tears streamed down his face as he ran to embrace his parents,
whom he had not seen since leaving Vietnam in 1978.
   For his 32-year-old brother Bruce, the wait had been even
longer. He last saw his mother and father in 1972 before he left
his native Saigon to join the army.
   ``It means so much to see my father for Christmas,'' he said as
his three sons met their grandfather for the first time. ``Now they
have freedom.''
   The Nguyens flocked together in the middle of the airport
terminal, hugging and crying as a group of more than 20 friends and
relatives welcomed the new arrivals with flowers and gifts.
   Three of the Nguyen children have been in the United States
since 1975 when the fall of Saigon forced them to flee by boat to
Thailand. Since then, Bruce, Catherine, 28, and Anna, 29, have been
joined by two brothers and a sister. All now have children of their
own.
   Friday's reunion capped a six-year effort to bring the rest of
the family to the United States permanently. The new arrivals
included Duc, 25; Hoa, 23; Binh, 22, and Thinh, 21. One sister,
35-year-old Luu, remains in Vietnam due to emigration problems.
   ``I remember my brothers and sisters in Vietnam when they were
just little children,'' said Bruce, who like most of his siblings
have adopted Anglicized names.
   Bruce, Catherine and Barry work for the U.S. Postal Service.
They, along with John, 30, and The, 37, have secured housing for
their parents and jobs for their siblings.
   ``The first thing we will do is have a party to celebrate,''
Bruce said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>