<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0204 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0824EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv27   12-18 0467</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv27,0488</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv27</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Wednesday, Dec. 27</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is Wednesday, Dec. 27, the 361st day of 1989. There are
four days left in the year.
   Today's Highlight in History:
   On Dec. 27, 1831, naturalist Charles Darwin set out on a voyage
to the Pacific aboard the HMS Beagle. Darwin's observations during
the voyage helped form the basis for his theory of evolution.
   On this date:
   In 1822, scientist Louis Pasteur was born in Dole, France.
   In 1900, militant prohibitionist Carry Nation carried out her
first public smashing of a bar, at the Carey Hotel in Wichita, Kan.
   In 1927, ``Show Boat,'' one of the major works of the American
musical theater, opened at the Ziegfeld Theater in New York.
   In 1932, Radio City Music Hall opened in New York.
   In 1945, 28 nations signed an agreement creating the World Bank.
   In 1947, the children's television program ``Howdy Doody,''
hosted by Bob Smith, made its debut on NBC.
   In 1949, Queen Juliana of the Netherlands signed an act granting
sovereignty to Indonesia after more than three centuries of Dutch
rule.
   In 1968, Apollo 8 and its three astronauts made a safe,
nighttime splashdown in the Pacific.
   In 1970, ``Hello, Dolly!'' closed on Broadway after a
then-record run of 2,844 performances.
   In 1978, Algerian President Houari Boumediene, one of the Third
World's most prominent and outspoken leaders, died after 40 days in
a coma.
   In 1983, President Ronald Reagan declared himself fully
responsible for the security lapses which led to the Beirut bombing
that took the lives of 241 U.S. servicemen.
   In 1983, Pope John Paul II met with the man who had shot him,
Mehmet Ali Agca, and pardoned him.
   Ten years ago: Soviet forces seized control of Afghanistan.
President Hafizullah Amin, who was overthrown and executed, was
replaced by Babrak Karmal.
   Five years ago: Amid rumors he was seriously ill, Soviet
President Konstantin U. Chernenko re-appeared in public to give out
several literature awards.
   One year ago: Hundreds of residents of Lockerbie, Scotland, paid
silent tribute to five Americans among the 270 killed in the
bombing of Pan Am Flight 103, as coffins containing the victims'
remains began their journey home.
   Today's Birthdays: Actress Marlene Dietrich is 88. Sen. James A.
McClure, R-Idaho, is 65. Psychologist Lee Salk is 63. Actress Tovah
Feldshuh is 37.
   Thought for Today: ``It is the steady and merciless increase of
occupations, the augmented speed at which we are always trying to
live, the crowding of each day with more work than it can
profitably hold, which has cost us, among other good things, the
undisturbed enjoyment of friends. Friendship takes time, and we
have no time to give it.'' _ Agnes Repplier, American essayist
(1858-1950).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Advance for Wednesday, Dec. 27</NOTE>

</DOC>