<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0338EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     12-26 0704</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0732</SECOND>
<HEAD>On the Light Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LAFAYETTE, Ind. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Charles Hunter accepted his teacher's
semester challenge, and last week he carried it to school: numbers
from one to 1 million listed on 2,400 pages and weighing 50 pounds.
   The project began after Steve Randak, who teaches a biology
class for gifted students at Lafayette Jefferson High School, told
the class he would give an A for the semester to anyone who wrote
out every number from one to a million.
   Unfortunately, Hunter didn't qualify for the A because he
generated the numbers on his home computer.
   ``I just thought it would be really neat to show someone could
do it and to prove how large a million is,'' said Hunter, who is
earning an A in the course anyway.
   Hunter said he first set out to write each number by hand, but
lost interest at about 5,000.
   His interest was renewed when he thought of printing the numbers
by computer. He ran the program at least seven hours a day for two
weeks. After 2{ boxes of computer paper and three ink cartridges,
he reached the magic number.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CAMBRIDGE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Harvard University may profess to be
striving to combat its image as a citadel of the privileged.
Sometimes, however, the Harvard of old, when titled and untitled
royalty paced the ivied campus, peeps through the modern curtain.
   In a new questionnaire, the school asks its graduates to own up
to their proper title. For alumni not content with Mr., Miss, Mrs.
or Ms., Harvard offers 43 other choices.
   Admiral? General? Baron? Contess? Chief Justice? The Right
Honorable Lord? The Most Reverend Archbishop? His Royal Highness?
Please check all that apply.
   But some titles were left out _ such as president.
   President Bush went to Harvard's archrival, Yale.
   The president of the Harvard Alumni Association, Charles J. Egan
Jr., said there was nothing unusual about the survey.
   ``It's like the census. It's the same principle, when you're
trying to determine exactly who is in that population,'' said Egan,
who signed a letter accompanying the survey urging alumni to fill
it out.
   Egan said at least four chief justices of the Massachusetts
Supreme Court were graduates of Harvard Law School. He said he
could think of at least two alumni who bore the title ``His royal
highness.''
   Harvard spokeswoman Barbara Welanetz said the university has
many illustrious alumni, but she wondered whether the survey used
the right tone.
   ``Perhaps it was not as well thought through as it might have
been,'' she said.
   The information is to be compiled in a two-volume, $85 directory
of Harvard's 200,000-plus graduates.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>KALAMAZOO, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Western Michigan University professor
is trying to encourage serious research on extraterrestrials by
reviving a professional journal.
   The Journal of UFO Studies, resurrected this year from a defunct
publication of the same name, aims to give researchers something
``they wouldn't be embarrassed by writing for,'' said its editor,
Michael Swords.
   ``It's meant to allow the serious people to have an outlet,
which doesn't really exist right now. This was a hole in UFO
publishing that had to be filled,'' the professor of natural
sciences said recently.
   Swords, who is working on the second annual issue, said the $15
journal, with a circulation of about 700, is too technical for the
general public.
   For example, one of the first issue's three articles of about 35
pages each discussed chemical analyses of a substance gleaned from
the Delphos Case, a supposed 1971 UFO landing site in Kansas.
Another looked at the effect of hypnosis in obtaining information
from people who claim they have been abducted by aliens.
   Swords wrote a third article, about whether other life exists in
the universe. He said it isn't a matter of if, but of how many.
   ``All the laws of nature are the same everywhere, and what
happens once is bound to happen twice. Chances of other high-tech
extraterrestrial civilizations are equal to how long it could exist
after reaching the danger zone of technology.
   ``Since we're made it 45 years past nuclear weapons, I think
people think there are at least dozens if not thousands of
high-tech civilizations out there,'' Swords said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>