<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1112EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AIDSStory     12-17 0321</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-AIDS Story,0329</SECOND>
<HEAD>Student with AIDS Tells Classmates During Show-and-Tell</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Parents and students at Chattahoochee Elementary
School knew that a child there had AIDS. They didn't know who. So
third-grader Brett Lykins decided to tell them.
   ``It was my turn to go up'' for show-and-tell on Friday, he said
afterward in a soft, unwavering voice. ``I just went up and said I
was the one. It's been hard to keep this secret. I decided not to
keep it anymore.''
   Brett's identity had been kept secret from all except the
principal and his teacher, in accordance with the Gwinnett County
school system's 2-year-old AIDS policy.
   ``I think the kids in class felt really happy that I did this,''
he said. ``I think some of them knew I had it, but there were some
who didn't.''
   One classmate told Brett, 9, she would pray for him every night,
said his mother, Marty Lykins, who accompanied her son to school
after he told her of his plans to reveal his secret.
   Another friend gave him a wind-up doll. ``She said she wanted me
to have it. But that's not why I did this. I don't want them to
give me a lot of stuff. I just want them to know.''
   After show-and-tell last week, Brett's teacher, Nancy Terry, led
the class in a health lesson that focused on AIDS, which destroys
the body's defenses against disease, leaving a person prey to
life-threatening infections and certain cancers.
   Brett's father, Steve Lykins, said his son's health has been
relatively good despite the AIDS infection, which was contracted
from a blood transfusion received shortly after his premature
birth. His parents learned in 1987 that he had the disease, and
Brett was told this year.
   Health experts say Brett's presence in class does not endanger
his classmates.
   Ms. Terry said Brett's show-and-tell session ``was a wonderful
experience. ... The children have been so nice.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>