<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0240EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Panama-NoriegaQuarters     12-22 0345</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Noriega Quarters,340</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soldiers Say Noriega Military Quarters Poshly Decorated</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   EDITORS: The following report was filed by members of a pool
flown to Panama by the Pentagon.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>FORT AMADOR, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega kept
extravagant quarters on the military base shared by the United
States and Panama, said U.S. soldiers Thursday who toured and
helped secure the building Noriega used.
   The structure, known as Building 8 at Fort Amador, contained a
cache of automatic weapons, a private movie theater and a poster of
Adolf Hitler on the wall in Noriega's library, the soldiers said.
   Until the U.S. invasion early Wednesday morning, the base was a
joint installation under terms of the Panama Canal Treaty.
   ``They have all our military manuals because we were allies,''
said Sgt. First Class Joseph Torregrossa, who looked over the
Noriega quarters Thursday.
   Torregrossa said the DEA report discovered was a 1986-87
hardcover book that read: ``The Battle Against Drugs in Panama.''
   Torregrossa said he found night-vision goggles in Noriega's
offices and fully-automatic weapons, top-of-the-line items like
Israeli Uzis. In all, about 250 weapons, including small
Derringers, were discovered, he said.
   Soldiers said Noriega's quarters, in the upper two floors of the
Building 8, contained plush carpeting, a fancy dining room and a
movie theater. There are no windows where Noriega spent his time,
one soldier said.
   ``This is what freaked me out,'' said another soldier identified
only as Sandridge. ``Underneath his glass coffee table he had a
ceramic leopard.''
   Sandridge said there was a row of Noriega bats and baseball caps
on a shelf and a box of Havana cigars, wrapped in paper printed
with the words: ``Manuel Antonio Noriega, 4 Stars.''
   Originally, reporters were to be taken to a so-called ``witch
house'' that is owned or was frequented by Noriega.
   According to folklore, the house contains entrails and vats of
blood. But after being diverted to the Army base to get clearance
to view the house, reporters were told ``a boobytrap'' had been
found inside and the house was not yet open to visits.
</TEXT>

</DOC>