<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0931EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-PentagonText ?Takes   12-20 1016</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Pentagon Text, ? Takes,1,000-up</SECOND>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is the text of statements at the Pentagon
Wednesday by Defense Secretary Dick Cheney and Gen. Colin Powell,
chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, and questions they fielded
at a news conference.
   
   Cheney:
   I think all of you have seen the president's statement
explaining the action that he ordered and explaining the background
and the rationale for it. Obviously, we've tried for more than two
years to resolve by peaceful means the difficult relationship that
had developed with the government of Panama.
   This past week it came to a head with the declaration of Manuel
Noriega as a maximum leader and his statement that a state of war
existed between Panama and the United States.
   That was, of course, followed by the shooting death of an
unarmed American off-duty Marine officer on Saturday and the brutal
treatment of other U.S. military personnel and dependents.
   On Sunday, the president made the decision to order U.S. forces
to Panama, specifically, as he indicated earlier, with the mission
of protecting American lives, of protecting American interests in
connection with our responsibilities under the Panama Canal Treaty,
with the effort being made also to restore democracy and to bring
Gen. Noriega to justice, should we capture him.
   The order went out late on Sunday to implement a plan that had
been in existence for some time. It was one of the first items I
was briefed on when I became Secretary of Defense last spring.
   The plan was developed to deal with various contingencies that
might arise in Panama. We have always been concerned for several
months by virtue of the fact that there are large numbers of
Americans in Panama, not only those that are there because they've
been assigned there, because of their military role and
responsibilities, but also American civilians who live in the area.
   The operation is continuing at this time. Some of the reporting
we have, obviously, is still fragmentary. It's our intention this
morning in this briefing to give you as much information as we
reasonably can, given the fact that the operation continues.
   At this point, of course Gen. Noriega is still at large. He is
no longer the maximum leader in Panama. A democratic government has
been reestablished with the duly elected officials selected by the
people of Panama last May. He is, at this point, a fugitive.
   As Secretary, I want to thank all of those individuals who
participated in the operation. It has been carried out in an
extremely professional manner. I think they have performed superbly
in carrying out their duties and their responsibilities.
   And, at this point, I'd like, to turn the briefing over to the
Chairman of the Joint Chiefs, Gen. Powell.
   
   Powell:
   Thank you, Mr. Secretary. Let me add my own caution that the
operation is only seven hours old and it is still ongoing and may
be continuing for some time to come. So we're going to give you as
much as we possibly can, but please understand that there will be
details that I cannot get into for purposes of operational security.
   As you know, at the direction of the president, United States
armed forces undertook operations in combat in Panama just prior to
0100 hours this morning, or roughly just before 1 a.m. this morning.
   The participating units include in-place forces in Panama, the
193rd Infantry Brigade, which in recent months had been reinforced
by Marine units, by a battalion from the 7th Infantry Division at
Fort Ord, Calif., by a mechanized battalion from the 5th Infantry
Division at Fort Polk, La., as well as additional supporting forces
to include military police.
   In the course of the evening additional forces have been added,
and I'll describe how they have been added. Those additional forces
include a brigade of the 82nd Airborne Division, two Ranger
battalions, selected special operating units.
   All of this, of course, was supported superbly by the United
States Air Force and the United States Navy, and there are
additional reinforcing units that will assist in stability
operations coming from the 7th Infantry Division at Fort Ord,
Calif., as well as from the 16th MP brigade at Fort Bragg, N.C. As
you know, our purpose, as stated by the president, is to protect
Americans, to protect the integrity of our treaty, to restore
democracy in Panama, and bring to justice the fugitive Mr. Noriega.
   We conducted operations this morning, beginning just before 1
a.m., in three general areas that Gen. Kelly will point out on the
map.
   First, in the central Panama Canal zone area, to the east of
that, near the International Airfield, and to the west down by Rio
Hato.
   Let me now turn to the larger map and discuss each one of these
pieces in turn.
   Let's start up on the Atlantic Caribbean side, with Task Force
Atlantic. Task Force Atlantic consisted of a battalion from the 7th
Infantry Division and a battalion from the 82nd Airborne Division,
which was in the Jungle Operations Training Center in Panama.
   Their mission was to secure several critical sites in the
southern portion of Task Force Atlantic AO _ the prison at Gamboa,
which was secured in the course of the morning and within which
there are some PDF personnel who had been put in jail as a result
of the coup attempt earlier in the fall, and we now have some 47,
48 very happy prisoners who have been released; the electrical
distribution center at Sierra Tigre is now secure; and Madden Dam,
a critical facility, is also secure.
   Other elements of Task Force Atlantic also ensured the security
of our installations in the Colon area, and they neutralized the
8th Infantry Company of the PDF, which did not take too active a
role in this operation, as well as neutralizing the naval infantry
unit, located up toward the north.
   There is still some sporadic firing up there. The situation
isn't completely resolved, but for the most part, Task Force
Atlantic has completed its assigned missions.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>MORE</BYLINE>

</DOC>