<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0142 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1949EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather 1stLd-Writethru a0720 12-19 0891</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0720,0912</SECOND>
<HEAD>Record Cold Continues, Snow Across Northern States</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 3 grafs after 4th to UPDATE with weather deaths, Mich.
cold; INSERTS 4 grafs after the 9th graf previous, ``Freeezing rain,''
to update with stranded travelers, Ark. conditions; And Inserts 2 grafs
after the 16th previous, ``A 200-mile,'' with Missouri River ice.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Temperatures hit record lows Tuesday from the western Plains to
the East Coast, including one at 26 below zero, and light snow fell
across the Ohio Valley, the Great Lakes and the Northwest.
   Tuesday's low for the Lower 48 states was 35 degrees below zero
at Bismarck, N.D., not a record.
   By noon, temperatures over much of the upper Mississippi Valley
and northern Plains had not risen above zero.
   In stark contrast, southern Florida had record warmth in the
upper 80s.
   Since Friday, at least 38 deaths have been blamed on the
weather, including traffic deaths on slippery roads and hypothermia.
   Michigan outreach centers pleaded for warm clothes to give to
help the needy stave off the unusual cold. The average mean
temperature in Michigan for the first 18 days of December was 14.1
degrees, far below the month's norm of 23.5 degrees.
   ``I don't recall a December being quite this cold,'' Detroit
police Sgt. George Anthony said Tuesday as he leafed through
reports about victims of hypothermia. Two freezing deaths have been
confirmed in Wayne County and at least three others are believed to
be hypothermia.
   An inch or more of snow covered much of the nation north of a
line from east-central Virginia across north-central Tennessee,
northern Arkansas, southern Colorado and northwestern Utah to
northwestern Idaho, the National Weather Service said.
   At midday, snow fell over western New York state, much of the
western half of Pennsylvania, eastern and northern Ohio, West
Virginia, much of Virginia, eastern Kentucky, Michigan, Montana,
Idaho, western Wyoming and eastern Washington state.
   There were no reports of measurable snowfall during the six
hours up to 1 p.m. EST, except in northwestern Indiana, where
Westville had 5 inches of new snow by noon, the weather service
said. Up to 4 inches fell early in the day in Illinois.
   A winter storm warning, in effect into Wednesday, was posted
over northwestern Montana.
   Freezing rain fell from northeastern Texas across northern
Louisiana and southern Arkansas, and over eastern Tennessee, much
of North and South Carolina and northeastern Georgia, where the
accumulating ice caused scattered power outages and glazed highways.
   More than 100 motorists stranded overnight at Hope, Ark., by ice
on Interstate 30 were able to get back on the road Tuesday.
   ``We escorted about 104 people to the Community Center last
night, starting around 9 p.m. and finishing at about one this
morning,'' Hope Police Chief Richard Thomas said.
   In addition, officials said hotels in the area were full while
other motorists spent the night in their vehicles. ``Wal-Mart's
parking lot was full of 18-wheelers,'' Thomas said.
   Some 70 school districts across Arkansas remained closed Tuesday
because of the inclement weather. State office workers were under
the state's inclement weather policy, which gives non-essential
administrative workers until 10 a.m. to arrive without being
deducted leave time.
   Many northern Georgia counties kept their schools closed,
although most Atlanta area schools reopened after being closed
Monday.
   Officials in Griffin, Ga., said ice brought tree limbs down on
power lines there, cutting electricity to large sections of the
city for as long as two hours.
   Ice on roads was blamed for accidents around metropolitan
Atlanta and Athens, and police blocked off several interstate
highway ramps that were littered with cars and trucks unable to
cross slick spots.
   Treacherous driving conditions in North Carolina caused at least
one death and scores of traffic accidents, and dozens of schools
and business closed.
   Rain fell from the remainder of Georgia into northern Florida
and northern Alabama, and was scattered along the Gulf of Mexico
coast.
   In the mountains of southeastern Wyoming, wind blew at 50 to 60
mph near Arlington and near Vedauwoo.
   A 200-mile stretch of the Mississippi River, from St. Louis to
Cairo, Ill., was closed to barge traffic by ice and low water, the
U.S. Coast Guard said.
   About 60 percent of the 195 miles of Missouri River north of
Omaha, Neb., to the Gavins Point Dam was frozen over Tuesday,
forming ice jams that reduced the amount of water flowing
downstream to towns and power plants.
   The river level was within one foot of the level at which some
power plants would be unable to operate because their water intake
systems would no longer work, said Chet Worm, chief of the
reservoir regulation section of the Corps Missouri River District.
   Record low temperatures were 8 at Atlantic City, N.J.; 6 at
Baltimore; 10 at Bridgeport, Conn.; 26 below zero at Dickinson,
N.D.; 6 below at Elkins, W.Va.; 19 below at Grand Island, Neb.; 5
at Harrisburg, Pa.; 20 below at Lincoln, Neb.; 24 below at Norfolk,
Neb.; 7 below at Wheat Ridge, Colo.; and 3 below at Youngstown,
Ohio.
   But in Florida, Miami hit a record high of 85 and West Palm
Beach reached a record 88.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EST ranged from 18
degrees below zero at Detroit Lakes and International Falls, Minn.,
to 87 at West Palm Beach.
</TEXT>

</DOC>