<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0438EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Obstetrician-Deaths     12-19 0502</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Obstetrician-Deaths,0517</SECOND>
<HEAD>Convicted of Second-degree Murder in Eight Infants' Deaths</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An obstetrician was convicted of
second-degree murder for the deaths of eight infants during bungled
high-risk deliveries he performed in his office rather than in
hospitals.
   Jurors deliberated 19 days before returning the verdict against
Dr. Milos Klvana, 47, who prosecutors accused of continuing his
practice even though he knew he wasn't qualified to handle risky
births.
   Klvana was convicted Monday of nine counts of second-degree
murder and of 43 other felonies including insurance fraud, grand
theft, perjury, conspiracy and practicing medicine without a
license.
   Klvana, a resident of suburban Santa Clarita, could be sentenced
to 15 years to life in prison on the second-degree murder charges.
Sentencing was set for Jan. 12.
   Midway through the return of the verdicts in Superior Court,
Klvana jumped to his feet and told Judge Judith Chirlin, ``I want
to be excused.''
   He was allowed to leave the courtroom, but returned after all
the verdicts were read. He asked the judge for a new trial and said
he would represent himself.
   Prosecutors said Klvana bungled deliveries in his Valencia and
Temple City medical offices between 1982 and 1986, causing one
stillbirth and the deaths of eight infants shortly after birth.
   Klvana, who was convicted in 1978 on 26 counts of illegally
prescribing drugs, was arrested in October 1986 following a
two-year investigation of the childbirth deaths.
   Prosecutors said the Czechoslovakian-born physician lacked the
training to deliver the babies but knew enough to realize the
mothers should have been taken to the hospital.
   ``There was no question that the man knew what he was doing was
dangerous,'' Deputy District Attorney Brian R. Kelberg said. ``He
did it for reasons that were selfish rather than in the best
interest of his patients. He's not just incompetent, but he knows
he's incompetent.''
   Among the women whose babies died, the prosecution said, were an
insulin dependent diabetic and two women who had RH factor blood
types, making their pregnancies risky even in hospitals.
   Klvana contended he was singled out because of his unorthodox
birthing practices including out-of-hospital deliveries and the use
of a labor-inducing drug that prosecutors said should only be
administered in hospitals.
   The prosecutor never contended that Klvana intended to kill the
babies. But he argued that the doctor knew that deaths or
stillbirths could result from his recommendations against
hospitalizing the mothers.
   Klvana's attorneys conceded that he was negligent but argued
there was no basis for a murder conviction, saying the doctor did
not understand his own incompetence.
   Early in the trial, Klvana's co-defendant, Dolores Doyle, 36, an
unlicensed midwife, unexpectedly pleaded guilty to involuntary
manslaughter and insurance fraud in a plea bargain. She was
released on probation, having already served two years in prison.
   Klvana has spent all but three months in jail since his 1986
arrest. His $200,000 bail was revoked when it was learned he had
applied for a new certification to prescribe drugs and was
dispensing oral contraceptives.
</TEXT>

</DOC>