<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0186 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0043EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Ireland-AircraftCenter     12-19 0445</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Ireland-Aircraft Center,0460</SECOND>
<HEAD>International Aircraft Maintenance Center to be Built in Ireland</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A $122 million aircraft maintenance center will be
built at Shannon Airport in Ireland by an aircraft leasing company
and two European airlines, the companies announced.
   Guinness Peat Aviation, the Ireland-based aircraft leasing firm,
will own 30 percent, while the West German airline Lufthansa and
the Swiss airline Swissair will own 35 percent each of Shannon
Aerospace Ltd., the company formed to construct, operate and own
the facility.
   Construction of the 300,000 square foot aircraft overhaul and
maintenance center will begin this spring, at the airport on
Ireland's west coast, the companies said Monday.
   The new company will start operations in late 1992 with an
initial work force of 350 which, the partners said, should rise to
1,000 by the mid-1990s.
   The facility will have two maintenance bays, one for Boeing
B737s and the other for McDonnell Douglas MD-80s. There will be an
aircraft painting hangar to accommodate the largest planes.
   ``It is planned to have two more additional bays commissioned by
1996 giving the company the ability to expand into other aircraft
types and related activities,'' the announcement said.
   At the official announcement made at Shannon Airport, Lufthansa
executive board member Jurgen Weber called his firm's expansion
into Ireland ``strategic.''
   ``Aircraft leasing is gaining in importance and we want to
develop our ability to deal with this growing segment of the
maintenance market,'' Weber said. ``The acknowledged expertise in
aircraft maintenance of Lufthansa and Swissair and GPA's
significant customer base are a first class combination and a firm
foundation for a profitable enterprise.''
   Irish Minister for Industry and Commerce Desmond O'Malley said
he hoped the new venture would be a forerunner of other projects
with European partners.
   ``Shannon Aerospace is an example of the industry we need in
Ireland, soundly based on the reputations and research of its
eminent shareholders, well funded and meticulously planned,''
O'Malley said.
   Airline analysts said the venture would help Swissair and
Lufthansa reduce their high aircraft maintenance costs.
   ``One of the problems in Europe is the shortage of aircraft
engineers,'' said Stephen Clapham, a transport analyst at Hoare
Govett. ``Labor and property, your two biggest overheads, are
higher in Germany. Shannon is not the busiest airport so the
property costs will be lower.''
   Richard Hannah, airline analyst at UBS-Phillips and Drew, said
the aircraft maintenance center will also benefit GPA Group PLC.
   ``Guinness Peat is very dominant in the aircraft leasing
business,'' Hannah said. ``This is a logical expansion for them.''
   The chairman of the board of Shannon Aerospace will be Peter
Sutherland, a former European commissioner and a director of GPA
Group.
</TEXT>

</DOC>