<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0232EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Panama-USRelief     12-27 0422</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-US Relief,0433</SECOND>
<HEAD>Relief Efforts for Panama Under Way in Florida, Massachusetts</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Medical supplies from Florida have been sent to Panama, and food
and clothing are being gathered in Massachusetts to help the
Central American country recover from the U.S. invasion its
resulting civil disorders.
   ``We realize this is just a small amount of what's needed,''
said Luis Endara Jr., a cousin of the new Panamanian president and
head of the group, Help Panama, which sent the $50,000 shipment
Tuesday. ``But at this point anything is a help. These supplies are
urgently needed.''
   The supplies included plasma and antibiotics, syringes and
needles, intravenous solutions and orthopedic devices and were to
be distributed at Panama City's two main hospitals.
   Help Panama's first shipment, mostly donated by several south
Florida hospitals, filled a chartered twin-engine Lear 25 jet.
   Endara said a cargo ship with six 40-foot containers of food is
expected to leave Miami on Friday for the four-day voyage to
Panama, and Help Panama has opened accounts at two Miami banks to
take donations.
   In Quincy, Mass., Mike Preble, a 23-year-old department store
statistician, began a drive to collect food and clothing for
victims of warfare and looting in the Central American country.
   ``I'm not a spokesman for the U.S. government,'' Preble said,
``But we did what we had to do and now it's our responsibility to
clean it up.''
   Preble said he was prompted into action Saturday when he phoned
his cousin, Jane Huff, whose husband, Bill, works as a pilot on the
Panama Canal. They live in Balboa, Panama, with their three
children.
   Mrs. Huff told Preble that a high school soccer stadium in
Balboa was filled with about 3,000 people seeking help at a refugee
center.
   Preble felt he had to do something about that. So he enlisted
the cooperation from the Quincy mayor's and he put out a call
asking donors to bring clothing and non-perishable food to fire
stations. Arrangements could also be made to have volunteers
collect the goods, he said.
   On Tuesday, he didn't know how much was collected, and he was
still trying to arrange for a military cargo plane to deliver the
goods to Panama.
   Panamanian hospitals have suffered in part because Gen. Manuel
Antonio Noriega's regime used medical supply areas to hide arms,
according to Roberto Dominguez, who on Tuesday was named the
Panamanian consul in Miami.
   ``It's going to take a lot more shipments like these to return
the hospitals to where they should be,'' said Dominguez.
</TEXT>

</DOC>