<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0227 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2053EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-WorldReax 2ndLd-Writethru a0858 12-20 0937</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-World Reax, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0858,0970</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Union Condemns, Britain Applauds; Others Sympathetic</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs, UPDATING with Manila, more on Libya. Picks
up 6th graf, Despite Soviet ...; 6 grafs SUB for final 2 grafs 24-25, In
Iran ... UPDATING and making conform</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MAUREEN JOHNSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Soviet Union used language reminiscent of the
Cold War on Wednesday to denounce the U.S. military attack in
Panama. Leaders from Europe and Latin America generally opposed the
U.S. move but said it had to be done.
   Britain's Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher was one of the few
heads of state who fully supported President Bush's attempt to
capture Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega. ``Someone has to uphold
democracy,'' she said.
   Angry condemnation came from Peru, where President Alan Garcia
announced he was withdrawing his ambassador from Washington until
U.S. troops leave Panama.
   Nicaragua called a military alert and asked for an emergency
meeting of the U.N. Security Council.
   Libyan leader Col. Moammar Gadhafi said the assault made Nero
and Hitler look like angels. He met the Soviet ambassador and gave
him a letter for President Mikhail S. Gorbachev on the invasion,
asking Moscow to ``live up to its international responsibilities,''
Libya's official news agency JANA said.
   In Manila, Filipino congressional leaders on Thursday asked
President Corazon Aquino to recognize the ``democratically elected
government'' in Panama of Guillermo Endara, who was sworn in as
president after U.S. troops went in. On Dec. 1, U.S. jets flew air
cover to help the Manila government fight off a coup attempt.
   The official Soviet news agency Tass said of the invasion,
``This action is an example of notorious `gunboat diplomacy' which
has been used for decades by the United States in an attempt to
turn Latin American and Caribbean nations into its back yard.''
   Despite Soviet anger, Foreign Ministry spokesman Vadim P.
Perfiliev played down the impact on improved superpower relations.
   ``We are now in a situation where an event in the East or the
West is not perceived, is not evaluated, in terms of confrontation
between East and West,'' Perfiliev said in Moscow.
   But Perfiliev said the U.S. action violated U.S. charters and
``should be condemned by the international community ... (and) must
immediately stop.''
   The 12-European Economic Community did not issue a joint
statement.
   France is the current president of the community and a French
Foreign Ministry spokesman said there were no plans for a statement.
   The French government said it could not approve of the U.S.
``recourse to force'' but that it nonetheless backed the fight
against drugs and supported democratic movements everywhere.
   In London, Mrs. Thatcher said she had spoken with Bush on the
phone and told him her government supported him.
   ``Someone has to uphold democracy, there were terrible things
happening in Panama. It was a tyranny,'' Mrs. Thatcher said.
   ``It was a courageous decision'' to send in American troops, she
said.
   The opposition Labor Party criticized the U.S. move. In angry
exchanges later in the House of Commons it accused Mrs. Thatcher of
humiliating Britain by supporting the United States.
   Canada said the U.S. action set a ``dangerous precedent'' but
expressed sympathy.
   ``What would you have us do?'' asked Canadian Prime Minister
Brian Mulroney. ``Here you've got a drug runner and thug running
the country. He declares war on the United States. He assassinates
some innocent American citizens.''
   Among other Western allies, the Dutch government said it also
sympathized with Bush, but Spain, which has close ties throughout
Latin America, ``deeply lamented'' the U.S. move.
   Venezuela summed up many reactions by saying it opposed the
intervention but also opposed Noriega's regime.
   During a meeting of regional leaders in Colombia, Venezuela
blamed a ``lack of an effective and firm response by our
countries'' in the past for the situation in Panama.
   The Organization of American States, which has tried to pressure
Noriega to step down, convened an emergency meeting in Washington
at which the Panamanian delegate, Jose Maria Cabrera, called on the
group to condemn the ``brutal and criminal aggression.''
   ``It is not possible, while Panamanian citizens are still being
massacred without distinction of age, sex or status for this
organization to keep its arms crossed,'' he said.
   China made no overt comment. Its official Xinhua News Agency
issued brief reports that said Noriega was ``safe'' and would
``fight for the nation's sovereignty.''
   Japan was noncommittal. Foreign Minister Taro Nakayama said in
Tokyo he hoped the confrontation would end soon and a democratic
government take over in Panama.
   Japan's Asahi Shimbun newspaper said in an editorial prepared
for Thursday's editions ``it is highly questionable that the global
community will buy'' the U.S. explanation for its action.
   ``The difference in strength between America and Panama is like
that between an elephant and an ant. The United States should not
be surprised if its advance into Panama is regarded by the rest of
the world as a blatant invasion of Panama's independence and
sovereignty.''
   In Iran, official Tehran radio said the United States wanted to
replace Noriega with a government acceptable to itself ``so as to
continue its domination over the (Panama) Canal and its arrogant
hegemony over central and south America.''
   Gadhafi, who has been accused by official Washington in the past
of promoting international terrorism, said of the U.S. action, ``I
could not find any expression in the dictionary to describe the
degree of anger toward the savagery of official terrorism and
powermania.''
   He said the assault makes ``Nero and Hitler angels compared to
the western Mongols and Nazis of the Americans and their allies,''
JANA reported, monitored in Rome.
</TEXT>

</DOC>