<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0147EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Grenada-Panama     12-22 0696</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Grenada-Panama,0715</SECOND>
<HEAD>Six Years Later, Grenada Said to Face `Precarious Future'</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GLASS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN JUAN, Puerto Rico (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Six years after U.S. troops invaded
Grenada and threw out a Marxist junta, the tiny Caribbean island
boasts a sturdy democracy but an expected economic bonanza has
failed to materialize.
   ``The story in Grenada has been a very mixed one,'' Larry Birns,
director of the Washington-based Council on Hemispheric Affairs,
said in a telephone interview Thursday. ``One of the failures is
that Grenada hasn't developed a dependable economy.''
   ``It still faces a rather precarious future,'' he said.
   Just this week, Grenada _ the last country invaded by U.S.
troops before Panama _ demonstrated its commitment to parliamentary
democracy with a smooth transfer of power after the death of Prime
Minister Herbert Blaize.
   Blaize, 71, the first prime minister elected after the 1983
intervention, died Tuesday after a long illness. The same day,
Deputy Prime Minister Ben Jones was sworn in to head an interim
government and prepare for elections within 90 days in strict
accordance with the constitution.
   But the former British colony of 94,000 inhabitants on the
southern tip of the Caribbean chain has been going through a long
period of political uncertainty and economic difficulty.
   This month, 7,000 public workers staged a crippling one-week
general strike after Blaize reneged on a promise to pay them $9.25
million in back wages, saying the government did not have the money.
   In 1983, Grenada was ruled by a revolutionary regime allied with
Cuba and the Soviet Union. A power struggle within the government
led to a bloody coup and the firing-squad execution of Prime
Minister Maurice Bishop. The radical junta that seized power
imposed a 24-hour curfew.
   A force of U.S. Marines and paratroopers, numbering 7,000 at its
height, along with 300 soldiers and policemen from neighboring
Caribbean islands, invaded on Oct. 25, 1983, and quickly gained
control.
   The Reagan administration, already alarmed by Bishop's Soviet
and Cuban ties, said the invasion was necessary to protect the
lives of 480 American medical students and their families on
Grenada and to keep the island from being used as a staging post
for communist aggression in the region.
   Despite criticism abroad, the invasion was almost universally
welcomed by Grenadians, who refer to the operation as a ``rescue
mission'' and observe Oct. 25 as an annual holiday known as
Thanksgiving Day.
   Since 1983, the United States has pumped more than $110 million
into Grenada's economy with the stated aim of transforming the
island into a haven for American investment.
   But U.S. aid has dropped off sharply in the past few years and
only a handful of American companies have set up operations on the
island.
   ``Unfortunately, foreign and private investment has lagged
behind optimistic expectations ... and only recently have we seen
an increase in new projects,'' said a 1988 report by the Grenada
office of the U.S. Agency for International Development.
   Although the economy grew by a respectable 5.3 percent last
year, Grenada remained saddled with a foreign debt of $48.7
million, a domestic debt of $35.9 million and a trade deficit of
$59.6 million by the end of 1988, according to the Caribbean
Development Bank.
   Unemployment is officially pegged at around 20 percent, and
among youthful workers is estimated as high as 40 percent.
Alcoholism and drug addiction are said to have reached record
levels.
   The lucrative tourism business is growing, but business leaders
complain that Americans tend to avoid Grenada because of a lack of
direct flights and the island's lingering image as a war zone.
   Meanwhile, years of factional disputes over Blaize's handling of
the economy and his authoritarian style of leadership have left
Grenada's centrist political parties in disarray.
   The disunity raises the prospect of a split in the moderate vote
in the upcoming election and a possible comeback by Sir Eric Gairy,
the eccentric former prime minister once described by The Economist
magazine of London as a ``corrupt buffoon.'' Gairy was ousted in
1979 by leftist elements ultimately overthrown by the United States.
   ``If Gairy wins, we may very well be back to square one,'' Birns
said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>