<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0538EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-David     12-23 0355</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-David,0366</SECOND>
<HEAD>Noriega Forces Surrender Without a Fight in Western Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN HOPPER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DAVID, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Members of the Panamanian Defense Forces
stacked their guns and raised a white flag in Panama's westernmost
city, even though the only sign of U.S. force was two Air Force
planes that buzzed the barracks.
   ``I was just doing my job. I'm not happy about the situation,''
said one police officer, who refused to give his name. The police
are part of the Defense Forces that were commanded by ousted
dictator Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   Although Noriega was toppled from power by U.S. forces early
Wednesday, he escaped the net thrown by 24,000 U.S. soldiers,
sailors and Marines.
   No U.S. troops showed up in David, despite reports of shooting
and fighting in the area, 200 miles west of Panama City and 30
miles east of Costa Rica.
   On Thursday, two Air Force jets buzzed the Defense Forces
barracks in the center of David, witnesses said.
   On Friday, members of the Defense Forces raised a white banner
across the front of the barracks and 100 turned in their weapons,
except for sidearms.
   ``They just stacked their weapons in a pickup truck,'' said
Carlos Antonio Rios, a photographer for the Houston Chronicle who
had entered Panama from Costa Rica. A small crowd gathered in front
of the barracks and waved American flags during the afternoon.
   Rumors that Noriega himself was in the area were rife during the
day, but none could be confirmed. Rumors that he had been captured
were scotched by U.S. Army spokesmen. Defense Forces members said
they didn't know where Noriega was.
   Unlike in Panama City, there were only scattered incidents of
looting, local residents said, largely because members of the
Defense Forces continued to police the streets. At one point,
Defense Forces members blocked the entrance to a store and
prevented armed men from entering.
   ``If they want me to work, I'll work,'' said the Defense Forces
policeman, when asked if he would work for the newly installed
president, Guillermo Endara. ``If they don't, I won't. Whatever
they want.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>