<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0055EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama-Scene     12-25 0567</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-Scene,0587</SECOND>
<HEAD>Noriega Surfacing Brings A Joyful Christmas</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Note language in 10th graf.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RAFAEL CANDANEDO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A wave of cheers roared through the
streets of the city as Panamanians, facing a grim Christmas,
learned Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega had surfaced and was seeking
political asylum.
   Some found it hard to believe Noriega had gone to the Vatican
mission Sunday afternoon. But when the report was confirmed,
elation ruled in besieged Panama City.
   ``Now we can have Christmas,'' said one man, who grabbed a
friend and hugged him. ``I don't have a turkey in the house, we
don't even have any hamburger. All we have is a can of sardines,
but what the hell.''
   People banged pots, cheered and honked horns as they drove up
and down streets, which were barricaded and still littered and
smoldering after days of looting.
   ``The man has fallen! He is gone!'' exclaimed two young men who
said they heard the report on the radio.
   ``Attention people of Panama. Attention people of Panama,'' said
one excited radio announcer. ``There is a report that Noriega has
turned himself in. If that's true, there is a fat man that is going
to be very happy tonight.''
   He was referring to newly-installed President Guillermo Endara.
   At the Vatican embassy, a throng of people soon amassed and grew
by the minute as the sun went down over the Panama City waterfront.
   For many, the news provided a release for their hate.
   ``Let's go lynch that son of a bitch,'' yelled a group of young
men in a car.
   Another group smashed a pineapple with their shoes and cursed
``pineapple face,'' as the hated dictator was often called because
of his pockmarked face.
   The capital of 1 million had faced a bleak Christmas. Days of
looting stripped stores bare, and there was a shortage of food and
items to buy for presents.
   ``Happy holidays to the people of Panama,'' said a European
ambassador who was visiting the embassy. He asked not to be further
identified.
   ``Mission accomplished,'' said a passing cab driver. ``That
coward.''
   ``Is it true?'' a woman asked people from her balcony. She
squealed with joy when told it was.
   Although there were 26,000 U.S. military personnel in Panama
trying to find the general, an informed military source said
Noriega drove himself or was driven through the city to the embassy
in an upper class shorefront neighborhood and entered the building
alone.
   There were no U.S. troops around the two-story building and
garden that occupy half a city block when Noriega arrived at about
3 p.m.
   Since the U.S. invasion last Wednesday sent Noriega into hiding,
U.S. soldiers have surrounded the Cuban, Libyan and Nicaraguan
embassies in the belief Noriega would seek refuge in one of those
countries.
   After it was reported that Noriega was inside the Vatican
embassy, armored cars and dozens paratroopers ringed the site as a
helicopter hovered overhead. The crowd of several hundred was kept
100 yards from the site.
   Newscasters issued calls on television for people to stay inside
their homes and not take part in demonstrations because they might
get in the way of U.S. troops still looking for Noriega loyalists.
   The broadcasts reminded people that a curfew began at 6 p.m.
Although the curfew has been widely ignored, the crowd began slowly
to disperse after sunset.
</TEXT>

</DOC>