<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0134 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1859EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Obit-Blaize 1stLd-Writethru a0692 12-19 0572</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Blaize, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0692,0589</SECOND>
<HEAD>Grenada's Blaize, Staunch U.S. Ally, Dead at 71</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS throughout with new material and editing, UPDATING with
new prime minister named, other. No pickup</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE WORME</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ST. GEORGE'S, Grenada (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister Herbert Blaize, who
hailed the 1983 U.S.-led invasion of Grenada as a ``rescue
mission'' that restored democracy and who won the election that
followed, died Tuesday after a long illness. He was 71.
   Sir Paul Scoon, the British governor-general, named Deputy Prime
Minister Ben Jones to succeed Blaize until general elections are
held.
   Scoon appealed for calm and asked the nation to lend the new
prime minister their support. He noted that elections for a new
government will be held shortly, but set no date.
   Grenada, the most southerly of the Windward Islands in the
Caribbean, was due to hold general elections by March 1990, but the
vote could be advanced.
   Blaize suffered for years from prostate cancer and crippling
arthritis. He died at his official Mount Royal residence, Scoon
announced. No cause of death was stated.
   Blaize walked with the aid of a cane and received regular cancer
treatment at Walter Reed Hospital in Washington. He had become
increasingly frail and was unable to raise his voice above a
whisper at a political luncheon this month.
   He was elected prime minister on Dec. 3, 1984, in the first
election after U.S. troops, supported by a small Caribbean force,
invaded Grenada on Oct. 24-28, 1983, and ousted a Marxist military
junta that had seized power and assassinated Prime Minister Maurice
Bishop.
   The invasion was widely criticized abroad as a breach of
Grenada's sovereignty, but Blaize said it saved Grenada from a
brutal clique that placed the 100,000 residents under a 24-hour
curfew.
   ``It was God who sent the Americans and Caribbean forces to
deliver them (Grenadians),'' he said in an interview with The
Associated Press in October 1988.
   Scoon, Queen Elizabeth II's representative in the former British
colony, called the main opposition members of Parliament in for
talks Tuesday on forming a successor government.
   Blaize had clung to power despite failing health, political
bickering that cost him the party leadership, and a growing public
clamor over what many called his authoritarian style of leadership.
   Herbert Augustus Blaize, born on Feb. 26, 1918, the son of a
laborer, on the Grenadian offshore island of Carriacou, became
leader of the Grenada National Party in 1959, and headed the
government from 1962 to 1967.
   Grenada became independent from Britain in 1974.
   After the 1983 invasion, a coalition of centrist parties was
cobbled together under the banner of the New National Party to
prevent a possible election victory by Sir Eric Gairy, a populist
who was ousted as prime minister in a 1979 leftist coup.
   Gairy's former administration had been riven by charges of
corruption and repression.
   Blaize, a Reagan administration favorite, was chosen to head the
coalition because of his previous government experience.
   His popularity declined with the government's inability to
improve the economy and put a dent in Grenada's 20-percent
unemployment rate.
   Since the invasion, the United States has pumped more than $100
million into Grenada, but a widely expected foreign investment boom
never materialized and U.S. aid dropped off.
   Blaize is survived by his wife, Venetia, and their three sons
and three daughters.
   A memorial service will be held Friday at St. George's Anglican
Church, with funeral and burial Sunday in Carriacou.
</TEXT>

</DOC>