<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0733EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WeatherpageWeather 1stLd-Writethru a0480 12-18 0562</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Weatherpage Weather, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0480,0571</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nationwide Cold Snap Won't Abate</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 2 grafs to tighten; PICKS UP 3rd graf pvs, `It might
...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   It was colder in Oklahoma than in Alaska today as a deep chill
continued to grip most of the nation before winter's official
start. Snow and sleet pelted the Deep South and freezing
temperatures extended to the Gulf Coast.
   The cold snap has chilled much of nation for the past several
days, and forecasters said there was no end in sight.
   ``It might not be that unusual if it was the middle of January
... but everyone agrees this is indeed atypical,'' said weather
service meteorologist Edward Yandrich in New York. ``In layman's
terms, it's just been very, very cold.''
   Temperatures this morning were below zero in the Upper Plains,
in the teens in the Rockies and in the 20s along the Texas
Panhandle. At 3 a.m. EST it was 20 degrees in Oklahoma City and 27
and snowing in Anchorage, Alaska.
   Light snow fell Sunday afternoon in Houston, Texas, while parts
of upstate New York got 3-4 inches and snow fell in northern Maine,
the Upper Plains, parts of Iowa, Minnesota, the Dakotas and the
Rockies.
   Today, sleet or freezing rain fell in Atlanta, Charleston, S.C.,
and Macon, Ga., and snow was expected from northern Texas through
Alabama. That storm was expected to reach South Carolina late
today, and in the Washington, D.C., area by Tuesday night.
   Record low temperatures were recorded in many cities. Records
were set shortly after midnight today in Cleveland, at minus 3
degrees, and Columbus, Ohio, at minus 4; on Sunday, records fell in
at least 19 cities, including Elkins, W.Va., at minus 8, and
Paducah, Ky., and Indianapolis, minus 10.
   The National Weather Service warned of frost likely near San
Diego, Calif., tonight.
   High temperature for the Lower 48 states on Sunday was 80
degrees at Fort Myers, Fla., and Miami.
   Other reports at 3 a.m. EST today:
   _EAST: Albany, N.Y., 18 partly cloudy; Atlanta 30 sleet; Boston
21 fair; Charleston, S.C., 31 freezing rain; Chattanooga 29 partly
cloudy; Cincinnati 01 partly cloudy; Cleveland 01 fair; Detroit 01
partly cloudy; Hatteras 34 cloudy; Jacksonville 40 foggy; Key West
72 fair; Knoxville 24 cloudy; Macon 32 freezing rain; Miami 70
fair; New York 23 fair; Philadelphia 16 partly cloudy; Pittsburgh
01 fair; Portland, Maine, 04 fair; Richmond 24 cloudy; Tampa 56
rain; Washington, D.C., 18 partly cloudy.
   _CENTRAL: Denver 16 snow; Des Moines 04 cloudy; Indianapolis 00
fair; Kansas City 09 partly cloudy; Little Rock 17 fair; Nashville
19 cloudy; New Orleans 38 showery; North Platte 11 snow; Oklahoma
City 20 fair; Omaha 06 cloudy; Rapid City 08 partly cloudy; St.
Louis 09 fair; Minneapolis-St. Paul 05 fair; Sault Ste. Marie 12
snow; San Antonio 34 cloudy.
   _WEST: Albuquerque 30 cloudy; Anchorage 27 snow; Boise 22 fair;
Casper 03 snow; Fairbanks 15 cloudy; Great Falls 02 fair; Honolulu
65 fair; Las Vegas 36 fair; Los Angeles 51 fair; Medford 27 foggy;
Pendleton 27 foggy; Phoenix 46 fair; Portland, Ore., 34 cloudy;
Reno 25 fair; Salt Lake City 31 snow; San Diego 52 foggy; San
Francisco 52 cloudy; Seattle 38 cloudy; Spokane 28 cloudy.
   _INTERNATIONAL: Calgary 00 snow; Montreal 00 partly cloudy;
Ottawa 00 cloudy; Regina 21 fair; Toronto 09 fair; Winnipeg 25
fair.
</TEXT>

</DOC>