<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0090 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1715EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Romanian-Embassy 1stLd-Writethru a0590 12-26 0641</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romanian-Embassy, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0590,560</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romanian Embassy Closed, Shifting Gears to New Romanian Government</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: CORRECTS spelling of Stoichici and Vasile throughout; SUBS 2nd
graf to clarify Romania televised pictures of executed bodies, not execution;
SUBS 6th graf pvs, Splattered, to correct embassy location; INSERTS two
grafs after 9th graf pvs, ``Last evening, with comment from State Department
official, and edits 10th graf pvs, Consular officials, for transition;
SUBS last graf with two grafs to update with White House comment</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRYAN BRUMLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ambassador Ion Stoichici and a few aides
struggled to conduct diplomacy from the barricaded, egg-splattered
Romanian Embassy Tuesday, consulting with U.S. officials and
helping Romanians who want to return home.
   The embassy was closed while the staff shifted gears and
loyalties from the deposed Nicolae Ceausescu to the revolutionary
National Salvation Committee, which televised pictures of the
executed despot and his wife Tuesday morning.
   ``We have the same feelings as other Romanians,'' said
Stoichici, who declared his loyalty to the new government on
Saturday, before the outcome of the fighting was clear.
   Another embassy officer, Vasile Leca, said ``all the staff ...
fully support the National Salvation Committee. We condemn the
crimes that were done to the Romanian people by Nicolae and Elena
Ceausescu.''
   Stoichici and Leca refused to allow a reporter inside the
embassy, speaking instead through iron bars on a window in the
consular section.
   Splattered, frozen eggs coated the white brick walls of the
embassy, a turn-of-century mansion on Sheridan Circle along Embassy
Row.
   Wooden police barricades and yellow plastic tape stretched
alongside the sidewalk where scores of Romanians braved frigid
temperatures over Christmas weekend to vent their rage against a
symbol of Ceausescu's 24-year rule.
   The ambassador said his first order of business was to ``work to
improve relations with the United States,'' which had grown
increasingly critical of Ceausescu's human rights policies.
   ``Last evening, the State Department informed us that they
recognized the staff of the Romanian Embassy'' as the
representative of the new government, said the ambassador. He said
he was in telephone contact with State Department officials.
   A State Department official said no meetings were scheduled
between Stoichici and American diplomats, ``but we remain in
contact with them as much as we can.''
   ``They are in telephone contact with us, but when we call them,
they don't answer,'' said the source, who spoke on condition of
anonymity. Press calls to the embassy were not answered, either.
   Romanian consular officials were also accepting, through the
barred window, visa applications from Romanian-Americans who wanted
to return home.
   ``I want to go back to help the people who are suffering. I
would like to offer blood, money, anything I can,'' said Ilie
Aurelian, a Romanian emigre artist who lives in Springfield, Va.
His wife is part of Romania's Hungarian minority and subject to
official persecution under Ceausescu. They emigrated from Romania
five years ago.
   Ioan Buburuzan, 38, a taxi driver and artist from Brooklyn,
N.Y., was also at the embassy seeking a visa to visit his father in
the village of Turdaa, in the Klug region of Romania. He emigrated
eight years ago.
   Buburuzan said his only regret is that Ceausescu and his wife
had been executed so quickly.
   ``I wish they had put him on trial. That would have given the
people a chance to see his crimes. And some of the evidence might
have been embarassing to people who are still in power now,'' said
Buburuzan.
   Aurelian disagreed, saying it was necessary to kill Ceausescu to
prevent security forces from rescuing him and restoring him to
power.
   ``So now the killing has stopped. That is good,'' said Aurelian.
   U.S. officials also regretted the secret trial.
   ``We would have preferred it if there had been a public trial,''
White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>