<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0033EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Panama 10thLd-Writethru a0869 12-25 1183</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Panama, 10th Ld-Writethru, a0869,1100</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Says Noriega Asylum Request Ends `Reign of Terror'</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 11th graf pvs bgng, `The Italian,' to UPDATE
with comment from Noriega's lawyer</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRYAN BRUMLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush welcomed news that Gen. Manuel
Antonio Noriega had sought asylum at the Vatican mission in Panama
City, declaring on Christmas Eve that the deposed dictator's
``reign of terror is over.''
   White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said top Bush
administration deputies were meeting into the night at the White
House ``considering an appropriate course of action for bringing
him to justice.''
   U.S. military officers, meanwhile, hoped Noriega's action would
``take the spirit to resist'' out of loyalists still fighting in
Panama, said a Pentagon spokesman, Col. Miguel Monteverde. He said
it was not clear whether the development would hasten the
withdrawal of U.S. troops.
   Under international law, diplomatic missions are safe havens for
those seeking asylum and Noriega is not the only prominent figure
to take advantage of this convention. Since June, Chinese dissident
Fang Lizhi has kept Chinese authorities at bay by taking refuge in
the U.S. Embassy in Beijing.
   While Fitzwater said the administration wants to bring Noriega
to justice, he declined to say whether that would involve a U.S.
effort to gain custody of the general, who is under indictment in
the United States on drug trafficking charges.
   Sen. Jesse Helms, R-N.C., said White House chief of staff John
Sununu told him ``strenuous negotiations'' with the Vatican were
ongoing.
   U.S. officials are ``pointing out that (Noriega) is not there
for political reasons, he is, as Sununu told me, a common
criminal,'' Helms told The Associated Press.
   ``I asked him if the prospects look good and he says they don't
look bad, because the church realizes how the people feel in
Panama,'' Helms said.
   Helms said ``sources in Panama say that he (Noriega) probably
went in with the escort of a diplomat. He is seeking to be
permitted to leave and go to one of two or three counties,
including Cuba.''
   Earlier, Defense Secretary Dick Cheney had said it was uncertain
whether the United States would seek to try Noriega or whether the
new government in Panama would deal with him.
   The Italian news agency ANSA quoted the papal nuncio in Panama
City, Monsignor Sebastiano Laboa, as indicating he would not hand
over Noriega to the United States or the U.S.-installed government
in Panama.
   Noriega's lawyer in Miami, Raymond Takiff, said Sunday that
Noriega's action surprised him: ``I was sure he'd die in Panama.''
   U.S. inability to capture Noriega had become a sore point for
the administration, which earlier Sunday fended off criticism that
civil order in Panama was being undermined by his continued freedom.
   Bush was at the presidential retreat at Camp David when he got
word Sunday afternoon of Noriega's request for asylum at the
Vatican mission. In Washington, press secretary Marlin Fitzwater
said on behalf of Bush: ``We have been notified by the papal nuncio
in Panama City that General Noriega has turned himself in at their
embassy.''
   ``I am pleased that the general is now under the control of
diplomatic authorities. His reign of terror is over,'' said the
statement. ``As we work to help return law and order to Panama
City, and as the government of President (Guillermo) Endara begins
its work, the demise of General Noriega sends a strong signal that
freedom and democracy in Panama are on the rise.''
   Earlier Sunday, Bush had traveled to the Pentagon for a briefing
on Panama developments, and he dispatched Defense Secretary Dick
Cheney to Panama City just hours before Noriega's asylum bid was
disclosed.
   Archbishop Marcos McGrath of Panama City, asked by CBS-TV why
Noriega went to the Vatican mission, said, ``Apparently he decided
that the moment had come to end his resistance. And he made
contacts by telephone and drove in a private car and walked into
the Papal Nuncio's residence and thereby entered into an area of
diplomatic immunity.''
   ``Apparently he went in alone and he would be out of the area of
arrest either by the Panamanian government authorities or any
action of the U.S. military,'' the Roman Catholic archbishop said.
   Under diplomatic tradition, Noriega is safe from arrest as long
as he remains inside the diplomatic mission, or until agreement is
reached on terms for him to leave the area of immunity.
   At the State Department's Panama Task Force, Richard Sanders
said administration officials had not decided whether to take steps
to bring Noriega to the United States.
   Putting Noriega on trial poses risks to the United States.
Noriega formerly had an association with the Central Intelligence
Agency and might be in a position to disclose embarrassing details
of that relationship. In defending himself for trial, he could seek
to use classified documents in his defense.
   U.S. military officials had anticipated that Noriega might seek
diplomatic sanctuary, and on Thursday troops were sent to ring the
Panama City embassies of Nicaragua and Cuba.
   Top administration officials discussed the Panama invasion on
television interview shows Sunday, acknowledging that the 24,000
U.S. soldiers now there ``still have a lot of work to do'' to
restore order.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III and Cheney defended the
administration against criticism it had not acted quickly enough to
quell looting in Panama City after U.S. troops invaded early
Wednesday.
   U.S. forces initially concentrated on military targets, but are
now working more with Endara's government to restore order, Cheney
said on ABC's ``This Week with David Brinkley.''
   ``The looting is dying out,'' said Cheney. He acknowledged that
some pro-Noriega paramilitary forces, known as ``Dignity
Battalions,'' were ``running loose in the streets, but the
situation appears to be steadily improving.''
   ``It's not all over yet,'' he said. ``We still have a lot of
work to do, but clearly we are in better shape today than at any
point since the effort started.''
   In a broadcast to U.S. Armed Forces around the world, Bush said
America ``has the strength to confront tyranny when we must. Gen.
Noriega is the latest to learn that lesson.''
   Bush told reporters outside the Pentagon that ``the emphasis now
is on cleaning up the last parts of resistance, seeing that
civilian government take over, (restoring) tranquility in the city
and then moving on food and medicine.''
   Baker, appearing on the NBC-TV program ``Meet the Press,''
reiterated the administration position that the U.S. troops will
remain in Panama ``as long as it takes to get the job done.''
   The Pentagon's casualty figures stood at 24 U.S. servicemen
killed in action, 284 wounded, and two civilian dependents killed.
Earlier, Pentagon officials had said 25 U.S. servicemen died, but
later reported that they had been counting one death twice.
   Casualties for the Panamanian Defense Forces were 154 killed,
113 wounded and 2,969 captured, the Pentagon reported.
Additionally, about 18,000 weapons had been captured.
   Official tallies of Panamanian civilian casualties were
unavailable, but the Air Force said a C-5 cargo plane loaded with
medical supplies was sent from South Carolina to help treat injured
civilians.
</TEXT>

</DOC>