<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0352EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-JobSeekers     12-30 0565</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Job Seekers,0585</SECOND>
<HEAD>Call-In Survey Reveals Insecurity Over Jobs</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CLIFF EDWARDS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Workers feel insecure about their jobs and worry
about layoffs in 1990, an informal call-in survey found, and an
economic forecaster called it ``a very reasonable fear.''
   About 600 of the 1,100 people who phoned in during a one-day
survey were employed and 44 percent of them felt 1990 would bring
significant changes for them in the workplace, said the survey's
sponsor, Challenger, Gray &amp; Christmas, an international
job-counseling firm.
   Workers calling from as far away as Los Angeles, Detroit, Boston
and Philadelphia said they worried about losing jobs to hostile
takeovers, economic decline and cutbacks and foreign competition,
Challenger said.
   ``People are worried that the security they once had ... is no
longer there,'' John Challenger, sales and marketing director for
the Chicago-based company, said Friday.
   The survey, conducted Thursday, is unscientific because it
reflects only the views of people who called in, rather than a
random sampling of the population.
   An economist at the WEFA Group, a consulting firm in Bala
Cynwyd, Pa., said the survey's results could be expected.
   ``It's a very reasonable fear,'' said John Hagens, who
specializes in short-term economic forecasting. ``There will be
more cuts in 1990 and fewer new hires than we've had in '89 and '88
and '87.''
   ``For the first time in many years, the national unemployment
rate will rise,'' Hagens predicted in a telephone interview.
   The adjusted national unemployment rate stood at 5.4 percent in
November.
   Layoffs and early retirement plans in blue-chip companies like
American Telephone &amp; Telegraph Co. and International Business
Machines Corp. and throughout the computer and automobile
industries are signals that growth in employment is slowing, Hagens
said.
   He predicted employment growth in 1990 will be only 1.5 percent,
about half the 1989 rate.
   Challenger, with 16 offices in the United States and Europe,
counsels people who have been fired and referred by their former
companies. Each year during the week after Christmas, the firm
advertises its telephone number and opens phone lines to counsel
individuals for free.
   The survey results are compiled from information the firm
collects during the call-in.
   The majority, 59 percent, of the working callers to the survey
were under 40 and earned an average of $30,000 to $50,000, said
James Challenger, John's father and president of the company.
   About 58 percent of the workers also indicated they would be
willing to leave their city to find new work, which shows Americans
learned to enlarge the scope of their job search during the last
recession, James Challenger said.
   Unemployed workers who called, 76 percent of whom were 30 or
older, worried they won't be able to find jobs quickly in 1990 and
sought tips on job hunting and interviewing, said Ann Marks, a
consultant at the company.
   ``You hear real worry from people,'' Ms. Marks said. ``It's
tough to be out of work any time, but especially during the holiday
season.''
   The average time a person went unemployed in 1989 was 3.2
months, she said, but 85 percent to 90 percent found equal or
better paying jobs.
   Workers who find themselves unemployed in 1990 need to be
extremely aggressive in the narrowing and highly competitive job
market, Ms. Marks said.
   ``You've got to get plugging, go out and see the employers and
call if they don't,'' she said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>