<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 0026EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NYTimesAppointment     12-31 0307</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-NY Times Appointment,0318</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lelyveld Succeeds Gelb As Times Managing Editor</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Joseph Lelyveld has been named managing editor
of The New York Times, replacing Arthur Gelb, who is retiring, the
newspaper announced Saturday.
   Lelyveld was promoted from foreign editor to deputy managing
editor in July in anticipation of succeeding Gelb.
   Gelb, 65, will retire Sunday and become executive vice president
of The New York Times Company Foundation, according to the
announcement by Arthur Ochs Sulzberger, chairman of the Times
Company and publisher of the newspaper.
   As managing editor, Lelyveld, 52, will be the main deputy to the
newspaper's executive editor, Max Frankel.
   Lelyveld started at the newspaper in 1962 as a copy boy and has
reported from New York, Washington, the Congo, India, Hong Kong,
Britain and South Africa. He won the Pulitzer Prize in 1986 for his
book about South Africa, ``Move Your Shadow.''
   A graduate of Harvard University and the Columbia Graduate
School of Journalism, Lelyveld has been a national correspondent
for The Times Magazine and deputy foreign editor from 1977 to 1980.
He became foreign editor in December 1986.
   Gelb worked 45 years at the Times, including as a reporter,
critic, news editor and metropolitan editor.
   As a theater critic, he was among the first to recognize talents
such as Barbra Streisand, Colleen Dewhurst, Woody Allen, Lenny
Bruce and Dick Gregory.
   In his new position, Gelb will work with the foundation's
president, Fred M. Hechinger, and will succeed Hechinger when he
retires in September. The foundation supports charitable,
educational, cultural, journalistic and environmental programs.
   The Times also announced that Carolyn Lee, 44, was appointed an
assistant managing editor. She will succeed Warren Hoge as
administrator of the 1,000-member news staff, with responsibility
for personnel and business affairs.
   Hoge, also an assistant managing editor, will supervise news and
feature coverage.
</TEXT>

</DOC>