<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0516EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-China-US     12-18 0498</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-China-US,0512</SECOND>
<HEAD>China, U.S. Hold Talks On Resuming Fulbrights</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHY WILHELM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   China and the United States said today they have
opened talks on resuming the Fulbright scholar exchange program, a
victim of the chill in relations after China's crackdown on
pro-democracy demonstrators.
   China's State Education Commission and the U.S. Embassy said
their representatives met for the first time last week _ just days
after U.S. National Security Adviser Brent Scowcroft's
fence-mending visit to Beijing.
   Neither side linked the talks to Scowcroft's visit, but embassy
spokesman Ed Loo acknowledged, ``There wasn't much going on
before.''
   He said the United States had been seeking a renewal of the
government-sponsored Fulbright program ``for some time.''
   China announced this fall that it was halting the program for a
year, apparently because of anger over U.S. condemnation of its
June army attack on students protesting for democratic reform. It
also canceled plans to accept Peace Corps volunteers.
   In other signs of a warming between the two countries since
Scowcroft visited with Undersecretary of State Lawrence
Eagleburger, China has indicated it is open to a negotiated
settlement for Fang Lizhi, the Chinese dissident who took refuge in
the U.S. Embassy.
   It has also said it will allow the U.S. government radio
station, the Voice of America, to send a new bureau chief to
Beijing. China expelled the former bureau chief, Al Pessin, in
June, accusing him of distorting facts and violating martial law
imposed during the protests.
   Reception of VOA Chinese-language broadcasts also has become
much clearer in the past week, although it is not clear if the
Chinese have halted all jamming. English-language broadcasts have
not been jammed.
   An official in the International Department of the State
Education Commission, who did not give his name, said China has not
yet decided if it will resume Fulbright exchanges. He refused to
say if China wants to change the terms of the program.
   ``We are talking about both sides' plans and conceptions,'' he
said. ``We originally halted it for a year, 1989 to 1990. Now we
are talking about restoring it for 1990-91.''
   Under the program, which exchanges American and foreign scholars
worldwide, two dozen American scholars lecture at Chinese
universities and a dozen Chinese scholars and a dozen students
visit the United States for research and studies. China has taken
part in the Fulbright program since shortly after U.S.-Chinese
relations were established in 1979.
   Scowcroft's visit has been criticized by some congressmen and
commentators in the United States as coming too soon after China's
bloody crackdown, in which hundreds of unarmed civilians were
killed.
   The Bush administration had halted all high-level visits in June
and imposed several other sanctions, including halting military
sales.
   However, it vetoed legislation that would have expanded the
sanctions and required the president to report to Congress before
lifting them. The administration has argued that Bush's softer
approach and his sending of Scowcroft will encourage China to
improve its human rights performance.
</TEXT>

</DOC>