<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 1257EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MerryMulch     12-23 0490</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Merry Mulch,0506</SECOND>
<HEAD>State Program Pushes Christmas Tree Recycling</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: This story was scheduled for Monday AMs in the FYI Planner.
It is being switched with the Montpelier-dated judicial retirement story,
which will move for Monday instead of Sunday.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL TIGHE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MONTPELIER, Vt. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After their time under lights, Christmas
trees in Vermont are being put out to pasture, and on the garden
and around the shrubs on the front lawn.
   More than 8,000 trees were ground up into bits of bark and
needles during last year's ``Merry Mulch'' project, and officials
say the practice is catching on nationwide as a way to save
landfill space.
   ``It's definitely an idea that's spreading,'' said Kate
Finley-Woodruff, marketing representative for the Vermont
Department of Agriculture.
   The statewide program was started last year as an experiment by
her department and the state's Agency of Natural Resources to
encourage recycling.
   ``We were overwhelmed by the response,'' Finley-Woodruff said.
   Queries have come in from around the country about the program,
while some communities already turn Christmas trees into wood chips.
   For a second year, sanitation workers in Chicago will collect
discarded trees for mulch. Indianapolis has been mulching trees
since it canceled its Christmas tree bonfire on ``Twelth Night'' a
few years ago.
   In Vermont, the state increased the number of drop-off and
chipping sites from nine to 33 this year. Residents who want to can
take their mulch home.
   The state is getting help for ``Merry Mulch'' from several
municipalities, electric utilities, ice cream maker Ben &amp; Jerry's
Homemade Inc. and regional solid waste managers and planners.
   Finley-Woodruff said the program developed from the problem of
solid-waste at landfills and a desire to help Vermont's Christmas
tree growers.
   ``We're trying to protect their market so people don't get
discouraged from buying a real Christmas tree because of the
landfill problems,'' she said.
   Nationwide, 34.3 million Christmas trees were sold last year and
the U.S. Agriculture Department expects sales to exceed 35 million
this year. Artificial trees were introduced in the 1950s and by
1985 held 47 percent of the market.
   Pam Dwyer, executive secretary of the New Hampshire-Vermont
Christmas Tree Association, said the state may be scaring people
into buying artificial trees.
   ``I don't have a problem with `Merry Mulch','' Dwyer said. ``But
I think it leads people to believe that Christmas trees are a solid
waste problem.''
   It takes a Christmas tree about 30 years to decompose in a
landfill, according to the American Christmas Tree Journal. An
artificial tree contains petroleum products and may never
decompose, Dwyer said.
   ``We've tried to push the idea that Christmas trees are a
renewable source,'' Dwyer said. ``I'm a forester's wife and I'm not
convinced that wood products are a solid waste problem.''
   As for her tree, Dwyer said she laces it with bread and puts it
in the yard for the birds when the family is finished with it.
</TEXT>

</DOC>