<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0339EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w BC-SuperfundList     12-20 0672</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Superfund List,620</SECOND>
<HEAD>With PM-Superfund</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are details of the nine Superfund
cleanups announced by the Environmental Protection Agency.
   _The F.T. Rose Disposal Pit in Lanesborough, Mass., contaminated
by polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs) and various volatile organic
compounds. The General Electric Co., the only known generator of
the contaminants, agreed to pay for a thermal cleanup process in
which the hazardous materials will be extracted through
evaporation, then incinerated. The process is estimated to cost the
company $6.45 million. In addition, GE will reimburse the
government $494,000 for costs already incurred.
   _The Old Springfield Landfill, Springfield, Vt., operated as a
27-acre garbage and industrial waste dump from 1948 to 1968, and
upon which a mobile home park was built in 1970. Park residents, of
whom few remain, complained of bad odors in their well water, and
EPA investigators found it contamined with organic compounds.
Browning-Ferris Industries of Vermont, Inc., Emhart Industries,
Inc., Textron, Inc., and the town of Springfield will share costs,
estimated at $5.4 million, for a groundwater extraction and
treatment system, and will repay the EPA $1.75 million for past
costs.
   _The Yaworski Lagoon at Canterbury, Conn., where industrial
wastes including solvents, paints, textile dyes, acid and resins
were dumped between 1950 and 1973. Pervel Industries, Revere
Textile Prints, InterRoyal Corp., Triangle PWC, Inc., the Rogers
Corp., Kaman Aerospace Corp., and C &amp; M Corp. will share the
estimated $3.4 million costs for surface cleanup and a cap and
diking system, and will repay the government $2.25 million.
   _Reich Farm, a three-acre disposal site in Dover Township, N.J.,
where approximately 4,500 drums containing industrial waste from
Union Carbide's Bound Brook plant were dumped. Union Carbide will
pay an estimated $5.8 million to extract contaminated groundwater
and excavate and treat contaminated soil, and will repay $1.67
million to the government.
   _Limestone Road site, an industrial dump about 2.5 miles west of
Cumberland, Md., where contamination by chromium, cadmium, lead and
organic solvents threatens area groundwater. Fairchild Industries
and the Cumberland Cement and Supply Co. will pay an estimated $3
million to grade the site, cap the contaminated soil and fence off
the area. The EPA and the state of Maryland, meanwhile, reserve the
right to pursue additional remedies if groundwater contamination is
found.
   _Miami County Incinerator, in Troy, Ohio, and just 1500 feet
west of the Great Miami River, where non-cumbustible solid wastes
were landfilled and where industrial liquid wastes were dumped into
an unlined pit from 1968 through the mid-1970s. A large number of
chemical contaminants, included 30 probable or possible
cancer-causing agents, have been detected at the site. Nearly 50
companies and 22 local governments will share the cost of a $20
million cleanup, including construction of an alternate water
supply for well-water users in the area.
   _The Pristine, Inc., site at Reading, Ohio, a Cincinnati suburb,
where liquid wastes including pesticides, PCBs, acids and solvents
were dumped from November 1974 to September 1981. A total of 111
companies, including Eli Lilly, General Electric, IBM, Monsanto,
Union Carbide and Westinghouse entered into the settlement.
Thirty-eight will share a $13.5 million cleanup program involving
incineration of the top foot of soil, extraction of contaminated
groundwater, and demolition of on-site structures. All 111 firms
will share payments to the government of nearly $5 million.
   _Dutchtown Oil Treatment Facility, in Dutchtown, La., a
five-acre site operated from 1965 to 1982 as a waste oil refinery,
and where hazardous wastes were dumped in to unlined pits.
Twenty-one firms, including Bethlehem Steel, Exxon Corp., Mobil
Oil, and Kaiser Aluminum will share a $6 million cleanup involving
incineration of sludges, excavation and treatment of the soil, and
backfilling the pits.
   _Lawrence Todtz site in Camanche, Iowa, where the Du Pont Co.
dumped an estimated 4,300 tons of cellophane processing wastes at a
2.7-acre impoundment between 1971 and 1975. The EPA said it found
groundwater at the site contaminated by arsenic, lead, benzene and
other chemicals. Du Pont agreed to a $5.9 million cleanup, and will
reimburse the government $450,000 for past costs.
</TEXT>

</DOC>