<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0193 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1216EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f PM-BusinessMirror Adv29   12-28 0599</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Business Mirror, Adv 29,0622</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv29</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release PMs Friday, Dec. 29</HEAD>
<HEAD>Legacy of The Reagan Years</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN CUNNIFF</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Analyst</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Grand economic hopes often disappear under a
mountain of emergencies, but some of the broader plans of the
Reagan administration held up remarkably well.
   Failures were big, such as budget deficits and negative trade
balances, and an inability to show statistically that Federal
spending had indeed been reduced as a percentage of gross national
product.
   Important parts of the vision were maintained, however, and the
impact of some of them can be seen in domestic and world politics
and economics, perhaps even in the overthrow of communist regimes.
   One of the primary aims of the administration was to bring
inflation and interest rates down by freeing the economy from
regulatory controls, restraining the money supply and lowering
spending.
   Such action was needed in order for other plans to work. In
December 1980, the prime rate had reached a record 21.5 percent and
three-month Treasury bills had doubled in yield in a matter of
months.
   Better control of the money supply, thanks to Federal Reserve
cooperation, helped reverse the climb in rates. An immediate tax
cut not only stimulated economic activity but helped take inflation
down from double-digit levels.
   The Economic Report of the President, sent to Congress in
February 1982, expressed the broad hopes. ``A critical element in
this outlook is the assumption that inflationary expectations will
continue to recede,'' it said.
   If the process continued as expected, the report stated,
``market rates of interest will decline significantly, wage demands
will continue to moderate, and the pro-inflationary biases ... will
quickly disappear.''
   They did, and the impact continues today.
   However, a far greater impact of the Reagan plan for the decade
can be traced to the report's section on government and the
economy. It had domestic and international ramifications.
   The section begins with this preamble:
   _``All nations which have broad-based representative government
and civil liberties have most of their economic activity organized
by the market.
   _``Economic conditions in market economies are generally
superior to those in nations (with a comparable culture and a
comparable resource base) in which the government has the dominant
economic role.''
   A major objective of the Reagan economic program, therefore, was:
   ``... to reduce the Federal government's role in economic
decision-making while strengthening the economic role of
individuals, private organizations and state and local
governments.''
   That objective, the report stated, emanated from a belief that:
   ``... the politicization of price decisions _ whether of wages,
commodities, or interest rates _ tends to reduce both the breadth
of popular support for the government and the efficiency of the
economy.''
   Nations all over the world, large and small, socialist,
capitalist and mixed, took their cue from the United States,
developing the concept of privatization, or turning over
governmental functions to the private sector.
   In every instance the goal was the same, to achieve economic
efficiency _ a higher level of responsiveness to individual and
collective needs _ by drawing on the creative self-interest of
private individuals and institutions.
   The revolution was smoothly accomplished in mostly capitalist
nations, sometimes convulsively in socialist economies, but to some
degree it occurred almost everywhere.
   Historians eventually will unravel the reasons for the
economic-political upheavals in the late 1980s, but even now they
can follow one fine thread to that 1982 economic report.
   It was written by Chairman Murray L. Weidenbaum and members
Jerry L. Jordan and William A. Niskanen, and transmitted to
Congress on February 6, 1982.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv PMs Friday, Dec. 29.</NOTE>

</DOC>