<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0096 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1514EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SAfrica-Exams     12-28 0497</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SAfrica-Exams,0510</SECOND>
<HEAD>Black High School Seniors Suffer Highest Failure Rate Since 1962</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID CRARY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Only 42 percent of South
Africa's black high school seniors passed their final exams, the
lowest rate since 1962, and only one of 190,081 youths who took the
tests got an ``A'' average, the government said Thursday.
   Bernhard Louw, director-general of the Department of Education
and Training, described the results as ``unsatisfactory.'' Among
the causes, he said, were a rapid growth in the number of black
pupils and the lingering effects of classroom boycotts that were
widespread during nationwide political unrest in 1984-86.
   A total of 74,249 black students passed the exams last month,
including 17,553 who did well enough to qualify for automatic
admission to universities, Louw said. Last year, 54 percent of
170,966 black exam takers passed, including 27,865 who qualified
for university admission, and in 1987 the overall pass rate was
56.3.
   The most recent year with a lower pass rate was 1962, when only
910 black students took the exams and 60 percent failed.
   Nationwide exam results for South Africa's three other official
race groups _ white, Indian and mixed-race _ have not yet been
released. But in Transvaal, the most populous province, 96.9
percent of the white students and 72.7 of the mixed-race students
passed the exams.
   Louw said one reason for the poor results at black schools was a
new grading policy aimed at ensuring that students from all race
groups were graded by identical standards. In the past, Louw said,
officials overseeing black education set their own grading
regulations.
   ``In view of the drastic effect'' of this policy, Louw said, the
government has ordered an urgent ``in-depth analysis of the
examination results.''
   Louw said several other factors contributed to the poor test
results, including an average annual increase in school enrollment
of 13 percent in recent years.
   Many teachers and administrators lack the experience to deal
effectively ``with the problems flowing from the provision of
education to such a large number of pupils, often under very
difficult conditions,'' he said.
   He said a period of relative tranquility at schools in recent
months ``was not enough to compensate for losses in groundwork
suffered over a period of years when severe disruption of the
education system occurred.''
   Past disruptions led to particularly bad results on math and
science exams, he said.
   Louw said was encouraged by recent appeals from black leaders
for youths to rededicate themselves to education.
   Among those making such calls was Walter Sisulu, a senior leader
of the outlawed African National Congress guerrilla movement who
was freed in October after 26 years in prison.
   ``Our young people must continue to participate in the struggle
for liberation,'' Sisulu said in a message to a black education
conference last month. ``But, at the same time, it is also very
important we learn to read and write so that we equip ourselves for
the South Africa of tommorrow.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>