<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0091 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1301EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-CampaignFunds Bjt   12-29 0868</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Campaign Funds, Bjt,770</SECOND>
<HEAD>Door Still Open for Senior Lawmakers to Pocket Campaign Funds on
Retiring</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE ROBINSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The much-criticized custom in which senior
members of Congress may pocket leftover campaign funds when they
retire or suffer defeat at the polls is targeted for repeal under
newly minted ethics legislation.
   But this wouldn't take effect until 1993 as lawmakers are
reluctant to slam the door too quickly. Thus, they are giving
themselves a chance to run for one more term and then retire with
the funds.
   ``I think there are some members who will take advantage of
it,'' says Rep. Al Swift, D-Wash., an advocate of abolishing the
practice. `` ... But I don't think you're talking about a massive
movement. I would be surprised if it were more than you could count
on one hand.''
   ``I have something in the vicinity of 200 grand in my campaign
fund and I have no intention whatever of retiring,'' he says.
   Under a bill approved before Congress adjourned for the
holidays, lawmakers raised their pay from the current level $89,500
for both houses to $96,600 for House members next year and $124,400
in 1991. Senate pay would rise to $98,400 in 1990 and $101,400 the
year thereafter.
   To propel the politically touchy pay package, lawmakers attached
an array of ethics features, including repeal in 1993 of the right
of departing senior House members to convert leftover campaign
funds to their personal use.
   Federal law already had barred defeated or retiring members of
Congress from carting off surplus political money. But that
prohibition contained a gaping loophole, a ``grandfather clause''
that exempted lawmakers who were on Capitol Hill before 1980.
   The pay and ethics package, already signed into law by President
Bush, would repeal the ``grandfather clause.'' But it would take
three years to do so, thus providing maneuvering room to lawmakers
who are planning a retirement and counting on a comfortable nest
egg of campaign cash.
   Lawmakers whose right to convert surplus funds had been
``grandfathered in,'' now can take the money only if they retire
before the start of the 103rd Congress in January 1993.
   ``This is a very major step,'' says Susan Manes, vice president
for issues of Common Cause, the citizens lobby. ``For too long the
grandfather clause has allowed certain members of Congress to take
their political money with them when they leave.''
   ``In effect, this allowed special interests to channel money to
sitting members of Congress, which they in turn can use when they
retire,'' she said.
   The measure also limits the amount they may take with them to
the balance in their campaign fund as of the date of enactment,
Nov. 30.
   It applies to senators as well as House members. But the Senate
already had a rule barring members, retiring or otherwise, from
converting campaign funds. It might be difficult to enforce the
rule against a former lawmaker, but the Senate Ethics Committee
says it has never known one to violate it.
   House members have not been bashful about converting the funds.
A January 1988 study by Congressional Quarterly said
``grandfathered'' lawmakers had converted at least $862,000 since
1980. The Ralph Nader group Congress Watch estimated that the total
potential ``hidden pension'' accumulated by these lawmakers totaled
$39 million.
   The Capitol Hill newspaper Roll Call in October counted 186
sitting lawmakers covered by the grandfather clause, including some
seniority-heavy powers in the House with huge cash reserves in
their funds. Rep. Stephen Solarz, D-N.Y., and House Ways and Means
Committee Chairman Dan Rostenkowski, D-Ill., were first and second
respectively, both topping $1 million.
   House Speaker Thomas Foley, D-Wash., had $639,513.
   Stories of lawmakers who have departed with campaign cash in
hand abound in the House. Former Rep. Gene Taylor, D-Mo., in what
some call the largest conversion in memory, disbursed $345,000 to
himself from his campaign fund early this year.
   And Rep. John J. Duncan, R-Tenn., died of cancer in June 1988,
bequeathing his $604,521 campaign fund to his wife and four
children.
   After voters rejected former Banking Committee Chairman Fernand
J. St Germain, D-R.I., last November, he told reporters he probably
would use his leftover campaign dollars ``for charitable and
political purposes.''
   Thus far, the largest outlay has been $67,500 to the Washington
law firm of Arent, Fox, Kintner, Plotkin &amp; Kahn, which represented
him over the last few years while his dealings with savings and
loan and other lobbyists were under investigation at the Justice
Department.
   ``They were legal fees for the overall inquiries,'' says the
silver-haired, 61-year-old Democrat whom the department eventually
declined to prosecute. He is now practicing law and doing a ``very
little'' lobbying.
   Actually, St Germain's action might just remain legal after the
grandfather clause is repealed once and for all. The House
Committee on Standards of Official Conduct has ruled more than once
that paying lawyers to keep congressmen out of jail is a legitimate
political expense.
   Reached at his Washington office recently, St Germain indicated
that the issue was less than fascinating to him. ``Frankly,'' he
said, ``I'm not in Congress anymore, I'm busy in other areas and I
leave these questions to sitting members of Congress.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>