<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0130 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1828EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Britain-Rushdie     12-19 0562</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Rushdie,0579</SECOND>
<HEAD>Britain Deporting Iranians Who Say They Are Rushdie Suspects</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Britain said Tuesday it would deport two Iranian
students. Their lawyer said they said were suspected of plotting to
kill Salman Rushdie, author of ``The Satanic Verses.''
   Two other Iranians arrested the same day were freed. One, a
40-year-old man who has four children and suffers from multiple
sclerosis, said he was accused in hours of police questioning of
being a terrorist.
   The four were arrested Friday at their homes in Manchester under
the Prevention of Terrorism Act, which gives police the right to
hold them for seven days without charges.
   The Home Office said in a statement Tuesday night that
engineering students Karen Abrinia, 32, and Mehrdad Kokabi, 33,
would be sent to Iran ``as soon as possible.'' It said they were
being deported ``for reasons of national security,'' but did not
elaborate.
   Another student, Hussein Gharibi, and Javad Mousavi, 40, the
disabled father of four, were freed. Gharibi's age was not
available.
   Attorney Zahir Aziz, who represents the four Iranians, said
Monday: ``The police have told me very little, but the men are
under the impression they have been arrested because they are
suspected of being a hit squad to kill Salman Rushdie.''
   The Indian-born British novelist was condemned to death Feb. 14
by the late Iranian leader Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini, who accused
him of blaspheming Islam in his novel. He has been in hiding since,
under police protection.
   Britain and Iran have taken tentative steps toward renewing
diplomatic relations, severed over the Rushdie affair, but the
latest arrests jeopardize that process.
   Mousavi said after his release Tuesday night that accused him of
masterminding a plot to kill Rushdie.
   ``I don't know how to make bombs,'' he said in the living room
of his Manchester home, his wheelchair nearby. ``They accused me of
plotting to kill Salman Rushdie, but I told them I was innocent.''
   ``I am against terrorism,'' Mousavi said. ``I am in favor of
Salman Rushdie being punished, but not by me. He should be punished
by Islamic law and Islamic courts.''
   He said police questioned him three hours a day for five days.
   ``A police lady was very nice,'' he sad, ``but then a
superintendent was very bad. He told me: `You are a terrorist.' I
said how could I be a terrorist? I am a disabled man. They said I
could be a mastermind telling the others how to make bombs.''
   Iran's official Islamic Republic News Agency on Monday quoted
the newspaper Kayhan on Monday as saying the arrests followed
anti-Rushdie demonstrations by Moslems at more than 1,000 mosques
in Britain.
   Tehran radio said Parliament speaker Mahdi Karrubi read a letter
Tuesday from several members urging the Foreign Ministry to take
``appropriate'' steps to protect the four Iranians.
   It quoted the letter as saying the Iranians were arrested
because ``the glory and size of the demonstrations had angered
British authorities.''
   ``If England does not change its hostile stance against Islam
and does not apologize to Moslems, the wave of these demonstrations
in England will surely increase,'' the radio quoted Karrubi as
saying.
   Patrick Stephenson, registrar at the University of Manchester
Institute of Science and Technology, said Kokabi and Abrinia were
engineering students who had completed their course work for
doctorates and were writing dissertations. It was not known where
Gharibi studies.
</TEXT>

</DOC>