<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0105 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1852EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WeatherpageWeather     12-26 0288</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0296</SECOND>
<HEAD>Snow Squalls From New Cold Wave</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A new mass of cold air moved across the lower Great Lakes on
Tuesday with snow, wind and dropping temperatures.
   The surge of cold air and wind was expected to produce wind
chill effects of from 20 below to 35 below zero during the night
over central New England.
   Snow fell across northern New England, over much of inland New
York state, northeastern and western Pennsylvania, northeastern
Ohio, eastern West Virginia, western Virginia, northwestern North
Carolina, northern Indiana, lower Michigan, northeastern Wisconsin,
eastern North Dakota, western and south-central Minnesota, and
north-central Iowa.
   The heaviest snowfall during the six hours up to noon was 4
inches at Watertown, N.Y.
   For the first time in more than a week, the National Weather
Service did not report any record low temperatures. And the
temperature reached 33 degrees at the New Castle County Airport
near Wilmington, Del., the first time the temperature there had
been above freezing since the evening of Dec. 15.
   There was dense fog in some valleys of the West early Tuesday.
   Heavy fog over Puget Sound delayed takeoffs and landings at
Sea-Tac Airport, which serves Seattle and Tacoma. Airport officials
could not say immediately how many flights were diverted.
   Heavy fog at Salt Lake City had flights running about 2{ hours
behind schedule during the night, with some incoming flights
diverted to Idaho Falls, Idaho, and Las Vegas, Nev.
   Tuesday's low for the Lower 48 states was 21 degrees below zero
at International Falls, Minn.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EST ranged from 5
degrees below zero at Sault Ste. Marie, Mich., to 76 at Bergstrom
Air Force Base at Austin, Texas.
</TEXT>

</DOC>