<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0282 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1800EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-FedPolicy     12-22 0472</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fed Policy,0486</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fed Remained Open To Lower Interest Rates</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN D. McCLAIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Federal Reserve policy makers decided not to
change monetary policy at their late fall meeting but left open the
possibility of lower interest rates if economic events dictated,
according to minutes released Friday.
   ``While current indicators of economic activity suggested a
somewhat weaker expansion, most of the members agreed that a steady
policy course was desirable at this point, especially in light of
the stimulus provided by recent easing actions,'' said the minutes
of the Nov. 14 meeting of the Federal Open Market Committee.
   Most of the policy makers agreed, however, ``some further easing
might be needed if the incoming information on business activity
suggested more softening than most members currently expected.''
   The Fed permitted short-term interest rates to drop a quarter of
a percentage point earlier this week to 8.25 percent. It was the
first decrease since Nov. 7 when the central bank also permitted
the federal funds rate to decline a quarter of a percentage point.
   Manipulation of this rate, the interest rate that banks charge
each other for overnight loans, is the primary lever the Fed uses
to control short-term interest rates. It has used this lever
several times since last June, when it began relaxing its grip on
credit to slow inflation.
   The initial decision to keep policy unchanged was reached on a
10-1 vote of the open market committee, composed of Fed governors
in Washington and five of the 12 Fed regional bank presidents.
   Gov. Martha Seeger cast the dissenting vote, contending a
further easing was needed in view of persisting weakness in the
manufacturing sector, particularly automobiles, and a likely
softening in construction and capital expenditures.
   The committee met again Monday and Tuesday, but minutes of that
meeting will not be released until next month. The committee
gathers in secret eight times a year to formulate monetary policy
and confers by telephone as needed.
   In its review of economic conditions last month, it found that
the economy continued to expand, ``though unevenly and at a
somewhat slower pace than earlier in the year.
   ``While the service-producing sector appeared to be growing
moderately, manufacturing had been weak, owing to sluggish demand
and to strikes and other disruptions to production,'' the minutes
said. ``Price increases had been smaller since midyear, but there
had been no abatement of wage inflation.''
   Non-farm employment grew appreciably in October, it said, but
slower than in previous months.
   ``Widespread job gains were apparent in the service-producing
sector, but manufacturing payrolls declined further as a result of
continued weakness in motor vehicles and other durable goods
industries,'' the report said.
   The minutes also showed the Fed staff expected the economy was
likely to grow at a slower pace over the next several quarters.
</TEXT>

</DOC>