<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0170 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 2221EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SinkingShip 1stLd-Writethru a0705 12-29 0375</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sinking Ship, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0705,0383</SECOND>
<HEAD>Crew Works to Keep Sinking Freighter Afloat</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: UPDATES throughout with captain of tanker saying ship not in
immediate danger of sinking, that Bulk was headed to South Korea, other
comments, edits to conform. No pickup.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HONOLULU (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Greek freighter's 28-member crew struggled to
keep their 600-foot ship afloat Friday, but the vessel was not in
immediate danger of sinking, said the captain of a tanker that came
to the rescue.
   Sailors were trying to pump water out of the freighter Bulka,
which was about 800 miles northeast of Hawaii, Barry Arrett,
captain of the tanker Chevron Colorado, said by radio.
   ``I can't determine if he's going to sink or not sink, but from
what I can see, and from my discussions with the master of the
vessel, he has no intention of abandoning ship,'' Arrett said.
``They're in no immediate danger.''
   The Bulka was listing 6 degrees to starboard and was down 40
feet at the bow, said Coast Guard Chief Petty Officer Dennis
Hubbard. Earlier in the day, the bow had been down only 15 feet.
   Hubbard said earlier that the situation did not look good, and
said it wasn't known whether the crew was going to abandon ship.
   The Colorado was 165 miles from the Bulka when it received a
distress call from the ship Thursday night. The tanker reached the
freighter around 7:30 a.m. Friday, and delivered three pumps
air-dropped to it by the Coast Guard.
   The Coast Guard cutter Sassafrass was headed to the vessel from
Honolulu, and was expected to reach the ship sometime Saturday,
Hubbard said.
   Weather was not a problem, Arrett said. Skies were mostly sunny,
with southwesterly skies at 12 knots and low southwest swells.
Winds hit 18 knots earlier in the day.
   The Colorado mostly provided communications assistance, and was
on hand in case the Bulka had to be abandoned.
   The Bulka's captain did not know what caused the ship to take on
water, Arrett said.
   The ship, which is owned by the Greek company Bacolistas and
Sons and based in Athens, had been headed for South Korea with a
load of scrap metal, Arrett said.
   The crew was equipped with life vests and life rafts.
</TEXT>

</DOC>