<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0505EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Panama-delCid     12-27 0586</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama-del Cid,0607</SECOND>
<HEAD>Noriega Aide Pleads Innocent to Drug Charges in Miami</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD COLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A close aide to Gen. Manuel Noriega pleaded
innocent to federal charges of drug smuggling, money-laundering and
racketeering, saying he chose to surrender to U.S. troops in Panama
so he could stand trial.
   Lt. Col. Luis del Cid is charged in the same February 1988
indictment that accuses the ousted Panamanian dictator and leaders
of Colombia's Medellin drug cartel of importing cocaine into the
United States.
   Del Cid, 46, commanded a Panamanian Defense Forces unit in the
province of Chiriqui until he gave himself up Saturday to U.S.
forces that invaded the country to oust Noriega.
   ``I surrendered myself _ I wanted to be brought here,'' del Cid
told U.S. District Judge William Hoeveler in Miami on Tuesday.
   Del Cid strongly denied the charges against him. He then
formally pleaded innocent to all four counts and demanded a jury
trial.
   ``He told his troops not to fire, not to engage in any combat,
to turn their arms in,'' Assistant Public Defender Ken Swartz said
after the hearing.
   ``He didn't want any more bloodshed. It was his desire to
surrender to the (U.S.) forces, and to come here to face these
charges,'' said Swartz.
   U.S. Attorney Dexter Lehtinen described del Cid as ``one of the
right-hand men of General Noriega.''
   ``We allege (del Cid) personally imported shipments of cocaine,
and he personally transmitted large amounts of cash,'' Lehtinen
said.
   Hoeveler appointed Swartz as del Cid's temporary counsel after
the Panamanian testified he had only $7,000 with him. Del Cid said
he couldn't get funds from his Panama savings account, which has
been frozen.
   Del Cid is unemployed, Swartz told the judge, adding, ``His
former employer is out of business.''
   The judge blocked efforts by the U.S. attorney's office to ask
detailed questions of del Cid in an effort to uncover any
additional assets. Hoeveler said such testimony could affect the
racketeering counts against the Panamanian.
   Del Cid, who if convicted could be sentenced to 70 years in
prison and fined $550,000, was ordered held without bond until a
full hearing Jan. 2.
   The judge also denied a request by prosecutors to block contact
between del Cid and Noriega's U.S. attorneys.
   ``Needless to say, we wish to monitor this case to see what's
happening, and obviously look at what, if any, evidence the
government may have,'' said Frank Rubino, one of the Noriega's
attorneys in Florida.
   After the hearing, Lehtinen referred all questions about Noriega
to officials in Washington, and refused to say what contacts his
office had made with del Cid.
   Lehtinen also refused to comment on whether del Cid has
indicated he might testify against Noriega.
   Del Cid, Noriega, cartel leader Pablo Escobar Gaviria and 12
others are accused in the Miami indictment of running drugs and
using Panama as a safe haven for traffickers.
   The indictment alleges that del Cid was used by Noriega as an
emissary as Noriega allowed the cartel to process drugs, launder
money, and ship cocaine through Panama.
   In addition, Noriega is accused of taking a $4.6 million bribe
from the Colombians.
   Del Cid is accused of being personally involved in a
400-kilogram cocaine shipment to Florida in December 1982.
   He also allegedly picked up $100,000 from Noriega's personal
pilot, Floyd Carlton Cacerez in November 1982, and delivered
$200,000 to Carlton at the military headquarters in Panama City a
month later.
   Carlton is a principal witness in the case.
</TEXT>

</DOC>