<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0147 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1909EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Bush-Drugs     12-21 0329</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Drugs,320</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mistrial in Drug Case Bush Cited in Speech; Jurors Can't Agree</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETE YOST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal judge Thursday declared a mistrial
after jurors failed to reach a verdict in the case of a teen-ager
accused of selling the cocaine that President Bush used as a prop
in a nationally televised address on drugs in September.
   U.S. District Court Judge Stanley Sporkin scheduled a new trial
o begin Jan. 8 in the criminal case of Keith Jackson, who is
accused of selling cocaine to an undercover agent in Lafayette Park
across the street from the White House. Jackson, 18, also is
accused of distributing crack at a mall and twice near a high
school.
   The transactions allegedly took place starting last April 24 and
ending Sept. 1 with the sale in Lafayette Park,
   ``We the jury cannot agree on any of the charges,'' the 12
jurors said in a note to Sporkin after four days of deliberations.
   In preparing for Bush's Sept. 5 speech about the war on drugs,
White House aides decided to have the president hold up a bag of
crack and arrangements were made to have a drug purchase near the
White House.
   At Jackson's trial, his attorney, Charles Stow, brought out that
a Drug Enforcement Administration agent at the scene of the
Lafayette Park transaction wore a body microphone that didn't work.
   A camerman who was supposed to videotape the deal was unable to
do so because he was assaulted by a homeless person, a fact which
elicited laughter from the jurors.
   During the courtroom testimony, Sporkin observed that ``this is
like a Keystone Kops thing.''
   DEA officials have said they had difficulty getting Jackson to
come to Lafayette Park because he didn't know where the White House
was.
   In closing arguments, assistant U.S. attorney Mark Carroll said
Stow ``has tried to nit-pick'' and said the four crack sales for
which Jackson is accused did take place.
</TEXT>

</DOC>