<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0214 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1534EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i AM-Cambodia-Non-Communists Adv26   12-18 0664</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cambodia-Non-Communists, Adv 26,0679</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv26</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Tuesday AMs, Dec. 26, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Non-Communist Cambodian Guerrillas Face Erosion of Western Support</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NATE THAYER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SVAY CHEK, Cambodia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Cambodia's non-communist guerrillas
are seeing an erosion of support from the Western world at a time
when they are making significant gains against the
Vietnamese-backed government in Cambodia.
   ``Everywhere in the world the communist system is falling,''
said Gen. Sak Sutsakarn, commander-in-chief of the Khmer People's
National Liberation Front. ``Why won't the world support the
non-communists in Cambodia? Especially Cambodia _ we have suffered
more than anyone.''
   The apparent reason for the diminishing support is a concern
that the non-communists are coordinating their military offensive
with the communist Khmer Rouge, which took power in 1976 and
inflicted a reign of terror on Cambodia that left a million or more
dead.
   The National Liberation Front, the Khmer Rouge and a
non-communist group loyal to Prince Nordom Sihanouk, the former
head of state, have formed a loose alliance that has been waging
war against the Vietnamese and the Cambodian government they
installed in Phnom Penh, the capital, in 1979.
   The coalition, which holds Cambodia's seat in the United
Nations, is largely armed by China, but the two non-communist
factions get U.S. and other Western financial and political support.
   The non-communists still reel from charges of corruption,
internal bickering and being militarily inneffectual. But they have
established better internal discipline over the past two years and,
in recent months, they have shown battlefield prowess.
   In recent weeks, a number of U.S. congressmen have criticized
Washington's support for the non-communists as tantamount to
support for the Khmer Rouge.
   Britain backed away from supporting the non-communists in
November following media reports that the British were training
soldiers ``under the control of Pol Pot,'' the shadowy Khmer Rouge
leader who led Cambodia's terror government until a Vietnamese
ousted him in 1979 after they invaded the country.
   Australia and France have voiced support for leaving Cambodia's
U.N. seat vacant, creating more cracks in what only months ago was
a solid Western bloc of support for the coalition.
   All three groups seek either the downfall of the government of
leader Hun Sen in Phnom Penh or leverage at the negotiating table,
but reporters able to reach battle zones or newly taken towns have
seen no sign of joint military operations between the
non-communists and the Khmer Rouge.
   With the bodies of government soldiers lying in nearby trenches,
National Liberation Front guerrillas celebrated their biggest
victory of the war recently with the capture of Svay Chek, a key
town.
   ``Where are the Khmer Rouge?'' said Gen. Khun Roeng pointing
toward hundreds of his guerrillas on the defense perimeter. ``The
Khmer Rouge are not invited to this party.''
   Resistance leaders acknowledge, however, that they do have field
communication with the Khmer Rouge but solely for reasons of not
getting in the way of each other's attacks.
   The non-communists have seized more than 100 square miles of
territory in northwest Cambodia since launching a general offensive
after Vietnam began withdrawing its last troops from Cambodia in
September.
   ``We have two enemies,'' says Gen. Dien Del, the National
Liberation Front's founder. ``The first is the Vietnamese and then
the Khmer Rouge. The Cambodian people understand that Vietnam wants
to swallow our country, and that is why all patriots have a duty to
work together to save Cambodia. But we are not with the Khmer
Rouge, and the Khmer Rouge knows this very well.''
   He added: ``We need the public support of the Americans. ... We
need to be able to say, `Look, we are backed by the West.'''
   Sak, the commander-in-chief, said: ``What happens to Cambodia if
support for the non-communist resistance stops? The war will
continue between the two communists _ the Khmer Rouge and the Hun
Sen government. There will be no peace, but it guarantees the
future government will be a communist one.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Tuesday AMs, Dec. 26</NOTE>

</DOC>