<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0234EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Census-States     12-29 0355</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Census-States,340</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Census Figures Could Affect Reapportionment</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Census Bureau figures released today indicate
that seven states are likely to gain seats in the U.S. House of
Representatives in reapportionment, while as many as a dozen states
will lose at least one seat, forecasters say.
   The next reapportionment will be based on the final 1990 Census
figures, which will be collected in the 10-year census next year.
The state population figures released today go up to mid-1989 and
represent one last checkpoint before the final, official count.
   The non-profit Population Reference Bureau said that if the
trends in this latest report hold true through the final 1990
figures, California will gain seven seats, Texas and Florida each
will gain three, and Virginia, North Carolina, Georgia and Arizona
will gain one apiece.
   At the same time, 11 states are likely to lose one or more
seats, the Population Reference Bureau said. It said New York will
lose three seats, Pennsylvania, Ohio, Michigan and Illinois each
will lose two, and New Jersey, Massachusetts, Iowa, Kansas, West
Virginia and Montana each will lose one.
   Comparable predictions by Election Data Services Inc., a
Washington-based political consulting firm, differed little. The
firm, however, added Kentucky to the list of losers, dropping one
congressional seat, and predicted that Florida will gain four
seats, rather than three.
   However, the Census Bureau figures on which the predictions are
based do not include members of the military and their dependents
living overseas. They will be counted in the 1990 reapportionment,
the government recently announced, and that change could mean the
difference in whether some states gain or lose a seat.
   The Census figures show that the populations of five states grew
at rates faster than 10 percent from 1985 to mid-1989.
   The state that experienced the largest percentage increase in
population between 1985 and mid-1989, Nevada, grew by 18 percent.
Second was Arizona, 12 percent, followed by Florida and New
Hampshire at 11 percent and California at 10 percent.
   At the same time, seven states lost population, the bureau said:
Iowa, North Dakota, Montana, West Virginia, Wyoming, Louisiana and
Oklahoma.
</TEXT>

</DOC>