<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0638EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Dollar-Gold     12-20 0337</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Dollar-Gold,0356</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar Higher in Nervous Trading, Gold Slightly Lower</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dollar rose in nervous trading today after
U.S. forces launched an attack to topple Panama's leader Gen.
Manuel Antonio Noriega. Gold prices were slightly lower in dull
trading.
   Dealers said the dollar shot up when news of the U.S. military
move broke about 1:40 p.m. In times of international tensions, the
market looks for a safe haven and usually turns to the dollar.
   ``The situation can escalate, and such an escalation means a
firmer dollar,'' said Jens-Uwe Fischer, a trader at Manufacturers
Hanover Trust in Frankfurt.
   The thinness of the pre-Christmas market, from which most
traders already have withdrawn, was contributing to the dollar's
strong reaction to the news, dealers said.
   Another trader at a U.S. bank in Frankfurt said the dollar was
rising before the Panamanian crisis on the selling of West German
marks.
   A trader in Milan said the mark was depressed by the unrest in
Romania and higher French interest rates.
   In Tokyo, the dollar rose 0.43 yen to a closing 144.23 yen.
Later, in London, it was quoted at a lower rate of 144.05 yen.
   Other dollar rates at midmorning compared with late Tuesday:
   _1.7415 West German marks, up from 1.7365
   _1.5630 Swiss francs, up from 1.5615
   _5.9438 French francs, up from 5.9300
   _1.9648 Dutch guilders, up from 1.9575
   _1,295.50 Italian lire, up from 1,291.25
   _1.1622 Canadian dollars, up from 1.1613
   In London, the dollar gained against the British pound. It cost
$1.5980 to buy one pound, cheaper than $1.6005 late Tuesday.
   Gold opened in London at a bid price of $412.50 a troy ounce,
down from $413.75 bid late Tuesday. At midmorning, the city's five
major bullion dealers fixed a recommended price of $413.15.
   In Zurich, the bid price was $413, down from $414 bid late
Tuesday.
   Gold in Hong Kong fell 76 cents to close at a bid $412.04.
   Silver rose in London to a bid price of $5.58 a troy ounce, up
from Tuesday's $5.57.
</TEXT>

</DOC>