<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0162 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1813EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Iran-Iraq     12-20 0437</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iran-Iraq,0450</SECOND>
<HEAD>Red Cross Official Fails to Arrange Iran-Iraq Prisoner Swap</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SALAH NASRWI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BAGHDAD, Iraq (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A senior Red Cross official flew to Geneva
on Wednesday after failing to arrange an immediate swap of ailing
and wounded prisoners held by Iran and Iraq more than a year after
their cease-fire.
   Angelo Gnadinger, the Middle East chief of the Geneva-based
International Committee of the Red Cross, ended his visit after
five days of talks in the Iraqi capital.
   He held similar meetings last week in Tehran with Iranian
officials, seeking the repatriation of 1,000 wounded and ailing
prisoners held by both sides.
   Gnadinger refused to comment to reporters on the outcome of his
visit before his departure.
   But Andreas Wigger, the chief Red Cross delegate in Baghdad,
said, ``I may say nothing concrete has been achieved. ... This is a
long process which needs more effort.''
   Gnadinger had hoped for an immediate release of the sick and
wounded as a first step toward settling the issue of the Iranian
and Iraqi prisoners of war under article 118 of the Third Geneva
Convention. The article calls for repatriation of POWs immediately
after hostilities cease.
   The Red Cross has registered some 50,000 prisoners held by Iran
and more than 19,500 in Iraqi camps. Many of the POWs have been
held since the early stages of the war that broke out in September
1980.
   However, diplomats and United Nations officials say the two
sides hold 100,000 POWs between them.
   Last year, Iran and Iraq released about 400 sick and wounded
prisoners. But the operation was stopped when both sides accused
the other of falsifying the number of captives seeking asylum.
   Earlier this week, hopes were raised that an agreement for a
prisoner swap was imminent. Akram al-Witri, chief of the legal
department at the Iraqi Foreign Ministry, said Baghdad had
responded positively to a Red Cross call to this effect.
   But Iranian Foreign Minister Ali Akbar Velayati quickly
reiterated the Iranian position, undermining the effort. Tehran has
insisted it will not agree to swap the prisoners or implement any
other peace move with Iraq until Iraqi troops withdraw from land
they occupied in the final weeks of the war.
   A U.N.-sponsored cease-fire halted hostilities on Aug. 20, 1988,
but peace talks have been deadlocked mainly over the withdrawal
issue and Iraq's demand for a border demarcation accord that gives
it sovereignty over the entire Shatt-Al-Arab waterway.
   The channel, a confluence of the great Tigris and Euphrates
rivers, is Iraq's sole gateway to the gulf. Before the war, the
border ran down the middle of Shatt-Al-Arab.
</TEXT>

</DOC>