<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1148EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Bulgaria 1stLd-Writethru a0479 12-29 0763</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bulgaria, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0479,0781</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bulgaria Allows Turks To Retake Moslem Names</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 10 grafs to UPDATE with government allowing Turks
to adopt their Moslem names; Picks up 5th graf, `At a ...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SLOBODAN LEKIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SOFIA, Bulgaria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bulgaria's Turkish minority will be
allowed to adopt the Moslem names they were forced to change in an
often violent campaign starting in the early 1980s, a senior
official announced today.
   National Assembly Chairman Stanko Todorov, stepping out of
Parliament to meet demonstrating Turks, told the crowd that in
future ``everybody in Bulgaria will be able to choose his name,
religion and language freely.''
   There was consensus among the demonstrators and observers that
the crucial decision was made at a meeting of the Central Committee
of Bulgaria's ruling Communist Party. The Communists convened
earlier in the day to consider growing opposition demands for
speeding up democratic reforms in the country.
   The name change campaign, which gathered momentum in 1984,
affected hundreds of thousands of people, including Pomaks, or
Moslem Slavs, living in southern Bulgaria.
   Meanwhile, about 2,000 journalists gathered in front of the
party headquarters demanding freedom of the press.
   At that rally, a Moslem speaker told them that the first birth
certificate with a Moslem name in the past 10 years, that of
1-month-old Osman Bajram Husseinov, had just been issued by the
municipal registrar's office.
   The forced name change and increasing curbs on ethnic and
religious rights of the 1.5-million-strong Turkish minority earlier
this year prompted more than 300,000 to emigrate to Turkey after
Bulgarian authorities gave them passports.
   The hastily convened plenary meeting of the Central Committee
also planned to discuss further ``high level cadre changes'' in the
party and state hierarchy, as well as demands by Bulgarian Moslems
for an end to official persecution, sources close to the Communist
leadership said.
   On Thursday, about 10,000 people rallied in a city park to hear
leaders of an independent trade union demand a faster pace for
reform that was promised after hard-line Communist leader Todor
Zhivkov was ousted last month.
   ``Political pluralism, access to the media and ... ethnic
problems are among some of the topics we will raise with the
authorities'' at the talks, Podkrepa head Konstantin Trenchev told
the cheering crowd.
   At a second rally in Sofia, thousands of ethnic Turks and other
Moslems demonstrated against government persecution and also
demanded more democracy.
   The gatherings came one day after the ruling Communist Party
Politburo agreed to talks with the opposition beginning Wednesday.
   Podkrepa is one of several opposition groups that has been
allowed to function publicly since Zhivkov was forced from power
Nov. 10. The new Communist leadership has agreed to pursue reform,
but dissidents say the changes have been slow.
   The reform movement gained impetus after police violently broke
up an Oct. 26 demonstration called by the environmental group
Eco-Glasnost. Two weeks later, hard-liner Zhivkov was driven from
power by more reform-oriented Communists.
   Eco-Glasnost spokesman Deyan Kyuranov said at the rally that he
was convinced that pressure from opposition groups was instrumental
in Wednesday's ouster of Interior Minister Georgi Tanev.
   Tanev was fired for ordering the police attack on demonstrators.
   Kyuranov said the Union of Democratic Forces, an umbrella
organization of opposition groups, also would press for the removal
of Sofia Mayor Stefan Ninov, whom they also held accountable for
the crackdown.
   Kyuranov described the scheduling of talks as ``a significant
victory.'' ``Despite the fact that the government was inclined to
eventually stage such a discussion, the threat of a general strike
by the Podkrepa independent trade union forced their hand,'' he
said.
   The unofficial trade union had plans for a general strike
Thursday but called it off ``to respect the government's goodwill''
after authorities said they would hold talks.
   ``We would like to produce a binding document whose topics would
include free elections and human rights,'' Kyuranov said.
   Earlier, a crowd of more than 5,000 Turks and Pomaks, ethnic
Bulgarian Moslems, marched through the capital chanting
``Democracy!'' and ``We want our names back!''
   Bulgarian Communist authorities forced hundreds of thousands of
Pomaks to change their Moslem names into Bulgarian-sounding names
in a campaign that began in 1984.
   ``We also want to know who was responsible for the atrocities
committed in that campaign,'' according to a demonstrator who
identified himself only as Mehmed.
   The mere existence of the demonstrations is evidence of the
changes in Bulgaria, where any form of dissent was often brutally
suppressed. All other nations in the Soviet alliance have embraced
reform to varying degrees this year.
</TEXT>

</DOC>