<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0265 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1526EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-WallStreet3pm     12-22 0337</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Wall Street 3pm,0354</SECOND>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The stock market pushed ahead in quiet
preholiday trading today, aided what analysts described as yearend
``bargain hunting.''
   The Dow Jones average of 30 industrials climbed 15.35 to
2,706.48 by 3 p.m. on Wall Street.
   Gainers outnumbered losers by nearly 9 to 5 in nationwide
trading of New York Stock Exchange-listed issues, with 946 up, 519
down and 445 unchanged.
   Traders appeared to be doing some last-minute shopping among
recently depressed stocks, hoping that the market will gather
strength after the pressure of tax selling is lifted with the
arrival of the new year.
   At the same time, however, the rally bid was faced with an
obstacle in the form of the Commerce Department's report that new
factory orders for durable goods rose 5.1 percent last month.
   That increase contrasted sharply with advance estimates of
little or no change in orders for relatively high-priced,
long-lasting goods.
   The suggestion it carried of unexpectedly brisk economic
activity helped push interest rates higher in the credit markets.
   Regional telephone stocks were standout gainers, following word
that the Federal Communications Commission plans to regulate local
phone companies on the basis of price rather than profits under a
plan to take effect Jan. 1, 1991.
   Bell South gained 2[ to 57~; Pacific Telesis ~ to 49; Nynex 2}
to 91{; Southwestern Bell 1| to 62], and U.S. West 1| to 78{.
   Elsewhere, Caterpillar dropped 2[ to 55{ on top of a 1~-point
loss Thursday, when the company reduced its earnings projection for
the fourth quarter.
   Campbell Soup fell 4[ to 52|. Recent takeover speculation about
the stock faded after a statement late Wednesday by three members
of the company's controlling Dorrance family that they were
committed to keeping it independent.
   The NYSE's composite index of all its listed common stocks rose
1.30 to 191.80. At the American Stock Exchange, the market value
index was up .40 at 369.95.
   Volume on the Big Board came to 107.53 million shares with an
hour to go.
</TEXT>

</DOC>