<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 0221EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-PanamaProducer     12-25 0512</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama Producer,0528</SECOND>
<HEAD>Captors Wanted CBS Producer To Tell Panamanian Story</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LISA GENASCI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Panamanians who held captive a CBS News producer
and another American had hoped to use them to bargain for the
release of troops captured by U.S. servicemen, the producer said.
   The people who held the men for four days ``cried hysterically''
when freeing them Saturday, 33-year-old Jon Meyersohn told a news
conference Sunday.
   ``Evidently they couldn't find anyone to negotiate with,''
Meyersohn said. ``They didn't really know what to do with us, they
just knew they had a hot property.''
   Meyersohn and Doug Mullen, a GTE executive, were seized
Wednesday at the Marriott hotel in Panama City by paramilitary
forces loyal to deposed strongman Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega. They
were released unharmed Saturday.
   At a news conference at CBS in New York, Meyersohn said he and
Mullen were tied up, threatened and psychologically abused but were
not physically harmed during their four-day ordeal.
   He said his captors appeared disorganized and confused before
surrendering to U.S. Embassy officials Saturday afternoon.
   ``Everyone was in tears,'' Meyersohn said.
   Meyersohn said his captors, armed with AK-47 and M16 automatic
rifles as well as hand grenades, told them: ``We just want people
to understand what we're going through. Tell the world we just want
dignity, we don't want to be a colonial nation.''
   At least 24 U.S. servicemen have been killed and about 280
injured since the United States invaded and occupied Panama late
Tuesday and installed the civilian government of President
Guillermo Endara.
   Just hours after Meyersohn's Sunday news conference, U.S.
officials announced Noriega had turned himself in to the Vatican
mission in Panama and requested political asylum.
   Meyersohn and Mullen were abducted at about 9 a.m. Wednesday by
members of Noriega's so-called Dignity Battalions. Meyersohn said
he, Mullen and two others were first driven to a Panamanian Defense
Forces building.
   ``There were guns everywhere, guns in our faces, and we heard
threats like `we're going to kill the gringos,''' Meyersohn said.
   They were marched up six flights of steps, ordered to sit with
their hands on their heads and interrogated, he said.
   Meyersohn said that at one point a captain of the Panamanian
Defense Forces took Mullen and Meyersohn aside and told them in
English, ``We need you as a hostage to bargain for.''
   The two Americans were then tied up with their shoelaces, taken
back to the pickup truck, made to lie beneath a tarpaulin and
driven away. Later they were driven about 30 minutes into the
countryside.
   The Americans were taken to three other locations, including a
jungle clearing, where they were tied up. On Saturday they were
taken to the apartment of a Panamanian friend of Mullen, who
negotiated their release.
   Meyersohn said that while in captivity he thought often of the
15 hostages held in Lebanon, particularly about Terry Anderson, the
chief Middle East correspondent for The Associated Press, who has
been held since 1985.
   ``I'll never look at a hostage situation in the same way
again,'' Meyersohn said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>