<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0302EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Bingo-Suicide     12-21 0314</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bingo-Suicide,0322</SECOND>
<HEAD>Official is Second Suicide During Federal Probe in Tennessee</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BILL RAWLINS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Secretary of State Gentry Crowell, whose
office has been at the center of a federal investigation of
corruption, has died of a self-inflicted gunshot wound.
   Crowell, 57, died Wednesday at Vanderbilt University Medical
Center. He never regained consciousness after he shot himself in
the head Dec. 12.
   ``He essentially was found to have no brain function,'' said Dr.
Joseph Ross, associate vice chancellor for medical affairs at
Vanderbilt. Tests Wednesday showed little blood flow to Crowell's
brain and doctors decided to remove him from life-support systems,
Ross said.
   The suicide was the second by a state Democratic official during
a statewide federal investigation of public corruption.
   Crowell's office has been a focus of an investigation that has
resulted in 25 people being indicted. Crowell twice testified
before federal grand juries, although he said he had been assured
he would not be indicted.
   Federal authorities investigating illegal bingo gambling and
public corruption reportedly had been closing in on Crowell.
Investigators reportedly were focusing on how Crowell solicited
political campaign money from architects, engineers and bingo
operators.
   As a result of the investigation, a one-time Crowell employee,
former chief bingo inspector W.D. ``Donnie'' Walker, is serving a
seven-year prison sentence on a conviction that includes extorting
payoffs from bingo operators.
   Crowell's longtime administrative assistant, Mary Sue Wright,
was named an unindicted co-conspirator in an illegally operated
Memphis bingo hall and given immunity from prosecution.
   The secretary's death followed by five months the suicide in
Knoxville of Ted Ray Miller, a state representative who reportedly
was under investigation in connection with bribes paid in
connection with legislation dealing with a Knox County incinerator
project. Miller had not been indicted.
   Crowell was elected to the Legislature in 1968, and was elected
secretary of state in 1977.
</TEXT>

</DOC>