<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0163 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1947EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-UnderageGamblers     12-21 0576</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Underage Gamblers,0594</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hearing Begins In Case of TV Show That Allegedly Induced Teens To
Gamble</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: TropWorld in 11th graf is CQ</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HENRY STERN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTIC CITY, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   One of two teen-agers allegedly
induced to gamble by staffers of a ``tabloid'' TV show testified
Thursday that he was offered free food and lodging for his
participation, but never got it.
   City prosecutor Steve Smoger said the charges of inducing a
teen-ager to gamble are the first such case to be prosecuted since
casino gaming was approved for Atlantic City in 1977.
   In an effort to convict the two staffers from ``Hard Copy,' a
nationally syndicated TV news show, Smoger said he offered a plea
bargain to Andrew Pearlstein and Jeff Gerson, both 19 and from
Cherry Hill.
   The youths pleaded guilty Thursday to charges of falsifying an
application on a driver's license and were fined $250 each.
   Smoger said the underage gambling charges Pearlstein and Gerson
face could be reduced after the resolution of the case against
``Hard Copy'' producer Ellen Gussenberg and reporter Daphne
Pinkerson.
   Ms. Gussenberg and Ms. Pinkerson face disorderly persons charges
_ an offense that carries up to a year in jail and a $2,000 fine.
   The staffers work as ``field directors,'' developing stories by
finding people to interview, said Jane Yollin, a spokeswoman for
the show.
   Under cross-examinatin by Ms. Guttenberg's attorney, Carl D.
Poplar, Pearlstein said he and a friend didn't got a free room or
food from ``Hard Copy,'' but he believed that Ms. Gussenberg
offered them over the telephone.
   Pearlstein, who was on the stand for more than an hour, said his
testimony was not influenced by a lawsuit he is contemplating
against Ms. Gussenberg and Ms. Pinkerson.
   John Maroccia, attorney for Pearlstein and Gerson, said he would
decide on the lawsuit in 30 days.
   The two youths were arrested Aug. 18 for allegedly gambling at
TropWorld Casino and Entertainment Resort.
   Under questioning by Smoger, Pearlstein said Ms. Pinkerson
called him in July after a friend of his sister suggested he might
be a good person to contact.
   The friend, Jennifer Denmark, 21, of Cherry Hill, testified
earlier that Ms. Gussenberg identified herself as being from MTV
when she approached her earlier in the month at Bally's Grand Hotel
&amp; Casino.
   Ms. Denmark, crying on the stand, said she believed Ms.
Gussenberg wanted to do a feature on youths at the Jersey shore in
the summer. But under cross-examination, Ms. Denmark said, ``Part
of the conversation dealt with underage gambling.''
   Pearlstein said he drove Aug. 18 from Cherry Hill to Atlantic
City with Gerson because the idea of a television interview
appealed to him and because several phone calls from Ms. Pinkerson
led him to feel sorry for her.
   ``I didn't completely blow her off in the beginning,'' he said.
``She was very nice to me and I felt bad for her.
   ``She seemed very persistent and had trouble finding people''
for the show, he said.
   After their arrest by casino security, Pearlstein said he told
state police that they were part of the television program. He said
he then called Ms. Gussenberg.
   ``I said to her that we got arrested and we need you to ... come
and take us out,'' Pearlstein said. ``She never came.''
   The trial is expected to resume either Jan. 8 or Jan. 9 with
continued testimony by Pearlstein and Gerson taking the stand,
Smoger said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>