<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0092 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1444EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Czechoslovakia Bjt   12-28 0633</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Czechoslovakia, Bjt,0655</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dubcek Elected Leader of Parliament</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PRA1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SYDNEY RUBIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Alexander Dubcek, the champion of
the ``Prague Spring'' reforms, triumphantly returned to power
Thursday as the leader of parliament after two decades in forced
obscurity.
   ``This is a moral satisfaction to the hundreds of thousands of
people who have upheld the ideals'' of political pluralism and
individual freedom, Dubcek told legislators after he was
unanimously elected by the 269 deputies present.
   The televised vote by the Communist-dominated 350-member Federal
Assembly for a man ousted and banished by authorities would have
been unimaginable just two months ago.
   Dubcek's political renaissance is just the latest in a series of
historic political victories for Czechoslovakia's pro-democracy
movement. Since mid-November, it has ousted the hard-line Communist
leadership and installed a reform government dominated by
non-Communists.
   Czechoslovakia's changes have come amid democratic reforms in
Poland, Hungary, East Germany, Bulgaria and Romania this year.
   On Friday, the parliament was to meet Prague's Hradcany Castle
to elect playwright and opposition leader Vaclav Havel as
president. Havel is to be inaugurated immediately after the vote.
   Deputies voted Thursday to amend the presidential oath to be
taken by Havel to eliminate the pledge of allegiance to socialism.
   In his acceptance speech before parliament, Dubcek praised the
peaceful revolution as a continuation of the reforms that began in
1968 and were crushed by a Soviet-led invasion.
   ``The deep changes in society ... have resulted in my return to
responsible work in the highest legislative body in the land,''
Dubcek said. ``The autumn of 1989 developed the ideals of the
Prague Spring of 1968 and inspires our nation today toward new
creative actions.''
   After the Soviet-led invasion, Dubcek was ousted as Communist
Party chief, expelled from the party and sent to work as a forestry
manager in Bratislava where he was kept under police surveillance.
Although renowned abroad, he was excluded from the state-controlled
media in Czechoslovakia.
   He recaptured the spotlight Nov. 24, speaking to 250,000
pro-democracy demonstrators on Prague's Wenceslas Square.
   Next to Havel, Dubcek is the second most powerful symbol of
reform in Czechoslovakia and is the favorite son in his native
Slovakia.
   Dubcek's role in the new government was decided during intense
negotiations between the opposition, representatives of the
Communist Party and members of smaller parties and political
groups. The talks also produced a list of new deputies to replace
23 hard-line Communists who resigned.
   The government is to serve until elections are held next year,
possibly in July.
   Parliament voted Thursday to amend the constitution to allow the
appointment of the new deputies, including Dubcek.
   Only one of the 23 new deputies is a Communist Party member. The
others are members of smaller parties or are independent, although
Communist Party members will continue to hold the majority until
free elections.
   Communist Party leaders Ladislav Adamec and Vasil Mohorita sent
a message of congratulations to Dubcek and said the ideals of 1968
are a ``source of political inspiration for the Party's new
policies of democratic socialism.''
   The Prague daily Vecerni Praha reported Thursday the first
arrest of a major Communist Party figure since the revolution.
   Miroslav Stepan, ousted Prague Communist Party boss, was being
held in custody following his arrest Dec. 23, the newspaper
reported.
   ``Stepan was indicted for preparing the criminal act of abuse of
power of a public official,'' the newspaper reported, quoting the
General Prosecutor's office.
   If convicted, Stepan faces up to 10 years in prison.
   Stepan was in charge of police actions against demonstrators in
January in Prague and was held largely responsible for the violent
police crackdown on students Nov. 17 which sparked the revolution.
   Together with former Communist party leader Milos Jakes, Stepan
was expelled from the party Dec. 12 ``for serious political
mistakes.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>