<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0149 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 2023EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Czechoslovakia 3rdLd-Writethru a0698 12-19 0570</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Czechoslovakia, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0698,0586</SECOND>
<HEAD>Communist Premier Backs Havel for President in Czechoslovakia</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with nine grafs, UPDATING with parliament approves broad
economic and political reforms. Picks up 7th, `The presidency ...</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto XPRA2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GIRARD C. STEICHEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Communist Premier Marian Calfa
endorsed opposition leader Vaclav Havel for president Tuesday,
signaling a major victory for the peaceful pro-democracy revolution
led by the playwright-activist.
   Parliamentary leaders met after a session of the
Communist-dominated Federal Assembly and agreed to reconvene it on
Dec. 29 to elect a new president. The meeting will be held at
Hradcany Castle, the presidential residence.
   Parliament late Tuesday also unanimously approved a new
government program outlining broad political and economic reforms,
including proposals to guarantee freedom of assembly and
association and freedom of religion.
   The program also calls for movement from a state-run economy
toward a free market system but no further details were immediately
available.
   Josef Bartoncik, head of the lower house and leader of the
People's Party, said his party would support Havel and that ``the
election would be in the interest of all citizens of our country.''
   The Socialists _ like the People's Party one of four small
parties in parliament _ also announced Tuesday it would support
Havel.
   In a speech to the Communist-dominated parliament, Calfa, urged
the deputies to elect a new president by the end of the year.
   ``It is the government's opinion that there is no alternative .
.. than to elect Vaclav Havel as president,'' Calfa said.
   He said the presidency should be filled at once in the
``interest of stability.''
   The presidency in Czechoslovakia is a largely ceremonial post,
but it has great symbolic importance because of the respect the
country's first president, Tomas Masaryk, enjoyed in the
independent Czechoslovakia he founded in 1918.
   Calfa said the new president should serve only until June or
July, when Czechoslovakia is to hold its first free elections in 43
years.
   Havel, whose works were banned when the uprising against rigid
Communist rule began a month ago, has said he would serve as
president only on an interim basis, until a replacement was chosen
by a democratically elected parliament.
   Havel was in prison as recently as May, when he completed a
four-month sentence on protest-related charges.
   Jockeying over the presidency has dominated politics for nearly
two weeks, after a series of stunning opposition triumphs forced
the Communists to relinquish their monopoly on power and name the
first government since 1948 not dominated by the party.
   Calfa's endorsement of Havel was an unprecedented show of
support. His government has been reported trying to overcome
resistance among Communist deputies to Havel's candidacy.
   Czechoslovakia has not had a president since Dec. 10, when
Gustav Husak, a member of the old guard, resigned after swearing in
the new government.
   Husak's resignation followed a series of leadership changes that
removed hard-line leaders associated with the crackdown after the
Warsaw Pact invasion that ended the ``Prague Spring'' reforms of
1968 led by Alexander Dubcek.
   Dubcek, later dismissed as party chief and assigned to an
obscure forestry job in Bratislava, also has been mentioned as a
potential presidential candidate.
   The Communist Party has been in disarray since a brutal police
crackdown on student protesters Nov. 17 started the anti-Communist
revolution.
   A two-day special party congress opens Wednesday in Prague, and
is expected to recommend more personnel and policy changes.
</TEXT>

</DOC>