<?xml version="1.0"?>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2348EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-NYCSchoolViolence     12-18 1003</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-NYC School Violence,1027</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rising Number of City Students Sling Guns With Schoolbooks</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Tuesday AMs report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIRGINIA BYRNE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Alexander ``Junior'' Stevens traveled seven
miles across the Bronx every morning to Alfred E. Smith High
School, an all-boys vocational school with a reputation as a quiet
place, a ``safe'' school.
   ``Junior'' was shot to death outside the school cafeteria Nov.
14; a 15-year-old classmate was charged. The two were playing with
a .22-caliber pistol when it accidentally went off, police said.
   ``There are plenty of safe schools all over the city where kids
are sitting there with guns in their bookbags. They just haven't
decided to shoot yet,'' said Ed Muir, of the United Federation of
Teachers, the teachers union.
   ``Junior's'' was the first killing in a city school since 1978.
But in a system where violence is routine, it caused little uproar
among students.
   ``The thing that everyone was taken aback by is that the kids
seem to be taking this so calmly. It's just another kid whacked,''
said Muir.
   Bruce Irushalmi, director of the Board of Education Office of
School Safety, said students ``bring guns to school because they
don't feel safe going to and from school. ... They say they need
them to create a balance of power.''
   Muir is more cynical. ``Some kids feel they actually need it for
protection, and some are businessmen who have large quantities of
cash and thought it the prudent thing not to apply for a pistol
permit.''
   From September 1988 to June 1989, 1,854 weapons were seized at
schools, ranging from razor-edged box cutters to automatic weapons.
At 15 schools where roving teams of security guards used metal
detectors, five guns and 815 other weapons were confiscated during
the 1988-1989 school year _ a year that saw 1,356 students
assaulted, 183 robbed, 78 sexually assaulted and 105 caught using
controlled substances. Figures for this year were unavailable.
   To balance the arms race, New York City spent $62 million on
security in 1988, about 1 percent of the $7 billion budget. Metal
detectors accounted for about $4 million of that; the rest
supported 2,450 uniformed, but unarmed, security guards who police
a system with just under a million students.
   ``If we were a police force, we would be the 10th largest police
force in the country,'' Irushalmi said.
   To Muir, it isn't enough. He cites the increase in gun incidents
_ twice a week last year, 19 in the first 34 school days of this
year _ as evidence that the city's schools are dangerous places to
be. Figures kept by his union show a 5 percent increase in crime
inside schools during the 1988-89 school year.
   Preliminary figures for 1989 showed an 11 percent increase in
school crime in September, and Muir said 44 teachers were assaulted
during the first month of school this fall, compared to 27 during
September 1988.
   But Irushalmi, whose two children attend public schools, says
the problem is not inside the buildings. Reports of violence inside
schools have fallen from 15,000 a year in 1981 to 9,000 in 1988-89.
Outside is another story.
   ``For anyone under 18 this is Dodge City and you have to carry a
piece,'' he said. ``Unfortunately, we don't have Miss Kitty at the
Long Branch to make sure you check your piece at the door.''
   In one corner of this Dodge City, outside Prospect Heights High
School in Brooklyn, a student was shot on the very first day of
school.
   ``There's no safety in Prospect Heights,'' despite spot checks
with metal detectors, said Bob ``Brother'' Abu, 15. ``If they don't
come on Monday, they put the weapons in their lockers. So when the
weapon detectors come on Wednesday, they have their weapons in the
school already.''
   ``There ain't no safety,'' said his 17-year-old friend, who
identified himself as Carl, or Shrapnel Insepticon, a senior at
Erasmus Hall High School in Brooklyn. He wore a blue bandana over
his lower face, Jesse James style, and said he was a member of the
Decepticons, a teen-age street gang named after evil characters in
``The Transformers,'' a cartoon show.
   The loosely knit gang, which has taken to bandanas as
identification, has been accused of taking part in Halloween
rampages on Manhattan's East Side, as well as in wolfpack-type
attacks on students at bus and subway stations.
   More than 100,000 students stayed away from school on Halloween,
apparently out of fear; more than 250 high school-age youths were
arrested as they roamed the city, robbing, intimidating and
assaulting pedestrians and merchants.
   Muir and the UFT have proposed some remedies: metal detectors in
every school, a police liaison for junior high schools, stiffer
penalties for anyone caught with guns. But these steps, all agree,
will not solve the underlying problems that lead to school violence.
   ``The schools are a mirror of society,'' Irushalmi said, citing
drugs and crime, the easy availability of weapons, ``the diminution
of values.''
   ``These kids don't distinguish between the schools and the
streets,'' Muir said. ``They don't see any difference.''
   ``We really think it's related to drugs. Part of it has to do
with the sales, but another part is a lot of the kid's parents are
using drugs, and the kids are acting out,'' said Gretchen Rausch,
an assistant commissioner of the Probation Department who began her
career as a probation officer in 1967.
   Arrests of kids ages 7 to 16 jumped 27 percent from 1987 to
1988, she said.
   But the kids say there is no simple reason why they prey upon
each other and their teachers.
   Sean Chittick, 17, is a senior at Murry Bergtraum High School,
located across from police headquarters and regarded by many as one
of the city's safer schools. Still, he sees violence all around
him, and he is mystified.
   ``It just be happening for no type of reason,'' he said. ``Now
they just be killing them for gold jewelry, or `You lookin' at my
girl.'''
</TEXT>

</DOC>