<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0247 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0930EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-DurableGoods 1stLd-Writethru f0034 12-22 0520</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Durable Goods, 1st Ld-Writethru, f0034,0534</SECOND>
<HEAD>Orders for Durable Goods Up 5.1 Percent in September</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: CORRECTS September to October in 2nd graf and August to September
in 3rd graf. This also moved on general news wires.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN D. McCLAIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Orders to U.S. factories for durable goods
jumped 5.1 percent in November, posting the biggest increase in a
year and averting the first three-month drop since mid-1986, the
government reported today.
   The Commerce Department said orders for durable goods _
``big-ticket'' items expected to last more than three years _
increased to a seasonally adjusted $130.7 billion last month after
dropping 0.7 percent in October.
   Durable-goods orders also fell 1.2 percent in September. Orders
had not fallen for three straight months since 1986.
   The November gain, the largest since a 7.4 percent jump in
December 1988, was an exception to recent evidence that the U.S.
manufacturing sector is in a severe slowdown. Many economists are
forecasting a growth rate of 1 percent or less in the current
quarter and some fear the economy's unprecedented seven years of
peacetime expansion may end.
   Much of the softness has been concentrated in the auto industry,
where weak sales have prompted layoffs and production cutbacks. But
the softness has been spreading recently to the computer and
defense-related industries.
   As a result, economists and government officials have been
calling for a further relaxation of the Federal Reserve's grip on
credit, which the central bank had applied early this year in
efforts to cool the economy and reduce inflation.
   The Fed began loosening its grip gradually last June as
inflation moderated, and it apparently acted earlier this week to
permit short-term interest rates to fall further for the first time
since late November.
   A surprise in today's report was an increase in the closely
watched non-defense capital goods sector, which rose 8.3 percent
last month to $39 billion, the largest gain since a 10.1 percent
increease in December 1988. Economists use this category as a
barometer of business investment plans.
   The Commerce Department reported Thursday that a survey
completed in November indicated that businesses plan to increase
their plant and equipment spending only 4.9 percent next year _ a
rate nearly half the 8.5 percent increase this year.
   Defense orders rose 15.6 percent. Excluding the volatile defense
category, orders would have gained 4.2 percent in November after
increasing 1.8 percent in October.
   Transportation orders rose a sharp 10.5 percent to $36.7 billion
in November after a 2.1 percent gain in October. The November
advance came from increased demand for both aircraft and motor
vehicles. Aircraft represented 40 percent of the gain.
   Excluding the transportation category, durable-goods orders were
up 3.1 percent last month.
   Orders for non-electrical machinery, including computers and a
wide variety of industrial equipment, rose 6.6 percent to $22.9
billion after a 4.7 decline in October.
   Electrical-machinery orders jumped 7.9 percent to $21.7 billion,
virtually all in communications equipment.
   Primary metals were up 1.7 percent to $22.1 billion.
   Shipments of durable goods in November rose 1.5 percent to
$123.7 billion after a 3.1 decline in October.
</TEXT>

</DOC>