<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 0637EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Philippines 1stLd-Writethru   12-28 0564</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Philippines, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0454,0578</SECOND>
<HEAD>Leading Law Agency Seeks Indictment of Top Senator in Latest Coup
Attempt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 11 grafs to UPDATE with Enrile denial. Picks up 8th
pvs, `Early today...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By OLIVER TEVES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The National Bureau of Investigation
recommended today that Sen. Juan Ponce Enrile be charged with
rebellion for an alleged role in this month's attempt to topple
President Corazon Aquino, an official said.
   Enrile denied involvement and said the accusations were meant to
harass the opposition.
   Fernando de Leon, the chief state prosecutor, said witnesses
claimed to have seen Enrile with mutiny leaders on Dec. 1, when
thousands of troops launched the sixth and strongest attempt to
topple Mrs. Aquino.
   De Leon said the recommendation would be referred to a panel of
prosecutors to decide whether charges would be filed. Enrile was
fired as defense minister in November 1986 after a failed coup by
his followers.
   ``The statement of the witnesses points to the fact that at the
height of the coup on Dec. 1, many soldiers with white patches on
their shoulders were seen at the residence of Sen. Enrile and some
guests there inside the house were conferring with him,'' said de
Leon.
   De Leon said those reportedly seen with Enrile included former
Lt. Col. Gregorio ``Gringo'' Honasan, believed to have been a key
leader in the failed putsch.
   De Leon said the witnesses were hotel waiters who were catering
a meal at Enrile's Makati residence on the first day of the
nine-day coup attempt, which claimed the lives of 113 people and
left more than 500 wounded.
   Enrile said there were no soldiers at his residence. He said
``not more than 20'' bodyguards in civilian clothes were present
that day along with some guests who attended a Mass traditionally
held every first Friday of the month at his house.
   ``I welcome the opportunity to face them ... in the courts,''
Enrile said. ``I know that I have not done anything that is
criminal under our laws. I am not part of the rebellion.
   ``They want to seal the lips of the opposition in the country
and to threaten them, but I will tell them now ... that they cannot
silence me,'' he said. ``This government is like a wounded tiger
flailing its paws.''
   Early today, panic-selling swept the country's major stock
exchange after a senior general warned of a possible new coup
attempt. Government institutions bought stocks to ease selling
pressure.
   Dealers blamed the decline on a statement Wednesday by Maj. Gen.
Ramon Montano, chief of the Philippine Constabulary, that a new
coup may be launched after Jan. 17.
   Montano warned the new attempt could be launched by renegade
leaders of this month's coup attempt. Many of the key ringleaders,
including Honasan, remain at large.
   ``Our intelligence data tell us that the next possible timetable
for a coup could be between Jan. 17 and 30,'' Montano told
reporters.
   In a related development, the newspaper Malaya today published
what it said was a secret government ``watchlist'' of 55 people
allegedly linked to the failed coup. The list included Vice
President Salvador Laurel and Enrile.
   Laurel, a longtime political rival of Mrs. Aquino, demanded that
the government confirm whether the report was true and if so,
explain the basis for the allegations. There was no immediate
comment from the presidential staff.
</TEXT>

</DOC>