<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0179 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 2043EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a w AM-DEA-LawnProfile Adv02   12-29 0893</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-DEA-Lawn Profile, Adv 02,0917</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv02</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Tues AMs, Jan. 2, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Top Drug Agent's Story Told in TV Miniseries</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WX6 of Dec. 28</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAROLYN SKORNECK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Drug Enforcement Administrator John C. Lawn
generally keeps a low profile. He speaks in a quiet, husky voice as
he guides the actions of agents throughout the world, trying to
keep them safe in the field and supported in Washington.
   But when a miniseries on the 1985 murder in Mexico of DEA Agent
Enrique ``Kiki'' Camerena airs on NBC-TV in January, he could
become something of a national hero.
   The television movie depicts Lawn tangling with Mexican
officials who stonewall efforts to find Camarena and his killers,
and going public to criticize those officials over the objections
of Reagan administration officials.
   At the conclusion of a National Archives screening, a choked-up
Lawn told the audience of about 100 DEA and Mexican Embassy
officials that it was ``an extraordinary piece of work.''
   The miniseries is based on the book ``Desperados'' by Elaine
Shannon and tells the story of Lawn and Camarena, who was kidnapped
Feb. 7, 1985, in Guadalajara.
   A Mexican pilot who had worked with DEA agents there, Alfredo
Zavala Avelar, was kidnapped a few days later. The bullet-riddled
bodies of the two men, showing signs of torture, were found March
5, 1985, wrapped in plastic bags and dumped on a ranch 60 miles
southeast of Guadalajara.
   Lawn was the DEA's deputy administrator when Camarena
disappeared. By the time the agent's body was found, Lawn was
administrator. It was his first crisis.
   DEA Deputy Administrator Terrence Burke called the film
``powerful,'' but operations director David Westrate said ``there's
a lot of pretend in there.'' Lawn said privately the miniseries was
``about 80 percent accurate,'' which he considered commendable for
television.
   The Mexican Embassy minister for narcotics affairs, Gustavo
Gonzalez Baez _ appointed by the new administration in Mexico that
has cracked down on drug traffickers and corrupt officials _ said
Americans ``are accustomed to seeing this kind of series and they
realize this is not reality, this is just amusement.''
   The movie, he said, suggests ``that all the Mexican authorities
were involved in protecting drug traffickers, and that is
absolutely inaccurate.''
   Gonzalez Baez noted that drug traffickers Rafael Caro Quintero
and Ernesto Rafael Fonseca Carrillo, along with several Mexican
judicial police officers, have been convicted and sentenced to long
terms in connection with the murders.
   Although the miniseries is generally grim, the National Archives
audience found some humor when suddenly, up on the screen in living
color, was William von Raab, the former U.S. Customs Commissioner,
playing himself as he vowed to shut down the U.S.-Mexican border
with car-by-car searches to put pressure on Mexican officials. The
audience's disbelief at seeing von Raab on the screen began with a
murmur and grew into surprised laughter, drowning out von Raab's
lines.
   Lawn, a 54-year-old ex-Marine who goes by the name ``Jack,''
seems somewhat abashed at being, in the words of one observer,
``canonized on television.''
   It may be because the subject matter is so difficult.
   In an interview before the screening, Lawn said the loss of any
of his 2,900 agents is the toughest part of his job.
   ``When you talk to families, the first question I have gotten
from each of the families _ the nine recent funerals that I have
presided over _ the question has always been, `Is what he did
important? Will it make a difference?'''
   It started with Camarena's wife, Mika.
   ``Her initial response was, `Please assure me that Kiki will not
just become a number. It has to mean more than that.'''
   In Camarena's case, it has meant more, in large part because the
DEA was determined to uncover who was responsible.
   ``Many individuals in the international community have said,
`The Mexican government has lost hundreds of people. The Colombian
government has lost hundreds of people. Why pursue Camarena?'''
Lawn recalled.
   To Lawn, Camarena ``was a symbol (that) we in the law
enforcement community, domestic and international, depend upon one
another.''
   ``Kiki depended upon law enforcement counterparts in Mexico who
failed that trust,'' Lawn said. ``And that's the reason we had to
pursue it with vigilance.''
   Lawn won't say how many more agents he'd like to have, but he
contrasts the $8.8 billion drug war budget for 1990 to the ``excess
of $30 billion a year'' the United States spent for the Vietnam War.
   ``To have fewer agents than there are musicians in the United
States Army, or to have fewer agents than there are New York City
Transit Police or female officers in the New York City Police
Department, you get a sense of too few people being asked to face a
Herculean challenge,'' Lawn said.
   But he doesn't believe the U.S. drug crisis will change without
a far greater emphasis on education to reduce demand.
   Even if his force were doubled, ``Twice as good a job is still
not good enough, because without a balance on the other side,
without demand reduction, without international cooperation, our
victory's a Pyrrhic victory,'' he said.
   The miniseries, ``Drug Wars: The Camarena Story'' starring
Steven Bauer, Elizabeth Pena, Treat Williams, Miguel Ferrer and
Craig T. Nelson, is to air Jan. 7, 8 and 9 on NBC-TV.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Tues AMs, Jan. 2</NOTE>

</DOC>