<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891223-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-23-89 0507EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AbortionFund     12-23 0338</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Abortion Fund,0346</SECOND>
<HEAD>North Carolina State Fund for Abortions Emptied</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DENNIS PATTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RALEIGH, N.C.(AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A state-funded abortion program that had
been sliced in half earlier in the year ran dry this week,
curtailing for six months the only state-funded abortion program in
the Southeast, officials said.
   The legislature cut the fund during its summer session from last
year's level of $924,000 to $424,500 for the fiscal year, and the
last funds were spent Tuesday, John Tanner of the state Department
of Human Resources said Friday. The new fiscal year begins July 1.
   North Carolina is one of only 11 states in the country that has
a fund for abortions for poor women.
   Republican state Rep. Paul Stam, who led the budget-slashing
effort in summer, said the House had rejected an amendment he
offered that would have eliminated state-funded abortions for birth
control purposes.
   If the fund had been limited to pay for abortion in cases of
rape, incest or where the mother's life is threatened, it would
have lasted through the fiscal year, he said.
   ``What we have done over the last 5{ months is spend 96 or 98
percent of the money on birth control abortions, so there is no
money left,'' Stam said. ``It's a crazy way to allocate the funds _
first-come, first-served.''
   ``I think it just reinforces that there is a great need for the
fund,'' countered state Rep. Sharon Thompson, a Democrat. ``It is
tragically unfair that whether or not you receive help from the
fund depends on what time of the year you get pregnant.''
   Poor women have few choices left with the state funds gone, said
Ruth Ziegler of the National Abortion Rights Action League.
   ``Our organization would like to see that every woman in this
state that feels the need to make a choice to have an abortion
would have freedom to make a choice,'' Ms. Ziegler said. ``We feel
rich women as well as poor women should be able to make that
choice.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>