<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0100 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1536EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-PanamaAid Bjt   12-28 0736</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Panama Aid, Bjt,710</SECOND>
<HEAD>Administration Seeks Help In Rebuilding Panamanian Economy</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RUTH SINAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United States has asked Japan to help
rebuild Panama's shattered economy and has dispatched a team of
experts to assess the costs of repairing the devastation caused by
last week's military invasion, officials said Thursday.
   In addition, representatives from the Treasury, State and
Commerce departments have begun deliberations on long-term plan to
repair the damage wrought by two years of U.S. economic warfare
against former Panamanian ruler Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   The Panama Economic Reconstruction Committee, the name for the
inter-agency task force, is holding meetings this week with a
three-man Panamanian team headed by a leading economic planner,
Guillermo Chapman.
   That task force will travel to Panama next week to review the
situation, said a State Department official who spoke on condition
of anonymity.
   The focus of the Panamanian-American meeting is the transfer of
some $400 million in Panamanian government money frozen last year
in the United States. President Bush last week ordered the funds
released, but the process is expected to take several weeks,
administration officials said.
   The administration, in talks both before and after the operation
that removed Noriega from power, urged Japan to help Panama, said a
Japanese Embassy official. ``The U.S. expects Japan to play a
significant role,'' said the official who spoke on condition of
anonymity.
   Japan stopped its aid to Panama six months ago because of the
instability created by Noriega, who has been twice indicted in the
United States on drug trafficking charges. The Japanese official
said that once his government recognizes the new Panamanian
government installed with U.S. support last week, ``we will offer
new economic programs.''
   Japan has a strong interest in Panama's stability because many
Japanese exports to the United States pass through the Panama Canal.
   To meet an urgent need for funds, the United States transferred
$5.82 million in money confiscated from Noriega to the new
government headed by Guillermo Endara, an American military
spokesman in Panama City said Thursday.
   The immediate U.S. priority is to assess the direct damage from
four days of bombing and shooting, which destroyed homes and
offices and left thousands homeless, and from several days of
extensive looting.
   Alfredo Maduro, president of the Panamanian Chamber of Commerce,
said Thursday that insurance brokers had estimated losses from
looting or other damage to businesses in the capital at $750
million to $1 billion.
   Maduro said businessmen planned to ask the United States for
``something like a Marshall Plan for Panama'' to recover.
   An estimated 570 people, of them 23 American servicemen, were
killed in the military operation launched last Wednesday to remove
Noriega from power in Panama.
   The team of experts assembled to deal with the immediate
problems resulting from the military intervention arrived in Panama
Thursday, led by the head of the Office of Foreign Disaster
Assistance, Andrew Natsios. The group will try to determine how
much money the Endara government needs for rehabilitation projects,
said a spokesman.
   It also will also consult with the Defense Department to
determine its needs for building shelters and providing food and
medicine to Panamanian refugees, said Michael Marlow of the Agency
for International Development. AID is the State Department's aid
arm.
   The administration has not yet asked Congress for money for
Panama's rehabilitation, relying for now on the $400 million in
unfrozen Panamanian assets.
   But Rep. Lee Hamilton, chairman of the Joint Economic Committee
of the House and Senate, said that money would not go far enough.
   ``The Panama economy is in a mess, maybe in a bigger mess than I
think,'' he said.
   Panama's needs must be identified and aid must be provided,
Hamilton said at a news conference. ``You can't promote their
democracy unless you help their economy.''
   The economy of Panama, once a prosperous banking center with a
per capita income far higher than that of its neighbors, has shrunk
at an estimated annual rate of 10 to 15 percent since 1987,
according to economic analysts.
   Economic sanctions by the United States and a loss of confidence
in Noriega led U.S. firms, including large-scale employers like
Xerox and IBM, to scale down their businesses in Panama.
Unemployment has risen to more than 20 percent.
   In addition, Panama owes at least $5.6 billion to foreign banks,
governments and international lending agencies such as the World
Bank and International Monetary Fund.
</TEXT>

</DOC>