<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0165 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1906EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Pakistan-Bomb     12-18 0406</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pakistan-Bomb,0416</SECOND>
<HEAD>Arrest Suspect in Attempted Airliner Bombing</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRYAN WILDER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ISLAMABAD, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police said Monday they had arrested
a man in the attempted bombing last month of a Saudi Arabian
Airlines jet with 339 people aboard.
   They said the bomb on the Boeing 747 did not explode because a
detonator wire apparently jarred loose. They said it was timed to
go off while the plane was over the Arabian Sea on a flight Nov. 23
from Islamabad to Jidda, Saudi Arabia.
   Officials would not reveal the name or nationality of the
suspect, but said he was a mechanical engineer from an Arab country
who ``is known to be an extremist.''
   ``We do not want to give other details yet, as the investigation
is still under way,'' said Mohammad Habib Khan, director of the
Federal Investigation Agency.
   An agency press release said the suspect admitted guilt after
witnesses identified him. It said he handed a school bag containing
a crude time bomb to a Saudi passenger identified as Abu Amaar, who
was told the bag contained stamps and a book, to be collected by
someone in Jiddah.
   ``Amaar is in custody in Saudi Arabia, but we expect him to be
sent here soon for questioning,'' Khan told The Associated Press.
   Authorities have not explained how the device escaped detection
during normally careful screening of baggage at the Islamabad
airport.
   The Nov. 23 flight was diverted to Karachi, a port city in
southern Pakistan, after security officers at the Islamabad airport
received a note demanding $15 million ransom, officials said.
   A taxi driver delivered the note, which said the Saudi jetliner
would blow up unless the money, in $500 bills, was delivered to a
specified location in Islamabad. Officials said it was not clear
why the ransom was demanded, when the bomb was set to go off
automatically.
   It was discovered after the jumbo jet landed and passengers were
ordered to identify their luggage. Experts said the bomb contained
only eight ounces of dynamite, but could have caused enough damage
to destroy the plane in flight.
   In its press release, the police agency said the suspect became
acquainted with Amaar in the Pakistani city of Peshawar, near the
border with Afghanistan, and they traveled together on a bus from
Peshawar to Islamabad a few days before the flight.
   Police recovered a pistol and ammunition from the suspect, along
with false papers.
</TEXT>

</DOC>