<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1236EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Christmas     12-19 0471</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Christmas,0488</SECOND>
<HEAD>Not Only `No Room at the Inn' _ No Inn</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EILEEN ALT POWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Traditional English versions of the Bible say
Jesus was born in a stable because there was no room in the inn,
but a new look at the old words suggests there probably wasn't even
an inn at Bethlehem.
   Biblical scholar Jim Fleming said Joseph and Mary more likely
couldn't get the guest room at a family compound, crowded with
other relatives home for a Roman-mandated census, and sought
privacy in a nearby stable.
   The stable, he adds, probably was not a cozy wooden structure
but a shepherd's cave cut into limestone.
   And the manger, or feeding trough, was not hewn from wood but
built of stone, he says.
   Fleming said at newsconference sponsored by Israel's Tourism
Ministry that he is not challenging doctrine but interpretation.
   ``The message is to try to help Christians to understand the
simplicity of Christ's birth,'' he said.
   Fleming, director of the Biblical Resources Study Center near
Bethlehem, believes the traditional image of the first Christmas
stems from inaccurate translation of early Greek versions of the
New Testament.
   These Greek texts of the nativity in Luke use the word
``katalymati.''
   ``Inn,'' he says, ``may be traditional, but it is a bad
translation. The word normally is translated as guest chamber.''
   So what, nearly 2,000 years ago, was a guest chamber? And why
wasn't it available to Mary and Joseph?
   ``Most houses from the time of Jesus were ... many roomed
apartment compounds for multiple families,'' Fleming said. ``In
such clusters, one room was reserved for relatives or friends of
any of the families living in the compound.''
   Fleming notes that Joseph and Mary, like thousands of other
families, were required to return to their home town for a census.
   ``If the katalymati, the guest chamber, was already taken, they
would go elsewhere, seeking privacy for the birth,'' he said.
   And what better place, he said, than a stable cut into
limestone. Such stable-caves still dot the surrounding landscape.
   ``Animals were kept in caves because they maintained a constant
temperature, not too cold in winter and not too hot in summer,''
Fleming said.
   In the Holy Land, most feeding and watering mangers for animals
still are built from stone. One lined with fresh hay ``would be a
comfortable place for a newborn infant,'' Fleming said.
   The cave scenario is reflected in the Church of the Nativity in
nearby Bethlehem, he said. The site revered as Christ's birthplace
is in a cave-like grotto below the church's main altar.
   Fleming, 46, a native of Los Angeles, earned a doctor's degree
at Southwestern Baptist Theological Seminary in Fort Worth, Texas,
and did post-graduate studies in historical geography and
archaeology at Jerusalem's Hebrew University, where he is a
lecturer.
</TEXT>

</DOC>