<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 1611EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Czech-News     12-17 0538</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Czech-News,0552</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rules Changing Fast For Czechoslovak Journalists</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Czechoslovakia, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SYDNEY RUBIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For Czechoslovak journalists, the
whirlwind revolution of the past month has set them free from the
dictates of ideology but left them grappling with the constraints
of the marketplace.
   ``What we need is an editor who is a humanist, a visionary, a
person with a clear moral point of view. But we also want someone
who is hardworking and aggressive, a manager who knows how to get
us a new printing press,'' said Michal Horacek, a reporter on the
mass circulation weekly Mlady Svet and a member of the opposition
group Civic Forum.
   Among the first acts of the new opposition-approved government
sworn in Dec. 10 was the firing of the official state censor. Last
Monday, reporters at Mlady Svet, who were required by unwritten
rule to be party members, celebrated the new government by
destroying their membership cards.
   Even the Communist Party dailies Rude Pravo and Pravda now carry
news. Instead of Pablum and propaganda, each day's pages offer
reports on formerly taboo subjects like the secret police and
corruption in the highest party circles.
   It's a big change from only a month ago when editors made weekly
visits to the Communist Party press office to hear about the
previous week's ``errors'' and receive ``advice'' that was passed
along to the staff.
   Offensive passages were deleted, offensive publications
confiscated before they hit the street and some journalists who
operated too far from the party line, like those editing
underground journals, wound up behind bars.
   ``The people of this country were trained to read between the
lines,'' said Horacek, whose column ``Letters of Love and Hate''
was addressed to dead heroes but with a political message that was
clear to Czechoslovak cognoscente.
   When information was strictly controlled, every text had a
sub-text, every word a hidden meaning. People knew better than to
believe what they read and literature became a refuge from reality.
   In this way, the traditionally important role of writers and
other intellectuals in Eastern Europe was enhanced. Cultural
variety substituted for political plurality, and the censor and the
written word both carried enormous weight in the battle for
readers' minds.
   Now, the rules of this Kafkaesque game have changed.
   ``What was only suggested before can now be said, and this means
we have to be more accurate, more tolerant and we have to learn to
compete in the marketplace,'' said Lubos Beniaka, Horacek's
colleague, who wrote 121 pages for his newspaper on the
pro-democracy demonstrations that began Nov. 17 and will end in
free elections next year.
   ``We are quite in the dark about what we are going to be,'' he
said.
   Whatever it is, newspaper staffs will have to decide quickly
since state subsidies in a democratic system will disappear.
   Reporters throughout Prague, exhausted by the non-stop coverage
of fast-breaking events but exhilarated by new opportunities, are
spending much time in meetings discussing their fate.
   ``We can be bought by Robert Maxwell or Rupert Murdoch now,''
Horacek said. ``Anything can happen. But, above all, we want to be
independent. And now we are asking, would we be independent in Mr.
Murdoch's world?''
</TEXT>

</DOC>