<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0444EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-VetShelter     12-30 0476</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Vet Shelter,0492</SECOND>
<HEAD>Homeless Shelter For Veterans Announced</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JONATHAN YENKIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When it opens next month, a shelter for homeless
veterans will offer help with housing and job searches and a chance
``to come and heal,'' the center's founder says.
   ``This is about Americans helping Americans, veterans helping
veterans,'' Ken Smith, president of the Vietnam Veterans Workshop
in Boston, said Friday in announcing the opening of the shelter.
   ``All these guys ever wanted to do is come home,'' he said.
   Smith, who was overcome by emotion as he made his remarks, was
surrounded by fellow veterans as he stood in the room that will be
home to the shelter starting Jan. 8.
   ``This is my dream, and it's very unusual to see your dreams
come to fruition,'' he said.
   The vacant downtown facility had been a clinic run by the
Veterans Administration. It was awarded to the Boston veterans
group under federal legislation that provides excess government
property for helping the homeless.
   The shelter will have space for 100 beds, and it will offer
counseling on drug and alcohol abuse, housing, job searches and
veterans benefits. The shelter also plans to offer workshops on the
history of Vietnam to help veterans understand their involvement in
the war.
   ``This is a place to come and heal, to come heal the pain and
network with other veterans,'' Smith said.
   Mayor Raymond Flynn, who participated in the ceremony, noted
that the veterans who returned from World War II were greeted with
many federal programs to ease their adjustment.
   ``Yet at the same time, there was no period when we have had as
little money spent on housing as the time when the Vietnam vet came
back to America,'' Flynn said.
   About 1,200 veterans in Boston are homeless, and about 30
percent of the nation's homeless are veterans, Smith said.
   ``I work in an ambulance at night and I see a lot of homeless
veterans,'' Smith said. ``I was finding my brothers sleeping on
grates, seeing people sleep under the BU (Boston University)
bridge.''
   Many still suffer the mental effects of combat violence, he
said, and others are too proud to seek help.
   But he said the homeless shelter should help people overcome any
shame since they will encounter and be assisted by other veterans.
   The shelter will operate with volunteers and private donations.
Officials estimate the annual cost of running the shelter will be
at least $350,000.
   One of the volunteers at the shelter, Eric Morse, of Cambridge,
was himself a homeless veteran until Smith's group helped him find
a job and a place to live last year.
   During the time he was homeless, Morse said he roamed the
streets and went to different shelters, but he had trouble finding
anyone to help him.
   ``Veterans care for each other more,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>