<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0196 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0133EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-AutoLayoffs Bjt   12-19 0726</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Auto Layoffs, Bjt,0750</SECOND>
<HEAD>107,700 Seasonal Layoffs, New Incentives, Recession Prediction</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FREDERICK STANDISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Auto Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Year-end holidays will be longer than usual for
107,700 autoworkers as manufacturers try to bring production in
line with slowing demand.
   That news came Monday as Ford Motor Co. joined Chrysler Corp. in
a new round of buyer incentives and Federal Reserve Board member
Martha Seger warned that the auto and housing industry slumps could
push the U.S. economy into recession.
   A check with the Big Three automakers Monday found that most
layoffs at 35 of the 54 assembly plants belonging to General Motors
Corp., Ford and Chrysler will be during the first two weeks of next
month.
   Auto plants will be shut down next week for the usual Christmas
holiday, but that will being extended at many of the plants.
   GM said it was suspending production at 22 of its 30 car and
truck assembly plants next month, each for at least two weeks,
affecting about 75,000 workers. Ford said it was closing 11 of its
16 assembly plants for a week or two apiece, affecting about 25,400
workers.
   Chrysler previously announced that two of its eight plants would
be idled for two-week periods in January, involving 7,300 workers.
That could change later in the week when the company's January
production figures firm up, spokesman Doug Nicoll said.
   While some of the moves by the Big Three had been reported
earlier, the latest announcements gave a clearer indication of the
size of the cutbacks.
   ``It's obviously symptomatic of current demand in the industry,
which is very low,'' said auto analyst Douglas Laughlin of Bear,
Stearns &amp; Co. in New York.
   While GM, Ford and Chrysler carve deeply into their January
production, the five Japanese-based automakers assembling vehicles
in the United States plan normal production next month.
   In fact, Honda Motor Co. Ltd. said Monday it was beginning
production at its second car plant in the United States.
   Laughlin and other auto analysts have predicted for months that
production levels in the first quarter of 1990 would be sharply
curtailed. During the second half of 1989, automakers continued
ambitious production schedules despite waning demand.
   Inventories rose and companies started and stopped incentives to
shrink the backlog. As the 1990 model year officially started Oct.
1, inventories began to shrink. Lately, they have been swelling
again.
   Ward's Automotive Reports, a weekly newsletter of the auto
industry, reported earlier this month that as of Nov. 30, dealers
had an 88 selling-day supply of new cars on hand.
   In other words, if the current selling pace continued and no
more cars were received from factories, the supply wouldn't dry up
for nearly three months.
   Recent 10-day sales reports from dealers have found cars and
trucks made by the Big Three selling at a pace far slower than
during the corresponding periods a year ago. Early December car
sales by dealers for the Big Three, for instance, were 29.7 percent
lower than they were during the same time last year.
   Sales of trucks, which have gained popularity in recent years,
were running 15.6 percent behind last year's pace during the early
December period.
   ``If sales don't recover in the next month it's going to be a
much larger problem,'' said analyst Scott Merlis of Morgan Stanley
&amp; Co. of New York,
   Seger, in Monday's edition of the trade journal Automotove News,
said the slumping auto and housing industries made a recession in
the overall economy a real threat.
   ``I think we're very vulnerable and very much at risk,'' Seger
said. ``I have a growth forecast for next year that is just barely
anything, just enough so you can write it in black ink.''
   Merlis said he expects the Federal Reserve Board to take action
soon to stimulate the economy because of the drop in car and truck
sales during the fourth quarter.
   ``The Fed has got to come to the rescue of the auto industry,''
he said.
   Meanwhile, Ford said Monday it was offering up to $1,000 on all
1989 and 1990 Aerostar minivans, matching incentives announced last
week by Chrysler.
   On Friday, Chrysler for the first time began offering rebates on
its popular minivans, the Dodge Caravan, Plymouth Voyager and
Chrysler Town and Country. General Motors Corp. hasn't said whether
it will offer similar incentives for its minivans.
</TEXT>

</DOC>