<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0212 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1712EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-AntonovichBankruptcy 1stLd-Writethru f0119 12-29 0337</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Antonovich Bankruptcy, 1st Ld-Writethru, f0119,0346</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fur Retailer Goes Chapter 11</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: To UPDATE with liability and asset figures ADDS 1 graf after
8th graf pvs, `Antonovich and ...' Picks up 9th graf pvs, `Phil Bell ...'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fur retailer Antonovich Inc. announced Friday it
has sought federal bankruptcy court protection because of financial
problems caused in part by a weak fur market.
   The New York-based company, which runs nine stores in New York,
New Jersey and Connecticut, blamed ``serious cash flow''
difficulties for its decision to file for protection from creditors
under Chapter 11 of the bankruptcy code.
   The cash crunch was created by a ``number of serious problems
over the past few months,'' the company said, but did not
elaborate. Company executives refused to discuss the situation.
   The financial trouble developed despite a $4 million infusion
Antonovich received in July when investors bought a controlling
interest in the company.
   Peter Masanotti, a Fairfield, Conn., attorney with the law firm
representing Antonovich, said the bankruptcy court filing was
necessary now because the company faces a series of hefty payments
to lenders in the next few months.
   Masanotti said weakness in the market also has contributed to
Antonovich's troubles.
   Fur sales have been in a slump that started with the October
1987 stock market crash, industry analysts say. More recently,
prices have been weighed down by an oversupply.
   Antonovich and the two other major publicly traded fur companies
all experienced losses in their past two fiscal years.
   As of Dec. 1, Antonovich had about $20.4 million in liabilities
and $18.8 million in assets, according to document filed in U.S.
Bankruptcy Court for the Southern District of New York.
   Phil Bell, Antonovich's president, said in a news release that
the company intends to reorganize and will continue operating
during bankruptcy court proceedings. Besides selling furs,
Antonovich provides related services such as storage, cleaning,
repair, restyling and insurance.
   ``Our current sales and sales projections are encouraging, and
at this juncture we are optimistic,'' Bell said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>