<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1041EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-OllieonStage     12-30 0650</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ollie on Stage,640</SECOND>
<HEAD>Oliver North is Upstaged in Musical Stage Debut</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WX7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT M. ANDREWS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Wearing a tuxedo with a floppy bow tie, Oliver
L. North tackled ``Peter and the Wolf'' with the same gritty,
square-jawed bravado that he mustered when he confronted his
Iran-Contra inquisitors in a bemedaled Marine uniform.
   This time, there was no quavering voice, no misty-eyed evocation
of God, country and duty. Instead, North gave a lively,
well-rehearsed narration of Sergei Prokofiev's classic musical tale
for children, embroidered with nasty growls and reassuring smiles.
   The audience of 1,000 Ollie oglers and music lovers _ including
North's probation officer _ greeted his musical stage debut in the
Capital Hilton Hotel ballroom Friday night with cheers, applause
and flashing cameras.
   He won the grownups, but he lost the kids. They sat on the front
row squealing and shrieking at the costumed animals.
   Oliver North, convicted felon in the Iran-Contra affair, was
upstaged by the big, bad wolf.
   ``It was right nice,'' said Aquil Robinson, 12. ``What I liked
best was when the wolf ate the duck.''
   ``Yeah, man,'' agreed his 6-year-old brother, Yusuf.
   North clearly enjoyed his half-hour performance with a 46-piece
orchestra and dancers from the American Contemporary Ballet, the
highlight of a holiday concert sponsored by the Beethoven Society,
a local musical group.
   The retired Marine colonel and former White House national
security aide, who is appealing his May 4 conviction on three
felony charges, appeared onstage as a favor to Maria Fisher, an
85-year-old cultural doyenne of Washington who is founder and
president of the Beethoven Society.
   Even though North reportedly charges $25,000 for every speech he
makes, Mrs. Fisher said he performed Friday night for free.
   Mrs. Fisher said she admired North when she watched his
nationally televised testimony at the congressional Iran-Contra
hearings in 1987. They became friends when they met later at a ball
at the Organization of American States, she said.
   About three months ago, she got the idea of introducing
classical music to inner-city children, and North accepted her
invitation to narrate ``Peter and the Wolf.''
   ``When the word got out, people called me and said, `How dare
you? Shame on you. He's a criminal.' But it takes all sorts to make
a world, doesn't it? Besides, he's a good friend of mine,'' she
said.
   In a pre-concert interview, Mrs. Fisher said: ``I don't know
about his talents as a narrator, but I know he's got a good
speaking voice. I watched those hearings and I'm sure he can read a
script.''
   North said it was his first stage appearance since he performed
in a high school production of ``How the West Was Won'' in his
hometown of Philmont, N.Y., nearly 30 years ago.
   ``I think I was the bad guy,'' he said.
   The audience Friday night included North's probation officer,
Ralph Ardito, and 100 youngsters from Save Our Youth, a private,
non-profit anti-drug program for inner-city children where North is
carrying out his sentence of 1,200 hours of community service.
   He also was sentenced to two years' probation and fined $150,000
after his conviction of aiding and abetting an obstruction of
Congress, shredding government documents and accepting an illegal
gratuity.
   Ardito said North's stage appearance will not reduce his
required hours of community service, even though children from Save
Our Youth were in the audience.
   Conductor Richard Weilenmann praised North for a ``very good''
performance with nary a missed cue.
   ``Some narrators are exaggerated and overblown, but he read very
naturally, as if he were reading to his own children,'' Weilenmann
said.
   Another enthusiast in the audience was Robert W. Owen, who
formerly was North's liaison with Nicaraguan Contra rebels during
the clandestine attempt to channel military aid to the
anti-Sandinista forces.
   ``It was wonderful,'' said Owen, who brought his 2-year-old
daughter Katie. ``Ollie may have a new profession.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>