<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0651EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Oswald-Theater     12-22 0414</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Oswald-Theater,0427</SECOND>
<HEAD>United Artists Plans To Close Theater Where Oswald Was Captured</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A perservation group is trying to save the
landmark Texas Theater, the movie house where Lee Harvey Oswald was
captured after the assassination of President Kennedy.
   The theater, built in 1931 by billionaire Howard Hughes and
considered one of the finest movie houses in Texas at the time, is
scheduled to close Dec. 31. United Artists, which owns the theater
in the Oak Cliff section of Dallas, says the Texas is losing money
showing second-run movies for a dollar.
   The Texas Theater Historical Society made a hurried appeal to
the company Thursday after learning of its decision earlier this
week to close the theater. The group says the Texas has historical
significance _ both as an example of a 1930s-style movie palace and
because of the Oswald connection.
   ``It's just losing money,'' said Dale Chappell, general manager
of the southwest division of UA Theaters. ``Our company's policy is
to close down the theaters that are not profitable.''
   ``We're not picking on the Texas,'' Chappell said, noting that
UA had closed 17 theaters this year, including five or six in this
region, because of their inability to make money.
   On Nov. 22, 1963, the movie house gained notoriety as the place
where Dallas police captured Oswald after Kennedy was shot.
   The Warren Commission later concluded that Oswald shot Kennedy
from a sniper's perch in the Texas Schoolbook Depository building
on the edge of downtown Dallas.
   The historical society was formed to work with UA or a future
owner to preserve the theater and help it turn a profit, the
society's president, Dennis Hamilton, said in a letter to UA. The
society is seeking to buy, lease or be given the theater, the
letter said.
   ``They say it's not making any money and that they're trying to
cut their losses,'' said Cheryl Griffith, secretary of the Texas
Theater Historical Society. ``But you can't give a movie house
third- and fourth-rate movies and expect it to make money,'' she
said.
   This week, the theater was showing ``Indiana Jones and the Last
Crusade,'' which made its big splash in the summer.
   UA's Chappell said the company, which has owned the theater
since the mid-1950s, would consider proposals from the preservation
group.
   ``I think there's a real possibility of leasing it out,''
Chappell said. ``Some of the others we've closed, we've leased
out.''
   Donating the property, however, would be another matter, he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>