<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1007EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Romania-Reax 1stLd-Writethru   12-27 0822</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Reax, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0484,0849</SECOND>
<HEAD>More Countries Debate Aid Effort, Observers Debate Executions</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 22 grafs to Chinese, Soviet, Israeli and Egyptian
statements. Pickup 17th pvs, `London's Conservative...</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GRAHAM HEATHCOTE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More countries today joined the major powers in
recognizing Romania's new government, and millions of dollars in
medical supplies and food were pledged to help the country recover
from its bloody revolution.
   More than 20 countries have recognized Romania's provisional
National Salvation Committee, which took charge Friday when the
popular revolt toppled President Nicolae Ceausescu.
   China, which violently crushed a pro-democracy movement in the
spring, today congratulated Romania's new leaders. Ceausescu was
one of the only world leaders to support China's crackdown.
   Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev gave his personal support
to Ion Iliescu, the chief of Romania's new provisional government
and an acquantance from their college days.
   Japan said it would send $1 million following an appeal by the
International Committee of the Red Cross for $4 million in medical
relief.
   The Japanese Red Cross Society sent medical supplies worth about
$700,000 to Romania and committed a six-member medical team to help
the wounded.
   The Irish Red Cross said today that it would send eight tons of
medical supplies, food and equipment, and it began a fund-raising
campaign to match a cash donation of about $43,000 promised by the
Irish government.
   An Israeli military spokesman said a plane loaded with six to
eight tons of medicine, bandages and equipment and two
Romanian-speaking surgeons left for Bucharest today.
   France said its post office would send free aid packages to any
``identified recipient'' in Romania until January. In a separate
statement, the government said that besides two planeloads of
medical aid sent Saturday, about 20 planeloads had been sent by
non-governmental organizations, including 100 tons of medical
supplies and 60 doctors and nurses.
   The Bush administration said Tuesday it was providing $500,000
to buy medical supplies.
   A score of countries including the United States and the Soviet
Union recognized Romania's provisional government over the past
several days and more joined in today.
   Israel formally announced its support for the new Romanian
leaders and condemned the mass slayings by forces allied with
Ceausescu.
   The statement by Foreign Minister Moshe Arens to Parliament was
the first time Israel openly criticized Ceausescu, who had been
highly regarded in Israel for maintaining a longstanding alliance
with the Jewish state.
   Gorbachev's contratulatory message was carried in the government
daily Izvestia and was strikingly informal, signed simply M.
Gorbachev, with no title. Accenting the unusual recognition of an
informal government was a shorter announcement immediately below,
signed by the Council of Ministers of the U.S.S.R., congratulating
Petre Roman on becoming the Romanian prime minister.
   Denmark sent a congratulatory telegram to Romania's newly
appointed leader, Ion Iliescu, said Hans Henrik Brunn of the
Foreign Ministry.
   In Zambia, President Kenneth Kaunda ``prayed that ongoing
changes will be without further loss of life,'' the official Zambia
News Agency reported.
   Assistant Secretary General Adnan Amran of the Arab League was
quoted as telling Abu Dhabi's state-run newspaper Al-Ittihad that
the changes in Romania were ``respected by all Arab states because
they express the will of the Romanian people.''
   Czechoslovakia's Communist daily Rude Pravo said the Cabinet
recognized Romania's National Salvation Committee on Saturday and
praised the army's decision to support the people.
   The United States was among several countries that criticized
the new government for trying and executing the Ceausescus in
secret.
   Today, Japan's liberal Asahi Shimbun daily newspaper said the
actions violated democratic principles.
   ``Granted, though, that the couple had committed great crimes,
it remained a categorical imperative of democracy to go through the
legitimate legal procedure and give the verdict of guilty,'' it
said.
   Egypt today also criticized the secret trial while supporting
the new Romanian government.
   London's Conservative Daily Mail newspaper said the criticisms
``come easy from the comfort of Western armchairs.''
   ``Such advice takes little account of the necessities imposed by
a civil war. ... While Ceausescu stayed alive, his Securitate
(secret police) had every incentive to carry on fighting and
killing in the hope of restoring him to power,'' the paper said.
   The British government has said it regretted the trial and
killings.
   Iolanda Stranescu, president of the British Romania Association,
said Ceausescu should have had a public trial.
   ``It is difficult at this range to know all the reasons for the
execution. Maybe it was security. Perhaps at a public trial too
much information might have come out about people who want to be
involved in the new government,'' Stranescu said.
   The Kuwait Times said Ceausescu deserved more time to answer the
charges against him.
   ``Those who tried the deposed head of state have proved
themselves overefficient in their performance. They seem to have
handed down a preordained death verdict to the accused without
judging its merit under the accepted canons of justice,'' it said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>