<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0165 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 1731EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-MenorahSuit     12-22 0426</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Menorah Suit,420</SECOND>
<HEAD>Justice Rules Menorah May Be Erected</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Justice William J. Brennan Jr. cleared the way
Friday for a Jewish group to erect a menorah on the steps of the
City-County Building in Pittsburgh for the start of Hanukkah.
   Brennan vacated a ruling made just hours before by a panel of
the 3rd Circuit U.S. Court of Appeals that would have prevented the
display, court spokeswoman Kathy Arberg said.
   The eight-day Jewish festival of lights began at sundown Friday.
   Brennan's action reinstated a preliminary injunction issued
Wednesday against the city by a U.S. district court judge, Arberg
said.
   City officials had refused to allow the Jewish group Chabad to
set up an 18-foot menorah next to a Christman tree. City officials
said they had not authorized the area outside the building to be
used as a public forum.
   A federal judge Thursday denied a request from the city to delay
the lower court's decision. The city immediately appealed, and
Judge Joseph Weis of the 3rd Circuit Court temporarily stopped the
federal judge's order until three members of his court could review
it.
   Chabad and three Jewish residents sued the city a week ago,
alleging their civil rights were violated by the exclusion of the
menorah from the holiday display. The menorah was part of the
display for most of the 1980s.
   In a hearing before Senior U.S. District Judge Barron McCune,
Chabad lawyer Nathan Lewin argued that the area in front of the
building is a public forum where free speech, including display of
religious symbols, cannot be denied.
   McCune agreed, ordering the city to allow Chabad to erect the
menorah in the same place it had been in 1986. That was the year
the city was sued by the American Civil Liberties Union over the
menorah and a Nativity scene at the City-County Building.
   The Supreme Court ruled in July that the menorah, placed next to
the Christmas tree, was constitutional, but that the Nativity scene
was unconstitutional because it was not part of a general holiday
display.
   Pittsburgh Deputy Solicitor George Specter told Weis the area in
front of the building was not a public forum simply because city
officials did not stop demonstrations from taking place.
   ``There is no evidence in this area at all that the city of
Pittsburgh even openly and intentionally authorized the use of the
building as a public forum,'' Specter said.
   Another Chabad lawyer, Elliot Katz, argued the city created the
public forum by allowing the menorah to be displayed in past years.
</TEXT>

</DOC>