<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0440EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AlaskaVolcano     12-18 0540</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Alaska Volcano,0560</SECOND>
<HEAD>Family Evacuated from Volcano's Shadow; No End in Sight</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL JENKINS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A family living in the shadow of
reawakened Redoubt Volcano was airlifted to safer ground, and
scientists warned that the mountain could go on launching ash and
steam for some time.
   The continent's most notorious volcano, Mount St. Helens in
Washington state, also showed signs of life after more than three
years of silence.
   In Alaska, the rescue came on the fourth day of intermittent ash
and steam eruptions from the mountain, which lies in a sparsely
populated region 115 miles southwest of Anchorage.
   Nancy and Steve Jones and their 13-month-old son, Henry, were
evacuated from Tuwalaka Lodge, 10 miles south of the volcano, by a
private helicopter company Sunday. For two days, ash clouds and
poor weather had stymied efforts to reach the Joneses, who are
caretakers at the lodge.
   The lodge wasn't damaged, and no debris landed nearby, but the
family fretted through the first days of the eruption, Mrs. Jones
said.
   ``It was a little bit worrisome,'' she said. ``We're real
thankful that the wind was blowing the other way. We were worried
the top might blow off our way and give us a bad time that way.''
   The Joneses weren't sure if they would return once the volcano
quiets.
   ``We really like it out there, it's beautiful,'' she said.
``It's a perfect place to spend the winter, barring the volcano.''
   Hunks of pumice the size of softballs rained on the roof of
another isolated dwelling, the Big River Lake Lodge, but caretakers
Mike and Sandy Coulter decided to stay, said owner Dennis Branham.
That lodge is 30 miles north of the Redoubt.
   Scientists at the Alaska Volcano Observatory relished the
opportunity to train modern instruments on the 10,197-foot mountain.
   They hoped to reach the peak today by helicopter for a
first-hand look, said John Richter, a geologist at the observatory.
   By correlating ground observations with instrument readings, the
scientists hope to gather information that could help anticipate
eruptions or determine the importance of seismic activity on the
mountain in Lake Clark National Park. ``We have no baseline data to
judge it by now,'' Richter said. ``This is the first time we're
getting good data on it.''
   He said scientists have no idea how long the volcano might spew
ash and steam. ``It could go on for quite a while at rate. We sort
of call it a (phase) five _ a long period of moderate explosive
activity, punctuated with some larger bursts.''
   The mountain Sunday hurled ash and steam 30,000 feet in the air.
   No injuries have been reported in the eruptions, but plumes of
gritty, sulfurous ash have disrupted aviation in this
plane-dependent state.
   The Anchorage International Airport was open Sunday, but service
remained spotty, with some airlines grounding aircraft and others
offering limited service. Some businesses covered sensitive
equipment for fear ash would filter into buildings.
   The skies over Anchorage were clear Sunday, after drifting ash
caused power outages and prompted health warnings Saturday.
   In Washington on Thursday, Mount St. Helens issued a small burst
of steam, gas and ash, but scientists said an eruption did not
appear to be imminent.
</TEXT>

</DOC>