<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0737EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-PikePlaceMarket 1stLd-Writethru a0465 12-19 0697</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Pike Place Market, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0465,0709</SECOND>
<HEAD>Investors Accused of Endangering Character of Seattle Marketplace</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf, `But the ...' to fix noun-verb agreement.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TIM KLASS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When New York investors quietly bought most of
the Pike Place Market in the early 1980s, the deal was seen as a
boon for the popular complex that many call ``the soul of Seattle.''
   The sale provided $3 million to finish more than a decade of
renovation, repair and refurbishing and was central to the
renaissance of the surrounding area that went from down and out to
up and in.
   But the Manhattan-based Urban Group's recent demands for a
better return on their investment have upset market managers and
sparked concern from residents that the nature of their cherished
institution would change.
   The partially open-air market, which opened in 1907 as a way for
farmers to sell directly to consumers, sits on a bluff overlooking
Puget Sound. It's a chaotic mix: Fishmongers hawk salmon,
craftspeople display hand-knit sweaters, parents drop off their
children at a day-care center, and tourists are everywhere.
   About 15 million visitors go to the market each year.
   Urban Group vice presidents Arthur B. Malman and Martin Major
say they don't want to change the market's special character to get
a better profit. But others say profits may only come with major
change.
   Malman said a 10 percent return on investment would be about
right for recent years. He said investors have gotten just $3,000.
   Urban Group manages historic properties around the nation. From
the initial $3 million payment, Malman said investors have gained
$10 million in tax writeoffs. But he added, ``We don't keep score
with tax benefits. We keep score with profits.''
   He has accused the market's landlord and manager, Pike Place
Market Preservation and Development Authority, of inefficiency and
of saddling the 30 owner-investors with costs they should not have
to bear.
   The dispute over operating costs goes to arbitration this week.
Each side has named a property management expert to review figures
and legal documents. If the experts fail to reach agreement, they
are to name a third to resolve the issue. Both sides hope for a
settlement within the next few weeks.
   The fight already is costly. So far, Urban Group has spent about
$200,000 for an audit by Arthur Anderson &amp; Co. of the management.
The authority has spent about the same in legal fees.
   Merchants feel caught in the middle of the battle. Many fear big
rent increases, which may force some to move or close their doors.
   While a few have joined Urban in criticizing market management,
``I think there's a pretty good consensus'' in favor of the
authority, said Paul Dunn, executive director of the Pike Place
Market Merchants Association.
   The issue drew about 250 people last week to an emotional market
community meeting that lasted more than three hours. Several
suggested buying back the market, a prospect rejected by Malman and
Major.
   Market businesses _ 114 farmers, 230 artists and craftspeople
and 225 commercial tenants, including a day-care center, parrot
store, winery, legal and dental offices and the city's lone kosher
cafe _ have gross annual receipts of about $50 million, said
Michael Carroll, director of the market authority.
   He said operating profits are unlikely because of his agency's
mission _ providing social services such as a clinic for seniors,
serving as an incubator of small business and giving food and
farmers top priority _ and restrictions such as a historic review
commission's veto power over many tenants.
   Carroll also said the push for profits is the biggest threat to
the market since voters defeated a plan in 1971 that would have
razed most of the buildings for a hotel and convention center.
   Urban Group, meanwhile, is trying to assure merchants _ and
residents _ that their demand for more profits won't force a major
turnover in tenants.
   ``I think it's unrealistic to assume that the merchants could
pay much higher rents,'' Malman said.
   ``I like the tenants who are now in the market,'' Major said.
``I don't want to change that mix in any way.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>