<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1100EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-JudgeExplosion     12-29 0560</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Judge Explosion,0578</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bomb-Victim Judge Surprised He Survived</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEB RIECHMANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HAGERSTOWN, Md. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The judge injured by a package of pipe
bombs has no idea who mailed him the explosives and says he was
surprised to have survived what he is calls a violent attack on the
entire Maryland bench.
   ``There is no way I should have survived. No way I should be
alive,'' Washington County Circuit Judge John P. Corderman said in
an interview published today by The Sun in Baltimore.
   Corderman arrived home at his apartment in downtown Hagerstown
on Dec. 22 and found a package leaning against his door. He took it
inside, opened it and it exploded. The judge suffered shrapnel
wounds to his right hand and abdomen and partial hearing loss.
   Corderman said that although ``it was a personal attack on me,
it has a larger dimension. It is an attack on the system I serve.''
   ``In a way, I represent the 200 judges at the trial and
appellate level in Maryland,'' he said.
   ``I am deeply disturbed by the level of violence that seems to
go unabated in our society,'' he added.
   Doctors at Washington County Hospital removed pieces of pipe
from his left groin and reconstructed the middle finger on his
right hand. The explosion punctured his eardrums and, before
releasing him Christmas Day, doctors told the 47-year-old judge
that he might need corrective ear surgery.
   ``It was the most remarkable Christmas I've ever had in the best
possible way,'' Corderman told The Sun. ``Some of the presents
weren't wrapped and that was OK. Some of the cards didn't make it,
and that was OK.
   ``Because I had the gift of life, that made everything material
pale in comparison.''
   Corderman has been helping postal inspectors and detectives try
to make a list of possible suspects. Inspectors continue to examine
hundreds of Corderman's cases looking for potential suspects.
   ``Unfortunately, this judge is very controversial,'' said Postal
Inspector Don Gattie. ``He sentences 150 cases a year and that's
just criminal.''
   Gattie, who said investigators were not close to making an
arrest, said Corderman also handled child support cases and had a
reputation for issuing harsh sentences against parents who failed
to pay and also in cases involving drugs or alcohol.
   ``They are portraying me as tough, but I give people a chance
all the time,'' he said. ``I modify sentences all the time. I give
people a chance to take a diferent path.''
   Gattie said investigators received a couple dozen calls on a tip
line the Postal Service set up in Hagerstown.
   Investigators with the federal Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and
Firearms have completed their preliminary forensic investigation of
bomb fragments.
   ``There were at least three pipe bombs, one of which did not
explode and was deactivated by the bomb squad,'' said Tom Hill, an
ATF spokesman.
   WRC-TV in Washington quoted unidentified investigators as saying
there were four bombs in the package and that three exploded.
   Federal investigators, however, have refused to confirm the
report. ``We don't want to inform the doer how we're doing,'' said
Jack Killorin, an ATF spokesman in Washington.
   Killorin said the investigation still was focused in Maryland.
   Mike Vision, a spokesman for the postal inspection service in
Baltimore, said he knew where the package was mailed but refused to
divulge information about the postmark.
</TEXT>

</DOC>