<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0207 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0843EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv30   12-18 0509</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv30,0528</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv30</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Saturday, Dec. 30</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is Saturday, Dec. 30, the 364th day of 1989. There is one
day left in the year.
   Today's Highlight in History:
   On Dec. 30, 1853, the United States bought some 45,000 square
miles of land from Mexico in a deal that became known as the
Gadsden Purchase, for the man who engineered it, James Gadsden. The
area became the southern part of Arizona and New Mexico.
   On this date:
   In 1865, author Rudyard Kipling was born in Bombay, India.
   In 1894, suffragist Amelia Jenks Bloomer died. She had gained
notoriety for wearing in public a short skirt and baggy trousers
that became known as ``bloomers.''
   In 1903, about 600 people died when fire broke out at the
Iroquois Theater in Chicago.
   In 1911, Sun Yat-sen was elected the first president of the
Republic of China after the fall of the Chinese dynasties.
   In 1936, the United Auto Workers union staged its first
``sit-down'' strike, at the Fisher Body Plant No. 1 in Flint, Mich.
   In 1944, King George II of Greece proclaimed a regency to rule
his country, virtually renouncing the throne.
   In 1947, King Michael of Romania agreed to abdicate, but charged
he was being forced off the throne by communists.
   In 1972, the United States halted its heavy bombing of North
Vietnam.
   In 1977, President Carter held the first news conference by an
American president in Eastern Europe as he told reporters in Warsaw
that both Americans and Poles shared the same aspiration for
``complete preservation and enhancement of human rights.''
   In 1978, Ohio State University fired Woody Hayes as football
coach, one day after Hayes punched Clemson University player
Charlie Bauman during the Gator Bowl after Bauman intercepted an
Ohio pass.
   Ten years ago: Broadway composer Richard Rodgers, who had
written the scores for such classics of American theater as ``Pal
Joey,'' ``Oklahoma!'' and ``South Pacific,'' died in New York at
age 77.
   Five years ago: The Madhya Pradesh state government in India
announced it was filing suit in U.S. courts against Union Carbide
following the leak of poison gas at a plant in Bhopal that killed
more than 3,500 people.
   One year ago: President Reagan and President-elect Bush were
subpoenaed to testify as defense witnesses in the pending
Iran-Contra trial of Oliver North. The subpoenas were subsequently
quashed.
   Today's Birthdays: Actress Jeanette Nolan is 78. TV personality
Bert Parks is 75. Actress Jo Van Fleet is 70. Singer Bo Diddley is
61. Actor Jack Lord is 59. Actor John Hillerman is 57. Baseball
hall-of-famer Sandy Koufax is 54. Singer-songwriter Del Shannon is
50. Singer-musician Michael Nesmith is 47. Singer-actress Tracey
Ullman is 30. Runner Ben Johnson is 28.
   Thought for Today: ``Work is a dull thing; you cannot get away
from that. The only agreeable existence is one of idleness, and
that is not, unfortunately, always compatible with continuing to
exist at all.'' _ Rose Macaulay, English poet and essayist
(1881-1958).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Advance for Saturday, Dec. 30</NOTE>

</DOC>