<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0262 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1755EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Dollar-Gold     12-21 0461</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dollar-Gold,0475</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar, Gold Decline</HEAD>
<HEAD>Precede LONDON BC</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dollar declined modestly against most major
currencies Thursday in quiet trading, tipped lower by renewed
anticipation of lower interest rates.
   Gold prices also slipped, despite the continuing fighting in
Panama and political turmoil in Romania. Republic National Bank in
New York quoted a bid for a troy ounce of gold at $412.20 as of 4
p.m. EST, down from $413.05 late Wednesday.
   Dealers said currency traders also shrugged off the U.S.
military intervention in Panama, which was in its second day.
   ``The market viewed it as a very short-lived situation,'' said
Stephen Flanagan, a vice president of foreign exchange at
Manufacturers Hanover Trust Co. ``Interest rates seem to be
dominating the market right now.''
   On Wednesday, the Federal Reserve appeared to signal an easing
of its monetary policy when the central bank added reserves to the
banking system. The action helped lower the federal funds rate, a
key barometer of interest rates.
   A drop in interest rates cuts yields on dollar-denominated
investments.
   Economists have expected the central bank to ease monetary
policy to stimulate the sagging economy.
   In Tokyo, where the business day ends before Europe's begins,
the dollar fell 0.46 Japanese yen to a closing 143.77 yen. Later,
in London, it was quoted at 143.68 yen. By the end of trading in
New York, the dollar had slipped to 143.65 yen, down from 143.93
yen late Wednesday.
   In London, the British pound rose to $1.6125 from $1.6052 late
Wednesday. Later, in New York, a pound cost $1.6145, more expensive
than $1.6060 late Wednesday.
   Other late dollar rates in New York, compared with late
Wednesday's rates, included: 1.7260 West German marks, down from
1.7320; 5.8900 French francs, down from 5.9125; 1.5580 Swiss
francs, up from 1.5555; 1,285.50 Italian lire, down from 1,288.50;
and 1.1597 Canadian dollars, down from 1.1609.
   Other late dollar rates in Europe, compared with late Wednesday,
included: 1.7250 West German marks, down from 1.7355; 1.5575 Swiss
francs, down from 1.5585; 5.8955 French francs, down from 5.9165;
1.9560 Dutch guilders, down from 1.9720; 1,287.50 Italian lire,
down from 1,288.00; and 1.1605 Canadian dollars, down from 1.1625.
   On the Commodity Exchange in New York, gold for current delivery
closed at $411.90 a troy ounce, down from $413.60 late Wednesday.
   Gold fell in London to a late bid price of $412.75 a troy ounce
from $413.50 late Wednesday. In Zurich, Switzerland, the metal was
unchanged at $413. Gold in Hong Kong fell 70 cents to close at a
bid $411.34.
   Silver bullion rose in London to a late bid of $5.57 a troy
ounce from $5.56 late Wednesday. On New York's Comex, silver for
current delivery closed at $5.543 a troy ounce, down from $5.548
late Wednesday.
</TEXT>

</DOC>