<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0235 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1621EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WKD--Snakes Adv29-31   12-18 0739</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--Snakes, Adv 29-31,0763</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv29</HEAD>
<HEAD>$adv30</HEAD>
<HEAD>$adv31</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Weekend Editions, Dec. 29-31, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP WEEKEND ENTERTAINMENT AND ARTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Nashville Sound: Delta Blues Shot With Rock Riffs</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SHERA GROSS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It's called ``Snake music'' _ Delta
blues shot through with rock riffs and punchy drumming.
   And if the drummer gives the beat a soulful touch, it's because
he once played for Aretha Franklin.
   The band is the Snakes, who have released their self-titled
debut album amid comparisons to the Fabulous Thunderbirds. The
group, composed of veteran recording session musicians, plays a
tight mix of original and reworked blues and rock 'n' roll tunes.
   The connection to the Fabulous Thunderbirds doesn't end with the
sound. Snakes pianist Wally Wilson co-wrote the Thunderbirds' hit
``Powerful Stuff,'' featured in the soundtrack for the movie
``Cocktail.''
   Wilson, who is also a veteran country music and rock songwriter,
says the band didn't plan for the new LP to sound like the
Thunderbirds, but he likes the comparison.
   The album contains Snakes' versions of two songs by the late
blues legends Robert Johnson and Bukka White: Johnson's ``32-20''
and White's ``Aberdeen,'' a marriage of acoustic Delta blues and
hard-edged rock. It also features ``Walkaway,'' heard on the
soundtrack for the movie ``Major League.''
   Perhaps the most unusual tune on the LP is ``Pay Bo Diddley,'' a
humorous but scathing look at how the famous rock 'n' roll pioneer
was cheated out of royalties by smooth talking record company
executives.
   Wilson persuaded Diddley to come to Nashville to sing and play
guitar on the cut.
   ``When we brought him up here to do the session, he loved it,''
Wilson said. ``It was his song. He was king for a day.''
   Wilson adds that he had to wire half of the cash fee for the
session to Diddley at his Florida home before the performer would
come to Nashville. He was paid the other half, in cash of course,
once he arrived.
   Recording an album wasn't on the minds of founding members
Wilson and guitarist-vocalist Mike Henderson when they met and
began playing the blues in Nashville.
   ``We decided we would get the Mike and Wally show together and
play Holiday Inns and places like that,'' Wilson joked.
   ``We got a four-piece band together to play Monday nights at the
Bluebird (Cafe),'' he said. The Bluebird is known as a breeding
ground for new talent and many artists have been signed to their
first recording contracts after appearing there.
   At first the Snakes played to an audience consisting mainly of
waitresses, but in time college students and members of the music
industry became fans.
   ``Pretty soon ... it was jam packed in there,'' Wilson said.
   He credits that success to the combination of original members
Henderson, bassist Glenn Worf and drummer Bill Swartz. But as the
group's sound began to evolve from straight blues to blues-rock,
guitarist Kenny Greenberg was added and Swartz was replaced by
veteran rhythm and blues drummer James Stroud.
   The lineup started playing more clubs in Nashville and attracted
the attention of Curb Records executive Dick Whitehouse, who signed
them to a record deal.
   The effortless dovetailing of the musicians' styles is the
reason for their success, Wilson says.
   ``Kenny is an incredible rock guitarist. When he came here (from
Louisville, Ky.,) he was going to play country. That lasted about
two days,'' said Wilson, who migrated to Nashville from Dallas and
started as a janitor at a music publishing company.
   ``Kenny is the leading guy in this part of the South for playing
rock 'n' roll. He has been featured in Guitar Player magazine. He's
done a lot of album work.''
   Wilson characterizes Worf as the best musician in the band.
``Glenn is an incredible bass player. He is very musical. He could
be a jazz musician.''
   Stroud also is a record producer and has drummed for such greats
as Aretha Franklin. Henderson grew up listening to the blues. He
usually sings and plays the harmonica wearing an old Esso service
station attendant's shirt and a battered straw cowboy hat.
   ``He is the strangest guy I've ever met. All of his clothes are
second hand,'' Wilson said. ``He thinks it's ridiculous for people
to pay more than $20 for an article of clothing. If you see him in
a suit, it will be a $10 suit.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Weekend Editions, Dec. 29-31</NOTE>

</DOC>