<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891217-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-17-89 0035EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-FatalFires     12-17 0292</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fatal Fires,0304</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fires Claim Six Lives in Chicago</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fires swept through apartments in several poor
neighborhoods Saturday, killing six people, injuring 15 and leaving
scores homeless in zero-degree weather. The dead included three
young children.
   Fast-moving blazes trapped many people on upper floors, and at
least two people jumped from a second-story window to escape
flames, firefighters said.
   ``People were hanging out of the windows when firefighters
arrived on the scene,'' Fire Department spokesman Stanley Spann
said of one fire on the city's southwest side. ``They must have
rescued 20 to 25 people.''
   Two people were killed and 12 injured, including three
critically, in that early evening blaze in a 60-unit building,
Spann said.
   A man was killed and three people injured in a South Side fire.
   The three young children who were killed were trapped in their
attic apartment by a fire that swept through their west side home
before dawn, firefighters said.
   Two women, including the mother of the victims, were forced by
the flames to jump from a second-story window, authorities said.
   Neighbors reported seeing two men running from the building
shortly before the fire was discovered early Saturday, but police
said their investigation turned up no evidence of arson.
   The fire apparently started at about 2 a.m. on an enclosed back
porch and spread quickly through the rest of the house, said
Battalion Chief Frank Chambers.
   The children, Andrew Smith, 2; Jasmine McKinney, 1, and
Dominique McKinney, 3 months, were pronounced dead at the scene.
   Two women, identified as sisters Janet and Geraldine McKinney,
escaped by jumping from a second-story window, and were both
reported in fair condition. Firefighters said one was the mother of
the dead children, but didn't know which one.
</TEXT>

</DOC>