<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0200 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0903EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i PM-Britain-Blasphemy Adv27   12-18 0877</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Britain-Blasphemy, Adv 27,0904</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv27</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Wednesday PMs, Dec. 27 or Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Film Based on St. Teresa Held as Blasphemous by British Film Censors</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BARR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The visions of St. Teresa of Avila, the
16th-century Spanish nun, have run afoul of Britain's film censors,
who have invoked the little-used blasphemy law for the first time.
   The producers of ``Visions of Ecstasy,'' a 20-minute video about
the saint, lost an appeal to the Video Appeals Committee, which has
met just six times since it was created five years ago.
   John Stephenson, producer of the video, said his company was
considering a further appeal, to Britain's High Court.
   ``We condemn the decision as a disgraceful act of censorship,''
Stephenson said. ``Free expression in relation to religion is a
fundamental right in a pluralistic society.''
   The video was defended by novelists Fay Weldn and Marina Warner
as a legitimate exploration of the connection between sexual
passion and religious fervor as expressed in such Christian notions
as ``the bride of Christ.''
   The video was ``not in any way an insult to God, who, I might
suggest, is not easily insulted,'' Ms. Weldon told the appeals
committee.
   The video shows Teresa caressing the body of Christ on the cross
and in amorous embraces with another woman. The producers say the
scenes are clearly Teresa's imagination, and the two women
represent two sides of her personality.
   It is the first time in 77 years that the board of censors had
rejected a film because of the blasphemy law. It was given
responsibility for reviewing videos in 1984.
   Recently, the board cleared Martin Scorsese's controversial
movie, ``The Last Temptation of Christ,'' though it was condemned
by many Christians because it included a brief scene of Christ
imagining that he was making love with Mary Magdalene.
   ``It indicated that Christ had sex,'' James Ferman, director of
the film classification board, told the appeals panel at the
hearing on ``Visions of Ecstacy.''
   Ferman said he thought the video showed contempt for the
divinity of Christ by presenting him as a living man, not a symbol,
and as an object of sexual passion. He said he was particularly
offended by intercutting the figure of Christ into the scene
between the two women.
   ``There is no attempt to flesh the character physically,
metaphysically or spiritually of St. Teresa, who undertakes
movements on the body of the crucified Christ. That is the kernel
of the objection,'' Richard Du Cann, attorney for the board, told
the appeals hearing.
   Geoffrey Robertson, attorney for Axel Ltd., which produced the
video, said the board was only speculating that a court would find
the production blasphemous. He called the video an ``imaginative,
metaphoric'' portrayal of religious ecstasy.
   ``One wonders what is going on, why the board decided to take
this attitude,'' said Andrew Puddephat, director of the National
Council for Civil Liberties.
   Though rarely applied, the blasphemy law has been discussed
frequently in the past year in the controversy over Salman
Rushdie's novel ``The Satanic Verse,'' which many Moslems charge
blasphemes Islam in its portrayal of the Prophet Mohammed.
   However, Britain's blasphemy law applies only to Christian
religions, and the government has rejected appeals to broaden it.
   Puddephat said he saw no parallel between the controversies over
``Visions of Ecstasy'' and ``The Satanic Verses,'' but he added:
``Sooner or later someone will make it.''
   Stephenson, the producer, told The Independent newspaper that he
thought the film would sell about 200 copies and disappear, and he
had not anticipated any trouble with the censors.
   ``Personally, I object to pornography _ probably more so than
the board,'' said Stephenson, who described himself as a former
devout Roman Catholic.
   ``Our intention was not to offend, to titillate or be
provocative. It was to explore something in our own way. ... The
whole iconography, language and meaning of the Catholic religion
are so bound up with images of blood, pain, suffering and
sacrifice. Those in turn are linked to beauty and eroticism.''
   Marina Warner, who has written scholarly studies of Joan of Arc
and the cult of the Virgin Mary, said that if the video was
blasphemous, it was blasphemous in the same sense as the writings
of Teresa and of St. Catherine of Siena, who both employed
erotically charged images.
   In 1970, they were the first two women to be cited as ``doctors
of the church'' by the Vatican.
   Teresa, born in Avila in 1515, fell into trances and experienced
vivid visions of Christ, Satan and angels.
   Teresa and her visions have long been a subject for art, notably
Gian Lorenzo Bernini's statue ``The Ecstasy of St. Teresa'' in the
chapel of Santa Maria della Vittoria in Rome.
   Film has a special problem, Ms. Warner said, because actors are
easily taken to represent real people, and ``the idea of allegory
starts evaporating.''
   Though such imagery might be congenial to 16th-century Spanish
Catholics, Ms. Warner said, it would be anathema to Protestants.
   ``One religion is a blasphemy against another; one sect is a
blasphemy of another,'' she said in an interview.
   ``I thoroughly disapprove of the law of blasphemy, and I think
it should be repealed. I think its divisive, unjust and
capricious.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Wednesday PMs, Dec. 27</NOTE>

</DOC>