<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0324EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-PentagonCuts Bjt   12-30 0735</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Pentagon Cuts, Bjt,740</SECOND>
<HEAD>Navy `Robbing Peter to Pay Paul' For 1991 Budget</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSANNE M. SCHAFER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Military Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Navy is ``seriously considering'' limiting
purchases of its prized $1.2 billion Trident submarine to every
other year in reaction to intense budget pressures for the new
fiscal year, a senior Pentagon official says.
   The service also is proposing to put two of its four battleships
in mothballs as it fights to retain at least 14 aircraft carriers.
   President Bush is scheduled to deliver his 1991 budget to
Congress on Jan. 22, and he may be called upon to make the final
calls on the controversial suggestions.
   ``We're robbing Peter to pay Paul,'' the Pentagon official said
of the current budget-juggling exercise. He spoke on condition of
anonymity.
   The fiscal 1991 spending plan is considered a key barometer of
the Pentagon's ability to respond to pressures from budget cutters
on Capitol Hill and in the Office of Management and Budget.
   White House budget planners have told Defense Secretary Dick
Cheney he can spend a little more than $292 billion in the new
budget year, which begins next Oct. 1.
   The Navy, like other services, is being forced to trim programs
it deems successful _ such as the Trident _ in order to meet these
goals, said the senior official.
   Asked whether the service was looking at stretching out the
annual purchases of the strategic submarines to every other year,
the official said, ``We're seriously considering it.''
   The sub's billion-dollar price tag has made it easy prey for
lawmakers advocating less lavish spending on strategic nuclear
weapons programs amid the warming of relations with the Soviet
Union.
   In November, the Electric Boat Division of General Dynamics
Corp. in Groton, Conn., won a contract to build the 17th Trident
submarine. Navy Secretary H. Lawrence Garrett III has told Capitol
Hill he expects to request full funding for the 18th Trident
submarine in the fiscal 1991 budget.
   But due to its high cost and complexity, funds for the submarine
are stretched out over several years and Garrett made no mention
about long-term procurement funds for additional submarines.
   ``I'd put my money on some type of stretch-out,'' said another
Defense Department official, asked about the Trident program's
future.
   The official said it was ``premature'' to talk about an end to
the program, and said that if an every-other-year purchase policy
is adopted, ``it may not even compromise the long-term number'' of
submarines, widely expected to be 24.
   The service's World War II-era battleships also have become
targets of budget cutters on Capitol Hill, particularly in the
aftermath of last spring's explosion aboard the USS Iowa, which
claimed 47 sailors' lives.
   Even the chief of naval operations, Adm. Carlisle A. Trost,
admitted at one congressional hearing that the future of the four
warships was ``up for grabs'' in the budget debate. But the Navy
leadership is loathe to let the warships go, the senior official
said.
   ``Nobody _ not the Army, not the Marine Corps, not the Navy _
wants to give those ships up,'' the official contended, arguing
that their mobile firepower offers a major boost when a president
calls for a little ``gunship diplomacy.''
   ``The '91 (budget) plan calls for putting two in mothballs. But
we'd still have two and we want to hang onto those,'' he said.
   The official did not specify which of the four ships would be
retired.
   The second Defense Department official noted that congressional
pressure may work against mothballing the battleships, since their
home ports were to be dispersed among four states under a revised
program.
   ``Our phones rang off the hook'' from lawmakers unhappy about
Trost's suggestion of the ships' possible demise, the official said.
   The senior official said the Navy is fighting to save at least
14 aircraft carriers during the next fiscal year.
   One carrier _ the World War II-era Midway _ is scheduled for
retirement next year, which would bring the fleet from 15 to 14.
   ``Tell me, which commitment are we supposed to walk away from?''
the official asked, pointing out that the U.S. commitment to sail
the Indian Ocean and keep tabs on the potentially explosive Persian
Gulf haven't changed.
   The official also said the Navy's requirements most probably
will increase as the service is asked to place more power on the
high seas to advance the nation's war against illicit drug
traffickers.
</TEXT>

</DOC>