<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0289 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2358EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Japan-DiscountRate 1stLd-Writethru f0277 12-18 0487</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Discount Rate, 1st Ld-Writethru, f0277,0500</SECOND>
<HEAD>Finance Minister Denies Reports That Japan To Raise Discount Rate</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 10 grafs to UPDATE with finance minister disputing
the reports. Picks up 8th graf pvs, `The official ... .'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Finance Minister Ryutaro Hashimoto denied news
reports Tuesday that Japan's central bank will raise its official
discount rate by 0.5 percentage point to 4.25 percent later this
week.
   Speaking at a news conference, Hashimoto said Bank of Japan
Governor Yasushi Mieno told him Tuesday morning that he knew
nothing about the news reports when the two met at a monthly
meeting of economy-related Cabinet ministers earlier in the day.
   The Yomiuri Shinbun and the Asahi Shinbun, the nation's two
largest newspapers, quoting unidentified sources, reported the
central bank is making final adjustments with the Finance Ministry
on the rate hike, which they said will be put into effect this week.
   If the bank action is taken, it will be the third such discount
rate hike in Japan this year.
   Hashimoto said Mieno gave no indication of a plan to boost the
discount rate during the meeting. The minister said the domestic
economic situation does not demand a third increase in the discount
rate this year because prices are stable, even though exchange rate
levels require watching.
   After the news conference, Hashimoto told Japanese reporters
that he has instructed the ministry's monetary officials not to
agree to any central bank plan to raise the official discount rate
if the bank came up with such a plan, Kyodo News Service said.
   Japan's current discount rate, after a 0.75 percentage point
raise March 31 and another 0.5 percentage point hike Oct. 11,
stands at 3.75 percent.
   A spokesman for the central bank refused to confirm or deny the
reports.
   Mieno, who assumed the central bank's highest post Sunday, told
reporters at his first news conference Monday that a strong yen is
necessary for the continued expansion of Japan's domestic
demand-led economy.
   Mieno said the nation's economic conditions are favorable, and
growth should continue as long as prices remain stable. But he said
the central bank must continue to keep the situation under close
surveillance.
   The official discount rate, the rate the central bank charges on
its loans to commercial banks, has a strong impact on other
domestic rates. Higher rates tend to make the country's currency
more attractive to investors.
   The newspapers said the rate hike is intended to curb
inflationary pressure and to stem the continuing weakness of the
yen against the dollar.
   A lower yen tends to make imports more expensive in Japanese
market, while making Japan's products in overseas markets less
expensive.
   The spread of rising land prices beyond Tokyo and the tightening
of the labor market are also behind the measure, the reports said.
   The measure is also aimed at narrowing the gap in interest rates
between Japan and other industrialized countries, they said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>