<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0523EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-UN-Panama     12-30 0434</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-UN-Panama,0448</SECOND>
<HEAD>General Assembly Says Panama Invasion Against International Law</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VICTORIA GRAHAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>UNITED NATIONS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Soviet Union, China and Spain joined
most Latin American nations in condemning the U.S. invasion of
Panama and demanding a swift withdrawal of U.S. troops.
   On a vote of 75-20 with 40 abstentions, the General Assembly on
Friday passed a resolution that ``deeply deplores'' the Dec. 20
invasion and calls the action a ``flagrant violation'' of
international law.
   General Assembly resolutions are not binding and have no legal
force, but they carry moral weight as the will of the international
community.
   U.S. Ambassador M. James Wilkinson said before the vote that the
resolution was unbalanced. He said it failed to mention the alleged
drug trafficking crimes of ousted dictator Manuel Antonio Noriega
and his suppression of democracy.
   ``The United States has no interest in military presence in
Panama beyond our obligations under the Canal Treaties,'' Wilkinson
said. ``The forces recently deployed will withdraw as rapidly as
Panamanian forces can restore security. We are confident this will
take place in a short time.''
   He said the international community should recognize that ``the
freely expressed will of the Panamanian people has opted decisively
for the (President Guillermo) Endara government and rejected the
despotic drug trafficker, Manuel Noriega.''
   Endara was believed to be have won the Panamanian elections
earlier this year but the results were voided by Noriega, who is
holed up in the Vatican embassy in Panama.
   Later, Panamanian envoy Leon Abadi Abadi, who switched sides
from Noriega to Endara, denounced Noriega as a ``narco-terrorist
who placed his interest above those of the Panamanian people.'' The
career diplomat denounced ``the tyrant dictator who rejected the
democratic election of May 7.''
   Panama voted against the resolution, and Cuba denounced Abadi
for changing sides.
   Countries the sided with the United States and voted against the
resolution included Portugal, Australia, Belgium, Britain, Canada,
Denmark, France, Italy, Japan, the Netherlands, New Zealand,
Norway, Turkey.
   The assembly, meeting in emergency session at the request of
Cuba and Nicaragua, heard a dozen speakers over two days denounce
the U.S. action. Some called it an example of gunboat diplomacy.
   The government in Panama, meanwhile, apparently won a limited
victory in a battle over U.N. credentials. In a compromise between
the envoys representing the Noriega regime and the government of
President Guillermo Endara, the Panamanian deputy envoy, Abadi, was
allowed to speak after the vote.
   Although he switched sides, Abadi still holds credentials from
the Noriega government.
   Endara's choice for U.N. envoy, Eduardo Vallarino, is not yet
accredited to the world body.
</TEXT>

</DOC>