<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1449EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ChristmasRescue     12-26 0299</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Christmas Rescue,0307</SECOND>
<HEAD>Motorists Save Stranded Woman From Freeway Attacker</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A band of motorists plunged across a busy
stretch of freeway on Christmas Day to save a woman in a stalled
car who was the target of a sexual assault, police said Tuesday.
   The passers-by thwarted a rape and risked their lives by running
across Interstate 5, known as the Golden State Freeway, to help the
woman, police said.
   ``It makes you feel good when you stop and realize there are
good people out there. It's something to risk running across the
I-5 freeway, which had pretty heavy traffic at that time,'' Police
Officer Gary Williams said.
   Pedro Sanchez, 20, of Santa Clarita, was booked for
investigation of attempted rape, Detective Steve Brazner said. Bail
was set at $12,500 pending arraignment Wednesday.
   The woman and her infant were alone in her northbound car when
it broke down near the junction of the interstate and the Antelope
Valley Freeway, about 25 miles north of downtown in the Sylmar area.
   The woman telephoned her boyfriend for help and was awaiting his
arrival when a car with four men inside stopped. One of them forced
his way inside, Brazner said.
   ``As her boyfriend pulled up, he witnessed her struggling with
the man,'' the detective said. Several motorists traveling in the
southbound freeway lanes at the same time also witnessed the
commotion, he said.
   The motorists stopped and ran across the freeway to help capture
Sanchez, who fled into nearby bushes along with the three other
men, authorities said.
   The 21-year-old woman, a resident of the Canyon Country area of
Santa Clarita, was sexually assaulted, but the motorists'
intervention prevented a rape, the officials said.
   She was treated for minor bruises at Holy Cross Hospital in
Mission Hills.
</TEXT>

</DOC>