<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 0507EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Australia-Quake     12-30 0372</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Australia-Quake,0387</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bulldozers Demolish Damaged Buildings, Troops Patrol Against Looting</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWCASTLE, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Workers, slowed by huge slabs of
concrete, today searched for more victims of Australia's most
destructive earthquake, and police said they believed there were
six bodies in the debris of one building.
   Ten people are known to have been killed in Thursday's quake,
and 142 were injured.
   Demolition crews today started bulldozing heavily damaged
buildings and 100 more army troops were dispatched to patrol
streets and prevent looting in Newcastle, a major industrial center
75 miles north of Sydney. Police said at least 50 buildings may
have to be torn down.
   The temblor measured 5.5 on the Richter scale and seismologists
called it unusually strong for Australia.
   Rescue efforts centered on the Newcastle Workers' Club, where
two floors collapsed onto a basement parking lot during the
earthquake.
   Police said the work was hampered today because the concrete
slabs that formed the floor were so heavy. A wall also threatened
to collpase.
   Police spokeswoman Jo Watts said the bodies workers expected to
recover were in this wreckage. However, workers did not expect to
reach the bodies until Sunday, she said.
   ``There are also nine cars in the basement but we've located and
contacted seven of the owners. Two, we couldn't get the numbers
of,'' she said.
   Ms. Watts said the 10 victims already identified were local
people.
   Emergency teams, which have been working non-stop since the
quake hit, had an especially tiring day.
   ``They started to remove sections of the wall where they believe
people are trapped. But it started to give way because of the time
spent trying to remove the heavy concrete slabs.''
   Initial estimates put the damage at $1 billion, and an official
of the Australian Insurance Industry Council said the damage could
run into ``hundreds of millions of dollars.''
   Australia's biggest earthquake was at Meeberrie, in remote
Western Australia in 1941 and measured 7.7 on the Richter scale, a
gauge of the energy released by an earthquake as measured by the
ground motion recorded on a seimograph.
   Every increase of one number means a tenfold increase in
magnitude. A quake measuring 5 can cause considerable damage and
one measuring 6 can cause severe damage.
</TEXT>

</DOC>