<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0312EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Brazil-Elections     12-20 0589</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Brazil-Elections,0608</SECOND>
<HEAD>Leftist Bitterly Concedes Defeat in Presidential Race</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JORGE MEDEROS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRASILIA, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Socialist Luis Inacio Lula da Silva
conceded defeat in the presidential election, but he accused
conservative victor Fernando Collor de Mello of deception and
pledged to build an opposition ``shadow government.''
   Election officials announced Tuesday that Collor de Mello, a
champion of free-market policies, had won Sunday's balloting.
   ``Fernando Collor de Mello is the winner and that must be
respected. But Brazil was the big loser in the election, gained
through lies and falsehoods,'' da Silva told a news conference in
Sao Paulo.
   ``He will govern in favor of big business, the armed forces, and
the International Monetary Fund,'' de Silva said. ``The Workers
Party and its allies will form a shadow government to prevent
Collor de Mello from committing abuses.''
   With 96.7 percent of the ballots tallied, Collor de Mello of the
National Reconstruction Party had 33,898,190 votes, or 42.7
percent, compared with 30,546,337, or 38.5 percent, for da Silva of
the Workers Party. The rest of the votes were abstentions or
nullified ballots.
   Jose Francisco Rezek, president of the Superior Electoral Court
that was supervising the tally, said Collor de Mello would be
declared the winner Wednesday, but an official announcement would
only be made Dec. 29.
   The election was the first direct vote for president in 29
years. Current president Jose Sarney was selected in an Electoral
College vote strongly influenced by the right-wing military
government that ran the country between 1964 and 1985.
   Collor de Mello has been secluded in his Brasilia mansion. Aides
say he will only address the nation after election officials
proclaim him the winner.
   TV Globo, the nation's largest television network, ran a
previously taped interview with the president-elect Tuesday night
in which Collor de Mello promised a government with ``dignity,
austerity and character.''
   The new president's first challenge will be harnassing inflation
racing at over 1,500 percent this year amid growing poverty.
   Collor de Mello's campaign advisers have told the press he will
seek to heal the wounds from the electoral campaign and call for a
government of ``national unity.''
   However, the wounds run deep.
   In the campaign's final week, Collor de Mello's campaign made
vicious personal attacks on da Silva and said his party wanted to
impose a communist dictatorship in Brazil.
   ``I would never sit at the same table with Collor de Mello. The
low blows he used caused me to lose all respect for him,'' da Silva
said at the Tuesday press conference.
   He said Collor de Mello, scheduled to take office on March 15,
will face strong opposition from labor unions and six leftist
parties.
   During the electoral campaign, Collor de Mello promised to end
inflation, privatize state-run firms, reduce the size of
government, and sell Cabinet minister's mansions to reduce the
public deficit.
   He also won the vote of a great part of the uneducated rural
poor by pledging to increase spending for housing, education and
health care.
   To realize these promises, Collor de Mello must seek allies in
the country's National Congress. The new president's party has 24
senators and representatives, only 3 percent of those in congress.
   Da Silva said his party would back Collor de Mello if he
sincerely attempted to carry out social reforms in this polarized
society, where the richest 1 percent receives almost half the
national income.
   ``But I'm afraid his call for national unity is nothing more
than a trick to keep the working class quiet,'' he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>