<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0213 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1847EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-MoneySupply 1stLd-Writethru f0276 12-28 0379</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Money Supply, 1st Ld-Writethru, f0276,0387</SECOND>
<HEAD>Money Supply Rises</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: NEW final 3 grafs to UPDATE with monetary base data, edit to
conform; No pickup</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The three principal measures of the nation's
money supply rose in the week ended Dec. 18, the Federal Reserve
Board reported Thursday.
   The Fed said the narrowest measure of the money supply, M1, rose
to a seasonally adjusted $795.7 billion from $793.2 billion the
previous week.
   The measure known as M2 rose to a seasonally adjusted $3,215.6
billion from $3,208.7 billion.
   An even broader measure, M3, rose to a seasonally adjusted
$4,036.6 billion from $4,036.2 billion.
   M1 includes cash in circulation, deposits in checking accounts
and non-bank travelers checks. M2 is M1 plus accounts like savings
deposits and money-market mutual funds. M3 is M2 plus less-liquid
accounts, such as certificates of deposit in minimum denominations
of $100,000.
   In judging its monetary policy, the Fed has indicated it is
monitoring the value of the dollar, commodity prices and the
difference between short- and long-term interest rates. It also has
shifted its attention from M1 to the two broader money supply
measures.
   The annual growth rate in M2 so far this year is 4.4 percent,
which is within the Fed's target range of 3 percent to 7 percent.
The annual growth rate in M3 is 3.3 percent, which is below the
Fed's target range of 3.5 percent to 7.5 percent. The Fed has not
set a target for M1 growth since early 1987.
   For the latest 13 weeks, M2 averaged $3,185.8 billion, a 7.5
percent seasonally adjusted annual rate of gain from the previous
13 weeks. M3 averaged $4,018.6 billion, up 2.4 percent, while M1
rose 6.2 percent to an average of $789.0 billion.
   In other reports:
   _The Federal Reserve said bank borrowings from the Federal
Reserve System at the discount window, excluding extended credit,
averaged $496 million a day in the week ended Wednesday, up from
$168 million the previous week.
   _The Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis reported that the
monetary base, the seasonally adjusted total of member bank
reserves held at Federal Reserve banks and cash in bank vaults and
in circulation, was $293.6 billion in the two-week period ended
Wednesday, down from $295.7 billion two weeks earlier.
</TEXT>

</DOC>