<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0518EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-HeatingCrisis     12-29 0627</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Heating Crisis,0646</SECOND>
<HEAD>Heating Oil Prices are Causing Problems For the Poor</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANNE M. PETERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The coldest December weather in New England in a
century is hitting people least able to withstand the blow _ people
on fixed incomes and those receiving a specified amount of fuel
assistance.
   But amid rising concern among the poor and increasing calls for
investigations by elected officials, there were signs Thursday that
the price of home heating oil may drop as rapidly as it rose.
   The U.S. Department of Energy reported record volumes of heating
oil flowing toward the Northeast. The department also granted the
first of what it expects to be several waivers allowing foreign
ships to carry oil from one U.S. port to another. Existing law
restricts such shipments to U.S.-owned vessels.
   People around the region say help can't come fast enough.
   ``I have one patient who must have oxygen. This week, she turned
it off to save money for fuel,'' said Jeanne Steenbeke, a visiting
nurse in the Concord, N.H., area. ``That's kind of scary.''
   ``Elderly people have every penny of their Social Security money
allotted,'' she said. ``There's X amount of dollars for rent, for
food and for utilities.''
   Topsy Corcoran, 82, a widow on a fixed income, paid $1.46 a
gallon to fill her heating oil tank Wednesday in Concord, N.H. On
Thursday, she would have paid $1.52. The last time she filled the
tank, it cost almost $100; this time it was $150.
   ``I've got to pay for it. What am I going to do?'' she said.
   The Massachusetts fuel assistance program already has received
17,000 applications for aid this year, about 4,000 more than it
received any previous year, said Ed McCauley, program director.
   McCauley said some 643 households on aid have already run out of
their allotted funds for the winter because of the high price of
heating oil.
   ``Those people are in trouble right now,'' he said.
   Federal Energy Department spokesman Thomas Olson reported two
price drops on the wholesale oil market Thursday. The January price
for home heating oil _ the price that wholesalers will pay for
future deliveries _ dropped 3 cents per gallon, according to Olson.
And the price on the ``prompt'' market in New York Harbor _ the
price being paid for oil at the wharf _ dropped 12 cents per gallon.
   ``It will take a few more days to see if there's a real trend
here,'' Olson said.
   Added Bernard Smith of the New England Fuel Institute, a group
that represents fuel delivery companies, ``What goes up will come
down. It will probably come down so fast people will hear it.''
   Several members of Congress, including U.S. Sen. John Kerry,
D-Mass., and Reps. Bruce Morrison, D-Conn., Christopher Shays,
R-Conn., and Joseph Moakley, D-Mass., on Thursday joined the chorus
of officials calling on energy Secretary James D. Watkins to
investigate the price increases for the possibility of price
fixing. But Olson said the department lacks authority over prices
and that the attorney general's office would have to conduct such
an inquiry.
   These developments in Washington did little to alleviate the
immediate crisis in the cold-bound Northeast.
   Gary Groleau, energy coordinator for New Hampshire's fuel
assistance program, said 1,200 more people have applied for
assistance this year than last.
   Boston's City Hall energy hotline reported record numbers of
poor people calling because they've used their fuel assistance
allotment already.
   Jean Fleischman of the Boston-based Citizens Energy Corp., a
private foundation that supplies affordable heating oil to the
poor, related a tale of winter misery.
   ``I had an elderly woman yesterday, a widow from East Boston;
she ran out of oil and her house was cold,'' Ms. Fleischman said.
``She was crying.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>