<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0192 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1816EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-SouthernBell     12-27 0400</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Southern Bell,0415</SECOND>
<HEAD>State Investigates Southern Bell Pay Phone Commissions</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CURT ANDERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TALLAHASSEE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Florida's attorney general said
Wednesday the state is investigating whether Southern Bell
underpaid commissions for pay telephone use to governments in
several Southeastern states.
   Attorney General Bob Butterworth said the delinquent commissions
could total in the millions of dollars but determining the exact
amount has been hampered by the telephone company's inability to
provide records.
   The commissions were to have been paid over two years starting
in August 1986. Butterworth said Atlanta-based Southern Bell knew
of the problem in February 1987, but did nothing until a report in
The Miami Herald last month.
   ``Computer mistakes do happen,'' he said. ``It is troubling,
however, that Southern Bell knew about this problem for more than
2{ years, yet apparently made little effort to reimburse its
short-changed government customers.''
   Southern Bell contracts with government agencies to put pay
phones in buildings and then pays a percentage based on usage.
   Southern Bell did not immediately return calls seeking comment.
Officials previously have denied any wrongdoing and said the
mistake was caused by a computer error.
   Butterworth said the failure to make back-payments promptly
could violate the state's grand theft law.
   Butterworth said he began sending letters Wednesday to federal,
state and local agencies advising them not to accept restitution
from Southern Bell until his office accounts for the delinquent
commissions.
   ``As soon as we can determine what appears to be owed, we will
advise you,'' Butterworth said in one letter. ``You may well be
entitled to to a claim exceeding the contract amount plus
interest.''
   Butterworth said Southern Bell may owe commissions to agencies
in Florida, Georgia, North Carolina and South Carolina.
   In a letter last week to Southern Bell President B. Franklin
Skinner, Butterworth said key documents regarding the commissions
were lost or destroyed and that the company initially said it could
not replace them. Now, however, Southern Bell is ``reconstructing''
those records, he said.
   Butterworth asked Skinner to ensure that Southern Bell does not
attempt to pay restitution and that whatever amount the utility
believes it owes be placed in an interest-bearing trust account
until the investigation ends.
   The Herald reported that Southern Bell had underpaid Broward
County agencies more than $150,000 in commissions. The newspaper
quoted a former utility manager as saying the company knew the
revenue reports were wrong.
</TEXT>

</DOC>