<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0555EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Obit-Binion     12-26 0429</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Obit-Binion,0443</SECOND>
<HEAD>Colorful Las Vegas Gaming Pioneer Benny Binion Dead at 85</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LAS VEGAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gaming pioneer Benny Binion, who started out
running illegal craps games and parlayed his fortunes to become
owner of one of Nevada's big-time casinos, has died. He was 85.
   Binion died Monday at Valley Hospital of a heart-related
condition, according to a statement by Henri Bollinger Public
Relations of Los Angeles. He had a history of heart problems and
entered the hospital several days ago for observation.
   ``I'd asked the doctors in gamblers' terms what were his odds,
and they told me six or eight to one against him,'' said his son,
Jack Binion. ``This morning I could see he wasn't going to make
it.''
   He said his father, who owned the Horsehoe casino, had been
given the last rites of the Roman Catholic Church on Friday.
   Benny Binion was born in Grayson County, Texas, to a family that
sold race horses on the county fair circuit, a connection that
provided his entry into the gambling world.
   He started out running illegal craps games, usually out of hotel
rooms.
   ``The craps table would have legs that folded down and it fit
into a crate that looked like a bed crate, and since hotels always
had beds going in or out, if you had 30 minutes notice that you
were going to be raided, you could clean the place out,'' he once
recalled.
   He was said to have killed two people in gunfights during those
days, but never went to prison for them, with the charges dropped
in each case. He never apologized for them either, once saying,
``Tough times make tough people.''
   He did serve time in prison for selling liquor during
Prohibition and for income tax evasion in the 1950s. But toward the
end of his life he had become such a friend of law enforcement that
police officers borrowed money from his casino to make major
undercover drug buys.
   Binion moved to Las Vegas in 1946 and bought the Horseshoe five
years later, quickly building it into one of the city's premiere
attractions.
   ``I was around it and just drifted into it,'' he once said.
   Among the gaming memorabilia featured at the club are $1 million
worth of $10,000 bills.
   The club, also known for its million-dollar craps table bets and
its annual $10,000 buy-in World Series of Poker tournament, now
occupies a city block.
   In addition to his wife, Teddy Jane, and son, surviors include
two daughters, Brenda Michael and Beckey Behnen, another son, Ted.
   Funeral arrangements were pending.
</TEXT>

</DOC>