<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1302EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-ColdRdp 4thLd-Writethru a0562 12-21 0935</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Cold Rdp, 4th Ld - Writethru, a0562,0957</SECOND>
<HEAD>It's Winter and It's C-C-C-C-Cold</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to UPDATE with engine freezing in passenger
train in North Dakota. PICKS UP 7th graf pvs, `Wind chills ...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Icy River, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DONNELLY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The arrival of winter today brought another punishing blast of
arctic air, dropping temperatures well below zero from Wyoming to
Michigan, giving shivers to the Deep South and stopping a passenger
train in North Dakota.
   Forecasters said the polar winds blamed in at least 42 deaths
around the country in the past week may stop by Christmas. But the
cold had much of the nation well prepared for the 4:22 p.m. EST
start of winter.
   ``I doubt we'll notice it,'' said Terry Conroy, a street cleaner
in Syracuse, N.Y., where crews have had to remove snow almost daily
in the past few weeks.
   The National Weather Service's Albany, N.Y., bureau described
the weather as ``cold, with a double underline on that.'' In
Chicago, where a minus 13 reading this morning broke a minus 12
record for the date set in 1872, the weather service warned
travelers to ``dress for arctic cold.''
   It was so cold in Minot, N.D., that the fuel froze in an engine
of a train bound for Chicago from Seattle, stranding about 300
passengers and crew overnight, said Mike Kirka, an Amtrak ticket
agent in Chicago.
   The temperature was about 30 below, with the wind chill near
minus 80, when the train pulled into the Minot station shortly
before midnight, Kirka said. The engine wouldn't restart, and after
three hours passengers were put up at hotels at Amtrak's expense,
he said.
   In addition to the 42 cold-related deaths, authorities in
Philadelphia were investigating the deaths of a homeless man who
was found Wednesday on an outdoor vent wrapped in blankets and two
elderly people who died in a home with no heat.
   Wind chills were expected today to be as low as 80 below in
North Dakota, 75 below in Minnesota and 65 below in Missouri.
People were urged to stay indoors, and some schools were closed
today in North Dakota and Nebraska.
   Today's low temperature in the Lower 48 states was minus 43 at
Jordan, Mont.
   Other early morning temperatures included minus 28 in Bismarck,
N.D.; minus 22 in Minneapolis-St. Paul; 17 below in Des Moines,
Iowa; minus 20 in Omaha, Neb.; minus 12 in Rapid City, S.D.; 16
below in Sault Ste. Marie, Mich., and minus 9 in Casper, Wyo.
   Little Rock, Ark., was a chilly 20, while Fort Worth, Texas, was
24.
   But today's surge of arctic air into northern Minnesota appeared
to be the last in the series of blasts that have crossed the border
into Minnesota and plagued the eastern half of the nation for 10
days, the weather service said.
   ``The trend looks hopeful for a change in the cold northwest
flow to a more westerly flow on the weekend over Minnesota,'' the
weather service said. ``This means a very slow moderation in
temperatures by Sunday and Christmas Day.''
   On the last day of fall, gusty winds dropped the wind chill to
81 below zero at Minot, N.D., 75 below at Devils Lake, N.D., 69
below at Alexandria, Minn., and Jamestown, N.D., and 61 below at
Aberdeen, S.D.
   The southern edge of the cold air on Wednesday extended from New
York state across Ohio, Indiana, Missouri, Iowa, Kansas, Colorado,
Wyoming and central Montana.
   By today, the cold dipped to northern Texas and northern
Louisiana. The temperature in Amarillo, Texas, dropped to 1 degree
overnight. By Friday, the arctic was expected to invade North
Carolina and northern Georgia.
   The weather service forecast a ``major freeze'' across the lower
Rio Grande Valley of Texas from tonight into Saturday.
   In the Midwest, many authorities warned people to take
precautions against the cold. Sheriff Stan Lyson of Williams
County, N.D., urged residents to stay home unless travel was
absolutely necessary.
   He suggested Christmas travelers inform someone of their
destination and the route they plan to take. ``I don't think anyone
would last out there very long,'' Lyson said.
   Temperatures hovered around 10 degrees Wednesday in Rochester,
N.Y., but the wind made it feel like 25 below zero. ``The place is
packed with people drinking hot toddies at the bar,'' said Mary
Camp, bookkeeper at the Sea Breeze Inn.
   The weather service's official low temperature for the Lower 48
states Wednesday was 34 below zero at International Falls and
Warroad, Minn., both on the Canadian border. Embarrass, an Iron
Range town in northeastern Minnesota, reached an unofficial 37
below zero.
   Wednesday's high at International Falls was only 21 degrees
below zero.
   In the southern Chicago suburb of Harvey, the bitter cold burst
a 24-inch water main, cutting service to six communities.
   Between 2,000 and 3,000 motorists called for help starting their
cars, the Automobile Association of America-Chicago Motor Club said.
   Snow fell from the northern Rockies across the northern Plains
and around the Great Lakes, where ``lake effect'' snow fed by the
moisture of the lakes piled up 4-foot drifts in western New York
state.
   The weather service at Syracuse had measured 50.4 inches of snow
for the fall. At this time last year, only 27.2 inches of snow had
fallen.
   Unusually low temperatures this month have strained utilities
throughout New York and New England, and could bring brownouts in
some areas as winter progresses, officials said.
   Temperatures 10 degrees lower than normal for this time of year
have forced New York, New England and the Maryland-Pensylvannia-New
Jersey power pools to share electricity.
</TEXT>

</DOC>