<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 0941EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-FetalSex     12-22 0407</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Fetal Sex,0417</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Test Allows Determination of Sex of Fetus from Blood Sample</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A sensitive new genetic test has enabled
researchers to determine the sex of 19 fetuses merely by taking
blood from their mothers' arms, says a new report.
   The technique might one day be used to diagnose birth defects
before birth, replacing present methods in which cells must be
obtained from the uterus, researchers said.
   The test, called the polymerase chain reaction, or PCR, was used
to search for Y chromosomes in the blood of the 19 mothers. Females
do not have Y chromosomes.
   The researchers were hoping that enough fetal cells had leaked
into the mothers' bloodstreams that the Y chromosomes from male
fetuses could be detected.
   They detected the Y chromosomes in seven of the mothers, and
predicted that those women were carrying males. All seven delivered
boys. All of the 12 women in whom Y chromosomes were not found
delivered girls.
   ``With stringent precautions against contamination, this
technique may assist prenatal diagnosis of sex-linked disorders,''
said the researchers, led by Dr. Kenneth Fleming of John Radcliffe
Hospital in Oxford, England. The researchers reported their results
in the Dec. 9 issue of The Lancet, a British medical journal.
   In May, Dr. Diana Bianchi of Boston Children's Hospital used a
different technique for analyzing mothers' blood samples and
correctly predicted the sex of two out of three male fetuses.
   Other studies had raised the possibility that fetal cells could
be found in mothers' blood, but no one had proven that fetal cells
could be reliably distinguished from the mothers' cells.
   The sex of a fetus can now be determined as early as the eighth
week of pregnancy through a technique called chorionic villus
sampling, or CVS, in which cells from the precursor of the placenta
are removed and tested.
   CVS allows the testing of cells for any of the genetic
abnormalities for which tests exist, including such disorders as
Down's syndrome, Huntington's disease and sickle cell anemia.
   The hope is that mothers' blood can one day be used for the
detection of these other genetic abnormalities, because getting a
blood sample is simpler and safer than CVS or the standard sampling
method, amniocentesis.
   In that procedure, a small amount of the amniotic fluid that
bathes the fetus is withdrawn about the 16th week of pregnancy.
Genetic testing is done on fetal cells that have escaped into the
fluid.
</TEXT>

</DOC>