<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0118 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1259EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-ScroogeAwards Bjt   12-20 0550</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Scrooge Awards, Bjt,0563</SECOND>
<HEAD>Scrooge Lives! Appalling Tales From the Underside of Christmas</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MITCHELL LANDSBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   `Tis the season for human folly, or, as the sign in the New York
City bus depot puts it: ``The holidays are here. PLEASE! Watch your
belongings.''
   With that in mind, we present our nominations for the 1989
Ebenezer Scrooge Awards, given just this once to those who best
exemplify the seamy underside of the Christmas spirit.
   These are nominations only; there will be no winners. As will
become appallingly obvious, everybody loses.
   For Worst Performance by a Santa, the nominees are:
   _ The Santa in sunglasses who held up a branch of Fidelity Bank
in West Chester, Pa., while softly singing, ``We wish you a merry
Christmas, we wish you a merry Christmas.'' Santa, whose
performance was captured by the bank's surveillance camera,
pocketed $1,000.
   _ The macho Santa who beat up a heckler in front of a crowd of
children in Salvador, Brazil. The heckler reportedly had shouted,
``How about giving me your mother as a present this Christmas,
Santa?'' Santa was arrested after attacking him, but proudly told
police, ``I gave that bum what he deserved.''
   _ The elderly Santa in Lowell, Ark., who made off with cash from
a convenience store after threatening to pour hot coffee on the
clerk.
   For Worst Treatment of a Santa, the nominees are:
   _ Either the employees, the custmers, or both, at the Capital
Plaza Mall, in suburban Landover, Md. A black Santa at the mall
quit after complaining of harassment by co-workers who thought
Santa had to be white. The mall management blamed customers, black
and white, who ``expressed concerns with having a black Santa
Claus.'' The mall later issued a public apology and asked Santa to
come back.
   _ The Marshalltown Mall in Marshalltown, Iowa, which fired a
female Santa because she was _ you guessed it _ female. ``Parents
tell children that Santa Claus is a man, and the mall tries to get
as close to that image as possible,'' mall manager Scott Ball
explained. The mall told Ms. Claus, 28-year-old Tammy Medberry,
that she could go to work as an elf.
   _ The boy from New Zealand whose letter to Santa contained a
bomb threat. Either Santa brings a computer, the child wrote, or
the chimney goes kaboom.
   For the Best or Worst Performance by a Grinch, Depending on How
You Look at It, the nominees are:
   _ Whoever took the nativity scene from Ann Webb's front yard in
Pinetops, N.C. The only thing left was the North Star, still
hanging from a pine tree. ``When I saw what happened,'' Ms. Webb
remarked later, ``I said, `I hope Santa Claus doesn't come to see
them.''' She apparently hadn't heard about the Santa from Brazil.
   _ The burglar who stole more than $1,000 worth of toys from the
Salvation Army in Lufkin, Texas.
   _ The man, described as a ``wino,'' who chopped down the
Hernandez family's live Christmas tree in front of their house in
Inglewood, Calif., and sold it to an unsuspecting neighbor for $7.
``It's awful,'' said another neighbor, Luis Frias. ``Especially at
this time of year, and to steal that kind of thing. Everybody
around here is real depressed.''
   The envelope? Burn it, please.
</TEXT>

</DOC>