<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0222EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Penthouse-Gobie     12-29 0389</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Penthouse-Gobie,380</SECOND>
<HEAD>Penthouse To Publish Gobie Article in March</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DIAMOND</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Penthouse magazine has broken weeks of silence
by announcing publication of an ``intimate'' interview with Stephen
Gobie, the prostitute who had a relationship with Rep. Barney Frank.
   The March 1990 issue will hit the newsstands the first week of
February, according to magazine spokeswoman Leslie Jay.
   Frank, D-Mass., who is under investigation by the House ethics
committee for his involvement with Gobie, promptly dubbed the
Penthouse announcement Thursday ``a non-story.''
   ``My guess is the only problem (Penthouse) is going to have is
whether to classify it as fiction or non-fiction,'' Frank said.
   Penthouse publisher Bob Guccione, in a one-paragraph
announcement, said the interview would detail ``the subterranean
gay scene in the nation's capital, and its hottest players.''
   ``This is the most intimate interview ever published concerning
a sitting member of Congress,'' Guccione said.
   Gobie was paid a reported $50,000 to tell his story to Penthouse.
   In a news conference earlier this week, Frank dismissed the
potential explosiveness of the Penthouse article. He said it was
``nonsense'' to believe recent reports that the ethics committee
was delaying its investigation until it can review the Penthouse
article.
   Ethics committee Chairman Julian Dixon, D-Calif., also rejected
such claims, noting that any information Penthouse could obtain the
committee also could get simply by issuing a subpoena.
   Gobie already has testified before the ethics committee. Frank
has not yet appeared before the committee _ which holds all its
hearings behind closed doors _ and has not said whether he has been
invited to testify.
   Frank said he is anxious for the opportunity to show the
committee that Gobie's charges are untrue.
   Gobie has an unlisted phone number in the Washington area and
could not be reached Thursday for comment.
   The ethics committee investigation began with Frank publicly
acknowledging late last summer that he had paid Gobie $80 for sex
in 1985, hired him with personal funds to serve as a housekeeper
and driver from July 1985 through August 1987 and intervened with
Virginia probation authorities on Gobie's behalf.
   But Frank has denied other allegations by Gobie, including
charges that Frank knew Gobie was running a prostitution ring from
Frank's apartment on Capitol Hill and that the two had engaged in
sex in the House gymnasium.
</TEXT>

</DOC>