<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0113 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 2023EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama 2ndLd-Writethru a0565 12-30 0932</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0565,0957</SECOND>
<HEAD>Panamanian Bishops Urge Vatican To Hand Noriega Over</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS thruout to conform translation of bishops' letter to official
English translation, ADD Tass report that bishops and nunciate agree Noriega
should be released soon, U.S. troops search Spanish news agency for suspect.
EDITS to TRIM. No pickup</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserColor NY15, LaserPhoto MGA2, PAN7,8,9</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOSEPH B. FRAZIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Panama's Roman Catholic bishops on
Saturday urged the Vatican to hand Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega over
for trial in the United States or Panama, calling him ``the author
of abominable crimes.''
   Noriega, under U.S. indictment for drug trafficking, took refuge
in the Vatican Embassy on Christmas Eve, four days after the United
States attacked Panamanian military bases and installed a civilian
government.
   ``It is quite justifiably feared that should he be set free in
any part of the world, Mr. Noriega would in a short time be causing
turmoil, conflict and violence in this already long-suffering
nation,'' the bishops said in a letter to Pope John Paul II.
   Meanwhile, U.S. officials said troops searching for weapons
caches made a mistake Friday when they searched the Nicaraguan
ambassador's residence.
   A senior U.S. Embassy official said the soldiers left as soon as
they realized they were on diplomatic premises.
   Nicaragua's leftist Sandinista government retaliated by ordering
the expulsions of 20 American diplomats and telling the U.S.
Embassy in Managua to cut its support staff. The State Department
called the response an ``overreaction'' designed to reduce the U.S.
presence before elections set for Feb. 25.
   President Bush told reporters in Houston that the search was ``a
screw-up. ... It shouldn't have happened and that's been explained
to the Nicaraguans.''
   In its letter to John Paul, the Panamanian bishop's conference
described Noriega as ``the author of abominable crimes.
   ``The mere possibility that the former general not be taken
before justice provokes justified fear in members of the church,''
the bishops said in the communique, translated into English by
church officials.
   They indicated it did not matter whether he was tried in the
United States or Panama as long as there were guarantees for his
personal and physical safety, the death penalty was excluded and he
received a fair trial.
   The letter defended the practice of political asylum but added,
``this is a very special case.''
   A church source said papal nuncio Sebastian Laboa, the Vatican's
ambassador in Panama, approved the letter.
   The official Soviet news agency Tass on Sunday paraphrased a
communique by the bishops of Panama as saying ``the national
leadership of the Catholic Church and the papal nunciature agreed
to hand over Gen. Noriega shortly.''
   Tass did not say when the communique was released, or if it was
referring to the same one sent to the pope. The report, which could
not be confirmed by any other source, did not specifically say
whether Noriega should be turned over to the United States or to
Panama.
   In Rome, Vatican spokesman Joaquin Navarro said Noriega could
not be handed over to U.S. authorities but that the Vatican was
urging him to leave the mission on his own.
   If Noriega does so, he can assume U.S. troops surrounding the
mission would arrest him immediately. The troops, posted as close
as 10 feet from the embassy gate, have been searching departing
vehicles for non-diplomatic personnel.
   In response to Vatican protests, U.S. troops Saturday turned off
the loud rap and rock music that they were blasting near the
mission in an apparent attempt to harass Noriega.
   ``I am sympathetic to the papal nuncio's plea that the music was
keeping him awake while Noriega slept,'' the senior U.S. Embassy
official said.
   The U.S. search of Nicaraguan Ambassador Antenor Ferrey's
residence heightened tension with the Sandinista government, which
has long predicted a U.S. invasion in Nicaragua.
   The U.S. Embassy official, who spoke on condition of anonymity,
contended the troops did not know the house was a diplomatic
residence. Ferrey said he argued with U.S. troops for 75 minutes
before they went in, asking them to call American diplomatic and
military officials.
   A communique from the Southern Command said the troops had
``good cause'' to make the search based on a tip and that they
thought the Nicaraguan envoy's residence was somewhere else. Ferrey
said the residence was moved to its current location about a year
ago.
   The U.S. official said American troops ``courteously withdrew''
when it was determined the situation was a diplomatic one.
   Troops found caches of assault rifles, anti-tank weapons,
grenades, pistols and ammunition in the house, the military said.
The weapons were not taken.
   The United States has surrounded the embassies of Cuba,
Nicaragua and Libya to prevent Noriega associates from seeking
asylum, but it had not ringed the Nicaraguan envoy's residence.
   The U.S. Embassy official corrected an earlier statement that
Noriega adviser Mike Harari had been arrested. He said agents
arrested someone they thought was Harari but determined it was not
him. It was not immediately clear if the man was released.
   Israel Television, meanwhile, reported that Harari was in
Israel. It cited family sources.
   Panama City's international airport, closed to all but relief
flights since the invasion, will open to commercial traffic on
Sunday with flights by the Panamanian airline COPA, a COPA
spokesman said.
   Also Saturday, U.S. soldiers searched the offices of the Spanish
news agency EFE and several homes in the neighborhood.
   Andreu Claret, the agency's Panama director, later said some of
the soldiers told him they were looking for a suspected looter who
according to neighbors had been hiding in a neighboring house.
</TEXT>

</DOC>