<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0208 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 1750EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-CommodityRdp     12-28 0674</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Commodity Rdp,0699</SECOND>
<HEAD>Orange Juice Futures Soar Higher; Heating Oil Falls</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID DISHNEAU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Orange juice futures prices added to their freeze-driven gains
Thursday on news that Brazilian officials had halted orange-juice
exports to assess the Florida situation and decide whether to raise
prices.
   Near-month heating oil futures closed lower for the first time
in nine days as waves of profit-seeking sellers swept through the
market.
   On other commodity markets, precious metals retreated; grains
and soybeans advanced; and livestock and meat futures were mixed.
   All frozen concentrated orange juice futures rose the
5-cents-a-pound daily limit on the New York Cotton Exchange except
the limitless contract for January delivery, which soared 7.85
cents to $1.58 a pound.
   The January contract had fallen on Wednesday, perhaps indicating
the market had fully absorbed the price impact of the weekend
freeze in Florida.
   But rumors surfaced late Wednesday, and were confirmed on
Thursday, that Brazil had suspended exports of orange juice until
Tuesday. Brazil is the world's largest producer of orange juice and
a major supplier to the U.S. market.
   ``I believe that caused a little bit of panic on the part of the
trade and the speculators,'' said Celeste Georkakis, an analyst
with Cargill Investor Services Inc.
   Forecasts for warmer temperatures in the Florida citrus belt
spurred further buying of futures. A warmup would hasten the
falling and rotting of freeze-damaged fruit, frustrating the
efforts of orange producers to get it all picked and processed
before it spoils.
   Heating oil for January delivery ended sharply lower on the New
York Mercantile Exchange, but not as sharply as it was down earlier
in the session during a virtual tidal wave of profit-taking.
   The selling peaked late in the morning when the January contract
fell to 88 cents a gallon, 11.71 cents below the previous day's
settlement, after peaking at $1.02. The contract finished Thursday
with a loss of 3.31 cents.
   ``The contract had gained almost 20 cents a gallon in a little
over two days' trading,'' noted analyst Andrew Lebow of E.D.&amp; F.
Man International Futures Inc. in New York. ``Certainly a market
like that is due for some liquidation and I think we saw it today.''
   The recent gains reflected tightening supplies of heating oil
due to unusually cold weather.
   Wholesale home heating oil settled 3.31 cents lower to .28 cent
higher with January at 96.40 cents a gallon; West Texas
Intermediate crude oil finished 17 cents to 28 cents lower with
February at $21.50 a barrel; unleaded gasoline was .44 cent to 1.06
cents lower with January at 60.11 cents a gallon.
   Gold and silver futures fell sharply for the second straight day
on New York's Commodity Exchange amid a continued lack of investor
demand for precious metals.
   Gold futures settled $2.40 to $3.50 lower with February at
$401.40 a troy ounce; silver was 9.6 cents to 11.6 cents lower with
January at $5.15 a troy ounce.
   Soybean futures prices rose strongly on the Chicago Board of
Trade, leading the grain markets higher amid widespread rumors of
new buying interest from Eastern Europe.
   Soybean futures settled 4{ cents to 7{ cents higher with January
at $5.69 a bushel; wheat was } cent to 2{ cents higher with March
at $4.08{ a bushel; corn was 1 cent to 2\ cents higher with March
at $2.40 a bushel; oats were 1\ cents to 2 cents higher with March
at $1.54 a bushel.
   On the Chicago Mercantile Exchange, pork belly futures advanced
in reaction to a monthly Agriculture Department cold-storage report
issued Wednesday that showed fewer-than-expected bellies in the
nation's commercial freezers.
   Most livestock futures retreated in light trading.
   Live cattle futures were .08 cent to .15 cent lower with
February at 77.37 cents a pound; feeder cattle were unchanged to
.25 cent lower with January at 84.70 cents a pound; live hogs were
.40 cent lower to .07 cent higher with February at 48.85 cents a
pound; frozen pork bellies were .40 cent to .57 cent higher with
February at 49.75 cents a pound.
</TEXT>

</DOC>