<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0041EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-PeaceDividend-Vietnam Bjt   12-18 0757</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Peace Dividend-Vietnam, Bjt,710</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON TODAY: Post-Vietnam `Peace Dividend' Was Quickly Spent</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALAN FRAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Optimists who hope defense cuts will produce
piles of money that can be spent on education, deficit-cutting and
other initiatives, take heed: That's not what happened after
Vietnam.
   As the United States withdrew its forces from Southeast Asia,
the share of the federal budget devoted to military spending
gradually shrank from nearly half to about one-fourth. But the
money was largely swallowed by rapidly growing federal benefit
programs like Social Security and Medicare, by inflation and by tax
cuts.
   ``There was a peace dividend, but it was gobbled up
automatically by the formulas of entitlement programs'' that
provide welfare and other benefits to millions of Americans, said
Roy Ash, federal budget director from 1973 to 1975 under Presidents
Nixon and Ford.
   ``It didn't produce any discretionary money'' the government
could distribute among domestic programs of its choosing, Ash, now
a Los Angeles investor, said in an interview last week.
   The Bush administration is expected to seek a $292 billion
defense budget for fiscal 1991, which begins next October 1, when
it introduces its spending plan on Jan. 22. Because of deficit
pressures and diminished East-West tension, military spending
increases for future years are expected to be reduced.
   In 1968, when President Johnson announced that the United States
would begin to pull out of Vietnam, the U.S. military budget hit
its wartime peak: $323.7 billion, in 1990 dollars. By 1975, when
Saigon fell to the North Vietnamese and the last American personnel
left the country, that spending had dropped to $209.3 billion.
   During that same period something else was happening. A slew of
income support programs, including Social Security and Medicare,
began dramatic growth spurts as Congress voted benefit increases
and expanded eligibility. And inflation spiraled upward,
accelerated by the Arab oil embargo of 1973.
   Social Security spending swelled from $89.4 billion in 1968 to
$156.6 billion in 1975, in 1990 money.
   Medicare, which provides health coverage to the elderly and
disabled, jumped from $17.2 billion in 1968 to $31.2 billion in
1975, in 1990 dollars, as benefits were liberalized and medical
costs soared. Welfare programs ballooned from $44.1 billion in 1968
to $121.5 billion in 1975, in 1990 money.
   ``There were no particular plans for the adjustment'' to lower
defense spending, director Gordon Adams of the Defense Budget
Project, a non-profit research group, said in an interview. ``We
just kind of ran into the train wreck of the oil price increases
and inflation.''
   The U.S. pullout from Vietnam coincided with a jump in consumer
prices from 6 percent a year at the start of the 1970s to double
digits by the middle of the decade. That, coupled with rising
unemployment and a slowing economy, prompted Congress to enact tax
cuts in 1969, 1971 and 1975, stimulating the private sector but
further preventing domestic federal agencies from reaping benefits
from the defense reductions.
   The defense savings did not go to reduce federal deficits, which
were minuscule by today's standards and of minor political
significance.
   The government actually ran a $3.2 billion surplus in 1969 _ the
last time federal books were in the black _ thanks to a temporary
10 percent income tax surcharge imposed to pay for the war. It was
not until 1975, when the shortfall hit $53.2 billion, that the
deficit began to attract much attention.
   ``I was trying so hard to make it a political issue, but I
couldn't stir any interest,'' Ash said.
   Today's economic and political climate is so different from the
Vietnam years that it is difficult to draw many budget lessons from
that experience.
   In today's era of $150 billion deficits, few people expect
lawmakers to tack huge new benefit increases onto existing income
support programs. Indeed, the deficit is so important a
consideration that President Bush and many lawmakers _ including
some Democrats _ are already insisting that any defense savings be
used to help balance the budget.
   Yet benefit programs remain ever-growing and costly drains on
government coffers, with Social Security due to hit $249 billion
this year and Medicare expected to cost another $99 billion. The
Medicare bill is expected to grow by about 14 percent next year
because of ballooning medical costs, while Social Security expenses
should rise 8 percent because of growing numbers of people covered
by the program.
   That means tough competition for advocates of improved
education, health care, environmental initiatives, child care,
anti-drug efforts, transportation, public works projects, and other
initiatives.
</TEXT>

</DOC>