<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891225-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-25-89 1222EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-RetirementHomeFire 2ndLd-Writethru a0500 12-25 0972</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Retirement Home Fire, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0500,0999</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fire Kills 16 at High-Rise Retirement Home; Other Fires Kill 32</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY15; JC2, JC3 of 12-24.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 15 grafs to update with news conference, all missing
residents believed located, deleting outdated references to missing, and
updates with additional N.H. deaths and deaths today, picking up at the
16th graf previous, ``It took more.''</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DUNCAN MANSFIELD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHNSON CITY, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Firefighters today found a 16th body
after a fire swept through a high-rise retirement home, and 11
residents who had been listed as missing were believed to be all
safe.
   ``All those have been confirmed. They have been found,'' fire
chief Doug Buckles said at a news conference this morning.
   Officials said 10 of those who had been unaccounted-for had been
located spending the holiday with relatives or friends and the
remaining person was believed to be with relatives out of state.
   City safety officials said at the news conference that the cause
of the fire was still unknown, but it was believed to have been
accidental.
   The Christmas Eve fire injured 51 people, including about 25
firefighters, authorities said.
   About 145 people were living at the 11-story John Sevier
Retirement Center.
   ``It was terrible last night. It was a terrible ordeal,'' Samuel
E. Williams, 52, said this morning after Red Cross volunteers
served him breakfast at a motel where he and 16 other survivors
were given temporary shelter.
   Williams said he escaped his third-floor apartment through
billowing smoke.
   ``What really got to me, after we were out on the street and
looking up,'' he said, ``we saw people laying out their windows,
saying, `Help me!' And we couldn't help them.''
   Christmas Eve fires killed at least 32 people in five other
states. Among the dead were six people at a holiday family reunion
in Atlanta; a mother and four daughters in a Dallas suburb; four
members of a Pittsburgh family; and a woman and her three children
in upstate New York.
   Firefighters in Manchester, N.H., wept as they tried to revive
three children who died in an apartment-building fire. Their mother
died later at a hospital. Elsewhere in the state, one man died in a
house fire in Londonderry.
   Also in the New Hampshire city on Sunday, faulty wiring in a
chapel's Nativity scene sparked a fire in a convent nursing home.
Firefighters rescued 26 elderly nuns, two of whom were hospitalized
in satisfactory condition.
   And today, three young boys were killed at Zanesville, Ohio,
when fire destroyed their home. Frozen fire hydrants slowed
firefighters. And a fire believed started when a heater ignited a
Christmas tree killed four young children and seriously burned
their parents in Hammond, La., firefighters said.
   In Johnson City, about 100 miles northeast of Knoxville,
authorities confirmed 15 deaths Sunday night, and a search turned
up a 16th body early this morning, said Police Maj. Ron Street.
   A temporary morgue was set up at the Downtown Centre Courthouse.
   It took more than six hours to bring the fire under control.
   Fire Chief Doug Buckles said the building had a history of false
fire alarms, which may have caused some residents to fail to
evacuate promptly.
   ``We grieve for the families,'' City Manager John Campbell said.
   C.F. Harris, 78, escaped the fiery building, where he lived on
the first floor.
   ``What I'm going to do now? ... My heart medication is in
there,'' Harris said.
   It was the second fire in as many months at the building, which
was renovated about 10 years ago to bring it up to new safety
codes, Campbell said. The first fire was contained to one unit.
   ``The building does not have a sprinkler system, but it does
have a standpipe system at every floor,'' he said.
   ``We've been worried about this facility for some time,'' he
said. ``Not because there is anything wrong with the building, but
when you have that many people in a (high-rise) building, there is
always cause for concern.''
   About 25 firefighters were treated first for smoke inhalation
and later for frostbite, hospital officials said.
   Officials said 26 others were admitted to hospitals, where they
were treated for mostly smoke inhalation. At least one person
suffered serious burns, said Dan Blevins, spokesman for Northside
Hospital.
   In Atlanta, fire gutted a one-story wood frame home, leaving
relatives who gathered for the reunion stricken, grieving and
homeless.
   ``We were all there for a family Christmas. Now, five of my
relatives are dead, and the others lost everything,'' said family
member Juanita McColumn. Another body was found later.
   In Manchester, N.H., about 35 firefighters rushed into a burning
apartment building and found a mother and her two boys and a girl,
ages 2 to 5, dead.
   ``It was a devastating sight,'' said Norman Chaput, district
fire chief. ``The firefighters were carrying the children out, and
they were crying while they were giving them mouth-to-mouth.''
   In other Christmas Eve fires:
   _In the Dallas suburb of Garland, a 31-year-old mother and four
daughters, ages 2 to 9, died when a fire that apparently began
around a Christmas tree engulfed their home.
   _In Pittsburgh, fire tore through a home, killing a 60-year-old
man, his 26-year-old daughter and two grandchildren. Eight other
relatives were injured, two critically and three seriously.
   _In Little Falls, N.Y., Robert E. Thomas struggled to save his
family through a rear door of their burning trailer home, but his
27-year-old wife and their three sons, ages 2 to 6, died.
   ``He thought he kept hearing (son) Robby's voice calling `Daddy'
through the door. He kept yelling `Help me, help me get my babies
out!''' next-door neighbor Theresa Gressler said.
   Fires also killed four people in Swan Lake, N.Y.; one person in
Albany, N.Y., and a woman and her two children in Conshohocken, Pa.
</TEXT>

</DOC>