<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0226 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1322EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-Japan-ChristmasEve Adv24   12-18 0675</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Japan-Christmas Eve, Adv 24,0692</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv24</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 24, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Christmas Eve in Japan Becoming a Time for Romance</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID THURBER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Christmas Eve is becoming a time for lovers in
Japan.
   While people in other countries attach bows to packages, more
and more Japanese young people hope to tie a marital knot on
Christmas Eve _ or at least seal a relationship.
   Hotels are packed with couples who pay about the yen equivalent
of $315 a person for dinner shows and Christmas Eve together;
cruise ships are booked months ahead for $360 overnight cruises in
Tokyo Bay.
   Behind the relentless commercialism and repeated refrains of
``Rudolph the Red-Nosed Reindeer,'' the Japanese have taken
Christmas and made it into something uniquely their own, as they
have with countless other imported products and customs. Japan,
where the vast majority of people practice Shintoism, has about 1.7
million Christians among its 121 million people.
   On Valentine's Day, women do the giving, declaring their love by
presenting their men with chocolates, but for Christmas, men are
advised by magazines and TV programs to plan a Christmas Eve that
will win a woman's heart.
   ``It's a test for a man, whether he can provide the right
luxuries for one day,'' said the weekly magazine SPA.
   The Christmas Eve tradition for decades in the Japanese home has
been for the father to bring home a cake, frequently after a night
out drinking.
   Cake sales remain twice as high in December as in any other
month, but they are falling as Christmas customs change, according
to the Japan Western Confectionery Association.
   ``In the past, Christmas for most people meant Christmas cakes,
but now people are beginning to celebrate Christmas in other ways _
with parties and presents and family activities,'' the
association's Kenji Nagao said.
   But the custom has left a bittersweet legacy: the term ``unsold
Christmas cake'' often is used to describe unmarried women over age
25.
   ``Twenty years ago, Christmas Eve was a time for men to go to
bars and get drunk; there would be drunk men all over the Ginza
wearing silly hats,'' said Masaki Oka, sales planning manager for
Matsuya department store. ``But now Ginza bars are virtually empty
on Christmas Eve and it's becoming a family holiday.
   ``People now are interested in the personal touch, creating a
warm family experience together.''
   A custom much older than Christmas in Japan is the giving of
year-end presents called ``oseibo.''
   ``Christmas presents are completely different from oseibo,'' Oka
said. ``Oseibo gifts are given out of business obligation, and
people think only about how much they need to spend on each person
when they shop. But Christmas gifts are a chance to pick out a
present that you think will make someone happy.''
   Many of those gifts men give are presented before Christmas as a
way of enticing a woman to accept a date on Christmas Eve; at
least, that's the advice in an 80-page article on Christmas Eve
dating in the biweekly men's magazine Hot Dog.
   According to the magazine's survey of young women, 38 percent
said they made their Christmas Eve plans a month ahead.
   Spending Christmas Eve together is seen as a public declaration
of a relationship, and for those not ready to make a commitment or
afraid of being left at home alone, some groups of friends make
plans together for Dec. 24 far in advance and then make sure their
other friends know.
   It hardly seems to matter that so few Japanese are Christians,
though Hot Dog magazine recommends a visit to a romantic chapel as
part of a Christmas Eve date.
   ``A good idea is to pray together quietly with your
girlfriend,'' it says. ``Do it somewhere fashionable. Your
relationship will quickly become more intimate.''
   Years ago, the minister of a Christian church in Tokyo said he
was putting up Christmas decorations when a passerby stopped and
asked: ``Oh, do you Christians celebrate Christmas, too?''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, Dec. 24</NOTE>

</DOC>