<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891228-0145 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-89 2231EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mongolia-Reform     12-28 0580</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mongolia-Reform,0593</SECOND>
<HEAD>Demands for Reform in Faraway Mongolia</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM ABRAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winds of change sweeping across the Communist
world have reached distant Mongolia, where a newly formed
organization is demanding democratic reform.
   The Mongolian Democratic Union, made up of students, writers,
artists and intellectuals, has held two Sunday open-air rallies in
the capital Ulan Bator this month, a foreign diplomat there said
Thursday.
   The diplomat, reached by telephone from Beijing, said the
government had not interfered in the peaceful demonstrations and
the official press and television carried reports on the rallies,
saying they attracted up to 1,000 people. He said there were no
reports of arrests.
   Mongolia, ruled by Communists since 1921 and long a client state
of the Soviet Union, in recent years has cautiously followed the
Soviet lead in embracing ``perestroika,'' or reform.
   But it appears the recent dramatic changes in the Soviet Union
and Eastern Europe, which have been reported in Mongolia's press,
may be reverberating in this sparsely populated nation of vast
grasslands and deserts.
   Ulan Bator Radio said in a recent broadcast the Mongolian
Democratic Union's 15-member coordinating council had adopted a
draft charter and had petitioned the Great Hural, the nation's
parliament, for official status.
   Soviet reports said the union was demanding an end to Communist
Party influence over government affairs, debate on setting up a
multiparty system, a full-time parliament and establishment of a
commission to investigate those who supported past repressive
regimes. The reports said demonstrators shouted for an end to
bureaucracy and special privileges for those in authority.
   The size of the union, and the outcome of its bid for
legitimacy, were not known, but it appeared to have sympathizers
within official quarters.
   The party-controlled press, while not outrightly criticizing
today's leaders, prints articles about social and economic
problems. The party paper Unen recently noted that thousands of
innocent people had been victimized by repression in the past, and
demanded ``large-scale legal renewal'' to guarantee the rights and
freedoms of Mongolia's 2 million people.
   Unen also wrote that writers in the past had been killed and
imprisoned for their social convictions, and called for the
state-run Union of Mongolian Writers to be replaced by an
independent national pen club.
   Ulan Bator Radio also said that at a session of the parliament
earlier this month, members were outspoken in criticizing the
slowness of economic reform, saying fundamental changes in price
and wage systems had yet to be carried out.
   The Communist Party, in a plenary session this month broadcast
for the first time on television and radio, reasserted its role as
the ``political vanguard'' of the nation. But it also said it must
``render active influence on the process of reconstruction in all
spheres of social life by renewing itself first.''
   Jambyn Batmonh, a former university rector who became party and
state leader five years ago, told the plenum Mongolia has ``natural
interest in the experiences of reforms and renovation taking
place'' in the Soviet Union and other Communist countries.
   So far, open criticisms of the party have been directed at the
Stalinist purges in the 1930s and 1940s, when the nation's religion
and culture were suppressed, and the forced collectivization
policies of Yumjaagiyn Tsedenbal, ruler for 40 years until his
ouster in 1984.
   The foreign diplomat said direct attacks on current leaders are
still avoided, and the Mongolian Democratic Union is working within
existing legal frameworks, ``not wishing to break from the mold.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>