<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891222-0280 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-89 2139EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f BC-ForbesMostProfitable Adv25   12-22 0655</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Forbes Most Profitable, Adv 25,0670</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv25</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Monday Dec. 25</HEAD>
<HEAD>Liz Claiborne Most Profitable U.S. Firm, Forbes Says</HEAD>
<HEAD>With BC-Most Profitable-List</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Embargoed to Monday Dec. 25 by source.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Liz Claiborne Inc., a top women's apparel maker,
was the most profitable public firm in the United States during the
1980s, according to a survey by Forbes magazine.
   Liz Claiborne had an average 51.8 percent return on equity
during the nine years since it went public, placing it ahead of the
second most profitable firm, Rollins Inc., a pest control and alarm
system firm, which had an average return on equity of 47.2 percent,
Forbes said in its Jan. 8 issue.
   In compiling its rankings, Forbes said it considered only firms
for which at least eight years' worth of financial data was
available. The magazine said it evaluated 1,150 U.S. companies in
20 industries.
   To be considered for Forbes' rankings, a company must have
revenue of at least $400 million, or in the case of banks and
electric utilities, $800 million. Biotechnology firms do not have
to meet the minimum revenue requirement.
   Return on equity is a measure of corporate profitability
expressed as a percentage of a company's net worth.
   Forbes ranked the wholesaler Price Co. third with an average
return of 40.5 percent, while the apparel retailer Limited Inc. was
No. 4 with an average return of 39.9 percent and the publisher
Commerce Clearing House Inc. ranked fifth with a 39.7 percent
return.
   Cereal maker Kellogg Co. was No. 6 was a return of 38.9 percent,
General Motors Corp.'s EDS subsidiary ranked seventh with a return
of 37.9 percent, Highland Superstores Inc. was eighth with 37.3
percent, Student Loan Marketing Association was listed ninth with
37.1 percent, and Apple Computer Inc. ranked 10th with 36.6 percent.
   The median return on equity for the entire survey was 14.3
percent, Forbes said.
   Forbes noted that a company's average return on equity during
the decade may not necessarily be a good indicator of how well the
company has fared most recently. For example, Apple Computer had a
36.6 percent average return during the decade, but in the past 12
months has enjoyed a return of 43.2 percent.
   The magazine also pointed out that special dividends paid out
during a corporate restructuring could distort a firm's results.
   The most profitable industry group during the 1980s was the
health industry, Forbes said. The 39 companies that comprise the
industry according to the magazine's rankings had a median average
return on equity of 18.7 percent.
   The food, drink and tobacco industry was second, with a median
average return of 18.4 percent; No. 3 was entertainment and
information, with a return of 17.3 percent; business services and
supplies was fourth with 16.7 percent; and retailing ranked fifth
with 16.7 percent.
   The No. 6 industry was aerospace and defense, with a return of
15.7 percent; consumer nondurables ranked seventh with 15.2
percent; No. 8 was chemicals with 15 percent; insurance was ninth
with 14.4 percent; and financial services was 10th with 14.3
percent.
   No. 1 Liz Claiborne is based in New York, the home city for the
most industry group leaders in the Forbes rankings. Other industry
group leaders included Exxon Corp. among international oil firms,
Bankers Trust Co. among multinational banking companies, CBS Inc.
in the broadcasting industry, Wal-Mart Stores Inc. among retailers
and Lockheed Corp. among aerospace and defense firms.
   While looking back over the 1980s, Forbes also looked ahead to
the 1990s, and selected 20 firms that it said were best positioned
for the coming decade. They included Boeing Co., Kelly Services
Inc., Emerson Electric Co., Dow Chemical Co., Apple Computer,
Ryland Group Inc., General Motors, Johnson &amp; Johnson, PacifiCorp,
Consolidated Natural Gas Co., Walt Disney Co., BankAmerica Corp.,
Sysco Corp., International Paper Co., Humana Inc., Geico Corp.,
Lafarge Corp., Wal-Mart, Norfolk Southern Corp. and AMR Corp.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Monday Dec. 25</NOTE>

</DOC>