<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0125 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1658EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-BushText 5thAdd   12-21 0553</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Bush Text, 5th Add,420</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHN: to go.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Q: Will you bring any troops home by Christmas?
   Q: Mr. President, we now find out that last summer when we
thought that your policy was no contact with the Chinese
government, that you sent a high-level delegation there to talk to
them. Don't you feel that American people deserve to know that when
you say something not's happening, that it's really not happening?
   A: Yes, I do think they do, but I didn't say that. I said ``no
high-level exchanges.'' So, please look at it carefully.
   Q: But you didn't tell us that this was happening _
   A: Well, but _ no, I feel no obligation to do that. I feel an
obligation to keep you informed, but I have an obligation as
President to conduct the foreign policy of this country the way I
see fit, reporting under the law to the United States Congress. You
could say, ``How come you didn't tell me that you were going down
to invade the _ send in those troops down into Panama?'' Because I
didn't want to take a chance the information would get out. That is
the responsibility of a President, and I will continue to exercise
it while having 37 press conferences next year.
   She's got a follow-up.
   Q: Does that mean all kinds of other secret diplomatic missions
going on around that we have no idea?
   A: Maybe not of that magnitude, but there's a lot going on.
There's a lot of going on that, in the conduct of the foreign
policy or a debate within the U.S. government, has to be sorted out
without the spotlight of the news. There has to be that way. The
whole opening to China would never have happened _ the whole _ the
whole _ yes, if Kissinger hadn't undertaken that mission. It would
have fallen apart. So you have to use your own judgment.
   And you've got your job, and that is to find out absolutely
everything you can _ careful, I'm sure _ most of you are about
legitimate national security concerns, but I have mine. And that is
to conduct the foreign policy of this country the way I think best.
If the American people don't like it, I expect they'll get somebody
else to take my job, but I'm going to keep doing it, and we've had
a very open administration _ very.
   But once in a while, if I go to try to set up a meeting with Mr.
Gorbachev, we've got people here who scream, who say, ``You should
have told us that the day you wrote the letter to him.'' I don't
agree with that, and I was elected so I'm going to keep on trying
to do this with an openness _ I hope, a new openness _ but also,
the right of a President to conduct his business _ in this case of
Panama, to safeguard the lives of American kids.
   And the other one _ to go and see what happens. I know how China
works _ see what we can do, make a representation of how strongly
we feel against human rights abuse, but see what it's going to take
to go forward.
   Thank you all.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END BUSH TEXT _ 6 TAKES</NOTE>

</DOC>