<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0140EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-FarmScene     12-18 0837</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Farm Scene,760</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report Says Cotton Farmers Likely are White, Male, Fiftyish</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Agriculture Department study shows that
most of the nation's cotton is produced by a relatively small,
specialized group of operators whose main occupation is farming but
who often don't live on their land.
   Based on a review of 1987 U.S. farm census figures, only 19
percent of the nation's cotton farm operators reported another
principal occupation, compared with 45 percent for U.S. farm
operators in general.
   However, only about half of the cotton farmers lived on the
farms they operated in 1987, compared with 71 percent for farmers
in general.
   The study by Leslie A. Meyer and Scott Sanford of the
department's Economic Research Service compared some of the
characteristics of cotton farming with other types of agriculture
and how those changed since 1982.
   According to the census of agriculture, which is taken every
five years, the typical cotton farm operator is male, white and
approximately 50 years old.
   ``However, female, younger, and certain minority operators are
becoming more prevalent, and one would expect them to play an
increasing role in the future operations of cotton farms,'' the
report said.
   Women increased their share of cotton farming to 3.5 percent in
1987 from 3 percent in 1982, with the largest number of female
operators in Texas and Mississippi.
   Despite the gain, women ``were still under-represented relative
to the 6.3 percent operating U.S. farms of all kinds,'' the report
said.
   Although there is ``no definitive explanation'' for the gradual
increase in female-operated farms, the report speculated that the
trend may be attributed to several factors:
   _The willingness of women to identify themselves as principal
farm operators.
   _A possible increase in unwillingness among young widows to sell
their farms or leave farming upon the death of a spouse.
   _A rise in the number of young women who feel the call and have
the confidence to run a farm.
   Under a ``standard industrial classification'' definition used
by the Commerce Department, a cotton farm is one that derives at
least 50 percent of its total annual sales value from cotton
production.
   Although acknowledging ``there are many farms that produce
cotton,'' the study dealt only with those ``SIC farms'' defined by
Commerce. Those totaled 27,673 farms in 1987, up 32 percent from
21,041 counted in the 1982 farm census, reflecting further emphasis
on cotton among farm operators.
   By comparison, U.S. farm numbers in general declined to fewer
than 2.2 million in 1987 from about 2.4 million in 1982.
   Leading states for cotton farms were reported as Texas, 11,741
farms in 1987 and 9,242 in 1982; Mississippi, 3,176 and 2,692; and
Louisiana, 2,223 and 1,899.
   The study showed that in 1987 about 69 percent of the so-called
SIC cotton farms contained 260 acres or more, compared with less
than 65 percent in 1982.
   States with the largest percentage of cotton farms 260 acres or
more were: South Carolina, 76 percent; Arizona, 74.1; Texas, 73.7;
and Georgia, 64.5. In addition, 15.5 percent of South Carolina's
cotton farms were 2,000 acres or more, compared with 12.5 percent
in Mississippi and 9.8 percent in Arizona.
   At the opposite end, small farms of fewer than 100 acres
represented only 13.9 percent of the total SIC cotton farms in
1987, compared with 17.5 percent of the total in the 1982 census.
   States with the highest percentages of small cotton farms
included New Mexico, 33.8 percent; Tennessee, 29.7 percent; and
North Carolina, 24.1 percent.
   ``Both censuses demonstrate that the preponderance of U.S.
cotton farmers are white,'' the report said. ``The proportion of
minorities decreased from 5 percent to 3 percent between 1982 and
1987, with all states except New Mexico and North Carolina showing
declines.''
   However, the report added, ``The absolute number of minority
cotton farm operators increased in Arizona, New Mexico, North
Carolina, Tennessee and Texas. Mississippi had the largest number
of minority operators in both 1982 and 1987.''
   Minority cotton farm operators in both 1982 and 1987 ``were more
likely than white to own the land they operated and somewhat less
likely to be tenants,'' the report said. ``However, by 1987
minority operators as a group were more likely to be part owners or
tenants and less likely to be full owners than they had been in
1982.''
   The report added: ``This shift toward more tenants and fewer
full owners was also apparent among white operators, although
blacks and other (minority) operators exhibited a
disproportionately large drop in their incidence of full
ownership.''
   In 1982 and 1987, the age group of 55 to 64 was the largest for
cotton farmers, with an average age of 48.8 years in 1982 and 49.7
in 1987, with the youngest in Georgia (45.9 in 1987) and the oldest
in Oklahoma (51.9).
   ``Thus, the average age of the U.S. cotton farm operator
increased only slightly,'' the report said. ``The slim advance can
be attributed to the meager expansion of the average age range of
operators in the producing states.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>