<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0117 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 2109EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Procrastinators'Predictions     12-30 0424</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Procrastinators' Predictions,0447</SECOND>
<HEAD>Procrastinator's Club Makes 1989? Predictions</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VONDA PAIGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soviet leader Mikhail Gorbachev will become
known as the nicest guy on the ``bloc'' in 1989.
   Get it? Bloc. Block.
   The Procrastinator's Club got it and made several other somewhat
tongue-in-cheek predictions for 1989 Saturday.
   As usual, the procrastinators were very late with their
prognostications and right on the mark.
   ``We're perfect,'' club president Les Waas said Saturday.
``We've never made a mistake yet. I don't know why that is. I guess
because we spend a whole year putting them together.''
   The rich, the famous, the infamous, the political and the sports
inclined will have a rough and rocky 1989, the club said.
   According to the club:
   _Ronald Reagan will become half of a skinhead.
   _Zsa Zsa will slap slap a cop cop.
   _An oil company will try to ``Exxonerate'' itself after a tanker
captain fails to get a designated driver in Alaska.
   _Hotel queen Leona Helmsley will get an additional room paid for
with taxes that only the little people pay.
   _Pete Rose, although becoming known as a ``bettor'' player, will
be hustled out of baseball.
   _The United States will send troops to a Central American
country in search of a pineapple.
   The Procrastinator's Club, established in 1956 by employees at a
Philadelphia advertising agency, has been making its
Johnny-come-lately predictions for at least 20 years, Waas said.
But still the members have trouble convincing folks the club has
high-powered crystal balls.
   ``We go out on a limb. Some of these (predictions) are
unconscionable. Nobody ever believes us. Some of these are pretty
far-fetched,'' Waas said.
   Waas said he has been president, or rather ``acting president,''
of the club since it began.
   ``The nominating committee hasn't reported back yet,'' he said.
``Wouldn't it be somehing if I wasn't made president.''
   The club, which claims 6,500 members worldwide and another half
million who haven't gotten around to joining yet, is currently in
the middle of the 1978 membership drive, Waas said.
   ``That was a dull year. We didn't do much that year,'' he
explained.
   Other 1989 predictions include:
   _Donald Trump will somehow get his name in the paper.
   _Jim Bakker will be rewarded by not having to live with Tammy
Faye for the next 40 years.
   _Jerry Ford will turn out to be right on his statement that
``Poland is not a communist country.''
   _A star named Rob will sink to a new ``Lowe'' when his video
goes national.
   _Millions will go batty over Jack Nicholson.
</TEXT>

</DOC>