<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0948EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Sweden-Terrorist     12-21 0561</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Sweden-Terrorist,0578</SECOND>
<HEAD>Palestinian Suspected in Lockerbie Crash Convicted in Another Attack</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EVA JANZON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>UPPSALA, Sweden (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Swedish court today convicted Mohammed
Abu Talb, a Palestinian suspected in the bombing of Flight 103, of
terrorism charges in connection with a fatal 1985 attack on an
airline office.
   The 35-year-old Palestinian was sentenced to life in prison for
the July 1985 bombing of a Northwest Airline office in Copenhagen.
The attack killed one person and wounded more than 20.
   A co-defendent, Marten Imandi, also 35, was convicted of charges
in connection with the Copenhagen attack and was sentenced to life
in prison.
   In Sweden, life imprisonment usually means 20 years at most.
   The court found Imandi guilty of murder for placing the fatal
explosive and convicted Abu Talb as an acessory.
   The convictions were part of a series legal actions concluded
today against a terrorist ring involved in bombings of U.S.,
Israeli and Jewish targets in Copenhagen and Amsterdam in 1985.
   They were acquitted of another bombing in Stockholm in 1986.
   The court also sentenced Mahmoud Al Mougrabi, 24, to six years
in prison and his 23-year-old brother Moustafa to a one-year
sentence for their involvement in the 1985 attacks.
   By coincidence, the verdict fell on the first anniversary of the
bombing of Flight 103, the Pan Am Boeing 747 that went down in
Lockerbie, Scotland, killing 270 people. Abu Talb is a suspect in
that bombing.
   Abu Talb's possible connection with the disaster surfaced when
it was established he had been in the Mediterranean island of Malta
two months before the explosion, when investigators believe the
bomb may have been prepared.
   Shreds from clothes wrapped around the bomb could match clothing
that Abu Talb brought back with him from Malta. Scottish police
seized 15 bags of clothing from his Uppsala home Nov. 27.
   Legal expers have said that if he was indicted for the Pan Am
explosion, he could be extradited to face trial in a foreign
country. He likely would be returned to Sweden to complete his
sentence, however.
   Abu Talb, who listed his birthplace as the Sabra refugee camp in
Beirut, Lebanon, is a former Egyptian army soldier who deserted to
join the Palestine Popular Struggle Front.
   Police have taken extra security precautions at airports around
Sweden this week in anticipation of a possible terror attack to
mark the Flight 103 anniversary. Experts warned that a guilty
verdict could heighten the risk.
   The 100-page decision by the court in Uppsala, 40 miles north of
Stockholm, was distributed at the courthouse without a hearing.
   Meanwhile, a Swedish newspaper reported today that further
evidence had been uncovered linking Abu Talb to the Pan Am
explosion over Lockerbie.
   The Dagens Nyheter newspaper said police found a 1988 calendar
with the date Dec. 21 circled, the day the plane was blasted by a
barometer-triggered explosive concealed in a radio-tape player
inside a suitcase.
   Scottish police tried to question Abu Talb on Tuesday, but he
refused to cooperate. The officers reportedly left Sweden, and were
due back after the holidays to continue their probe.
   Lord Fraser, Scotland's chief law officer, has said no
prosecutions were imminent in the case and no extraditions had been
requested. He was quoted in London last week as saying the United
States likely would claim jurisdiction and any trial would be held
there.
</TEXT>

</DOC>