<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 0854EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Israel-Tutu     12-26 0510</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Israel-Tutu,0526</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tutu Defends Criticism, Accuses Israeli Leaders of Terrorism</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LOUIS MEIXLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   South African Archbishop Desmond Tutu today
defended his criticism of Israel's treatment of Palestinians and
said that former Israeli leaders engaged in terrorism in the past.
   Minister of Religion Zevulun Hammer told the Nobel Peace Prize
winner that he showed a ``simple lack of understanding'' toward the
problems of the Middle East.
   Hammer, who held a one-hour meeting with the Anglican leader,
was the only Israeli official to meet with Tutu during his five-day
Christmas pilgrimage to the Holy Land.
   Tutu has visited Bethlehem and the Christian village of Beit
Sahur in the occupied West Bank, met with Palestinian leaders and
prayed at Yad Vashem, Israel's memorial to the 6 million Jews
killed in the Holocaust.
   Israelis have been highly critical of Tutu's remarks, and he
told reporters that an Israeli shouted, ``Black Nazi pig!'' at him
during one rally.
   When asked if he would condemn Palestinian attacks on Israelis
as ``terrorism'' and whether he considered Palestine Liberation
Organization chief Yasser Arafat a terrorist, Tutu said the
definition of terrorism must include military attacks on civilians.
   Tutu also said Israeli leaders have practiced terrorism.
   ``There are people in high positions in Israel who did things
which they would now call terrorism, for example the bombing of the
King David Hotel,'' he said. He was referring to the July 1946
bombing that killed 91 Britons, Arabs and Jews.
   The attack on the hotel, which contained British military
headquarters, was carried out by the Jewish Irgun underground led
by former Israeli leader Menachem Begin.
   ``That was a terrorist act and Mr. Begin later became prime
minister,'' Tutu said.
   Tutu said he did not meet with Israeli politicians because of
his tight schedule, but added if he had met Prime Minister Yitzhak
Shamir he would have repeated his call for Israel to end its harsh
treatment of Palestinians.
   ``I would say to him that I cannot myself understand people who
have suffered as Jews have suffered inflicting suffering of the
kind that I have seen on the Palestinians,'' Tutu said.
   He rejected Israelis' criticism of his comparison of South
Africa's oppression of blacks with Israel's treatment of
Palestinians, which he has repeated throughout his visit.
   ``Some of the things I have seen here are things I have seen at
home,'' he said. ``When I find injustice in the world, whoever
perpetrates it must know that I will condemn them.
   ``If I am accused, as I am often accused, of being anti-Semitic,
tough luck,'' he said.
   Hammer, who joined Tutu in an informal news conference after
their meeting, said the bishop's views of the Middle East showed
``to my sorrow, a simple lack of understanding.''
   ``I tried to explain that with us, in Judaism, and in the State
of Israel, freedom is part of the rights of man and part of our
beliefs,'' he said. ``The ones who have been denied their
historical rights are us and we are the ones who were persecuted.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>