<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0905EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Panama 6thLd-Writethru   12-20 0853</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama, 6th Ld - Writethru,2 Takes,a0574,0874</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>U.S. Forces Try To Oust Noriega, Scores Dead</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads throughout with details of canal closing, more Bush comments,
scene descriptions, Noriega bodyguard saying Noriega safe; no pickup</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Waves of U.S. troops attacked
Panamanian military bases early today in an all-out bid to capture
Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega and break his tenacious hold on power.
   Mortar, machine-gun and cannon fire crackled across the capital,
and one hospital reported 50 dead and hundreds wounded. Noriega was
not captured and his bodyguard said he was in hiding, directing his
forces.
   U.S. troops were backed by warplanes and armored personnel
carriers and fighting raged into the mid-morning before Panamanian
resistance was quelled.
   By dawn, a pall of smoke lit by the flames of dying fires
covered the capital. Only sporadic firing could be heard, but
residents were warned to stay indoors and away from the fighting.
   Gen. Colin Powell, chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, said
in Washington that nine Americans had been killed in action, 39
were wounded and one was missing.
   Opposition leader Guillermo Endara, winner of May elections the
Noriega-controlled government nullified, was sworn in as president
and given immediate U.S. backing.
   President Bush, in a nationwide broadcast in the United States,
said Noriega was in hiding and ``the action is not over yet.''
   ``Tragically, some Americans have lost their lives in defense of
their fellow citizens, in defense of democray,'' he said. ``We also
regret and mourn the loss of innocent Panamanians.''
   The invasion by American troops is the violent climax of
Washington's long battle with the cagey military leader, who had
set up a succession of puppet presidents while running a military
empire that purportedly trafficked in Colombian cocaine.
   The bellicose Noriega survived two coup attempts, a losing
election, and tough U.S. economic sanctions while brashly flouting
Washington's futile attempts to break his grip on power.
   The Panama Canal, where about 30 ships cross the isthmus daily,
was closed at 1 a.m. because of the fighting, according to Panama
Canal Commission spokesman Franklin Castrellon. He said landslides
had caused the only previous canal closings.
   The capital's sky was bright with the light of gunfire for
hours; blacked-out planes and helicopters roared overhead under a
full moon.
   The U.S. assault began about midnight as forces dispatched from
U.S. bases attacked Panamanian military headquarters, which
witnesses in nearby apartments said was in flames at 12:40 a.m. and
virtually destroyed by 2 a.m.
   American troops from bases in the United States were airlifted
in on Tuesday to augment the 12,000 soldiers based in Panama.
Powell said another 9,500 troops from U.S. bases were sent to
augment the force.
   Bush said Noriega's ``reckless'' behavior had ``created an
imminent danger to the 35,000 American citizens living in Panama.''
   Fighting also was reported at a Panamanian cavalry unit about
seven miles east of the Defense Forces headquarters; and at the
Panamanian base Fort Cimarron, about 20 miles from the capital.
   Noriega's main bodyguard, Lt. Asuncion Gaitan, spoke on the
national radio network after dawn to say that Noriega was ``well
and in a safe place.''
   ``Don't anyone give up your positions. In the provinces, prepare
to resist. The attacks are going to continue when they find we are
not going to cede,'' he said.
   Gaitan, who is well-known as Noriega's prime bodyguard and is
with Noriega whenever the general is seen in public, then gave a
series of messages using code names and instructions. The codes
mentioned names like ``Alex, Omar,'' or said, ``Alex, take the man
to the hangar and Yeyo.''
   Others were more comprehensible. One was a reference to the
so-called civilian Dignity Battalions of Noriega loyalists.
   ``Dignity Battalions operate in small operations during the day
or look for positions and mix with the people who support you and
at night move and act against the enemy positions in the periphery
of the city,'' ran one.
   Meanwhile, casualty reports were climbing. Dr. Marcel Pena of
the Santo Tomas Hospital in Panama City said wounded had been
coming in all night and the number increased with daybreak.
   ``There are many more than 50 dead and an enormous number of
wounded,'' he said. Earlier, doctors had said there were at least
50 dead at the hospital.
   Hospitals were short of blood, surgical materials and other
supplies and were issuing international appeals for help, he said.
   Fighting after dawn was still continuing in Old Panama, just
east of the Marriott, and in San Miguelito, a poor district hill
district northeast of the city center where some of the strongest
Dignity Battalions are based. U.S. forces were apparently trying to
take the Panama Defense Forces barracks at San Miguelito and
helicopters were buzzing the area.
   On Friday, Noriega's rubber-stamp declared that the country was
in a ``state of war'' with the United States and named the general
head of state to deal with the threat. A day later, a U.S. military
officer was shot to death by Panamanians in what American officials
called an unprovoked attack.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>