<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0188 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0045EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-MarriottRestructuring Bjt   12-19 0762</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Marriott Restructuring, Bjt,0787</SECOND>
<HEAD>Marriott Selling Its Fast Food, Family Restaurant Businesses</HEAD>
<HEAD>With BC-Marriott-Glance</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOYCE M. ROSENBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Marriott Corp. says it will restructure its
business to focus on its profitable hotel and service segments and
jettison its weaker fast-food and family restaurant divisions.
   The nation's largest hotel company also said Monday it would
reorganize its corporate staff and lay off an as-yet undetermined
number of workers. Marriott said the restructuring would result in
as much as $325 million in pre-tax charges against its
fourth-quarter earnings.
   The company also announced the planned repurchase of 10 million
of its shares.
   Monday's announcement marked the third time this year that a
major hotel company said it would pare its businesses to a core
group. Ramada Inc. and Holiday Corp. have already begun their
restructuring plans.
   Marriott Chairman J.W. Marriott Jr. said his company's
restaurants could not keep pace with the growth rate of its hotels
and contract services divisions. He said he hoped overall profits
would grow 15 percent to 20 percent as a result of the
restructuring.
   ``We couldn't do both,'' Marriott said at a news conference at
his company's Marquis hotel here. ``We decided to concentrate on
hotels'' and contract services.
   Opportunities for restaurant growth have been limited by
increasing competition from pizza and other fast-food chains and by
a growing tendency for Americans to eat at home, Marriott said.
   Marriott said the company, based in Washington, D.C., would
retain its restaurants at airports and on turnpikes. Those
operations would be combined with Marriott's contract services
division, which supplies hotel management and food services to
institutions and companies.
   Marriott also said his company would continue to expand its
retirement community division. It currently has 12 communities and
hopes to have 150 within five years, he said.
   ``They're getting rid of some of their worst businesses,'' said
Daniel Lee, an analyst with Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc. ``These are
slow-growing, capital- using businesses, which had held back the
corporate growth rate.''
   Despite praise for the moves by some analysts, Marriott stock
slipped in New York Stock Exchange trading, falling $1 a share to
close at $33.62{.
   The company also announced it had completed the sale of its
airline catering division to the unit's senior managers for $570
million. That sale was expected to yield more than $200 million
after taxes, which would partially offset the costs of the
restructuring, J.W. Marriott said.
   Marriott said it would sell its 358 company-operated Roy Rogers
fast-food restaurants in the Middle Atlantic states in the first
quarter of 1990. Those stores were expected to register about $400
million in sales this year.
   Marriott also said it intends to sell the 434 units operated by
its family restaurants division, including 235 Bob's Big Boy, 79
Wag's, 31 Bickford's, 57 Howard Johnson's and 32 Allie's
restaurants. In total, these restaurants had 1989 anticipated sales
of about $440 million.
   The sale of Allie's represented a defeat for Marriott, Lee said.
The company had hoped to convert many of its other family
restaurants to Allie's but was forced to abandon the idea.
   Unlike Ramada and Holiday, Marriott does not plan major hotel
divestitures. Ramada sold its hotels and restaurants to concentrate
on its gambling operations and Holiday has sold its well-known
Holiday Inn hotels and focused on its casinos and newer hotel
chains.
   The hotel companies said they wanted to channel their resources
into their most profitable or expandable businesses.
   James Murren, an analyst with C.J. Lawrence-Morgan Grenfell,
said the slowing economy is one factor behind the restructurings.
   ``That squeezes all competitors and forces them to review their
business portfolio,'' he said.
   In addition, the hotel firms ``have broadened and diversified
away from core businesses and found those talents were not
necessarily transferable,'' Murren said.
   Sarah Sheckler, an analyst with Duff &amp; Phelps in Chicago, said
of Marriott, ``At least 50 percent of their profits come from
lodging, and they're focusing on their higher growth businesses.''
   Marriott said the stock buyback would be accomplished as soon as
possible. The company said it has repurchased 32 million shares, or
24 percent, of its common stock over the past three years, leaving
104 million outstanding.
   Marriott has projected 1990 sales of $7.5 billion. In its third
quarter, the company reported earnings of $63 million, up 9 percent
from a year earlier, on revenue of $1.93 billion.
   Besides its flagship Marriott hotels, the company also owns or
operates Courtyard, Residence Inn and Fairfield Inn hotels. Its
food service operations include Host, Howard Johnson and Hot
Shoppes outlets.
</TEXT>

</DOC>