<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0098 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1813EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Martin     12-26 0643</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Martin,0664</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prosecutor Questions Cancellation of Martin Autopsy</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALAN FLIPPEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PORT CRANE, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An autopsy on former New York Yankee
manager Billy Martin was canceled Tuesday at his family's request,
and a prosecutor said that could make it harder to charge the
driver of the truck in which Martin died.
   The Broome County sheriff's department reported slow progress in
investigating the Christmas night accident that killed Martin, 61,
and injured a longtime friend, William Reedy of Detroit, who was at
the wheel of Martin's pickup.
   Sheriff Anthony Ruffo said it would be another day or two before
the alcohol level in Reedy's blood was confirmed through laboratory
tests.
   Reedy was charged Christmas night with a misdemeanor charge of
driving-while-intoxicated and faces a fine of up to $1,000 and a
year in jail.
   Authorities said the pickup skidded off an icy road Monday
evening in front of Martin's 148-acre farm near Binghamton, 150
miles northwest of New York City. Neither man was wearing a seat
belt, authorities said.
   Ruffo said the accident happened at a hairpin curve that has a
history of accidents.
   Icy, slippery roads and Reedy's unfamiliarity with the area were
believed to be factors in the accident, Ruffo said. He said the
speed limit on the road was 55 mph, but did not know how fast the
truck had been going.
   Mechanical failure of Martin's four-wheel-drive pickup was ruled
out, the sheriff said. ``The truck checked out fine,'' he said.
   An autopsy scheduled Tuesday was canceled at the request of
family members, said Michael Doll, spokesman for Wilson Memorial
Hospital in Johnson City.
   Broome County District Attorney Gerald Mollen said he hoped to
persuade County Coroner Patrick Ruddy to conduct an autopsy in
spite of the family's wishes in order to pinpoint the exact cause
of Martin's death.
   But Ruddy said an autopsy would reveal little that an external
examination did not.
   ``He died, basically, of a fractured neck,'' Ruddy said. ``The
chest X-ray was reasonably intact, belly was normal, blood count
was normal. It's all in the neck area.''
   Reedy, owner of Reedy's Bar near Detroit's Tiger Stadium,
suffered a broken hip and possible broken ribs in the accident. He
was listed in fair condition Tuesday at the Upstate Medical Center
Hospital in Syracuse.
   Reedy said he and Martin had gone to a store and then stopped
for a quick drink at a Binghamton bar, said Deputy Steve Glanville.
   Mollen said it would be ``days, at least'' before he decides
whether to charge Reedy with anything more serious than driving
while intoxicated, such as manslaughter.
   The lack of an autopsy would not preclude further charges,
Mollen said.
   Martin purchased the farm in September 1988, three months after
he was fired by Yankee owner George Steinbrenner for the final
time. He said he was attracted to the area for its fishing and
quiet surroundings.
   The feisty Martin made a good name for himself by narrating the
Binghamton Symphony Orchestra's production of ``Billy the Kid'' and
speaking at a local girls' softball league dinner, but he and his
wife, Jill, were also in the news for confronting a group of
children riding horses.
   Mrs. Martin and an unidentified man with a gun chased the youths
off the land, saying they were destroying property and setting
fires, and Martin confronted the manager of the stable that
organized the ride. The stable said it had negotiated an easement
with the previous owner of the land.
   The Internal Revenue Service last summer placed a $35,562 tax
lien on the property, reportedly to cover an alleged underpayment
on Martin's 1987 income tax return. Laurie Ruffino, an IRS
spokesman in Buffalo, said the lien had been paid recently.
   In addition to Martin's wife, survivors include one son and one
daughter, both from previous marriages.
   Funeral services were not immediately announced.
</TEXT>

</DOC>