<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0145 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1754EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Students-Drugs 1stLd-Writethru a0572 12-18 0817</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Students-Drugs, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0572,790</SECOND>
<HEAD>Survey Finds White High School Seniors More Likely to Use Drugs</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 3 grafs after 4th graf pvs `The key ...' to UPDATE with
quotes from news conference. Picks up 5th graf pvs `The survey ...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAROLYN SKORNECK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A drug-use survey of students nationwide found
that white high school seniors are more apt to abuse drugs than
black seniors, according to figures released Monday.
   ``It goes against conventional wisdom _ particularly television
has portrayed the problem of drug abuse in the United States as a
black, inner city problem,'' said Doug Hall, vice president of the
national Parents' Resource Institute for Drug Education Inc.
   Atlanta-based PRIDE surveyed 296,180 white students and 59,898
black students in grades 6-12 at 958 schools in 38 states during
the 1988-89 school year, including students in inner city areas in
Atlanta, Chicago, Dallas, Houston, New York and Washington, D.C.
   ``The key is keeping teen-agers in school,'' PRIDE co-founder
Marsha Keith Schuchard said in a statement. ``Black students who
stay in school have significantly fewer drug and alcohol problems.''
   The focus on inner-city drug use by blacks ``feeds the
increasing expressions of racism that surface daily in our
country,'' she said at a news conference announcing the survey
results.
   ``The preoccupation with blacks and crack also misleads white
parents into underestimating the temptations and dangers their
teens face from the multibillion-dollar drug culture.''
   Judge Reggie Walton, associate director of the Office of
National Drug Control Policy, called drugs an American problem.
   ``For all too long, this problem has been portrayed as a black
problem, and I think the end result has been that there are some
people who have not really cared a lot about it because of that,''
he said. ``This is an American problem, not just a black problem.''
   The survey found that ``black students find cocaine about twice
as available as white students, but they use cocaine less than
white students, by a substantial amount,'' Hall said.
   About 15 percent of black students overall said cocaine was easy
to get, compared with 8 percent of white students who responded
that way, he said, noting that cocaine referred to both the powder
and its smokable derivative, crack.
   However, in the 12th grade, in which some 40,000 students were
surveyed, only 4 percent of the black students said they had used
cocaine at least once in the previous year, while 7 percent of
white students said they had done so.
   The picture changes a bit when the students were asked about
frequency of use of cocaine.
   Three percent of black male seniors and 2 percent of white male
seniors said they used cocaine ``very frequently,'' meaning once a
week, three times a week or daily.
   At the same time, 4 percent of both black and white male seniors
reported using cocaine ``frequently,'' meaning at least once a
month.
   Meanwhile, 11 percent of black male seniors and 12 percent of
white male seniors said they used marijuana very frequently, and 14
percent of black male seniors and 17 percent of white male seniors
said they used liquor very frequently.
   The students surveyed by PRIDE filled out anonymous
questionnaires that were spot checked internally with somewhat
duplicated questions to determine the truthfulness of responses.
There also were occasional retests of groups of students, Hall said.
   There was no overall margin of error because the results were
based on actual responses and the survey was not a scientific,
random poll.
   Hall said the survey found that, in general, the girls used less
drugs than the boys.
   ``The person who is least likely to use is a black female,'' he
said.
   In general, use of drugs is greatest for white male seniors,
followed by black males, white females and black females, he said.
   Among the survey's findings for overall drug use for high school
seniors _ boys and girls who had used certain drugs at least once
in the year before they were questioned _ were:
   _Hard liquor: 65 percent of white seniors, 37 percent of black
seniors. For high school students in general, 57 percent of white
students, 29 percent of black students.
   _Marijuana: 29 percent of white seniors, 17 percent of black
seniors. For all high school students, 24 percent of white
students, 13 percent of black students.
   As for intoxication levels, a higher percentage of white male
seniors than black male seniors reported getting very high, bombed
or stoned on liquor, marijuana and cocaine.
   For alcohol, the figures were 42 percent of white male seniors
saying they got very intoxicated vs. 22 percent for black male
seniors.
   The figures were 23 percent for white males and 15 percent for
black males for marijuana and 7 percent for white males and 5
percent for black males for cocaine.
   PRIDE was founded by a group of parents to fight drug abuse.
</TEXT>

</DOC>