<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0241 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0343EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-FloridaTourism     12-29 0374</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Florida Tourism,0387</SECOND>
<HEAD>Florida Hotels, Attractions Hope to Recover Lost Business</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Ice Refugees, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ORLANDO, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Frigid weather in Florida and the Northeast
disrupted travel plans for many vacationers, putting a dent in one
of the busiest tourist weeks of the year in the central part of the
state, officials say.
   But hotels, theme parks and other attractions expect to make up
much of the lost business by year's end, with sunshine and
60-to-70-degree temperatures dissipating the effects of a Christmas
weekend freeze that tied up airports and highways.
   Hotel occupancy and attendance at attractions began picking up
rapidly Wednesday after drops earlier in the week.
   ``Between Christmas and New Year's it's usually a bonanza. But
this year, no,'' said Ron Caimano, general manager of the Embassy
Suites hotel in Orlando.
   He said the hotel was only about 75 percent occupied Tuesday
because of cancellations.
   Northern visitors normally overflow attractions such as Walt
Disney World, the Kennedy Space Center and Busch Gardens during
this school-holiday week. Theme parks reported good crowds, but not
the usual long waiting lines, at the start of the week.
   Cathy Sauer, a spokeswoman for the newly opened 758-room Walt
Disney World Swan hotel, said, ``We had more cancellations that we
expected, more than is traditional'' for Disney hotels.
   Frigid weather in the eastern part of the country might have
forced some travelers to stay home, said John Rutherford, a
spokesman for the Orlando-Orange County Convention &amp; Visitors
Bureau Inc.
   Airports were temporarily closed in some areas of the state due
to the cold and ice, and Interstates 75 and 95 had to be closed for
a time over the weekend.
   Some theme park and hotel managers reported damage to
landscaping plants and plumbing from the weekend cold wave.
   The 1,500-room Marriott Orlando World Center hotel had to
contend with at least $10,000 in damage to foliage and water lines,
said General Manager Jim McDonnell. Many flowering annuals were
destroyed on its 200 acres and must be replaced, he said.
   At Boardwalk &amp; Baseball, spokeswoman Kim Sams said the park was
back to normal Tuesday after frozen pipes were repaired. It was
forced to close five hours Saturday and all day Sunday because of
power blackouts.
</TEXT>

</DOC>