<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0234 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 2330EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NoriegaPenPal     12-20 0431</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Noriega Pen Pal,0443</SECOND>
<HEAD>Noriega's Pen Pal `Disappointed' by U.S. Invasion</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEGAUNEE, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.S. invasion of Panama on Wednesday
upset the 12-year-old pen pal to Panama's deposed Gen. Manuel
Noriega.
   ``I'm really disappointed about what our two governments are
doing and I feel for the safety of Panamanian and United States
soldiers,'' Sarah York said in an interview with Marquette
television station WLUC.
   The schoolgirl said she was worried about the safety of Noriega,
who went into hiding when U.S. troops attacked.
   ``I hope that he's doing OK and nothing bad will happen to
him,'' she said. ``He's very nice and intelligent and seems like
the kind of person someone can trust. He never let me down and I
feel like I can trust him.''
   Sarah struck up a correspondence with Noriega following his 1988
indictment on U.S. drug charges. She has visited the dictator
twice, first as his guest last year, then in October on her own.
   Her parents, criticized for allowing the visits, condemned the
invasion.
   ``We are a family among the American people who support the
Panamanians in their struggle for self-determination and
sovereignty,'' Pauline York said in a recorded telephone message at
her home.
   ``We join the people and the nations of the world in calling on
the president and his military to end this invasion. To the
Panamanian people: Todo por la patria,'' which means ``all for the
motherland,'' the recording said.
   Sarah's father, prison guard Mitchell York, questioned U.S.
motives for the invasion.
   ``Do you think it's worth American lives to go after one man?''
he asked. ``Do you think it's worth alienating the entire
hemisphere against us for political vanity?''
   During Sarah's last visit, nine days after the October coup
attempt, Noriega called Sarah a ``meritorious daughter'' of Panama.
She said then she feared for Noriega if he ever was brought to the
United States.
   ``They probably won't even listen to him on trial,'' she said.
``They will just put him in jail.''
   The United States has tried to oust Noriega with economic and
political pressure since his February 1988 indictment. U.S.
sanctions depressed the economy, but did not budge Noriega. Two
attempts at coups failed.
   Sarah York went to school as usual Wednesday, but her parents
told officials to keep reporters away from the girl, said Negaunee
Middle School spokeswoman Mary Grober.
   The City Council has rejected Mrs. York's requests that the
Upper Peninsula mining town declare a sister city in Panama. City
Manager John Korhonen said the council did not want to get involved
with a hostile regime.
</TEXT>

</DOC>