<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 0726EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Czechoslovakia 1stLd-Writethru   12-21 0711</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Czechoslovakia, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0477,0735</SECOND>
<HEAD>Communist Party Militia Disbanded in Czechoslovakia</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 10 grafs to UPDATE with party militia disbanded.
PickS up 4th pvs, `Urbanek, who...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GIRARD C. STEICHEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Communist Party voted today to
immediately disband the despised paramilitary People's Militia in
another concession to the country's increasingly powerful
pro-democracy movement.
   The delegates' vote came at a special party congress aimed at
shoring up the party's plummeting popularity, the state-run news
agency CTK reported.
   The paramilitary force, which had been under the direct control
of the party, was disarmed on Dec. 3 and its weapons stored in army
warehouses.
   The militia last acted in January when it helped riot police
suppress a weeklong series of demonstrations in Prague.
   Disbanding the militia was among the earliest demands of the
pro-democracy movement, which began rallying hundreds of thousands
of Czechoslovaks last month and has since won broad reforms from
the party and government.
   Delegates were expected to elect a new Central Committee by the
close of the congress late today.
   Falling in line with the reform movement in Eastern Europe,
Czechoslovakia's Communist Party on Wednesday replaced its top
leaders with men who accept that the party will no longer enjoy
unquestioned supremacy.
   Delegates at the special party congress also apologized for the
harsh repression of the past. Today, they were expected to approve
a program aimed at bringing democratic socialism to Czechoslovakia.
   On Wednesday, the delegates sent a clear message that they want
a clean break with the hard-line policies of the past by dumping
party boss Karel Urbanek. He had served less than a month in the
post.
   The delegates gave the job to former Premier Ladislav Adamec,
who arranged the first official negotiations with opposition leader
Vaclav Havel.
   Urbanek, who served less than a month, was viewed as too closely
associated with the hard-line leadership that was ousted by the
``gentle revolution'' that has brought to an end four decades of
one-party tyranny.
   The delegates also elected Politburo member Vasil Mohorita first
secretary. Mohorita was a key negotiator in talks with the
opposition that led to the nation's first non-Communist dominated
government in 41 years.
   The chairmanship, the more powerful of the two posts, is
responsible for dealings with other political forces, which are
expected to increase as the country moves toward its first free
elections in 43 years.
   They are to be held in June or July.
   ``I'm aware things won't be easy in the future,'' Adamec told
the delegates in his acceptance speech.
   He said he took the job out of feelings of responsibility for
correcting the mistakes of the past, and he told the 1,500
delegates that their principal task was to ``not let the party
disintegrate.''
   The delegates also passed a resolution apologizing for harsh
policies after the Warsaw Pact invasion that crushed the 1968
``Prague Spring'' reforms.
   ``We apologize to our youth and all citizens afflicted by
unjustified repression,'' the resolution said.
   Last month, the party re-evaluated its stance on the period,
condemning the Soviet-led invasion. It was one of a series of
dramatic policy reversals made in response to the popular revolt.
   A top Communist official also delivered an apology on live
television Wednesday night.
   ``The Communist Party of Czechoslovakia apologizes to the
Czechoslovak people for its past policies,'' said Evzen Prusa, a
member of a working group responsible for guiding the Congress.
``It also apologizes for the events following 1968 and for
expelling and harassing the innocent.''
   In late November, the party ousted hard-line leader Milos Jakes
and others responsible for the crackdown after 1968. Jakes also was
among former leaders behind the 1970 expulsion of half a million
people from the party including Alexander Dubcek, the leader of the
1968 reforms.
   The party said his most recent failure was being responsible for
the brutal police crackdown on peaceful demonstrations Nov. 17 that
ignited the mass movement for an end to authoritarian rule.
   In a speech that illustrated the party's current crisis, Urbanek
told the congress that it had lost 66,290 of its 1.7 million
members in the past month.
   About 1,000 new members have joined, including 143 people purged
from the party after the 1968 invasion who were recently
rehabilitated, he said.
</TEXT>

</DOC>