<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 0615EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Dollar-Gold     12-18 0356</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Dollar-Gold,0375</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar, Gold Down</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dollar was mostly lower in thin trading in
Europe late this morning, and dealers predicted it will move only
slightly throughout the day as most investors have concluded their
currency transactions for the year.
   Gold prices also fell.
   Traders said a year-end holiday spirit has settled over the
market, giving little incentive to take positions or launch new
initiatives.
   They cautioned that the market could be vulnerable to sharp
swings due to the thinness of trading, but they predicted most
major currencies would hold to narrow ranges before the end of the
year.
   ``We've pretty much finished any major movements,'' said one
trader in Milan, Italy.
   ``This is a classic year-end market. Just as the summer market
usually shows a stronger dollar, the winter market shows a weaker
dollar.''
   A dealer at a U.S. bank in Frankfurt agreed: ``Most of the
players closed their books Friday and have withdrawn from the
market. We are also effectively finished for the year. There is no
more interest; it is typical for Christmas.''
   In Toyko, where trading ends as Europe's business day begins,
the dollar fell slightly against the Japanese yen, closing at
144.22 yen, down 0.08 yen. Later, in London, it was quoted at
144.26 yen.
   Other dollar rates at midmorning compared with late Friday:
   _1.7218 West German marks, down from 1.7225
   _1.5456 Swiss francs, down from 1.5485
   _5.8825 French francs, down from 5.8885
   _1.9415 Dutch guilders, down from 1.9480
   _1,285.50 Italian lire, down from 1,286.50
   _1.1609 Canadian dollars, up from 1.1606
   In London, the dollar rose marginally against the British pound.
It cost $1.6053 to buy one pound, compared with $1.6055 late Friday.
   Gold opened in London at a bid price of $412.75 a troy ounce, up
from $412.25 bid late Friday. At midmorning, the city's five major
bullion dealers fixed a recommended price of $411.65.
   In Zurich, the bid price was $410.70, down from $412.50 bid late
Friday.
   Gold in Hong Kong fell $2.10 to close at a bid $410.97.
   Silver slipped in London to a bid price of $5.61 a troy ounce
from Friday's $5.62.
</TEXT>

</DOC>