<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1057EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Burma     12-29 0372</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Burma,0384</SECOND>
<HEAD>Burmese Troops Seize Major Rebel Base on Thai Frontier</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MAE SOT, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Burmese forces backed by more than 800
rounds of mortar fire today captured a major Karen rebel base on
the Thai border, Thai border patrol police said. Dozens were
reported killed.
   The border police said a force of as many as 3,000 Burmese
soldiers fought hundreds of rebels for four days before overrunning
the camp at Pa Loo, about 10 miles southwest of the Thai border
town of Mae Sot.
   Rebel sources said hundreds of government troops were killed and
wounded in the attack.
   In Rangoon, the government spokesman, Kyaw Sann, claimed 50
rebels were killed in the victory. He said 22 government troops
were killed and 52 wounded.
   The Burmese had launched a simultaneous but unsuccessful attack
on the nearby rebel base of Kaw Moo Ra, said the Thai police on
condition of anonymity.
   The Karens, one of the largest of the diverse ethnic groups
fighting the Burmese government, have resisted the integration of
the Karen state into the Union of Burma since Rangoon gained
independence from Britain in 1948.
   Thai border police said that during the final attack, 600
Burmese troops crossed the Moei River into the Thai village of Ban
Mae Kon Kaen to attack Pa Loo from the rear, while most of the 700
defenders were positioned at the front of the camp, they said.
   At least 800 mortar rounds were fired at Pa Loo overnight and at
least 20 fell into Ban Mae Kon Kaen, the police said.
   During the fighting, some 500 to 600 Karen fighters fled into
Thailand before moving back across the border to another Karen base
farther south, they said.
   The rebel sources claimed that up to 300 Burmese troops had been
killed and another 100 wounded since Tuesday. Even more were killed
in the final assault, they claimed.
   Rebel casualties today were 20 killed and 13 wounded, they
claimed.
   Htay Tin, a leader of the All Burma Student's Democratic Front,
which fights alongside the Karens, said 50 students were thought to
have been captured.
   Thousands of Burmese students fled to join the rebels after the
military brutally crushed a nationwide uprising for democracy in
1988.
</TEXT>

</DOC>