<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 0517EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>b i AM-Panama 10th-Ld-Writethru a0518 12-20 1205</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama, 10th-Ld-Writethru, a0518,1245</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>U.S. Forces Battle To Oust Noriega, Endara Proclaims Himself President</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 2nd, ``We have...' to UPDATE with hospital
death toll. Picks up 4th pvs, `Noriega's whereabouts...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. troops fought Panamanian forces
early Wednesday in a bid to oust Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega,
surrounding his headquarters in a blaze of cannon and machine-gun
fire. Opposition leader Guillermo Endara proclaimed himself
president.
   ``We have many dead and wounded caused by the attack on the city
of Panama,'' national radio said.
   An doctor at the city's Santo Tomas Hospital said there were
about 50 dead at the hospital and hundreds wounded. It was unclear
how many of the victims were civilians and how many were soldiers.
   Noriega's whereabouts were not known. However, Maj. Edgardo
Lopez, head of the Panamanian Defense Forces' press office, said on
Mexican television that Noriega had been warned and was safe in
another part of the country.
   ``They (U.S. forces) have destroyed the headquarters because
they thought Noriega was there,'' Lopez said. ``General Noriega is
in another part of the country and is on top of the situation.''
   In Washington, White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater announced
U.S. troops were on a mission ``to apprehend Manuel Noriega.''
   ``We are there to apprehend him and bring him back to America to
prosecute him,'' he said.
   Late Tuesday, mortar, machine-gun and cannon fire echoed across
the capital as truckloads of American troops headed from U.S.
military bases toward the Panamanian Defense Forces headquarters.
   ``We're kicking ass tonight,'' said one U.S. soldier who stopped
reporters along a road about two miles north of the headquarters.
   The Britich Broadcasting Corp. reported Wednesday morning that
the headquarters was in flames.
   By 3:45 a.m., the fighting in Panama City generally had quieted
down although there was sporadic gunfire, including the booming of
artillery and anti-aircraft fire.
   The main fighting appeared to take place around the defense
headquarters at the western tip of Panama City, in the poor and
densely populated neighborhood of El Chorillo.
   Fighting also was reported near Paitilla, a small airstrip along
the coast three miles to the east of the headquarters; near the
Marriott Hotel, about six miles east of the headquarters; at Fort
Cimarron, just over 20 miles east of the city; in Colon, 50 miles
to the north; and near an airport in Chiriqui, about 200 miles to
the west.
   On Tuesday night, planes and helicopters roared over Panama
City. At the Marriot hotel on the capital's eastern edge, armed
Panamanians took 12 foreigners hostage.
   Among them were three reporters, including from The Associated
Press, the New York Times and the Reuters news agency. They were
released unhurt about two hours later.
   ``A lot of Panamanians have died and we could kill you. Don't
think they won't,'' one of the Panamanians told the New York Times
reporter.
   CBS said there was a report of a fire at the U.S. Embassy.
   The United States has tried to oust Noriega with economic and
political pressure since he was indicted on federal drug
trafficking charges in February 1988. U.S. sanctions depressed the
economy, but did not budge Noriega, and two coup attempts _ most
recently in October _ failed to unseat him.
   Noriega has denied the drug charges and claims the United States
wanted him out so it could renege on 1977 treaties that cede
control of the Panama Canal by the year 2000.
   U.S. troops in Panama had been on maximum alert and restricted
to base since a U.S. Marine lieutenant was killed by Panamanians on
Saturday in what American officials called an unprovoked incident.
   On Tuesday, U.S. military transports flooded into American bases
in the country.
   Early Wednesday, government-controlled radio said, ``The general
headquarters is being bombarded with heavy artillery ... We are
being invaded by U.S. troops in a synchronized plan.''
   A man on the 16th floor of a building with a view of the
military headquarters in the poor residential neighborhood of El
Chorillo said: ``El Chorillo is in flames,'' he said. ``You can see
a mountain of flares.''
   Two ambulances were seen heading for Fort Clayton, a U.S. base,
from the combat zone near Defense Forces headquarters about an hour
after the fighting began under a full moon.
   In a radio broadcast shortly after the fighting broke out at
about midnight Tuesday, Endara called on Panamanian forces to
surrender peacefully and accept his electoral victory in May 7
balloting.
   Those elections were annulled by Noriega.
   ``Men of honor of the Defense Forces will have an important role
in a democratic Panama that will belong to all Panamanians,'' said
Endara.
   Radio Nacional, the national radio station, was still under
control of Noriega loyalists and broadcast an appeal for all
doctors to go to Santo Tomas hospital, a hospital on Panama Bay
about two miles east of the Panamanian Defense Headquarters and
near the U.S. Embassy.
   It said the headquarters had been ``cruelly bombarded.''
   Fighting also was reported east of the Marriott, about seven
miles east of the headquarters, where a Panamanian cavalry unit is
based.
   An Associated Press reporter saw 24 armored personnel carriers
and at least seven trucks carrying American troops head in the
direction of Panamanian Defense Forces headquarters.
   U.S. soldiers surrounding the main Panamanian military
installations yelled over megaphones for the Panamanian troops to
surrender, residents living near the installations said.
   The Soviet news agency Tass, reporting from Panama City, said:
``Panamanian radio is reporting that military planes and
helicopters of the U.S. Air Force are bombing the central part of
Panama ... At different points of the Panamanian capital armed
clashes have begun between American and Panamanian units.''
   ``There is all kinds of hell loose out there,'' three young
Panamanian soldiers told an AP reporter.
   Channel 8, television station of the U.S. Southern Command,
issued an Echo level alert, its highest, and said movement by
unauthorized U.S. personnel was prohibited.
   The United States has 12,000 troops based near the Panama Canal.
   The Panamanian Defense Forces, controlled by Noriega, come to
about 15,000 men. Noriega also has armed citizen ``Dignity
Battalions'' of his loyalists.
   Further aggravating tensions after Saturday night's shooting of
the American, another U.S. Army officer wounded a Panamanian
policeman because he thought the man was about to draw a weapon,
according to Southern Command.
   On Tuesday evening, a New York Times reporter and a Reuters
reporter were detained for about an hour by U.S. military police
when they tried to enter Howard air base to determine whether U.S.
forces were landing.
   The Times reporter's notebooks were confiscated by the U.S.
Army, the Times said in New York, and the two reporters were
released without incident.
   The Panama attack was the first U.S. military invasion of
another nation since Oct. 25, 1983, when a U.S.-led force invaded
Grenada, southernmost of the Caribbean Sea's Windward Isles, six
days after Marxist Prime Minister Maurice Bishop was executed
following a coup by radical army officers.
   More than than 6,000 U.S. soldiers participated in the assault,
which cost the lives of 19 Americans, 42 Cubans building an airport
on the island and 24 Grenadian civilians. All U.S. troops have left
the island.
</TEXT>

</DOC>