<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891221-0151 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-21-89 1921EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-Political     12-21 0648</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Political,0669</SECOND>
<HEAD>Panama's Endara Orders Curfew; Makes Appointments</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Guillermo Endara on Thursday made
his first appearance in public since being sworn in and announced
an 18-hour-long curfew would go into effect immediately in the face
of widespread looting.
   The order had little initial impact and it was unclear how it
would be enforced. Panama City was a scene of chaos, with thousands
looting stores amid scattered gunfire. No police were seen on the
street.
   Endara said in a speech at the National Assembly building that
he will preside over a government of reconstruction and
reconciliation. He asked Panamanian exiles to return because ``the
military dictatorship has fallen.''
   ``One of first problems that we have to face is the problem of
anarchy and public order that now exists. Because of this I have
ordered the closing for two days, today and tomorrow, of all
private and public establishments,'' Endara said .
   ``With all these measures and other police measures that we will
take, we hope to re-establish public order before Christmas.''
   Although he mentioned two days of closing, the curfew he
proclaimed began at 2 p.m. Thursday and was to expire at 6 a.m.
Friday. He did not say whether it would be extended.
   Endara was sworn in as president early Wednesday morning by a
Panamanian judge in a private ceremony shortly after U.S. troops
attacked Panamanian Defense Forces. The Americans failed in their
effort to seize Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega, who last May annulled
a presidential election won by Endara.
   Endara said he talked to President Bush by phone and asked him
for immediate, emergency help in ``food and medicine for those who
are injured, hungry and sick.'' He said he was told aid was coming.
   Endara's speech was transmitted over the U.S.-controlled
Patriotic Network for Broadcasting the Truth, the only radio
station on the air. The speech at the National Assembly was
attended by about 200 people, most of them members of political
parties who opposed Noriega.
   U.S. military officials confirmed that Endara had stayed on a
U.S. military base from the time he was sworn in to the assembly
address.
   Endara appointed First Vice President Ricardo Arias Calderon as
minister of government and justice, responsible for internal
security. He named Second Vice President Guillermo Ford as minister
of planning and political economy.
   Arias and Ford had been sworn in along with Endara.
   Endara also announced the appointments of Eduardo Vallarino as
ambassador to the United Nations, Lauren Fabrega as ambassador to
the Organization of American States and Carlos Rodriguez as U.S.
ambassador.
   No other appointments were announced, and it was not clear when
he would get around to structuring a government.
   Arias said he was contacting police officials asking them to
return to their jobs. He said he had started contacting some
military ``to offer them an opportunity to define their loyalty to
the people so they can resume their service to fatherland.''
   The police force is part of the Defense Forces, which were in
large measure either resisting the U.S. occupation or were
dispersed by the fighting. It was not clear who would enforce
Endara's order, or any kind of law and order here.
   Also unclear was how much support Endara had among Panamanians,
or the extent of his grip on the government.
   But he emphasized the importance of restoring order to Panama.
   Francisco Rodriguez, who was appointed Noriega's provisional
president after election results were annulled, told reporters
Wednesday, ``We are prepared to resist.''
   Rodriguez was apparently in hiding Thursday.
   In elections held May 7, Endara beat Noriega's handpicked
presidential candidate by a 3-1 margin, according to international
observers. Noriega nullified the results, ignoring the outcry at
home and abroad.
   Endara is a member of the Liberal Authentic Party and ran for
president as the compromise candidate of an eight-party
anti-Noriega alliance.
</TEXT>

</DOC>