<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891224-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-24-89 1025EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Panama     12-24 0874</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Panama,0903</SECOND>
<HEAD>Top Noriega Military Leader Surrenders</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A military leader charged with drug
smuggling with Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega pledged loyalty to the
new government and said he will submit to U.S. military authority,
officials said Sunday.
   Col. Luis del Cid, commander of the 5th Military Zone, held a
news conference Saturday in the western city of David to make his
announcement. Details of the development did not reach the capital
until Sunday.
   U.S. airplanes and helicopters flew observation patrols over the
capital Sunday. No airborne fire or bombing was heard, but gunfire,
heavy at times, crackled in some streets in the working-class
neighborhood of San Miguelitos.
   The U.S.-installed civilian government of President Guillermo
Endara began forming a security force to quell looting and
lawlessness in the streets.
   About 2,000 U.S. troop reinforcements, including a helicopter
company, were sent Saturday, the fourth day of the largest U.S.
combat operation since the Vietnam War, boosting the U.S. troop
strength in the country to 26,000.
   Noriega, the object of a massive U.S. search, remained at large.
   The number of U.S. servicemen killed in the five days of
fighting rose to 25. Two American dependents also have been killed,
241 troops wounded and one was missing. The U.S. military said 139
Panamanian soldiers have died and 95 have been wounded. At least
260 Panamanian civilians have been killed, according to Dr. Elmer
Miranda, director of Santo Tomas Hospital.
   The U.S. Southern Command said 2,250 people have been detained.
   Del Cid, long one of Noriega's principal associates, said
concern for the security of his 10 children weighed heavily in his
decision not to resist the U.S. invasion and occupation force.
   U.S. troops had not reached David, 210 miles west of Panama
City, by early Sunday. The commander ordered David's airfield blown
up Wednesday to prevent the landing of American aircraft.
   Noriega, Del Cid and 14 others were indicted on drug charges in
U.S. federal court in Miami in February 1988.
   Del Cid told reporters his officers should be considered during
formation of a Panamanian military force to replace the routed
Defense Forces of Noriega.
   He also presided over the public surrender of arms by more than
100 members of local ``Dignity Battalions,'' paramilitary units
loyal to Noriega.
   U.S. military authorities were unavailable for comment early
Sunday as to whether Del Cid would be arrested and flown to Florida
for trial.
   Noriega's Dignity Battalions have surprised the U.S. military
with their strength and endurance. Joined by an unknown number of
soldiers and officers from the 15,000-member Defense Forces, they
turned to guerrilla warfare.
   The battalions are ``increasing their activities of harassing
attacks with small arms and mortar fire, threatening the civilian
population and hostage-taking,'' Lt. Col. Jerry Marguila, spokesman
for the U.S. Southern Command, said.
   Earlier, Gen. Maxwell Thurman, the Southern Command chief, said
the battalions are believed to have about 1,800 members and to be
operating in groups of about a dozen.
   An Air Force plane repeatedly bombed a hilltop position of
loyalists Saturday in San Miguelito, and dozens of troops then
descended on the district. Residents said eight houses were
destroyed in the bombing, aimed at a house that reportedly stocked
weapons for Noriega supporters.
   Endara, sworn in as president Wednesday at the start of the
invasion, said he did not agree with the intervention but could
work with the Americans.
   The invasion was ``like a kick in the head,'' he said in an
interview. ``It was not the best thing I would have thought.''
   ``We were not really consulted,'' said Endara. He said he was
told of the plans two or three hours before the first attacks were
launched.
   ``I would have been happier without an intervention,'' he said.
Plans for maintaining public order should have been laid in
advance, he said.
   Panama City is a busy duty-free commercial center jammed with
stores that before the political crisis did a booming business in
imported electronic equipment, cameras, watches, clothes, cloth and
other merchandise.
   Looters began ransacking its well-stocked supermarkts and other
stores hours after the invasion began and by Saturday hadn't
stopped.
   Citizens took the law into their own hands, forming patrols and
building barricades to protect their homes.
   Twenty members of the new public safety force were sworn in
Friday, and more were to be sworn in over the weekend, Endara said.
All the members, including the force commander, Col. Roberto
Armijo, had been members of the Noriega-run police force, which was
part of the Defense Forces.
   ``They swore allegiance to a new president, a new constitution
and democracy,'' Endara said.
   Parts of the city of 1 million were in ruins from the U.S.
bombing and debris from the looting littered the streets.
   Supplies of food and medicine were dwindling.
   ``We are trying to open the airport and trying to open the
Bridge of the Americas so we can bring in medicine and food,''
Endara said. The bridge is the main crossing over the Panama Canal,
which divides the country in two.
   On Saturday, Noriega supporters released Jon Meyersohn, a CBS
News producer seized Wednesday at the Marriott Hotel, and Doug
Mullen, an executive with GTE who was taken along with Meyersohn.
</TEXT>

</DOC>