<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0202EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-IndustrialOutlook     12-29 0692</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Industrial Outlook,690</SECOND>
<HEAD>High-Tech Industries Are Expected to Do Well in 1990</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN CRUTSINGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Economics Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government, making its annual forecast of
winners and losers in American business, says jet aircraft and
other high-technology areas will be strong in 1990, but automakers
and construction firms will not fare as well.
   The Commerce Department assessed the prospects of 350 U.S.
industries for its 31st edition of the ``U.S. Industrial Outlook.''
   On the industrial side, it predicted that three-fourths of the
193 manufacturing firms it reviewed should enjoy rising shipments
next year while 18 percent will suffer declines and the rest will
have stagnant shipments.
   It predicted a median growth rate in manufacturing shipments of
2 percent next year, after removing the effects of inflation. That
would compare with estimated growth of 2.2 percent this year and
2.5 percent in 1988.
   The department predicted that service industries, especially
those providing information and health care, would outperform the
manufacturing sector.
   Commerce Undersecretary J. Michael Farren, briefing reporters on
the forecast Thursday, said the United States is evolving steadily
into an ``information economy.''
   ``Industries involved in the collection, processing and
communication of information are among the fastest growing,'' he
said.
   For 1990, the government projected the fastest growth in
services would be in satellite communication and electronic
information services, both forecast to enjoy revenue gains of 20
percent next year.
   Computer software, data processing, management consulting,
medical services and the cable television industry all were
projected to have growth rates of 10 percent or higher.
   In manufacturing, the big winners in 1990 were expected to be
the makers of surgical and medical instruments, with a projected 10
percent rise in shipments, followed by makers of surgical supplies,
with shipments forecast to be up by 9 percent.
   The biggest loser in manufacturing was forecast to be makers of
household washers and dryers, where shipments were projected to
decline by 5 percent, followed by glass makers, facing a forecasted
4.9 percent drop in shipments.
   Both of those industries are tied closely to housing
construction, which is expected to be lackluster next year.
   Overall, construction was expected to show no gains as a modest
increase in housing construction will be offset by a decline in
non-residential construction, reflecting expected declines in
office and hotel construction, two sectors with high vacancy rates.
   Another key sector likely to perform poorly next year is autos.
Car sales were projected to drop another 1 percent to 9.9 million
units in 1990 following a 5 percent fall in 1989.
   Many of the industries that are not expected to do well in 1990
are closely tied to the auto or construction sectors, including
producers of construction materials, big-ticket household
appliances and steel.
   Steel shipments should drop by 4 percent in 1990, down to a
level of 78 million tons. While that would be the lowest level
since 1987, it still would be above the depressed sales recorded
from 1982 through 1986.
   Farren said that U.S. export sales, which have been one of the
economy's main supports over the past two years, will continue to
rise next year although the trade deficit will show only a small
improvement, in part because U.S. demand for imports remains high.
   Among the exporting industries expected to do the best are
aircraft makers, chemical producers and businesses catering to
foreign tourists.
   ``For the first time, receipts from foreigners traveling in the
United States will exceed expenditures by Americans traveling
abroad,'' Farren said, forecasting that the surplus in travel will
lower the U.S. trade deficit by about $1 billion next year.
   In 1989, shipments of civilian aircraft surpassed military
aircraft shipments for the first time since 1981 and the government
forecast that trend will continue. Based on record orders already
received, the department predicted approximately 512 deliveries of
commercial jetliners in 1990, more than three times the level of
commercial shipments just six years ago.
   Chemicals, the leading U.S. export industry, will see moderate
growth in 1990 with export sales topping $38 billion, enough to
generate a $16 billion surplus over the amount of chemical products
expected to be imported into the United States.
</TEXT>

</DOC>