<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891220-0105 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-89 1212EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r k BC-EditorialRdp 3Takes   12-20 0849</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Editorial Rdp, 3 Takes,0880</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are excerpts from recent editorials in newspapers
throughout the country:
   Dec. 18
   Fort Worth (Texas) Star-Telegram on military cuts:
   As the Defense Department budget shrinks in response to the
improving climate of superpower relations and the unravelling of
the Soviet Union's satellite system in Eastern Europe, intense
internecine warfare already has erupted among the different
branches of the U.S. military over the available bucks.
   That is evidenced in the reaction of Marine Corps planners to
Army plans to trim down and tailor its forces. ... The Marine Corps
contends that the Army would be trespassing upon its mission and
attempting to do something that the Marine Corps can do better. ...
   By 1995, Army personnel would be reduced from 764,000 to
630,000. About 70,000 of the 220,000 troops now stationed in Europe
would be brought home. More emphasis would be placed on airborne,
air assault and light infantry divisions, effectively transforming
the Army into a contingency force capable of being deployed
worldwide.
   Far beit from mere civilians to decide which point of view is
the more correct militarily. But it doesn't take a general to
figure out that the real quarrel is about how the reduced Defense
Department pie will be sliced.
   Over the years, interservice rivalry has bedeviled defense
budgeting. With the cutbacks that are coming, however, the separate
branches may be forced to take a more comprehensive view of
national security needs and learn to fit their plans into the big
picture.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Dec. 18
   The Tulsa (Okla.) Tribune on open skies:
   Almost 30 years after American pilot Gary Powers was brought
down by a surface-to-air missile as he flew a U-2 spy plane over
the Soviet Union, NATO, at U.S. urging, is prepared to allow
overflights by Warsaw Pact aircraft. This could be a major break in
East-West tensions provided that the proposal works both ways.
   It was President Dwight D. Eisenhower who proposed a policy of
``Open Skies,'' but the Soviets, mired in their traditional
paranoia, rejected the idea. Today, while nothing seems out of the
question, it still will require a major attitude adjustment by the
Soviets if overflights are to become routine military activity. ...
   Here is a chance for the Soviets to prove that glasnost extends
to the skies, too.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Dec. 14
   The Free Press, Mankato, Minn., on U.S.-China relations:
   When it comes to diplomacy, George Bush believes in the personal
touch.
   Bush prepared for the Malta summit with a series of telephone
calls to other world leaders, and it's generally conceded that the
president's penchant for handwritten notes, phone chats and
informal get-togethers has eased the frictions that are inevitable
even between allies.
   But sometimes Bush puts too much stock in such methods. Such is
the case with China.
   Bush was the envoy to Beijing for a while in the 1970s, and he
believes that he and China's leaders are personal friends.
   Bush's eagerness to overlook the bloodshed under the nose of
Deng Xiao-Ping is pathetic.
   Bush is all too eager to forget about this spring's violence in
Tiananmen Square. At the behest of the Chinese government, he
vetoed a bill that would allow Chinese students already in the
United States to stay _ even though most of them face a dangerous
future should they return home today. ...
   Bush wants business as usual with China. The problem is that as
long as Deng and his cohorts run the show, business as usual comes
down to death and repression. We can do better than that.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Dec. 15
   The Courier-Tribune, Asheboro, N.C., on U.S.-China relations:
   Last June when the Chinese authorities brutally quashed
students' peaceful protest for democracy in Tiananmen Square,
Americans were horrified. ...
   (W)hen President Bush sent three diplomatic officals to meet
with the Chinese authorities, we were incredulous.
   Acting under unfortunate aplomb, Bush saw a need for our country
to inform Chna on the happenings of the Malta summit. And
apparently that need eclipsed the memory of June's massacre: Bush's
move comes off as a slap in the face of the student protesters who
lost their lives on June 4 and in countless executions since.
   America cannot continue to cry democratic wolf. As a nation, we
support and defend democracy and human rights around the world _ in
the Philippines, Central America and Eastern Europe. ...
   Yet our top officials also take tea with top-level Chinese
officials, a move that sends a worldwide message that all is well
on the Chinese-American front.
   The President cannot undo his diplomatic lapse of reason, but
America can try to temper the negative ramifications of this visit.
We can continue economic sanctions begun last June against China.
Congress can override Bush's veto of a bill that would have allowed
Chinese students fearful of returning home to stay in America. And
Bush can keep his diplomatic officials out of Chinese conference
rooms.
   Otherwise, what's to prevent the rest of the world, particularly
as the nations of Eastern Europe cut their democratic teeth, from
doubting the sincerity of our support?
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>