<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 0154EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Bush-Pay     12-27 0329</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bush-Pay,300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Signs Order Implementing Pay Hikes</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Top government salaries will rise by up to 35
percent in the next 13 months, under an executive order signed by
President Bush that carries out the recently enacted pay raise and
ethics bill.
   Also under the plan, all federal workers will receive a 3.6
percent cost-of-living pay increase.
   The order, signed by Bush on Tuesday at the presidential retreat
at Camp David, Md., follows his signature earlier this month on the
pay raise and ethics bill.
   The measure will raise top government salaries by up to 35
percent over the next 13 months, with House salaries jumping from
the current $89,500 to $96,600 in 1990 and more than $120,000 in
1991, plus a cost-of-living adjustment.
   But by then the 435 members of the House will be barred from
accepting honoraria, generally fees for making speeches.
   Senate salaries would climb in 1990 from $89,500 to $98,400. But
senators balked at giving up their honoraria. The new law would not
bar speaking fees for senators, but they also would not get the big
jump in salaries in 1991 that the House gets.
   Senators could keep $26,900 in honoraria compared to $35,800
presently.
   Federal judges and top executive branch officials also would get
an immediate 4.1 percent raise and 3.6 percent, compounded on that,
on Jan. 1, 1990, as a catch-up for two years without a
cost-of-living adjustment.
   House employees and other top federal executive and judicial
officials also would be barred from accepting speech fees beginning
in 1991. Currently, House members are limited to earning speech
fees equivalent to 30 percent of their salary. Senators can make up
to 40 percent, but that will fall with their pay increase to
slightly more than 27 percent.
   Under the pay package, top-level members of the executive
service level, who now earn a maximum of $99,500, would earn up to
$107,300 under the legislation and the executive order signed by
Bush.
</TEXT>

</DOC>