<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0138 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 1724EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-BushText ??Takes   12-18 0819</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Bush Text, ?? Takes,650-up</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Sees `Pretty Good Year' in Assessment of 1989</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a transcript of President Bush's
interview on Monday with The Associated Press and three other news
agencies.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   BUSH: Well, I understand it, this is to review the calendar of
1989, so let me just click off a couple of areas that have been of
keen interest to me, and then be glad to take some questions.
   First, in foreign policy _
   Q: No, I was trying to see if my _ (laughter) _ you may
continue. (laughter.)
   BUSH: No, but we have established a new course of relations with
the Soviet Union. I continue to feel the Gorbachev meeting was
extraordinarily helpful in a lot of ways. And we are determined to
move forward with the CFE proposal that I made at NATO. I think
that next year's summit, which has now been set _ was set in '89,
will be fulfilled in 1990 _ will be a driving factor in other arms
control agreements. I'd like to see the START agreement finished by
then. But I think in general, the Soviets would also like to see
that.
   We've talked about, with the Soviet Union, given the
unprecedented changes in Eastern Europe and in the Soviet Union,
talked about _ obviously about reforms and how these Eastern
European countries, and indeed, the Soviet Union, is trying to go
forward on the economic side of perestroika.
   We've set a course for guiding our actions with Eastern Europe.
As you know, Jim Baker was over at NATO following my visit, and
that he talked there about the future and how the United States
would continue to interact, not just with the EC, but foreseeing an
expanded role for NATO. We've obviously moved to help Poland and
Hungary in specific ways. I tried very hard during this year to
reach new levels of consultation with heads of state and
government, and I'm going to continue that next year. But it wasn't
limited, obviously, to Eastern Europe. We've had a lot of
consultations in this hemisphere and in Asia as well.
   We see democracy on the move, and I want to be sure in 1990 that
we play an active and appropriate role in encouraging democratic
change and in being helpful to the countries that are going through
unprecedented change.
   You're familiar with the domestic agenda. I'm disappointed in
some ways that we didn't bring to fruition the changes in the Clean
Air Act on the environment. And the education summit was deemed by
most, I believe, to be a success, and we are now following up.
Indeed, some of the governors were here last week to discuss a
follow-on to the declarations coming out of the summit.
   I was happy that at the end of the year we've got some ethics
legislation passed, and that _ there were other items that _ the
crime package didn't go quite as _ the way I want to see it. We
need to move on it now in toto. We've tried to push forward our
thought on child care, but obviously the Congress has some
different views on that.
   On the minimum wage, we took the position what the minimum wage
ought to be. Congress tried to exceed that and to veto the
legislation, and that was passed in accordance with my wishes _ the
program that I set out earlier. And the S&amp;L legislation was a major
accomplishment, but I continue to worry about the S&amp;Ls.
   The Brady plan on Third World debt received a lot of support
around the world, and I _ again, we've got to follow through on
that _ not just us, but a lot of these private banks, the private
banks not just in the United States, but in Europe and elsewhere.
So we set a good groundwork early on as to how we can address
ourselves to the debt problems plaguing people in this hemisphere.
   So it's been a year of _ obviously a beginning for this
administration, but new beginnings in terms of some of these
initiatives. As the year ends, I think we're on the brink of a
tremendous opportunity. And I look forward to next year when we can
strengthen some of the initiatives that we've already taken and get
going on our new programs _ work to ensure the economic _ that the
economic recovery continues. We're now in the final throes of a
budget process here, but I'm very pleased that we were able to
essentially keep my pledge to the American people last year that I
would not raise taxes.
   So those _ that is not an inclusive list, but those are the ones
that are mainly on my mind, and if you said do you think it's been
a good year, I'd say it's been a pretty good year.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>

</DOC>