<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891226-0148 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-26-89 1424EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--AsbestosVictims ADV07   12-26 1167</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Asbestos Victims, ADV 07,1200</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv07</HEAD>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Jan. 7</HEAD>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<HEAD>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 4 b&amp;w photos,
1 graphic. ColorFoto subscribers get 3 35mm slides.)</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Once considered a miracle fiber, asbestos is now
recognized as a serious health threat and will be taken off the
U.S. market in a series of bans beginning this year. But for
utility workers like Kevin Quinn, who says he was exposed to
asbestos on the job, the damage may already have been done.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By BETH J. HARPAZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Kevin Quinn's father began working for
Consolidated Edison in the 1940s, when asbestos was still
considered a miracle fiber and no regulations governed its use.
   William Quinn died in 1980 of cancer linked to asbestos.
   His son was hired by the same utility in 1979. In the years
since his father first came in contact with asbestos, numerous laws
had been passed to protect workers from what was now acknowledged
as a prime health risk.
   But in 1987, Quinn says, he was working at a plant when
asbestos-covered doors were removed from boilers and dropped to the
floor. The doors remained for weeks while workers went about their
duties without protective gear amid clouds of asbestos dust, he
says.
   ``I used to walk past that area every day,'' he says. ``They
told us it was safe. And it turns out it wasn't.''
   Now, Quinn has joined 180 co-workers and the Environmental
Protection Agency in suing Con Ed, charging that he was exposed to
the same material that killed his father.
   Eighteen years after passage of the first federal law regulating
asbestos, thousands of workers _ at utilities like Con Ed, and in
other industries where asbestos was used as an insulator _ still
face its effects.
   ``We are talking to people who are extremely surprised that
asbestos is still a problem,'' said Heather Maurer, executive
director of Asbestos Victims of America. ``But the incidence of
asbestos disease is on the increase instead of the decrease,
despite restrictions that have been applied to make the use of
asbestos safer.''
   A recent union-sponsored screening of 538 Con Edison workers
found that 20 percent had either scarred lungs or mesothelioma, an
asbestos-caused cancer of the lining of the abdomen or the lungs.
   Since 1987, Con Ed has been cited by the Occupational Safety and
Health Administration for more than a half-dozen alleged violations
_ mostly failure to monitor the level of asbestos fibers in the air
_ at the Indian Point nuclear plant in Buchanan, a plant in
Astoria, Queens, and at Quinn's 74th Street plant in Manhattan.
   Some allegations are still under investigation, some have been
contested and dropped by OSHA, and Con Ed settled others by paying
a fine.
   ``Prior to 1973, we didn't know what the asbestos risks were,''
said Con Ed spokeswoman Rosalie Zuckerman. ``We're not denying that
prior to that time, there was exposure. But now that we're aware of
it, whenever we do any asbestos work, we follow all the
regulations.''
   She added that since 1973, the company has had two medical vans
visiting Con Ed plants, carrying X-ray machines to test for
asbestos scarring.
   She would not comment on Kevin Quinn's suit. But Quinn says the
company was negligent in 1987, when he was exposed. The workers, he
says, were kept in the dark.
   ``We didn't realize we were working around asbestos 'til a shop
steward took an air sample to the White Lung Association,'' he said.
   Because asbestos cancers can take 20 to 35 years to develop,
workers like Quinn who believe they have been exposed recently may
not become sick until the year 2020. And people who were exposed to
asbestos in the 1950s, '60s and '70s are just now getting sick.
   A study by Dr. Irving Selikoff, perhaps the world's most noted
asbestos researcher, and his colleagues at the Mount Sinai School
of Medicine projects that asbestos cancer rates won't peak until
1992 and won't drop off significantly until after the year 2000.
   Smoking exacerbates the risk of asbestos-related lung cancer,
which is incurable in 70 to 95 percent of cases, said Dr. Stephen
Levin, who works with Selikoff. Mesothelioma is always fatal.
Asbestos exposure also increases the risk of colon cancer, which
has an 80 percent cure rate if caught early.
   The study predicts that 9,739 deaths from asbestos exposure will
be recorded in 1992 in just 11 industries, including utilities,
construction, car and railroad engine repair, shipbuilding, and
asbestos manufacturing.
   Many Con Ed workers fear they might surface among those
statistics:
   _Gene Duffy, 46, has worked for Con Edison for 25 years. His
chest X-rays show lung scarring; he often has trouble breathing.
Duffy said he can't even cut his lawn without taking a rest halfway
through to catch his breath.
   _Artie Sagevick, 58, a 31-year veteran. He gave up smoking 25
years ago, but he has ``coughing fits 15 minutes at a time a couple
of times a day.''
   _Says Steven Amato, a 21-year employee: ``If you had to do a
strenuous job, go up and down stairs, I could not do it. In the
wintertime, I throw the phlegm all day long. ... I'm 51 years old
and I feel like an old man.''
   All three want compensation from Con Ed, more help from their
union, and along with many of their co-workers, they are suing
asbestos manufacturers.
   Lawyer Chris Placitella is handling similar suits by 130 Con Ed
workers. His firm represents 3,300 additional workers from other
utility companies who are involved in similar suits, and the number
of plaintiffs rises daily.
   Con Edison has other asbestos-related worries. City officials
have raised concerns about public exposure to asbestos from Con Ed
accidents. In several recent incidents, asbestos insulation wrapped
around underground Con Ed steam pipes has blown off when the pipes
or nearby water mains burst.
   One explosion killed three people and contaminated Manhattan's
entire Gramercy Park neighborhood with asbestos, forcing hundreds
of people to relocate.
   Con Ed was faulted for failing to report the presence of
asbestos for several days, which delayed the cleanup and increased
health risks. Other accidents contaminated streets and subways.
   The city Department of Environmental Protection has called on
federal officials to come up with new techniques to deal with these
outdoor and underground emergencies, since the usual procedures
have not always applied.
   Most asbestos products will be taken off the U.S. market under a
three-stage EPA ban that begins in 1990 and ends in 1997. Advocates
for asbestos victims applaud the ban but wish more were being done.
   Asbestos manufacturers have filed a lawsuit challenging the ban,
claiming today's products are safe because the fiber is encased in
hard materials like cement and won't deteriorate.
   Whether or not the manufacturers are successful, AFL-CIO
occupational safety expert Peg Seminario predicts, ``It's going to
be some time before our asbestos problems are over.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>

</DOC>