<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 0151EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Israel-Prisoners     12-19 0366</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Israel-Prisoners,0378</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rabin Says He Authorized Meetings Between POW Families, PLO</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TEL AVIV, Israel (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Defense Minister Yitzhak Rabin says he
authorized meetings between the families of Israeli soldiers
missing in action in Lebanon and PLO leaders in Tunisia.
   Negotiations with the Palestine Liberation Organization have
been authorized for the families of three soldiers missing since
the battle with Syrian forces at Sultan Yaakoub in eastern Lebanon
on June 11, 1982, during Israel's invasion of Lebanon, Rabin said
Monday.
   ``I have allowed the families to meet with the PLO, and to some
family members even to travel to Tunisia,'' Rabin said.
   ``To get information, family members may hold meetings without
any reservations or limitations, and with our financing,'' Rabin
added, speaking to students at Tel Aviv University.
   Israel officially considers the PLO to be a terrorist group and
refuses to let it participate in the Middle East peace process.
   The three soldiers missing since the Sultan Yaakoub battle are
Sgt. Zvi Feldman, U.S.-born Sgt. Zachary Baumel and Cpl. Yehuda
Katz.
   Israel Television and reliable sources said Baumel's father,
Yona, traveled to Tunisia twice in January, meeting with senior PLO
officials at the organization's headquarters in Tunis. There were
no positive results.
   Rabin said another Israeli soldier, Samir Assad, who disappeared
in 1982 in Lebanon, ``was kidnapped and apparently killed.''
   In 1986, the Democratic Front for the Liberation of Palestine
offered to exchange Assad's body for 50 captive guerrillas. Israel
has turned down the offer.
   Two other Israeli soldiers, Yosef Fink and Rachamim Alsheikh,
were kidnapped in southern Lebanon in February 1986.
   Rabin spoke a day after the wife of an Israeli airman captured
three years ago in Lebanon said Israeli authorities told her that
her husband, Ron Arad, was still alive and being held by Iranians.
   The statement over Israeli radio stations was intended to be a
public message to the Iranians ``who have control over those who
are holding Ron Arad,'' said Defense Ministry adviser on prisoners
of war, Uri Slonim.
   Arad, a navigator, was shot down with an F-4 Phantom fighter jet
during an Israeli bombing mission in southern Lebanon on Oct. 16,
1986. The plane's pilot was rescued by Israeli troops.
</TEXT>

</DOC>