<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891230-0095 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-89 1601EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Bush 1stLd-Writethru a0552 12-30 0890</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0552,790</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Says Nicaraguan Search Was Mistake, But Questions Arms Haul</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 2 grafs after 8th graf pvs, In Washington, to UPDATE
with further State Department comment about weapons. Picks up 9th graf
pvs, Earlier Saturday</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER CONNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush called the ransacking by U.S.
troops of the Nicaraguan ambassador's residence in Panama City ``a
screw-up'' that should not have happened, but questioned why the
Sandinista envoy was ``up to his eyeballs'' in rocket launchers,
grenades and automatic weaponry.
   At the same time, Bush predicted the diplomatic standoff with
the Vatican over the fate of deposed Panamanian dictator Manuel
Antonio Noriega soon would be resolved to the United States'
satisfaction.
   Bush, winding up a year-end vacation, told reporters after a
round of golf that ``the death of a lot of our kids'' in the Dec.
20 invasion of Panama has made him determined to bring Noriega to
justice, not let him slip off into exile in a third country.
   Bush said U.S. military authorities have apologized to
Nicaraguan Ambassador Antenor Ferrey for the incident Friday, which
has led Nicaragua to order 20 U.S. diplomats out of their country.
   ``It's a screw-up and they have expressed their regrets that it
took place,'' Bush said at the 18th hole of the Houston Country
Club after finishing a round with national security adviser Brent
Scowcroft, friend Will Farish and golf pro Doug Sanders.
   But Bush said the arms cache that U.S. troops found inside
Ferrey's house ``makes you wonder exactly what our young men are up
against down there. I don't know what they need rocket launchers
for in a man's house.''
   ``I'd like to know what the man's doing with rocket launchers
and grenades and Uzis and automatic weapons up to his eyeballs in
his house,'' the president said. ``Having said that, we should not
have gone into that diplomatic premises.'
   In Washington, the State Department said the cache included four
Uzi machine guns, six rocket-propelled grenade launchers, 12
AK-47s, three hand grenades, 10 FEN rifles, 17 bayonets, one M-1
carbine, one shotgun, four rocket-propelled grenade sights, one
light anti-tank weapon, 27 rocket-propelled grenade rounds and
approximately 1,300 rounds of ammunition of various caliber.
   The weapons were ``in excess of normal requirements for
defending the residence,'' the State Department said. A department
official who spoke only on condition of anonymity declined to
define ``normal requirements for defending'' a residence.
   The official also declined to say what types of weapons U.S.
envoys in places such as Managua might have at their homes, calling
it ``a security question.''
   Earlier Saturday, the Vatican, which on Friday had called the
United States an ``occupying power,''' issued a conciliatory
statement saying talks about Noriega's fate continued between the
Holy See and U.S. authorities ``in a spirit of serene
collaboration.''
   The Vatican predicted they will eventually yield ``a just
solution which will be mutually satisfactory.'' It said the papal
nuncio, in allowing Noriega into the embassy, never intended ``to
block the course of justice regarding a person accused of serious
crimes.''
   Bush said, ``I think it's time to cool it on both sides.'' He
said he would personally call Pope John Paul II if need be.
   Bush said the church has a long history of granting asylum, even
to ``thugs'' like Noriega.
   ``We have a complicated three-way conundrum at this point,''
Bush said. ``I really believe this matter will be resolved, one way
or another, to the satisfaction of the United States.''
   Bush even cracked a joke about the loud rock 'n' roll music the
U.S. troops encircling the Vatican Embassy have been playing,
apparently to harass Noriega. The blaring loudspeakers were turned
off Saturday.
   ``I think it aggravated the people inside. It was stopped,''
Bush said. It would have aggravated me, I'll tell you. I'm not into
rock. Country music, maybe that's different.''
   Earlier, White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater told reporters
``They did not know it was a diplomatic residence. We do not enter
diplomatic residences.''
   Fitzwater said Bush had no advance knowledge of the U.S.
soldiers' raid on Ferrey's home.
   Nicaraguan President Daniel Ortega, in ordering 20 U.S.
diplomats out of his country in 72 hours and slashing the U.S.
Embassy's support staff from 320 to 100, said ``They acted
arrogantly, like Rambos.''
   Bush was spending the weekend in his adopted hometown after
three days of fishing and hunting in South Texas. He and Barbara
Bush were flying to San Antonio on Sunday morning to visit soldiers
wounded in Panama. They were to spend New Year's Eve in their hotel
suite at the Houstonian.
   Fitzwater, asked about the lopsided United Nations vote Friday
condemning the U.S. invasion of Panama and demanding immediate
withdrawal of the occupation forces, said ````We felt we did the
right thing for the right reasons.'
   Fitzwater said the ambassador's house was raided because U.S.
military authorities ``got a tip'' there was an arms cache inside.
   ``They were looking for arms and they found arms,'' Fitzwater
said.
   ``We were looking for arms caches. We're finding them all over
Panama City. Arms caches are turning up everywhere,'' he said.
   The United States and Nicaragua expelled each other's
ambassadors in an earlier diplomatic dust-up last year. The United
States had about 35 accredited diplomatic personnel in Managua,
headed by a charge d'affaires.
</TEXT>

</DOC>