<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891219-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-89 1244EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Glasnost-Tecumseh     12-19 0435</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Glasnost-Tecumseh,0449</SECOND>
<HEAD>Students In Home Of `Amerika' Hear From Soviet Counterparts</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TECUMSEH, Neb. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Glasnost has come to the home of
``Amerika,'' a 1986 television mini-series that depicted fictitious
life in the United States after a Soviet takeover.
   Techumseh high school and elementary students recently began
receiving responses to letters they wrote in August to students in
Ryazan, 150 miles southwest of Moscow.
   Teachers are hoping the letters educate their students about the
vastness of the world and about the society and politics of the
Soviet Union, which had ``taken over'' Tecumseh during the filming
of the mini-series in this southeastern Nebraska town of 1,900.
   ``I hope they get a better understanding of the world _ that
it's a much bigger place than just Tecumseh, and that people around
the world do similar things,'' said Janene Bartels, a first-grade
teacher who helped initiate the project.
   High school English teacher Sheryl Allen said world politics
seemed too distant for most of today's students.
   ``They're more concerned with what they're doing this weekend or
what they're doing after the basketball game,'' Allen said. ``I'm
hoping this might personalize it for them so that they'll turn on
the news at night.''
   Students in Allen's senior English classes received individual
responses, while students in Bartels' first-grade class received
one letter for the entire class, complete with photos of the class
and Ryazan.
   The letters already have dispelled some stereotypes.
   Jamie Carson, a 17-year-old senior, said she perceived the
Soviet Union as ``cold, gray and very strict'' but discovered that
teen interests in music, clothes and sports were very similar.
   Soviet students mentioned Billy Joel and Michael Jackson as rock
music idols, and talked of brands of clothing available in America.
   Mark Sherman, a 17-year-old senior, said he was amazed that his
pen pal, a 16-year-old aspiring actress, was so stylishly dressed,
and that her photograph had appeared in a national magazine.
   ``I had the impression there were people walking around the
streets with guns,'' Sherman said. He and the other senior English
students said they hoped they could dispell some myths about
Americans, too.
   The letter exchange was intitiated by Col. Barney Oldfield, a
Johnson County native who is now a Beverly Hills, Calif., author,
publicist and consultant on Soviet affairs to the Litton Corp. The
wife of Oldfield's Russian interpreter, Galina Korzhikova, is an
English teacher in Ryazan.
   Bartels said she hoped the student letter exchange would pay
dividends in promoting better U.S.-Soviet relations.
   ``Maybe by the time they grow up, communications with Russia
will be very open,'' she said. ``But for now, it's a start.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>