<?xml version="1.0"?>

<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0118 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 1452EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Czechoslovakia-Havel     12-29 0991</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Czechoslovakia-Havel,1026</SECOND>
<HEAD>Havel Revives Tradition of Philosopher President</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Czechoslovakia, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MORT ROSENBLUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Months ago, Vaclav Havel was a
prisoner of faceless men, jailed yet again for ``antisocial''
behavior in a system he called morally rotten.
   On Friday, he became president of Czechoslovakia.
   A playwright, Havel scripted much of the high drama which
brought the Communist Party off center stage after 41 years of
command performance.
   His work was banned after Soviet armor silenced the ``Prague
Spring'' of 1968. Writing in the shadows, publishing abroad, he
sliced away Communist underpinnings with strokes of his pen.
   Havel exposed the abyss between words and reality, hurling scorn
at the Orwellian spin on terms like ``people's democracy'' and
``socialism.''
   His goal, he said recently, was a ``modern contemporary system
which would return to people their honor and freedom.''
   Although Havel recently called the prime minister's job 10 times
more important than the president's, he is likely to loom large as
Czechoslovaks rediscover democracy.
   He revives a tradition of the philosopher president. His hero,
and the nation's, is Tomas Garrigue Masaryk, the professor and
author who in 1918 created Czechoslovakia from the ruins of the
Austro-Hungarian Empire.
   Czechoslovaks, who love ideas eloquently expressed, have turned
frequently to intellectuals for guidance in times of crisis.
   At first glance, Havel appears less a president than a
53-year-old Dennis- the-Menace lookalike with a blond mustache.
Impish eyes gleam, and a half-amused smile leaves people wondering
what he is up to next.
   When he speaks, however, his gravely voice rumbles wit and
wisdom. He is small and shy, but his presence can fill a room.
   Four years in prison during the last 20 have edged Havel's
whimsy with flint. Mostly, he has often said, time alone with his
tormentors gave him a chance to weigh his values.
   His ``Letters To Olga,'' written from his cell to his wife and
published as a book, reveal a man putting his mind through rigorous
daily aerobics.
   Havel sweeps broadly from intense inner searching and musing in
foreign languages to mundane details of life. Characteristically,
he blends the extremes.
   In one letter, he warns Olga to fight when authorities cut off
her fuel. ``It's not just the heating oil,'' he wrote. ``This could
become a monstrous precedent. (Franz Kafka: Man is an eternal
rebel).''
   He urges her to care for their farmhouse, clearly the place to
which he longs to escape to craft the plays that nourish him.
   Havel's plays are only obliquely political. He targets the
unjust and the hypocritical, taking them apart with swift,
sometimes imperceptible razor cuts.
   In public comments, however, Havel was blunt as a hammer blow.
At his trial in February, given a final word in his own defense,
Havel denounced authorities who arrested people for laying flowers
at a patriot's memorial:
   ``I must say that words `anti-state' and `antisocialist' lost
any semantic meaning long ago, since during their long years of
wanton use, they became a perjorative label for all citizens who,
for various reasons, made the government feel uncomfortable.''
   Havel's parents were wealthy, but only until he was 5.
Communists took power and marked him as too bourgeois for higher
education. To be near the theater, he worked as a stagehand.
Eventually he earned a degree at night school.
   Like Shakespeare's Caesar, Havel refused laurels until they were
forced upon him by a nation chanting his name. In a Dec. 7 news
conference, he said:
   ``I have repeatedly said that my occupation is writer and that I
have no political ambitions. I don't feel myself to be a
professional politician. But I have always put the public interest
ahead of my own.
   ``And if, God help us, the situation should develop in such a
way that the only service I could render my country would be to do
this, then, of course, I would do it.''
   That was quickly the case.
   In the heady momentum of the November uprising, the opposition
wanted a balanced government that would steer the nation quickly
toward free elections.
   The Communist premier resigned. His successor haggled with
opposition leaders, including Havel, over a cabinet. President
Gustav Husak, under an ultimatum, stepped down. A general strike
was averted. Czechoslovakia needed a leader.
   At a Dec. 9 rally, it was Havel on a balcony over Wenceslas
Square who listed each triumph of the people. He thundered, ``Love
and love must prevail over lies and hatred.'' The crowd of 100,000
roared, ``We want Havel.''
   Havel's sudden emergence was not a total surprise. As the crisis
widened, mysterious Hungarian-made ``Havel for President'' buttons
popped up all over Prague.
   Asked about them at the news conference, Havel shrugged. ``I
don't wear one,'' he said, skillfully evading three follow-up
questions on whether he approved of them.
   He was red-eyed and falling-down tired, but his answers were all
Havel. When someone taxed him for squirming away from direct
questions, he laughed.
   ``You talk of the presidency but don't accept the basic
presidential quality of answering in a roundabout way,'' he said.
He had seen George Bush in action, he added. ``I so far have not
said, `No comment.'''
   More seriously, he underlined the character of a revolution by a
strong people who finally had enough of something they did not
believe in.
   ``What is important,'' he said, ``is what the students began
with, that is, the humanitarian dimension, resistance to violence,
the longing for truth and moral integrity.''
   One reporter asked him to list the lessons he had drawn from 20
years of standing up to the state. He reflected a moment and
replied:
   ``I have learned that when a person behaves in accordance with
his conscience, and when he tries to speak the truth, behave as a
citizen even when citizenship as such is degraded, it may not lead
to anything, but it might.
   ``What certainly will not lead to anything is when you calculate
that it might.''
</TEXT>

</DOC>